<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.3" nospeaker="true" ><p>The following are questions tabled by Members for written response and the ministerial replies as received on the day from the Departments [unrevised].</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.4" nospeaker="true" ><p>Question No. 1 answered orally.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.6" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300058#WRA00400">Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.5" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300058#WRA00350">Public Transport</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.6.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1486" speakername="Br&iacute;d Smith" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300058#WRA00400"><p><i>2.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport if he will commission a study into the provision of free public transport that examines the costs and benefits of such a policy; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12313/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.7.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300058#WRA00500"><p>I am very cognisant of the importance of incentivising greater use of our public transport services; however, I am not convinced that providing free public transport is the most balanced means of achieving this objective. </p>  <p>  COVID gave us some insight into the level of funding that might be required in the absence of fare revenue. For example, in 2020, an additional &euro;370 million was required to enable the continued operation of services due to the collapse of fare intake. In 2021, &euro;659m was required to run PSO services, and this year we have allocated &euro;538 million for the continuation of these essential services. Apportioning such significant levels of Exchequer resources to one goal would undoubtedly impact the State&rsquo;s ability to support other worthy public services. </p>  <p>  While free public transport is available in some European locations, I understand that results have varied. The intention is commendable - encouraging modal shift, reducing congestion, and capitalising on the associated environmental benefits. However, the Schemes can have unintended consequences, most noticeably a significant reduction in active travel. This is counter to our core Government goals of improving citizen&rsquo;s health and reducing greenhouse gas emissions. </p>  <p>  While I might not agree that free transport provides a silver bullet solution - I do believe there is merit in incentivising fares when an appropriate balance can be struck. I am delighted to soon launch the Young Adult Card - allowing those aged between 19 and 23 to avail of an average 50% fare discount. Simultaneously, as part of the suite of measures aimed at tackling the increasing cost of living, we will also introduce an average 20% fare reduction for all PSO passengers  </p>  <p>  Further, the raft of fare initiatives being introduced this year, paired with the significant increase in investment in vehicles and infrastructure, will make public transport an overall more attractive proposition and support greater modal shift ultimately helping us reduce our transport emissions. </p></reply>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.8" nospeaker="true" ><p>Questions Nos. 3 to 7, inclusive, answered orally.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.9" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300058#WRA00650">Rail Network</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.10.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1616" speakername="Matt Shanahan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300058#WRA00700"><p><i>8.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport his views on the reopening of the Waterford to Rosslare rail line to increase transport flexibility and development in the south-east region given the increasing importance of Waterford and Wexford ports in both national import and export activity in addition to facilitating future offshore wind development installations; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[10485/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.11.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300058#WRA00800"><p>As the Deputy is aware, a decision to remove passenger services on the Waterford to Rosslare line was made in 2010 and a maintenance arrangement was put in place then to allow for its continued maintenance since then. </p>  <p>  I have commissioned a Strategic Rail Review to help inform the development of inter-urban / inter-regional rail on the Island of Ireland over the coming decades.  It will also consider the potential scope for improved rail services and infrastructure along the various existing, or future potential, corridors of the network including disused and closed lines such as the Waterford to Rosslare line. An important aspect of the Review will be to consider the potential for rail freight and whether opportunities exist to increase its role on the island. </p>  <p>  The Deputy is right to highlight the growing importance of our port network in the south east. It is the case that Waterford and Rosslare handle different types of cargo and that can influence the potential of each with regard to rail freight. Waterford port handles LoLo which is suitable for rail freight, while Rosslare is of course principally a RoRo port and RoRo does not lend itself easily to rail freight. </p>  <p>  I do believe there is real potential for Ireland&rsquo;s ports in the area of offshore renewable energy (ORE). That is why I published a policy statement on the matter last December which makes it clear to the offshore industry that the Government is committed to the provision of port facilities in Ireland for ORE developments. In that regard I very much welcome the fact that Rosslare Europort has submitted an application for EU funding to support it ambitious plans to develop an offshore renewable energy hub.   </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.12" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300058#WRA00850">Parking Provision</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.13.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1564" speakername="Duncan Smith" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300058#WRA00900"><p><i>9.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport if he will set aside plans for a linear park as part of the MetroLink proposals given the strong opposition to this plan from local residents; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[11046/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.14.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300058#WRA01000"><p>I understand that there has been extensive engagement on this matter, but am aware that there are different views on the matter too.</p>  <p>  As a point of principle, I welcome the idea that for projects of the scale of MetroLink opportunities to enhance the public realm are fully explored. I think improving the public realm can provide significant benefits for local communities and improve our urban environment generally as well. I imagine the Deputy shares my general perspective on the issue.</p>  <p>  I understand that in relation to this specific issue, Transport Infrastructure Ireland did identify an opportunity to provide a linear park along the R132 to Swords. The proposal was to provide play areas, leisure cycling, biodiversity planting and a very pleasant green environment which would enhance the amenity value of the area for use by all, and especially those living adjacent to MetroLink.</p>  <p>  I am informed that after extensive engagement with residents and local representatives, the design has been modified significantly to address concerns raised by local residents. Some residents still remain opposed to the public realm designs and these concerns will continue to be engaged with, and where possible, solutions will be presented for further consideration. As part of this design development, the project team are committed to working with the residents to achieve optimal outcomes for all. The services of an independent engineering expert have also been made available to the local residents to provide them with impartial assistance.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.15" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300058#WRA01050">Fuel Prices</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.16.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1498" speakername="Ruairi &Oacute; Murch&uacute;" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300058#WRA01100"><p><i>10.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the supports that are available to truckers in relation to the rising cost of fuel which is pushing businesses to the brink; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12138/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.17.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1578" speakername="Hildegarde Naughton" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300058#WRA01200"><p>The current spike in energy prices arises from the global recovery from the Covid-19 pandemic in conjunction with current international tensions and supply constraint issues. This is being witnessed across the European Union as well as many other regions. </p>  <p>  The final retail price of fuel is determined by a number of factors which include the costs of production, distribution, global market factors, international exchange rates, taxation, wholesale market contracts negotiated at different rates for the purchase of oil as well as individual retail pricing policies.  </p>  <p>  In order to mitigate the impact of fuel price increases for hauliers, the Diesel Rebate Scheme offers a partial excise refund to qualifying operators when the price of diesel is relatively high. In Budget 2020, in light of the challenges arising from Brexit uncertainty facing the industry, the marginal rate of compensation at prices over &euro;1.32 (VAT inclusive) was doubled up to the maximum repayment rate of 7.5 cents per litre. In recognition of the vital role that the haulage sector plays in the economy, this increase has been maintained since.</p>  <p>  In addition, businesses that are registered for VAT may deduct the VAT charged to them on the purchase of business inputs, such as road diesel and other motoring costs.</p>  <p>  Minister Ryan and I met with the Irish Road Haulage Association (&lsquo;IRHA&rsquo;) on 10 December 2021 and again on 10 February 2022 to discuss the spike in fuel prices for hauliers and the need for the sector to make progress towards decarbonisation.  While no way forward was agreed, discussions are ongoing at official level on these issues. </p>  <p>  Already however some supports are available for operators to switch to alternatively fuelled vehicles. These include a purchase grant and reduced tolls for vehicles powered by a number of alternative fuels including hydrogen, electric, and gas. In addition, Budget 2022 announced an expansion of the Accelerated Capital Allowance (&lsquo;ACA&rsquo;) scheme for Gas Vehicles and Refuelling Equipment. This ACA scheme provides an accelerated wear and tear allowance for capital expenditure incurred on qualifying vehicles and refuelling equipment.</p></reply>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.18" nospeaker="true" ><p>Questions No. 11 to 13, inclusive, answered orally.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.19" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300058#WRA01350">Public Transport</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.20.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1498" speakername="Ruairi &Oacute; Murch&uacute;" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300058#WRA01400"><p><i>14.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport his plans in relation to making the public transport system accessible for all; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12139/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.21.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300058#WRA01500"><p>In line with the United Nations Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities and Ireland's National Disability Inclusion Strategy, I am fully committed to strengthening public transport offerings and progressively making them accessible for all, especially for Persons with Disabilities, Persons with Reduced Mobility, and Older People. </p>  <p>  To this end, all new public transport infrastructure and services are accessible from the design stage. This means that accessibility features, such as wheelchair accessibility and audio/visual aids, are built into from the start. Newer public transport systems, such as the Luas for instance, are fully accessible, as are all new buses purchased by the National Transport Authority.</p>  <p>  We also have dedicated funding of over &euro;15 million and a programme of works in place to retrofit our older and legacy infrastructure and facilities to make them accessible as well.</p>  <p>  In addition, to making our &ldquo;hard&rdquo; infrastructure and services accessible, it is crucial to provide the &ldquo;softer&rdquo; types of support as well, to enable Persons with Disabilities to travel independently on public transport. </p>  <p>  The NTA and the transport companies are very active in this field; they have a number of initiatives underway including the provision of Disability Awareness Training to frontline staff, the rollout of the Just A Minute (JAM) Card to assist anyone with a communications difficulty, and ensuring that information is provided in accessible formats for public transport services. </p>  <p>  In addition, there is the Travel Assistance Scheme which is a free service managed by Dublin Bus that aims to give people with disabilities the confidence they need to use public transport.  Under the scheme an assistant can accompany people who need help using public transport and give advice how to plan a journey on Dublin Bus, Luas, DART and Go-Ahead Ireland services. Due to the success of the Scheme in the Greater Dublin Area it is planned to extend it to include Cork later this year which will be of great benefit in the region.</p>  <p>  While my Department and its Agencies have responsibility for open public transport services only, we work closely with other Departments and Agencies which have responsibility for dedicated and specialist disability transport services. An example of such collaboration, with colleagues in Health and the HSE, was the launch last year of non-emergency transport services in Leitrim. This scheme enhanced local rural public transport services and improved the number of stops at key health and care centres, thereby negating some of the need for specialist, dedicated services. All the vehicles used in this pilot are accessible and low floor to meet the needs of many service users.</p>  <p>  I am strongly committed through the provision of new and retrofitting older infrastructure, as well as by supporting softer measures and collaborations, to continue to improve the accessibility of our public transport system.   </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.22" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300058#WRA01550">Road Network</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.23.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1579" speakername="Mairead Farrell" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300058#WRA01600"><p><i>15.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the action that will be taken to combat flooding on the Kylemore Road, County Galway given the serious issue of flooding on the road making it regularly impassable; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[11386/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.24.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300058#WRA01700"><p>As Minister for Transport, I have responsibility for overall policy and exchequer funding in relation to the National Roads Programme. Once funding arrangements have been put in place with Transport Infrastructure Ireland (TII), under the Roads Acts 1993-2015, and in line with the National Development Plan, the planning, design and maintenance of individual national roads is a matter for TII, in conjunction with the local authorities concerned. </p>  <p>  The matter at issue here - the flooding of the N59 at Kylemore - is not a matter for TII.  I understand from TII that Galway County Council have assessed the cause of the flooding at Kylemore Road and have determined that the problem is associated with the capacity of the river channel and blockage of the bridge opening by material transported by the river. </p>  <p>  It is a matter for Galway County Council as road authority for the area, in conjunction with the Office of Public Works (OPW) to resolve this issue. I understand that works to remove the build-up of material in the river channel, which is leading to the flooding problem, must also have agreement of the National Parks and Wildlife Service and Inland Fisheries Ireland.  I understand that engagement is taking place between Galway County Council, OPW and these agencies in an attempt to find a solution. </p>  <p>  TII has indicated to my Department that it is available to liaise with and provide support to Galway County Council, insofar as it can, in this matter.  I will also bring the matter to the attention of my colleague Minister Patrick Donovan who has responsibility for the OPW.</p></reply>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.25" nospeaker="true" ><p>Question No. 16 answered orally.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.26" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300058#WRA01850">Electric Vehicles</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.27.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1507" speakername="Darren O'Rourke" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300058#WRA01900"><p><i>17.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport if an update will be provided on the roll-out of electric vehicle charging infrastructure; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12134/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.28.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300058#WRA02000"><p>The Deputy will be aware that Ireland has set an ambitious target of 945,000 EVs on our roads by 2030 that reflects the scale of the transformation needed to achieve its climate targets in the coming years. Under the National Development Plan &euro;1bn has been allocated to specific carbon reduction measures, including vehicle electrification.</p>  <p>  The Government is fully committed to supporting a significant expansion and modernisation of the electric vehicle charging network over the coming years. A national charging infrastructure strategy is being developed which will set out a pathway to stay ahead of demand over the critical period out to 2030. My Department is engaging with relevant stakeholders to inform this work and it is envisaged that the strategy will be published for consultation shortly. </p>  <p>  EV sales continue to grow strongly and it is imperative that a seamless network of recharging infrastructure is available to support that growth. In the development of the strategy officials from my Department have engaged with local authorities. other public sector bodies, and the private sector in identifying how to best support the prompt rollout of infrastructure both to address challenges in domestic and neighbourhood charging as well as the need for fast charging.  My officials have also reviewed international best practice in the provision of EV charging infrastructure to understand what mix of infrastructure provision will best address the needs of Irish EV owners. </p>  <p>  A package of supports aiming to facilitate a swift delivery of infrastructure across the country is being prepared to be launched alongside the strategy. I look forward to providing more information on those aspects towards the end of this month.   </p>  <p>  I am also pleased to say that preparations are progressing well to establish an Office of Low Emission Vehicles.  This Office will play an important role in our transition to zero emission vehicles. It will co-ordinate measures to support the uptake of EVs and the rollout of charge point  infrastructure.   </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.29" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300058#WRA02050">Public Transport</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.30.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1515" speakername="David Stanton" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300058#WRA02100"><p><i>18.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the expected timeline for the 20% reduction in the cost of public transport fares as part of the measures to help reduce the cost of living; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12081/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.31.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300058#WRA02200"><p>The Government is strongly committed to helping combat the rising cost-of-living being experienced throughout the country. As such, as part of a suite of new measures is being introduced, I was delighted to be able to bring forward a proposal to reduce fares on PSO public transport services by an average of 20% until the end of 2022. These discounted fares will benefit the hundreds of thousands of people across the country who use public transport every day.</p>  <p>  &euro;54m in Exchequer funding has been secured to allow for the introduction of these discounted fares, this is in addition to the &euro;538m that has already been allocated to PSO and Local Link services this year. </p>  <p>  My Department is working closely with the NTA and the various PSO public transport operators to commence rolling out these fare reductions across the public transport network by late April and early May.</p>  <p>  As the Deputy will appreciate, time is needed to make and test the necessary changes to the wide array of ticketing systems employed across the network, including, the Leap card, on-board ticketing equipment, vending machines and online web platforms. Updates are needed across all the PSO operators, at the different stations and depots, as well as on thousands of individual vehicles, to ensure the discounts are applied across the board.</p>  <p>  In addition to the average 20% fare reduction, and in recognition of the importance of incentivising young people to use public transport, I secured funding to provide for the introduction of a young adult card. This card will allow any person who is between 19 and 23 years old, to avail of an average 50% discount fares across all services, including city, intercity and rural services. It is envisaged that this discount will initially be made available on PSO services at the same time as the average 20% fare discount (April/May) - providing significant travel savings for this age cohort. It is my intention to broaden the eligibility of the Young Adult Card to include commercial operators at a later date.  The NTA are currently assessing deployment options in this regard.</p>  <p>  Furthermore, I anticipate that the average 20% PSO fare reduction will also apply to eligible annual Taxsaver tickets - again from April/May time.   </p>  <p>  Collectively, these fare reduction initiatives, should help promote greater modal shift and encourage a reduced reliance on private transport with associated benefit of transport emission savings.</p>  <p>  In conclusion, the introduction of a 20% average fare discount and the Young Adult Cards in late April/early May, means that 2022 looks set to be an exciting year for public transport provision across the country, as we slowly return to pre-pandemic travel patterns.</p></reply>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.32" nospeaker="true" ><p>Question No. 19 answered orally.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.33" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300058#WRA02350">Rail Network</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.34.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1509" speakername="Maurice Quinlivan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300058#WRA02400"><p><i>20.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the status of plans to progress a rail stop on the existing rail line at locations in Moyross and Corbally in Limerick city; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[10361/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.35.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300058#WRA02500"><p>The draft Limerick-Shannon Metropolitan Area Transport Strategy (LSMATS) was published by the National Transport Authority (NTA) in September 2020.  The draft was developed in collaboration with Limerick City and County Council, Clare County Council and Transport Infrastructure Ireland and public consultation was held on the draft for an 8-week period. </p>  <p>  Since the conclusion of the public consultation exercise, the main task the NTA has engaged in has been to undertake a more detailed examination of the potential for suburban rail to play a major role in the Limerick-Shannon Metropolitan Area&rsquo;s transport system.  While that work is ongoing, works are planned to upgrade Colbert Station. </p>  <p>  With regard to any new stations, the NTA has allocated funding of &euro;250,000 to Iarnr&oacute;d &Eacute;ireann in 2022 to carry out the Concept, Feasibility and Option Selection studies required to identify a preferred location and preferred option for a new railway station in the Moyross area of Limerick.</p>  <p>  The Deputy may wish to note that the NTA has also allocated funding of &euro;250,000 in 2022 to enable Iarnr&oacute;d &Eacute;ireann to undertake the Concept, Feasibility and Option Selection studies that will lead to a preferred option for double tracking between Limerick Junction and Limerick Colbert Station.</p>  <p>  As to next steps for the LSMATS, the NTA intend to undertake a second round of public consultation in due course with a consultation period of about one month.   Following receipt of feedback from the second round of public consultation, it is intended to finalise the LSMATS and publish as the completed transport framework for the city.  The finalisation of the strategy is a matter for the NTA.</p>  <p>  I would encourage the Deputy and all interested parties to participate in this important consultation process when it opens and contribute to the future plans of public transport in the Limerick City Metropolitan Area.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.37" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB00200">Ports Policy</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.38.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1521" speakername="P&aacute;draig O'Sullivan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB00300"><p><i>21.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport if his attention has been drawn to delays and congestion problems at the port of Cork, Tivoli; when the new port terminal in Ringaskiddy is due to open; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12108/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.39.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1578" speakername="Hildegarde Naughton" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB00400"><p>The Port of Cork is connected to a number of European container hub ports, such as Rotterdam, Antwerp and Dunkirk. Hub ports accommodate very large container vessels that trade on intercontinental trade routes, operated by global shipping lines. The majority of LoLo services to and from the port of Cork link direct to European Hub ports via smaller container vessels (feeder vessels) with seven such services currently trading between Tivoli and Hub ports in the UK and the EU.</p>  <p>  Due to disruptions to global supply chains primarily as a result of COVID, European Ports have been prioritizing large intercontinental container vessels, with much less prioritization of the smaller &ldquo;feeder&rdquo; vessels that serve other ports such as Cork. This has resulted in peaks and troughs in cargo flows to the Port of Cork, resulting in port users leaving their cargo in Tivoli for longer periods than normal.</p>  <p>  I understand from the Port of Cork Company that this, in addition to the recent spate of storms that crossed the country have led to delays in their ship operations at the Tivoli docks.  The Company has put additional resources in Tivoli to alleviate these difficulties.  In addition, underpinning cargo operations, the Company also operates an automated vehicle booking system for hauliers to manage waiting times and reduce delays at the terminal.    </p>  <p>  The development at Ringaskiddy will see the port over time relocate its business from the current city centre Tivoli location and the City Quays to a new facility known as Cork Container Terminal (CCT). The construction work is complete with commissioning works currently underway and the facility is expected to be operational in Quarter 2, 2022. This will bring additional LoLo capacity on stream, easing congestion at Tivoli. Ringaskiddy will future proof the Port as an international gateway for trade and will allow the Port to continue to meet the needs of its customers and the economic developmental needs locally and at regional and national level. Due to planning conditions, the continued operation of Tivoli terminal to accommodate a percentage of the current and future LoLo trade to Cork will be necessary until the M28 dual carriageway is completed.  </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.40" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB00500">Transport Policy</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.41.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1455" speakername="Aindrias Moynihan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB00600"><p><i>22.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the engagement that he has had with the Minister for Finance on measures that could be implemented to assist persons who cannot avail of public transport for work with driving as their only option given the rising costs of living; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12077/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.42.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB00700"><p>My goal as Minister of Transport is to increase the number of sustainable mobility options available to all citizens. Where possible I am incentivizing public transport use through investment in new services and infrastructure as well as reducing fare structures. In recognition that it is not always possible to provide public transport, particularly in remote areas, I also have a complementary suite of incentives to electrify private transport such as the EV purchase grant and the domestic charger grant scheme.  I am also strongly committed to funding active travel infrastructure to provide more walking and cycling facilities to increase peoples green travel options.  </p><p>The Government is strongly committed to helping combat the rising cost-of-living being experienced throughout the country. In this context, a suite of new measures is being introduced by Government to help with this issue, including a 20% average fare reduction on PSO services until the end of 2022. These discounted fares will benefit the hundreds of thousands of people across the country who use public transport every day. A further &euro;54m in Exchequer funding has been secured to allow for the introduction of these discounted fares, this is in addition to the REV22 allocations. The NTA will work with the PSO public transport operators in the coming weeks to commence rolling out these fare reductions across the public transport network in late April/ early May.</p><p>Also, in recognition of the importance of incentivising young people to use public transport, as part of Budget 2022 I secured &euro;25m of funding to provide for the introduction of a young adult card (YAC) which will allow any person nationwide who is between 19 and 23 years old, to avail of an entitlement for discounted travel costs, and to increase the level of discount over and above the current student discount to an average of discount of 50% across all services, including city, intercity and rural services. It is envisaged that the discount will initially be made available on PSO services, and then broadened to include commercial operators at a later date.  This will not only promote modal shift in the transport sector among this age group but should also contribute towards a reduced reliance on private transport with associated benefit of transport emission savings.  The NTA has commenced work in relation to the implementation of the new fares&rsquo; structures for young adults, and this includes the application process and establishing a definitive timeline for the introduction of the Scheme. </p><p>A new 90-minute fare has also been  introduced by the NTA to coincide with Phase 2 of BusConnects  which gives customers the option to transfer between Dublin Bus, Luas and most DART, commuter rail and Go-Ahead Ireland services in Dublin at no additional fare.</p><p>In addition, the Deputy will be pleased to hear that the new Connecting Ireland Rural Mobility Plan will significantly benefit those living in rural Ireland. Starting this year, this plan is a major national public transport initiative funded by my Department and managed by the National Transport Authority. The aim of this plan is to increase public transport connectivity over a five-year period, particularly for people living outside the major cities and towns. That means that by 2025, Ireland will see a 25% overall increase in rural bus services. Over 100 rural towns and villages will benefit from frequent public transport services for the first time ever. To ensure timely rollout, I have secured &euro;5.6 million in Budget 2022 to support the NTA in planning and implementing these services.</p><p>The NTA are currently analysing the feedback received from the public consultation and will issue a report once this process is finalised. They are also in the process of finalising the proposals, with a<b></b>rollout of new and improved services planned on a phased basis starting this year to 2025<b>. </b>I believe that Connecting Ireland will greatly improve the mobility options for many currently unable to avail of public transport services. </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.43" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB00800">Road Safety</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.44.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1482" speakername="Se&aacute;n Canney" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB00900"><p><i>23.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport if he will alter the criteria for the active travel scheme to include villages and settlement centres that do not have speed limits which would benefit enormously from the scheme to safely link schools and amenities by means of footpaths and cycleways; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12071/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.45.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB01000"><p>The Safe Routes to School Programme was launched in March 2021 to support Active Travel infrastructure for selected schools around the country. This Programme aims to create safer walking and cycling routes within communities, alleviate congestion at the school gates and increase the number of students who walk or cycle to school by providing new or improved walking and cycling facilities. Funding is provided to local authorities as part of the Department of Transport's funding allocation to the National Transport Authority (NTA), is supported by the Department of Education and coordinated by An Taisce&rsquo;s Green Schools.</p>  <p>  &euro;15m has been allocated for projects at the 170 schools included in Round One of the Programme. The schools not included in Round One will be engaged with on a rolling basis in each local authority area. This funding is being provided from the &euro;1.8 billion funding earmarked in the Programme for Government to support sustainable transport</p>  <p>  It is important to note that local authorities have the power to introduce bye-laws to set special speed limits in designated areas such as built up areas or around schools, and typically have done so. The Safe Routes to School Programme is focusing more on urban and suburban areas, as there is greater population densities within walking and cycling distance to schools in these areas. There are also a significant number of schools on the edge of towns and villages, within walking distance, which do not have continuous footpaths on the route to schools. These schools are viewed as urban/suburban for the purposes of the Programme.</p>  <p>  However, the Programme will also work with a small number of rural schools - for example schools on 80km/h roads outside town or village boundaries - to devise some infrastructure interventions that can promote active travel in such locations. These will be based more on slower speeds and highlighting the presence of a school. </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.46" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB01100">Public Transport</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.47.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1564" speakername="Duncan Smith" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB01200"><p><i>24.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport his plans to review all bus, rail and tram infrastructure to ensure transport hubs are adequately resourced and accessible for persons with disabilities; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[11049/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.48.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB01300"><p>As Minister for Transport, I am fully committed to strengthening public transport offerings and progressively making them accessible for all, especially for Persons with Disabilities, Persons with Reduced Mobility and Older People. </p>  <p>  In line with the United Nations Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities (UNCRPD), and the National Disability Inclusion Strategy (NDIS) my Department and its agencies are progressively making public transport accessible for people with disabilities, including in rural areas.</p>  <p>  We are doing that by ensuring that new infrastructure and services are accessible from the start and retrofitting older (legacy) infrastructure and facilities to make them accessible.</p>  <p>  This means that accessibility features, such as wheelchair accessibility and audio/visual aids, are built into all new public transport infrastructure projects and vehicles from the design stage. Newer systems such as the Luas are fully accessible, as are all new buses purchased by the NTA. </p>  <p>  However, the real challenge is in relation to upgrading older infrastructure and facilities to make them accessible. The difficulties and frustrations experienced by people with disabilities using such legacy infrastructure, bus and train stations, have been outlined many times.</p>  <p>  In relation to these legacy bus and trains stations, or hubs as they are sometimes called, my Department funds the multi-annual ringfenced Public Transport Accessibility Retrofit Programme. This programme, which is managed by the NTA, includes projects to upgrade bus bays at regional bus and train stations and to upgrade train stations to make them accessible to wheelchair users.</p>  <p>  In relation to bus stations, accessibility audits have now been carried out at 18 stations, In 2021, the NTA provided funding to install wheelchair accessible bays for coaches with wheelchair lifts and other external improvements in 23 Bus Eireann stations.</p>  <p>  Turning to train stations, accessibility works have either been recently completed or are ongoing at several stations. For example, footbridges were installed at Carlow, Ennis and Edgeworthstown stations last year, while works are underway at Dalkey and Gormanstown stations.</p>  <p>  This is in addition to the four-year &ldquo;Big Lift&rdquo; programme that Irish Rail is undertaking to upgrade lifts at 52 stations across the network. On the Luas network,  a system-wide upgrade of lifts is planned, with a scoping exercise currently being undertaken. These projects are particularly important as lifts out of service significantly impacts people with disabilities.</p>  <p>  Of course, in addition, to make the &ldquo;hard&rdquo; infrastructure and services accessible, it is crucial to provide the &ldquo;softer&rdquo; type of support to enable Persons with Disabilities to travel independently on public transport, including traversing through bus and train stations.</p>  <p>  The NTA and the transport companies have several initiatives underway which aligns with the UNCRPD, including the provision of Disability Awareness Training to frontline staff, the rollout of the Just a Minute (JAM) Card to assist anyone with a communications difficulty, and ensuring that information is provided in accessible formats for public transport services at stations and platforms.</p>  <p>  In addition, the Travel Assistance Scheme, managed by Dublin Bus, aims to give people with disabilities the confidence they need to use public transport and has been successfully operating for 13 years in the Greater Dublin Area. To further this, the NTA plans to roll out the Travel Assist Scheme to Cork later this year.</p>  <p>  I am fully committed to the continual improvement of accessibility within the public transport system. </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.49" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB01400">Road Projects</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.50.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1491" speakername="Brian Stanley" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB01500"><p><i>25.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the position regarding prioritising the provision of a new relief road for the N80 in Mountmellick. <b>[11271/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.51.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB01600"><p>As Minister for Transport, I have responsibility for overall policy and exchequer funding in relation to the National Roads Programme. Once funding arrangements have been put in place with Transport Infrastructure Ireland, under the Roads Acts 1993-2015, and in line with the National Development Plan, the planning, design, improvement and upgrading of individual national roads is a matter for TII, in conjunction with the local authorities concerned. TII ultimately delivers the National Roads Programme in line with Project Ireland 2040, the National Planning Framework and the NDP.</p>  <p>  The proposed N80 Mountmellick Bypass is not included among those projects which have been identified for development during the period of the NDP. However, following consultation with TII, I can advise the Deputy that Laois County Council is currently in the process of finalising the Strategic Assessment Report as required by the Public Spending Code which will set out the project rationale, the objectives and establish and assess a long-list of potential options.</p>  <p>  I understand that an allocation of &euro;100,000 was previously provided by TII to the Council to assist in this regard.  Submission of the final report to TII for review is expected in early 2022. If TII is satisfied that the report meets the required standards and that there is a justification for developing the proposal further, it can approve the project to proceed to the next stage of Preliminary Business Case. </p>  <p>  Any progression will be subject to compliance with government policy, availability of funding and further approvals. All projects under the NDP, or indeed any proposed projects outside of the scope of the Plan, will typically require the necessary approvals under the Public Spending Code. This will include Government approval in cases where project costs are estimated to be above &euro;100 million.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.52" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB01700">Public Transport</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.53.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1584" speakername="Bernard Durkan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB01800"><p><i>26.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the way that the commuter belt in north County Kildare is likely to be served by proposed changes in bus and rail services in the area; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[11493/22]</b></p></ques>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.54.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1584" speakername="Bernard Durkan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB01900"><p><i>235.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the extent to which the bus services serving north County Kildare will be reorganised to provide a better service to all areas; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12274/22]</b></p></ques>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.55.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1584" speakername="Bernard Durkan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB02000"><p><i>236.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the extent to which bus and rail services are likely to interact to provide a better service to the commuters of north County Kildare; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12275/22]</b></p></ques>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.56.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1584" speakername="Bernard Durkan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB02100"><p><i>237.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the revised bus services that are likely to serve Clonaugh, Maynooth, County Kildare as per previous representations; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12276/22]</b></p></ques>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.57.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1584" speakername="Bernard Durkan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB02200"><p><i>238.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the steps being taken to ensure that places such as Ardclough, Straffan, County Kildare receive coverage under the revised bus services currently proposed; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12277/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.58.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB02300"><p>I propose to take Questions Nos. 26, 235, 236, 237 and 238 together.</p>  <p>  As Minister for Transport, I have responsibility for policy and overall funding in relation to public transport; however, I am not involved in the day-to-day operations of public transport. The National Transport Authority (NTA) has statutory responsibility for securing the provision of public passenger transport services nationally and for the scheduling of these services in conjunction with the relevant transport operators.   </p>  <p>  In light of the Authority's responsibility in this area, I have forwarded the Deputy's specific questions in relation to the proposed changes in bus and rail services in the commuter belt in north County Kildare to the NTA for direct reply.  Please advise my private office if you do not receive a response within ten working days.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.59" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB02400">Rail Network</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.60.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1501" speakername="Rose Conway-Walsh" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB02500"><p><i>27.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport if he will seek to have the Western Rail Corridor included in the TEN-T programme; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[11992/22]</b></p></ques>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.61.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1501" speakername="Rose Conway-Walsh" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB02600"><p><i>94.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport if the all-Ireland strategic rail review will provide the basis for the inclusion of the north of Ireland within the TEN-T programme as is the case with other territories outside of the EU; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[11993/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.62.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB02700"><p>I propose to take Questions Nos. 27 and 94 together.</p><p>As the Deputy may be aware, the European Commission&rsquo;s review of the 2013 Trans-European Transport Network (TEN-T) Regulation commenced in 2019.  My Department participated fully in the review process. In August 2019, my predecessor, Minister Ross, made a submission to the European Commissioner for Transport, Violeta Bulc, regarding the review.  A copy of that submission, and Commissioner Bulc&rsquo;s reply, is available on my Department&rsquo;s website at the following link:</p><p><i>www.gov.ie/en/publication/3c921e-submission-to-commissioner-bulc-for-a-revision-of-the-core-ten-t-net/</i>.</p><p>Regarding the rail network, my Department informed the Commission that our position on the TEN-T rail network will be informed by the results of the ongoing all-island Strategic Rail Review and that we would hope to have the outcome of the Review reflected in the maps. The Strategic Rail Review is being undertaken in co-operation with the Department for Infrastructure Northern Ireland and will inform the development of the railway sector on the Island of Ireland over the coming decades.  The Review will consider the potential scope for improved rail services along the various existing, or future potential, corridors of the network.  That scope includes the Western Rail Corridor and connectivity with Northern Ireland.</p><p>For the Deputy&rsquo;s information, the Commission completed its review of the TEN-T Regulation in May 2021 and the evaluation report is available at the following link:</p><p><i>eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX%3A52021SC0117</i>.</p><p>In December 2021, the EU Commission published its proposal for a revised TEN-T Regulation and negotiations on the text have now begun in Brussels. My Department is currently examining the proposal in depth to ensure that Irish concerns can be identified and addressed during the negotiation process.</p><p>The full text of the proposal is available here:</p><p><i>eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/ALL/?uri=COM:2021:812:FIN</i>.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.63" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB02800">Public Transport</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.64.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1577" speakername="Catherine Connolly" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB02900"><p><i>28.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport further to Parliamentary Question No. 14 of 16 December 2021, the timeline for the upcoming review of the Galway Transport Strategy; the terms of reference for the review; the timeline and terms of reference for the feasibility study for light rail in Galway which will be undertaken as part of the review; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[11943/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.65.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB03000"><p>The review of the Galway Transport Strategy will commence later this year and will be led by the National Transport Authority (NTA), in cooperation with Galway City Council and Galway County Council.  </p>  <p>  As I have stated previously, I believe there is a need to review the Strategy and take stock of developments since its publication in 2016.  In my view, the feasibility study for light rail in Galway is best considered within the context of this review rather than carrying out a stand-alone study.  This approach allows for a multi-modal perspective and integration within an overall land-use plan. </p>  <p>  The review of the Strategy will include a comprehensive analysis of changes to population projections, development density, employment forecasts and future travel demand patterns since the finalisation of the current Strategy.  This analysis will be utilised to reassess the public transport needs across Galway city and the potential role all modes of transport, including light rail, can play in meeting those needs.  </p></reply>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.66" nospeaker="true" ><p>Question No. 29 answered orally.</p></speech>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.68.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1504" speakername="Peadar T&oacute;ib&iacute;n" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB03300"><p><i>30.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the breakdown of public transport spending per county from 2015 to 2021, in tabular form <b>[12106/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.69.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB03400"><p>As Minister for Transport, I have responsibility for policy and overall funding in relation to public transport; however, I am not involved in the day-to-day operations of public transport services. The National Transport Authority (NTA) has responsibility for the collection and publication of statistics relating to public transport.</p>  <p>  Therefore, I have forwarded the Deputy&rsquo;s question, in relation to the breakdown of public transport spending per county from 2015 to 2021, to the NTA for direct reply.  Please advise my private office if you do not receive a reply within ten working days.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.70" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB03500">Driver Licences</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.71.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1508" speakername="Michael Fitzmaurice" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB03600"><p><i>31.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport his views on a motion calling on the Road Safety Authority to set up a competitive tendering process to provide a walk-in service at multiple centres to issue and renew driving licences, which is adequately staffed and take cash payments; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12128/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.72.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1578" speakername="Hildegarde Naughton" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB03700"><p>The motion referred to by the Deputy was discussed in the D&aacute;il on Wednesday 2 March 2022 as part of Private Members Business. The motion was not opposed and I would ask the Deputy to refer to my speech for my views..</p></reply>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.73" nospeaker="true" ><p>Question No. 32 answered orally.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.74" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB03900">Cycling Facilities</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.75.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1594" speakername="Brian Leddin" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB04000"><p><i>33.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport his plans for the development of safe and segregated cycle lanes in towns and villages outside of regional cities and larger urban centres; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12118/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.76.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB04100"><p>The Programme for Government has committed to Exchequer spending of approximately &euro;360 million per annum on walking and cycling over the lifetime of the Government, equivalent to 20% of the 2020 transport capital budget. This investment will help support the planned delivery of almost 1,000 kilometres of improved walking and cycling infrastructure by 2025 as well as additional investment in Greenways.</p>  <p>  2021 saw the first ever major Active Travel investment programme for rural Ireland. &euro;72.8m was allocated to 19 local authorities to support the delivery of 340 sustainable transport projects. It should be noted this allocation was more than the entire Active Travel budget for 2019.</p>  <p>  This year has seen another increase in my Department's overall funding for cycling and walking, in line with the Government&rsquo;s prioritisation of Active Travel and Greenways. As well as an increased allocation of &euro;289 million administered through the National Transport Authority (NTA) to Active Travel, I was delighted to also announce funding of &euro;60 million for investment in our Greenways.</p>  <p>  The overall increase in funding across urban and rural Ireland will not only support the construction and improvement of safe and connected walking and cycling infrastructure, but also the deployment of almost 250 dedicated Active Travel staff in local authorities around the country.</p>  <p>  In addition to the increased funding for walking and cycling infrastructure, a number of smaller-scale initiatives are being progressed by my Department to support and promote efforts to increase safe Active Travel. The Department of Transport funds the delivery of CycleRight training through Cycling Ireland, which delivers cycling training to school-children around the country and equips them with the skills to cycle safely.</p>  <p>  In partnership with the Department of Education we also launched the Safe Routes to Schools Programme last year, which aims to accelerate the delivery of safe walking, scooting and cycling infrastructure on key access routes to schools. It has had a great response, with applications received from schools in every county in Ireland.</p>  <p>  The step-change in funding and the introduction of various innovative measures to encourage safe and connected Active Travel is proof of the Government's commitment to this area, and I look forward to the delivery of the numerous projects and programmes around the country, including in rural areas. </p>  <p>  Furthermore, TII (Transport Infrastructure Ireland) are developing a National Cycle Network that will identify routes for development all around the country that will work with the Regional and Local Cycle Networks being developed by the NTA. </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.77" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB04200">Public Transport</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.78.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1516" speakername="James O'Connor" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB04300"><p><i>34.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport if an update will be provided on the roll-out of the youth travel card. <b>[12112/22]</b></p></ques>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.79.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1564" speakername="Duncan Smith" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB04400"><p><i>46.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport when he expects the roll-out of 50% discount fares for students and those under 23 years of age; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[11048/22]</b></p></ques>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.80.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1617" speakername="Marc &Oacute; Cathasaigh" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB04500"><p><i>54.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport his views on the inconsistencies in public transport fares for 16- to 18- year-olds; the steps he will take to ensure that an appropriate fare is available to all young persons across all types of public transport in Ireland; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12130/22]</b></p></ques>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.81.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1564" speakername="Duncan Smith" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB04600"><p><i>56.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport if he will provide an update on the student travel card; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[11047/22]</b></p></ques>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.82.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1523" speakername="Colm Burke" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB04700"><p><i>73.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the progress made by his Department to date in respect of the reduction in public transport fares by approximately 20% as part of measures to help with the cost of living; the timeline of when this measure will be put in place; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[11946/22]</b></p></ques>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.83.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1593" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB04800"><p><i>75.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the progress on the introduction of the new half price public transport fare for 19-23-year-olds; and the timeline for the reduction of fares by 20% as part of measures to help with the cost of living <b>[12103/22]</b></p></ques>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.84.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1562" speakername="Alan Farrell" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB04900"><p><i>85.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the progress made at introducing the new half price public transport fare for young persons. <b>[12145/22]</b></p></ques>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.85.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1515" speakername="David Stanton" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB05000"><p><i>106.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport if he will report on the progress made by his Department in introducing a half price public transport fare for young persons; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12082/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.86.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB05100"><p>I propose to take Questions Nos. 34, 46, 54, 56, 73, 75, 85 and 106 together.</p>  <p>  As Minister for Transport, I have responsibility for policy and overall funding in relation to public transport; I am not involved in the day-to-day operations of public transport, nor decisions on fares. It is the National Transport Authority (NTA) that has responsibility for the regulation of fares charged to passengers in respect of public transport services, provided under public service obligation (PSO) contracts.</p>  <p>  The Government is strongly committed to helping combat the rising cost-of-living being experienced throughout the country. In this context, a suite of new measures is being introduced by Government to help with this issue, including a 20% average fare reduction on PSO services until the end of 2022. These discounted fares will benefit the hundreds of thousands of people across the country who use public transport every day. A further &euro;54m in Exchequer funding has been secured to allow for the introduction of these discounted fares, this is in addition to the REV22 allocations. The NTA will work with the PSO public transport operators in the coming weeks to commence rolling out these fare reductions across the public transport network in late April/ early May. </p>  <p>  Also, in recognition of the importance of incentivising young people to use public transport, as part of Budget 2022 I secured &euro;25m of funding to provide for the introduction of a young adult card (YAC) which will allow any person nationwide who is between 19 and 23 years old, to avail of an entitlement for discounted travel costs, and to increase the level of discount over and above the current student discount to an average of discount of 50% across all services, including city, intercity and rural services. It is envisaged that the discount will initially be made available on PSO services, and then broadened to include commercial operators at a later date.  This will not only promote modal shift in the transport sector among this age group but should also contribute towards a reduced reliance on private transport with associated benefit of transport emission savings.  The NTA has commenced work in relation to the implementation of the new fares&rsquo; structures for young adults, and this includes the application process and establishing a definitive timeline for the introduction of the Scheme. </p>  <p>  In light of the NTA's responsibility in this area, I have forwarded the Deputies  questions  to the NTA for direct reply.  Please advise my private office if you do not receive a response within ten working days.</p></reply>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.88.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1523" speakername="Colm Burke" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB05300"><p><i>35.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the progress made to date in respect of the process to procure up to 80 double-deck battery electric buses; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[11947/22]</b></p></ques>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.89.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1473" speakername="Neale Richmond" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB05400"><p><i>92.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the number of electric hybrid buses in operation on public service transport routes; when more are expected to be added to the public transport fleet; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[11828/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.90.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB05500"><p>I propose to take Questions Nos. 35 and 92 together.</p><p>As Minister for Transport, I have responsibility for policy and overall funding in relation to public transport.  The National Transport Authority (NTA) has statutory responsibility for the planning and development of public transport infrastructure, including the procurement of the PSO bus fleet. </p><p>Noting the NTA's responsibility in the matter, I have referred the Deputy's question to the NTA for a direct reply.  Please contact my private office if you do not receive a reply within 10 days.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.91" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB05600">Electric Vehicles</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.92.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1564" speakername="Duncan Smith" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB05700"><p><i>36.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport if he will consider introducing a grant to purchase electric vehicles for persons with disabilities for whom public transport is an unreliable option; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[11050/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.93.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB05800"><p>The Government is fully committed to supporting the roll out of EVs so as to ensure the ambitious commitments as set out in the Programme for Government and the Climate Action Plan are met. In this regard, this year has seen continued support to further enable the roll out of Electric Vehicles and related charging infrastructure.  </p>  <p>  As the Deputy will be aware, a comprehensive suite of measures is available to assist individuals, including those with disabilities, who wish to drive an EV, including purchase grants for private car owners and taxi drivers, VRT relief, reduced tolls, home charger grants, favourable motor and BIK tax rates, as well as a comprehensive charging network. These measures have collectively contributed to increased take up of EVs in Ireland in recent years, albeit from a low base, to over 50,500 now. </p>  <p>  In addition, the Department convened the Electric Vehicle Policy Pathway (EVPP) Working Group to produce a roadmap to achieving the 2030 EV target. The recommendations of the EVPP Working Group were approved by Government and the full report is available online. In line with the Group&rsquo;s recommendations to support the transition to EVs:  </p>  <p>  - The generous suite of EV supports already in place in Ireland has been retained until at least end-2022. Work is ongoing to identify additional measures to further incentivise EVs and/or disincentivise fossil fuelled vehicles. Overall, cost-effective, targeted policy supports will continue to be developed and strengthened over the coming years; and   </p>  <p>  - Work is underway to establish An Office for Low Emission Vehicles, as a matter of priority, to co-ordinate the implementation of existing and future EV measures and infrastructure.  </p>  <p>  Overall, the Department is acutely aware that the cost of electric vehicles remains an issue for many consumers. To this end, electric vehicle policy is kept under continuous review to endeavour to make low emission vehicles affordable.   </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.94" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB05900">Driver Licences</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.95.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1601" speakername="Alan Dillon" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB06000"><p><i>37.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the reason walk-in services at National Driver Licence Service offices across the west are no longer available; the reason a hybrid system to book an appointment is not in place for those who have limited internet connectivity or difficulties with digital illiteracy; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12123/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.96.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1578" speakername="Hildegarde Naughton" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB06100"><p>Attendance at National Driver Licence Service (NDLS) front offices is no longer available without an appointment. Previously, people with an appointment had preference and attendance without an appointment was facilitated if time permitted. </p>  <p>  Market analysis undertaken by the Road Safety Authority in advance of the procurement of the current service contract showed that more bids and better value for money would be attainable if the service was delivered on the basis of appointments only. An appointment-only service manages queues, gives certainty to customers and prevents overcrowding, queueing and long waits. It also allows the service provider to manage the resourcing of the service because demand is predictable rather than having peaks and troughs during different times of the day.</p>  <p>  The decision to move to appointments only was assisted by the availability of an online licence renewal and application service (which accounts for 40% of total applications) and the option for older customers to apply by post.  </p>  <p>  Appointments to attend at a NDLS office can be made by telephone on 0818 919 090 as well as online. </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.97" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB06200">Bus Services</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.98.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1486" speakername="Br&iacute;d Smith" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB06300"><p><i>38.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport his views on the requirement of some bus routes to meet specific timing points across Dublin as part of the National Transport Authority's minimum performance standards and the impact these are having on the services provided to passengers; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12060/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.99.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB06400"><p>As Minister for Transport, I have responsibility for policy and overall funding in relation to public transport; however, I am not involved in the day-to-day operations of public transport. The National Transport Authority (NTA) has statutory responsibility for securing the provision of public passenger transport services nationally and for the scheduling of these services in conjunction with the relevant transport operators.  </p>  <p>  In light of the Authority's responsibility in this area, I have forwarded the Deputy's specific question in relation to the timetabling of some bus routes to meet specific timing points across Dublin to the NTA for direct reply.  Please advise my private office if you do not receive a response within ten working days.  </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.100" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB06500">Rail Network</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.101.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1509" speakername="Maurice Quinlivan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB06600"><p><i>39.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the plans there are to increase the frequency of trains on the Castleconnell Station to Limerick route; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[10360/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.102.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB06700"><p>As the Minister for Transport, I have responsibility for policy and overall funding in relation to public transport; however, I am not involved in the day-to-day provision and operation of public transport. </p><p>The issue raised by the Deputy regarding plans to increase the frequency of trains on the Castleconnell Station to Limerick route is an operational matter for the National Transport Authority (NTA) in conjunction with Iarnr&oacute;d &Eacute;ireann and I have therefore forwarded the Deputy's question to the NTA for direct reply. </p><p>Please advise my private office if you do not receive a response within ten working days.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.103" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB06800">Electric Vehicles</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.104.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1482" speakername="Se&aacute;n Canney" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB06900"><p><i>40.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport if his attention has been drawn to an issue between the ESB and electrical contractors in which the ESB is preventing electrical contractors from connecting electric vehicle chargers directly to the meter board in circumstances in which a connection to the meter cabinet is not possible even though the works are being carried out in compliance with the ESB protocols; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[5193/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.105.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300059#WRB07000"><p>Having an effective and reliable recharging network is essential to enabling drivers to choose electric. Charging at home is the most convenient and cheapest way to recharge. Targeting the installation of smart home chargers is a priority as we look to moving towards more energy efficient and sustainable ways to charge. A grant is available from the SEAI for those individuals seeking to install a home charger. Work is currently being progressed to expand the EV home charger grant to include shared parking in apartment blocks and similar developments. My Department is working closely with the SEAI and expects a scheme for apartments to open shortly.</p>  <p>  I have been informed that ESB Networks contacted the National Standards Authority of Ireland (NSAI) in late 2020 around the provision of EV Home Charging connection on a customer&rsquo;s electrical installation at the outside meter box.</p>  <p>  ESBN received confirmation that installation was acceptable and in early 2021 Safe Electric published a newsletter to inform their members of the possibility of using this connection.</p>  <p>  Safe Electric are due to publish an update shortly containing further information for registered electrical contractors. </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.107" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC00200">Fishing Industry</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.108.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1625" speakername="John Brady" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC00300"><p><i>41.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the progress that has been made towards the awarding of compensation to a person (details supplied) as directed by the European Commission; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[11733/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.109.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC00400"><p>I would like to express sympathy for the challenging situation of this case. However, my department has no role in providing financial compensation to the fishing sector. The Marine Survey Office of my department does not become involved with the financial arrangements for individual vessels in order to maintain the necessary separation of commercial and safety considerations. Matters regarding compensation may be within the remit of my colleague the Minister of Agriculture, Food and the Marine. I would suggest that the individual concerned should make contact with the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine to pursue such matters.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.110" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC00500">Ports Policy</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.111.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1473" speakername="Neale Richmond" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC00600"><p><i>42.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport if he will undertake upgrades to Irish ports to ensure they are equipped to deal with the increase of activity due to Brexit; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[11829/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.112.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC00700"><p>As a consequence of Brexit, substantial physical infrastructure was put in place at Dublin Port and Rosslare Europort to provide for the effective management of new check and control requirements on trade with Great Britain. This infrastructure was in place at the end of the Transition Period and has been operational since 1 January 2021. This was one of the most critical and visible aspects of the Government&rsquo;s preparations for Brexit. This work was coordinated by the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform with the development of the required infrastructure by the Office of Public Works on behalf of the Revenue Commissioners, the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine, and the HSE.</p>  <p>  Planning is continuing for a new state of the art Border Control Post in Rosslare Europort for the carrying out of customs, agriculture and health checks on trade with Great Britain. Currently these checks are undertaken in temporary facilities in Kilrane, some 1.3km outside of the Port. Planning permission for the permanent facilities was secured by the OPW in 2021 and a public procurement process is underway. The project will avail of funding under the Brexit Adjustment Reserve. </p>  <p>  Overall, Ireland has seen a significant number of new shipping services develop over the last two years in response to Brexit.  Our ports continue to respond with new and additional direct ferry links to mainland Europe with increased capacity coming on stream in response to Brexit and the pandemic (including to Cherbourg, Dunkerque, Zeebrugge, Rotterdam, Amsterdam, Antwerp, Roscoff and Santander). </p>  <p>  In line with NDP objectives and National Ports Policy, the State ports are continuing to progress projects under their Masterplans. The Ports of Dublin, Cork, Shannon Foynes and Rosslare will spend &euro;144m in capital expenditure in 2022 and up to &euro;473m over the next five years. These non-exchequer funded investments will enhance Ireland&rsquo;s capacity and connectivity and will allow the ports to respond to market needs, handle increases in ship sizes and frequency and serve the import and export needs of the economy.</p>  <p>  In Ireland, the State Ports operate as independent commercial entities with no funding from the State. All infrastructure development must be funded through their own revenues, borrowing or disposal of assets. Additionally eligible TEN-T ports can apply for funding for port infrastructure under the Connecting Europe Funding facility (CEF) which is the funding instrument for the EU's Trans-European Transport Network (TEN-T). </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.113" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC00800">Public Transport</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.114.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1584" speakername="Bernard Durkan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC00900"><p><i>43.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the measures taken or proposed to ensure that the transport sector is capable of doing its job without contributing to inflation; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[11492/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.115.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC01000"><p>As the Deputy will be aware, transport is a derived demand - one that is driven by economic and social need.  A cost-efficient sector, including affordable and accessible public transport services, is vital to a functioning economy.</p>  <p>  In this context, a number of measures have been taken to ensure services remain affordable.  In Budget 2022, my department secured approximately &euro;538m of funding for Public Service Obligation (PSO) and Local Link services. &euro;25m was also provided for the introduction of a young adult card (YAC).  This new measure will enable any person aged between 19 and 23 years old to avail of an average fare discount of 50% across all public transport services, including city, intercity and rural services.</p>  <p>  Further, as part of a suite of new measures being introduced by Government to help combat the rising cost-of-living being experienced throughout the country, a 20% average fare reduction on PSO services is also due to be introduced over the coming weeks. These discounted fares, which will benefit the hundreds of thousands of people across the country who use PSO public transport every day, will cost &euro;54m and will be in place until the end of 2022. </p>  <p>  Finally, in relation to the impacts of increasing biofuel rates on fuel prices, an offsetting policy measure of a 1c per litre reduction in the NORA Levy and a 1c per litre reduction in excise has been introduced in agreement with the Minister for Finance. The excise relief takes effect from 1 April 2022 and will be in place until Budget Day in October 2022. </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.116" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC01100">Road Network</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.117.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1575" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC01200"><p><i>44.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the allocation for the capital development of national roads for each of the past five years; the reason planning has ceased on a number of urgently needed national roads in 2022; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[11777/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.118.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC01300"><p>As Minister for Transport I have responsibility for overall policy and exchequer funding in relation to the National Roads Programme. Under the Roads Acts 1993-2015 and in line with the National Development Plan (NDP), the planning, design and construction of individual national roads is a matter for Transport Infrastructure Ireland (TII), in conjunction with the local authorities concerned.</p><p>Approximately &euro;615 million of exchequer capital funds have been provided for national roads through TII to local authorities in 2022. The 2022 funding allocations are made having regard for the NDP, which balances investment in transport against other priorities of Government, such as housing and health over the lifetime of the Plan. It was necessary to prioritise projects for funding in a manner which seeks to achieve key outcomes in line with the NDP. Resulting from this, while a large majority of the projects under the NDP were issued a funding allocation in 2022, TII were unable to provide an allocation for a small number of projects. The delivery programme for these projects will be kept under review for next year and considered in terms of the overall funding envelope available to TII.</p><p>The table below sets out the exchequer allocations made to TII for new capital projects in the past 5 years.</p><p><b>Allocations to TII for last 5 years for new projects</b> <table>    <tr>       <th>Year </th>       <th>&euro; New project development</th>    </tr>    <tr>       <td>2017 </td>       <td>147,759,475 </td>    </tr>    <tr>       <td>2018 </td>       <td>97,802,019 </td>    </tr>    <tr>       <td>2019 </td>       <td>131,759,472 </td>    </tr>    <tr>       <td>2020 </td>       <td>228,756,229 </td>    </tr>    <tr>       <td>2021 </td>       <td>301,315,000 </td>    </tr> </table> </p><p>Regarding the progression of certain projects in the NDP, I have referred your question to TII for a direct reply. Please advise my private office if you do not receive a reply within 10 working days.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.119" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC01400">Driver Licences</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.120.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1522" speakername="Mick Barry" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC01500"><p><i>45.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport if he will ensure that possession of a public services card will not be made obligatory to obtain a driver&rsquo;s licence or learner&rsquo;s permit; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12109/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.121.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1578" speakername="Hildegarde Naughton" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC01600"><p>A public services card (PSC) is only required when applying for or renewing a learner permit or driving licence online. The PSC is used to confirm a person&rsquo;s identity and image in place of face-to-face verification. The Road Safety Authority is recognised as a specified body for the use of a PSC under the Social Welfare Consolidation Act 2005 (as amended by the Social Welfare and Pensions (No. 2) Act 2009).</p>  <p>  When applying for a driving licence, a person can verify their identity in person at a National Driver Licence Service (NDLS) front office. NDLS offices are open to the public, but an appointment must be made to attend. It is no longer possible to attend an office without an appointment. Appointments can be made online or by telephone. A public services card is not needed to book an appointment.</p></reply>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.122" nospeaker="true" ><p>Question No. 46 answered with Question No. 34.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.123" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC01800">Electric Vehicles</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.124.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1549" speakername="Richard Bruton" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC01900"><p><i>47.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport if he will indicate his approach to having rental schemes for e-scooters; and the framework under which they will evolve. <b>[11830/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.125.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC02000"><p>I am committed to decarbonising the transport sector by encouraging a modal shift away from travel by private car towards sustainable alternatives. Micromobility vehicles like e-scooters have an important role to play as we transition to a cleaner and greener economy and society.</p>  <p>  The Programme for Government has committed us to legislating for e-scooters and e-bikes and this process has been commenced through the Road Traffic and Roads Bill, which is shortly expected to move to committee stage before the Oireachtas. </p>  <p>  The bill proposes the establishment of a new vehicle category called &ldquo;powered personal transporters&rdquo;, which will include micromobility vehicles like e-scooters, segways and hoverboards. Registration, taxation, and licensing will not be required for their use.</p>  <p>  The bill will also confer powers to set out appropriate technical and safety standards and rules for the safe use of e-scooters in regulations and preparatory drafting work has already commenced. My Department has consulted with key stakeholders to inform this process, including the Road Safety Authority, the National Transport Authority, An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, representation from industry and accessibility advocates and local authorities.</p>  <p>  The Road Traffic Acts do not provide for powers to establish public or private vehicle rental schemes and accordingly such matters are not addressed in the bill. The governance of such schemes would be a matter for the local authority in question.</p>  <p>  I will shortly publish a new Sustainable Mobility Policy which will set out a strategic framework to 2030 for active travel and public transport to support Ireland's overall requirement to achieve a 51% reduction in carbon emissions by the end of this decade.  The policy will primarily focus on measures to promote and facilitate active travel and public transport for all and, in doing so, encourage less private car usage nationally to support our climate commitment.   This will include considering how best to promote the adoption of micromobility schemes and the integration of newer modes such as e-scooters with other modes.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.126" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC02100">Road Projects</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.127.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1482" speakername="Se&aacute;n Canney" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC02200"><p><i>48.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport if his Department has received an application from Galway County Council for funding for the inner relief road for Tuam, County Galway; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12072/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.128.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC02300"><p>The improvement and maintenance of regional and local roads (RLR) is the statutory responsibility of each local authority, in accordance with the provisions of Section 13 of the Roads Act 1993. Works on those roads are funded from local authorities' own resources supplemented by State road grants.  The initial selection and prioritisation of works to be funded is also a matter for the local authority. </p>  <p>  The primary focus for capital investment under the Regional and Local Road Grant Programme continues to be the protection and renewal of the regional and local road network with some limited investment in road improvement projects. </p>  <p>  Any projects proposed by local authorities for consideration under the Specific or Strategic Grant Programmes are assessed by the Department on a case-by-case basis.  All projects put forward by local authorities for consideration must comply with the requirements of the Public Spending Code and my Department's Capital Appraisal Framework. Given the limited funding available for regional and local road improvement works it is important for local authorities to prioritise projects within their overall area of responsibility with these requirements in mind.</p>  <p>  My Department has not received an application from Galway County Council for funding for an inner relief road for Tuam.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.129" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC02400">Bus Services</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.130.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1480" speakername="Jennifer Carroll MacNeill" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC02500"><p><i>49.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the status of the BusConnects roll-out in Dublin, specifically the proposed E1, Balbutcher Lane via city centre, route; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[11801/22]</b></p></ques>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.131.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1469" speakername="Mark Ward" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC02600"><p><i>104.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the status of the BusConnects C spine in the Lucan area; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[11581/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.132.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC02700"><p>I propose to take Questions Nos. 49 and 104 together.</p><p>As Minister for Transport, I have responsibility for policy and overall funding in relation to public transport.  The National Transport Authority (NTA) has statutory responsibility for the planning and development of public transport infrastructure in the Greater Dublin Area, including the BusConnects programme.</p><p>Noting the NTA's responsibility in the matter, I have referred the Deputy's question to the NTA for a direct reply.  Please contact my private office if you do not receive a reply within 10 days.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.133" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC02800">Road Projects</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.134.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1568" speakername="Paul McAuliffe" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC02900"><p><i>50.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the status of the Finglas roundabout scheme; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12080/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.135.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC03000"><p>As Minister for Transport, I have responsibility for policy and overall funding in relation to public and sustainable transport. The National Transport Authority (NTA) is responsible for the development and implementation of public transport and active travel infrastructure, allocating the funding provided by my Department at project level and working in conjunction with the relevant local authorities. This includes the project mentioned by the Deputy, namely the Finglas roundabouts scheme.</p>  <p>  Noting the NTA's responsibilities in the matter, I have referred your question to the NTA for a detailed reply. Please advise my private office if you do not receive a reply within 10 working days.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.136" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC03100">Public Transport</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.137.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1549" speakername="Richard Bruton" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC03200"><p><i>51.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport if he has encouraged the development of consumer satisfaction feedback on public transport to provide a spur to delivering passenger needs. <b>[11831/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.138.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC03300"><p>As Minister for Transport, I have responsibility for policy and overall funding in relation to public transport; however, I am not involved in the day-to-day operations of public transport. The National Transport Authority (NTA) has statutory responsibility for securing the provision of public passenger transport services nationally.</p><p>In light of the Authority's responsibility in this area, I have forwarded the Deputy's specific question in relation to the possible development of consumer satisfaction feedback on public transport to provide a spur to delivering passenger needs, to the NTA for direct reply.  Please advise my private office if you do not receive a response within ten working days.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.139" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC03400">Bus Services</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.140.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1482" speakername="Se&aacute;n Canney" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC03500"><p><i>52.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the progress is being made with the proposal to provide a bus lane from Claregalway to Galway city along the N83; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12073/22]</b></p></ques>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.141.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1453" speakername="Thomas Gould" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC03600"><p><i>76.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport if he will confirm that the next draft of BusConnects in Cork will have a route from the northside to the Munster Technological University <b>[12065/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.142.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC03700"><p>I propose to take Questions Nos. 52 and 76 together.</p><p>As Minister for Transport, I have responsibility for policy and overall funding in relation to public transport.  The National Transport Authority (NTA) has statutory responsibility for the planning and development of public transport infrastructure, including the BusConnects programme in our cities. </p><p>Noting the NTA's responsibility in the matter, I have referred the Deputy's question to the NTA for a direct reply.  Please contact my private office if you do not receive a reply within 10 days.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.143" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC03800">Road Projects</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.144.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1611" speakername="Jackie Cahill" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC03900"><p><i>53.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the details of the &euro;30,000 recently allocated to the Thurles inner relief road under the local and regional roads programme of his Department; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[11863/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.145.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC04000"><p>The improvement and maintenance of regional and local roads is the statutory responsibility of each local authority, in accordance with the provisions of Section 13 of the Roads Act 1993. Works on those roads are funded from local authorities' own resources supplemented by State road grants.  The initial selection and prioritisation of works to be funded is also a matter for the local authority. </p>  <p>  The primary focus for capital investment under my Department's Regional and Local Road Grant Programme continues to be the protection and renewal of the regional and local road network with some limited investment in road improvement projects. </p>  <p>  &euro;30,000 has been allocated to the Thurles Inner Relief Road scheme in 2022 to allow Tipperary County Council to appoint consultants to progress the detailed design of the scheme.</p></reply>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.146" nospeaker="true" ><p>Question No. 54 answered with Question No. 34.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.147" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC04200">Transport Policy</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.148.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1516" speakername="James O'Connor" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC04300"><p><i>55.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport his plans to place existing diesel vehicles ahead of the ban on new diesel car sales; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[10501/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.149.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC04400"><p>Passenger cars account for over half of all land transport emissions in Ireland; therefore, a transition to low and zero emission cars is one of the necessary changes if Ireland is to substantially reduce its transport emissions. Accordingly, electric vehicles (EVs) are a prominent mitigation measure in the Climate Action Plan and Ireland has set an ambitious target of nearly one million EVs on our roads by 2030. With approximately 50,500 EVs currently in Ireland, this target is very challenging but indicative of the scale of the transformation that is needed across all sectors if Ireland is to reduce national emissions and reach its legally binding emission ceiling in future years.</p><p>A national ambition has been firmly established that by 2030 all new cars and vans sold in Ireland will be zero-emission capable. </p><p>The European Commission have indicated that a complete ban of the marketing, import or registration of new ICE vehicles in a single Member State is not compatible with EU law, and an EU-wide approach is therefore required. Ireland was signatory to a non-paper to the Commission earlier this year requesting a phase-out date for the sale of new petrol and diesel cars and vans in the EU in line with the objective of climate neutrality by 2050 as well as the introduction of a legal framework that allows Member States to move ahead by taking action at national level to incentivise early phase-out of new petrol and diesel cars and vans. The paper can be viewed at <i>www.permanentrepresentations.nl/permanent-representations/pr-eu-brussels/documents/publications/2021/03/10/non-paper---transition-to-zero-emission-light-duty-vehicles</i>.</p><p>In addition, on Transport Day at COP26,  I signed a sponsored declaration to accelerate the transition to 100% zero emission cars and vans. The declaration is an important signal of ambition at a global level. In line with our Programme for Government commitments, Ireland has even greater ambitions, targeting a switch over of one million electric vehicles by 2030 to bring us on a trajectory to achieving electrification of all new car sales well ahead of 2035 </p><p>These declarations are consistent with Ireland&rsquo;s ambitions to tackle transport emissions. They follow the publication of the Climate Action Plan (CAP) &rsquo;21 which outlines a pathway to a radical and equitable transformation in Ireland&rsquo;s transport sector over the next nine years as it moves towards decarbonisation. Car manufacturers are responding to these initiatives by introducing a wide range of electric vehicles to the market, and over the coming decade, I envisage a progressive transition to EVs in our car fleet as electric vehicle technology becomes mainstream. </p><p>In this regard, my Department recently joined together with three other member states (BE, DK and LU) to propose joint amendments of the CO2 standards for cars and vans standards regulation regarding the 2027 targets, the ZLEV incentive mechanism and the small volume derogation. </p></reply>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.150" nospeaker="true" ><p>Question No. 56 answered with Question No. 34.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.151" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC04600">Public Transport</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.152.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1521" speakername="P&aacute;draig O'Sullivan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC04700"><p><i>57.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the status of the travel assistance scheme which is to be rolled out in Cork in 2022; when it is likely the pilot project will commence; if Bus &Eacute;ireann has recruited persons to work on the programme in Cork; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12107/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.153.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC04800"><p>As Minister for Transport, I have responsibility for policy and overall funding in relation to public transport. While I'm aware of the rollout of the Travel Assistance Scheme to Cork and welcome the pilot, I am not involved in the day-to-day operations of public transport. The National Transport Authority (NTA) has statutory responsibility for securing the provision of accessible public passenger transport services in conjunction with the respective service operator.  </p>  <p>  In that regard, the rollout of the Travel Assist Scheme is a matter for the NTA and l and I have forwarded your correspondence to the NTA for direct reply. Please advise my private office if you do not receive a response within ten working days.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.154" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC04900">Electric Vehicles</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.155.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1486" speakername="Br&iacute;d Smith" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC05000"><p><i>58.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport if he will commission a study to examine the impact on CO2 emissions of the delivery and production of one million electric vehicles; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12056/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.156.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC05100"><p>The European Commission has put forward a proposal to revise the existing CO<b><sub>2</sub></b>Standards Regulation to align it with the ambition of the EU Climate Law. It will put in place stronger CO<b><sub>2</sub></b>emissions standards for cars and vans to accelerate the transition to zero-emission mobility by requiring manufacturers, on a fleet-wide basis, to reduce the average emissions of cars and vans they produce. </p><p>Under the proposal, average emissions of new cars should be reduced by 55% from 2030 and 100% from 2035 compared to 2021 levels. For new vans, the net reduction targets would be 50% and 100% respectively. As a result, all new cars and vans registered as of 2035 in the EU will be zero-emission.</p><p>The proposal would also remove the ZLEV (zero- and light-emission vehicle) incentive scheme after 2030. This is part of the existing Regulation and allows manufacturers that produce more ZLEVs additional leeway in their overall target. It is expected that, at this stage, the market uptake of ZLEVs will be driven by the stricter CO2 targets applicable from 2030 rather than any incentive mechanisms. </p><p>Accelerating the transition to low emitting light duty vehicles (LDVs) is paramount to achieving Ireland's emission reduction targets. Emissions from cars and vans in Ireland dominate land transport emissions at 51% and 7% respectively, and Ireland has a national commitment to phase out sales of new petrol/diesel cars by 2030. Wider availability of zero-emission vehicles will provide Irish consumers with greater choice and accelerate the transition to zero-emission mobility.</p><p>While the proposed targets are welcome, Ireland is seeking opportunities to accelerate and increase the ambition of the file in recognition that early momentum in this decade is crucial to affect the substantial change required to reach the EU 2030 greenhouse gas emission reduction target and commitments made under the Paris Agreement.</p><p>Analysis for the uptake of EVs in Ireland is based on the assumption that Irish car fleet growth between 2020 and 2030 will be at a rate similar to between 2010 and 2020. It is expected that the sale of electric vehicles will displace those of internal combustion engines in the coming years which will replace CO2 emitting vehicles with zero-emission tailpipe equivalents. While EV battery production can result in higher CO2 emissions, as technology improves and more renewable energy sources are deployed globally, I anticipate that the CO2 impacts of battery production will reduce over the coming years.  I also note that Ireland does not have a vehicle-manufacturing sector, so the issue of production does not arise specifically with regard to our national emissions.  </p></reply>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.157" nospeaker="true" ><p>Question No. 59 answered orally.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.158" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC05300">Rail Network</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.159.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1491" speakername="Brian Stanley" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC05400"><p><i>60.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport his plans for increasing the services and passenger numbers on the Ballybrophy to Limerick rail line. <b>[11272/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.160.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300060#WRC05500"><p>As the Minister for Transport, I have responsibility for policy and overall funding in relation to public transport; however, I am not involved in the day-to-day provision and operation of public transport. </p><p>The issue raised by the Deputy regarding plans for increasing the services and passenger numbers on the Ballybrophy to Limerick rail line is an operational matter for the National Transport Authority (NTA) in conjunction with Iarnr&oacute;d &Eacute;ireann and I have therefore forwarded the Deputy's question to the NTA for direct reply. </p><p>Please advise my private office if you do not receive a response within ten working days.</p></reply>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.163.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1491" speakername="Brian Stanley" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD00300"><p><i>60.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport his plans for increasing the services and passenger numbers on the Ballybrophy to Limerick rail line. <b>[11272/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.164.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD00400"><p>As the Minister for Transport, I have responsibility for policy and overall funding in relation to public transport; however, I am not involved in the day-to-day provision and operation of public transport. </p><p>The issue raised by the Deputy regarding plans for increasing the services and passenger numbers on the Ballybrophy to Limerick rail line is an operational matter for the National Transport Authority (NTA) in conjunction with Iarnr&oacute;d &Eacute;ireann and I have therefore forwarded the Deputy's question to the NTA for direct reply. </p><p>Please advise my private office if you do not receive a response within ten working days.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.165" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD00500">Road Projects</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.166.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1575" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD00600"><p><i>61.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the processes that will have to be gone through to bring the development of the Galway city bypass M6/N6 road to construction; the projected timescale involved with each process; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[11776/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.167.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD00700"><p>As Minister for Transport I have responsibility for overall policy and exchequer funding in relation to the National Roads Programme. Under the Roads Acts 1993-2015 and in line with the National Development Plan (NDP), the planning, design and construction of individual national roads is a matter for Transport Infrastructure Ireland (TII), in conjunction with the local authorities concerned. This is also subject to the Public Spending Code and the necessary statutory approvals.</p>  <p>  Planning permission was granted by An Bord Plean&aacute;la on 6 December 2021, subject to conditions. As of today, three Judicial Reviews have been lodged. The progression of this project is dependent on the outcome of these reviews. In this context, TII is best placed to advise you on the current status of this project.</p>  <p>  Noting the above position, I have referred your question to TII for a direct reply. Please advise my private office if you do not receive a reply within 10 working days.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.168" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD00800">Road Network</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.169.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1510" speakername="John Paul Phelan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD00900"><p><i>62.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the changes he plans to make to ensure those national route improvements not funded by Transport Infrastructure Ireland in 2022 will still be progressed towards construction including the N25 Waterford bypass to New Ross bypass road; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12079/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.170.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD01000"><p>As Minister for Transport, I have responsibility for overall policy and exchequer funding in relation to the National Roads Programme. Once funding arrangements have been put in place with Transport Infrastructure Ireland (TII), under the Roads Acts 1993-2015 and in line with the National Development Plan (NDP), the planning, design and construction of individual national roads is a matter for TII, in conjunction with the local authorities concerned. This is also subject to the Public Spending Code and the necessary statutory approvals. In this context, TII is best placed to advise on the current status and funding of this proposed project.  </p>  <p>  Approximately &euro;615 million of exchequer capital funds have been provided for national roads through TII to local authorities in 2022. The 2022 funding allocations are made having regard for the NDP, which balances investment in transport against other priorities of Government, such as housing and health over the lifetime of the Plan. It was necessary to prioritise projects for funding in a manner which seeks to achieve key outcomes in line with the NDP. Resulting from this, while a large majority of the projects under the NDP were issued a funding allocation in 2022, TII were unable to provide an allocation for the N25 Waterford to Glenmore project. The delivery programme for this project will be kept under review for next year and considered in terms of the overall funding envelope available to TII.</p>  <p>  However, funding was allocated to a number of other schemes on the N25. In this context, TII is best placed to advise on the current status of funding for these improvements.  </p>  <p>  Noting the above position, I have referred your question to TII for a direct reply. Please advise my private office if you do not receive a reply within 10 working days.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.171" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD01100">Bus Services</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.172.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1469" speakername="Mark Ward" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD01200"><p><i>63.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the plans of his Department to utilise the two-kilometre-long bus lane on the Adamstown Road that leads to a strategic development zone that has gone unused for ten years; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[11580/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.173.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD01300"><p>As Minister for Transport, I have responsibility for policy and overall funding in relation to public transport.  The National Transport Authority (NTA) has statutory responsibility for the planning and development of public transport infrastructure in the Greater Dublin Area, including bus infrastructure. </p>  <p>  Noting the NTA's responsibility in the matter, I have referred the Deputy's question to the NTA for a direct reply.  Please contact my private office if you do not receive a reply within 10 days.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.174" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD01400">Transport Policy</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.175.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1507" speakername="Darren O'Rourke" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD01500"><p><i>64.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport if an update will be provided on the actions his Department is taking to research, promote and expand green hydrogen use in the transport sector; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12133/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.176.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD01600"><p>Thank you Deputy O&rsquo;Rourke for your question. My Department is very supportive of hydrogen as a transport fuel with a potential role in decarbonising hard to abate sectors such as freight, public transport and moving forward the role it may play in decarbonising aviation and maritime. </p>  <p>  To date, my Department has been acting as a policy advisor for any and all working groups looking at hydrogen development in Ireland such as the Hydrogen Mobility Ireland (HMI). In 2021, three double-deck hydrogen buses were procured, trialled and put into service by the NTA on Bus &Eacute;ireann&rsquo;s Rathoath to Dublin route. In continuing to support the hydrogen rollout, the Department established the Alternatively Fuelled Heavy-Duty Vehicle (AFHDV) Purchase Grant Scheme which, while being technology-neutral, will allow applicants to apply for forty to sixty per cent of the cost differential of a new hydrogen FCEV. In Budget 2021, the Department worked with the Department of Finance to introduce hydrogen refuelling equipment into the Accelerated Capital Allowance Scheme which allows applicants to claim 100% of the capital cost of eligible equipment. </p>  <p>  The Renewable Fuels for Transport Policy Statement was published in November 2021. The Policy Statement sets out the pathway for increasing the supply and use of renewable fuels in transport. The Policy Statement also addresses Ireland&rsquo;s obligation under European directives to require increased supply of renewable fuels used in transport, such as hydrogen. As an incentive for producing renewable hydrogen, suppliers will be allowed to claim multiple credits when supplying green hydrogen onto the market. </p>  <p>  The Department has also been working with the Department of the Taoiseach under the Shared Island initiative to progress all-island hydrogen research. On January 31, the Department published a request for tender requesting a desktop study exploring hydrogen safety regulation and how this may be established in Ireland and ensuring the interoperability of refuelling stations on the island. Once finished, this will lead to further work with our colleagues in the Northern Ireland Executive. This in addition to research my Department is co-funding with the SEAI on looking at appropriate fuels for certain contexts in Ireland which will explore where hydrogen is best suited for use.</p>  <p>  Finally, my Department also sits on the Interdepartmental Working Group on Hydrogen which is chaired by officials in the Department of the Environment, Climate and Communications and actively contributes to the development of national hydrogen policy. </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.177" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD01700">Driver Test</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.178.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1547" speakername="Thomas Pringle" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD01800"><p><i>65.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the number of persons awaiting a driving test in County Donegal; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[11041/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.179.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1578" speakername="Hildegarde Naughton" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD01900"><p>The Road Safety Authority is responsible for the operation of the driving test service and the information requested is held by them. I have therefore forwarded the Deputy's query to the RSA for direct reply. I would ask the Deputy to contact my office if a response has not been received within ten days.  </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.180" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD02000">Small Public Service Vehicles</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.181.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1507" speakername="Darren O'Rourke" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD02100"><p><i>66.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport if an update will be provided on his engagements with the taxi sector; the actions he is taking to support the sector; the regulatory reforms that have been introduced since the taxi protests in September 2020; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12132/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.182.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD02200"><p>Since the start of the pandemic I have, on three occasions, met with the Advisory Committee on Small Public Services (SPSVs), the statutory committee established under the Taxi Regulation Act 2013 to advise the Minister and the NTA in relation to the SPSV sector, the most recent of which was on 25 November 2021.  That meeting provided me with a valuable opportunity to get first-hand information on the issues affecting the industry and, in particular, an initial assessment of the impact that the Covid-related restrictions that had been introduced at that time were having on operators.  </p>  <p>  The Committee's membership represents a broad range of interests and stakeholders, including four positions for SPSV drivers.  The Committee is the primary forum for dealing with issues affecting the sector and many of the measures taken to date have originated as recommendations from the Committee, including the extension of taxi age limits and the waiver of licence fees.  At the start of the pandemic, the NTA extended the age limits for taxis and hackneys, and repeated this on three further occasions.   The most recent extension ensures that standard age limits for taxis and hackneys are waived until the end of 2022,thereby ensuring no operator exits the industry simply because of the need to replace a vehicle.  </p>  <p>  During the period of the pandemic, I also met with a group of representatives of several taxi associations/unions on two occasions, and also with representatives of taxi dispatch operators in November last. Other members of Government, including the Taoiseach and T&aacute;naiste, have also met with taxi driver representatives. On each of these occasions, we have been able to hear first-hand of the issues affecting the taxi industry. </p>  <p>  In relation to supports for the sector, the vast majority of measures taken to support the taxi industry from the start of the pandemic, remain in place. </p>  <p>  As many as 70% of SPSV drivers availed of the Pandemic Unemployment Payment at the height of the pandemic. The PUP was re-opened before the end of last year until 25 March to support people who lost their employment as a result of COVID public health restrictions introduced from 7 December 2021. For some people, PUP will have ended before this date as the payment rates are gradually reduced.     </p>  <p>  In addition to this, in Budget 2022, I secured funding of &euro;6.5 million for a series of specific measures to support the sector, with a view to addressing statutory costs faced by operators which cannot be deferred. Standard licence renewal fees for SPSVs were waived in 2021 and are being waived again in 2022 at an estimated cost of &euro;3 million. The NTA has put in place schemes to refund the Motor Tax paid by SPSV operators in the period 1 September 2021 to 31 August 2022, and to waive NCT fees for the same period. Further details on these schemes are available on the NTA website. Many of the major costs faced by SPSV operators, such as insurance and dispatch operator fees, can be deferred or cancelled during a period of inactivity. </p>  <p>  Recognising that the replacement of a vehicle is the single largest cost faced by any SPSV operator, and in view of my commitment to support the transition of the SPSV fleet towards zero/low-emission vehicles, I announced on February 4th last, the re-opening of the eSPSV Grant Scheme with a further &euro;15 million allocated to it for 2022.  The take-up rate for this Scheme was exceptionally high in 2021: almost 600 drivers successfully applied for grants, with over &euro;11 million paid out as well as &euro;4 million in provisional grant offers. </p>  <p>  As the independent regulator of the sector, the NTA has been in constant contact with taxi operators, drivers and representatives throughout the pandemic via email, text messages and phone calls.  In addition, the Deputy should be aware that the NTA has now started work on a new National Maximum Fare Review and is engaging with its service providers in the matter.  This Review, which is undertaken on a regular basis by the NTA, assesses any changes in the market facing the taxi industry as well as changes in annual taxi operating costs.  These costs include the fixed and running costs of an average taxi and labour costs.  The objective of the Review is to determine whether changes need to be made to the current level of maximum fares and the NTA has confirmed that it is endeavouring to conclude the review process as quickly as possible in 2022, whilst still ensuring that all steps, including a consultation process, are appropriately completed. </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.183" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD02300">Public Transport</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.184.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1547" speakername="Thomas Pringle" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD02400"><p><i>67.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the details of bus stations in County Donegal that are included in the Public Transport Accessibility Programme; the type of works planned; the date for the completion of the works; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[11040/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.185.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD02500"><p>As Minister for Transport, while I have responsibility for policy and overall funding in relation to public transport, it is the National Transport Authority (NTA) which has statutory responsibility for securing the provision of accessible public passenger transport services and infrastructure. The NTA is also managing the Public Transport Accessibility Programme to retrofit legacy facilities and services.</p>  <p>  In light of the NTA's responsibilities for accessible public transport, including at bus stations, I have referred your question to the NTA for direct reply to you. Please advise my private office if you do not receive a reply within ten working days.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.186" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD02600">Road Projects</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.187.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1557" speakername="Niamh Smyth" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD02700"><p><i>68.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport if he has met with Monaghan County Council regarding the omission of funding for the N2 Clontibret to the Border scheme from the National Development Plan. <b>[11988/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.188.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD02800"><p>As Minister for Transport I have responsibility for overall policy and exchequer funding in relation to the National Roads Programme. Under the Roads Acts 1993-2015 and in line with the National Development Plan (NDP), the planning, design and construction of individual national roads is a matter for Transport Infrastructure Ireland (TII), in conjunction with the local authorities concerned. </p>  <p>  In January this year, I received an invitation from Monaghan County Council for a meeting regarding the N2 Clontibret to the Border and the N2 Ardee to Castleblayney projects, but due to diary constraints I was unable to schedule a meeting.</p>  <p>  Noting the above position, I have referred your question to TII for a direct reply to provide an update on the projects mentioned above. Please advise my private office if you do not receive a reply within 10 working days.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.189" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD02900">Active Travel</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.190.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1511" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD03000"><p><i>69.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport if he will report his work to promote active travel in County Carlow <b>[12098/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.191.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD03100"><p>The Programme for Government committed that &euro;360 million in cross-Government funding will be spent on walking and cycling per annum over the lifetime of the Government, equivalent to 20% of the entire transport budget. This investment will help support the planned delivery of almost 1,000 kilometres of improved walking and cycling infrastructure by 2025 as well as additional investment in Greenways.</p>  <p>  2021 saw the first ever major Active Travel investment programme for rural Ireland. &euro;72.8m was allocated to 19 local authorities to support the delivery of 340 sustainable transport projects, including an allocation of &euro;2.426m to Carlow County Council. 2022 saw this allocation increase to &euro;2.515m.</p>  <p>  This year has seen another increase in my Department's overall funding for cycling and walking, in line with the Government&rsquo;s prioritisation of Active Travel and Greenways. As well as an allocation of &euro;289m administered through the National Transport Authority (NTA) to Active Travel I was delighted to announce funding of &euro;60m for investment in our Greenways. This included &euro;60,000 for the feasibility, and pre-appraisal of the Barrow Valley Greenway in Carlow. </p>  <p>In addition to the increased funding for walking and cycling infrastructure, a number of smaller-scale initiatives are being progressed by my Department to support and promote efforts to increase Active Travel. The Department of Transport funds the delivery of Cycle Right training through Cycling Ireland which delivers cycling training to school children around the country. In partnership with the Department of Education we also launched the Safe Routes to School Programme last year which aims to accelerate the delivery of walking, scooting and cycling infrastructure on key access routes to schools. All schools were eligible to apply to the Programme and information was circulated from the Departments of Education and Transport to schools nationwide. By the deadline of 16th April 2021, 931 applications had been received from schools in every county in Ireland. 170 schools were notified on 21st June that they have been selected for inclusion in the first round of the SRTS Programme, including 4 schools in Co. Carlow.</p>  <p>  The step-change in funding committed in Budget 2022 and the introduction of numerous innovative measures to encourage Active Travel is proof of the Government's commitment to this area, and I look forward to the delivery of the numerous projects and programmes around the country. </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.192" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD03200">Electric Vehicles</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.193.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1594" speakername="Brian Leddin" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD03300"><p><i>70.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the steps he is taking to incentivise and support the use of small and light electric vehicles, including electric bikes and electric cargo bikes, over and above heavier and more carbon intensive electric vehicles; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12113/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.194.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD03400"><p>The use of e-bikes, including e-cargo bikes, is proving to be an increasingly popular method of travel, whether for commuting or leisure purposes, and is encouraging more people to choose to cycle. </p>  <p>  I welcomed the announcement by my colleague, the Minister for Finance, of increased thresholds under the existing Cycle to Work Scheme as part of the 2020 July Stimulus package, as well as the expansion of the scheme to electric bikes, including e-cargo bikes. The changes to the Scheme are in line with the commitment made in the Programme for Government. </p>  <p>  The Programme for Government also committed us to legislating for e-bikes. While e-bikes are already provided for in Irish legislation in the Road Traffic Acts, the Road Traffic and Roads Bill, which is currently before the Oireachtas, proposes to clarify the legal definitions for high-powered and low-powered e-bikes. This will act to encourage the growing cohort of e-cyclists in      Ireland by giving certainty as to the legal status of their vehicle. In line with European legislation, high-powered e-bikes will be considered to be a kind of light moped or &lsquo;L-category&rsquo; vehicle. Accordingly, they will be required to be registered, taxed and insured. Users will require a driver&rsquo;s licence for L-category vehicles and the relevant rules of the road for mopeds and      motorbikes will apply.</p>  <p>  Low-powered pedal-assist e-bikes, capable of achieving speeds up to 25 km/h, will continue to be treated in the same way as pedal bicycles under law and the relevant rules of the road for bicycles will apply accordingly. As is currently the case, this type of e-bike will not require registration, taxation, or a licence.</p>  <p>  No distinction is drawn in the Road Traffic Acts between cycles (bicycles or tricycles) used for the carriage of persons or the carriage of goods and these rules therefore apply equally to e-cargo bikes.</p>  <p>  Providing a sustainable, low-carbon transport system is a key priority of my Department. The Programme for Government commits to 7% average annual emissions reduction to 2030; ultimately, the goal is for a zero-emission mobility system by 2050. Electrification will be key to achieving this objective in the transport sector. </p>  <p>  Electric vehicles (EVs) are the most prominent transport mitigation measure in the Climate Action Plan, and Ireland has set an ambitious target of 945,000 EVs on our roads by 2030. This target is challenging but indicates the scale of the transformation that is needed across all sectors if Ireland is to achieve its climate targets in the coming years. </p>  <p>  Considerable progress has been made, as a result of the work of the Low Emission Vehicle Taskforce, to ensure that conditions and policies are in place to support citizens in making greener vehicle choices. A comprehensive suite of measures is available to EV drivers, including purchase grants for private car owners and taxi drivers, VRT relief, reduced tolls, home charger grants, favourable motor and BIK tax rates, as well as a comprehensive charging network. These measures have collectively contributed to increased take up of EVs in Ireland in recent years, albeit from a low base, to over 50,500 now. </p>  <p>  In addition, my Department convened the Electric Vehicle Policy Pathway (EVPP) Working Group to produce a roadmap to achieving the 2030 EV target. The EVPP Working Group comprises senior officials and has considered regulatory, financial, and taxation policies to help drive a significant ramp-up in passenger EVs and electric van sales.  </p>  <p>  The recommendations of the EVPP Working Group were approved by Government and the full report is available online. </p>  <p>  My Department is acutely aware that the cost of electric vehicles remains an issue for many consumers. To this end, electric vehicle policy is being kept under continuous review to endeavour to make low emission vehicles affordable. </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.195" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD03500">Public Transport</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.196.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1486" speakername="Br&iacute;d Smith" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD03600"><p><i>71.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport if he will commission a study into the impacts and benefits of moving to the provision of fare free public transport across the country, specifically its impact on transport greenhouse gas emissions; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12057/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.197.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD03700"><p>As Minister for Transport, I have responsibility for policy and overall funding in relation to public transport. I am not involved in the day-to-day operations of public transport, nor decisions on fares. </p>  <p>  It is the National Transport Authority (NTA) that has the statutory responsibility for the regulation of fares in relation to public passenger transport services and also has statutory responsibility for securing the provision of public transport services by way of public transport services contracts in respect of services that are socially necessary but commercially unviable.  The funding of those services comprises both the fares paid by passengers and the subvention payments from the Exchequer.  The main purpose of the subvention payment is to meet the gap between income from fares and the cost of operating services.</p>  <p>  The provision of public transport services is heavily dependent on passenger fare revenue as it normally contributes about 65% of the operational cost.  The remaining 35% of cost is covered by the PSO grant and the Department of Social Protection grant under the free travel scheme.  </p>  <p>  Prior to COVID-19, &euro;287 million of Exchequer funding was provided for PSO services in Budget 2020; however, since 2020, additional funding has been required to continue to address the significant COVID impacts on public transport provision. All PSO providers are currently in receipt of emergency support funding to compensate for fare revenue loss arising as a result of the impact of Covid-19 on the sector, and the associated fall in passenger numbers (passenger numbers fell to below 10% of 2019 levels at the height of the restrictions in 2020 and 2021). Further, on 25/06/2020 Government approved the introduction of temporary financial supports for the licensed bus sector &ndash; commercial operators (in accordance with EU and national legislation).</p>  <p>  In 2022, I secured &euro;538m to support PSO services including over &euro;200m to address COVID expenses (i.e. loss of fare revenue, cleaning costs). &euro;9m of the &euro;538m allocation has been provided as ongoing support for the licensed bus sector for the first three months of the year. While, over &euro;15m has also been allocated to support Local Link regular service provision in rural Ireland. </p>  <p>  The Government is strongly committed to helping combat the rising cost-of-living being experienced throughout the country. In this context, a suite of new measures is being introduced by Government to help with this issue, including a 20% average fare reduction on PSO services until the end of 2022. These discounted fares will benefit the hundreds of thousands of people across the country who use public transport every day. A further &euro;54m in Exchequer funding has been secured to allow for the introduction of these discounted fares, this is in addition to the REV22 allocations. The NTA will work with the PSO public transport operators in the coming weeks to commence rolling out these fare reductions across the public transport network in late April/ early May.</p>  <p>  Also, in recognition of the importance of incentivising young people to use public transport, as part of Budget 2022 I secured &euro;25m of funding to provide for the introduction of a young adult card (YAC) which will allow any person nationwide who is between 19 and 23 years old, to avail of an entitlement for discounted travel costs, and to increase the level of discount over and above the current student discount to an average of discount of 50% across all services, including city, intercity and rural services. It is envisaged that the discount will initially be made available on PSO services, and then broadened to include commercial operators at a later date.  This will not only promote modal shift in the transport sector among this age group but should also contribute towards a reduced reliance on private transport with associated benefit of transport emission savings.  The NTA has commenced work in relation to the implementation of the new fares&rsquo; structures for young adults, and this includes the application process and establishing a definitive timeline for the introduction of the Scheme. </p>  <p>  The PSO programme represents a significant expenditure of taxpayers' money, and funding has increased in recent years to cater for additional services and growing capacity.  Any assessment of a proposed change to public transport fare structures would be a matter for the NTA to consider in the first instance.  </p>  <p>  In light of the Authority's responsibility in this area, I have forwarded the Deputy's specific question in relation to the possible commissioning of  a study into the impacts and benefits of moving to the provision of fare free public transport across the country, specifically its impact on transport greenhouse gas emissions to the NTA for direct reply.  Please advise my private office if you do not receive a response within ten working days.</p></reply>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.199.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1499" speakername="Richard O'Donoghue" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD03900"><p><i>72.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport if his attention has been drawn to the fact that public transport remains a major issue in rural communities given that rural dwellers are not adequately serviced by the existing transport network (details supplied). <b>[8935/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.200.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD04000"><p>As Minister for Transport, I have responsibility for policy and overall funding for public transport,</p><p>It is the National Transport Authority (NTA) which has statutory responsibility for securing the provision of public passenger transport services nationally. It is the public transport operators, for example, Bus &Eacute;ireann, that have responsibility for delivering and operating public transport services, in conjunction with the NTA.</p><p>Furthermore, the NTA has national responsibility for integrated local and rural transport, including management of the Rural Transport Programme which operates under the TFI Local Link brand.  </p><p>In light of the NTA's responsibilities for accessible public transport services in rural areas, I have forwarded your question to the NTA for a direct reply to you. Please advise my private office if you do not receive a response within ten working days.</p></reply>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.201" nospeaker="true" ><p>Question No. 73 answered with Question No. 34.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.202" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD04200">Road Traffic Offences</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.203.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1570" speakername="Patrick Costello" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD04300"><p><i>74.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport further to the increased fines for parking on footpaths which his Department introduced in January 2022, if he has considered other measures to support increased enforcement. <b>[10834/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.204.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1578" speakername="Hildegarde Naughton" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD04400"><p>Parking regulations are enforced by local authority traffic wardens and by An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na. While my department consulted extensively with both bodies before taking the decision to increase the penalties for parking on a footpath, bus lane or cycle track earlier this year, I have no role in devising or implementing increased enforcement strategies and cannot answer on the responsible bodies' behalf.</p>  <p>  The Deputy may wish to raise this matter with the local authorities and with An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na directly.</p></reply>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.205" nospeaker="true" ><p>Question No. 75 answered with Question No. 34.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.206" nospeaker="true" ><p>Question No. 76 answered with Question No. 52.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.207" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD04700">Public Transport</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.208.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1525" speakername="Holly Cairns" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD04800"><p><i>77.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the steps he is taking to increase transport accessibility in public transport in rural areas. <b>[11734/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.209.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD04900"><p>As Minister for Transport, I have responsibility for policy and overall funding in relation to public transport; however, I am not involved in the day-to-day operations of public transport. </p>  <p>  The National Transport Authority (NTA) has statutory responsibility for securing the provision of accessible public passenger transport services in conjunction with the respective service operator. The NTA also has national responsibility for integrated local and rural transport, including management of the Rural Transport Programme which operates under the TFI Local Link brand.  </p>  <p>  In light of the NTA's responsibilities for accessible public transport servcies in rural areas, I have referred your question to the NTA for direct reply to you. Please advise my private office if you do not receive a reply within ten working days.</p></reply>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.211.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1556" speakername="Brendan Smith" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD05100"><p><i>78.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport if he will consider the issues outlined by a representative organisation in correspondence (details supplied); and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12064/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.212.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD05200"><p>As Minister for Transport, I have responsibility for policy and overall funding in relation to public transport; I am not involved in the day-to-day operations of public transport, nor decisions on fares. It is the National Transport Authority (NTA) that has responsibility for the regulation of fares charged to passengers in respect of public transport services, provided under public service obligation (PSO) contracts.</p>  <p>  The Government is strongly committed to helping combat the rising cost-of-living being experienced throughout the country. In this context, a suite of new measures is being introduced by Government to help with this issue, including a 20% average fare reduction on PSO services until the end of 2022. These discounted fares will benefit the hundreds of thousands of people across the country who use public transport every day. A further &euro;54m in Exchequer funding has been secured to allow for the introduction of these discounted fares, this is in addition to the REV22 allocations. The NTA will work with the PSO public transport operators in the coming weeks to commence rolling out these fare reductions across the public transport network in April/May. </p>  <p>  Also, in recognition of the importance of incentivising young people to use public transport, as part of Budget 2022 I secured &euro;25m of funding to provide for the introduction of a young adult card (YAC) which will allow any person nationwide who is between 19 and 23 years old, to avail of an entitlement for discounted travel costs, and to increase the level of discount over and above the current student discount to an average of discount of 50% across all services, including city, intercity and rural services. It is envisaged that the discount will initially be made available on PSO services, and then broadened to include commercial operators at a later date.  This will not only promote modal shift in the transport sector among this age group but should also contribute towards a reduced reliance on private transport with associated benefit of transport emission savings.</p>  <p>  Licensed bus operators are an integral part of the overall public transport system particularly in areas which are not covered by existing public service bus and rail services. In recognition of this, throughout the COVID-19 pandemic the Government have provided temporary financial supports for certain licensed commercial services with a view to protecting capacity across the public transport sector throughout the crisis. To date c.&euro;60m has been provided to support the Commercial Bus Operators during this challenging time.</p>  <p>  As the Deputy will understand, I receive a large number of diary requests that are considered and coordinated with my private offices in both the Department of Transport and Department of Environment, Climate and Communications in a weekly joint meeting. I note that it is not always possible to respond in the affirmative to every request.</p>  <p>  However, I would like to reassure the Deputy that both the National Transport Authority (NTA) and my Department have been engaging directly with commercial bus operators throughout the crisis to help inform policy decisions in relation to the public transport sector as we continue to deal with the impact of Covid-19.</p>  <p>  In this context, my Department has been liaising with the Coach Tourism &amp;amp; Transport Council of Ireland (CTTC) since May 2020 - to date 22 meetings have taken place, and a further meeting is scheduled for 8th April 2022. I also previously met with the CTTC and I am aware of the issues facing the sector. </p>  <p>  I hope to meet again with representatives from the CTTC to discuss the highlighted issues at a future date when my diary allows.</p></reply>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.214.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1483" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Cannon" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD05400"><p><i>79.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport if he will carry out a study of rail fares nationally and in particular the great disparity that exists between the fares charged to daily commuters in greater Dublin and those in regional cities. <b>[11838/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.215.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD05500"><p>As Minister for Transport, I have responsibility for policy and overall funding in relation to public transport; I am not involved in the day-to-day operations of public transport, nor decisions on fares. It is the National Transport Authority (NTA) that has responsibility for the regulation of fares charged to passengers in respect of public transport services, provided under public service obligation (PSO) contracts.</p>  <p>  In light of the Authority's responsibility in this area, I have fowarded the Deputy's specific question, in relation to the possibility of a study of rail fares being carried out nationally, to the NTA for direct reply. Please advise my private office if you do not receive a response within ten working days.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.216" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD05600">Road Projects</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.217.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1625" speakername="John Brady" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD05700"><p><i>80.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport when funding will be made available to allow the N11/M11 improvement scheme to proceed to phase 3; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[11732/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.218.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300061#WRD05800"><p>As Minister for Transport I have responsibility for overall policy and exchequer funding in relation to the National Roads Programme. Under the Roads Acts 1993-2015 and in line with the National Development Plan (NDP), the planning, design and construction of individual national roads is a matter for Transport Infrastructure Ireland (TII), in conjunction with the local authorities concerned.</p>  <p>  Noting the above position, I have referred your question to TII for a direct reply. Please advise my private office if you do not receive a reply within 10 working days.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.220" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE00200">Electric Vehicles</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.221.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1626" speakername="Steven Matthews" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE00300"><p><i>81.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the position regarding supports and incentives for persons living in apartments and other multi-unit dwellings to install chargers for electric vehicles; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[10090/22]</b></p></ques>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.222.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1598" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE00400"><p><i>99.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the status of the steps that he has taken to ensure that residents of apartments and duplexes can access electric vehicle schemes and install electric vehicle chargers to proactively encourage transition to such vehicles; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[9325/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.223.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE00500"><p>I propose to take Questions Nos. 81 and 99 together.</p>  <p>  The Deputy will be aware that the Government is fully committed to supporting a significant expansion and modernisation of the electric vehicle charging network over the coming years. A national charging infrastucture strategy is due to be published for public consultation early this year which will set out a pathway to stay ahead of demand over the critical period out to 2030.</p>  <p>  The Government&rsquo;s policy regarding the increased usage of Electric Vehicles (EVs) is primarily driven by the Climate Action Plan which sets a target of 945,000 EVs by 2030. </p>  <p>  Home charging is considered the primary method of charging for the majority of EVs in Ireland and is a convenient, cost effective and environmentally friendly means of charging, especially when using night rate electricity. It accounts for circa 80% of EV charging sessions and will continue to be the primary method of charging in the future.</p>  <p>  The Government has introduced a requirement that new buildings and those undergoing substantial renovation works will have to include charging points for electric vehicles if they have more than 10 car parking spaces. </p>  <p>  The EV Home Charger Grant Scheme has been in operation since January 2018 to support the installation of home chargers for purchasers of new and second-hand BEVs and PHEVs.  The grant provides generous support towards the full cost of installation of a home charger up to a maximum of &euro;600. As regards existing apartment buildings, work is currently being progressed to expand the EV home charger grant to include shared parking in apartment blocks and similar developments. My Department is working closely with the SEAI and expects a scheme for apartments to open shortly.</p>  <p>  In terms of existing supports for public charging, the Public Charge Point Scheme continues to be available during 2022 to provide local authorities with a grant of up to &euro;5,000 to support the development of on-street public chargers. The primary focus of the scheme is to provide support for the installation of infrastructure which will facilitate owners of electric vehicles, who do not have access to a private parking space, but instead rely on parking their vehicles in public places near their homes to charge their EVs. My Department is reviewing the Scheme at present to ensure that it is as effective as possible in driving the decarbonisation effort and which will support installation of public chargers particularly in areas without own driveway.</p>  <p>  In addition, the national charging infrastucture strategy will consider this issue in particular and develop proposals to address the current disparity between homeowners with and without off street parking.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.224" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE00600">Public Transport</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.225.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1485" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE00700"><p><i>82.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport if his attention has been drawn to the alternative proposal by a group (details supplied) for Metrolink which would opt for St. Stephen&rsquo;s Green rather than Charlemont being the interchange between Metrolink and the Luas Green Line and continuing the Metrolink to an underground station at Portobello which could also facilitate future expansion of Metrolink to the south west of the city; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[11978/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.226.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE00800"><p>MetroLink is likely the largest ever public investment project in the history of the State and has been subject to extensive non-statutory public consultation since 2018. The strategic rationale for a metro corridor from north to south Dublin has been well established in numerous strategic transport frameworks, including most recently the statutory Transport Strategy for the Greater Dublin Area.</p>  <p>  The Preferred Route for the MetroLink project is that as consulted upon in 2019 and extends from North Dublin to Charlemont as available to view on the project&rsquo;s dedicated website www.metrolink.ie. The Preliminary Business Case for the project, as well as the environmental impact assessment reports and other associated planning documentation, is prepared on the basis of that Preferred Route.</p>  <p>  Subject to Government approval in the coming months, the project will proceed to the statutory planning process with submission of a Railway Order application to An Bord Plean&aacute;la and will then be subject to further public consultation as part of that process.</p>  <p>  It is my strong belief that we urgently need to see progress on delivery of major public transport infrastructure projects, including MetroLink. It is my view that this focus on delivery is one shared by both citizens and political representatives and, while I recognise there will always be different perspectives on the details of major projects such as MetroLink, my aim is to see this project move off the drawing board and into construction. In that regard I think it important to note that substantial changes to the planning and design of the project as evolved since 2018 through extensive public consultation will add significant delay to the delivery of the project</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.227" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE00900">Airport Policy</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.228.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1601" speakername="Alan Dillon" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE01000"><p><i>83.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the details of the next round of funding under the Regional Airport Programme 2021-2025; the funding awarded to Ireland West Airport Knock annually since 2016; if additional Exchequer funding will be provided to support the aviation sector as it starts to rebound; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12122/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.229.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1578" speakername="Hildegarde Naughton" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE01100"><p>Funding of &euro;36m has been allocated by government in 2022 to support regional airports and PSO Air services through the Regional Airports Programme 2021-2025. In a substantial increase in funding available under this Programme, it will deliver &euro;26m in current and &euro;10m in capital funding to support regional airports of Ireland West, Donegal, Kerry, Shannon and Cork in 2022.</p><p>Funding under this Programme targets safety and security related operations at airports as well as projects which focus on reducing emissions and building climate resilience. Capital funding is allocated to eligible airports annually following an assessment of project proposals submitted by airports at the start of each year. Capital projects proposals from airports for 2022 are currently being evaluated by an assessment panel set up by my Department.I hope to be in a position to announce capital project allocations to these airports in the coming weeks.</p><p>Invitations for current funding will issue to airports, including Ireland West Airport, later in 2022, with funding allocations made by the end of the year.</p><p>In line with the Deputy&rsquo;s request, Exchequer funding provided to Ireland West Airport under the Regional Airports Programme between 2016 and 2021 is set out as follows:  <table>    <tr>       <th>AIRPORT</th>       <th></th>       <th>2016</th>       <th>2017</th>       <th>2018</th>       <th>2019</th>       <th>2020</th>       <th>2021</th>       <th>Total</th>    </tr>    <tr>       <td>IWAK</td>       <td>CAPITAL</td>       <td>&euro;1,965,654</td>       <td>&euro;1,330,916</td>       <td>&euro;2,259,543</td>       <td>&euro;7,746,387</td>       <td>&euro;883,035</td>       <td>&euro;2,173,563</td>       <td>&euro;16,359,098</td>    </tr>    <tr>       <td></td>       <td>CURRENT</td>       <td>&euro;967,765</td>       <td>&euro;1,868,439</td>       <td>&euro;1,916,563</td>       <td>&euro;1,736,516</td>       <td>&euro;1,353,859</td>       <td>&euro;1,017,826</td>       <td>&euro;8,860,968</td>    </tr>    <tr>       <td>TOTAL </td>       <td></td>       <td>&euro;2,933,419</td>       <td>&euro;3,199,355</td>       <td>&euro;4,176,106</td>       <td>&euro;9,482,903</td>       <td>&euro;2,236,894</td>       <td>&euro;3,191,389</td>       <td>&euro;25,220,066</td>    </tr> </table> </p><p>COVID-19 has had a devastating impact on our aviation sector.  My Government colleagues and I worked closely together to ensure that a suite of aviation specific supports were provided to the sector during 2021 to facilitate recovery and enable our airports to plan for a brighter future.  These aviation specific Exchequer supports exceeded &euro;160 million in 2021, and as outlined above, funding will continue under the Regional Airports Programme into 2022. </p><p>This level of funding is a clear indication of the importance Government attaches to airports being well positioned for recovery and growth into the future.As was the case in 2021, Government will continue to keep aviation supports under review in 2022.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.230" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE01200">Bus Services</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.231.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1486" speakername="Br&iacute;d Smith" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE01300"><p><i>84.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport his views on the National Transport Authority's competitive tendering process for public service obligation bus services; and if he will examine alternatives ahead of future tendering processes; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12059/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.232.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE01400"><p>As Minister for Transport, I have responsibility for policy and overall funding in relation to public transport; however, I am not involved in the day-to-day operations of public transport. Under the Dublin Transport Authority Act 2008 it is a statutory function of the National Transport Authority (NTA) to procure public transport services by means of Public Service Obligation (PSO) contracts. </p>  <p>  In light of the Authority's responsibility in this area, I have forwarded the Deputy's specific question in relation to the competitive tendering process for PSO bus services to the NTA for direct reply.  Please advise my private office if you do not receive a response within ten working days.</p></reply>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.233" nospeaker="true" ><p>Question No. 85 answered with Question No. 34.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.234" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE01600">Road Projects</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.235.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1454" speakername="Michael Creed" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE01700"><p><i>86.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport if an update will be provided on the Cork-Limerick motorway project; when the preferred route will be identified; when the project will proceed to planning; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12119/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.236.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE01800"><p>As Minister for Transport I have responsibility for overall policy and exchequer funding in relation to the National Roads Programme. Under the Roads Acts 1993-2015 and in line with the National Development Plan (NDP), the planning, design and construction of individual national roads is a matter for Transport Infrastructure Ireland (TII), in conjunction with the local authorities concerned.</p>  <p>  With regard to the Cork to Limerick project, the preferred transport corridor is expected to be announced before the end of Q1 2022, with a public consultation to follow. TII is best placed to advise on the current status and funding of this proposed project.  </p>  <p>  Noting the above position, I have referred your question to TII for a direct reply. Please advise my private office if you do not receive a reply within 10 working days.</p></reply>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.238.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1453" speakername="Thomas Gould" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE02000"><p><i>87.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the status of the northern ring road. <b>[12066/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.239.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE02100"><p>As Minister for Transport I have responsibility for overall policy and exchequer funding in relation to the National Roads Programme. Under the Roads Acts 1993-2015 and in line with the National Development Plan (NDP), the planning, design and construction of individual national roads is a matter for Transport Infrastructure Ireland (TII), in conjunction with the local authorities concerned.</p>  <p>  Noting the above position, I have referred your question on the Cork Northern Ring Road to TII for a direct reply. Please advise my private office if you do not receive a reply within 10 working days.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.240" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE02200">Public Transport</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.241.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1570" speakername="Patrick Costello" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE02300"><p><i>88.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport if the NTA will carry out a feasibility study for a new DART station in the Inchicore/Ballyfermot area. <b>[10835/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.242.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE02400"><p>As Minister for Transport,  I have responsibility for policy and overall funding in relation to public transport.  The National Transport Authority (NTA) has statutory responsibility for the planning and development of public transport infrastructure in the Greater Dublin Area, including the DART+ programme and any stations planned within the Programme.</p>  <p>  Noting the NTA's responsibility in the matter, I have referred the Deputy's question to the NTA for a more detailed reply.  Please contact my private office if you do not receive a reply within 10 days.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.243" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE02500">Aviation Industry</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.244.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1593" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE02600"><p><i>89.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the status of the resumption of transatlantic flights from Shannon Airport; the State supports provided to a company (details supplied) to date; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12102/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.245.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1578" speakername="Hildegarde Naughton" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE02700"><p>Shannon Airport is forecasting close to one million passengers in 2022 with 3 airlines and 25 routes expected for Summer 2022, compared to 6 airlines and 30 routes pre-COVID-19. Aer Lingus transatlantic services to Boston are expected to return on 10 March and New York on 11 March 2022. The United Airlines daily Newark seasonal service will recommence on 27 March.</p><p>During the COVID-19 crisis Shannon Group benefited from a suite of measures to support businesses across the economy, including but not limited to, the wage subsidy scheme, grants, a commercial rates waiver, deferred tax liabilities and the COVID Restrictions Support Scheme.  These supports to Shannon Group totalled almost &euro;17 million in 2020 and 2021.  In an effort to protect jobs in the Mid-West, emergency operational funding of &euro;105,000 was also provided to Shannon Group by my Department in 2020 to ensure two Castles, Bunratty and King John&rsquo;s, operated by Shannon Heritage could remain open at that time.</p><p>In addition to these supports, over &euro;22.7 million in aviation sector-specific supports have been allocated to Shannon Airport in 2020 and 2021.  Over &euro;6 million of this funding was in the form of capital grants under the Covid-19 Regional State Airports Programme in 2021.  Funding under this Programme targeted safety &amp;amp; security related operations as well as projects which focused on reducing emissions and building climate resilience at airports. Over &euro;5.5 million in operational support was also provided under this Programme in 2021, funding 100% of eligible operational costs at Shannon Airport last year.</p><p>Additional emergency capital funding of &euro;5.65m has also been provided to Shannon Airport in 2020 and 2021 for a Hold Baggage Screening (HBS) project and an Embankments project.  A further &euro;5.5m was provided to Shannon Airport under the Department's Covid Supplementary Support Scheme to Irish airports. This funding has provided Shannon Airport with flexibility to roll out route incentives/charge rebates, in consultation with airlines, with a view to supporting recovery and growth of connectivity.</p><p>A summary of funding provided to Shannon Group over 2020 and 2021 is outlined as follows: <table>    <tr>       <th>Shannon Group</th>       <th colspan="2">2020</th>       <th colspan="2">2021</th>       <th>TOTAL </th>    </tr>    <tr>       <td></td>       <td>Current<br /><br />&euro;m </td>       <td>Capital<br /><br />&euro;m </td>       <td>Current &euro;m </td>       <td>Capital &euro;m </td>       <td>&euro;m </td>    </tr>    <tr>       <td>Horizontal Supports (approx.) </td>       <td>&euro;8.40 </td>       <td></td>       <td>&euro;8.24 </td>       <td></td>       <td>&euro;16.64 </td>    </tr>    <tr>       <td>Covid Support to Shannon Heritage</td>       <td>&euro;0.11 </td>       <td></td>       <td></td>       <td></td>       <td>&euro;0.11 </td>    </tr>    <tr>       <td>Emergency Capital Support</td>       <td></td>       <td>&euro;0.30 </td>       <td></td>       <td>&euro;5.35 </td>       <td>&euro;5.65 </td>    </tr>    <tr>       <td>Covid-19 Regional State Airports Programme 2021</td>       <td></td>       <td></td>       <td>&euro;5.53 </td>       <td>&euro;6.07 </td>       <td>&euro;11.60 </td>    </tr>    <tr>       <td>Covid Supplementary Support Scheme</td>       <td></td>       <td></td>       <td>&euro;5.49 </td>       <td></td>       <td>&euro;5.49 </td>    </tr>    <tr>       <td>TOTAL </td>       <td>&euro;8.51 </td>       <td>&euro;0.30 </td>       <td>&euro;19.26 </td>       <td>&euro;11.42 </td>       <td>&euro;39.49 </td>    </tr> </table> </p><p>This year, funding of &euro;36 million will be provided under the Regional Airports Programme 2021-2025, supporting regional airports of Shannon, Cork, Ireland West, Donegal and Kerry.  This budget allocation represents a significant increase in funding available under the Programme in 2022, which takes account of the broadening of the Programme to include both Cork and Shannon Airports.  In addition to this, funding of &euro;1.1m will be provided to Shannon Airport in 2022 for the completion of the airports HBS and Embankments projects.</p><p>The National Aviation Policy recognises the important role of Shannon Airport in the economic and social fabric of Mid-West Region. Funding of almost &euro;40 million provided to Shannon Group since 2020 is a clear indication of the importance Government attaches to Shannon Group being well positioned for recovery and growth into the future. </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.246" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE02800">Active Travel</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.247.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1480" speakername="Jennifer Carroll MacNeill" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE02900"><p><i>90.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the status of the &euro;240 million funding for 468 sustainable travel projects across the country, specifically in Dublin and D&uacute;n Laoghaire; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[11800/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.248.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE03000"><p>The Programme for Government committed that &euro;360 million in cross-Government funding will be spent on walking and cycling per annum over the lifetime of the Government. This investment will help support the delivery of almost 1,000 kilometres of improved walking and cycling infrastructure by 2025 as well as additional investment in Greenways.</p>  <p>  In 2021 my Department allocated &euro;240 million to support the addition of 233 new walking and cycling projects in the Greater Dublin Area and Regional Cities. The four Dublin local authorities received allocations as follows under the Sustainable Transport Measures Grants programme: Dublin City Council &euro;49.875m, Dun Laoghaire Rathdown County Council &euro;34.145m, Fingal County Council &euro;14.87m, South Dublin County Council &euro;20.705m.</p>  <p>  I recently announced an allocation of &euro;289m to support walking and cycling projects for 2022. Under this allocation the four Dublin local authorities received allocations as follows under the Active Travel Investment Programme: Dublin City Council &euro;52.810m, Dun Laoghaire Rathdown County Council &euro;38.990m, Fingal County Council &euro;25.535m, South Dublin County Council &euro;18.158m</p>  <p>  The National Transport Authority (NTA) is responsible for the development and implementation of public transport and active travel infrastructure, allocating the funding provided by my Department at project level and working in conjunction with the relevant local authorities. The NTA work with the local authorities to determine the projects and precise funding allocations for the current year. The full list of allocations is then published on the NTA's website. In 2021 unspent capital funding was carried into 2022 as approved by my colleague the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.249" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE03100">Road Projects</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.250.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1616" speakername="Matt Shanahan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE03200"><p><i>91.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport his views on the realistic timelines for an upgrade of the N24 and N25 roads in the south-east; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[10520/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.251.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE03300"><p>As Minister for Transport I have responsibility for overall policy and exchequer funding in relation to the National Roads Programme. Under the Roads Acts 1993-2015 and in line with the National Development Plan (NDP), the planning, design and construction of individual national roads is a matter for Transport Infrastructure Ireland (TII), in conjunction with the local authorities concerned.</p>  <p>  Noting the above position, I have referred your question to TII for a direct reply. Please advise my private office if you do not receive a reply within 10 working days.</p></reply>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.252" nospeaker="true" ><p>Question No. 92 answered with Question No. 35.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.253" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE03500">Road Network</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.254.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1513" speakername="Pauline Tully" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE03600"><p><i>93.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the reason for the reduction in funding for the community involvement scheme in counties Cavan and Monaghan in the Regional and Local Road Allocations 2022; the reason there was no former national roads funding for County Cavan in the Regional and Local Road Allocations 2022; the reason there was no active travel funding for County Monaghan in the Regional and Local Road Allocations 2022; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[10489/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.255.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE03700"><p>The improvement and maintenance of regional and local roads is the statutory responsibility of local authorities, in accordance with the provisions of Section 13 of the Roads Act 1993. Works on those roads are funded from the Council's own resources supplemented by State road grants.  The initial selection and prioritisation of works to be funded is also a matter for the local authority.</p>  <p>  Based on an overall budget of &euro;30 million for the 2022/2023 Community Involvement Scheme, local authorities were allocated funding on a pro-rata basis unless an individual authority had sought less than the pro-rata amount. The 2022 funding allocations for Cavan and Monaghan reflect this approach. </p>  <p>  Towards the end of 2021 local authorities were invited to apply for funding under the Former National Roads Grant Programme. While Cavan County Council was allocated funding under this programme in 2021, the Council indicated that it did not have suitable roads which would be eligible for funding under the terms of the programme in 2022.</p>  <p>  As part of the 2020 July Jobs Stimulus Plan, over &euro;30 million was allocated by the Department&rsquo;s Regional and Local Roads Division to eligible local authorities for active travel schemes. A reallocation of some unspent monies (from 2021) has been provided this year to a small number of local authorities to allow for the completion of works.</p>  <p>  Active Travel funding is now being administered by the National Transport Authority and both Cavan and Monaghan County Councils have been allocated funding in 2022 for active travel projects under the NTA investment programme.</p></reply>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.256" nospeaker="true" ><p>Question No. 94 answered with Question No. 27.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.257" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE03900">Bus Services</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.258.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1525" speakername="Holly Cairns" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE04000"><p><i>95.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport his plans to install new bus shelters in south-west areas of County Cork. <b>[11735/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.259.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE04100"><p>As Minister for Transport, I have responsibility for policy and overall funding in relation to public transport.  The National Transport Authority (NTA) has statutory responsibility for the planning and development of public transport infrastructure, including the provision of bus shelters. </p>  <p>  Noting the NTA's responsibility in the matter, I have referred the Deputy's question to the NTA for a direct reply.  Please contact my private office if you do not receive a reply within 10 days.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.260" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE04200">Aviation Industry</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.261.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1562" speakername="Alan Farrell" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE04300"><p><i>96.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the detail of the new routes from Cork, Dublin, Shannon, Donegal, Kerry and Ireland West Knock airports introduced since restrictions on non-essential international travel were lifted in July 2021 <b>[12144/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.262.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1578" speakername="Hildegarde Naughton" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE04400"><p>Since the lifting of the restrictions on non-essential travel last July, we have welcomed the resumption of flights and the early signs of the restoration of connectivity from our airports. </p>  <p>  As part of a &euro;160 million funding package provided by Government to support the sector, &euro;116 million was allocated to our airports under a Covid Supplementary Support Scheme to support the aviation sector&rsquo;s recovery as European and international air transport resumed.  This funding helped compensate our smaller regional airports for the damage caused by COVID -19 as well as providing our State airports with flexibility to roll out route incentives/charge rebates, in consultation with airlines, which has helped facilitate the recovery of connectivity.</p>  <p>  Decisions on the operation of new routes from Irish Airports are made on a commercial basis by individual operators.  My Department&rsquo;s role in relation to air services includes granting authorisations to third country air operators seeking to carry out commercial services to and from Ireland.  No such authorisations are required for European operators operating within the Single Aviation Market.  Therefore, the information requested is not readily available in my Department. However, my Department is seeking this information from the relevant airports and will forward it to the Deputy as shortly.  </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.263" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE04500">Road Network</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.264.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1510" speakername="John Paul Phelan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE04600"><p><i>97.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the changes he plans to make to ensure those national route improvements not funded by Transport Infrastructure Ireland in 2022 will still be progressed towards construction including the N24 Waterford to Cahir road; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12078/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.265.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE04700"><p>As Minister for Transport, I have responsibility for overall policy and exchequer funding in relation to the National Roads Programme. Once funding arrangements have been put in place with Transport Infrastructure Ireland (TII), under the Roads Acts 1993-2015 and in line with the National Development Plan (NDP), the planning, design and construction of individual national roads is a matter for TII, in conjunction with the local authorities concerned. This is also subject to the Public Spending Code and the necessary statutory approvals. In this context, TII is best placed to advise on the current status and funding of this proposed project.  </p>  <p>  Approximately &euro;615 million of exchequer capital funds have been provided for national roads through TII to local authorities in 2022. The 2022 funding allocations are made having regard for the NDP, which balances investment in transport against other priorities of Government, such as housing and health over the lifetime of the Plan. It was necessary to prioritise projects for funding in a manner which seeks to achieve key outcomes in line with the NDP.  </p>  <p>  Noting the above position, I have referred your question to TII for a direct reply. Please advise my private office if you do not receive a reply within 10 working days.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.266" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE04800">Bus Services</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.267.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1486" speakername="Br&iacute;d Smith" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE04900"><p><i>98.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport if he will clarify the causes of the cancellation of bus services provided by a company (details supplied) in the Dublin area; if he will examine whether this is a result of an inability to retain staff; if this is impacting on plans to improve public transport services generally; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12058/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.268.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE05000"><p>As Minister for Transport, I have responsibility for policy and overall funding in relation to public transport; however, I am not involved in the day-to-day operations of public transport. The National Transport Authority (NTA) has statutory responsibility for securing the provision of public passenger transport services nationally and for the scheduling of these services in conjunction with the relevant transport operators.   </p>  <p>  In light of the Authority's responsibility in this area, I have forwarded the Deputy's specific question in relation to Go-Ahead Ireland bus services to the NTA for direct reply.  Please advise my private office if you do not receive a response within ten working days.</p></reply>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.269" nospeaker="true" ><p>Question No. 99 answered with Question No. 81.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.270" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE05200">Road Projects</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.271.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1451" speakername="Matt Carthy" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE05300"><p><i>100.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the expected timeframe to deliver the N2 Clontibret to the Border road scheme. <b>[11296/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.272.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300062#WRE05400"><p>As Minister for Transport, I have responsibility for overall policy and exchequer funding in relation to the National Roads Programme. Once funding arrangements have been put in place with Transport Infrastructure Ireland (TII), under the Roads Acts 1993-2015 and in line with the National Development Plan (NDP), the planning, design and construction of individual national roads is a matter for TII, in conjunction with the local authorities concerned. This is also subject to the Public Spending Code and the necessary statutory approvals. </p>  <p>  Approximately &euro;615 million of exchequer capital funds have been provided for national roads through TII to local authorities in 2022. The 2022 funding allocations are made having regard for the NDP, which balances investment in transport against other priorities of Government, such as housing and health over the lifetime of the Plan. It was necessary to prioritise projects for funding in a manner which seeks to achieve key outcomes in line with the NDP. Resulting from this, while a large majority of the projects under the NDP were issued a funding allocation in 2022, TII were unable to provide an allocation for the N2 Clontibret to the Border scheme. The delivery programme for this project will be kept under review for next year and considered in terms of the overall funding envelope available to TII.</p>  <p>  Noting the above position, I have referred your question to TII for a direct reply. Please advise my private office if you do not receive a reply within 10 working days.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.274" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300063#WRF00200">Greenways Provision</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.275.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1581" speakername="Brendan Griffin" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300063#WRF00300"><p><i>101.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport if funding will be provided to build the South Kerry Greenway; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12094/22]</b></p></ques>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.276.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1581" speakername="Brendan Griffin" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300063#WRF00400"><p><i>105.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport if he has engaged with Transport Infrastructure Ireland in relation to the South Kerry Greenway; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12095/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.277.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300063#WRF00500"><p>I propose to take Questions Nos. 101 and 105 together.</p>  <p>  Transport Infrastructure Ireland (TII) became the Approving Authority for Greenways in September 2021 and have allocated &euro;1.7m to progress the South Kerry Greenway in 2022.</p>  <p>  I understand that discussions are ongoing between TII and Kerry County Council to progress this iconic route through the Public Spending Code and the implications of the planning permission granted for the majority of the route. Some elements remain without planning permission and this will be addressed over the coming months. I would not imagine that funding would be an issue, once the Public Spending Code and TII Project Management Guidelines are followed, as my Department is providing significant funding for Greenways through TII.</p>  <p>  I have not personally engaged with TII in relation to this specific project but am updated on progress on Greenways by officials in my Department who engage with TII on a regular basis. </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.278" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300063#WRF00600">Transport Policy</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.279.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1617" speakername="Marc &Oacute; Cathasaigh" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300063#WRF00700"><p><i>102.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the position regarding the Sustainability Mobility Policy to help enable persons to choose healthy and sustainable modes of transport over private car journeys; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12129/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.280.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300063#WRF00800"><p>I will shortly publish the new Sustainable Mobility Policy which will set out a strategic framework to 2030 for active travel and public transport to support Ireland's overall requirement to achieve a 51% reduction in carbon emissions by the end of this decade.  The policy will primarily focus on measures to promote and facilitate active travel and public transport for all and, in doing so, encourage less private car journeys nationally to support our climate commitment.  It will replace the existing active travel and public transport policy as set out in the 2009 policy documents: Smarter Travel, A Sustainable Transport Future and the National Cycle Policy Framework.  </p>  <p>  A collaborative approach has been taken by my Department in developing the Sustainable Mobility Policy through public consultation and extensive stakeholder engagement.  The policy will include a comprehensive set of actions to be completed by 2025 to increase walking and cycling infrastructure provision and improve public transport capacity and services across the country.  These will be supported by behavioural change and demand management measures to make sustainable modes the preferred choice for as many people as possible.  Transport needs are not uniform across the country and we recognise that tailored solutions will be needed for both urban and rural areas. A further action plan will then be developed to cover the remaining period of the policy out to 2030.</p>  <p>  The new policy will be underpinned by capital funding under the National Development Plan which provides &euro;35 billion for transport over the next decade.  This will enable significant investment in active travel, bus and rail infrastructure and expand sustainable mobility options in our cities, towns and villages. This will be complemented by expanded public transport services throughout the country as supported by the Public Service Obligation programme.</p>  <p>  The targets of the policy will be aligned with the transport target metrics in the Climate Action Plan 2021 of 500,000 additional daily active travel and public transport journeys and a 10% reduction in kilometres driven by fossil fuelled cars by 2030.  </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.281" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300063#WRF00900">Road Projects</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.282.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1513" speakername="Pauline Tully" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300063#WRF01000"><p><i>103.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the status of the Carrickmacross to Ardee and the Clontibret to the Border road schemes; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[10490/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.283.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300063#WRF01100"><p>As Minister for Transport, I have responsibility for overall policy and exchequer funding in relation to the National Roads Programme. Once funding arrangements have been put in place with Transport Infrastructure Ireland (TII), under the Roads Acts 1993-2015 and in line with the National Development Plan (NDP), the planning, design and construction of individual national roads is a matter for TII, in conjunction with the local authorities concerned. This is also subject to the Public Spending Code and the necessary statutory approvals.</p>  <p>  Approximately &euro;615 million of exchequer capital funds have been provided for national roads through TII to local authorities in 2022. The 2022 funding allocations are made having regard for the NDP, which balances investment in transport against other priorities of Government, such as housing and health over the lifetime of the Plan. It was necessary to prioritise projects for funding in a manner which seeks to achieve key outcomes in line with the NDP. Resulting from this, while a large majority of the projects under the NDP were issued a funding allocation in 2022, TII were unable to provide an allocation for the N2 Clontibret to the Border project. The delivery programme for this project will be kept under review for next year and considered in terms of the overall funding envelope available to TII.</p>  <p>  Funding of &euro;1 million has been allocated by TII for the progression of the N2 Ardee to south of Castleblayney project. TII is best placed to advise on the current status and funding of this proposed project.   </p>  <p>  Noting the above position, I have referred your question to TII for a direct reply. Please advise my private office if you do not receive a reply within 10 working days. </p></reply>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.284" nospeaker="true" ><p>Question No. 104 answered with Question No. 49.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.285" nospeaker="true" ><p>Question No. 105 answered with Question No. 101.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.286" nospeaker="true" ><p>Question No. 106 answered with Question No. 34.</p></speech>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.288.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1598" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300063#WRF01600"><p><i>107.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport the status of discussions or plans that have taken place further to his meeting with this Deputy on 7 December 2021 regarding a key strategic road infrastructure project for Drogheda; and his views on the matter. <b>[11802/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.289.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300063#WRF01700"><p>As indicated previously, Louth County Council is the statutory planning and road authority in its functional area. In this context the first section of the Port Access Northern Cross Route (PANCR) which is under consideration is aimed at facilitating housing development and contacts since the meeting with the Deputy in December indicate that the Council is engaging with developers with a view to advancing this element of the scheme.  My Department has no role in that process.</p>  <p>  I should again mention, as I said to the Deputy at our meeting, that there is a limited budget available for projects under the Regional and Local Road Strategic Grant Programme and that the implementation of a number of the larger NDP schemes which are now at construction stage will absorb much of the funding available in the period to 2025.  It should also be noted that, under the Public Spending Code, a Strategic Assessment Report (SAR) is required for all projects which are estimated to cost in excess of &euro;10 million. To date no SAR report has been received by my Department for this proposed project.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.290" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300063#WRF01800">Road Network</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.291.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1482" speakername="Se&aacute;n Canney" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300063#WRF01900"><p><i>108.</i> To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport if his Department will provide funding to support the local improvement scheme which is presently funded by the Department of Rural and Community Development; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12070/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.292.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300063#WRF02000"><p>Since the post 2008 recession a substantial backlog of works on regional and local roads has built up in all local authority jurisdictions across the country. The estimated cost of the backlog is in excess of &euro;5 billion. For this reason, grant assistance from the Department continues to be focussed on the protection and renewal of the public road network. </p>  <p>  It bears restating that the public regional and road network is over 96,000 kilometres in size and while there has been significant increases in grant funding in recent years, it has not been possible to address the backlog of works across the country even with 90% of available funds being directed to protection and renewal works.  For this reason and in view of the funding being provided under a Local Improvement Scheme by the Department of Rural and Community Development, I consider that I need to continue to concentrate funding on public roads.</p>  <p>  If I were to consider allocating funding for non-public roads this would reduce the funding available for public roads.  In this context one initiative taken since the Department of Rural and Community Development's introduction of a Local Improvement Scheme is the provision by my Department of ring-fenced funding for the Community Involvement Scheme (CIS).  This scheme is designed to provide for the repair of more lightly trafficked public rural roads, which tend to be considered only towards the end of road authorities&rsquo; annual roadworks programmes.  Under this scheme, &euro;29 million approximately was paid to local authorities over the 2 year 2020-2021 period and this year's grants include funding of a further &euro;15.2 million for the CIS.  </p>  <p>  All available grant funding for 2022 has been allocated.</p></reply>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.293" nospeaker="true" ><p>Questions Nos. 109 to 113, inclusive, answered orally.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.295" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300063#WRF02300">Department of Housing, Planning, and Local Government</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.294" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300063#WRF02200">Housing Provision</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.295.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1473" speakername="Neale Richmond" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300063#WRF02300"><p><i>114.</i> To ask the Minister for Housing, Planning, and Local Government the number of commencements of new homes in 2021, by county; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[11833/22]</b></p></ques>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.296.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1562" speakername="Alan Farrell" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300063#WRF02350"><p><i>143.</i> To ask the Minister for Housing, Planning, and Local Government the number of commencements in 2021 on new homes. <b>[12143/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.297.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1561" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300063#WRF02400"><p>I propose to take Questions Nos. 114 and 143 together.</p>  <p>  Housing for All is the Government&rsquo;s plan to increase the supply of housing to an average of 33,000 per year over the next decade. Over 300,000 new homes will be built by the end of 2030, including a projected 90,000 social homes, 36,000 affordable purchase homes and 18,000 cost rental homes.</p>  <p>  Indications of increased construction activity are becoming evident which will help increase the supply and availability of housing.</p>  <p>  There is a strong supply pipeline, with Commencement Notices data showing a total number of 30,724 residential dwellings commenced in 2021. This is a 42% increase when compared to the number of residential dwellings commenced in 2020 (21,686). The 2021 total is almost equal to the combined totals for 2016 and 2017 (30,816).</p>  <p>  New figures shows that in the past twelve months (February 2021 to January 2022), Commencement Notices for 31,201 new homes were received. This is the highest rolling 12-month total since comparable data was first published. The breakdown, by local authority area, is published on the Housing for All campaign page of gov.ie.</p>  <p>  With regard to the number of homes built, there were 20,433 new dwellings completed in 2021. Completions for 2022 and 2023 are projected to exceed the Housing for All targets of 24,600 and 29,000 respectively. The Central Bank forecasts that some 27,000 and 31,000 homes will be completed in 2022 and 2023 respectively.</p>  <p>  Increasing the supply of housing as set out in Housing for All is the top priority for me and the Government and we have made a good start on our path towards this goal. However, I acknowledge that we are coming from a low base of supply and that it will take some time before the full benefits of the strategy are tangible to our citizens.</p>  <p>  The housing challenge remains immense, and continues to be affected by ongoing challenges including COVID-19 related delays, supply chain difficulties and inflationary pressure. The cost of housing &ndash; for those buying or renting - will continue to be a challenge in the short-term and, while we do not underestimate the difficulties this is causing for our citizens, I am confident that the delivery of Housing for All will create a sustainable housing system into the future.</p>  <p>   </p></reply>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.298" nospeaker="true" ><p>Questions Nos. 115 to 117, inclusive, answered orally.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.299" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300063#WRF02600">Housing Schemes</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.300.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1522" speakername="Mick Barry" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300063#WRF02700"><p><i>118.</i> To ask the Minister for Housing, Planning, and Local Government if he will ensure there are no barriers in relation to waiting lists for social housing that pressure persons to remain in abusive relationships in order to maintain their position on waiting lists; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12110/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.301.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1512" speakername="Malcolm Noonan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300063#WRF02800"><p>To  qualify for social housing support and be placed on a housing list, an applicant household must be assessed by the local authority concerned as meeting all of the eligibility and need criteria set down in the Housing (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act 2009 and the associated Social Housing Assessment Regulations.</p>  <p>  Local authorities may prioritise certain classes of households for allocation on the basis of severity of need. They may also reserve a certain proportion of dwellings for, among other things, allocation to particular categories of households, particular forms of tenure, and households transferring from other forms of social housing support. </p>  <p>  Local authorities may also provide for exceptional or emergency cases, allowing immediate housing outside of normal waiting lists priorities, should circumstances require. As an immediate and short term response, a local authority may provide short-term emergency housing to persons forced to leave their homes because of domestic violence, without having to assess their eligibility for social housing support.</p>  <p>  A new protocol was also established in 2020 when the Minister for Social Protection agreed to make rent supplement more accessible to victims of domestic violence, ensuring they would not be prevented from leaving their homes because of financial or accommodation difficulties.</p></reply>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.302" nospeaker="true" ><p>Questions Nos. 119 and 120 answered orally.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.304" nospeaker="true" ><p>Question No. 121 answered orally.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.305" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG00300">Defective Building Materials</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.306.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1599" speakername="Gerald Nash" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG00400"><p><i>122.</i> To ask the Minister for Housing, Planning, and Local Government the status of the emergency repair grant allocated to MICA homeowners; if that grant is controlled by his Department or by the local authority; the way the emergency repair grant can be accessed by homeowners who need the grant urgently particularly in view of recent storms; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12044/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.307.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1561" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG00500"><p>I brought a Memorandum to Government on an enhanced Defective Concrete Blocks Grant Scheme on the 30 November 2021. It included an unprecedented suite of improvements to the current scheme. Government approved the enhanced scheme which it is estimated will cost approximately &euro;2.2Bn.</p>  <p>  Full details in relation to the changes announced are available on my Departments website. I aim to bring the required primary legislation to give effect to the enhanced scheme before the Oireachtas as soon as possible with Spring 2022 being the indicative target timeline.</p>  <p>  In the interim, three enhancements to the current scheme have been brought into effect through amending regulations which I signed on the 24 February. These regulations make provision for the inclusion as an allowable cost of essential immediate repair works, up to a value of &euro;5,555, where such works relate to the structural stability of an affected home. The regulations also make provision in specific circumstances for the recoupment of the fees connected with the provision of the engineer&rsquo;s report without the need for a prior stage 1 confirmation of eligibility and for an increase from 75% to 85% in the value of stage payments which can be recouped prior to the final grant payment.</p>  <p>  It is a matter for the relevant local authorities, as scheme administrators, to roll out the benefits of these immediate enhancements to eligible homeowners. My Department has provided detailed guidance to assist local authorities in this regard and I expect to see eligible homeowners benefit from these changes quite quickly.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.308" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG00600">Housing Policy</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.309.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1454" speakername="Michael Creed" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG00700"><p><i>123.</i> To ask the Minister for Housing, Planning, and Local Government if he will review housing supports available from his Department for first-time buyers of new and second-hand properties in view of the difficulties that existing schemes pose in particular for single persons on modest incomes; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12115/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.310.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1595" speakername="Peter Burke" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG00800"><p>The Housing for All strategy is a multi-faceted approach to step up housing supply and put affordability at the heart of the housing system. </p>  <p>  The strategy introduces two new affordable purchase schemes (the Local Authority Affordable Purchase Scheme and the First Home shared equity scheme), as well as an improved Local Authority Home Loan scheme, which are primarily targeted to support First-time Buyers.</p>  <p>  The Local Authority Affordable Purchase Scheme will support eligible purchasers of Local Authority-delivered new homes. Regulations setting out the detailed eligibility criteria for the scheme will be issued in the coming weeks.</p>  <p>  The First Home shared equity scheme will be available to eligible First-time Buyers purchasing new build homes through the private market. It is anticipated the scheme will be available from the second half of this year.</p>  <p>  Both of these schemes can be used in conjunction with the Help-to-Buy incentive which supports First-time Buyers in meeting the deposit requirements for new build and self-build homes.</p>  <p>  The new Local Authority Home Loan scheme commenced on 4 January 2022, replacing the Rebuilding Ireland Home Loan, and incorporates more favorable terms for eligible First-time Buyers purchasing new or second-hand homes, or self-builds. The new scheme incorporates a lower interest rate and, specifically for single applicants, has increased income eligibility thresholds from &euro;50,000 to &euro;65,000  in Cork, Dublin, Galway, Kildare, Louth, Meath and Wicklow which will support homeownership for single people.</p></reply>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.311" nospeaker="true" ><p>Questions Nos. 124 and 125 answered orally.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.312" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG01000">Housing Provision</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.313.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1570" speakername="Patrick Costello" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG01100"><p><i>126.</i> To ask the Minister for Housing, Planning, and Local Government if he will provide an update on the planned cost-rental development at a location (detail supplied). <b>[10836/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.314.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1512" speakername="Malcolm Noonan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG01200"><p>Emmet Road is an important project for the development of the Cost Rental sector in Ireland. I understand the Deputy's specific interest in this project and the need to keep local residents informed of what is a large-scale project within their area. I know Minister O'Brien has met with the residents directly, most recently in December last. I am also aware of how rigorous the design process for such a large site can be, and appreciate the work undertaken by the Council to date. </p>  <p>  The plan to deliver Cost Rental homes here under a Local Authority-led financing structure is a key element in the long-term delivery of Cost Rental more generally, and one that could be replicated elsewhere. A dedicated Dublin City Council Project Manager and project team is working on the development and it is a key deliverable in its Housing Programme. </p>  <p>  Along with Minister O'Brien, I am pleased that the Council has advised that the concept design was presented to Councillors on Tuesday and to the Inchicore Regeneration Consultative Forum yesterday. This design will be presented to the public during Phase 3 of the Consultation process, running from the 8th to the 31st of March. Following this consultation and some further refinements, it is the Council's intention to submit a full planning application by end 2022.  </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.315" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG01300">Housing Schemes</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.316.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1569" speakername="Joan Collins" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG01400"><p><i>127.</i> To ask the Minister for Housing, Planning, and Local Government his plans to upgrade or amend the HAP scheme (details supplied); his further plans to increase the HAP rent caps to a level that reflects current rents; and his views on whether families in accommodation that no longer suits their needs should be allowed to move to another tenancy and at the same time hold onto the HAP given that many of these tenancies are now years in existence <b>[12104/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.317.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1595" speakername="Peter Burke" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG01500"><p>The Housing Assistance Payment (HAP) scheme plays a vital role in housing eligible families and individuals. </p>  <p>  HAP rent limits were set in conjunction with the Department of Social Protection in 2016. Local authorities also have discretion, because of local rental market conditions, to exceed the maximum rent limit by up to 20%, or up to 50% in the Dublin region for those households either in, or at immediate risk of homelessness. </p>  <p>  Under Housing for All, my Department was tasked with undertaking an analytical exercise to examine whether an increase in the level of discretion available to Local Authorities under HAP is required, in order to maintain adequate levels of HAP support.  </p>  <p>  The Housing Agency undertook to carry out this analytical exercise on behalf of my Department. The review was submitted on 20 December 2021. It is undergoing analysis by my Department and Minister O&rsquo;Brien  expects to receive recommendations following that analysis. </p>  <p>  HAP provides flexibility to tenants to source accommodation in the private rental market that suits their needs. </p>  <p>  In relation to moving from one tenancy to another, on entering HAP, the tenant is required to stay in the same property for at least two years. However, you may be able to apply to your local authority for a new HAP payment for another property sooner if your circumstances change. For example, if you receive a job offer in another area, or if your family changes in size and the property is no longer big enough.  </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.318" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG01600">Building Regulations</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.319.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1599" speakername="Gerald Nash" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG01700"><p><i>128.</i> To ask the Minister for Housing, Planning, and Local Government his plans to issue revised ministerial guidelines to harmonise apartment standards in respect of build-to-sell and build-to-rent apartments in order to incentivise the development of build-to-sell homes; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12042/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.320.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1595" speakername="Peter Burke" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG01800"><p>Build-to-rent was first referenced in 2015 in response to emerging trends, which include on-going population growth, a move towards smaller average household size, an ageing population and a greater proportion of households in the rented sector. At that time, apartments had become a more common form of dwelling in urban areas, comprising 11% of all occupied households in Ireland and almost one-third of occupied households in Dublin City (Census 2011).  </p>  <p>  By 2016, this had risen to 12%. In 2018, my Department published the updated Sustainable Urban Housing Development Guidelines to respond to changing housing need, in light of emerging dynamics in the urban employment market and ongoing demographic trends. The 2018 Guidelines addressed the relatively new build-to-rent sector and sets out a number of key distinct characteristics.  </p>  <p>  Since 2018, build-to-rent developments have formed a relatively small proportion of all planning applications lodged, accounting for less than 20% of the total units approved under the SHD process.  </p>  <p>  The Government supports home ownership and has taken firm action to protect traditional family homes (from bulk purchases), while maintaining investment where it is needed. Housing for All includes the introduction of the &lsquo;owner-occupier&rsquo; guarantee, the Croi Conaithe (Cities) Fund and the Croi Conaithe (Towns) Fund, in addition to affordable purchase, shared equity, Local Authority Home Loan and Help to Buy Schemes. Build-to-rent is not the only solution but is a legitimate form of tenure, with secure long-term professional landlords that will provide a proportion of much needed accommodation for those who wish to rent. Following a review of co-living in 2020, updated Sustainable Urban Development guidelines were published and I have no plans to further amend the guidelines from this perspective.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.321" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG01900">Derelict Sites</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.322.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1604" speakername="Claire Kerrane" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG02000"><p><i>129.</i> To ask the Minister for Housing, Planning, and Local Government the way that he plans to address ongoing issues in relation to the dereliction and regeneration of derelict buildings under the Town Centre First policy particularly in relation to incentivising or penalising persons who own vacant or derelict properties but are not utilising them; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[8610/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.323.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1512" speakername="Malcolm Noonan" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG02100"><p>The Town Centre First policy, jointly developed by my Department and the Department of Rural and Community Development, sets out 33 actions which will provide a co-ordinated framework across established national policy objectives (in particular the National Planning Framework, Housing for All and Our Rural Future) to address the decline in the health of our towns and sets out actions to regenerate and revitalise them.</p>  <p>  Addressing vacancy and maximising the use of existing housing stock is a primary objective of this Government and a number of measures are provided for in the Town Centre First policy and Housing for All to address vacancy and dereliction. The Cro&iacute; C&oacute;naithe (Towns) Fund will be delivered by local authorities for the provision of serviced sites for housing, to attract people to build their own homes and to support the refurbishment of vacant properties, enabling people to live in small towns and villages, in a sustainable way. This scheme is currently being designed with a call for proposals intended to issue to Local Authorities later this Quarter.</p>  <p>  In addition, Housing for All provides for the launching of a programme of Compulsory Purchase Orders to bring vacant units to the market for sale, as well as activating unused State owned properties for this purpose. A central advisory service is being established in the Housing Agency that will assist the Local Authorities in implementing this programme which seeks to bring 2,500 properties into residential use by 2026. The programme will also be supported by a bridging finance facility from the Housing Finance Agency for property acquisitions. </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.324" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG02200">Housing Policy</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.325.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1604" speakername="Claire Kerrane" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG02300"><p><i>130.</i> To ask the Minister for Housing, Planning, and Local Government if his attention has been drawn to the recent research by an organisation (details supplied) which found that the overall poverty rate of households receiving housing subsidies rises to 19% after they have paid their rent; the steps he will take to address this issue; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[5330/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.326.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1561" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG02400"><p>I recently met with representatives from Social Justice Ireland and I had a good engagement in relation to findings in their report and what this Government is doing to address housing affordability.</p>  <p>  Housing for All is the Government&rsquo;s plan to increase the supply of housing to an average of 33,000 per year over the next decade, rising to more than 40,000 by 2030. The plan provides for an optimal mix of social, affordable and private housing for sale and rent. It is underpinned by measures to support availability of the land, workforce, funding and capacity to enable both the public and private sectors to meet the targets. </p>  <p>  Increasing supply is at the centre of Housing for All. This includes direct investment in social and affordable housing, reforms to ensure availability of land, removal of obstacles to and supporting viability of development, and ensuring there is sufficient investment and capacity to support construction. </p>  <p>  The cost of housing - for those buying or renting &ndash; will continue to be a challenge in the short-term and, while I do not underestimate the difficulties this is causing for households, I am confident delivery of Housing for All will help meet demand, moderate costs and create a more sustainable housing system.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.327" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG02500">Housing Provision</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.328.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1599" speakername="Gerald Nash" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG02600"><p><i>131.</i> To ask the Minister for Housing, Planning, and Local Government the breakdown per local authority area of the affordable housing that is planned to be delivered in 2022; the details of each affordable housing scheme planned to be delivered in each local authority area in 2022; the details relating to the number of homes per scheme and the nature of the tenure in tabular form; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12043/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.329.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1561" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG02700"><p>At a national level 4,100 Affordable Purchase and Cost Rental homes are targeted for delivery in 2022 through a combination of Local Authorities, Approved Housing Bodies, the Land Development Agency and the First Home shared equity scheme. The annual national targets will increase incrementally over the Housing for All period.   </p>  <p>  Despite the impacts of Covid-19, 65 Cost Rental homes were delivered by Cl&uacute;id Housing last year. The 1,500 Cost Rental target for 2022 will be delivered by the LDA, AHBs supported by the Cost Rental Equity Loan, as well as Local Authorities partnering with AHBs, as can be seen on the upcoming Enniskerry Road development in D&uacute;n Laoghaire-Rathdown.  </p>  <p>  Further affordable homes for purchase are coming on stream, with Cork City Council delivering 22 Affordable Purchase homes in Boherboy in the coming weeks, South Dublin County Council recently advertising 16 Affordable Purchase homes in Kilcarbery and Fingal County Council will make available 39 Affordable Purchase homes in Lusk. </p>  <p>  The First Home scheme will be available on a national level from the second half of this year. This demand-led scheme targets 1,750 supports for 2022.  </p>  <p>  A Housing Delivery Action Plan prepared by each Local Authority will underpin delivery in the period 2022 to 2026 and provide projected affordable housing delivery. Local authorities submitted the first iteration of their plans in December and my officials have now met with each. I expect that the final Delivery Action Plans will be published in Q2. </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.330" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG02800">Derelict Sites</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.331.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1583" speakername="James Lawless" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG02900"><p><i>132.</i> To ask the Minister for Housing, Planning, and Local Government if he will report on his work to tackle vacancy and dereliction in County Kildare. <b>[12096/22]</b></p></ques>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.332.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1577" speakername="Catherine Connolly" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG03000"><p><i>205.</i> To ask the Minister for Housing, Planning, and Local Government the engagement he has had with Galway City and County Councils in 2021 and to date in 2022 with regard to addressing the issue of vacant houses in both local authority areas; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[11944/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.333.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1561" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG03100"><p>I propose to take Questions Nos. 132 and 205 together.</p>  <p>  Housing for All (published in September 2021) provides a new housing plan for Ireland to 2030 with the overall objective that every citizen in the State should have access to good quality homes through a steady supply of housing in the right locations, with economic, social and environmental sustainability built into the system. The strategy sets out, over four pathways, a broad suite of measures to achieve its policy objectives together with a financial commitment of in excess of &euro;4 billion per annum.</p>  <p>  My ongoing engagement with local authorities on the delivery of the objectives under Housing for All includes engagement through the delivery of the suite of measures under the pathway to addressing vacancy and efficient use of existing stock. I am ensuring that all local authorities, including Galway City and County Councils, and Kildare County Council, are best positioned and funded to deal with the challenges of vacancy in their town and villages in an appropriate and timely manner.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.334" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG03200">Building Regulations</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.335.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1513" speakername="Pauline Tully" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG03300"><p><i>133.</i> To ask the Minister for Housing, Planning, and Local Government his plans to review the Building Regulations, 2010, Part M (Access and Use) to ensure higher wheelchair accessibility standards in new houses and apartments; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12083/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.336.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1595" speakername="Peter Burke" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG03400"><p>The Building Regulations apply to the design and construction of all new buildings (including dwellings) and to certain works to existing buildings. They are subject to ongoing review in the interests of safety and the well-being of persons in the built environment and to ensure that due regard is taken of changes in construction techniques, technological progress and innovation.</p><p>The Building Regulations (Part M Amendment) Regulations 2010, and the accompanying Technical Guidance Document M &ndash; Access and Use (2010), which came into effect on 1 January 2012, set out the minimum statutory requirements that a building must achieve in respect of access and use. </p><p>The accompanying Technical Guidance Document M &ndash; Access and Use (2010), sets out the minimum statutory requirements that a building must achieve in respect of access. The TGDs are available on my Department&rsquo;s website at: .</p><p>The requirements of Part M aim to ensure that regardless of age, size or disability:</p><p>-  new buildings other than dwellings are accessible and usable;</p><p>-  extensions to existing buildings other than dwellings are, where practicable, accessible and useable;</p><p>-  material alterations to existing buildings other than dwellings increase the accessibility and usability of existing buildings, where practicable;</p><p>-  certain changes of use to existing buildings other than dwellings increase the accessibility and usability of existing buildings where practicable; and</p><p>-  new dwellings are visitable.</p><p>Part M aims to foster an inclusive approach to the design and construction of the built environment. While the Part M requirements may be regarded as a statutory minimum level of provision, the accompanying technical guidance encourages building owners and designers to have regard to the design philosophy of universal design and to consider making additional provisions where practicable and appropriate.</p><p>Since 2011 housing for disabled people has been addressed in a dedicated joint Strategy between the Department and the Department of Health. A new joint National Housing Strategy for Disabled People (NHSDP) 2022-2027  was launched on 14 January 2022. (See Press release available at .</p><p>The new Strategy sets out the vision for the cooperation and collaboration of Government Departments, state agencies and others in delivering housing and the related supports for disabled people over the next five years. This new Strategy will operate within the framework of Housing for All &ndash; A New Housing Plan for Ireland which is committed to ensuring that affordable, quality housing with an appropriate mix of housing design types provided within social housing, including universally designed units, is available to everyone in Irish society, including those with disabilities and older people. Preparation of an Implementation Plan for the Strategy will begin in the first quarter of 2022 with a target for completion by the second quarter.</p><p>Separately, Action 97 of the National Disability Inclusion Strategy 2017-2021 states &ndash; &ldquo;We will prepare policy advice on ways of achieving universal design solutions for new housing so that new homes can be accessed and used by all persons, irrespective of size, age, ability or disability. We will advise on any implications of same for stakeholders including designers, builders, homeowners and tenants.&rdquo; I understand that the National Disability Authority (NDA), which falls under the remit of my colleague, the Minister for Children, Equality, Disability, Integration, and Youth, is working on this policy advice. The NDA are an independent statutory body that provides information and advice to the Government on policy and practice relevant to the lives of persons with disabilities.</p><p>The NDA also provides comprehensive guidance on how to design, build and manage buildings and spaces so that they can be readily accessed and used by everyone, regardless of age, size, ability or disability. 'Building for Everyone, A Universal Design Approach', a NDA publication, may be accessed at <i>www.nda.ie</i>.</p><p>The &lsquo;Programme for Government Our Shared Future&rsquo; commits to ensuring that there is an appropriate mix of housing design types provided, including universally designed units, and accommodation for older people and people with disabilities. </p><p>The joint policy statement Housing Options for Our Ageing Population, launched by my Department and the Department of Health in 2019, includes an Action on universal design to &ldquo;In partnership with industry, introduce measures to ensure that over a five year period delivery is increased to ensure that 30% of all new dwellings are built to incorporate universal design principles to accommodate our ageing population.&rdquo;  Appropriate analysis to identify delivery approaches to address this commitment is currently being undertaken by the NDA.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.337" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG03500">Local Authorities</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.338.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1480" speakername="Jennifer Carroll MacNeill" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG03600"><p><i>134.</i> To ask the Minister for Housing, Planning, and Local Government the status of his plans in relation to maternity leave for councillors; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12053/22]</b></p></ques>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.339.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1473" speakername="Neale Richmond" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG03700"><p><i>198.</i> To ask the Minister for Housing, Planning, and Local Government the status of the work to ensure that councillors can access maternity leave; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[11832/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.340.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1595" speakername="Peter Burke" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG03800"><p>I propose to take Questions Nos. 134 and 198 together.</p>  <p>  Councillors, like members of the Oireachtas, are office holders rather than employees. As such, they are not covered by the statutory framework for employees in relation to maternity leave. </p>  <p>  I recognise that this is an obstacle to the participation of women in local government, which I am determined to address urgently and comprehensively.  The role of the councillor must be one that is accessible, manageable and sustainable for all, thus helping to ensure that councillors are more fully representative of the constituents they serve. </p>  <p>  As matters currently stand, it is only under the provisions of Section 18 of the Local Government Act 2001 that councillors may be absent from the role for maternity purposes. Under Section 18, a councillor shall be deemed to have automatically resigned from membership of a local authority if he or she is absent from meetings for a continuous period of 6 consecutive months. Where the absence is due to illness or &ldquo;in good faith for another reason&rdquo;, then the period of absence may be extended first to 12 months and then to up to 18 months by resolution of the Council. </p>  <p>  It should be acknowledged that a councillor who is absent for 6 months for maternity related reasons will continue to receive the full amount of her Representational Payment. Thereafter this payment is reduced by 50% for absences of 6 to 12 months duration. A councillor who is absent for more than 12 months will not receive any further payments regardless of the reason for the absence. </p>  <p>  With effect from January 2017, the Social Welfare Acts were amended so that councillors gained access to the same benefits as self-employed contributors. Accordingly, councillors are now reckonable for the purposes of accessing Class S benefits, including Maternity Benefit. </p>  <p>  On 29 March 2021, I hosted the first meeting of a working group of women councillors established to examine all maternity-related matters, including wider supports other than maternity leave. This group, which is a representative and cross political party group of women councillors, met a number of times in 2021. Their extensive deliberations have given my officials and I greater understanding of the needs of women councillors and have been important in the development of a policy approach.  </p>  <p>  My Department has since engaged extensively with the Office of the Attorney General on legal questions arising. My officials are also engaging very constructively with the Department of Children, Equality, Disability, Integration and Youth with a view to bringing councillors under the maternity protection legislative framework.   </p>  <p>  Following this work, it is my intention to bring forward a package of maternity-related supports and measures for councillors, including progressive proposals for legislative change, which is currently being finalised by my Department. </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.341" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG03900">Housing Provision</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.342.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1516" speakername="James O'Connor" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG04000"><p><i>135.</i> To ask the Minister for Housing, Planning, and Local Government the plans of his Department to provide social and affordable housing in an area (details supplied). <b>[12136/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.343.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1561" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG04100"><p>Housing for All is the Government&rsquo;s plan to increase the supply of housing to an average of 33,000 per year over the next decade. Over 300,000 new homes will be built by the end of 2030, including a projected 90,000 social homes, 36,000 affordable purchase homes and 18,000 cost rental homes. Social housing build and lease targets for the period 2022 - 2026 issued to local authorities in September 2021.</p><p>The social housing build and lease targets for Cork City Council and Cork County Council are set out below.  <table>    <tr>       <th>-</th>       <th>2022 Lease</th>       <th>2022 Build</th>       <th>2023 Lease</th>       <th>2023 Build</th>       <th>2024 Lease</th>       <th>2024 Build</th>       <th>2025 Build</th>       <th>2026 Build</th>    </tr>    <tr>       <td>Cork City</td>       <td>81 </td>       <td>515 </td>       <td>71 </td>       <td>536 </td>       <td>50 </td>       <td>548 </td>       <td>589 </td>       <td>601 </td>    </tr>    <tr>       <td>Cork County</td>       <td>0 </td>       <td>560 </td>       <td>0 </td>       <td>622 </td>       <td>0 </td>       <td>636 </td>       <td>683 </td>       <td>697 </td>    </tr> </table> </p><p>My Department publishes a detailed Social Housing Construction Status Report (CSR) each quarter, which provides scheme level detail on new build activity. The most recent publication covers the period up to the end of Quarter 3 2021 and is available at the following link: . The CSR provides details of the individual projects that make up the social housing new build programme for each local authority. An excel version of this file can be downloaded at the following link:  <i>data.gov.ie/dataset/social-housing-construction-status-report-q3-2021?package_type=dataset</i>.</p><p>The Affordable Housing Act 2021, the first ever standalone affordable housing legislation, established a basis for four new affordable housing measures. These measures will deliver on the Programme for Government commitment to put affordability at the heart of the housing system and prioritise the increased supply of affordable homes through (1) delivering affordable homes on local authority lands, (2) the introduction of a new form of tenure in Cost Rental, (3) a First Home shared equity scheme and (4) expanding Part V planning requirements to increase the 10% contribution requirement to 20% and to apply it to cost rental as well as social and affordable housing.</p><p>At a national level, 2,550 Affordable Purchase homes and 1,580 Cost Rental homes are targeted for delivery for 2022. Annual targets will increase incrementally in subsequent years. These homes will be delivered by the local authorities, Approved Housing Bodies and the Land Development Agency.</p><p>Delivery of affordable housing will be underpinned by local authorities' Housing Delivery Action Plans. Each local authority submitted a Plan to me in December 2021, and my Department has been engaging with local authorities on the Plans.  The Housing Delivery Action Plans will be published in Quarter 2 and will set out details of affordable delivery in each local authority. </p><p>The first Affordable Purchase homes delivered through the Local Authority Affordable Purchase Scheme will be made available in Boherboy, Cork City later this month. Cork City Council indicated the prices to be &euro;218,000 and &euro;243,000 for a 3-bedroom dwelling. Two separate Cost Rental schemes, managed by Cl&uacute;id and Respond, will be provided in Cork City and will be available in the second half of this year.</p><p>The First Home shared equity scheme will be available nationally on a demand-led basis. This scheme will primarily support first-time buyers purchasing new homes through the private market. I expect that a significant proportion of First Home supported home purchases will be located in Cork, in proportion to the market for newly constructed homes.</p></reply>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.345.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1611" speakername="Jackie Cahill" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG04300"><p><i>136.</i> To ask the Minister for Housing, Planning, and Local Government the details of the plans of his Department to deliver social housing in County Tipperary between 2022 and 2026; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[11862/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.346.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1561" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG04400"><p>Housing for All is the Government&rsquo;s plan to increase the supply of housing to an average of 33,000 per year over the next decade. This includes the delivery of an average of 10,000 new social homes and 6,000 affordable homes each year. Over 300,000 new homes will be built by the end of 2030, including a projected 90,000 social homes, 36,000 affordable purchase homes and 18,000 cost rental homes. Housing for All is supported by an investment package of over &euro;4bn per annum, through an overall combination of &euro;12bn in direct Exchequer funding, &euro;3.5bn in funding through the Land Development Agency and &euro;5bn in funding through the Housing Finance Agency, over a five year period. </p><p>Social housing build and lease targets for the period 2022 - 2026 issued to local authorities in September 2021.  The social housing new build targets for Tipperary are set out in the table below. <table>    <tr>       <th>Target 2022 Build</th>       <th>Target 2023 Build</th>       <th>Target 2024 Build</th>       <th>Target 2025 Build</th>       <th>Target 2026 Build</th>    </tr>    <tr>       <td>230 </td>       <td>155 </td>       <td>158 </td>       <td>170 </td>       <td>174 </td>    </tr> </table> </p><p>Under Housing for All, each local authority, including Tipperary County Council were required to prepare a Housing Delivery Action Plan, setting out details of social and affordable housing delivery in the period 2022-2026. I received a plan from Tipperary County Council in December 2021 and my Department is working with the Housing Delivery Coordination Office to review the plan, having regard to Housing for All targets and policy objectives.  The Housing Delivery Action Plans will be published in Quarter 2. </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.347" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG04500">Rental Sector</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.348.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1577" speakername="Catherine Connolly" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG04600"><p><i>137.</i> To ask the Minister for Housing, Planning, and Local Government the details of any analysis carried out or commissioned by his Department into the impact of the lifting of the Covid-19 moratorium on evictions both nationwide and in Galway city and county; the analysis his Department has carried out or commissioned into the rise in homelessness figures in Galway city and county in 2021; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[11945/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.349.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1561" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG04700"><p>The Emergency Measures in the Public Interest (Covid-19) Act 2020 was enacted on 27 March 2020. Part 2 of the 2020 Act provided for the operation of the Residential Tenancies Act 2004 during the Covid-19 emergency period up to 1 August 2020, to better protect tenants by prohibiting rent increases in all cases, and tenancy terminations in all but limited and exceptional cases having regard to:</p>  <p>- the threat to public health presented by Covid-19,</p>  <p>- the highly contagious nature of that disease, and</p>  <p>- the need to restrict the movement of persons in order to prevent the spread of the disease among the population.</p>  <p>  From 1 August 2020, the blanket ban on rent increases inside or outside of a Rent Pressure Zone (RPZ) was lifted for all, apart from the most vulnerable tenants, with regard to the prevailing threat to public health at that time. The Residential Tenancies Act 2020 was enacted and came into operation on 24 October 2020. This Act provides for a moratorium on evictions taking place in the event of peoples&rsquo; movements being restricted on public health grounds to within 5km of their home under Section 31A Health Regulations made by the Minister for Health. These tenancy protections also apply during the 10 days directly following the period specified by the Minister for Health in the aforementioned Regulations.</p>  <p>  The Residential Tenancies and Valuation Act 2020 (RTVA) and subsequently, the Planning and Development, and Residential Tenancies, Act 2020 (PDRTA) provided that rent increases were not permitted to take effect during, or in respect of any part of, the period from 1 August 2020 until 12 July 2021, for tenants with rent arrears due to Covid-19 and at risk of losing their tenancy who make the necessary declaration. The Residential Tenancies (No. 2) Act 2021, which was signed into law on 9 July 2021, provided for an extension of the enhanced protections under the PDRTA until 12 January 2022.</p>  <p>  During the 18 months from August 2020 to January 2022, 579 tenants out of almost 300,000 tenancies, sent a self-declaration to the RTB indicating they were unable to pay their rent as a result of the impact of Covid-19. </p>  <p>  The RTVA also provides that permanent protections apply, through new procedures requiring landlords to serve both the RTB and the tenant with both the 28-day warning notice seeking payment of rent arrears and also any related notice of termination. Upon receipt of the warning notice, the RTB acknowledges receipt to the landlord and the tenant and provides information to the tenant to enable him or her to get advice from the Money and Budgeting Advice Service (MABS) and offers assistance to the tenant in obtaining this advice. Any notice of termination grounded on rent arrears must be copied to the RTB and will be invalid if it is not so copied. A notice of termination grounded on rent arrears can only be served by a landlord on the condition that a written rent arrears warning was given to both the tenant and the RTB and that the arrears were not paid within 28 days following receipt of the warning by the tenant or by the RTB, whichever occurs later. The aim is to ensure that early action is taken to address rent arrears, to the benefit of both the tenant and the landlord.</p>  <p>  My Department's role in relation to homelessness involves the provision of a national framework of policy, legislation and funding to underpin the role of housing authorities in addressing homelessness at a local level.  Statutory responsibility in relation to the provision of homeless services rests with individual housing authorities.</p>  <p>  While responsibility for the provision of accommodation for homeless persons rests with individual housing authorities, the administration of homeless services is organised on a regional basis, with nine administrative regions in place.  A homelessness consultative forum has been established in each region in accordance with Chapter 6 of the Housing (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act, 2009.  It is a matter for the management group of the consultative forum, in the first instance, to determine the services and the funding required to address homelessness in each region.</p>  <p>  My Department has issued guidance to local authorities on the preparation of Homelessness Action Plans, with particular focus on the incorporation of Housing for All actions into these plans. This guidance advised that the Plans should contain measures to address relevant actions in Housing for All, particularly those that have been identified as to be led by local authorities. Additionally, all measures to be included in these Plans must be accompanied by details on how they will be progressed and monitored.</p></reply>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.351.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1581" speakername="Brendan Griffin" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG04900"><p><i>138.</i> To ask the Minister for Housing, Planning, and Local Government the details of his Department&rsquo;s efforts to regulate short-term rental properties in the context of the shortage of long-term properties for rent; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12093/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.352.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1595" speakername="Peter Burke" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG05000"><p>Legislative reforms to regulate the short-term letting sector through the planning code, in areas designated as &ldquo;rent pressure zones&rdquo; (RPZs), were introduced under the Planning and Development Act 2000 (Exempted Development) (No. 2) Regulations 2019 which came into effect on 1 July 2019.</p>  <p>  Notwithstanding the impact of the Covid-19 pandemic, significant work on the implementation and enforcement of the Regulations has been undertaken by planning authorities since they came into effect.</p>  <p>  The Government's housing plan, Housing for All, contains a specific action (Action 20.4), to &ldquo;develop new regulatory controls requiring short-term and holiday lets to register with F&aacute;ilte Ireland with a view to ensuring that houses are used to best effect in areas of housing need&rdquo;. Minister O&rsquo;Brien has engaged with the Minister for Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sports and Media to progress this action, and a number of meetings have been held between officials of the two Departments and with F&aacute;ilte Ireland, and further engagement is expected to take place in the near future.</p>  <p>  Funding was allocated in Budget 2022 to F&aacute;ilte Ireland which has been tasked with the design and implementation of a new short term lettings registration system. The agency is currently recruiting staff to work on this project. The Department of Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sport and Media is also presently scoping out the legislative provisions that will be required to underpin the new registration system with a view to these provisions being enacted in 2022.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.353" nospeaker="true" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG05100">Housing Schemes</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.354.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1504" speakername="Peadar T&oacute;ib&iacute;n" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG05200"><p><i>139.</i> To ask the Minister for Housing, Planning, and Local Government the vetting procedures in place for approving properties for the purposes of HAP tenancies. <b>[11267/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.355.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1561" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG05300"><p>A key principle of the Housing Assistance Payment (HAP) scheme is that eligible households source their own accommodation in the private rented sector, which best suits their needs, in their area of choice.</p>  <p>  The minimum standards for rental accommodation are prescribed in the Housing (Standards for Rented Houses) Regulations 2019. All landlords have a legal obligation to ensure that their rented properties comply with these Regulations. Responsibility for enforcement of the Regulations rests with the relevant local authority. </p>  <p>  The HAP scheme is underpinned by the Housing (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act 2014. Under section 41 of the 2014 Act, local authorities are required to commence the inspection process within 8 months of HAP support being provided in relation to a particular dwelling, if the dwelling was not already inspected within the previous 12 months. Local authorities carry out HAP inspections as part of their overall private rented inspections programme.</p>  <p>  Given the need for inspectors to enter tenants&rsquo; homes, Covid-19 pandemic restrictions did impact on the inspection of all rented dwellings. The City and County Management Association&rsquo;s (CCMA) Local Authority Services Frameworks for Future Covid-19 Pandemic Response did not permit on-site rental inspections from January 2021 until mid-July 2021. This was in order to protect tenants, landlords and inspectors. A revised Framework which issued on 13 July 2021 permitted the resumption of on-site rental inspections from 14 July 2021.</p>  <p>  It is anticipated that &euro;9 million could be spent on rental inspections in 2022. This compares to just under &euro;2.8 million last year.</p></reply>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.357.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1593" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG05500"><p><i>140.</i> To ask the Minister for Housing, Planning, and Local Government when the outcome of the review on income eligibility for social housing under the Housing for All plan will be announced; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12100/22]</b></p></ques>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.358.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1451" speakername="Matt Carthy" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG05600"><p><i>160.</i> To ask the Minister for Housing, Planning, and Local Government when he intends to publish and act upon the review completed in November 2021 into the current banding model and income limits applicable to local authorities regarding housing supports. <b>[11294/22]</b></p></ques>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.359.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1564" speakername="Duncan Smith" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG05700"><p><i>169.</i> To ask the Minister for Housing, Planning, and Local Government if he will address the urgent need to reassess the income limits for social housing support on the grounds of persons being unable to qualify for the housing assistance payment; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[10095/22]</b></p></ques>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.360.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1575" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG05800"><p><i>170.</i> To ask the Minister for Housing, Planning, and Local Government when a decision will be made to increase the income limits for eligibility for local authority housing; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[11779/22]</b></p></ques>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.361.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1491" speakername="Brian Stanley" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG05900"><p><i>185.</i> To ask the Minister for Housing, Planning, and Local Government when the review into income thresholds for social housing eligibility will be published. <b>[11273/22]</b></p></ques>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.362.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1469" speakername="Mark Ward" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG06000"><p><i>187.</i> To ask the Minister for Housing, Planning, and Local Government his plans for increasing the social housing income eligibility; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[11576/22]</b></p></ques>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.363.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1468" speakername="Eoin &Oacute; Broin" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG06100"><p><i>192.</i> To ask the Minister for Housing, Planning, and Local Government the status of the review of the eligibility thresholds for social housing. <b>[12048/22]</b></p></ques>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.364.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1556" speakername="Brendan Smith" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG06200"><p><i>195.</i> To ask the Minister for Housing, Planning, and Local Government if he will improve without further delay the income eligibility limits for social housing for areas such as counties Cavan and Monaghan; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[12062/22]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2022-03-03a.365.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1561" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2022030300064#WRG06300"><p>I propose to take Questions Nos. 140, 160, 169, 170, 185, 187, 192 and 195 together. </p><p>Applications for social housing support are assessed by the relevant local authority, in accordance with the eligibility and need criteria set down in Section 20 of the Housing (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act 2009 and the associated Social Housing Assessment Regulations 2011 (as amended).</p><p>If a household meets the eligibility and need criteria, it qualifies for the suite of social housing supports, including Housing Assistance Payment (HAP), and is placed on the housing list to be considered for the allocation of suitable tenancies in accordance with the authority&rsquo;s allocation scheme.</p><p>The Regulations prescribe maximum net income limits for each local authority, in different bands according to the area concerned, with income being defined and assessed according to a standard Household Means Policy.</p><p>Housing for All &ndash; A New Housing Plan for Ireland was published in September 2021 and, as part of a broad suite of social housing reforms, committed to reviewing income eligibility for social housing.</p><p>The review, which examined inter alia the efficiency of the current banding model and income limits applicable to local authorities, was completed in Q4 2021. I am currently considering its findings and expect to decide on proposed changes and recommendations shortly.</p><p>I will publish the review thereafter.</p></reply>
</publicwhip>