<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.3" nospeaker="true" ><p>The following are questions tabled by Members for written response and the ministerial replies as received on the day from the Departments [unrevised].</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.4" nospeaker="true" ><p>Questions Nos. 1 to 9, inclusive, answered orally.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.6" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA00400">Department of Finance</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.5" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA00350">Credit Availability</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.6.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1020" speakername="Tommy Broughan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA00400"><p><i>10.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance further to Parliamentary Question Nos. 147 and 171 of 26 November 2013, if he will provide an up-to-date report on the work of officials in his Department and their counterparts in Germany to progress the establishment of a mechanism so that the German development bank, KfW, can begin lending to businesses here; if a potential value on the level of assistance to be provided to Irish businesses by KfW has been agreed upon.  <b>[1510/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.7.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA00500"><p>As the Deputy will be aware, the Taoiseach mentioned in this House shortly before the recess that he had held discussions with Chancellor Merkel on finding ways to reinforce Ireland&rsquo;s economic recovery by improving funding mechanisms for the real economy, including access to finance for Irish SMEs. The German Government has asked KfW, the German development bank, to work with the German and Irish authorities swiftly, in order to deliver on this initiative at the earliest possible date. </p><p>  Officials at my Department with assistance from staff of the NPRF have worked quickly to investigate ways to ensure that the benefit of this cooperation to Irish SMEs can be maximised.</p><p>  A small party of my officials travelled to a meeting with their counterparts in Berlin in early December and a week later a similar meeting was held at KfW&rsquo;s headquarters in Frankfurt. Officials from KfW and the German Ministry have also met with the project team from Ireland in Dublin for a further exchange shortly before Christmas. Both sides have been represented at senior management level for each engagement.  In addition, there have been regular conference calls between the parties. </p><p>  As the Deputy may be aware, KfW channel their funding for SMEs in Germany through a system of on-lending using commercial banks in Germany as the distribution mechanism. Typically the SMEs can avail of KfW funding at different terms and conditions applicable to that offered directly by the financial institutions. This model is similar to the on lending arrangements available to Irish domestic institutions using funds from the European Investment Bank. </p><p>  The precise arrangements for the structure, level of funding and distribution options are the subject of the discussions between the relevant officials at present and will have to adhere to EU State Aid considerations.  Experience in other countries suggests that any lending facilitated by a state sponsored investment institution like KfW is generally complementary to SME lending already taking place in an economy and can in fact assist in improving both the supply and demand for finance. </p><p>  The Government recognises that SMEs are the lifeblood of the Irish economy and play a crucial role in employment growth in our country.  Since March 2011 Government policy has concentrated on ensuring that viable micro, small and medium sized enterprises have access to capital, equity and debt funding from a more diverse range of sources. The potential new arrangement with KfW, which my officials are currently exploring, represents a continuation of this Government&rsquo;s concerted focus on ensuring that viable SMEs have access to finance in a manner that supports economic recovery and employment growth. </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.8" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA00550">NAMA Operations</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.9.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1100" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA00600"><p><i>11.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance his views on the impact of recent allegations regarding the alleged leaking of confidential information from the National Asset Management Agency on the organisations ability to fulfil its mandate; the way security of information can be guaranteed within NAMA; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[1633/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.10.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA00700"><p>The Deputy, as a member of the D&aacute;il Committee of Public Accounts (PAC), will be aware that the Chairman and Chief Executive of NAMA appeared before that Committee on 20th December 2013 and robustly defended the Agency against allegations that had been circulated to certain outlets in the media and to certain members of the Oireachtas during the preceding week.   </p><p>  The NAMA Chief Executive stated clearly that the allegations, in so far as NAMA had knowledge of them, were unsubstantiated. The NAMA Chairman stated clearly that NAMA has no tolerance for misdemeanour or any wrongdoing and that where it is made aware of any complaint, it fully investigates it and, if appropriate, refers the matter to the Garda&iacute;.  </p><p>  I am advised by NAMA that it will fully and robustly continue to defend its position in relation to any allegations made against it in such proceedings, and I am further informed that NAMA has a 100% track record in defending any such cases.</p><p>  Members of this House will be aware that s.19 of Criminal Justice Act obliges anybody with information which might be relevant in the context of the potential commission of an offence by any person, to disclose that information to a member of An Garda Siochana, and this section makes it an offence not only to fail to disclose that information, but to fail to disclose it as soon as it is practicable to do so.</p><p><b>Valuations</b></p><p>  Amongst the allegations was a claim that NAMA engaged in a deliberate process of manipulating the valuation of property which was collateral for its acquired loans.  NAMA refuted this allegation and set out their position during the PAC proceedings in December. The NAMA Chief Executive indicated that NAMA did not in fact set the property valuations and that the entire valuations process was subject to extensive independent auditing, including on behalf of the European Commission and by the Comptroller and Auditor General. I note that the Comptroller and Auditor General, Mr McCarthy, also advised the PAC that he could not see on a broad scale how there could have been any undervaluation of loans acquired by NAMA given the Agency&rsquo;s approach to securing independent valuations.</p><p><b>Safeguards to protect the confidentiality of information</b></p><p>  There are extensive safeguards in place to protect the confidentiality of information held by NTMA employees, including those assigned to NAMA. Employees assigned to NAMA by the NTMA, as is the case with all NTMA staff, are subject to Section 14 of the National Treasury Management Agency Act, 1990 which prohibits an employee from disclosing any information obtained while carrying out their duties as employees of the NTMA. Employees assigned to NAMA are also subject to a prohibition on release of confidential data under Sections 99 and 202 of the NAMA Act 2009. All NTMA employees, including those assigned to NAMA, are subject to the Official Secrets Act.  Contravention of these prohibitions is a criminal offence.  On conviction there is a fine not exceeding &euro;5m and/or imprisonment for a term not exceeding five years. These protections do not cease at the point of resignation but rather apply indefinitely and extend to former employees.  </p><p>  The NAMA Chairman outlined to the PAC in December that NAMA has enhanced IT arrangements in place that limit access to information: access for staff is now confined and limited only to the information that the individual needs to do his or her work on a day-to-day basis.  The NAMA Chairman also pointed out that there is an extensive audit trail right across NAMA IT systems in respect of e-mails and documentation making it possible for NAMA to track access and printing of documents. The NAMA Chairman added that while the NAMA systems are now well advanced, the Board remains focused on continual improvement.</p><p><b>Progress</b></p><p>  I would like to draw the Deputy&rsquo;s attention to the NAMA&rsquo;s 2013 End-of-year Review, which was published on the 3rd of January and which details the continued significant progress that the Agency is making by reference to the objectives set for it by the Oireachtas; it is also available on NAMA&rsquo;s website www.nama.ie.  This includes the generation of &euro;16.5bn in cash inflows from inception to end-December 2013, some &euro;5.8bn of which was generated in 2013, and the repayment of &euro;7.5bn or one quarter of its senior debt by end-2013. The achievement of its first major debt repayment milestone is very significant, not only for NAMA in terms of its own progress, but also because it was a key Troika target and it reinforces, at a critical time in our recovery, the very positive international perception that Ireland as a country is resolute in addressing its difficulties and meeting its targets. I also point out that NAMA has generated sufficient cash reserves to cover its costs, including debt interest and loan servicing fees.  It is important to note that NAMA is self-funding and does not draw on the Exchequer and therefore is not a burden for the Government in the context of its annual budgetary arithmetic. NAMA is also in a position, as a result of its strong performance, to invest in various commercial and residential projects which, when completed, are expected to yield returns to assist the economy.</p><p><b>Conclusion</b></p><p>  When addressing the PAC, the NAMA Chairman made clear the NAMA Board&rsquo;s determination that the Agency will not be deflected from achieving its objectives by the circulation of allegations designed to serve not the interest of Irish taxpayers but rather the narrow interests of individuals who are in dispute with the Agency.  Members of the House should, I believe, consider carefully what both the NAMA Chairman and Chief Executive have had to say on this matter.  NAMA has been the subject of efforts to spread damaging and unfounded stories about it in the past.  At no stage since its inception has NAMA been deflected by these efforts from doing its work on behalf of Irish taxpayers and I fully accept the NAMA Board&rsquo;s commitment that it will not allow itself to be so deflected now or at any time in the future.  I would regard it as a more serious matter if NAMA was not being criticised but rather was being universally praised by debtors and others as this would tell an altogether different story of how NAMA is working to recover monies for the State.  By necessity NAMA has to have a hard edge in the work it does.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.11" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA00750">Mortgage Resolution Processes</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.12.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1100" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA00800"><p><i>12.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance if he is still pursuing an arrangement to deal with loss making tracker mortgages in Irish banks; when he expects progress to be make in this regard; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[1634/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.13.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA00900"><p>As the deputy will be aware Tracker mortgages were a particular feature of the Irish mortgage market in the recent past with many tracker mortgages originated during the property market boom in 2004 to 2008.   Tracker mortgages were lent for both primary dwellings and buy-to-let investments and represent 60 per cent of the aggregate mortgage lending of AIB, BoI, and PTSB. These are low interest earning assets with a variable rate set at a fixed margin above the ECB policy rate &ndash;the majority of which result in a negative carry for the originating banks, that is, the rate that tracker mortgage borrowers pay on their mortgage is lower than the rate the banks fund themselves.</p><p>  Although, these assets continue to be loss-making and represent a drag on the Banks profitability the situation is improving and is not preventing the banks returning to viability.</p><p><b><i>Improvements in Bank funding</i></b></p><p>  In the past year improved confidence in the Irish Sovereign and its Banks together with the normalisation of money market interest rates in the Euro area has helped to further stabilise the domestic banking sector. This has allowed the profile of Bank funding to revert to a more normal sustainable mix. Funding rates in the wholesale markets are also starting to converge towards the banks more higher- rated European peers.</p><p>As recent capital market transactions have demonstrated the Irish banks have been able to access both secured and unsecured funding at competitive rates in a range of maturities across the curve. In addition, the deposit base has stabilised resulting in reduced reliance on central bank funding. Taken together this has helped to reduce the impact of the negative carry associated with tracker mortgages  .</p><p>  Furthermore, over the medium to long term an eventual increase in ECB policy rates will further reduce this negative carry, insofar as the differential between the rate that the banks fund themselves on the markets and the rate that tracker mortgage borrowers pay on their mortgage will narrow or ultimately yield a positive margin.  </p><p><b><i>Banks becoming profitable again</i></b></p><p>  Recent  interim results and disclosures by the Banks indicate that the banks have made a lot of progress on re-pricing deposits and certain loan portfolios. In addition, operating costs and government guarantee fees are falling, boosting pre-provision profits. Both AIB and BOI have signalled a return to profitability in 2014 and over time it is expected that both banks will trade their way into sustainable profitability. This will place them in a better position to absorb the impact of the Trackers mortgages.</p><p><b><i>Self help measures</i></b></p><p>  In recent times the Banks have pursued self-help measures to address this issue by introducing innovative solutions such as offering negative equity type mortgages and allowing borrowers to retain tracker facilities when moving house for a fixed period. These initiatives together with the recovery in the property market and an associated rise in housing transactions will also help to alleviate the issue. </p><p><b><i>Conclusion</i></b></p><p>In conclusion as I have previously advised the house, during recent Review Missions of the Troika the Irish authorities discussed the issues associated with tracker mortgages though these interactions did not yield any viable solution to the problem .While the trackers are less of a concern for the banks than in the recent past,   we naturally remain interested in examining any sensible ideas that could help lower the funding cost associated with these assets.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.14" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA00950">Tax Reliefs Application</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.15.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1110" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA01000"><p><i>13.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance if he will confirm regarding the rent a room tax relief scheme if the income up to &euro;10,000 threshold per annum is exempt from PRSI in addition to the exemption from standard income tax; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[1553/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.16.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA01100"><p>Section 216A of the Taxes Consolidation Act 1997 provides for the rent-a-room scheme. This scheme was introduced in Finance Act 2001 as an incentive to encourage individuals to let rooms in their principal private residence in order to bring about an increase in the availability of rental accommodation, particularly for the student sector.</p><p>  The scheme provides an exemption from Income Tax, PRSI and USC on rent received where a person rents out a room or rooms in his or her principal private residence and the rent received does not exceed &euro;10,000 per year. This was increased from &euro;7,620 in Budget 2008.  </p><p>  In order to qualify for the exemption, it is necessary for the residential premises to be situated in the State and occupied by the individual as his or her sole or main residence during the tax year.</p><p>  The relief only applies to individuals. It does not apply to companies or partnerships. In addition, an individual cannot avail of the relief in respect of payments for accommodation in the family home by a child of the individual. There is no restriction where rent is paid by other family members, for example, nieces or nephews.</p><p>  The latest figures available relate to the tax year 2011 when the cost of the relief was estimated at &euro;5.6 million and was availed of by 3,920 claimants. This equates to rental income of &euro;21.7 million. The corresponding 2010 cost was &euro;5.3m and was availed of by 3,770 claimants. </p><p>  Figures relating to PRSI foregone are not captured by the Revenue Commissioners. Any queries in relation to PRSI should be directed to the Minister for Social Protection.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.17" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA01150">Proposed Legislation</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.18.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1090" speakername="Mattie McGrath" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA01200"><p><i>14.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance the reasons for his opposition to the introduction of a mandatory invoicing system for all work carried out by farm contractors; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[1555/14]</b></p></ques>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.19.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1090" speakername="Mattie McGrath" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA01300"><p><i>16.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance if he will introduce an amendment to the Finance Act to mandate for the requirement of all farm contractors to produce a receipt to match payment made by cheque or other monetary means and so eliminate the ongoing threat to registered farm contractors posed by unregistered operators in the so called black economy; and if he will make a statement on the matter.  <b>[1554/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.20.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA01400"><p>I propose to take Questions Nos. 14 and 16 together. </p><p>  I am informed by the Revenue Commissioners that farmers and agricultural contractors are subject to the same requirements in relation to record keeping as other businesses. All businesses are required to keep proper books and records and to retain such books and records for a period of six years.  In particular, any farming or other business that claims a tax deductible expense for any expenditure must have a satisfactory record of that expenditure.  </p><p>  I am also informed by the Revenue Commissioners that they tackle the problem of the shadow economy through a range of compliance and audit interventions including through targeted special projects.  In addition, they deploy a range of compliance activities such as risk analysis, covert surveillance, intelligence gathering, information exchange with other State Agencies, working with Government agencies and working with business representative bodies.</p><p>  The Revenue Commissioners keep their tax compliance programmes under constant review to ensure that they are focussed on the areas of greatest risk, including risks from the shadow economy.   I am conscious that the need to tackle the shadow economy must be balanced against imposing additional administrative burdens and cost on business, but I will respond positively where Revenue makes a persuasive case for further powers or new obligations on business to strengthen their hand in dealing with shadow economy activity. In this regard I am aware that representative bodies representing agricultural contractors have raised concerns about tax evasion and unfair competition in the agricultural services sector and I would encourage them to provide whatever information they have to the Revenue Commissioners. I understand that the Commissioners would be very happy to meet the representative bodies to discuss their concerns and to receive any information they have about specific instances of fraud.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.21" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA01450">Consumer Protection</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.22.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/959" speakername="Pearse Doherty" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA01500"><p><i>15.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance the legal protections provided for under the Consumer Credit Act for mortgage holders whose distressed mortgages have been sold by their original lender to a debt factoring company or other financial service provider; and if the holders of these mortgages continue to have recourse to the mortgage arrears resolution process and Code of Conduct on Mortgage Arrears.  <b>[1648/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.23.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA01600"><p>I have no statutory role in the sale of loan books which is a commercial matter for the financial institutions concerned. </p><p>  The Code of Conduct on Mortgage Arrears and the Consumer Protection Code apply to services providers regulated by the Central Bank. The Consumer Protection Code obliges the regulated entities to ensure that their own activities and any outsourced activity, such as debt collection, complies with the requirements of the Code. This means that activity should uphold principles in the Code such as the requirement for institutions:</p><p>  -  not to exert undue pressure or undue influence on a customer;</p><p>  -  to act honestly, fairly and professionally in the best interests of customers and to act with due skill, care and diligence in the best interest of its customers; and</p><p>  -  to prohibit personal visits or oral communications except in specified circumstances.   </p><p>  The Code of Conduct on Mortgage Arrears sets out requirements for mortgage lenders dealing with borrowers facing or in mortgage arrears.  The CCMA provides a strong consumer protection framework to ensure that borrowers struggling to keep up mortgage repayments are treated in a fair and transparent manner by their lender, and that long term resolution is sought by lenders with each of their borrowers. </p><p>  The matter of sales of loans or transfers of loans is a very complex legal area, particular to the terms and conditions of individual consumer agreements and the specific &lsquo;transfer&rsquo; involved.  For example, some transfer documentation includes a clause which stipulates that the lender (not the transferee) remains responsible for administration including setting interest rates and arrears handling.</p><p>  The position may be further complicated where the transferee (the new holder of the loan book) engages in a restructuring which changes the terms of the credit to the consumer. </p><p>  Where Central Bank regulated financial institutions sell part, or all, of their mortgage loan book to another regulated financial institution, the same protections apply to borrowers, including the Code of Conduct on Mortgage Arrears and the Consumer Protection Code. Any agent acting on behalf of a regulated lender must comply with the requirements of Irish financial services law. Failure to do so may result in the Central Bank imposing penalties on the regulated lender concerned.   </p><p>  By virtue of an exemption in Part V of the Central Bank Act 1997(as amended), an unregulated entity to which a cash loan is transferred by a regulated entity is not subject to Central Bank supervision under the Consumer Protection Code and CCMA.</p><p>  However, statute law provides for certain protections where the property is a principal private residence.  For example, the Land and Conveyancing Law Reform Act 2013 provides the power to a Court to adjourn repossession proceedings in respect of a principal private residence for a period to see if a Personal Insolvency Arrangement could be agreed as an alternative resolution of the matter.   This statutory provision will be applicable in all repossession cases that involve a principal private residence, irrespective of the particular categorisation/status of the mortgagor.</p><p>  I should also point out that to all debt collectors that operate across any or all sectors of the economy, including private individuals and debt collecting firms are subject to the provisions of the Non-Fatal Offences against the Person Act 1997 .  Under section 11 of this Act, it is an offence to demand payment of a debt in a way that is designed to cause alarm, distress or humiliation. A person found guilty of offences under this Act is subject to large fines and up to 14 years imprisonment.</p></reply>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.24" nospeaker="true" ><p>Question No. 16 answered with Question No. 14.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.25" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA01750">Economic Policy</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.26.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/959" speakername="Pearse Doherty" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA01800"><p><i>17.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance the reason the medium-term economic strategy contained only forecasts based on a baseline macroeconomic economic assumption and a high growth macroeconomic assumption; if other forecasts were made based on other assumptions such as lower growth; if he will publish these forecasts; and if he will make a statement on the matter.  <b>[1652/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.27.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA01900"><p>The baseline scenario set out in the Medium-Term Economic Strategy (MTES) is based on the Budget 2014 projections out to 2016. Projections thereafter are based on an estimate of Ireland&rsquo;s potential output, factoring in assumptions regarding population growth, participation rates and labour productivity growth. Projections over 2017 to 2020 benefitted from input from PMCA consultants and constitute a reasonable trajectory for real growth, labour productivity and employment. The baseline scenario represents my Department&rsquo;s current best estimate of the future path of the macroeconomic variables set out in the MTES. GDP growth over 2013 to 2020 is projected to average 2.6 per cent per annum, compared with an equivalent figure of 3.6 per cent in ESRI&rsquo;s July 2013 <i>Medium Term Review</i>  .</p><p>  It is important to emphasise that the high-growth scenario which the Deputy refers to is not a forecast for the economy. Rather, my Department, working with the ESRI&rsquo;s HERMES model, sought to quantify the economic impact of a suite of potential policy measures. The range of conditions modelled included greater dividend from existing labour market activation policies, re-orienting the tax system away from labour-related taxes, a lower cost of credit, and improvements in the stock of human capital. In broad terms, the aggregated effect of these was added to my Department&rsquo;s baseline projections to show what the impact of implementing policies to support such conditions would be on the economy. Their combined impact on output, employment and the public finances constitutes the &lsquo;high-growth scenario&rsquo;. Again, I stress that it does not represent a forecast for what will happen to the economy; rather the objective was to demonstrate the impact which reforms would have on the economy.</p><p>  As part of its enhanced risk function, my Department constantly evaluates emerging economic risks, both positive and negative, and assesses their potential impact upon the economy. In undertaking this modelling exercise, a number of different potential policy measures were considered. Not all of these measures were modelled and not all of the measures that were modelled were included in the final suite of policy measures included in the MTES high-growth scenario. As the HERMES model results are broadly symmetric, the results of a number of the policy measures modelled can be considered as having either a positive or negative impact upon output. For instance, the results of an improvement in competition policy which lowers inflation and boosts growth can also be interpreted negatively as the results of a deterioration in competition which raises inflation and lowers growth.</p><p>  Packages of policy measures which negatively impact upon the economy were also considered. The purpose of modelling these policies was to quantify downside risk and estimate the potential cost of policy errors. However, as the Government does not intend to knowingly undertake erroneous policy choices, the results of these scenarios were not included in the MTES.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.28" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA01950">Ministerial Correspondence</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.29.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/959" speakername="Pearse Doherty" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA02000"><p><i>18.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance if he will release the letter of 19 November 2010 from Jean-Claude Trichet in view of the investigation by the EU Parliament into the role of the troika in Ireland and other countries.  <b>[1649/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.30.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA02100"><p>The European Parliament has decided to draft an own initiative report evaluating the structure, role and operation of the Troika&rsquo;s actions in euro area programme countries, including Ireland.</p><p>  The EU Parliament&rsquo;s review of the role and operations of the Troika is ongoing, indeed a delegation from the Parliament&rsquo;s Economic and Monetary Affairs Committee is in Ireland today and tomorrow for meetings as part of the review. </p><p>  However, the Parliament&rsquo;s review has no connection with the core issue of your question on which the position remains as I outlined in my replies to Parliamentary Questions 155 of 28th June 2011, 125 of 18th July 2013 and 37 of 3rd October 2013.</p><p>  While the immediate crisis that this Government inherited when it took office has been averted, it remains important for relationships between institutions to be developed and sustained, in order to allow for confidential negotiations to take place, especially on particularly sensitive issues. This is particularly the case in relation to the Irish authorities dealing with the ECB. It is normal practice for states to protect the confidentiality of these discussions, and in fact is usually enshrined in the rules of association of institutions.</p><p>  Requests to release the letter have been considered a number of times under the Freedom of Information Acts. The decision has been made to refuse these requests in line with the relevant sections of the Act. This provides for exemptions for records relating to, for example, information received in confidence, commercially sensitive information and the financial and economic interests of the state in sections 26 and 31 and particularly 24.2. These factors counterbalance the public interest, protecting the ability of the Government when negotiating or deliberating on matters of national importance. The refusal to release the letter has been upheld on one occasion by the Office of the Information Commissioner. </p><p>  I do however understand that, on foot of a special request from the European Ombudsman, the ECB is to consider the release of the letter, and should they decide to do so, the need to respect the confidentiality of the letter will no longer apply. </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.31" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA02150">Budget 2014</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.32.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1003" speakername="Richard Boyd Barrett" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA02200"><p><i>19.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance in view of recent ESRI analysis of budget 2014, which stated that the budget hit the lowest income bracket hardest, if he intends remedial measures or adjustments to the budget to address this issue; and if he will make a statement on the matter.  <b>[1656/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.33.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA02300"><p>I would firstly point out that the ESRI analysis showed that the highest income decile was the hardest hit in Budget 2014 not the lowest income decile. Furthermore, notwithstanding the fact that the lowest income bracket was impacted significantly, I note that the ESRI&rsquo;s research continues to show that the highest losses have been borne by those in the highest 10 per cent of the income distribution. </p><p>  While the ESRI&rsquo;s assessment does suggest that significant losses have occurred in the lowest decile, the estimate of the effect on the lowest decile is strongly influenced by the changes to indirect taxes. As the best way to tackle poverty and inequality is to create jobs and reduce unemployment through economic growth, and evidence from the OECD shows that indirect taxes are less harmful than income taxes. Indeed, implementing this policy is bearing fruit with employment increasing by some 60,000 in the first three quarters of 2013 and unemployment decreasing to 12.4% from a peak of 15.1%.</p><p>  The ESRI also acknowledge some difficulties in their paper with capturing the effects of some of the budgetary measures likely to impact upon higher earners, particularly in relation to increases in DIRT and Capital Gains Tax. For this reason, we have to treat the results with a degree of caution.  </p><p>  The ERSI assessment indicates that the overall consolidation process from 2009 to 2014 has not been regressive and it is worth re-iterating that the OECD and the European Commission have shown that Ireland still retains one of the most progressive income tax systems in the developed world.</p><p>  Looking to the future, the research of the ESRI will inform deliberations in advance of Budget 2015.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.34" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA02350">Stock Markets Regulation</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.35.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1177" speakername="Denis Naughten" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA02400"><p><i>20.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance the steps being taken to regulate food securities trading on the stock market; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[1607/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.36.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA02500"><p>Proposals to regulate food securities at an EU level form part of the current MiFID II and MiFIR proposals which aim to make financial markets more efficient, resilient and transparent, and to strengthen the protection of investors.</p><p>  The Irish Presidency achieved a Council General Approach on this file which has enabled negotiations, via Trilogues, with the European Parliament and the European Commission.  </p><p>  Under the current MiFID II proposals, the level of exemptions available has been reduced and more products will be defined as derivative financial instruments when compared with MiFID I, and will therefore fall within the scope of MiFID II and other financial legislation such as Market Abuse. MiFID II also contains important provisions relating to position management, position limits and product intervention. These provisions are in respect of all financial instruments, including commodity derivatives, and have the purpose of providing regulators with tools to avoid excessive speculation in financial instruments, including commodity derivatives. The Council is proposing that competent authorities, with the guiding hand of ESMA, will be obligated to establish and apply position limits on the size of a position in a commodity derivative which a person can have over a specified period of time. </p><p>  Furthermore, subject to the final agreement between the co-legislators, competent authorities will have product intervention powers whereby they may prohibit or restrict trading of financial instruments or prohibit or restrict investment activities when there is a threat to the orderly functioning and integrity of financial markets or commodity markets. The European Securities and Markets Authority (ESMA) will have contingency and coordination powers in position management and product intervention to ensure consistent application across all Member States. In the exercise of its powers, ESMA will also have to consult public bodies competent for the oversight, administration and regulation of physical agricultural markets. </p><p>  MiFID II contains important provisions which set out new rules for commodity derivative markets.   However, the regulation of commodity derivative markets, including where they take place Over the Counter (OTC) and as they are related to the physical commodity markets, must be assessed based on how they are dealt with across the totality of financial services files.    </p><p>  The MiFID II proposals complement the European Market Infrastructure Regulation (EMIR), which seeks to make the derivative markets, including commodity derivative markets, safer and more transparent. This is achieved by obligating entities to report all derivative transactions, to put in place risk mitigation techniques and to centrally clear contracts with counterparties, where the entity holds a large position. In addition, regulators will now have full information on this market which has not previously been available. The provisions contained in the European Market Infrastructure Regulation (EMIR) will be activated upon the entry into force of the relevant technical standards</p><p>  The Market Abuse Regulation, agreed under the Irish Presidency, also extends its scope within commodity derivative markets and to spot commodity markets. It clarifies that the manipulation of benchmarks, including commodity derivative benchmarks, will be an offence.</p><p>  This will be complemented by two other EU legislative instruments, a criminal sanctions Directive on Market Abuse and a Regulation on Benchmarks. The Regulation on Benchmarks is set to be particularly prescriptive towards commodity benchmarks.</p><p>  All of these EU financial services files combined are expected to result in a tighter regime for all commodity derivative markets, including food securities, whether traded OTC or through exchanges. This new legislative environment will be much more prescriptive than the current situation and will serve to prevent market abuse and to support orderly pricing in commodity derivatives and related commodity markets.</p><p>  We support the stronger rules as applied to commodity derivative markets to guard against market abuse and support price stability. This will curb excessive speculation and serve to reduce price volatility in the underlying commodity markets. Negotiations continue under the Greek Presidency and we will continue to monitor developments on the MiFID II file throughout the legislative process.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.37" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA02550">Economic Policy</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.38.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/957" speakername="Bernard Durkan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA02600"><p><i>21.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance the extent to which he continues to remain satisfied in the matter of this country&rsquo;s economic performance in the wake of the exit from the bailout and with particular reference to the need to remain competitive in the context of all other European countries inside and outside the eurozone and the wider global community with whom this country trades; if he can foresee greater opportunities for economic recovery in the emerging climate; and if he will make a statement on the matter.  <b>[1587/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.39.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA02700"><p>Recent Quarterly National Accounts data show that the Irish economy recorded a second successive quarter of growth in the third quarter of 2013, with real GDP increasing by 1.5 per cent when compared with the second quarter. Particularly encouraging have been the recent tentative signs of recovery in domestic activity, with total domestic demand increasing by 2.4 per cent over the quarter to Q3 &ndash; the strongest such growth in over three years. This was driven by double digit investment growth in the quarter &ndash; a clear sign that confidence is returning to businesses domestically. Indeed core investment (excluding the volatile aircraft component) has now increased robustly in each of the last three quarters.</p><p>  Further improvements in confidence are important to support a continued recovery in domestic demand. In this context, the ending of the programme of external financial assistance will help to further enhance confidence as it clearly demonstrates that we have moved to the next stage of our recovery.</p><p>  On the external side, although goods exports continue to be impacted by sector specific issues related to the pharma-chem sector, services exports were up by 3.3 per cent in year-on-year terms in the third quarter. The strong performance of services exports has been supported by the significant competitiveness gains achieved in Ireland over the last number of years. Irish unit labour costs are forecast to improve by 23 per cent relative to the euro area average between 2008 and 2015 according to the latest Commission forecasts. Price levels have also corrected considerably in Ireland in recent years, with annual inflation rates in Ireland below the euro area average for every year since 2009.</p><p>  Encouragingly, the positive output trends are having a favourable impact on the labour market, with year-on-year employment growth of 3.2 per cent &ndash; the highest rate in the entire EU in the quarter &ndash; recorded in the third quarter, representing an additional 58,000 jobs over the year. In line with these developments we&rsquo;ve seen the unemployment rate fall nearly 3 percentage points in less than two years, down to 12.4 per cent in December.</p><p>  Looking towards the future, my Department is forecasting growth of 2.0 per cent for this year &ndash; a figure endorsed by the Irish Fiscal Advisory Council &ndash; and for growth to average around 3.0 per cent over the medium-term. Central to these projections is the assumption of a sustained recovery in our key trading partners. In this regard I am encouraged by developments in key trading partners of late.	</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.40" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA02750">Better Energy Homes Scheme Administration</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.41.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/999" speakername="Charlie McConalogue" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA02800"><p><i>22.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance his plans for the better energy home scheme and the reason his Department is penalising this sector under the new home renovation incentive scheme by introducing the rule that qualifying expenditure over &euro;4,405 plus VAT under this scheme will be reduced by three times the amount of any grant for the works as opposed to being reduced by the total amount of the grant; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[1635/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.42.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA02900"><p>As the Deputy is aware, I announced the Home Renovation Incentive in the recent Budget. This scheme came into operation on 25 October 2013 and will run until 31 December 2015. The incentive provides tax relief for homeowners by way of a tax credit at 13.5% of qualifying expenditure incurred on repair, renovation or improvement work carried out on a principal private residence. Qualifying expenditure is expenditure subject to the 13.5% VAT rate.  The work must cost a minimum of &euro;5,000 (inclusive of VAT) which would attract a credit of &euro;595.  Where the cost of the work exceeds &euro;30,000 (exclusive of VAT) a maximum credit of &euro;4,050 will apply. The credit is payable over the two years following the year in which the work is carried out.  Works carried out between 25 October 2013 and 31 December 2013 will be considered to have taken place in 2014 for the purposes of awarding the tax credit.</p><p>  I do not accept that I am penalising the energy efficiency retrofit sector, as works which are grant-aided by the SEAI under the Better Energy Homes Scheme will also qualify for the incentive. Three times the amount of the grant will be deducted and any additional expenditure will attract the tax credit of 13.5%. This is to align with best fiscal practice in that relief is not provided twice for the same expenditure. The reason that the qualifying expenditure is reduced by three times the grant amount is because the SEAI state that the cash grants under the Better Energy Homes scheme are set values based on 30% of the average cost of energy efficiency works.</p><p>  It is worth noting that the deduction in respect of grant-aided work is not taken into consideration for the purposes of reaching the minimum spend threshold of &euro;5,000 (including VAT).</p><p>  The Better Energy Homes scheme is administered by the SEAI and, as such, any queries about the future of the scheme should be directed to the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.43" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA02950">Equality Proofing of Budgets</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.44.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/998" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA03000"><p><i>23.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance if following the the recent analysis by Social Justice Ireland which stated that Ireland&rsquo;s poorest 10% lost 18.4% of their disposable income since the start of the crash in 2008, by contrast the richest 10% lost 11.4%, if he will support the introduction of equality budgeting or the equality impact assessment of all future budgets.  <b>[52791/13]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.45.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA03100"><p>The Social Justice Ireland (SJI) report to which the Deputy refers, makes reference to the percentage change in average real incomes by decile of disposable income per adult equivalent between 2008-2011. These figures capture wider effects on incomes over the period which are not as a direct result of budgetary measures taken during the period. A more recent analysis by the ESRI focuses on the impact of budgetary measures and shows that the largest reduction in income on this basis over the period was experienced by those in the top decile. The lowest reduction in income was experienced in the third decile from the bottom.  This is consistent with previous analysis by the ESRI, the European Commission and the IMF which showed that the richest bore the highest burden. Whilst it is regrettable that the first decile may have experienced losses of close to 12%, this is far below the SJI estimate of 18.4% and also below the ESRI estimate of the losses experienced by the highest decile of close to 16%. I also note that the ESRI estimate of losses for the top decile is higher than the SJI estimate for that decile. </p><p>  Maintaining fairness in the budgets while ensuring the public finances return to a sustainable level is of upmost importance and my department has a number of procedures in place to assess the distributional impact of budgets. These procedures include a distributional analysis of taxation measures, published in the budget book and performed on various income levels for the different categories of income earners. These categories include single individuals, married one-earner couples with no children and married one-earner couples with children. Where possible a separate distributional analysis estimating the impacts on disposable income by income decile using SWITCH, the ESRI Tax-Benefit model, is also undertaken in evaluating various taxation options. Illustrative examples are included in the budgetary documentation.</p><p>  In addition to these measures I would advise the Deputy that my Department received over 700 pre-budget submissions this year from a variety of sources, both from individuals and organisations. It is a standard part of the budgetary process that each submission is examined and taken into account during the formulation of budget measures. This allows for the opinions of a cross section of society to be considered in the preparation of the overall budgetary package. </p><p>  While achieving a fair and balanced budget is an important guiding principle in preparing budgetary options, the surest way of making a positive impact on disadvantaged people is through jobs and growth. The budgetary measures over the period concerned have been formulated with a view to promoting economic growth and this is reflected in the most recent employment data showing strong jobs growth in the economy and reductions in unemployment.</p><p>  In addition, beyond the evaluation of budgetary measures; the Cabinet handbook requires a statement on the likely effects of the decision sought on gender equality, persons experiencing or at risk of poverty or social exclusion and persons with disabilities to be included in Memoranda to Government. Furthermore, I would like to reiterate that the State and its bodies take the provisions of equality legislation into account in the development and delivery of policies and services. These procedures ensure fairness and balance in Government decision-making beyond the budgetary process.</p></reply>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.46.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA03200"><p><i>24.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance the steps being taken by the regulatory authorities to ensure the health of the credit union sector and that any weak credit unions are supported; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[1630/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.47.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA03300"><p>Under section 84 of the Credit Union Act 1997, the functions of the Registrar of Credit Unions at the Central Bank are to regulate credit unions with a view to the protection by each credit union of the funds of its members and the maintenance of the financial stability and wellbeing of credit unions generally. </p><p>  The Registry of Credit Union applies a risk based approach to the supervision of credit unions which supports early identification of problems and mitigation by credit unions of risks identified. The Probability Risk and Impact System - PRISM, is the Central Bank&rsquo;s risk-based framework which allows for the identification of risks by their impact on financial stability and the consumer and by the probability of the risk occurring. </p><p>  The Government established the Commission on Credit Unions in May 2011 to make recommendations in relation to the most effective regulatory structure for credit unions, taking into account their not-for-profit mandate, their volunteer ethos and community focus, while paying due regard to the need to fully protect members&rsquo; savings and financial stability. The Commission published its final Report in March 2012 and over sixty of its recommendations have been implemented in the Credit Union and Co-operation with Overseas Regulators Act 2012. The Government has accepted fully the Commission on Credit Union&rsquo;s Report and the recommendations are currently being rolled-out under the Credit Union and Co-operation with Overseas Regulators Act 2012.</p><p>  The Credit Union and Co-operation with Overseas Regulators Act 2012 helps underpin the stability of credit unions. The Act contains measures to reform and strengthen credit unions and deals with four broad areas namely: </p><p>- Prudential regulation: including reserves, liquidity, lending and risk management </p><p>- Governance: dealing with the roles and responsibilities of the Chair, Board, Manager and Board Oversight Committee   </p><p>- Restructuring, including the establishment of the Credit Union Restructuring Board &ndash; ReBo:  restructuring via transfers, mergers and amalgamations on a 		voluntary, incentivised and time-bound basis</p><p>- Stabilisation: provision of support to credit unions that are viable but undercapitalised </p><p>  The Act is being commenced in accordance with the published Implementation Plan, which will allow credit unions sufficient time to prepare for these changes.</p><p>  The Government has made available &euro;500 million to support the stability of the credit union sector.  This amount is divided between two funds with &euro;250 million in each. The Resolution Fund which provides funding for credit unions requiring resolution and the Credit Union Fund which provides funding for voluntary restructuring under ReBo.  A stabilisation levy will be introduced in 2014 to support credit unions that are under capitalised but are otherwise viable.</p><p>  ReBo is a statutory body set up to facilitate the restructuring of credit unions on a voluntary, incentivised and time-bound basis. The focus of restructuring is to bring stability to the credit union sector without impinging on some credit unions to succeed on a standalone basis.  All restructuring proposals require Central Bank approval. </p><p>  Under the Central Bank and Credit Institutions (Resolution) Act 2011 the Central Bank can take resolution action where necessary via a High Court process. This provision was used to safeguard members&rsquo; savings at Newbridge Credit Union.</p><p>  The Registry of Credit Unions introduced a Fitness and Probity regime on 1 August 2013 for credit unions with total assets of greater than &euro;10m. This was the beginning of a phased approach to the introduction of Fitness and Probity measures for all credit unions, with the second phase due to commence on 1 August 2015 when all remaining credit unions will be brought within the scope of the regime. Currently relevant credit unions require pre-approval by the Central Bank for a Chair and Manager prior to either of these positions been taken up. This will ensure that any individual carrying out these roles is fit and proper to do so.</p><p>  This Government has introduced a number of measures in relation an effective regulatory structure for the sector and I am satisfied that these measures will underpin a stable credit union sector into the future. </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.48" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA03350">Fuel Laundering</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.49.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1177" speakername="Denis Naughten" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA03400"><p><i>25.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance the estimated loss to the Exchequer as a result of fuel laundering; the steps taken to curb this practice; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[1606/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.50.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA03500"><p>I am advised by the Revenue Commissioners, who have responsibility for the collection of mineral oil tax and for tackling illicit trade in mineral oil products, that estimating the extent of any illegal activity and the associated cost to the exchequer is inherently problematic. </p><p>  The most serious risk in relation to illicit trade in mineral oil products is from the laundering of markers from diesel that is subject to a reduced rate of mineral oil tax on condition that it is not used for road vehicles.  Revenue collects some &euro;1.1 billion annually in excise duty from road diesel and, while there is no reliable estimate of the scale of the problem, they recognise that the potential for loss of tax revenue from fuel laundering represents a significant threat to the Exchequer and to the legitimate trade.</p><p>  Fuel laundering, to remove the marker added to lower-taxed mineral oil for off-road use, has been a problem for many years.  However, it remained a marginal activity because the sulphur content of marked fuel was higher than that for road fuel and therefore the sulphur content continued to distinguish laundered fuel from genuine road fuel.  Environmental requirements in relation to the sulphur content of fuel changed from the beginning of 2011, which resulted in marked fuel with the same sulphur content as road fuel coming onto the market.  With the change, fuel laundering became more viable and criminal gangs intensified their laundering and distribution activities dramatically from the first half of 2011.</p><p>  In response to the intensification of fraud in this area, Revenue has made action against fuel laundering one of its priorities and is implementing a comprehensive strategy to tackle the problem through enhanced supply chain controls, the acquisition of a more effective fuel marker and continued robust enforcement action.#</p><p>  Revenue&rsquo;s strategy included strengthening the licensing conditions for auto-fuel traders in 2011 and the introduction of a new licensing system for marked fuel traders in October 2012.  In addition, since January 2013, all licensed fuel traders are required to make electronic returns to Revenue of their monthly fuel transactions.  These supply chain control measures are designed to make it difficult for fuel criminals to source marked fuel for laundering and to get laundered product onto the market.  Analysis of the monthly returns enables Revenue to identify suspicious or anomalous fuel transactions and patterns of distribution.   Traders found to be involved in suspicious activity are investigated and if they are unable to account properly for the source or disposal of product face revocation of their licence, tax assessment and prosecution, where appropriate.</p><p>  In addition, Revenue and HM Revenue &amp;amp; Customs in the UK are collaborating on identifying a more effective marker for use in both jurisdictions and signed a Memorandum of Understanding in May 2012.  A number of proposals for a new marker were received in response to an Invitation to Make Submissions and were evaluated by a joint evaluation group.  The evaluation group has completed the final evaluation and presented its recommendations to the joint project board.  The final decision on the implementation of any new marker rests with the Economic Secretary to the Treasury in the UK and the Board of the Revenue Commissioners in Ireland; the Revenue Authorities expect to make an announcement shortly.</p><p>  Revenue, in co-operation with other law enforcement agencies on both sides of the border, continues to intensify enforcement action against fuel fraud and this work has yielded significant results to date.  In the period from 2011 to end December 2013 119 filling stations throughout the State were closed for breaches of licensing conditions.  Since the beginning of 2011, over 2.7 million litres of fuel have been seized and 29 oil laundries detected and closed down, including 9 oil laundries in 2013.</p><p>  Revenue regularly reminds motorists and the public generally that, in addition to its impact on the exchequer and legitimate trade, they should be aware of the risks that the use of laundered fuel poses to their vehicles and that sourcing fuel in this way is funding criminal activity.</p><p>  The legitimate trade can also contribute to closing down this illicit trade by providing information on the outlets that are selling laundered diesel.  Revenue chairs the Hidden Economy Monitoring Group (HEMG) and has established regional sub-groups of the HEMG to facilitate the reporting of information by traders through their representative associations.  Retailers who suspect or have evidence that laundered diesel is being sold in their area should report this through their representative associations to Revenue.  Any such reports are treated as confidential and are fully investigated by Revenue.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.51" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA03550">Real Estate Investment Trusts</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.52.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/956" speakername="Mick Wallace" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA03600"><p><i>26.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance the reason real estate investment trusts were introduced in Ireland, despite the fact that, according to budget 2013, they entailed a loss to the Exchequer of &euro;14 million; and if he will make a statement on the matter.  <b>[1511/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.53.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA03700"><p>The introduction of tax framework for Real Estate Investment Trust companies was announced in Budget 2013, and enacted in Finance Act 2013 in March of last year, and the Deputy may recall that detailed discussion of the proposal took place at that time.  I would like to highlight again that the REIT regime is not a tax relief.  It can better be understood as a structural reform of property investment vehicles, allowing for lower-risk, sustainable long-term investment.</p><p>  The overarching objective of the REIT regime is to remove a tax bias - caused by a double layer of taxation &ndash; which has typically discouraged collective investment in property through a company.</p><p>  The 2013 Budget Book estimated cost of introducing REITs was &euro;2 million in 2013, rising to a potential &euro;14 million per year in a mature REIT market. The cost estimate relates to a potential fall in tax revenue related to foreign investors in Irish REITs, to the extent that REITs displace direct ownership of investment property.  Direct owners of investment property are taxable under Irish income or corporate tax rules.  In contrast foreign REIT shareholders will be liable to a flat Dividend Withholding Tax of 20%, with potential to reduce this to a lower rate if they qualify for relief under a tax treaty.</p><p>  Where an Irish-resident investor invests in property through a REIT rather than directly, the rate of taxation is the same, so no cost is associated with Irish investors.</p><p>  This potential cost to the Exchequer was felt to be outweighed by the benefits which REITs could bring to the market, including the following:</p><p>  1. Attraction of new investment capital to the Irish property market.</p><p>  2. Freeing up bank finance from the property market, allowing it to be re-directed to other businesses in need of bank financing.</p><p>  3. A new, lower-risk, property investment option for small and large investors alike.</p><p>  4. Professional property management and improvement of standards for tenants.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.54" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA03750">NAMA Operations</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.55.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/959" speakername="Pearse Doherty" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA03800"><p><i>27.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance if he shares the view expressed by the National Asset Management Agency that there is an organised campaign of misinformation whose objective is to undermine the effectiveness of NAMA; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[1650/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.56.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA03900"><p>It is not clear to me what the motivation behind these allegations is or how they found their way into the media or to the Oireachtas member who made a statement in the Seanad in December. It is unfortunate that the press coverage and speculation appears to call into question the integrity and professionalism of NAMA and its staff. The progress the Agency is making in hitting its targets is a testament to the focus and hard work of the staff, management and board of NAMA. </p><p>  I was encouraged by NAMA&rsquo;s request to appear before the Public Accounts Committee and felt this gave both NAMA and the Oireachtas an opportunity to air their respective concerns and clarify any confusion or misunderstanding.</p><p>  I would like to reiterate, in relation to the recent reports, if any party has evidence of any impropriety, they are legally obliged, under Section 19 of the Criminal Justice Act 2011, to bring it to the immediate attention of the Garda Siochana. Needless to say if any matter is brought to the Garda or NAMA&rsquo;s attention, it will be fully investigated.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.57" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA03950">Central Bank of Ireland Investigations</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.58.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA04000"><p><i>28.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance if he is satisfied with the progress being made by the Central Bank of Ireland in their investigation into the misselling of payment protection insurance policies; when the investigation will be completed; the expected number of customers who will be entitled to some remediation; and if he will make a statement on the matter.  <b>[1631/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.59.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA04100"><p>On 3 October 2013 the Central Bank issued an update on its on-going investigation into the sales of Payment Protection Insurance (PPI).  Eleven firms are reviewing their sales and, where appropriate, offering a refund to their customers where the PPI sale is found to be in breach of the Consumer Protection Code since July 2007.</p><p>  I have been informed by the Central Bank that the review of the eleven firms is drawing to a close and that all customers covered by this review have been contacted, with the majority of those eligible for a refund, having already received their refunds. </p><p>  I am satisfied that the investigation is progressing. Pending completion of the investigation, I will not comment on the expected number of customers to receive remediation. </p><p>  When the investigation has been completed to its satisfaction, the Central Bank will issue a statement.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.60" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA04150">Economic Policy</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.61.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1003" speakername="Richard Boyd Barrett" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA04200"><p><i>29.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance in view of the recent acknowledgement to the EU Parliament in responses to its questionnaire on the troika programme that the lowest income bracket had been disproportionately affected by austerity measures under the programme, the policy measures he proposes to address this unfairness; and if he will make a statement on the matter.  <b>[1655/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.62.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA04300"><p>As the Deputy will be aware, the response given to the questionnaire was referring to an assessment, recently published by the Economic and Social Research Institute (ESRI), of the distributional impact of the budgetary adjustments undertaken since the onset of the financial crises in 2008.</p><p>  Over the full period from 2009 to 2014, the study found that all income groups experienced losses, but it continues to show that the highest losses have been borne by those in the highest 10 per cent of the income distribution.</p><p>  While the ESRI&rsquo;s assessment does suggest that the next highest losses have occurred in the lowest decile, the estimate of the effect on the lowest decile is strongly influenced by the changes to indirect taxes. As the best way to tackle poverty and inequality is to create jobs and reduce unemployment through economic growth, and evidence from the OECD shows that indirect taxes are less harmful than income taxes. Indeed, implementing this policy is bearing fruit with employment increasing by some 60,000 in 2013 to the third quarter and unemployment down to 12.4% from a peak of 15.1%</p><p>  Finally, the ERSI assessment indicates that the overall consolidation process from 2009 to 2014 has not been regressive and it is worth re-iterating that the OECD and the European Commission have shown that Ireland still retains one of the most progressive income tax systems in the developed world.</p><p>  Looking to the future, the research of the ESRI will inform deliberations in advance of Budget 2015.	</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.63" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA04350">Banks Recapitalisation</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.64.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/959" speakername="Pearse Doherty" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA04400"><p><i>30.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance if he proposes to apply for a retroactive recapitalisation of Ireland&rsquo;s banking debt in 2014 through the ESM; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[1651/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.65.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA04500"><p>The Euro Area Heads of State or Government (EU HoSG) agreed in June 2012 to break the vicious circle between banks and sovereigns, and that when a Single Supervisory Mechanism, involving the ECB, is in place and operational, the European Stability Mechanism could, following a regular decision, have the capacity to recapitalize banks directly. </p><p>  The Eurogroup meeting of 20th June 2013 agreed on the main features of the ESM&rsquo;s Direct Bank Recapitalisation instrument (DBR). The DBR instrument will come into effect when the SSM is operational. There is a specific provision included in those main features that provides for retroactive recapitalisation. This provision states that: &ldquo;The potential retroactive application of the instrument should be decided on a case-by-case basis and by mutual agreement.&rdquo; Therefore, the agreement that we were active in negotiating keeps open the possibility to apply to the ESM for a retrospective direct recapitalisation of the Irish banks should we wish to avail of it.  The SSM is expected to be place and operational towards the end of 2014.</p><p>  The Eurogroup has agreed that there will be strict eligibility criteria as well as a clear pecking order for the ESM DBR instrument, so any possible application for DBR will be determined on its own merits within the rules laid down by the ESM&rsquo;s DBR instrument.</p><p>  The overall framework agreed in Summer 2013 builds upon the earlier Euro Area Heads of State or Government agreement secured on the 29th of June 2012, and is an important step in the Eurozone&rsquo;s efforts in this regard. </p><p>  I remain confident that the commitment made by the EU HoSG in June 2012 to break the vicious circle between banks and sovereigns will be respected. </p><p>  The question of whether Ireland may apply for retroactive recapitalisation of our banks has yet to be decided upon and will, in due course, be a matter for Government, with any recommendation based on what is in Ireland&rsquo;s best interest. </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.66" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA04550">Road Safety</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.67.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1110" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA04600"><p><i>31.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance if he will give consideration, in the context of the recent road safety statistics, to exempting safety equipment such a helmets, visibility clothing and so forth from VAT; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[1552/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.68.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA04700"><p>The VAT rating of goods and services is subject to the requirements of EU VAT law with which Irish VAT law must comply.  The VAT Directive does not make specific provision for a reduced or zero rate, or an exemption from VAT, to apply to safety equipment, including helmets and visibility clothing.  As such, they are subject to the standard VAT rate, which is currently 23%.  </p><p>  However, for historic reasons the zero rate of VAT applies to safety clothing, helmets and visibility clothing, for children up to 10 years of age, while the supply of such clothing for adults and children older than 10 years is liable to VAT at the 23% rate.  As Ireland applied the zero rate to clothing and protective clothing for children up to 10 years of age on 1 January 1991, we are entitled to retain that zero rated application.  However, as the standard VAT rate applied to safety equipment and safety clothing for adults and older children on 1 January 1991, it is not possible to apply a reduced or zero rate to them, nor to exempt them from VAT.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.69" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA04750">Tax Code</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.70.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1015" speakername="Clare Daly" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA04800"><p><i>32.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance the reason he has not introduced a third band of taxation for high earners. <b>[1507/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.71.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA04900"><p>As the Deputy is aware, a progressive taxation system ensures that the burden of taxation falls most heavily on those with a higher ability to pay. The latest OECD data indicates that Ireland already has the most progressive tax system of the 21 EU countries which are members of that organisation.  It is in this context that the Government has committed in the Programme for Government not to increase the marginal rate of income tax.</p><p>  The Revenue Commissioners estimate that in 2014 the top 5 per cent of income earners will pay 44 per cent of the total income tax collected and those earning &euro;50,000 or less, which represents 77 per cent of income earners, will only pay 19 per cent of the total income tax collected. In addition, 856,000 individuals, representing approximately 39 per cent of the income tax base, will be exempt from income tax altogether.  </p><p>  Since 2008 marginal rates of taxation on income have increased from 43.5% for PAYE workers and 46.5% for the self-employed, to 52 per cent and 55 per cent, respectively. Moreover, single employees incur this relatively high marginal rate where their income exceeds &euro;32,800 per year. From an international perspective, Ireland is already considered to have a high marginal rate of tax on income. According to the latest data, Ireland has the 9th highest marginal tax rate out of the 34 members of the OECD.</p><p>Marginal tax rates are important because they influence individual decisions to work, or indeed to work more. A further increase in the marginal rate would reduce the incentive for income earners to work extra hours or for the self-employed to expand their business and take on more employees. Higher marginal rates of taxation undermine the competitiveness of businesses operating in Ireland, and act as a disincentive to future foreign direct investment. The OECD in its working paper &lsquo;Tax and Economic Growth&rsquo;  points to the <i>&ldquo;possibility that high top marginal rates will increase the average tax rates paid by high-skilled and high-income earners so much that they will migrate to countries with lower rates resulting in a brain drain which may lower innovative activity and productivity&rdquo;</i>  . </p><p>  For all of the above reasons, I have decided not to introduce a third band of taxation for high earners.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.72" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA04950">Corporation Tax Regime</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.73.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1015" speakername="Clare Daly" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA05000"><p><i>33.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance if he has undertaken a cost benefit analysis of the effect of increasing Ireland's corporation tax rate; and if not, the reason this sector has been excluded from tax increases.  <b>[1508/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.74.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA05100"><p>It is possible to estimate the full year yield to the Exchequer of increasing the standard rate of corporation tax.  I am informed by the Revenue Commissioners that the full year yield to the Exchequer, estimated in terms of expected 2014 profits, of increasing the standard rate of corporation tax from 12.5% to 13.5% is tentatively estimated on a straight line arithmetic basis to be about &euro;326 million.</p><p>  However, while such an estimate would be technically correct it does not take into account any possible behavioural change on the part of taxpayers as a consequence. In terms of an increase in the 12.5% rate, estimating the size of the behavioural effects is difficult but they are likely to be relatively significant. </p><p>  To give the Deputy an idea of what the effects of such a change would likely be, an OECD multi-country study found that a 1% increase in the corporate tax rate reduces inward investment by 3.7% on average. On this basis, it would take only a 2.5% increase in the rate (to 15%) to decrease Ireland&rsquo;s inward investment by nearly 10%. This OECD study assumes the average applies across the board but in fact the effect is likely to be more extreme for Ireland, given the economic challenges faced by a small island such as ourselves. </p><p>  The very major importance of maintaining the standard 12.5% rate of corporation tax to Ireland&rsquo;s international competitive position in the current climate must also be borne in mind. Ireland, like other smaller member states, is geographically and historically a peripheral country in Europe. A low corporate tax rate is a tool to address the economic limitations that come with being a peripheral country, as compared to larger core countries. Ireland&rsquo;s low corporation tax rate plays an important role in attracting foreign direct investment to Ireland and thereby increasing employment here. Recent research by the OECD also points to the importance of low corporate tax rates to encourage growth. </p><p>  Cost benefit analyses aside, it also would be difficult to justify such a move in the context of Ireland&rsquo;s stated position that we will not change our corporation tax strategy. Even a marginal change would undermine both our long held stance on this issue and the certainty of business, domestic and international, in our resolve to maintain that position.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.75" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA05150">Illicit Trade in Tobacco</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.76.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/999" speakername="Charlie McConalogue" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA05200"><p><i>34.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance the cost to the State in 2011, 2012 and 2013 of the illegal cigarette trade; the procedures and plans his Department have in place to tackle this growing problem especially in Border counties in view of the fact that a nationwide survey found that 24.5% of cigarettes sold in Letterkenny are illegal compared to a national average of 13%; and if he will make a statement on the matter.  <b>[1636/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.77.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA05300"><p>I am advised by the Revenue Commissioners that the extent of the illicit cigarettes market in Ireland is estimated through annual surveys of smokers.  These surveys are undertaken for Revenue and the National Tobacco Control Office of the Health Services Executive by IPSOS MRBI. The survey for 2012 found that 13% of cigarettes consumed in Ireland are illicit. The comparable figure for 2011 was 14%. This would suggest that the extent of the problem is being contained, as a result of the extensive action being taken against the smuggling and sale of illicit product. A further survey was carried out at the end of 2013 and that the results of this will be available in the coming months.</p><p>  The Deputy will of course appreciate that estimating the scale of any illegal activity and the resultant tax loss is difficult. I am however satisfied that the IPSOS MRBI survey is the best indicator of the extent of the market in illicit cigarettes<font color="#FF0000">. </font> This is because of the methodologies used and the consistent manner in which the survey has been undertaken over a number of years. In addition, the survey methodology<font color="#FF0000"> </font>  is, unlike other methodologies such as empty pack surveys, capable of distinguishing between legal personal imports and illicit cigarettes. The survey is also geographically representative and takes social class, age, gender and nationality into account. Data from the IPSOS MRBI surveys would indicate a nominal annual loss in the order of &euro;240 million in excise duty and VAT.</p><p>  I am assured by the Revenue Commissioners that combating the illegal tobacco trade is, and will continue to be, a high priority for them. Their work against this illegal activity includes a range of measures designed to identify and target those who are engaged in the supply or sale of illicit products, with a view to seizing the illicit products and prosecuting those responsible. This multi-faceted strategy includes ongoing analysis of the nature and extent of the problem, developing and sharing intelligence on a national, EU and international basis, the use of analytics and detection technologies and ensuring the optimum deployment of resources at points of importation and within the country.</p><p>  Interception of illicit tobacco products is achieved through a combination of risk analysis, profiling, intelligence and the screening of cargo, vehicles, baggage and postal packages. Revenue officers also target the illicit trade at the post-importation level by carrying out intelligence-based operations and random checks at retail outlets, markets and private and commercial premises.</p><p>  There is extensive cooperation with An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na in combating the illicit trade, and the relevant agencies in the state also work closely with their counterparts in Northern Ireland, through a cross-border group on tobacco enforcement, to target the organised crime groups that are responsible for a large proportion of the illegal tobacco market. In addition, cooperation takes place with other Revenue administrations and with the European Anti-Fraud Office, OLAF, in the ongoing programmes to tackle the illicit trade at international level.</p><p>  In relation to tackling this problem in border counties in particular, Revenue advise me that they have an enforcement presence at key strategic locations in the border counties, and enforcement strength is regularly augmented with additional personnel on a risk-assessment basis, or when particular operations against illegal activity are taking place. 10.66 million illicit cigarettes were seized in Revenue&rsquo;s Border Midlands West Region in 2013, and there were 15 convictions during 2013 arising from detections in the Region of the selling or smuggling of illicit tobacco products </p><p>  The Revenue Commissioners will remain committed to acting against all stages of the supply chain for illicit tobacco products and will continue to make very effort to ensure that those involved in the illicit trade are brought to account before the Courts for their criminal activities.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.78" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA05350">Departmental Reports</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.79.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1001" speakername="Thomas Pringle" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA05400"><p><i>35.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance the date on which the report on the standard bank account pilot project is due to be published; and if he will make a statement on the matter.  <b>[1644/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.80.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600051#WRA05500"><p>The Report on the Standard Bank Account pilot project was published on my Department&rsquo;s website on 10 January 2014. </p><p>  The Financial Inclusion Working Group (FIWG), chaired by my Department, and including stakeholders from other Government Departments, the Central Bank of Ireland, retail banks, An Post, the National Consumer Agency and voluntary sector organisations will work closely together on the finalisation and roll out of the Standard Bank Account. It is expected that the rollout of the Standard Bank Account will be achieved during 2014.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.82" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600052#WRB00150">Commercial Debt</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.83.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600052#WRB00200"><p><i>36.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance the steps being taken to ensure that the issue of small and medium-sized enterprise debt is being tackled; if he is satisfied with the progress being made; and if he will make a statement on the matter.  <b>[1632/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.84.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600052#WRB00300"><p>In June 2013 the Central Bank set quarterly institution-specific performance targets for covered banks to move distressed SME borrowers onto longer-term solutions.  The targets set reflect the banks&rsquo; capacity, processes and systems.  It is not intended that these targets will be published. I am informed by the Central Bank that the banks have reported that they have met their required targets to date. </p><p>  I should stress that the Credit Review process remains available to any SMEs whose credit has been reduced or withdrawn by AIB or Bank of Ireland as well as when credit is refused by them. I would strongly advise any SME whose credit is reduced or withdrawn to avail of the services of the Credit Review Office.</p><p>  The Government recognises that SMEs are the lifeblood of the economy and play a vital role in the continuing recovery of employment growth in our country. In this regard specific measures to promote access to finance amongst SMEs, including measures relating to debt restructuring, have been a central feature of the Government&rsquo;s Action Plan for Jobs.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.85" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600052#WRB00350">Government Bonds</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.86.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/957" speakername="Bernard Durkan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600052#WRB00400"><p><i>37.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance arising from recent experience in the bond market, the extent to which it might be found possible to issue specific bonds targeting investment leading to job creation such as the public housing building programme in view of the serious need in this area and the opportunities for a major boost in terms of job creation in the construction sector which is currently lagging way below normal economic requirements; and if he will make a statement on the matter.  <b>[1586/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.87.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600052#WRB00500"><p>The proceeds of all borrowings by the Exchequer, as well as tax revenues, non-tax revenues and other receipts are lodged to the Exchequer account at the Central Bank of Ireland to fund on-going Government expenditure. </p><p>The National Treasury Management Agency (NTMA) has advised that project-specific bonds issued by the State which are linked to a specific project and which are <i>serviced and repaid from the Exchequer in the same way as standard Government bonds</i>  , may be of limited interest to investors as they would be concerned about a relative lack of liquidity. Investors in project-specific bonds would require higher yields than standard Government bonds to reflect the inferior liquidity. </p><p>The NTMA had advised that project-specific bonds which are <i>serviced and repaid according to the performance of the project</i>   would be considered by investors to carry more risk than standard bonds issued by the State and serviced and repaid by the Exchequer. Investors in project-specific bonds would require higher yields to reflect the increased risk and a Government guarantee could be required in order to make a project viable. </p><p>  I am happy to confirm that the Government remains committed to exploring alternative means of financing capital projects. The National Development Finance Agency (NDFA) is charged with advising on the optimal means of financing the costs of all public investment projects over &euro;20 million in order to achieve value for money, including the &euro;2.25 billion stimulus package announced by the Government in July 2012. NDFA continues to facilitate securing funding for both Public Private Partnerships (PPPs) and traditional projects from a wide range of sources including domestic and international banks, institutional investors and supranational organisations such as the European Investment Bank and the Council of European Investment Bank.</p><p>  The Government has announced the creation of the Ireland Strategic Investment Fund (ISIF) to channel investment from the National Pensions Reserve Fund (NPRF) towards productive investment in sectors of strategic importance to the Irish economy. Within its existing statutory investment policy and in line with the ISIF announcement, the NPRF has undertaken a number of investments and initiatives under which NPRF capital will be invested on a commercial basis in Ireland. The funding structure for two current PPP projects involved the participation of the NPRF alongside EIB and Bank of Ireland. In addition, the NPRF continues to source investment opportunities, in preparation for the creation of the ISIF, a number of which are expected to involve construction activity.</p></reply>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.89" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600052#WRB00600">Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.88" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600052#WRB00550">Departmental Expenditure</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.89.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1057" speakername="Niall Collins" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600052#WRB00600"><p><i>38.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade if he will detail, in tabular form, the total photography costs for his Department since coming to office inclusive of costs incurred from use of the ministerial allowance; the list of occasions for which photographers were booked; the photographers used; the breakdown of costs associated with each occasion that a photographer was used; if there is a policy regarding the booking of photographers within his Department; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[1852/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.90.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/951" speakername="Eamon Gilmore" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600052#WRB00700"><p>My Department only avails of the services of external photographic agencies where it is warranted, in particular, for major events and State occasions. This is a service which my Department provides so that the media can easily and freely avail of photography where their own staff photographers cannot be fully accommodated. There was a significant number of such events in the period in question, including the State Visit of Queen Elizabeth II, the visit by President Obama and  the Irish Chairmanship of the OSCE, all of which resulted in very positive international coverage of Ireland. In the case of Ireland&rsquo;s Presidency of the EU, there was a demand for photography which would not routinely apply. </p><p>  In September 2011, my Department led a collaborative advertised tender process for the procurement of a multi-supplier competitive framework of photographic service providers. This is now available for use by all Government Departments. Details of the new framework arrangements are posted on the National Procurement Service website:   . The purpose of this framework is to ensure Departments&rsquo; compliance with EU procurement rules and to ensure value for money by having a competitive process for photographic assignments.  </p><p>  In addition, my Department now makes greater use of in-house resources for photography, including, for example, at the recent lecture delivered by Sir John Major in Iveagh House. </p><p>  The total cost of photography to my Department over the period in question is &euro;119,284.80.</p><p>  The table below indicates the cost associated with particular events.<table><tr><th><div>Event </div></th><th><div>Cost</div></th></tr><tr><td>State Visit of Queen Elizabeth II</td><td><div>&euro;22,662.70</div></td></tr><tr><td>Expenditure on photography of missions abroad*</td><td><div>&euro;21,456.36</div></td></tr><tr><td>Diplomatic Credentials Ceremonies</td><td><div>&euro;14,912.44</div></td></tr><tr><td>Official Visit by Chinese Vice President</td><td><div>&euro;7,321.58</div></td></tr><tr><td>State Visit of Prince Albert of Monaco</td><td><div>&euro;6,213.35</div></td></tr><tr><td>OSCE Ministerial Council</td><td><div>&euro;4,786.55</div></td></tr><tr><td>Official Visit by Japanese Prime Minister</td><td><div>&euro;2,555.94</div></td></tr><tr><td>Official Visit by Canadian Prime Minister</td><td><div>&euro;2,553.36</div></td></tr><tr><td>Official Visit by the King &amp;amp; Queen of Lesotho</td><td><div>&euro;2,473.14</div></td></tr><tr><td>Official Visit to Mozambique, Malawi &amp;amp; Tanzania</td><td><div>&euro;2,388.30</div></td></tr><tr><td>Global Irish Economic Forum 2013</td><td><div>&euro;2,175.20</div></td></tr><tr><td>Diplomatic Corps New Years Greetings </td><td><div>&euro;2,015.97</div></td></tr><tr><td>Global Irish Economic Forum</td><td><div>&euro;1,923.90</div></td></tr><tr><td>Inauguration of President Higgins</td><td><div>&euro;1,817.30</div></td></tr><tr><td>OSCE Event: Lessons learned from NI Peace Process</td><td><div>&euro;1,479.35</div></td></tr><tr><td>Our World Awards</td><td><div>&euro;1,268.05</div></td></tr><tr><td>Africa Ireland Economic Forum 2011</td><td><div>&euro;1,220.59</div></td></tr><tr><td>Presidential Distinguished service Awards 2013</td><td><div>&euro;1,074.20</div></td></tr><tr><td>Our World Irish Aid Awards (National + Regional Finals)</td><td><div>&euro;942.18</div></td></tr><tr><td>Haiti Photographic exhibition </td><td><div>&euro;919.90</div></td></tr><tr><td>Irish Aid Centre education materials</td><td><div>&euro;741.80</div></td></tr><tr><td>Science for Development Award at BT Young Scientist </td><td><div>&euro;711.71</div></td></tr><tr><td>Commemoration Lecture Series </td><td><div>&euro;658.82</div></td></tr><tr><td>Irish Aid - One World One Future Policy Launch</td><td><div>&euro;637.14</div></td></tr><tr><td>Official Visit to Kenya</td><td><div>&euro;606.40</div></td></tr><tr><td>Official Visit by Indian Minister</td><td><div>&euro;599.75</div></td></tr><tr><td>2010 Irish Aid annual report</td><td><div>&euro;569.00</div></td></tr><tr><td>EU Presidency Logo</td><td><div>&euro;560.84</div></td></tr><tr><td>Africa Day 2011 - Dublin</td><td><div>&euro;526.35</div></td></tr><tr><td>Official Farewell for the British Ambassador </td><td><div>&euro;524.84</div></td></tr><tr><td>Meeting of EU Development Ministers</td><td><div>&euro;521.19</div></td></tr><tr><td>Western Balkans Conference</td><td><div>&euro;482.16</div></td></tr><tr><td>Africa Day 2013</td><td><div>&euro;478.45</div></td></tr><tr><td>Visit of Elders </td><td><div>&euro;430.50</div></td></tr><tr><td>OSCE 5+2 Conference</td><td><div>&euro;417.76</div></td></tr><tr><td>Visit of Congressman Morrison</td><td><div>&euro;412.05</div></td></tr><tr><td>Visit of Aung San Suu Kyi</td><td><div>&euro;393.92</div></td></tr><tr><td>Official Visit by US Congressional Delegation</td><td><div>&euro;388.62</div></td></tr><tr><td>Hunger Envoy&rsquo;s Report </td><td><div>&euro;379.33</div></td></tr><tr><td>Visit of Governor of Massachusetts</td><td><div>&euro;361.62</div></td></tr><tr><td>Simon Cumbers Fund Exhibition</td><td><div>&euro;350.86</div></td></tr><tr><td>Official Visit by US First Lady</td><td><div>&euro;327.18</div></td></tr><tr><td>Africa Ireland Economic Forum - 2012</td><td><div>&euro;319.80</div></td></tr><tr><td>Meeting with Japanese Ambassador</td><td><div>&euro;318.84</div></td></tr><tr><td>Launch of Certificate of Irish Heritage </td><td><div>&euro;296.23</div></td></tr><tr><td>Hunger Nutrition Climate Justice Conference</td><td><div>&euro;284.63</div></td></tr><tr><td>Irish Aid Trade and Development Conf.</td><td><div>&euro;282.41</div></td></tr><tr><td>UNRWA Commissioner General</td><td><div>&euro;246.00</div></td></tr><tr><td>Official Visit by Chinese Vice Premier Ma</td><td><div>&euro;223.86</div></td></tr><tr><td>Meeting with British delegation</td><td><div>&euro;209.10</div></td></tr><tr><td>Irish Aid Annual Report launch</td><td><div>&euro;206.64</div></td></tr><tr><td>100 Objects launch</td><td><div>&euro;206.64</div></td></tr><tr><td>Visit of Bill Gates</td><td><div>&euro;195.20</div></td></tr><tr><td>Visit of German Opposition Leader</td><td><div>&euro;194.88</div></td></tr><tr><td>Visit of Norwegian Foreign Minister</td><td><div>&euro;189.19</div></td></tr><tr><td>Irish Aid Our World Awards - 2013</td><td><div>&euro;171.23</div></td></tr><tr><td>EU Affairs Ministers Meeting</td><td><div>&euro;166.05</div></td></tr><tr><td>Visit of French Minister for European Affairs</td><td><div>&euro;166.05</div></td></tr><tr><td>Irish Aid Int'l Conf. on Agriculture</td><td><div>&euro;164.60</div></td></tr><tr><td>EU Working Group on Humanitarian Aid</td><td><div>&euro;154.98</div></td></tr><tr><td>OSCE 5+2 Conference (2)</td><td><div>&euro;153.75</div></td></tr><tr><td>Irish Aid Volunteering Fair 2013</td><td><div>&euro;137.76</div></td></tr><tr><td>Visit of Romanian Foreign Minister</td><td><div>&euro;137.76</div></td></tr><tr><td>Visit of Head of International Rescue Committee</td><td><div>&euro;137.76</div></td></tr><tr><td>Forum on female entrepreneurship</td><td><div>&euro;134.33</div></td></tr><tr><td>Irish Aid - AWEPA Conference</td><td><div>&euro;120.54</div></td></tr><tr><td>Lecture by Mark O'Neill</td><td><div>&euro;120.54</div></td></tr><tr><td>Visit of Swiss Foreign Minister</td><td><div>&euro;120.54</div></td></tr><tr><td>Irish Aid Fellowship Annual Meeting</td><td><div>&euro;119.55</div></td></tr><tr><td>Volunteering Fair, Limerick - 2011</td><td><div>&euro;119.55</div></td></tr><tr><td>Forum with Arab Ambassadors</td><td><div>&euro;116.85</div></td></tr><tr><td>Africa Day Launch, Limerick - 2011</td><td><div>&euro;115.85</div></td></tr><tr><td>BT Young Scientist - 2013</td><td><div>&euro;109.25</div></td></tr><tr><td>Meeting with UN Special Envoy to the Great Lakes Region</td><td><div>&euro;103.32</div></td></tr><tr><td>Visit of Secretary General, Council of Europe</td><td><div>&euro;103.32</div></td></tr><tr><td>Global Irish Network Advisory Group</td><td><div>&euro;102.15</div></td></tr><tr><td>Official Visit to Korea and Japan</td><td><div>&euro;95.00</div></td></tr><tr><td>Total </td><td><div>&euro;119,284.80</div></td></tr></table>  *It was not possible to provide a full breakdown in the time available.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.91" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600052#WRB00750">Consular Services Expenditure</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.92.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1057" speakername="Niall Collins" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600052#WRB00800"><p><i>39.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade if he will detail, in tabular form, the use of external public relations firms employed by his Department since coming to office; the list of uses of the external public relations firm; his internal Department policy regarding employing external groups; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[1867/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.93.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/951" speakername="Eamon Gilmore" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600052#WRB00900"><p>For the period referred to by the Deputy my Department has not incurred expenditure on external public relations and communications services. From time to time, consultants or companies with a public relations and communications background are commissioned to provide other professional services such as project management, logistics and event management.  </p><p>   DHR Communications has been contracted since 2010 to manage and administer grants under the Simon Cumbers Media Fund (SCMF). This involves managing two funding rounds each year, including through national and regional information workshops; managing and administering the application process; organising the judging process and providing detailed feedback to all applicants; processing grant payments and keeping detailed administrative and financial records; maintaining and updating the SCMF website and managing the SCMF student competition.  DHR was awarded a two-year contract to 2012 and was re-engaged in February 2012 for a further two years following a competitive tendering process.   </p><p>  Following a competitive tendering process, DHR has been engaged to plan, manage and execute a national Africa Day flagship event in Dublin. This includes the administration of a small grants scheme for regional events which DHR managed on behalf of the Department in partnership with a number of local authorities.  DHR also worked to raise public awareness of the Africa Day events, including through the use of social media and the Africa Day website. This work represented a very minor element of the project and was conducted in close cooperation with my Department&rsquo;s communications office.</p><p>  Africa Day Family Days, incorporating musical entertainment, cultural activities and an African Bazaar, were hosted by the Department in Iveagh Gardens in 2009 and 2010, in CHQ in Georges Dock in 2012 and at the Farmleigh Estate in 2013. In 2011, the Department supported a series of smaller-scale performances, family events, art exhibitions, debates and educational activities instead of hosting a flagship event. </p><p>  DHR also provided short-term management support services for the Review of the White Paper on Irish Aid, including the logistical management of the nationwide public consultation activities.</p><p>  The table below sets out the use of DHR engaged by my Development Cooperation Division since March 2011.   </p><p><b>Project and Event Management March 2011 to date 14 January 2014</b><table><tr><th>Name of Project/Event</th><th><div>Year</div></th></tr><tr><td>Simon Cumbers Media Fund (SCMF) grants scheme</td><td><div>2011, 2012, 2013</div></td></tr><tr><td>The Irish Aid White Paper Review</td><td><div>2011, 2012</div></td></tr><tr><td>Africa Day</td><td><div>2011, 2012, 2013</div></td></tr></table></p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.94" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600052#WRB00950">Consultancy Contracts Data</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.95.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1037" speakername="Se&aacute;n Crowe" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600052#WRB01000"><p><i>40.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade the number of consultants or consultancy firms employed by his Department during each of the past five years; the purpose and duration of each of these consultancies or consultancy contracts; the names of the consultants or firms; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[1874/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.96.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/951" speakername="Eamon Gilmore" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600052#WRB01100"><p>The Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade is responsible for two Votes &ndash; Vote 28: Foreign Affairs and Trade, and Vote 27: International Cooperation. <font color="#004080"> </font>Consultants are engaged only where specialised knowledge and skills are not available within the Department and, especially in the case of Ireland&rsquo;s official overseas aid programme, known as <i>Irish Aid</i>, where independent appraisal, audit, monitoring and evaluation of programmes and projects is required.  Decisions on the need to commission outside expertise are subject to the establishment of appropriate business cases and an approvals process overseen by senior management of the Department&rsquo;s Development Cooperation Division.  Expenditure on consultancy services is constantly monitored to ensure that it does not exceed the level required for the proper management of the aid programme.</p><p>  Details of the consultants engaged by the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade during the period in question are set out in the tables below.  It was not possible in the time available to review each individual case in order to determine its duration.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.97" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600052#WRB01150">Global Economic Forum</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.98.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/969" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600052#WRB01200"><p><i>41.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade the process and timeframe for the comprehensive review of Ireland&rsquo;s diaspora policy which he announced at the Global Irish Economic Forum; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[1893/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.99.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/951" speakername="Eamon Gilmore" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600052#WRB01300"><p>The current structures and policies for engagement with the Diaspora have been in place for some years, during which time my Department has been providing assistance and support to Irish people overseas through the Emigrant Support Programme, as well as establishing and coordinating the Global Irish Network and hosting successive meetings of the Global Irish Economic Forum to enhance engagement with senior Irish business figures overseas. </p><p>  As I noted at the Global Irish Economic Forum in October, however, the face of emigration has changed. Recent years have seen a wave of new, young and largely skilled emigrants heading to new destinations as well as the more traditional ones. No matter where they go, or why, they still face challenges. So while continuing to support the older generation of emigrants, we also need to identify ways of better engaging with the younger generation. We would hope that these young people will, in the future, bring the experience they gained overseas back home to Ireland and we must examine how best to facilitate their return. </p><p>  In that context, the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade will this year carry out a comprehensive review of our Diaspora Policy to examine all elements of our engagement with the Irish abroad.  The review will build upon the success of the Global Irish Network and the Emigrant Support Programme, address the legacy of the Gathering and the needs and potential of both long-standing and new emigrants.  </p><p>  Consultations as part of the review will be wide-ranging, and will include Irish community organizations overseas, members of the Global Irish Network and other business figures, academia, as well as other Government Departments and bodies.</p><p>  The consultation process will begin in the coming weeks and conclusions of the review will be finalized by the mid-point of this year. I will keep my Oireachtas colleagues informed of progress on the review and the implementation of any recommendations.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.100" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600052#WRB01350">Consultancy Contracts Data</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.101.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1037" speakername="Se&aacute;n Crowe" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600052#WRB01400"><p><i>42.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade if he will provide in tabular form a list of all professional fees, including but not limited to legal, consultancy, IT-related, advisory, capital, advertising and accountancy, charged to his Department and agencies under the aegis of his Department, detailing the company name and the amount invoiced between 1 May 2011 and 31 December 2013.  <b>[1946/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.102.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/951" speakername="Eamon Gilmore" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600052#WRB01500"><p>My Department engages a range of external service providers in a number of areas where the required skills are not available in-house and it is more cost-effective to source them externally.  Details of payments in respect of the areas specified by the Deputy for the period in question are set out in the tables below in respect Vote 28 (Foreign Affairs and Trade) and of Vote 27 (International Cooperation).  The list of service providers also includes a number of other professional services such as advertising, interpretation and translation (including payments to the European Commission for Interpretation Services provided during the EU Presidency), language and other training, and travel booking services.</p><p>  With regard to legal services, litigation is dealt with on my Department&rsquo;s behalf by the Chief State Solicitor&rsquo;s Office and the State Claims Agency who engage lawyers to act for the Department where necessary in relation to personal injuries claims and other matters.  Legal advice on contractual and other matters arising from time to time is initially sought from the Chief State Solicitor&rsquo;s Office and/or the Office of the Attorney General, and the use of external legal advisors for such requirements is kept to a minimum. </p><p>  There are also small costs incurred on professional fees at missions abroad where advice is sought from time to time on a range of local matters.</p><p><b>Vote 28 Foreign Affairs and Trade</b><table><tr><th>Service Provider </th><th>Amount &euro;</th></tr><tr><td>A&amp;amp;O SYSTEMS &amp;amp; SERVICES IRL</td><td><div>2,695</div></td></tr><tr><td>ABRIS TRANSLATIONS</td><td><div>135</div></td></tr><tr><td>ALLIANCE FRANCAISE DE LIMERICK LTD</td><td><div>2,000</div></td></tr><tr><td>ALLIANCE FRANCAISE DUBLIN</td><td><div>17,411</div></td></tr><tr><td>AMS LTD</td><td><div>6,682</div></td></tr><tr><td>B CONNECTED LTD</td><td><div>2,886</div></td></tr><tr><td>B T IRELAND</td><td><div>1,288,002</div></td></tr><tr><td>BCT COMMUNICATIONS LTD</td><td><div>5,725</div></td></tr><tr><td>BEARING POINT</td><td><div>6,069,815</div></td></tr><tr><td>BERNADETTE NIC AN TSAOIR</td><td><div>57</div></td></tr><tr><td>BLUEWAVE TECHNOLOGY</td><td><div>14,936</div></td></tr><tr><td>BRIDGE INTERPRETING</td><td><div>4,097</div></td></tr><tr><td>BRINDLEY ADVERTISING</td><td><div>54,355</div></td></tr><tr><td>BUTLER TECHNOLOGIES</td><td><div>35,469</div></td></tr><tr><td>CARLSON WAGONLIT IRELAND LTD</td><td><div>288</div></td></tr><tr><td>CENAD</td><td><div>19,500</div></td></tr><tr><td>CENTRAL SOLUTIONS LTD</td><td><div>22,243</div></td></tr><tr><td>CIVICMEDIA LTD</td><td><div>5,166</div></td></tr><tr><td>CIVIL SERVICE LANGUAGE CTR</td><td><div>2,718</div></td></tr><tr><td>CLARE MULLIGAN CONSULTING LTD</td><td><div>600</div></td></tr><tr><td>CLARE MULLIGAN CONSULTING LTD</td><td><div>1,000</div></td></tr><tr><td>CLEAR OCEAN INTERNET SOLUTIONS</td><td><div>47,834</div></td></tr><tr><td>CMI LTD</td><td><div>950</div></td></tr><tr><td>CODEC-DSS</td><td><div>1,000</div></td></tr><tr><td>CODEC-DSS</td><td><div>2,952</div></td></tr><tr><td>COMMERCIAL MEDIA GROUP</td><td><div>395</div></td></tr><tr><td>CORE FINANCIAL SYSTEMS LTD</td><td><div>514,276</div></td></tr><tr><td>CORE INTERNATIONAL LTD.(IRL)</td><td><div>284,573</div></td></tr><tr><td>CORPORATE AUDIO VISUAL SERVICES</td><td><div>2,460</div></td></tr><tr><td>CREA LANGUES FRENCH ACCOUNT</td><td><div>7,309</div></td></tr><tr><td>CW SYSTEMS INTEGRATION</td><td><div>33,020</div></td></tr><tr><td>DATAPAC LTD</td><td><div>917</div></td></tr><tr><td>DCULS LTD</td><td><div>615</div></td></tr><tr><td>DELAP &amp;amp; WALLER</td><td><div>5,651</div></td></tr><tr><td>DIARMUID P KELLY &amp;amp; ASSOCS</td><td><div>3,630</div></td></tr><tr><td>E TEAMS (INTERNATIONAL)</td><td><div>19,636</div></td></tr><tr><td>EMCO CUMARSAID TEO</td><td><div>6,000</div></td></tr><tr><td>EN FRANCAIS</td><td><div>780</div></td></tr><tr><td>EUROPEAN ACADEMY FOR TAXES ECONOMICS &amp;amp; LAW</td><td><div>1,653</div></td></tr><tr><td>EUROPEAN COMMISSION</td><td><div>406,336</div></td></tr><tr><td>EUROPUS TEO</td><td><div>63,905</div></td></tr><tr><td>EUROTEXT TRANSLATIONS LTD</td><td><div>1,498</div></td></tr><tr><td>FENNELL PHOTOGRAPHY</td><td><div>918</div></td></tr><tr><td>FREASTAL.IE</td><td><div>4,679</div></td></tr><tr><td>FUJITSU IRELAND</td><td><div>114,435</div></td></tr><tr><td>FUSIO LTD.</td><td><div>1,457</div></td></tr><tr><td>GAELCHULTUR TEORANTA</td><td><div>12,690</div></td></tr><tr><td>GERMAN LANGUAGE CENTRE</td><td><div>1,187</div></td></tr><tr><td>GMM MEDIA LTD</td><td><div>7,211</div></td></tr><tr><td>GOETHE INSTITUTE DUBLIN</td><td><div>480</div></td></tr><tr><td>HIGH PERFORMANCE</td><td><div>15,265</div></td></tr><tr><td>ICC INFORMATION LTD</td><td><div>258</div></td></tr><tr><td>ICS SKILLS TRAINING &amp;amp; CERTIFICATION</td><td><div>16,810</div></td></tr><tr><td>INDEPENDENT COLLEGES</td><td><div>295</div></td></tr><tr><td>INSTANT TRANSLATION</td><td><div>900</div></td></tr><tr><td>INSTITUTE FOR SECURITY &amp;amp; RESILIENCE STUDIES</td><td><div>291</div></td></tr><tr><td>INSTITUTEOFPUBLICADMINISTRATION</td><td><div>102,948</div></td></tr><tr><td>INSTITUTO CERVANTES</td><td><div>6,263</div></td></tr><tr><td>INTEGRITY SOLUTIONS LTD</td><td><div>336,348</div></td></tr><tr><td>IRIS OIFIGIUIL</td><td><div>1,724</div></td></tr><tr><td>IRISH MANAGEMENT INSTITUTE</td><td><div>5,000</div></td></tr><tr><td>ISAS</td><td><div>743,981</div></td></tr><tr><td>IT ROLLOUT CONSULTANCY</td><td><div>406,402</div></td></tr><tr><td>JK NETWORK ARCHITECTURE DESIGN LTD</td><td><div>931,131</div></td></tr><tr><td>KEELVAR SYSTEMS LTD</td><td><div>6,150</div></td></tr><tr><td>KEYTRAINERIRELANDLTD</td><td><div>4,450</div></td></tr><tr><td>KL COMMUNICATIONS</td><td><div>4,491</div></td></tr><tr><td>KROLL ONTRACK</td><td><div>10,032</div></td></tr><tr><td>LANGUAGES UNLIMITED SERVICES LTD</td><td><div>5,983</div></td></tr><tr><td>LENSMEN &amp;amp; ASSOCIATES</td><td><div>344</div></td></tr><tr><td>LIONBRIDGE INTERNATIONAL</td><td><div>34,870</div></td></tr><tr><td>MAC INNES PHOTOGRAPHY LTD</td><td><div>263</div></td></tr><tr><td>MAXIMA MANAGED SERVICES IRELAND</td><td><div>26,687</div></td></tr><tr><td>MAXWELL PHOTOGRAPHY</td><td><div>310</div></td></tr><tr><td>MAXWELL PHOTOGRAPHY</td><td><div>2,789</div></td></tr><tr><td>MCGRATH BARRETT &amp;amp; ASSOCIATES</td><td><div>450</div></td></tr><tr><td>MEDIATION NORTHSIDE</td><td><div>1,145</div></td></tr><tr><td>PUBLIC AFFAIRS IRELAND LTD</td><td><div>16,683</div></td></tr><tr><td>PATRICK SUTTON T/A COMMUNICATE</td><td><div>24,413</div></td></tr><tr><td>PAUL LOFTUS &amp;amp; ASSOCIATES INC</td><td><div>2,400</div></td></tr><tr><td>PEANNAIRI IRISH CALLIGRAPHERS</td><td><div>100</div></td></tr><tr><td>PITMAN TRAINING CENTRE</td><td><div>2,900</div></td></tr><tr><td>PKA TRAINING AND DEVELOPMENT</td><td><div>2,348</div></td></tr><tr><td>PRIVATE FILE</td><td><div>590</div></td></tr><tr><td>PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT LTD</td><td><div>1,393</div></td></tr><tr><td>PT CONSULTING</td><td><div>242,268</div></td></tr><tr><td>RED DOG</td><td><div>143,588</div></td></tr><tr><td>RITS</td><td><div>113,023</div></td></tr><tr><td>SABEO CONTRACTING SERVICES LTD</td><td><div>10,375</div></td></tr><tr><td>SAGEM IDENTIFICATION</td><td><div>763,965</div></td></tr><tr><td>SANDFORD LANGUAGE INST. LTD.</td><td><div>15,537</div></td></tr><tr><td>SCHOOL OF ORIENTAL &amp;amp; AFRICAN STUDIES</td><td><div>72,316</div></td></tr><tr><td>SEAN DE FREINE</td><td><div>4,118</div></td></tr><tr><td>SECOND LANGUAGE TESTING FOUNDATION INC</td><td><div>210</div></td></tr><tr><td>SELECTION BY DESIGN LTD</td><td><div>775</div></td></tr><tr><td>SL GRAPHICS LTD</td><td><div>3,850</div></td></tr><tr><td>SMART LICENCE LTD</td><td><div>23,616</div></td></tr><tr><td>SOFTWARE ONE UK LTD</td><td><div>13,442</div></td></tr><tr><td>SOFTWORKS COMPUTING Ltd</td><td><div>100,170</div></td></tr><tr><td>SURESKILLS</td><td><div>26,070</div></td></tr><tr><td>TERMINAL FOUR SOLUTIONS LTD</td><td><div>108,388</div></td></tr><tr><td>THE COMMUNICATIONS CLINIC</td><td><div>5,400</div></td></tr><tr><td>THE SIMULTANEOUS TRANSLATION CO </td><td><div>16,421</div></td></tr><tr><td>TIGER CONSULTING</td><td><div>43,650</div></td></tr><tr><td>TOMORROWS WORLD LTD</td><td><div>792,529</div></td></tr><tr><td>TONY TAAFFE</td><td><div>3,850</div></td></tr><tr><td>WORD PERFECT TRANSLATION SERVICES LTD</td><td><div>1,805</div></td></tr><tr><td>WORLDREACH SOFTWARE CORPORATION</td><td><div>14,037</div></td></tr><tr><td>WORLDREACH SOFTWARE CORPORATION</td><td><div>161,471</div></td></tr><tr><td>WRIGHT CONSULTANCY</td><td><div>47,550</div></td></tr><tr><td>ZERO DOWNTIME LTD</td><td><div>364,555</div></td></tr><tr><td>ZINOPY</td><td><div>63,456</div></td></tr></table></p><p><b>Vote 27 International Cooperation</b><table><tr><th>Service Provider </th><th>Amount &euro;</th></tr><tr><td>Carlson Wagonlit Ireland</td><td><div>           31,168 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Club Travel Ltd</td><td><div>           30,983 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Core Financial Systems</td><td><div>             2,113 </div></td></tr><tr><td>DTalk   Kimmage Manor</td><td><div>             1,500 </div></td></tr><tr><td>International Human Rights Network</td><td><div>             1,675 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Paula Ni Shlatarra</td><td><div>                665 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Ana Bela</td><td><div>                676 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Abairtin Teo - T/A Europus</td><td><div>                830 </div></td></tr><tr><td>SDL Global Solutions (Ireland) Limited</td><td><div>                148 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Word Perfect Translations Ltd</td><td><div>             1,953 </div></td></tr><tr><td>ISAS Information Security &amp;amp; Assurance Service</td><td><div>             2,490 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Core Financial Systems</td><td><div>        435,613 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Equiniti ICS Limited</td><td><div>           71,672 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Actra  Advisers Limited</td><td><div>           21,811 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Astec Global Consultancy Limited</td><td><div>           41,881 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Mary Brady</td><td><div>           25,643 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Caroline Burke</td><td><div>             3,000 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Gerald Cawley</td><td><div>             5,815 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Mary Corbett</td><td><div>           40,492 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Anne-Maire Cunningham</td><td><div>             9,424 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Vicky Dillon</td><td><div>           82,371 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Marie T Fanning</td><td><div>             1,500 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Kevin Farrell</td><td><div>           18,730 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Dr Margaret Fitzgerald</td><td><div>             8,140 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Fitzpatrick Associates</td><td><div>           41,246 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Nicholas Freeland</td><td><div>             6,642 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Cathy Gaynor</td><td><div>           15,706 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Marcel Grogan</td><td><div>           53,660 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Bronagh Hynes Karen McMinn</td><td><div>           18,389 </div></td></tr><tr><td>ITAD Ltd</td><td><div>        147,442 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Grace Kelly Hartnett</td><td><div>           15,600 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Jim Kinsella</td><td><div>             6,300 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Nogugu  Mafu</td><td><div>             8,800 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Hunter McGill</td><td><div>           12,394 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Bernard Mcloughlin</td><td><div>             5,043 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Stefanie Meredith</td><td><div>             8,621 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Mokoro Ltd</td><td><div>        124,690 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Kevin Moore</td><td><div>             5,507 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Una Murray T/A Nua Consulting</td><td><div>           12,500 </div></td></tr><tr><td>NUI Galway</td><td><div>           15,730 </div></td></tr><tr><td>NUI Maynooth Central Account</td><td><div>           42,565 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Mairtin O Fainin</td><td><div>             3,800 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Prof Helen O'Neill</td><td><div>             4,675 </div></td></tr><tr><td>International Organisation Dev</td><td><div>        180,982 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Pieternella Pieterse</td><td><div>             2,000 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Pat McMullin</td><td><div>             7,650 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Philip Regan</td><td><div>             6,704 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Rodney Rice</td><td><div>           12,300 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Samia Saad</td><td><div>             8,621 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Aisling Swaine Consultancy Ltd</td><td><div>           17,798 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Tony Taaffe</td><td><div>           25,350 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Ronan Tierney</td><td><div>           13,758 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Emma Warwick</td><td><div>        107,315 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Mike Williams</td><td><div>           20,328 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Bernard Wood + Associates Ltd</td><td><div>             9,316 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Chartered Institute of  Internal Auditors</td><td><div>           22,755 </div></td></tr><tr><td>Annemarie Cunningham</td><td><div>             7,093 </div></td></tr></table></p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.103" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600052#WRB01550">Departmental Bodies</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.104.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1106" speakername="Simon Harris" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600052#WRB01600"><p><i>43.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade the number of quangos, State agencies or organisations under the remit of his Department that have been merged, reformed or abolished since 2011; the details of each of these measures in tabular form; the cost saving or service delivery improvement which has resulted; how many more he expects to be merged, reformed or abolished and the timeline for same; if he will provide a full list of all agencies and organisations under his remit; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[1978/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.105.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/951" speakername="Eamon Gilmore" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600052#WRB01700"><p>There are no state agencies or other organisations of the type referred to by the Deputy under the aegis of my Department. </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.106" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600052#WRB01750">Undocumented Irish in the USA</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.107.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1049" speakername="Michael Healy-Rae" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600052#WRB01800"><p><i>44.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade the progress that is hoped to be made in 2014 regarding the undocumented Irish in the USA; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[1986/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.108.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/951" speakername="Eamon Gilmore" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600052#WRB01900"><p>This is an issue to which I accord very high priority. I am conscious of the difficulties experienced by Irish citizens who are undocumented in the United States, and I have met and spoken with many of them on my working visits there, and also with the various groups who lobby on their behalf.</p><p>  I have maintained contact, both directly and through our Embassy in Washington, with many key players in Congress who are influential in steering the process of US immigration reform.  Over the last four months, both the Embassy and I have had direct contact with some 70 Members of the House of Representatives and their staff.   These have included Republican Congressman Paul Ryan, Chair of the House Budgetary Committee and former Vice-Presidential nominee; Republican Congressman Bob Goodlatte, Chair of the House Judiciary Committee and several other leading Republican members of that Committee, including Immigration Sub-Committee Chairman Trey Gowdy; Minority House Leader Nancy Pelosi;  Chair of the Congressional Friends of Ireland, Pete King; with House Speaker John Boehner and House Majority Whip Kevin McCarthy and their staffs.   I have also maintained contact with key figures in the US Administration and with Irish-American community representatives. </p><p>  I have reiterated throughout all these contacts the Government&rsquo;s interest in all aspects of immigration reform and in particular our interest in seeing an overall agreement reached which provides relief for currently undocumented Irish migrants and a facility for future flows of legal migration between Ireland and the US.  </p><p>  In this context, we very much welcomed the US Senate&rsquo;s approval of the Border Security, Economic Opportunity and Immigration Modernization Bill by a 68-32 margin on 27 June last year.    </p><p>  The comprehensive draft legislation, which was prepared over several months by a bipartisan group of eight US Senators, provides for extensive reform of the US immigration system. It includes provisions that would legalise the status of undocumented Irish people and provide a path to permanent residency.  It also provides for future flows of legal migration between Ireland and the US via the proposed E-3 visa. </p><p>  The focus has since shifted to the House of Representatives for its consideration of the issues and a key factor here remains convincing the Republican House Majority of the importance of making progress.     It remains to be seen whether a consolidated Bill can be agreed between the Senate and the House of Representatives.   It is generally accepted that securing overall agreement will be a complex and challenging process, also in light of other issues on the Congressional agenda which may be unrelated but can impact negatively on efforts to secure the necessary bipartisan agreement.    The next window of opportunity for any movement on immigration reform is expected to arise during the first months of this year but the exact shape and form of such movement remains to be seen.   The most recent development has been the announcement last week by Speaker Boehner that he is preparing to release a set of &ldquo;principles&rdquo; and &ldquo;standards&rdquo; to guide the House Republican side&rsquo;s consideration of immigration reform.    These are expected to become available in the coming weeks.      </p><p>  I am determined to continue to deploy all necessary resources at political, diplomatic and Irish community level to make progress on this vital issue.   In support of this ongoing effort, a delegation of the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs and Trade visited Washington DC in October last for a programme arranged by our Embassy during which they met with key members of Congress and with Irish-American community representatives.    More recently, I wrote to US House of Representatives Speaker John Boehner on 12 December last, reiterating our position and underlining our continuing strong interest in the prospect of reform of the US immigration system. I expressed the hope that the House will engage further in these issues in early 2014 leading to a positive legislative outcome.    The Government will continue to raise this issue with high-level political contacts in the period ahead, particularly during the St Patrick&rsquo;s Day period in Washington DC. </p><p>  In addition, the Embassy in Washington continues our intensive follow-up work with all of our contacts on Capitol Hill and particularly with the Republican House leadership.   It also continues to coordinate our lobbying efforts with our Irish-American community representatives.   I wish to acknowledge the critically important role being played by these community organisations, including the Ancient Order of Hibernians, the Chicago Celts for Immigration Reform and the Irish Lobby for Immigration Reform.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.109" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600052#WRB01950">Departmental Expenditure</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.110.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1091" speakername="John Deasy" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600052#WRB02000"><p><i>45.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade if he will provide details of each allocation from his Department&rsquo;s expenditure budget to registered charities in each of the past three years. <b>[2102/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.111.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/951" speakername="Eamon Gilmore" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600052#WRB02100"><p>My Department is responsible for two Votes &ndash; Vote 28: Foreign Affairs and Trade, and Vote 27: International Cooperation. <font color="#004080"> </font>  The Government&rsquo;s international aid programme, Irish Aid, which is managed by my Department, is recognised internationally for its effectiveness in improving the lives of the poorest and most vulnerable communities. </p><p>  About a quarter of Ireland&rsquo;s overseas development assistance is channelled through development Non-Governmental Organisations (NGOs).  This reflects the strong contribution which NGOs are making to the fight against world poverty and hunger, and the broad support which they continue to receive from the Irish public.  Funding is provided to support the long-term development work carried out by NGOs in developing countries, as well as emergency humanitarian assistance and development education programmes.</p><p>  Funding is provided to partner organisations following a rigorous appraisal process by Irish Aid.  Funding applicants must meet strict and transparent criteria, have clearly identified, specific objectives, and have a record of demonstrable results indicating a sustainable and positive impact in improving the lives of some of the world&rsquo;s poorest communities. </p><p>The statistical annexes to the Irish Aid Annual Report provide detailed analysis of Ireland&rsquo;s ODA, across a range of metrics, including details of funding to non-governmental and civil society organisations.  Statistical analysis of funding to NGOs in 2013 is currently being compiled and will be published in the middle of 2014.  This will be on the lines of the details provided in the Annual Report for 2012, which included a breakdown of funding to NGOs and civil society organisations, across all funding schemes operated by Irish Aid, above a grant threshold of &euro;50,000.  For 2011, the Annual Report provided information on funding to NGOs through the main civil society funding schemes operated by Irish Aid at headquarters level.   The Annual Reports are available on the Irish Aid website, at   .</p><p>  My Department provides funding for the Ireland-United States Commission for Educational Exchange (the Fulbright Commission), which is a registered charity, on an annual basis. The Commission was established by the Educational Exchange (Ireland and the United States of America) Act, 1991 to facilitate the administration of educational and cultural exchanges between Ireland and the United States of America. The Act provides that the Commission be for charitable purposes only within the meaning of section 333 of the Income Tax Act, 1967. The members of the Commission are nominated by the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade and by the U.S. Ambassador to Ireland. Funding provided to the Commission in each of the past three years was as follows: 2011: &euro;254,000, 2012: &euro;254,000 and 2013: &euro;254,000</p><p>In addition, my Department&rsquo;s <b>Emigrant Support Programme</b>   (ESP) provides funding to non-profit organisations and projects to support Irish communities overseas and to facilitate the development of more strategic links between Ireland and the global Irish. Applicant organizations to the ESP should be established as registered charities, charitable bodies or voluntary/not for profit organizations.  </p><p>While the vast majority of funding under the Emigrant Support Programme (ESP) is provided to organisations overseas, almost 12% of the budget is allocated to Irish based organisations. Recipient organisations here are typically active in providing services to returning or departing Irish emigrants or in promoting Irish heritage and sport abroad. Organisations receiving grants under the ESP are required to submit a financial report for each programme funded and financial accounts or audited financial statement. Full details of all funding provided by the Emigrant Support Programme can be found here: </p><p>  In addition, my Department manages a small budget aimed at supporting projects linked to DFAT&rsquo;s commitment to international peace, security and human rights. This funding is designed to complement and support Ireland&rsquo;s priorities in relation to the Common Foreign and Security Policy (CFSP). The discretionary funding available to support such activities is approximately &euro;300,000 per annum, the bulk of which is made up of payments to the UN and other international organisations. However, funding is also provided to support a number of projects managed by international civil society organisations, in areas such as human rights, conflict resolution and disarmament, and non-proliferation activities. A summary of the relevant expenditure over the last three years is set out below.</p><p><b><i>2011:</i></b><table><tr><th>Organisation Name</th><th>Policy Area</th><th>Amount (&euro;)</th></tr><tr><td>International Action Network on Small Arms</td><td>Disarmament &amp;amp; Non-Proliferation</td><td>10,000</td></tr><tr><td>Seibersdorf Analytical Laboratories</td><td>Disarmament &amp;amp; Non-Proliferation</td><td>10,000</td></tr><tr><td>Institute for Security and Democracy</td><td>Conflict Resolution</td><td>50,000</td></tr><tr><td>TOTAL</td><td></td><td>&euro;70,000</td></tr></table></p><p><b><i>2012</i></b><table><tr><th>Organisation Name</th><th>Policy Area</th><th>Amount (&euro;)</th></tr><tr><td>Eastern Europe Studies Centre</td><td>Human Rights</td><td>2,065</td></tr><tr><td>Equis: Justicia para las mujeres </td><td>Human Rights</td><td>10,000</td></tr><tr><td>TOTAL</td><td></td><td>&euro;12,065</td></tr></table></p><p><b><i>2013</i></b><table><tr><th>Organisation Name</th><th>Policy Area</th><th>Amount (&euro;)</th></tr><tr><td>Femmes Africa Solidarite</td><td>Conflict Resolution</td><td>33,000</td></tr><tr><td>Atomic Reporters</td><td>Disarmament &amp;amp; Non-Proliferation </td><td>10,000</td></tr><tr><td>Geneva International Centre for Humanitarian Demining</td><td>Disarmament &amp;amp; Non-Proliferation</td><td>20,000</td></tr><tr><td>Gmedia Center</td><td>Human Rights</td><td>19,000</td></tr><tr><td>International Service for Human Rights (ISHR)</td><td>Human Rights</td><td>17,800</td></tr><tr><td>Eastern Europe Studies Centre</td><td>Human Rights</td><td>2,200</td></tr><tr><td>Centre for Equality Advancement</td><td>Human Rights</td><td>1,220</td></tr><tr><td>Auschwitz-Birkenau Foundation</td><td>Human Rights</td><td>5,000</td></tr><tr><td>Equis: Justicia para las mujeres </td><td>Human Rights</td><td>10,000</td></tr><tr><td>Network on Small Arms</td><td>Disarmament &amp;amp; Non-Proliferation</td><td>15,000</td></tr><tr><td>TOTAL</td><td></td><td>133,220</td></tr></table></p><p>Through the <b>Reconciliation and Anti-Sectarianism Funds</b>  , which support community development and outreach in Northern Ireland and the border counties, cross-border co-operation and sensitive commemorative and cultural events, my Department has awarded a total of &euro;8,383,797 in the past three years (2011-2013 inclusive).  A table of all organisations that have been awarded funding is set out below.  Funding is awarded for project costs primarily. There are mechanisms for annual reporting and accounting by recipient organisations. Organisations in receipt of grants of &euro;10,000 and above are required to submit a tax clearance certificate from the Revenue Commissioners and those in receipt of grants of &euro;12,500 and above are required to submit independently audited accounts.</p><p>  Additional table to follow by e-mail as lotus will not accept.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.112" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600052#WRB02150">Passport Applications</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.113.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/957" speakername="Bernard Durkan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600052#WRB02200"><p><i>46.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade if and when passport will issue in the case of a person (details supplied) in Dublin 24; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2165/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.114.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/951" speakername="Eamon Gilmore" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600052#WRB02300"><p>All passport applications are subject to the provision of the Passports Act, 2008 (the Act). The issue of a passport is, therefore, the culmination of an important and legally-binding process.  The checks and balances within the passport process embrace the standard principles that are provided for in the Act and help to ensure that the identity of the applicant is known and that the person in question is an Irish citizen.  This serves to maintain the worldwide good reputation and integrity of the Irish passport, which, in turn, ensures the safe travel and wellbeing of Irish citizens, as they travel abroad.  Moreover, it helps to combat passport and identity fraud. </p><p>  The person concerned was born in Dublin on 21 February 2013.  His application for an Irish passport would, therefore, be made under the provisions of the Irish Nationality and Citizenship Act, 2004 (the Act).  The Act provides that persons born in the State on or after 1 January 2005, where neither parent is an Irish or British citizen or otherwise entitled to reside in the State or Northern Ireland without restriction, may claim citizenship by birth in the State (and thereby establish eligibility for a passport) only where a parent has been lawfully resident in the State for three of the four years preceding their birth.</p><p>  The Department assesses such passport applications in line with guidelines provided by the Department of Justice and Equality, which is the Department responsible for immigration and citizenship.  </p><p>  The Passport Service received an application from the person in question on 26 March, 2013.  In order to make a decision on the application, the Passport Service has had ongoing correspondence with the Department of Justice and Equality on the matter of lawful residence in the State.  The Passport Service is now in a position to issue a passport in this case.  The passport will issue on Thursday 16/01/2014. </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.115" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600052#WRB02350">Irish Language Issues</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.116.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1044" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600052#WRB02400"><p><i>47.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade the estimated number and percentage of civil servants who are competent to carry out their duties through the medium of Irish and English in his Department; his views on whether this number is adequate; his plans to increase this number and percentage; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2629/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.117.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/951" speakername="Eamon Gilmore" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600052#WRB02500"><p>My Department fully supports the measures to support Irish language proficiency in the civil service which were approved recently by Government and is committed to providing services and answering correspondence through Irish whenever required.  A skills audit of all staff carried out in 2012 revealed that 55 staff members in my Department had advanced or fluent Irish language skills while a further 160 officers declared that their Irish language skills were at an intermediate level.  In total, this is approximately 20% of permanent HQ-based staff.</p><p>  Irish Language Classes are regularly provided in-house in my Department and, from 2010 to 2013, over 200 officers registered to attend these classes. Tailored, in-house Irish language classes are currently available in our Passport Office in Cork and will shortly be available in the Passport Office in Molesworth Street. Officers are also encouraged to develop their Irish language skills in their own time and my Department is happy to support and fund this.</p></reply>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.119" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600052#WRB02600">Department of Finance</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.118" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600052#WRB02550">Consultancy Contracts Data</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.119.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/959" speakername="Pearse Doherty" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600052#WRB02600"><p><i>48.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance the number of consultants or consultancy firms employed by his Department during each of the past five years; the purpose and duration of each of these consultancies or consultancy contracts; the names of the consultants or firms. <b>[1818/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.120.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600052#WRB02700"><p>The information requested by the Deputy is set out in the following table:<table><tr><th>Name of Consultant/Consultancy Firm</th><th>Year</th><th>Purpose</th></tr><tr><td>Stratathree</td><td>2013-2014</td><td>Website development for Medium Term Economic Strategy (MTES)</td></tr><tr><td>A &amp;amp; L Goodbody Solicitors</td><td>2013</td><td>Company secretarial work for Seal&uacute;chais &Aacute;rachais Teoranta (SAT)</td></tr><tr><td>Arthur Cox</td><td>2013</td><td>Legal advice on restructuring of Irish Banking System, related litigation, further emerging issues</td></tr><tr><td>Creative A.D. Ltd</td><td>2013</td><td>Graphic design for Budget Day publications: Report of the Review of the R&amp;amp;D Tax Credit and the International Tax Strategy</td></tr><tr><td>Crowe Horwath</td><td>2013</td><td>Independent survey of R&amp;amp;D Active firms for the 2013 Review of the R&amp;amp;D Tax Credit</td></tr><tr><td>Dr. Anil Shivdasani</td><td>2013</td><td>Expert Witness for High Court case</td></tr><tr><td>Economic &amp;amp; Social Research Institute (ESRI)</td><td>2013</td><td>Modelling Support - MTES</td></tr><tr><td>Economic &amp;amp; Social Research Institute (ESRI)</td><td>2013</td><td>MTES - Spatial development principles</td></tr><tr><td>Indecon</td><td>2013</td><td>Independent cost benefit analysis of Living City Initiative</td></tr><tr><td>Matheson</td><td>2013</td><td>Legal advice regarding the acquisition and sale of Irish Life and related matters</td></tr><tr><td>Mercer (Ireland) Ltd</td><td>2013</td><td>Review of Remuneration Practices &amp;amp; Frameworks at the Covered Institutions . This was a once off consultancy.</td></tr><tr><td>National Asset Management Agency</td><td>2013</td><td>National Asset Management Agency (NAMA) Ministerial Advisory Group</td></tr><tr><td>PMCA Economic Consulting</td><td>2013</td><td>Modelling Support - MTES</td></tr><tr><td>RED C Research &amp;amp; Marketing Lim</td><td>2013</td><td>Professional services in relation to the SME Lending Survey</td></tr><tr><td>Arthur Cox</td><td>2012</td><td>Ongoing legal advice on restructuring of Irish Banking System, related litigation, further emerging issues and issues related to development of proposals with Troika</td></tr><tr><td>A &amp;amp; L Goodbody Solicitors</td><td>2012</td><td>Company secretarial work for SAT</td></tr><tr><td>BDO and Amarach</td><td>2012</td><td>Reports on film industry (a) Survey of audio-visual producers (b) Review on international review of audio-visual state supports</td></tr><tr><td>Deloitte &amp;amp; Touche</td><td>2012</td><td>External Review of General Government Debt (GGD) error</td></tr><tr><td>Mazars</td><td>2012</td><td>Professional services in relation to the SME Lending Survey</td></tr><tr><td>Matheson Orsmby Solicitors</td><td>2012</td><td>Legal advice regarding the acquisition and sale of Irish Life and related matters.</td></tr><tr><td>McCann Fitzgerald</td><td>2012</td><td>Bankruptcy/Personal Insolvency Reform</td></tr><tr><td>Thomas J. Foley</td><td>2012</td><td>Consultancy Services (Mortgage Arrears/Personal Insolvency Project)</td></tr><tr><td>Aram International Partners LL</td><td>2011</td><td>Advices in relation to Framework Development - Mortgage Arrears</td></tr><tr><td>Arthur Cox</td><td>2011</td><td>Legal advice in relation to the Bank Guarantee Scheme; redundancies and remuneration issues and general banking advice.</td></tr><tr><td>Charles River Associates</td><td>2011</td><td>Advice on competitions and mergers</td></tr><tr><td>David Barneville</td><td>2011</td><td>Competition and State aid advisors</td></tr><tr><td>Mazars</td><td>2011</td><td>Professional advice in relation to SME lending surveys</td></tr><tr><td>McCann Fitzgerald</td><td>2011</td><td>Bankruptcy/Personal Insolvency Reform</td></tr><tr><td>Niamh Hyland</td><td>2011</td><td>Competition and State aid advisors</td></tr><tr><td>Arthur Cox</td><td>2010</td><td>Legal advice in relation to the Bank Guarantee Scheme; Eligible Liabilities Guarantee (ELG), recapitalisation and restructuring issues; general banking advice.</td></tr><tr><td>Paul O'Higgins SC</td><td>2010</td><td>Independently appointed by the Banking Inquiry</td></tr><tr><td>Price Waterhouse Coopers</td><td>2010</td><td>Accounting advice on promissory notes to Anglo Irish Bank and Irish Nationwide Building Society</td></tr><tr><td>Arthur Cox</td><td>2009</td><td>Legal advice in relation to the Bank Guarantee Scheme; ELG, recapitalisation and restructuring issues; general banking advice</td></tr><tr><td>Carr Communication Ltd.</td><td>2009</td><td>Editorial and design service in preparation of the Report of the Commission on Taxation </td></tr><tr><td>Economic and Social  Research Institute  (ERSI)</td><td>2009</td><td>Economic and social policy on various proposals considered by the Commission on Taxation and on the overall economic impact of the Report s approach. In addition, some detailed advice received on technical issues, including SWITCH amd Hermes model analysis</td></tr><tr><td>Hay Group Consulting</td><td>2009</td><td>Advice to Covered Institutions Remuneration Oversight Committee ( CIROC) in relation to Banking Remuneration</td></tr><tr><td>Life Strategies Limited</td><td>2009</td><td>Parallel Benchmarking of Pensions</td></tr><tr><td>Mercer (Ireland) Ltd</td><td>2009</td><td>Advice to CIROC in relation to Human Capital.</td></tr><tr><td>Watson Wyatt (Ireland) Limited</td><td>2009</td><td>Advice to CIROC in relation to the Executive Compensation market</td></tr><tr><td>Total number of consultancy projects</td><td>39</td><td></td></tr><tr><td>Total number of consultancy firms</td><td>30</td><td></td></tr></table></p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.122" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600053#WRC00150">Credit Unions Mergers</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.123.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1182" speakername="Terence Flanagan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600053#WRC00200"><p><i>49.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance if he will provide a breakdown of the third party costs involved in a merger (details supplied); and if he will make a statement on the matter.  <b>[1822/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.124.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600053#WRC00300"><p>I have been informed by the Central Bank that in order to facilitate Naas Credit Union&rsquo;s consideration of a proposed merger with Newbridge Credit Union, the Central Bank agreed to cover the transaction adviser costs incurred by Naas Credit Union on a capped basis.</p><p>  On 22 November 2013, the Central Bank paid &euro;750,422 to cover the cost of transaction advisers incurred by Naas Credit Union in relation to the proposed merger. The &euro;750,422 costs are split as follows:</p><p> - &euro;224,993 for legal advisers</p><p> - &euro;288,264 for accounting and financial advisers</p><p> - &euro;237,165 for other advisers (comprising Property, Public Relations, Project Management, IT, HR and Business Consultants).</p><p>  These costs were agreed by the Central Bank and paid for from the Central Bank&rsquo;s own resources. These costs were not chargeable to the Credit Union Resolution Fund and there will not be scope for recoupment through levies by the Central Bank.</p><p>  Naas Credit Union requested payment for a further &euro;25,341 in adviser costs on 8 January 2014 (legal advisers &euro;19,452 and other advisers &euro;5,889) within the permitted cap. The Central Bank is currently reviewing whether or not these costs are in line with the cost recovery arrangements.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.125" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600053#WRC00350">Departmental Expenditure</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.126.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1057" speakername="Niall Collins" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600053#WRC00400"><p><i>50.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance if he will detail, in tabular form, the total photography costs for his Department since coming to office inclusive of costs incurred from use of the ministerial allowance; the list of occasions for which photographers were booked; the photographers used; the breakdown of costs associated with each occasion that a photographer was used; if there is a policy regarding the booking of photographers within his Department; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[1851/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.127.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600053#WRC00500"><p>In response to the Deputy&rsquo;s question the following table gives details of the costs of engaging photographers since march 2011. When booking photographers my Department follow  public procurement guidelines.</p><p><b><i>Use of Photographer </i></b><table><tr><th><b>Company used</b></th><th><b>Details</b></th><th><b>Cost &euro;</b></th></tr><tr><td>Maxwell Photography Ltd</td><td>Brian Lenihan - photo required for Minster&rsquo;s Conference -  Engaged on 30th March 2011<font color="#000080">   </font></td><td>&euro;424.41    </td></tr><tr><td>Maxwell Photography Ltd</td><td>Signing of Taxation agreement with Germany &ndash; Minister Noonan &amp;amp; German Ambassador - Engaged on 31st March 2011        </td><td>&euro;400.21</td></tr><tr><td>Maxwell Photography Ltd</td><td>Signing ceremony for Double Taxation Agreement with Uzbekistan  - Minister of State Hayes &amp;amp; The Chairman of State Taxation Committee of Uzbekistan - Engaged July 2012</td><td>&euro;147.60</td></tr><tr><td>Maxwell Photography Ltd</td><td>Signing ceremony for Double Taxation Agreement with Switzerland &ndash; Minister of State Hayes &amp;amp; Swiss Ambassador- Engaged 26th January 2012</td><td>&euro;285.05</td></tr></table></p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.128" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600053#WRC00550">Public Relations Contracts Data</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.129.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1057" speakername="Niall Collins" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600053#WRC00600"><p><i>51.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance if he will detail, in tabular form, the use of external public relations firms employed by his Department since coming to office; the list of uses of the external public relations firm; his internal Department policy regarding employing external groups; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[1866/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.130.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600053#WRC00700"><p>I take it that the Deputy is referring solely to public relations services and not to advertising costs that would be incurred by my Department in the normal course of business, such as entries into telephone directories, the placing of advertisements in national newspapers, recruitment advertising, etc.</p><p>  No such costs have been incurred in respect of my Department in the period since I came into office.</p><p>  The Department&rsquo;s policy regarding employing external groups is to follow the general public procurement rules and in particular the guidance as set out in the &quot;Guidance Note on engaging Advertising, Public Relations and Creative Design Services&quot; and the &quot;Guidelines for the Engagement of Consultants and Other External Support by The Civil Service&quot;.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.131" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600053#WRC00750">Tax Yield</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.132.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/969" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600053#WRC00800"><p><i>52.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance the total number of deposit-savings accounts on which DIRT tax was paid in each year from 2010-2012; and if he will make a statement on the matter.  <b>[1894/14]</b></p></ques>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.133.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/969" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600053#WRC00900"><p><i>53.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance the average payment of DIRT tax per deposit to savings accounts in each year from 2010-2012; and if he will make a statement on the matter.  <b>[1895/14]</b></p></ques>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.134.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/969" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600053#WRC01000"><p><i>54.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance if he will provide in a tabular form the number of deposit-savings accounts yielding less than &euro;50 in DIRT tax; the number yielding between &euro;50 and &euro;100; the number yielding between &euro;101 and &euro;200; the number yielding between &euro;201 and &euro;500; the number yielding between &euro;501 and &euro;1000; the number yielding over &euro;1000 in 2012; and if he will make a statement on the matter.  <b>[1896/14]</b></p></ques>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.135.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/969" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600053#WRC01100"><p><i>55.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance if he will provide in a tabular form a breakdown of the &euro;580m raised from DIRT tax in 2012; the overall revenue raised from accounts yielding less than &euro;50 in DIRT tax; the overall revenue from accounts yielding between &euro;50-&euro;100; the overall revenue from accounts yielding between &euro;101-&euro;200; the overall revenue from accounts yielding between &euro;201-&euro;500; the overall revenue from accounts yielding between &euro;501-&euro;1000; the overall revenue from accounts yielding over &euro;1000 in 2012; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[1897/14]</b></p></ques>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.136.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/969" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600053#WRC01200"><p><i>56.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance the tax forgone as a result of the DIRT tax exemption scheme in 2010, 2011 and 2012; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[1898/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.137.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600053#WRC01300"><p>I propose to take Questions Nos. 52 to 56, inclusive, together.</p><p>  The amount of Deposit Interest Retention Tax (DIRT) collected by the State in the most recent tax year (2013) is &euro;499.5 million approximately.  I am advised by the Revenue Commissioners that DIRT on interest bearing deposits is returned on a four-times yearly basis by financial institutions: in April, July and October of the tax year in question and in the following January.  Returns for each year are due by 15 January of the following year and the total value of DIRT due and paid is reported to Revenue on the January returns at institutional level.  Sufficiently detailed figures are not captured in these returns to enable distributional information to be compiled by reference to deposit amounts, interest amounts or DIRT amounts.</p><p>  Separately, under regulations, as provided for in Section 891B of the Taxes Consolidation Act 1997, certain financial institutions, such as banks and credit unions, are required to make automatic annual returns at account level electronically to Revenue.  The primary purpose of this Section is to provide information for use in risk analysis by Revenue and therefore the requirement to report interest focuses on account holders in receipt of larger payments.  The information under section 891B is provided where the total payment of interest is greater than &euro;635 in a year, regardless of deduction of DIRT, and in all instances of a first interest payment irrespective of threshold for accounts opened on or after 1 January 2008.  These returns include DIRT exempt accounts.  Returns for 2010, 2011 and 2012 were due by the end of March 2011, 2012 and 2013 respectively.</p><p>  The total number of interest bearing deposit accounts reported under the regulations for 2010, 2011 and 2012 is 1,494,663, 1,428, 648 and 1,100, 991 respectively.  The total value of interest paid to these accounts for 2010, 2011 and 2012 is &euro;2.67 billion, &euro;2.37 billion and &euro;2.01 billion respectively.  Financial institutions reported 202,807, 188,915 and 170,085 such accounts as being exempt from DIRT for 2010, 2011 and 2012 respectively but data on the amount of DIRT forgone in respect of such accounts is not available.</p><p>I am also advised by the Revenue Commissioners that the information provided under the<b></b>  Section 891B regulations does not include information on the amounts of deposits or linking deposits with DIRT amounts. It is also important to note the information received under Section 891B is not limited to individuals but also includes interest payments on accounts held by corporations and other entities. </p><p>  The Deputy may, however, be interested in a breakdown of the number of accounts for 2010, 2011 and 2012 by reference to ranges of interest amounts. A table with this information is as follows. It should be noted that financial institutions report each party to an account where the account is a Joint Account. This could mean that a joint account is included more than once (i.e., for each of the parties).<table><tr><th><b>Range of Interest Reported (&euro;)</b></th><th><b>Number of Records Reported</b></th><th>-</th><th>-</th></tr><tr><td> -</td><td><b>2010</b></td><td><b>2011</b></td><td><b>2012</b></td></tr><tr><td>Up to 10,000</td><td>1,465,185</td><td>1,401,391</td><td>1,078,398</td></tr><tr><td>10,001 - 25,000</td><td>18,940</td><td>17,938</td><td>14,724</td></tr><tr><td>25,001 - 50,000</td><td>5,850</td><td>5,599</td><td>4,518</td></tr><tr><td>50,001 - 100,000</td><td>2,694</td><td>2,268</td><td>1,941</td></tr><tr><td>100,001 - 200,000</td><td>1,215</td><td>951</td><td>835</td></tr><tr><td>200,001 - 300,000</td><td>335</td><td>267</td><td>255</td></tr><tr><td>300,001 - 400,000</td><td>152</td><td>98</td><td>112</td></tr><tr><td>400,001 - 500,000</td><td>99</td><td>75</td><td>44</td></tr><tr><td>500,001 - 600,000</td><td>67</td><td>51</td><td>45</td></tr><tr><td>600,001 - 750,000</td><td>54</td><td>37</td><td>39</td></tr><tr><td>750,001 - 1,000,000</td><td>58</td><td>36</td><td>39</td></tr><tr><td>1,000,001 or greater</td><td>124</td><td>80</td><td>63</td></tr></table></p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.138" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600053#WRC01350">Home Renovation Incentive Scheme Applications</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.139.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/969" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600053#WRC01400"><p><i>57.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance the number of applications received for the home renovation incentive scheme since 25 October 2013; the number of applications approved in the same period; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[1899/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.140.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600053#WRC01500"><p>As the Deputy is aware, I announced the Home Renovation Incentive in the recent Budget. This schemecame into operation on25 October 2013 and will run until31 December 2015. Itprovides for tax relief for homeowners by way of a tax credit at 13.5% of qualifying expenditure incurred on repair, renovation or improvement work carried out on a principal private residence.</p><p>  Qualifying expenditure is expenditure subject to the 13.5% VAT rate. The work must cost a minimum of &euro;5,000 (inclusive of VAT). Where the cost of the work exceeds &euro;30,000 (exclusive of VAT) a maximum credit of &euro;4,050 will apply.The credit is payable over the two years following the year in which the work is carried out. </p><p>  The scheme will be administered through Revenue s online systems. Contractors will be required to inform Revenue in advance of details of works to be carried out and will also be required to notify Revenue in relation to any payments received in respect of the works. Homeowners will be able to view the information provided to Revenue by the contractor through the Revenue electronic systems and will also claim the relief through those systems.It is anticipated that this system will 'go live' in early April 2014. Contractors will need to enter the details of works carried out within 28 of the electronic system becoming available.</p><p>  Full details of the scheme are available on the Revenue website at    along with a newly produced  Guide for Homeowners . Copies of the Guide are being distributed to all local Revenue Offices and Citizens Advice centres.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.141" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600053#WRC01550">Irish Language Issues</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.142.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1182" speakername="Terence Flanagan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600053#WRC01600"><p><i>58.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance the reason a cheque book in the Irish language is not available from a bank (details supplied); and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[1918/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.143.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600053#WRC01700"><p>Permanent TSB has confirmed to me that it can provide cheque books in the Irish language and is happy to do so in the specific case referred to if the details of the individual customer (whose details were supplied) are provided to it. Permanent TSB has informed me that it regrets that due to the infrequency of requests for such a service some of its staff may be unaware of the availability of such a service. Permanent TSB informs me that it will now take action to ensure that this gap in its internal communications is addressed.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.144" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600053#WRC01750">Hospital Equipment</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.145.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1178" speakername="R&oacute;is&iacute;n Shortall" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600053#WRC01800"><p><i>59.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance further to Parliamentary Question No. 149 of 14 February 2013, the action that has been taken to close off this anomaly. <b>[1945/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.146.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600053#WRC01900"><p>In my reply to the previous Parliamentary Question cited by the Deputy I explained the practical difficulties in putting a value on the use by hospital consultants of public health facilities for private practice. I also indicated that the Revenue Commissioners had this situation under active consideration. </p><p>  I am advised by the Revenue Commissioners that the matter continues to be under review and the question of whether the circumstances referred to by the Deputy do indeed give rise to a benefit-in-kind charge that is capable of being applied has yet to be determined.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.147" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600053#WRC01950">European Court of Justice Rulings</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.148.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1051" speakername="Brendan Griffin" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600053#WRC02000"><p><i>60.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance if the Revenue Commissioners has finalised guidelines on a potential VAT refund for member-owned golf clubs in view of the recent European Court of Justice decision on a club (details supplied); if so, the details of same; and if he will make a statement on the matter.  <b>[1964/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.149.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600053#WRC02100"><p>I am advised by the Revenue Commissioners that the European Court of Justice issued its judgement in the Bridport &amp;amp; West Dorset Golf Club Ltd case, C-495/12, on 19 December 2013. The issue in dispute centred on Article 132(m) of the EU VAT Directive that provides exemption for the supply of certain services closely linked to sport or physical education by non-profit-making organisations to persons taking part in sport or physical education. The question before the ECJ was whether the supply of golf facilities by non-profit making organisations to non-members could also benefit from this exemption. The Court found that non-members could not be excluded from the exemption. </p><p>  Irish VAT law must comply with the EU VAT Directive and Article 132(m) is transposed in Irish VAT legislation in paragraph 3(4) of Schedule 1 to the Value-Added Tax Consolidation Act 2010, which states that the provision by non-profit making organisations of facilities for participation in sporting or physical educational activities is exempt from VAT. This exemption means that while such non-profit making organisations do not charge VAT on their supplies they have no entitlement to a credit for VAT incurred on their inputs. </p><p>  In Ireland, green fees charged by non-profit making organisations, such as member owned clubs, to visitors have been liable to VAT at 9% and such clubs have been claiming a VAT credit for inputs that relate to these visitor green fees. Revenue are currently examining the ECJ judgement and are identifying the implications, current and historic, in terms of VAT exemption and related non-allowable input credits. Revenue expects to issue guidelines for member-owned golf clubs outlining their position on the matter as soon as that examination is completed. </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.150" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600053#WRC02150">Property Taxation Data</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.151.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1015" speakername="Clare Daly" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600053#WRC02200"><p><i>61.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance the number of those in receipt of the State pension who are having the property tax deducted; and the amount per week of the &euro;1 million the Revenue Commissioners states it is receiving that is coming from the State pension payments.  <b>[1969/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.152.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600053#WRC02300"><p>I am informed by the Revenue Commissioners that owners of more than 25,000 residential properties have opted to pay their Local Property Tax (LPT) for 2014 by way of deduction at source from the various Department of Social Protection payments within the LPT scheme and almost &euro;216,000 has been collected to date in 2014, which is about &euro;108,000 per week. The Commissioners expect to be in a position to publish data which shows a breakdown of this figure among the various Department of Social Protection schemes, including the State pension in due course.</p><p>  I am advised that the deduction at source payment option has been implemented only on a voluntary basis, and there is ongoing dialogue between Revenue and the Department of Social Protection to ensure that it operates as smoothly as possible.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.154" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600054#WRD00150">Departmental Bodies</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.155.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1106" speakername="Simon Harris" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600054#WRD00200"><p><i>62.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance the number of quangos, State agencies or organisations under the remit of his Department that have been merged, reformed or abolished since 2011; the details of each of these measures in tabular form; the cost saving or service delivery improvement which has resulted; how many more he expects to be merged, reformed or abolished and the timeline for same; if he will provide a full list of all agencies and organisations under his remit; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[1977/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.156.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600054#WRD00300"><p>In response to the Deputy&rsquo;s question the attached table gives details of the bodies which come under the aegis of my Department. None of these bodies have been abolished since 2011. The Financial Services Ombudsman is under review for a merger with the Pension Ombudsman. </p><p><b><i>Bodies under the Aegis of my Department </i></b><table><tr><th>Name  of  Body </th></tr><tr><td>National Treasury Management  Agency *</td></tr><tr><td>State Claims Agency ( SCA)</td></tr><tr><td>National Pensions Reserve Fund Commission(NPRF)</td></tr><tr><td>National Development Finance Agency (NDFA)</td></tr><tr><td>NewERA (New Economy and Recovery Authority</td></tr><tr><td>Financial Services Ombudsman</td></tr><tr><td>National Asset  Management Agency</td></tr><tr><td>Irish Financial Services Appeals Tribunal </td></tr><tr><td>Credit Union Advisory Committee</td></tr><tr><td>Credit Union Restructuring Board (ReBo)</td></tr><tr><td>Central Bank Commission</td></tr><tr><td>Irish Fiscal Advisory Council</td></tr><tr><td>Disabled Drivers Medical Board of Appeal </td></tr><tr><td>Credit Review Office </td></tr><tr><td>Social  Finance Foundation </td></tr></table></p><p>  *The NTMA has taken on a range of additional functions since its establishment in 1990. The opportunity is now being taken to simplify and streamline NTMA governance structures. The approach is also in line with the Government&rsquo;s commitment in the area of the rationalisation of State bodies. </p><p>  The NTMA was set up to manage the National Debt and this will continue to be a core function. Over the years, additional activities have been awarded to the Agency and some of these were established as legal entities that were distinct from the Agency but which operated through it (i.e. the NDFA and the NPRF). The new simpler structure that is being proposed involves these activities being assigned directly to the Agency under the direction of a new over-arching Board which will be responsible to the Minister for Finance. It is proposed that the various corporate bodies and committees, including the NTMA Advisory Committee, which will no longer be required under the new structure, will be dissolved. No changes are proposed to the existing arrangements in respect of NAMA which will continue to have its own separate board.</p><p>  Legislation to affect the changes to the organisation structure of the NTMA is being prepared and I expect to be in a position to bring it before the Oireachtas in the first quarter of this year.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.157" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600054#WRD00350">Tax Credits</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.158.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1182" speakername="Terence Flanagan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600054#WRD00400"><p><i>63.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance his plans to introduce a tax credit to help parents who have to deal with high cr&egrave;che fees and after school fees; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2000/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.159.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600054#WRD00500"><p>The Government acknowledges the continuing cost pressures on parents, particularly those with young children. In recognition of these cost pressures, a number of support measures are in place to ease the burden on working parents. These include the Community Childcare Subvention (CCS) programme, which funds community childcare services to enable them to charge reduced childcare fees to qualifying parents, the Childcare Education and Training Support (CETS) programme which provides free childcare places to qualifying F&Aacute;S and VEC trainees and the Early Childhood Care and Education (ECCE) programme which provides for a free pre-school year for children in the year before commencing primary school. Generous entitlements to paid and unpaid maternity leave as well as child benefit payments are also provided. </p><p>  The Department of Social Protection provides financial support to families on low pay by way of the Family Income Supplement (FIS) and to one-parent families through the one-parent family payment. </p><p>In addition, a Single Person Child Carertax credit of &euro;1,650 is provided as well as an additional standard rate band of &euro;4,000. This credit and bandis payable to any single person with a child under 18 years of age or over 18 years of age if in full time education or permanently incapacitated. The primary claimant may relinquish this credit and<b></b>increase in the rate band to a secondary claimant with whom the child resides for not less than 100 days in the year.<b></b>  To claim the Single Person Child Carer Credit a claimant must not be married, in a civil partnership or cohabiting.</p><p>  The Universal Social Charge (USC) was introduced in Budget 2011 to replace the Income Levy and Health Levy. It was a necessary measure to widen the tax base, remove poverty traps and raise revenue to reduce the budget deficit. It is a more sustainable charge than those it replaced and is applied at a low rate on a wide base with very few exemptions. </p><p>  In Budget 2012 I announced that those earning less than &euro;10,036 would no longer be subject to the Universal Social Charge. This in itself has removed almost 330,000 individuals from the charge and is of particular benefit to the low paid.</p><p>  I have no plans to introduce any further tax reliefs for childcare costs. </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.160" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600054#WRD00550">Exchequer Deficit</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.161.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1182" speakername="Terence Flanagan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600054#WRD00600"><p><i>64.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance when he expects to achieve a balanced budget here; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2032/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.162.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600054#WRD00700"><p>In the short term, fiscal policy in Ireland will continue to be driven by our obligations under the corrective arm of the Stability and Growth Pact, namely to bring the headline deficit below 3% of GDP by 2015. Notwithstanding the legal requirement to comply with the recommendations issued as part of the excessive deficit procedure, it is imperative in its own right that we bring our deficit down to more sustainable levels. </p><p>  On the basis of the economic and fiscal projections contained in Budget 2014, as well as developments in the period since then, it is clear that we remain on track to correct our excessive deficit in a timely manner.</p><p>  Once the excessive deficit has been corrected, the public finances in Ireland will be subject to the requirements of the preventive arm of the Pact and those of the Treaty on Stability, Co-ordination and Governance (TSCG). Essentially these involve being at or adjusting sufficiently rapidly towards our (country-specific) medium term objective (MTO), which is for a balanced budget in structural terms. From 2016 onwards, therefore, the general government deficit, after adjusting for the impact of the economic cycle and one-off factors, is required to converge at a sufficiently rapid pace towards balance. </p><p>  The Medium-Term Economic Strategy, published last December, contained economic and fiscal projections covering the period 2014-2020. These projections were based on an estimate of Ireland's potential output; on the basis of these growth assumptions and continued fiscal prudence, a balanced budget is set to be achieved in 2018, in compliance with our obligations.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.163" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600054#WRD00750">Economic Data</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.164.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1182" speakername="Terence Flanagan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600054#WRD00800"><p><i>65.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance the GDP, GNP, national debt, inflation rate, national debt/GDP ratio predicted for 2014; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2033/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.165.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600054#WRD00900"><p>Budget 2014 published on 15<sup></sup>October 2013, contained the latest macroeconomic and fiscal forecasts from my Department. These forecasts are set out in section C of the Budget booklet.</p><p>  I note that the Deputy has asked for information on national debt. As general government debt expressed as a percentage of gross domestic product is the standard metric internationally for accessing debt levels, information on general government debt has been included instead of national debt.</p><p>  The information requested by the Deputy is set out in the table below.<table><tr><th> -</th><th>Forecast for 2014</th></tr><tr><td>Nominal GDP (rounded to nearest &euro;25m)</td><td>170,600</td></tr><tr><td>Nominal GNP (rounded to nearest &euro;25m)</td><td>138,500</td></tr><tr><td>General Government Debt ( &euro; billion)</td><td>204.7</td></tr><tr><td>General Government Debt (as % of GDP)</td><td>120.0%</td></tr><tr><td>Inflation rate (HICP)</td><td>1.2%</td></tr><tr><td>Source: Department of Finance</td><td></td></tr></table></p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.166" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600054#WRD00950">NAMA Expenditure</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.167.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1182" speakername="Terence Flanagan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600054#WRD01000"><p><i>66.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance if he will provide a full breakdown of the set up costs in the establishment of the National Asset Management Agency; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2036/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.168.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600054#WRD01100"><p>NAMA&rsquo;s establishment costs are set out in the Comptroller and Auditor General&rsquo;s special report into NAMA&rsquo;s &lsquo;Acquisition of Bank Assets&rsquo;, which was published in October 2010 and is available on the NAMA website, <i><font color="#0000FF">www.nama.ie</font></i>  .  As per this Report, the costs incurred by the NTMA in the establishment of NAMA totalled &euro;2.3 million.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.169" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600054#WRD01150">Proposed Legislation</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.170.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1182" speakername="Terence Flanagan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600054#WRD01200"><p><i>67.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance his plans to update National Asset Management Agency legislation; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2039/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.171.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600054#WRD01300"><p>I currently have no plans to update the NAMA legislation. Under Sections 13 and 14 of the NAMA Act I have the power to issue guidelines and directions to NAMA. To date I have issued nine directions to NAMA which are available on the NAMA website at <i><font color="#0000FF">www.nama.ie</font></i>. </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.172" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600054#WRD01350">Vehicle Registration Issues</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.173.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/988" speakername="&Aacute;ine Collins" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600054#WRD01400"><p><i>68.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance the way persons will be able to fulfil a requirement if a list of authorised dealers in not available (details supplied). <b>[2069/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.174.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600054#WRD01500"><p>I am informed by the Revenue Commissioners that Section 136, Finance Act, 1992 provides that a person may be authorised by the Revenue Commissioners to deal in unregistered vehicles. Since this provision came into force in 1993, the Revenue Commissioners have authorised a large number of companies and individuals who are involved in the manufacture, distribution, storage, modification, repair and sale of unregistered vehicles. The list of authorised persons increases as new companies and individuals become involved in the motor sector and decreases as companies or individuals leave the sector.</p><p>  In relation to disabled drivers and passengers, I am also informed by the Revenue Commissioners that Statutory Instrument No. 353 of 1994 (Disabled Drivers and Disabled Passengers (Tax Concessions) Regulations, 1994) provides that a vehicle must be purchased from an authorised person. This provision is included for sound control and customer protection reasons and the requirement is clearly set out in information material on the scheme. </p><p>  I am informed by the Revenue Commissioners that there is no legislative provision for the publication of the list of authorised persons. However, a buyer can readily satisfy him or herself that a dealer is authorised by asking the dealer in question for evidence of authorisation. </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.175" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600054#WRD01550">National Pensions Reserve Fund Investments</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.176.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600054#WRD01600"><p><i>69.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance the amount invested to date by the NPRF in respect of the installation of water meters; the full amount it expects to invest; the return that will be generated from the investment; and if he will make a statement on the matter.  <b>[2076/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.177.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600054#WRD01700"><p>In September 2013, the National Pensions Reserve Fund (NPRF) agreed to provide a &euro;250 million two-year bridging facility to Irish Water to provide short-term funding for its start-up costs and metering installation costs. Irish Water has drawn down &euro;160 million to date and the balance is expected to be drawn down on 16 January 2014.</p><p>  The NPRF have advised that the return on their investment is commercially sensitive and cannot be disclosed.  The NPRF Commission required a guarantee for its lending to Irish Water in the light of the Fund&rsquo;s commercial investment mandate and the fact that Irish Water would have no revenues until 2015. The Government agreed in June 2013 to the provision of such a guarantee by the Minister for Finance. The fee for the guarantee is two per cent per annum on the amount of the loan facility drawn down by Irish Water. The fee reflects the fact that the loan arrangements are commercial in nature and are made on an arm&rsquo;s-length basis. A payment of &euro;823,504 was paid to the Exchequer in respect of the guarantee for the period 5 October 2013 to 5 January 2014.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.178" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600054#WRD01750">Bank Charges</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.179.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600054#WRD01800"><p><i>70.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance his views on whether the increase in online business banking fees by AIB, in particular the 25% increase in the cost of a basic online business account, will be detrimental to the interests of small and medium enterprises; if he will request that AIB consider the wider economic interests when reviewing its fees; his views on whether the actions of AIB further highlight the need for more competition in the banking sector; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2077/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.180.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600054#WRD01900"><p>I have been informed by AIB that the bank is to increase iBusiness Banking (iBB) service charges with effect from 1st March 2014. This is the first time AIB has increased the iBB service charge since it was introduced in 2001. The increase is necessary in order to continue to develop and invest in electronic channels for customers.</p><p>  Business Start-up customers and Young Farmer Account holders are entitled to a free subscription to IBB for two years. AIB also offers an online Banking service for SME sole traders and partnerships which is free of charge.</p><p>  As the Deputy will be aware under the Relationship Framework the State does not intervene in the day to day operations of the bank or their management decisions regarding commercial matters.  While I am in favour of a greater level of competition in the market I have no control over the entry or exit of foreign owned subsidiaries operating in the Irish market and I would add that it is a source of disappointment to me that a number of players have taken the decision to downsize or exit the market in recent times. The Government remains focused on ensuring that the  economy recovers I would hope that as this occurs there will be a reversal in this current trend.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.181" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600054#WRD01950">IBRC Liquidation</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.182.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600054#WRD02000"><p><i>71.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance further to Parliamentary Question No. 63 of 10 October 2013, the Irish Bank Resolution Corporation has made a voluntary disclosure to the Revenue Commissioners; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2089/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.183.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600054#WRD02100"><p>The Special Liquidators have informed me that on their appointment, Irish Bank Resolution Corporation Limited was already in dialogue with the Revenue Commissioners in relation to an open tax audit. The Special Liquidators are working with the Revenue Commissioners to close out the tax audit and some additional tax issues that have come to their attention. As these are matters which are still being reviewed and discussed between IBRC Limited (in Special Liquidation) and the Revenue Commissioners it would not be appropriate to comment any further at this time.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.184" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600054#WRD02150">Departmental Funding</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.185.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1091" speakername="John Deasy" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600054#WRD02200"><p><i>72.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance if he will provide details of each allocation from his Department&rsquo;s expenditure budget to registered charities in each of the past three years. <b>[2101/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.186.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600054#WRD02300"><p>No allocation from my Department's expenditure budget has been allocated to registered charities in each of the past three years.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.187" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600054#WRD02350">Economic Competitiveness</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.188.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/957" speakername="Bernard Durkan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600054#WRD02400"><p><i>73.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance the extent to which this economy remains competitive when compared to other competing jurisdictions within the EU and without; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2109/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.189.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600054#WRD02500"><p>Substantial progress has been made in terms of improving Ireland&rsquo;s competitiveness in recent years.  Relatively low consumer price inflation over the last five years has meant that Irish price levels have fallen considerably relative to our euro area peers. For instance, annual HICP inflation in Ireland has been below that of the euro area average for every year since 2009. This trend continued in 2013, with inflation over the first 11 months of the year coming in below the comparable rate in the euro area. </p><p>  At the same time there has been a significant improvement in economy-wide cost competitiveness. Indeed, the European Commission recently forecast that our nominal unit labour costs will improve by 23 per cent relative to the euro area average over the period 2008-2015.</p><p>  The real Harmonised Competitiveness Indicator (HCI) measures the trade weighted exchange rate for Ireland, adjusted for relative price developments. From mid-2008 to end-2013 Ireland's real HCI has fallen by 15 per cent, indicating a significant improvement in our competitiveness over the period and leaving Irish-based firms better equipped to compete on the international market.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.190" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600054#WRD02550">Credit Availability</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.191.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/957" speakername="Bernard Durkan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600054#WRD02600"><p><i>74.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance the extent to which he continues to receive indications from the banking sector regarding the availability of credit throughout the domestic market; if any particular issues have arisen which might indicate a lack of interest in lending by some institutions; the steps required to address this issue; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2110/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.192.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600054#WRD02700"><p>Access to finance for SMEs was a key aspect of the Action Plan for Jobs 2013 and will continue to be the focus of Government policy in this area in 2014. It is the Government&rsquo;s vision that all viable businesses operating in Ireland should have the opportunity to access sufficient finance to meet their enterprise needs in a manner that supports growth and employment in the economy. </p><p>  The Government has imposed SME lending targets on AIB and Bank of Ireland for the three calendar years, 2011 to 2013. Each bank was required to sanction lending of at least &euro;3 billion in 2011, &euro;3.5 billion in 2012 and &euro;4 billion in 2013 for new or increased credit facilities to SMEs. Both banks achieved their 2011 and 2012 targets. </p><p>  AIB and Bank of Ireland are expected to lend to viable businesses both for investment and working capital purposes. The Credit Review Office is available to assist businesses which have been refused credit. The recent CRO report shows that the Credit Review Office upheld the credit appeal in 150 cases or 55% of cases decided. The upheld appeals have resulted in &euro;18.5m in credit being made available to SMEs and farms, protecting 1,521 jobs. In the recent Budget I increased the CRO appeals threshold from &euro;500,000 to &euro;3 million and I would strongly encourage SMEs refused credit to seek a review by the Office. </p><p>  The Government has taken a number of actions to improve the situation in relation to credit availability to SMEs. The range of credit options available to SMEs now include the Microenterprise Loan scheme which can facilitate up to &euro;40million in additional lending to microenterprises over the next five years.  In addition, the Credit Guarantee Scheme is designed for SMEs who, because of lack of collateral or because of the specialised sector they operate in, face difficulties in accessing bank credit.  </p><p>  The SME State Bodies Group develops key policy initiatives to support SME access to credit and other forms of finance and ensures their implementation through the annual Action Plan for Jobs. It has continued in 2013 to engage intensively in proactively addressing issues associated with SME funding and financing in conjunction with the relevant stakeholders through the SME Funding Consultation Committee. My officials also meet frequently with additional stakeholders who wish to contribute to policy development in relation to access to finance.</p><p>  It is vital that the banks continue to make credit available to support economic recovery. However, it is not in the interest of the banks, businesses or the economy for finance to be provided unless the business is viable and has the capacity to meet the interest payments and repay the sum borrowed.</p><p>  Competition in the mortgage market is a good thing for Irish customers. The decision by a mortgage provider on what credit products to offer is a commercial decision for the lending institution concerned.  It is important that each lending institution is allowed to assess properly and independently the risks that it is considering when making such a decision. Mortgage lending decisions must be undertaken on a sustainable and prudential basis by financial institutions and conform fully to the regulatory requirements, both in relation to the financial institution itself, and also with regard to the safeguarding of the borrower's interests.</p><p>  There is a consensus amongst industry commentators that there may be an emerging supply shortage in the Greater Dublin Housing market which is leading to an increase in property prices and rents across the area. A higher demand for houses in Dublin is not surprising considering the concentration of employment and the need to meet the rising demand for rental accommodation.  The Central Bank has advised me that it does not set the credit lending policies of individual banks. In a supervisory capacity, the Central Bank oversees and reviews Bank practices and regulatory adherence.  Available information on new mortgage lending activity is published by the Irish Banking Federation on a quarterly basis and this demonstrates that while recent increases in lending is evident, long term mortgage lending is at a low ebb.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.194" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600055#WRE00150">Financial Services Regulation</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.195.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/957" speakername="Bernard Durkan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600055#WRE00200"><p><i>75.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance the basis on which lending institutions currently existing or having exited from the Irish market remain accountable to the regulatory mechanisms here in terms of their winding up operations; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2111/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.196.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600055#WRE00300"><p>Where a Central Bank regulated lender transfers all or part of its regulated activities to another regulated financial institution, the same protections apply to borrowers, including the Code of Conduct on Mortgage Arrears (CCMA) and the Consumer Protection Code.  Any agent acting on behalf of a regulated lender must comply with the requirements of Irish financial services law and failure to do so may result in the Central Bank imposing penalties on the regulated lender concerned.   </p><p>  The Central Bank&rsquo;s Consumer Protection Code 2012 imposes obligations on regulated entities in relation to their interactions with consumers.  Where a regulated entity intends to cease operating, merge with another, or to transfer all or part of its regulated activities to another regulated entity, Provision 3.11 of the Consumer Protection Code states that it must:</p><p>  a. notify the Central Bank immediately; </p><p>  b. provide at least two months&rsquo; notice to affected consumers to enable them to make alternative arrangements; </p><p>  c. ensure all outstanding business is properly completed prior to the transfer, merger or cessation of operations or, alternatively in the case of a transfer or merger, inform the consumer of how continuity of service will be provided following the transfer or merger; and </p><p>  d. in the case of a merger or transfer of regulated activities, inform the consumer that their details are being transferred to the other regulated entity, if that is the case.</p><p>  By virtue of an exemption in Part V of the Central Bank Act 1997, an unregulated entity to whom a cash loan is transferred by a regulated entity is not subject to Central Bank supervision under the Consumer Protection Code and CCMA<b>. </b>  Under the Central Bank (Supervision and Enforcement) Act 2013, the Central Bank may exercise its information-gathering and authorised officers&rsquo; powers in respect of a person, including a corporate entity, which is or has been a regulated financial service provider.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.197" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600055#WRE00350">Housing Data</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.198.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/957" speakername="Bernard Durkan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600055#WRE00400"><p><i>76.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance if his attention has been drawn to a shift in savings by private investors to the private housing market with obvious implications for buyers seeking to provide themselves with a family home; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2112/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.199.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600055#WRE00500"><p>As the Deputy may be aware, there has been much commentary of late on an increase in demand for private housing in certain urban areas.  Industry reports suggest that a significant portion of property purchase does not rely on credit.</p><p>  However, I wish to assure the Deputy that this Government has implemented a series of measures which reflect the important role that the banking sector has to play in supplying credit and in doing so to assist buyers seeking to provide themselves with a family home.   As shareholders in the main banks, the Government&rsquo;s objective is to ensure that they are managed commercially so as to create and protect value for the taxpayer but also to ensure that they supply the credit lines necessary to sustain and grow the economy.  I am satisfied that the Central Bank is monitoring lending decisions of the banks.</p><p>  It is not immediately evident that investors who are becoming active again in the market after an absence for some time are necessarily competing for the same property types as borrowers of residential mortgages. </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.200" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600055#WRE00550">Banking Sector Issues</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.201.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/957" speakername="Bernard Durkan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600055#WRE00600"><p><i>77.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance the extent to which lending institutions here have successfully attracted savings from other jurisdictions; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2113/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.202.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600055#WRE00700"><p>Table A.12 from the Central Bank&rsquo;s Money and Banking Statistics () </p><p>  shows outstanding deposits held in Irish resident credit institutions by non-residents.</p><p>  The Central Bank&rsquo;s most recent information release dated 4 January covers the period to November 2013. It stated that non-resident deposits decreased by &euro;1.3 billion during November 2013, following a &euro;333 million decrease in October. November&rsquo;s decrease reflects decline in deposits from both the non-euro area and the other countries euro area of &euro;662 million and &euro;606 million, respectively. In annual terms, private-sector deposits from non-euro area and other euro area residents decreased by 1 per cent and 11.6 per cent, respectively.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.203" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600055#WRE00750">Economic Growth Rate</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.204.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/957" speakername="Bernard Durkan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600055#WRE00800"><p><i>78.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance the extent to which this country&rsquo;s economic performance is likely to benefit from the post-bailout environment; and if he will make a statement on the matter.  <b>[2114/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.205.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600055#WRE00900"><p>The ending of the programme of external financial assistance will help to further enhance confidence as it clearly demonstrates that we have moved to the next stage of our recovery. </p><p>  The restoration of confidence in the Irish economy will have tangible benefits in terms of supporting domestic demand. In this regard the successful completion of the programme in December 2013 has had a noticeable impact on confidence domestically. Consumer confidence, as measured by the ESRI/KBC Consumer Sentiment Index three-month moving average, has increased for eight consecutive months, reaching very high levels in December.</p><p>  In addition to this, the recent Quarterly National Accounts release from the CSO showed double digit year-on-year growth in investment in the third quarter &ndash; a clear sign that confidence is returning to businesses domestically. Indeed core investment (excluding the volatile aircraft component) has seen strong year-on-year growth in each of the last three quarters. Business expectations for both investment and employment &ndash; as measured by Ibec and ISME respectively &ndash; both improved in the latter half of 2013.</p><p>  Further improvements in confidence are important and will continue to support the on-going recovery in the Irish economy, in particular domestic demand.	</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.206" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600055#WRE00950">Credit Availability</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.207.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/957" speakername="Bernard Durkan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600055#WRE01000"><p><i>79.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance the extent to which the credit needs of business here is being met by banks in other jurisdictions; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2115/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.208.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600055#WRE01100"><p>I, as Minister for Finance, have no statutory role in relation to the issues raised by the Deputy.</p><p>  I have been advised by the Central Bank that it does not publish statistics regarding lending by banks in other jurisdictions to business in Ireland.</p><p>  The Central Bank of Ireland has overall responsibility for the authorisation, regulation and supervision of credit institutions operating in Ireland. In addition the Central Bank is responsible for oversight of liquidity and conduct of business for branches of non-Irish licensed banks operating in Ireland.</p><p>  The authorisation, regulation and supervision of credit institutions operating in foreign jurisdictions are matters for the regulatory authorities of each jurisdiction.</p></reply>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.210.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/957" speakername="Bernard Durkan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600055#WRE01200"><p><i>80.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance the extent to which Irish lending institutions have provided credit or other lending facilities to applicants in other EU jurisdictions; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2116/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.211.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600055#WRE01300"><p>I am informed by the Central Bank of Ireland that the information sought by the Deputy is contained in Credit, Money and Banking Statistics: Publications and Releases in Table A.7.1 Loans to Non-Residents &ndash; Other Euro Area and Table A.7.2 Loans to Non-Residents &ndash; Non-Euro Area. <i><font color="#0000FF"></font></i></p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.212" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600055#WRE01350">National Debt</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.213.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/957" speakername="Bernard Durkan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600055#WRE01400"><p><i>81.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance the extent to which he expects to convince his EU colleagues of the necessity to make provision for legacy debt in this country; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2117/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.214.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600055#WRE01500"><p>The Euro-area Heads of State or Government (HoSG) agreed in June 2012 that &ldquo;it is imperative to break the vicious circle between banks and sovereigns&rdquo;, and that when a Single Supervisory Mechanism, involving the ECB, is in place and operational, the European Stability Mechanism could recapitalize banks directly. </p><p>  The Eurogroup meeting of 20th June 2013 agreed on the main features of the European Stability Mechanism&rsquo;s Direct Recapitalisation Instrument or DRI. There is a specific provision included in those main features, which states that &ldquo;The potential retroactive application of the instrument should be decided on a case-by-case basis and by mutual agreement.&rdquo; Therefore, the agreement, that we were active in negotiating, keeps open the possibility to apply to the European Stability Mechanism for a retrospective direct recapitalisation of the Irish banks, should we wish to avail of it. </p><p>  The DRI will come into effect when the Single Supervisory Mechanism is in place and operational. This is not expected to take place until late 2014.</p><p>  The Eurogroup has agreed that there will be strict eligibility criteria as well as a clear pecking order for the ESM DRI, so any possible application for a DRI will be determined on its own merits within the rules established for the DRI.</p><p>  The overall framework agreed in summer 2013 builds upon the earlier Euro area Heads of State or Government agreement secured on the 29th of June 2012, and is an important step in the Eurozone&rsquo;s efforts in this regard. </p><p>  Finally, I can assure the Deputy that the Irish case is made at all levels as appropriate and in this context I often engage on these matters with my European Ministerial colleagues.</p><p>  I remain confident that the commitment made by the EU HoSG in June 2012 to break the vicious circle between banks and sovereigns will be respected. </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.215" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600055#WRE01550">Credit Ratings</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.216.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/957" speakername="Bernard Durkan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600055#WRE01600"><p><i>82.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance the extent to which the Irish Credit Bureau receives correspondence from the various lending institutions on a weekly, monthly or annual basis, the result of which may be a restriction on their ability to operate their business; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2119/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.217.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600055#WRE01700"><p>The Irish Credit Bureau is a private entity and I have no role in regulating the mechanism by which lending institutions report to the Bureau.  It a commercial matter between the ICB and the relevant institutions.</p><p>  The Deputy will be aware that the Credit Reporting Act, 2013 provides for the establishment of a statutory credit register that will be owned and operated by the Central Bank of Ireland. There will be mandatory reporting of a comprehensive range of credit information by credit providers to specified reporting standards (e.g. formats, timelines etc.). Credit providers will be required to make mandatory credit checks with the Register for all credit applications above a threshold of &euro;2,000.  The Act also provides that the Central Bank will ensure the robust regulation of regulated financial service providers who fall under this Act.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.218" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600055#WRE01750">Bank Charges</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.219.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/957" speakername="Bernard Durkan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600055#WRE01800"><p><i>83.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance the extent to which bank charges in this country are comparable to those that exist in other EU jurisdictions; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2120/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.220.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600055#WRE01900"><p>As the Deputy may be aware, the Programme Documents (the Memorandum of Understanding on Specific Economic Policy Conditionality and the Memorandum of Economic and Financial Policies) agreed following the 10th Review of the EU-IMF Programme of Financial Support include a commitment to carry out an assessment of banks&rsquo; fee income by end-December 2013 as follows:</p><p>  The authorities will assess banks&rsquo; fee income relative to peers in selected other jurisdictions. Based on this assessment they will complete an external review of the regulation of bank fees.</p><p>  The assessment and review were undertaken by the Department and completed in December 2013. The review was sent to the Troika on completion and my intention is that the report containing analysis such as that sought by the Deputy will be published shortly.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.221" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600055#WRE01950">Tax Code</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.222.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1026" speakername="Olivia Mitchell" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600055#WRE02000"><p><i>84.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance if he will reconsider the cases where the loss of the single person child carer credit results in the secondary carer moving into a higher tax band, as the loss of income caused is much larger than &euro;1,650 per annum; and if he will make a statement on the matter.  <b>[2122/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.223.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600055#WRE02100"><p>As you are aware the One-Parent Family Credit ceased with effect from 31 December 2013 and was replaced by the Single Person Child Carer Credit, which is applicable from 1 January 2014. The restructured credit is of the same value i.e. &euro;1,650 per annum as the one-parent family tax credit and also carries the same entitlement to the additional &euro;4,000 extended standard rate band, which increases it to &euro;36,800 per annum, before liability to higher rate of income tax arises. However, the credit will be more targeted, in that it will in the first instance, only be available to the principal carer of the child. </p><p>  The withdrawal of the extended standard rate band for non-primary carers results in a maximum additional income tax liability of &euro;840 per annum, depending on the income of the individual concerned.</p><p>  To allowretention of the extended standard rate band while removing the credit would act to benefit those non-primary carers with greater incomes while providing no benefit tothose on lowerincomes. It would also go against the thrust of Government policy, which is that only one carer per family unit should attract the benefit of the new credit and band. </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.224" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600055#WRE02150">Tax Rebates</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.225.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/957" speakername="Bernard Durkan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600055#WRE02200"><p><i>85.</i> To ask the Minister for Finance the total Med 1-Med 2 refund for which a person (details supplied) in County Kildare is eligible and has been paid; and if he will make a statement on the matter.  <b>[2128/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.226.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600055#WRE02300"><p>I have been advised by the Revenue Commissioners that in November 2013 they received Forms MED1 from the person concerned for the years 2010, 2011 and 2012. These claims have been processed and PAYE Balancing Statements (P21s) issued dated 29 November 2013, and 4 December 2013 respectively. As no income tax was paid for 2010, no refund is due for that year. Refunds for 2011 and 2012 have issued in the amounts of &euro;6.33 and &euro;34.82 respectively.</p></reply>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.228" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600055#WRE02400">Department of Education and Skills</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.227" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600055#WRE02350">Departmental Funding</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.228.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/984" speakername="Jonathan O'Brien" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600055#WRE02400"><p><i>86.</i> To ask the Minister for Education and Skills the funding options available for community based migrant groups who wish to start language lessons for children; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[1819/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.229.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1035" speakername="Ruairi Quinn" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600055#WRE02500"><p>Under the Intercultural Education Strategy (2010-2015) which covers the continuum of education from pre-school through to further and higher education, current funding is being prioritised by my Department within schools for school based language provision, including English language support and support for mother tongue. </p><p>  As the Deputy may be aware the Office for the Promotion of Migrant Integration in the Department of Justice and Equality has responsibility for leading and coordinating work relating to the integration of legally resident immigrants. </p><p>  The Office is also responsible for the European Refugee Fund and the European Fund for the Integration of Third-Country Nationals both of which financially assist integration of members of their target group.  From 2014, these Funds will be replaced by the Asylum and Migration Fund. Arrangements for this Fund will involve a policy or programming dialogue with the European Commission after which a national multi-annual programme will be drawn up for the period 2014-2020.</p><p>  National funding for integration of immigrants is also provided by OPMI subject to the reduced resources which are available for all categories of public expenditure at present.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.230" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600055#WRE02550">Consultancy Contracts Data</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.231.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/984" speakername="Jonathan O'Brien" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600055#WRE02600"><p><i>87.</i> To ask the Minister for Education and Skills the number of consultants or consultancy firms employed by his Department during each of the past five years; the purpose and duration of each of these consultancies or consultancy contracts; the names of the consultants or firms; and if he will list architectural consultancies separately; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[1820/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2014-01-16a.232.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1035" speakername="Ruairi Quinn" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014011600055#WRE02700"><p>For the Deputy's information the attach table lists the consultants and consultancy firms engaged by my Department for the years 2009 to 2012 inclusive. Information in relation to consultancy expenditure is compiled retrospectively in respect of the previous year. The details in respect of 2013 are not yet available but will be provided to the Deputy as soon as they are to hand.</p><p>  Architects are appointed on all major school building projects as part of the design team which designs the school, secures the statutory approvals, tenders </p><p>the works and oversees the contractor selected to build the school. Such appointments are not generally considered as consultant appointments. Details </p><p>in relation to architectural and other design team appointments are available on the Departments web-site.</p><p><b>YEAR 2009</b><table><tr><th><b>Consultants,Experts, Advisors</b></th><th><b>Start date</b></th><th><b>Completion date</b></th><th><div><b>Purpose</b></div></th><th><div><b>Total Cost</b></div></th></tr><tr><td><div><b></b></div></td><td><div><b></b></div></td><td><div><b></b></div></td><td><div><b></b></div></td><td><div>&euro;</div></td></tr><tr><td>Norcontel</td><td><div>May-08</div></td><td><div>Aug-09</div></td><td>Schools Broadband Access Programme- Technical, Commercial and Financial Advisor for the Advisor for the Evaluation &amp;amp; Contract Phases of the Procurement of Broadband Internet Connectivity for Schools</td><td><div>33,959</div></td></tr><tr><td>FGS</td><td><div>Mar-09</div></td><td><div>Oct-09</div></td><td>Review of overhead/indirect costs re work carried out by Bus Eireann on behalf of DES for the administration of the school transport scheme</td><td><div>67,677</div></td></tr><tr><td>Centre for Cross Border Studies</td><td><div>Oct-09</div></td><td><div>Dec-09</div></td><td>2009 annual review re courses in Northern Ireland</td><td><div>2,430</div></td></tr><tr><td>Gillian Boyd</td><td><div>Oct-08</div></td><td><div>Dec-09</div></td><td>To evaluate the provision of a post-graduate Diploma in SEN (Autistic Spectrum Disorder) in St Angela's College, Sligo</td><td><div>5,000</div></td></tr><tr><td>Russell Brendan Keane</td><td><div>Feb-09</div></td><td><div>Feb-09</div></td><td>European Regional development fund-Look Back Exercise </td><td><div>3,742</div></td></tr><tr><td>Gartner</td><td><div>Oct-08</div></td><td><div>Oct-10</div></td><td>Provision of ICT Research, advice, guidance &amp;amp; related services to the IT Unit</td><td><div>51,030</div></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td><div><b>2009 Total:</b></div></td><td><div><b>&euro;163,838</b></div></td></tr></table>.</p><p><b>YEAR 2010</b><table><tr><th><b>Consultants,Experts, Advisors</b></th><th><b>Start date</b></th><th><b>Completion date</b></th><th><div><b>Purpose</b></div></th><th><div><b>Total Cost</b></div></th></tr><tr><td><b></b></td><td><b></b></td><td><b></b></td><td><div><b></b></div></td><td><div>&euro;</div></td></tr><tr><td>Centre for Cross Border Studies</td><td><div>Oct-10</div></td><td><div>Dec-10</div></td><td>2010 annual review of Post grad courses in Northern Ireland</td><td><div>2,420</div></td></tr><tr><td>Gartner</td><td><div>Nov-10</div></td><td><div>Oct-11</div></td><td>Subscription for provision of ICT research, advice, guidance &amp;amp; related services to the IT Unit</td><td><div>37,026</div></td></tr><tr><td>Ina McGrath</td><td><div>Jun-10</div></td><td><div>Jun-10</div></td><td>Ergonomic workstation assessment &amp;amp; report</td><td><div>300</div></td></tr><tr><td>Indecon</td><td><div>Jan-10</div></td><td><div>May-10</div></td><td>Mid term review of the Lifelong Learning Programme &amp;amp; prepare a report for Departmetn of Education &amp;amp; Skills for onward transmission to the European Commission</td><td><div>59,284</div></td></tr><tr><td>Deloitte</td><td><div>May-10</div></td><td><div>2010</div></td><td>Declaration of Assurance 2009 Audit - to review procedures &amp;amp; workflows in the National Agencies for the Lifelong Learning Programme &amp;amp; to provide a basis for the yearly Declaration of Assurance from DOES to the EU Commission</td><td><div>16,299</div></td></tr><tr><td>Mazars</td><td><div>Mar-10</div></td><td><div>Mar-10</div></td><td>Review procedures &amp;amp; workflows in the National Agencies for the Lifelong Learning Programme &amp;amp; to provide a basis for the yearly Declaration of Assurance from the Department of Education &amp;amp; Skills to the EU Commission</td><td><div>4,795</div></td></tr><tr><td>Public Authority Pension Services</td><td><div>Jul-10</div></td><td><div>Sep-10</div></td><td>Expertise relating to the model public service pension scheme to assist in the establishment of a pension scheme for the NCTE</td><td><div>5,324</div></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td><div><b>2010 Total:</b></div></td><td><div><b>&euro;125,448</b></div></td></tr></table></p><p><b>YEAR 2011</b><table><tr><th><b>Consultants,Experts, Advisors</b></th><th><b>Start date</b></th><th><b>Completion date</b></th><th><div><b>Purpose</b></div></th><th><div><b>Total Cost</b></div></th></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td><div>&euro;</div></td></tr><tr><td>Centre for Cross Border Studies</td><td><div>Oct-11</div></td><td><div>Dec-11</div></td><td>2011 annual review of Post graduate courses in Northern Ireland</td><td><div>2420.00</div></td></tr><tr><td>Jim Duffy &amp;amp; Pat McLoughlin members of an independent panel appointed by the Secretary General re designation of a single awarding authority</td><td><div>Feb-11</div></td><td><div>Apr-11</div></td><td>The independent panel shortlisted a number of proposals, made recommendations to the Minister on the preferred proposal for designation of a single awarding authority and made recommendations it considered necessary in relation to modification or development of the preferred proposal for implementation purposes</td><td><div>1,927.86</div></td></tr><tr><td>Gartner</td><td><div>Oct-11</div></td><td><div>Oct-14</div></td><td>Subscription for provision of ICT research, advice, guidance &amp;amp; related services to the IT Unit 1/10/2011 - 30/09/2012</td><td><div>35,150.49</div></td></tr><tr><td>Sr. Eileen Randles</td><td><div>May-10</div></td><td><div>Nov-10</div></td><td>External Reviewer in an appeal against an inspection under section 13 (9) of the Education Act 1998</td><td><div>920.00</div></td></tr><tr><td>Dr Simon Marginson</td><td><div>Jan-11</div></td><td><div>Mar-11</div></td><td>Development &amp;amp; submission to DOES of draft criteria for the proposed re-designation of amalgamated institutes of Technology Universities arising from the recommendations of the National Strategy  for Higher Education to 2030</td><td><div>&euro;9,075.00</div></td></tr><tr><td>Farrell Grant Sparks</td><td><div>Oct-10</div></td><td><div>Jun-11</div></td><td>Follow up work and provision of advice in relation to the FGS report (redacted report due to commercially sensitive issues in original report)</td><td><div>&euro;8,410.71</div></td></tr><tr><td>Forum on Patronage &amp;amp; Pluralism in the Primary Sector-Professor John Coolahan, Dr Caroline Hussey, Fionnuala Kilfeather</td><td><div>Apr-11</div></td><td><div>Jan-12</div></td><td>Advisory Group to convene the Forum on Patronage &amp;amp; Pluralism in the Primary Sector, to receive and distil the various views and perspectives of participants and to report and advise the Minister</td><td><div>&euro;20,000.00</div></td></tr><tr><td>Price Waterhouse Coopers LLP (PWC) Belfast</td><td><div>Dec-10</div></td><td><div>Mar-12</div></td><td>Evaluation of the Special Education Support Service established by the Department in 2003 to address the then rather fragmented provision of continuing professional development in the area of special education.</td><td><div>&euro;97,866.01</div></td></tr><tr><td>Goodbody Economic Consultants</td><td><div>Apr-11</div></td><td><div>Dec-11</div></td><td>Evaluation of the Initial Implementation of S&iacute;olta, the National Quality Framework for Early Childhood Education</td><td><div>&euro;31,280.92</div></td></tr><tr><td>The PA Consulting Group</td><td><div>Jul-11</div></td><td><div>Nov-11</div></td><td>Evaluation of the training &amp;amp; education programmes for the unemployed delivered under LMAF 2010</td><td><div>&euro;52,003.38</div></td></tr><tr><td>Fitzpatrick &amp;amp; Associates</td><td><div>Feb-11</div></td><td><div>Aug-11</div></td><td>Mid term Evaluation of the Human Capital Investment Operational Programme 2007-2013</td><td><div>&euro;61,589.00</div></td></tr><tr><td>Deloitte</td><td><div>Apr-10</div></td><td><div>Apr-12</div></td><td>To carry out audits of the national agencies for the Lifelong Learning Programme in Ireland, these will serve as the basis for the submission of Declarations of Assurance from International Section to the European Commission</td><td><div>&euro;16,299.00</div></td></tr><tr><td>Public Authority Pension Services Ltd</td><td><div>Jun-10</div></td><td><div>Jun-11</div></td><td>Pensions advisory work relating to the establishment of a pension scheme for staff of the NCTE</td><td><div>&euro;4,791.60</div></td></tr><tr><td>Analysys Mason</td><td><div>Jul-11</div></td><td><div>Apr-12</div></td><td>Commercial Financial &amp;amp; Technical Procurement advice for Schools Broadband Tender</td><td><div>&euro;63,632.51</div></td></tr><tr><td>Grant Thornton</td><td><div>Sep-11</div></td><td><div>Oct-11</div></td><td>External audit of Dell and Waterford Crystal EGF programmes</td><td><div>&euro;5,445.00</div></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td><div><b>2011 Total:</b></div></td><td><div><b>&euro;410,811.48</b></div></td></tr></table></p><p><b>YEAR 2012</b><table><tr><th><b>Consultants,Experts, Advisors</b></th><th><b>Start date</b></th><th><b>Completion date</b></th><th><div><b>Purpose</b></div></th><th><div><b>Total Cost</b></div></th></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td><div>&euro;</div></td></tr><tr><td>Analysys Mason</td><td><div>Jul-11</div></td><td><div>Mar-13</div></td><td>Commercial, financial and technical advice on the procurement of broadband services for schools</td><td><div>&euro;52,040.42</div></td></tr><tr><td>Goodbody Economic Consultants</td><td><div>Apr-11</div></td><td><div>Dec-11</div></td><td>Evaluation of the Initial Implementation of S&iacute;olta, the National Quality framework for Early Childhood Education</td><td><div>&euro;16,747.68</div></td></tr><tr><td>Mazars</td><td><div>2012</div></td><td><div>2012</div></td><td>IT Security Audit of the EUSF IT Database</td><td><div>&euro;5,063.91</div></td></tr><tr><td>Mazars</td><td><div>Jul-11</div></td><td><div>Jun-12</div></td><td>Audit of Labour Market Activation Fund (LMAF)</td><td><div>&euro;9,839.14</div></td></tr><tr><td>Version 1</td><td><div>Apr-12</div></td><td><div>Dec-12</div></td><td>Provision of Oracle Financials training support along with training documentation in the implementation of Performance Budgeting</td><td><div>&euro;2,070.00</div></td></tr><tr><td>Mokum Change Management Ltd</td><td><div>Apr-12</div></td><td><div>Dec-12</div></td><td>Provision of Oracle Financials training support along with training documentation in the implementation of Performance Budgeting</td><td><div>&euro;17,302.88</div></td></tr><tr><td>Seamus O'Dwyer-Consulting and Training</td><td><div>Jul-12</div></td><td><div>Jan-13</div></td><td>Training and expert advice relating to the Public Service Pensions Bill</td><td><div>&euro;2,700.00</div></td></tr><tr><td>Sydney Blain</td><td><div>Oct-11</div></td><td><div>Feb-12</div></td><td>Review of an appeal against an inspection under section 13(9) of the Education Act</td><td><div>&euro;718.75</div></td></tr><tr><td>Mokum Change Management Ltd</td><td><div>Apr-12</div></td><td><div>Dec-12</div></td><td>Provision of Oracle Financials functional &amp;amp; accounting advice in moving from a four vote operating unit to a single operating unit</td><td><div>&euro;11,606.90</div></td></tr><tr><td>Sir Jim Rose</td><td><div>Dec-11</div></td><td><div>2020</div></td><td>Provision of international expertise on Literacy &amp;amp; Numeracy to the Literacy &amp;amp; Numeracy Implementation Advisory Committee</td><td><div>&euro;3,870.13</div></td></tr><tr><td>Gartner</td><td><div>Oct-11</div></td><td><div>Oct-14</div></td><td>Subscription for provision of ICT research, advice, guidance &amp;amp; related services to the IT Unit<font color="#FF0000"> </font></td><td><div>&euro;36,788.67</div></td></tr><tr><td>Sion Quality Healthcare Solutions</td><td><div>Oct-12</div></td><td><div>Oct-12</div></td><td>Completion of a workplace assessment for staff member with a disability and resulting report</td><td><div>&euro;370.00</div></td></tr><tr><td>Pat McLoughlin</td><td><div>Feb-11</div></td><td><div>Apr-11</div></td><td>Chair of Independent Panel re the establishment of the single grant awarding authority</td><td><div>&euro;83.66</div></td></tr><tr><td>The Centre for Cross Border Studies</td><td><div>Oct-12</div></td><td><div>Dec-12</div></td><td>2012 review paper of Republic of Ireland post graduates in Northern Ireland</td><td><div>&euro;1,845.00</div></td></tr><tr><td>Deloitte</td><td><div>Mar-12</div></td><td><div>Apr-12</div></td><td>Preparation of a Declaration of Assurance in respect of the Lifelong Learning Programme</td><td><div><font color="#000080">&euro;16,568.10</font></div></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td><div><b>2012 Total:</b></div></td><td><div><b>&euro;177,615.24</b></div></td></tr></table></p></reply>
</publicwhip>