<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.3" nospeaker="true" ><p>Questions Nos. 1 to 86, inclusive, resubmitted.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.4" nospeaker="true" ><p>Questions Nos. 87 to 97, inclusive, answered orally.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.6" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA00400">Department of Communications, Energy and Natural Resources</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.5" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA00350">Warmer Homes Scheme Funding</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.6.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1083" speakername="Michael Colreavy" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA00400"><p><i>98.</i> To ask the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources the projected cost of providing funding for window and door insulation as part of the better energy warmer homes scheme.  <b>[31750/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.7.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA00500"><p>The Better Energy Warmer Homes Scheme is administered by the Sustainable Energy Authority of Ireland (SEAI) on behalf of my Department as part of the Better Energy Programme.  Since 2009, the scheme has supported the renovation of almost 97,000 homes in Ireland.</p>  <p>  Under the Better Energy Warmer Homes Scheme, energy efficiency upgrades are provided free of charge to those households who meet the application criteria.  Measures are provided under the scheme on an "as needed" basis and include draught proofing, attic insulation, lagging jackets for hot water tanks, low energy light bulbs and cavity wall insulation. </p>  <p>  Window and door insulation are not currently supported under the Better Energy Warmer Homes Scheme due to the need to balance the limited resources available with the demands for this scheme.  Therefore, the measures currently supported are those that can deliver the most energy savings at the lowest cost. While both window and door insulation do improve the energy efficiency of a home, the cost of such measures is high in relation to the energy efficiency gains made.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.8" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA00550">Inland Fisheries Ireland</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.9.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1083" speakername="Michael Colreavy" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA00600"><p><i>99.</i> To ask the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources if his Department will provide resourcing to Inland Fisheries Ireland to ensure that it is able to meet its statutory obligations, as legislated under the Fisheries Acts.  <b>[31749/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.10.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA00700"><p>Inland Fisheries Ireland was established in 2010. In the five year period 2010-2014 substantial Exchequer support, amounting to almost &euro;130 million, has been provided for IFI.  Almost &euro;24 million has been provided for IFI in my Department's Vote this year.</p>  <p>  The establishment of IFI has provided for an improved national perspective in the formulation of inland fisheries policy which is more streamlined, coherent and integrated.  It also facilitates the achievement of efficiencies in the effective management of the inland fisheries resource. </p>  <p>  The Deputy will also appreciate that the Board and Senior Management of IFI have a key role in ensuring that the Agency continues to meet its objectives towards the conservation, protection, promotion and development of the inland fisheries resource.  In achieving its objectives, IFI is delivering on the imperative, common to all Public Bodies, to achieve efficiencies and to maintain a high level of service.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.11" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA00750">National Postcode System Implementation</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.12.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1190" speakername="Tommy Broughan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA00800"><p><i>100.</i> To ask the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources if he will report on the roll out of the recently introduced Eircode; if his Department is monitoring the usage of Eircode; and if he will make a statement on the matter.  <b>[31688/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.13.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA00900"><p>Eircode, the National Postcode System for Ireland was officially launched by the Minister on 13 July 2015 together with the new online &lsquo;Eircode finder tool&rsquo; on the website .  The Eircode Finder, is an eircode look up application that helps citizens and business to fully utilise the new postcode system.  There was significant interest in the &lsquo;Eircode finder tool&rsquo; on launch day with over 800,000 look ups when it went live. During the three weeks following the launch, the 2.2 million residential and business address in Ireland received a letter in the post informing them of the new eircode for that address.</p><p>A successful national information campaign was completed over the summer to inform the public about eircodes and promote their usage.  The campaign included advertisements in the national media, including TV, radio and newspapers. The media campaign ran until 30 August 2015. </p><p>An integral element of the communications strategy was the Community Outreach Programme for eircodes using networks of community and voluntary organisations, in conjunction with the Wheel and Irish Rural Link.  The aim of this programme was to provide information on eircodes and their benefits to people and groups that mainstream communications may not have reached.  This approach allowed any concerns to be addressed locally in a timely manner.  Over the course of the Community Outreach Programme 15,377 organisations received information about Eircode with 10,620 volunteers recruited to assist. During this phase 4,722 local organisations were mobilised and 1,235 events were held involving the target group.</p><p>During the dissemination phase of eircodes, Am&aacute;rach, an independent body, conducted two parallel surveys, a face-to-face survey of 1,200 households and 200 business premises.  The results of the surveys showed that 89% of the public knew the eircode for their address.</p><p>Public Sector bodies, particularly those with large customer facing operations, have started using eircodes in customer engagement and this process will continue over the coming months.</p><p>Since launch the Eircode contractor has been engaging with commercial organisations and, to date, has signed up a total of eighteen Value Added Resellers who provide a broad spectrum of eircode specialist services to businesses including Database cleansing, Address lookup and GeoCoding.  In accordance with the contract for the development and maintenance of eircodes, my Department has put in place reporting structures with the contractor which will, inter alia, include information on the commercial use of the Eircode system.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.14" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA00950">National Broadband Plan Implementation</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.15.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/987" speakername="Michael Moynihan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA01000"><p><i>101.</i> To ask the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources the broadband technology that the planned State intervention under the national broadband plan will use; his views on the timeframe to connect all premises to high speed broadband Internet; and if he will make a statement on the matter.  <b>[31786/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.16.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA01100"><p>The National Broadband Plan proposed Intervention Strategy document, which was published on 15 July last, sets out a series of detailed proposals by Government in respect of the proposed State intervention. It sets out the key elements of the intervention - what services are proposed and how they will be delivered. It outlines various aspects of the proposed intervention including the type of network envisaged, the minimum speeds being demanded, the length of the contract for services, and whether the network should be public or privately owned.  The draft Intervention Strategy has been developed following intensive engagement with industry and wider stakeholders. </p>  <p>  In addition, the European Commission has set out detailed guidelines on what is required to obtain State Aid approval for Government interventions in the broadband sector. The Department of Communications, Energy and Natural Resources has followed these guidelines when formulating the proposed intervention strategy. Key among those guidelines is the requirement to observe a strict policy of technology neutrality in designing an intervention programme and in running a procurement process.</p>  <p>  Therefore, the Department cannot and will not specify any particular technology platform when going to the market to secure a potential bidder or bidders for the NBP contract. It will be up to bidders to set out clearly in their bid how they propose to meet the standard of services being sought by the Government. However, it is anticipated that any proposals from bidders will have fibre technology as a key element within their solution. It is recognised within industry that fibre is the technology of choice for at least the backhaul part of the network. </p>  <p>  The Strategy demonstrates clearly the Government&rsquo;s commitment to honouring its pledge to deal definitively with the challenge of providing resilient and high-quality broadband connectivity to every premises in the country, irrespective of location.</p></reply>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.18.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1110" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA01200"><p><i>102.</i> To ask the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources the status of the national broadband plan; the level of engagement between his Department and private telecommunications operators with regard to those companies' plans for broadband, particularly in rural locations; and if he will make a statement on the matter.  <b>[31757/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.19.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA01300"><p>The Minister published the draft Intervention Strategy for public consultation on 15 July 2015 and the draft strategy and relevant expert reports are available on the NBP website . This public consultation closes on the 25<sup>th</sup>of this month. Following the consultation process, the Minister plans to move to formal procurement phase towards the end of this year in order to select a preferred bidder or bidders.The physical build of the network is expected to begin in late 2016, and it will take 3-5 years to fully complete &ndash; depending on the details of the bid or bids selected. </p><p>This complex national infrastructure project will definitively address the long-standing challenge of deploying a resilient and high-quality broadband network, particularly in rural parts of Ireland.</p><p>An intrinsic part of the Department's approach to planning and developing the NBP strategy has been to engage with all stakeholders and, in particular, with industry. This engagement has enabled the production of the national high speed broadband coverage map in November last which is currently being updated, again in close collaboration with industry.</p><p>Details of meetings with industry and of site visits to particular trials or projects being run by individual operators are provided in the Department's monthly NBP update which is available on the Department's website and which is emailed to all Oireachtas members. </p><p>Departmental officials will continue to liaise closely with the commercial operators until such time as the project moves to formal procurement phase.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.20" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA01350">Transatlantic Trade and Investment Partnership</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.21.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1005" speakername="Maureen O'Sullivan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA01400"><p><i>103.</i> To ask the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources his views on the investment State dispute settlement as part of the Transatlantic Trade Investment Partnership, and its ability to challenge indirect expropriation, when the potential profits of an investment may be reduced because of a regulatory change or other decisions by a public authority which includes bans on energy extraction; and if he will make a statement on the matter.  <b>[31760/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.22.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA01500"><p>As the Deputy may be aware, in June 2013, EU Member States authorised the European Commission to commence trade and investment negotiations with the US and those negotiations are ongoing. The purpose of the trade negotiations is to reduce barriers to trade and investment in order to generate jobs and growth. Ireland stands to gain significantly from this because of the existing significant flows of trade and investment between Ireland and the US and briefing and update material on these negotiations can be found on the website of the Department of Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation <i><font color="#0000FF">.</font></i>I can assure the Deputy that conclusion of an agreement will have no impact on the public policy approach adopted by Ireland in the area of exploration for hydrocarbon resources. </p><p>The scope of the EU Commission&rsquo;s mandate to negotiate with the United States includes investment protection and investor state dispute settlement. Countries sign such agreements in order to set out certain ground rules when foreign companies invest on their territory. The EU Commission&rsquo;s mandate to negotiate clearly provides that the objectives of any investment protection provisions would be without prejudice to the right of the EU and Member States to adopt and enforce measures necessary to pursue legitimate public policy objectives such as social, environmental, security, stability of the financial system, public health and safety, in a non-discriminatory manner.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.23" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA01550">Renewable Energy Projects</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.24.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/956" speakername="Mick Wallace" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA01600"><p><i>104.</i> To ask the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources the measures his Department is considering in order to facilitate community renewable energy generation projects; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[31791/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.25.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA01700"><p>One of the central themes in the Green Paper on Energy Policy, published in May 2014, is citizen empowerment. Since its publication the Department undertook a public consultation process which included analysis of over 1200 written submissions and thirteen stakeholder seminars, held in Dublin, Westmeath, Sligo, Cork and Wexford, on the various priority areas highlighted in the Green Paper.  A recurring message coming from both the written submissions and the seminars was the role that community energy could play in our future energy systems. The views submitted are being considered in the formation of the Energy White Paper, which will be published before the end of the year, and which will, <i>inter alia,</i>address community energy projects and how best to facilitate communities in playing their part.</p><p>I should also highlight the various community level initiatives administered on behalf of the Department by the SEAI. These include the development of community energy projects through the Better Energy Areas and Communities Programme which allows community and locally based organisations to apply for funding on a competitive basis to support sustainable energy upgrades to existing buildings and facilities. It also promotes the creation and development of locally based entities that can engage and mobilise community resources to lower energy bills and boost local employment.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.26" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA01750">Renewable Energy Feed in Tariff Scheme Implementation</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.27.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1053" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA01800"><p><i>105.</i> To ask the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources his views that the current tariffs imposed on biodigesters are uncompetitive; his plans to raise these tariffs in order to encourage all sources of renewable energy; and if he will make a statement on the matter.  <b>[31691/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.28.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA01900"><p>Electricity and heat produced from anaerobic digestion (AD) are supported under the REFIT 3 scheme. The rates of tariff for AD technologies available under the scheme were calculated following analysis by the Department along with the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine, the Sustainable Energy Authority of Ireland, and Teagasc. Since the introduction of the scheme in 2012, the Department has received a number of applications from AD plants for support.</p>  <p>  The cost effectiveness of support for renewables is a key consideration in the work now underway in the Department to consider the appropriateness and design of new support schemes for renewable electricity and renewable heat. The initial public consultations on the two proposed new schemes for heat and electricity respectively closed on Friday, 18 September 2015. There will be a further two opportunities for the public to contribute to the development of the schemes. A key consideration in the design of the schemes will be the available technologies, their cost effectiveness and the level of any support required. Both schemes are expected to be available in 2016 subject to EU state aid clearance and Government approval.</p>  <p>  It is also worth noting that academic and industry research suggests that there is the potential for a significant role in the heat and transport sectors for biogas, which is produced by anaerobic digestion. The draft Bioenergy Plan, published by the Minister last year, recommended that a detailed economic assessment of the costs and benefits of biogas would be conducted. </p>  <p>  The Bioenergy Steering Group, which has been established to coordinate the implementation of the draft Plan, is currently finalising the request for tender document and the Department expects to be inviting tenders for this work shortly.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.29" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA01950">Renewable Energy Generation</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.30.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1005" speakername="Maureen O'Sullivan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA02000"><p><i>106.</i> To ask the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources the action being taken by his Department to encourage development of new wave technology, which provides a sustainable way to harness the natural resources available on the coast here by the use of tidal turbines; and his views that given the extensive coastline here, this form of renewable energy has significant potential to allow a move away from fossil fuels. <b>[31761/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.31.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA02100"><p>The development of Ireland's abundant offshore renewable energy resource will be an increasingly important element of Ireland's future energy policies. Offshore renewable energy has the potential to: generate carbon free renewable electricity; reduce our dependence on imported fossil fuels; enhance our security of energy supply; and deliver green growth and jobs to the economy.</p>  <p>  Policy action across a range of areas is required to support developers in bringing ocean energy devices, including wave and tidal, from prototype to full scale commerciality. Such action is being taken in the context of the implementation of the 2014 Offshore Renewable Energy Development Plan (OREDP), which sets out Government policy in relation to the sustainable development of Ireland's abundant offshore renewable energy resources. A Steering Group, chaired by the Department of Communications, Energy and Natural Resources (DCENR), has been established which includes representatives from other relevant government departments and agencies. The Steering Group is overseeing the implementation of the Plan. </p>  <p>  Exchequer support for ocean research, development and demonstration has been provided to the sector in recent years and is being increased under the OREDP. In total, my Department has allocated &euro;26.3 million for ocean energy for the period 2013 to 2016. This supports the development of the test sites in counties Mayo, Galway and Cork, the Integrated Maritime Energy Resource Cluster (IMERC) at Ringaskiddy, and the Prototype Development Fund operated by the Sustainable Energy Authority of Ireland (SEAI), which provides grant aid for the development of prototype ocean energy devices. </p>  <p>  Further funding options are being discussed cross-departmentally and the OREDP also proposes, subject to further Government approval, an initial market support scheme for wave and tidal energy from 2016 onwards.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.32" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA02150">Hydraulic Fracturing</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.33.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1192" speakername="Clare Daly" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA02200"><p><i>107.</i> To ask the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources if he has considered and is concerned by a British Columbia Oil and Gas Commission report that notes that 231 earthquakes triggered by hydraulic fracturing were recorded in the Montney region of British Columbia in 2014; if he has considered and is concerned by recent reports that a hydraulic fracturing company (details supplied) was responsible for triggering an earthquake in August 2015 that measured 4.6 on the Richter scale; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[31714/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.34.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA02300"><p>The research programme directed at examining the potential environmental and human health impacts of hydraulic fracturing commissioned by the Environmental Protection Agency is ongoing. That research programme will have regard to experiences in other countries and draw on published reports and other sources. While the research programme is ongoing, it would not be useful for me as Minister to comment on individual reports.</p>  <p>  I can once again reiterate that no decision will be made on any proposal for the use of hydraulic fracturing in exploration drilling in Ireland as part of an unconventional gas exploration programme until there has been time to consider the outcome of the research programme commissioned by the Environmental Protection Agency.</p></reply>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.36.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/956" speakername="Mick Wallace" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA02400"><p><i>108.</i> To ask the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources if he has read the recent study on water quality across the Barnett Shale in Texas in the United States of America, which appeared in the peer-reviewed Environmental Science and Technology, and which found that, near to hydraulic fracturing centres, drinking water has more chemicals and carcinogens; in view of this study, and the extensive scientific research that has found hydraulic fracturing to have substantial risks and negative consequences for public health, the environment, and the climate, if he is satisfied with the fact that Ireland is currently considering the viability of this practice through the Environmental Protection Agency study; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[31792/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.37.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA02500"><p>The research programme directed at examining the potential environmental and human health impacts of hydraulic fracturing commissioned by the Environmental Protection Agency is ongoing. That research programme will have regard to experiences in other countries and draw on published reports and other sources. While the research programme is ongoing, it would not be useful for me as Minister to comment on individual reports.</p>  <p>  I can once again reiterate that no decision will be made on any proposal for the use of hydraulic fracturing in exploration drilling in Ireland as part of an unconventional gas exploration programme, until there has been time to consider the outcome of the research programme commissioned by the Environmental Protection Agency.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.38" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA02550">Bord na M&oacute;na</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.39.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/987" speakername="Michael Moynihan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA02600"><p><i>109.</i> To ask the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources his recent discussions with Bord na M&oacute;na on planned redundancies at Bord na M&oacute;na and its subsidiaries; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[31789/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.40.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA02700"><p>While the matter raised by the Deputy is an operational one for the management team at Bord na M&oacute;na, and not one in which the Minister has any function, it is a matter of concern to him. Accordingly, he has been closely monitoring developments in relation to this issue.</p>  <p>  I am advised that the matter of compulsory redundancies at a Bord na M&oacute;na subsidiary, Anua, has recently been the subject of discussions at the Labour Relations Commission. Management and union representatives have agreed to refer the matter to the Labour Court. I am further advised by Bord na M&oacute;na that no action will be taken in relation to these proposed redundancies in advance of the Labour Court&rsquo;s consideration and decision on the matter. </p>  <p>  In relation to the wider Bord na M&oacute;na group, I understand that management and union representatives have engaged under the auspices of the Labour Relations Commission since February 2015 on a range of issues, including possible redundancies, relating to the business transformation agenda within the company. I am advised that management and union representatives have subsequently agreed to refer these issues to the Labour Court. </p>  <p>  It would not be appropriate for me to comment further on these matters while these processes are ongoing.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.41" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA02750">Energy Policy</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.42.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1083" speakername="Michael Colreavy" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA02800"><p><i>110.</i> To ask the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources the measures he has taken at a European level to tackle fuel poverty. <b>[31751/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.43.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA02900"><p>The protection of consumers vulnerable to energy poverty is a critical element of both EU and national energy policy.As the Deputy may be aware, the Department of Communications, Energy and Natural Resources is preparing a new Affordable Energy Strategy following a public consultation held earlier this year. As part of this work, officials are participating in the European Commission's Vulnerable Consumers Working Group having participated in the Energy Citizens Forum held in London in March of this year. I welcome this European Commission initiative along with the publication by the Commission in July of this year of their Communication &quot;Delivering a New Deal for Energy Consumers&quot;.</p><p>That Commission Communication is a supporting policy document to the Energy Union Framework Strategy which sets out the vision of an Energy Union &quot;<i>with citizens at its core, where citizens take ownership of the energy transition, benefit from new technologies to reduce their bills, participate actively in the market, and where vulnerable consumers are protected</i>&quot;.</p><p>&quot;Delivering a New Deal for Energy Consumers&quot; identified energy poverty as an important issue requiring Member State action. The Communication also identified energy efficiency as the best way to address energy poverty in the long term, while recognising that this must take place in the wider context of action on poverty. It is the stated position of the Commission that the citizen must be at the heart of the new Energy Union. This means that both the EU, and Member States, must find more effective ways to address energy poverty as part of the action also needed to support and empower energy consumers. The Minister will continue to push for energy poverty to be kept high on the EU energy agenda, and ensure that improving the energy efficiency of homes of those vulnerable to energy poverty remains central to Ireland&rsquo;s Better Energy Programme.</p><p>The Minister expects to publish the new Affordable Energy Strategy around the end of this year.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.44" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA02950">Bord na M&oacute;na</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.45.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1192" speakername="Clare Daly" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA03000"><p><i>111.</i> To ask the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources his views on changes in terms and conditions for Bord na M&oacute;na employees, which will amount to substantial reductions in pay; and on serious allegations of consistent bullying and harassment taking place in the company; his level of awareness of these issues; the action he has taken; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[31713/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.46.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA03100"><p>While the matter raised by the Deputy is an operational one for the management team at Bord na M&oacute;na, and not one in which I, as Minister, have any function, it is a matter of concern to me. Bord na M&oacute;na is facing significant business challenges in the context of the deregulation of the electricity market and increasingly competitive and challenging environments across all its business areas. In order to ensure its continued profitability, the company is implementing a programme to transform all areas of its operations and structure, the key objective of which is to improve business effectiveness and efficiency.</p>  <p>  I am aware that management and union representatives have engaged under the auspices of the Labour Relations Commission since February 2015 on a range of issues relating to the business transformation agenda within the company. These discussions include areas related to the terms and conditions of employees. I am advised that management and union representatives have agreed to refer these issues to the Labour Court. I hope you will appreciate that it would not be appropriate for me to comment further on this matter while this process is ongoing.  In relation to alleged instances of bullying within the company, I am assured by the Board of Bord na M&oacute;na that there are appropriate systems in place to deal with any allegations of bullying. Any employee who has concerns in this regard should bring it to the attention of the appropriate authorities in Bord na M&oacute;na.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.47" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA03150">Telecommunications Infrastructure</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.48.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/957" speakername="Bernard Durkan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA03200"><p><i>112.</i> To ask the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources the steps taken to identify those parts of the country most seriously affected by a lack of a telecommunications service or by a deficient telecommunications service in respect of all forms of all electronic communication, wireless and otherwise; the extent to which adequate infrastructure and investment has been made to address such deficiencies which have shown that in some cases, access to broadband and mobile telephony is non-existent; if the various agencies, bodies, statutory or otherwise, responsible have set out fully their proposals to address the issue; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[31753/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.49.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA03300"><p>The provision of mobile telephony services is subject to a requirement to secure access to the required radio spectrum by way of licence. The management of the radio spectrum is a statutory function of the Commission for Communications Regulation under the Communications Regulation Act, 2002 as amended. Licences issued by ComReg apply terms and conditions on Mobile Network Operators, such as quality of service and minimum population coverage obligations.</p><p>However, given that mobile services are a radio based technology, services can be affected by several factors. These include topography, the capacity of the network and more generally the level and quality of access customers have to mobile phone antennas. Difficulties for service providers in erecting masts and antennas due to planning issues can also impact negatively on the quality of coverage experienced by consumers.</p><p>In terms of improving the quality and coverage of mobile services in all areas throughout the country, there are various initiatives underway to achieve this aim. </p><p>The commercial telecommunications sector is currently investing approximately &euro;2.5bn in upgrading and modernising both fixed and mobile networks. This includes some &euro;850m invested in acquiring spectrum under the 2012 Multi-Band Spectrum Auction run by ComReg. Since then, the mobile operators have all continued to invest in rolling out 4G and enhanced 3G services nationwide. These investments are improving both the coverage and quality of voice and data services throughout the country, although I understand that some temporary disruptions to service have been encountered when upgrades are taking place.</p><p>While investment in communications infrastructure and services is primarily a matter for the private sector, the National Broadband Plan (NBP) commits to a range of actions that will facilitate the more efficient<font color="#1F497D"> </font>commercial<font color="#1F497D"> </font>investment in the rollout of communications infrastru<font color="#1F497D">c</font>ture.</p><p>The NBP is a Government policy initiative which aims to deliver high speed broadband to every citizen and business in Ireland. This is being achieved through a combination of accelerated commercial investment by telecoms operators, and a proposed State intervention to provide high speed broadband to those parts of the country where the commercial sector will not invest. </p><p>The NBP proposed Intervention Strategy document, which was published on 15 July last, sets out a series of detailed proposals by Government in respect of the proposed State intervention. It sets out the key elements of the intervention - what services are proposed and how they will be delivered. It outlines various aspects of the proposed intervention including the type of network envisaged, the minimum speeds being demanded, the length of the contract for services, and whether the network should be public or privately owned.</p><p>Since publication of the Plan in 2012, a working group has been established to address infrastructure issues which were identified by industry as creating barriers to deployment of services. The group is chaired by the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport and includes representatives from my Department, the Local Government Management Agency, the National Roads Authority (NRA) and Local Authorities. The Group is currently consulting with industry on a range of issues relating to the siting of telecommunications infrastructure. My Department will continue to actively engage on this issue with a view to facilitating the removal of barriers and the improvement of mobile service nationwide. </p><p>Local Authorities also have an important role to play in terms of facilitating the siting of necessary infrastructure such as masts and antennae etc. The Telecommunications and Internet Federation (TIF, which is part of IBEC) has been proactive in seeking to meet with Local Authorities and public representatives to fully discuss the various issues around mobile coverage and the factors that can impact on the quality of service consumers experience.</p><p>I would encourage all Local Authorities and public representatives to engage with the TIF on these important issues.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.50" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA03350">Energy Resources</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.51.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1005" speakername="Maureen O'Sullivan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA03400"><p><i>113.</i> To ask the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources the action being taken to explore the possibilities of treatment and extraction from wastewater, which has great potential as a sustainable resource. <b>[31762/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.52.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA03500"><p>Ireland&rsquo;s energy policies recognise the importance of waste material as an energy resource. Both the Alternative Energy Requirement and Renewable Energy Feed-in Tariff schemes support electricity generated from landfill gas and the biodegradable element of municipal solid waste as well as energy from anaerobic digestion (AD). Anaerobic digestion is a technology that can be used to produce energy from organic material including byproducts of wastewater treatment such as sewage sludge. These are now established technologies and are making a contribution to Ireland&rsquo;s renewable energy targets.</p>  <p>  In terms of further developing waste as an energy resource, the draft Bioenergy Plan, published by the Minister last year, recommends that the Department of Environment, Community and Local Government would endeavour to optimise the availability of waste for energy production.</p>  <p>  The forthcoming Energy Policy White Paper, which will be published before the end of the year, will provide a solid policy foundation to encourage more energy innovation, research, development and deployment in Ireland.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.53" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA03550">Broadband Service Provision</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.54.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1001" speakername="Thomas Pringle" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA03600"><p><i>114.</i> To ask the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources in view of the high percentage of premises without access to broadband in County Donegal, if he will consider an expediency plan for the most rural counties like County Donegal, as the timeline for formal procurement for State intervention is already running into the end of this year with no delays expected; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[31794/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.55.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA03700"><p>The National Broadband Plan (NBP) is a Government policy initiative which aims to deliver high speed broadband to every citizen and business in Ireland. This is being achieved through a combination of accelerated commercial investment by telecoms operators, and a proposed State intervention to provide high speed broadband to those parts of the country where the commercial sector will not invest.</p>  <p>  The NBP proposed Intervention Strategy document, which was published on 15 July last, sets out a series of detailed proposals by Government in respect of the proposed State intervention. It sets out the key elements of the intervention - what services are proposed and how they will be delivered. It outlines various aspects of the proposed intervention including the type of network envisaged, the minimum speeds being demanded, the length of the contact for services, and whether the network should be public or privately owned.</p>  <p>  The Government is determined to ensure that the network is built out as quickly as possible and engagement with industry stakeholders has indicated that this could be achieved within 3-5 years of the contract award.</p>  <p>  In this context, the NBP proposes that through the combination of commercial investment and State intervention, 85% of addresses in Ireland will have access to high speed services by 2018 with all addresses passed by 2020. </p>  <p>  The prospective bidder(s) are experts in network roll-out and each will offer different network architectures and technologies to deliver the network. Industry is best placed to determine the sequencing of the network deployment to maximise efficiencies during network build.</p>  <p>  It is proposed however to engage with the winning bidder(s) on the optimum rollout strategy, having regard to business and consumer needs, areas of particularly poor service and areas of strong demand. All these factors will need to be balanced against the most efficient network rollout and will be agreed during the procurement process.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.56" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA03750">Renewable Energy Incentives</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.57.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1083" speakername="Michael Colreavy" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA03800"><p><i>115.</i> To ask the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources if there is a proposed legislative framework to provide for developing renewable energy co-operatives. <b>[31752/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.58.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA03900"><p>Various community level energy initiatives are supported by the Government through the Better Energy Areas and Communities Programme which is administered on behalf of the Department by the Sustainable Energy Authority of Ireland (SEAI). That programme allows community and locally based organisations to apply for funding on a competitive basis to support sustainable energy upgrades to existing buildings and facilities. It also promotes the creation and development of locally based entities that can engage and mobilise community resources to lower energy bills and boost local employment.</p>  <p>  One of the central themes in the Green Paper on Energy Policy, published in May 2014, is citizen empowerment. Since its publication the Department undertook a public consultation process which included analysis of over 1200 written submissions and thirteen stakeholder seminars, held in Dublin, Westmeath, Sligo, Cork and Wexford, on the various priority areas highlighted in the Green Paper. A recurring message coming from both the written submissions and the seminars was the role that community energy could play in our future energy systems. The views submitted are being considered in the formation of the Energy White Paper, which will be published before the end of the year. </p>  <p>  While I do not intend to introduce any legislative proposals that would be specific to the development of renewable energy cooperatives, it is my intention that the forthcoming White Paper would address community energy projects and how best to facilitate communities in playing their part in the transition to a low carbon future.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.59" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA03950">National Broadband Plan Implementation</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.60.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1110" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA04000"><p><i>116.</i> To ask the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources the current status of the decision with regard to the ownership of the new network to be created under the national broadband plan; and if he will make a statement on the matter.  <b>[31758/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.61.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200060#WRA04100"><p>Both the draft Intervention Strategy and accompanying expert reports which I published for public consultation in July last deal in some considerable detail with the various ownership options and models available to Government.</p>  <p>  I am interested in the views of industry and wider stakeholders on this subject and will make a final decision on this aspect of the Intervention Strategy after the public consultation has been concluded.</p></reply>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.64" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB00200">Department of An Taoiseach</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.63" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB00150">Unemployment Data</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.64.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1195" speakername="Ruth Coppinger" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB00200"><p><i>117.</i> To ask the Taoiseach the number of unemployed persons that are not on the live register. <b>[31249/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.65.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1098" speakername="Paul Kehoe" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB00300"><p>The exact information requested by the Deputy is not available.</p>  <p>  The Quarterly National Household Survey (QNHS) is the official source of estimates of unemployment in the State and the seasonally adjusted number of persons (aged 15-74) unemployed as of the second quarter of 2015 was 207,300.  While the QNHS provides quarterly benchmark estimates of unemployment, the CSO also publishes monthly unemployment estimates.  The latest seasonally adjusted monthly unemployment figures for August 2015 indicate that the number of unemployed persons aged 15-74 years in that month was estimated to have been 206,500.</p>  <p>  The primary classification used for the QNHS results is the ILO (International Labour Office) labour force classification.  The classification for unemployed persons includes those persons aged 15-74 years who, in the week before the survey, were without work and available for work within the next two weeks, and had taken specific steps, in the preceding four weeks, to find work.  The QNHS does not capture a respondent's status as measured by the Live Register.</p>  <p>  The Live Register is compiled from returns made for each local office to the Central Statistics Office by the Department of Social Protection.  It comprises persons under 65 years of age in the following classes:</p>  <p>  All Claimants for Jobseeker's Benefit (JB) excluding systematic short-time workers.</p>  <p>  Applicants for Jobseeker's Allowance (JA) excluding smallholders/farm assists and other self-employed persons.</p>  <p>  Other registrants including applicants for credited Social Welfare contributions but excluding those directly involved in an industrial dispute.</p>  <p>  It should be noted that the Live Register is not designed to measure unemployment as per the ILO unemployment classification used by the QNHS.  It includes part-time workers (those who work up to three days a week), seasonal and casual workers entitled to Jobseeker's Benefit or Allowance.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.66" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB00350">Employment Data</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.67.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1065" speakername="Robert Troy" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB00400"><p><i>118.</i> To ask the Taoiseach the number of employed persons on a national basis. <b>[29645/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.68.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1098" speakername="Paul Kehoe" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB00500"><p>The Quarterly National Household Survey (QNHS) is the official source of estimates of employment in the State.  The most recent figures available are for Q2 2015. </p><p>The estimated number of persons aged 15 years and over in employment (ILO) in that quarter was 1,958,700.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.69" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB00550">Economic Data</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.70.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1065" speakername="Robert Troy" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB00600"><p><i>119.</i> To ask the Taoiseach the current gross national product. <b>[29646/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.71.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1098" speakername="Paul Kehoe" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB00700"><p>Nominal Gross National Product (GNP) increased by 7.1% to &euro;162,877m between 2013 and 2014.  Real GNP in 2014 was &euro;162,537m, an increase of 6.9% over the same period.  The table below illustrates the trends in nominal and real GNP for the years 2009 - 2014.  These data are sourced from the National Income and Expenditure accounts results 2014 (NIE 2014) that were published on 30th July 2015 by the Central Statistics Office.<table><tr><th>From National Income &amp;amp; Expenditure 2014 (NIE 2014) results published 30.07.2015</th><th>2009</th><th>2010</th><th>2011</th><th>2012</th><th>2013</th><th>2014</th></tr><tr><td>Gross National Product at Current Market Prices - &euro; million</td><td>140,915</td><td>139,732</td><td>141,813</td><td>143,331</td><td>152,042</td><td>162,877</td></tr><tr><td>Annual Percentage Change</td><td>-12.9%</td><td>-0.8%</td><td>+1.5%</td><td>+1.1%</td><td>+6.1%</td><td>+7.1%</td></tr><tr><td>Gross National Product at Constant Market Prices - &euro; million (Chain Linked Annually and referenced to year 2013)</td><td>141,031</td><td>144,169</td><td>142,976</td><td>145,318</td><td>152,042</td><td>162,537</td></tr><tr><td>Annual Percentage Change</td><td>-8.0%</td><td>+2.2%</td><td>-0.8%</td><td>+1.6%</td><td>+4.6%</td><td>+6.9%</td></tr></table></p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.72" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB00713">Income Data</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.73.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/990" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Lynch" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB00725"><p><i>120.</i> To ask the Taoiseach the current pay as you earn average industrial wage, gross and net, on an annual and on a weekly basis; and if he will make a statement on the matter.  <b>[29601/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.74.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1098" speakername="Paul Kehoe" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB00737"><p>The Earning, Hours and Employment Costs Survey (EHECS) is the source of earnings and labour costs data for Ireland.</p><p>The most recent final results available are for quarter 1 2015.</p><p>EHECS collects gross earnings and labour costs at firm level and thus cannot provide data on net earnings.</p><p>The gross average weekly earnings for production workers, in the <i>Industry</i>sector  (NACE B-E), in firms with 3 or more employees, in Quarter 1 2015 is estimated to be &euro;654.85.  This is the equivalent of the gross average industrial wage.</p><p>An annual average earnings for production workers in the <i>Industry </i>sector is not produced.  However, using four quarterly estimates an annual average can be derived. </p><p>The derived gross annual average earnings for production workers in the <i>Industry </i>sector for 2014 is &euro;35,349.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.75" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB00750">European Banking Sector</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.76.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1197" speakername="Paul Murphy" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB00800"><p><i>121.</i> To ask the Taoiseach his discussions with other European Union Heads of Government, from 11 to 13 July 2015, regarding the Greek financial situation. <b>[30485/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.77.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1072" speakername="Enda Kenny" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB00900"><p>On 12-13 July I attended a special meeting of the Euro Summit in Brussels aimed at seeking a resolution to the Greek crisis.  After lengthy and difficult discussions, the Euro Summit reached agreement on a series of measures that enabled negotiations on a third programme of assistance to begin between Greece and the Institutions.  Satisfactory progress in these negotiations, supported by the urgent implementation by Greece of a number of demanding conditions, allowed for a political agreement to be reached at Eurogroup level on 14 August and for a first disbursement of additional support on 20 August.</p>  <p>  At the European Council meeting of 25-26 June, Heads of State and Government urged Prime Minister Tsipras to make every effort to conclude an agreement and put an end to the instability which was having such a detrimental effect on the Greek economy and people.  At that time, negotiations were being taken forward with the Institutions and by Finance Ministers through the Eurogroup.  However, following the breaking off of negotiations by the Greek government, the holding of a referendum on 5 July, and the radical deterioration of Greece&rsquo;s financial situation, the situation in Greece was felt to require a special Euro Summit meeting on 7 July.  It was agreed that the Greek government would, on Thursday 9 July at the latest, present proposals for a comprehensive and specific reform agenda for assessment by the three institutions and presentation to the Eurogroup.  The Eurogroup considered these proposals at meetings on 11 and 12 July, prior to the meeting of the Euro Summit.</p>  <p>  Throughout all of the European Council and Euro Summit negotiations, I expressed Ireland's understanding and empathy with the difficult situation faced by the Greek people.  I highlighted our willingness to negotiate a way forward and achieve a sustainable solution that took account of the realities of the situation in Greece, while also respecting existing commitments.  I stressed our determination to ensure that Greece can continue as a member of the euro area.  At both of the Euro Summits in July, I intervened along these lines, and participated in the Summit&rsquo;s negotiations on the texts of the Conclusions. </p>  <p>  The negotiations were undoubtedly difficult and Greece remains in a very challenging situation.  However, if the agreed measures continue to be taken forward swiftly in accordance with the commitments made, as they have been to date, I believe that there is a real basis for Greece, with the support of partners, to return to stability and growth within the euro area.  That is the objective towards which we have all worked and will continue to work. </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.78" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB00950">Departmental Strategies</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.79.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1206" speakername="Terence Flanagan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB01000"><p><i>122.</i> To ask the Taoiseach his Department's priorities for the remainder of this D&aacute;il; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[30487/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.80.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1072" speakername="Enda Kenny" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB01100"><p>The priority for my Department is to support the Government in implementing the commitments set out in the Programme for Government and the more recent Statement of Government Priorities which set out the key priorities for the remainder of the Government's term of office:</p><p>- Strengthening the Domestic Economy &amp;amp; Prioritising New Jobs for the Unemployed </p><p>- Delivering Better Living and Working Standards </p><p>- Improving Housing Availability &amp;amp; Affordability </p><p>- Responsible and Sustainable Management of the Public Finances </p><p>- Rebuilding Trust in Politics &amp;amp; Public Institutions </p><p>- Protecting &amp;amp; Enhancing Peace in Northern Ireland </p><p>Progress on the implementation of these priorities is included in the Programme for Government Annual Report published each March.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.81" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB01150">Departmental Expenditure</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.82.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1177" speakername="Denis Naughten" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB01200"><p><i>123.</i> To ask the Taoiseach the cost of issuing hard-copy payslips to staff or retired staff by his Department and by agencies under the control of his Department, in 2013; and in 2014; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[30488/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.83.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1072" speakername="Enda Kenny" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB01300"><p>As a matter of policy my Department and the National Economic and Social Development Office issue electronic payslips to staff.  However, in exceptional circumstances, where a staff member demonstrates a requirement for a hard-copy payslip, they may be accommodated.</p>  <p>  While there is no direct cost to my Department, any costs in issuing hard-copy payslips are borne by the Payroll Shared Services Centre which is in the Department of Public Expenditure are Reform.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.84" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB01350">Departmental Advertising Expenditure</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.85.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1177" speakername="Denis Naughten" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB01400"><p><i>124.</i> To ask the Taoiseach the cost of public advertising, statutory and non-statutory, funded by his Department in 2013; and in 2014; the corresponding figure for agencies under the control of his Department; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[30489/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.86.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1072" speakername="Enda Kenny" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB01500"><p>The following tables details expenditure by my Department and the Bodies under the aegis of my Department on public advertising, statutory and non-statutory, in 2013 and 2014.<table><tr><th>Department</th><th></th><th></th></tr><tr><td>Year</td><td>Statutory Advertising</td><td>Non-Statutory Advertising</td></tr><tr><td>2013</td><td>&euro;3,470.00</td><td>&euro;68,128.27</td></tr><tr><td>2014</td><td>&euro;5,712.00</td><td>&euro;6,191.82</td></tr></table><table><tr><th>NESDO</th><th></th><th></th></tr><tr><td>Year</td><td>Statutory Advertising</td><td>Non-Statutory Advertising</td></tr><tr><td>2013</td><td>NIL</td><td>NIL</td></tr><tr><td>2014</td><td>NIL</td><td>NIL</td></tr></table>*The majority of Non-Statutory Advertising in 2013 related to the EU Presidency.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.87" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB01550">Departmental Expenditure</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.88.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1177" speakername="Denis Naughten" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB01600"><p><i>125.</i> To ask the Taoiseach if his Department or agencies under the authority of his Department have performed an assessment of the potential savings to be accrued, if current paper-based application processes by members of the public were replaced with a fully online application system; and if he will make a statement on the matter.  <b>[30490/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.89.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1072" speakername="Enda Kenny" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB01700"><p>My Department's work focuses primarily on dealings with Government and with other Government Departments and agencies, however, it does receive a small number of applications from members of the public for funding under a limited number of schemes (for example the Communicating Europe Initiative and the Local Diaspora Engagement Fund).  In all cases the application forms are available online and applications are received via e-mail.  Given the small number of applications and the capital costs in developing an automated online application process, there would be limited or no potential savings to be accrued by moving to a fully online application process.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.90" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB01750">Departmental Funding</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.91.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1177" speakername="Denis Naughten" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB01800"><p><i>126.</i> To ask the Taoiseach the current funding, and the capital funding, allocated to his Department; the underspend or overspend in each category, in 2015 to date, based on his Department's spending profile; the funding made available within, and external to, his Department's functions in supporting innovation; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[30491/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.92.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1072" speakername="Enda Kenny" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB01900"><p>My Department has no capital funding.  The total current funding allocation in 2015 is &euro;27.022 million.  At end of August spend was at 88% of profiled expenditure.  My Department supports the implementation of Government policy on innovation in a range of ways, including through the work of Cabinet committees and through support for implementation of the Action Plan for Jobs.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.93" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB01950">Departmental Expenditure</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.94.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1177" speakername="Denis Naughten" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB02000"><p><i>127.</i> To ask the Taoiseach the cost in 2013, and in 2014, of printing reports by his Department and by agencies under the control of his Department; the corresponding figures for annual reports; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[30492/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.95.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1072" speakername="Enda Kenny" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB02100"><p>No printing costs for the production of reports were incurred by my Department or the agencies under my Department in 2013 or 2014.  </p><p>Any reports that were produced during the years mentioned above were either published on my Department's website or produced by the shared printing service in the Department of Finance.</p></reply>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.97.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1204" speakername="Lucinda Creighton" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB02200"><p><i>128.</i> To ask the Taoiseach if he will outline and itemise expenditure by his Department on the travel undertaken by the Taoiseach's private office on hotel accommodation, for him and-or his private office staff during the 12 month period to 30 June 2015; if he will outline and itemise expenditure by his Department on legal fees; and on consultancy fees, during the 12 month period to 30 June 2015; and if he will make a statement on the matter.  <b>[30543/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.98.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1072" speakername="Enda Kenny" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB02300"><p>The table below provides details of expenditure by my Department on travel undertaken by my private office and myself on hotel accommodation from 30th June 2014 to 30th June 2015.<table><tr><th>Vendor Name</th><th>Amount Paid</th><th>Description</th><th>Payment Date</th></tr><tr><td>DEPT OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS &amp;amp; TRADE</td><td>&euro;220.00</td><td>Renaissance Hotel, Brussels, Taoiseach's Personal Assistant, 16 July, 2014, Special European Council Meeting.</td><td>11-Dec-14</td></tr><tr><td>DEPT OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS &amp;amp; TRADE</td><td>&euro;220.00</td><td>Renaissance Hotel, Taoiseach, Enda Kenny, 16 July, 2014. Special European Council Meeting.</td><td>11-Dec-14</td></tr><tr><td>DEPT OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS &amp;amp; TRADE</td><td>&euro;208.00</td><td>Renaissance Hotel, Brussels, 30 August 2014 for Taoiseach Enda Kenny.</td><td>11-Dec-14</td></tr><tr><td>DEPT OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS &amp;amp; TRADE</td><td>&euro;220.00</td><td>Renaissance Hotel, Taoiseach's Security Detail, 16 July, 2014. Special European Council Meeting.</td><td>11-Dec-14</td></tr><tr><td>DEPT OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS &amp;amp; TRADE</td><td>&euro;220.00</td><td>Renaissance Hotel, Brussels, Assistant Private Secretary  to the Taoiseach, 16 July, 2014, Special European Council Meeting.</td><td>11-Dec-14</td></tr><tr><td>ADC to the Taoiseach</td><td>&euro;49.00</td><td>Representing An Taoiseach at Funeral </td><td>30-Dec-14</td></tr><tr><td>BANK OF IRELAND (credit card transaction)</td><td>&euro;271.92</td><td>Central Sporthotel Davon 23 Jan 2015, refreshments for 2 briefing meetings with Taoiseach Enda Kenny TD with 7 delegates</td><td>23-Feb-15</td></tr><tr><td>BANK OF IRELAND (credit card transaction)</td><td>&euro;1,274.29</td><td>PublicisLive - Hotel accommodation, World Economic Forum Annual meeting 2015 Davos-Klosters 21-24 Jan 2015 for Taoiseach Enda Kenny TD</td><td>23-Feb-15</td></tr><tr><td>BANK OF IRELAND (credit card transaction)</td><td>&euro;986.39</td><td>PublicisLive - Hotel accommodation World Economic Forum Annual meeting 2015 Davos-Klosters 21-24 Jan 2015 for Taoiseach's Personal Assistant accompanying the Taoiseach Enda Kenny TD</td><td>23-Feb-15</td></tr><tr><td>DEPT OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS &amp;amp; TRADE</td><td>&euro;2,548.72</td><td>Accommodation at Fitzpatrick Grand Central Hotel, New York, 22-24 September 2014 for the Taoiseach, Taoiseach's Personal Assistant, Taoiseach's Security Detail and Private Secretary to Taoiseach -  Climate Change Meetings.</td><td>05-Mar-15</td></tr><tr><td>DEPT OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS &amp;amp; TRADE</td><td>&euro;835.98</td><td>Accommodation at Fitzpatrick Hotel, New York, 13 November 2014 for Taoiseach, Assistant Private Secretary and Personal Assistant </td><td>05-Mar-15</td></tr><tr><td>DEPT OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS &amp;amp; TRADE</td><td>&euro;378.00</td><td>Renaissance Hotel, Brussels, 22 &amp;amp; 23 October 2014,  Assistant Private Secretary to the Taoiseach,  European Council Meeting.</td><td>12-Mar-15</td></tr><tr><td>DEPT OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS &amp;amp; TRADE</td><td>&euro;498.00</td><td>Renaissance Hotel, Brussels,  22nd and 23rd October 2014, Taoiseach's Security Detail. European Council Meeting.</td><td>12-Mar-15</td></tr><tr><td>DEPT OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS &amp;amp; TRADE</td><td>&euro;400.00</td><td>Renaissance Hotel, Brussels, 24th October 2014. Briefing Room Hire for European Council Meeting,</td><td>12-Mar-15</td></tr><tr><td>DEPT OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS &amp;amp; TRADE</td><td>&euro;319.00</td><td>Stormont Hotel, Belfast, Accommodation, 11-12 December 2014. Taoiseach Enda Kenny. Stormont Talks.</td><td>12-Mar-15</td></tr><tr><td>DEPT OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS &amp;amp; TRADE</td><td>&euro;723.91</td><td>DAVOS Hodel: Apartment Accommodation at World Economic Forum, 2015 for Taoiseach's Security Detail.</td><td>12-Mar-15</td></tr><tr><td>DEPT OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS &amp;amp; TRADE</td><td>&euro;95.70</td><td>Stormont Hotel, Belfast, Accommodation, 11-12 December 2014. Private Secretary to the Taoiseach, Stormont Talks.</td><td>12-Mar-15</td></tr><tr><td>DEPT OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS &amp;amp; TRADE</td><td>&euro;249.00</td><td>Renaissance Hotel, Brussels, 23 October, 2014, Personal Assistant - European Council Meeting.</td><td>12-Mar-15</td></tr><tr><td>DEPT OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS &amp;amp; TRADE</td><td>&euro;38.28</td><td>Stormont Hotel, Belfast, Press Conference, 11-12 December 2014. Stormont Talks.</td><td>12-Mar-15</td></tr><tr><td>DEPT OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS &amp;amp; TRADE</td><td>&euro;723.91</td><td>DAVOS Hodel: Apartment Accommodation at World Economic Forum, 2015 for Private Secretary to the Taoiseach.</td><td>12-Mar-15</td></tr><tr><td>DEPT OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS &amp;amp; TRADE</td><td>&euro;249.00</td><td>Renaissance Hotel, Brussels, 23 October 2014, Taoiseach, Enda Kenny. European Council Meeting</td><td>12-Mar-15</td></tr><tr><td>DEPT OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS &amp;amp; TRADE</td><td>&euro;555.06</td><td>Stormont Hotel, Belfast, Meeting Room &amp;amp; Refreshment, 11-12 December 2014. Stormont Talks.</td><td>12-Mar-15</td></tr><tr><td>DEPT OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS &amp;amp; TRADE</td><td>&euro;319.00</td><td>Stormont Hotel, Belfast, Accommodation, 11-12 December 2014. Taoiseach's Security Detail. Stormont Talks.</td><td>12-Mar-15</td></tr><tr><td>DEPT OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS &amp;amp; TRADE</td><td>&euro;756.00</td><td>Accommodation at The Renaissance Hotel, Brussels for Taoiseach, Enda Kenny, Assistant Private Secretary to the Taoiseach, Personal Assistant,  &amp;amp; Taoiseach's Security Detail, 18 December 2014. EC Meeting.</td><td>19-Mar-15</td></tr><tr><td>ADC to the Taoiseach</td><td>&euro;70.00</td><td>Representing An Taoiseach at Funeral </td><td>15-May-15</td></tr></table>*It should be noted that some travel which occurred during the twelve month period to 30 June 2015 has not yet been invoiced by the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade and so is not included in the table above. </p><p>The tables below provide details of expenditure by my Department on legal fees and consultancy from 30th June 2014 to 30th June 2015.</p><p><b><i>Legal Fees</i></b><table><tr><th>Vendor Name</th><th>Amount Paid</th><th>Description</th><th>Payment Date</th></tr><tr><td>State Claims Agency</td><td>&euro;442.80</td><td>Legal charges</td><td>17-Nov-14</td></tr><tr><td>State Claims Agency</td><td>&euro;8,284.50</td><td>Legal charges</td><td>17-Nov-14</td></tr><tr><td>State Claims Agency</td><td>&euro;31.68</td><td>Legal charges</td><td>30-Mar-15</td></tr><tr><td>State Claims Agency</td><td>&euro;63.20</td><td>Legal charges</td><td>20-Apr-15</td></tr><tr><td>State Claims Agency</td><td>&euro;452.64</td><td>Legal charges</td><td>20-Apr-15</td></tr><tr><td>State Claims Agency</td><td>&euro;565.80</td><td>Legal charges</td><td>21-May-15</td></tr><tr><td>State Claims Agency</td><td>&euro;126.61</td><td>Legal charges</td><td>11-Jun-15</td></tr></table></p><p><b><i>Consultancy</i></b><table><tr><th>Vendor Name</th><th>Amount Paid</th><th>Description</th><th>Payment Date</th></tr><tr><td>UNIVERSITY COLLEGE DUBLIN</td><td>&euro;3,567.00</td><td>Leadership Development Programme</td><td>29-Sep-14</td></tr><tr><td>QTS LIMITED</td><td>&euro;1,783.50</td><td>Risk Assessment &amp;amp; full review and update of Health &amp;amp; Safety Statement</td><td>28-Oct-14</td></tr><tr><td>RA CONSULTING</td><td>&euro;9,298.80</td><td>Design &amp;amp; Implementation of a Staff Consultation Initiative</td><td>22-Dec-14</td></tr><tr><td>RA CONSULTING</td><td>&euro;9,298.80</td><td>Design &amp;amp; Implementation of a Staff Consultation Initiative</td><td>09-Mar-15</td></tr></table></p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.99" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB02350">Departmental Funding</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.100.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/956" speakername="Mick Wallace" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB02400"><p><i>129.</i> To ask the Taoiseach if he will provide a breakdown of the State funding that his Department has awarded to foreign private companies and to indigenous private companies, from 2011 to 2014 and in 2015 to date; and if he will make a statement on the matter.  <b>[30545/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.101.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1072" speakername="Enda Kenny" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB02500"><p>My Department has not awarded State funding to foreign private companies or to indigenous private companies in the years 2011 to 16 September 2015.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.102" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB02550">Departmental Reports</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.103.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/983" speakername="Billy Kelleher" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB02600"><p><i>130.</i> To ask the Taoiseach when his Department will publish its annual report for 2014.  <b>[30546/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.104.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1072" speakername="Enda Kenny" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB02700"><p>The Department of the Taoiseach Annual Report 2014 was published on the Department's website and laid before the Houses of the Oireachtas in July 2015.  </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.105" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB02725">Departmental Legal Costs</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.106.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/959" speakername="Pearse Doherty" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB02800"><p><i>131.</i> To ask the Taoiseach if he will provide details of all barristers, senior and junior counsel, briefed by the Office of the Attorney General for the years 2011 to 2014 and up to September 2015; and if he will provide details of their remuneration and specifically the amount of fees earned by each individual barrister for the years 2011 to 2014 and up to September 2015. <b>[31559/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.107.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1072" speakername="Enda Kenny" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB02900"><p>The following tables show the information requested by the Deputy.</p><p>In relation to all the figures supplied it is important to note that they are based on total payments made to counsel during each of those years.  It is possible that some of the payments relate to work that actually took place in earlier periods, including those made to judges in respect of work prior to their appointment.  Similarly, it is likely that counsel have been briefed or have carried out work during more recent periods but if they had not been paid by end of August 2015 they would not appear on the list.  Some payments may have been made to the estate of a deceased counsel which is why <i>Deceased </i>or<i>Personal Representative </i>may appear as the payee. It is also possible that there are instances where an individual has two entries in a single year, one showing payments for their work as a junior counsel and one showing payments for their work as a senior.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.108" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB02988">Pension Provisions</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.109.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1207" speakername="Billy Timmins" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB03000"><p><i>132.</i> To ask the Taoiseach the number of annual pension payments made by his Department that exceed &euro;60,000; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[32012/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.110.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1072" speakername="Enda Kenny" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB03100"><p>My Department has made no annual pension payments in excess of &euro;60,000 in 2015.  In general, the payment of pensions to retired staff of the Department of the Taoiseach is a matter for the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.111" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB03150">Departmental Functions</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.112.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1034" speakername="Eoghan Murphy" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB03200"><p><i>133.</i> To ask the Taoiseach the status of internal audit across his Department; internal audit's relationship with external auditors and audit committees, as well as internal audit's adherence to professional standards; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[32556/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.113.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1072" speakername="Enda Kenny" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB03300"><p>The Audit Committee and Internal Audit Unit provide assurances to my Department&rsquo;s Accounting Officer on the adequacy and effectiveness of the organisation&rsquo;s system of internal controls.  The audit function&rsquo;s terms of reference are set out in the Internal Audit Charter (set out below). </p>  <p>  The Internal Audit Unit is an independent advisory service and outside of this has no operational role.  It has a staff of three (Principal Officer, Higher Executive Officer and Executive Officer) and delivers on a work programme agreed with the Audit Committee, reporting on its audits to the Committee three to four times per year prior to submission to the Accounting Officer. </p>  <p>  The members of the Audit Committee, including two external members, are appointed by the Secretary General of my Department in his capacity as Accounting Officer.  No fees or remuneration are paid for their services.</p>  <p>  Annually the Audit Committee submits a report to the Accounting Officer and the Audit Committee Chair briefs the Accounting Officer on the work of the Internal Audit Unit and the operation of the Audit Committee.  As Taoiseach, I also receive a copy of the annual report as does the Comptroller and Auditor General and the Management Advisory Committee of my Department. </p>  <p>  The Internal Audit Unit maintains regular contact with the Office of the Comptroller &amp;amp; Auditor General and circulates its internal audit reports to it.  The Audit Committee meets annually with the C&amp;AG auditor to the Department to discuss the internal audit work programme and other matters of common interest, including issues identified in the context of the C&amp;AG audits.</p>  <p>  The Audit Committee regularly reviews its operation and procedures.  In 2013 the Committee arranged an external Quality Assurance Review of the audit function and it is currently updating the Internal Audit Charter in line with the most recent guidelines for audit committees issued by the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform.</p></reply>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.114" nospeaker="true" ><p>Department of the Taoiseach

Internal Audit Charter



1.0Introduction

1.1This Charter sets out the purpose, authority and responsibilities of the Internal Audit function in the Department of the Taoiseach.



2.0Internal Audit Unit

2.1The Internal Audit Unit&rsquo;s function is to provide assurance to the Accounting Officer on the adequacy and effectiveness of the Department&rsquo;s system of internal controls.

2.2The Unit operates as a resource for Departmental and Divisional managers through its analysis and appraisal of Departmental control systems.  In its reports the Unit makes recommendations to management based on &lsquo;Best Practice&rsquo;.

2.3The Unit will also act in an advisory capacity to projects under development to ensure the adequacy of control measures.



3.0Internal Audit Committee

3.1The Accounting Officer is the person responsible for appointing the membership of the Internal Audit Committee.  The Committee comprises 2 Department officials and 2 external representatives from another Government Department.  The Accounting Officer may change the membership of the Committee as and when required.

The current membership of the Audit Committee is as follows: -</p><p>3.2Although not members of the Committee, the Heads of the Finance Unit and Internal Audit Unit may attend Committee meetings.  The managers of any Divisions or Offices may attend Committee meetings discussing internal audit reports on their particular sections.  The Committee mayoccasionally decide to hold meetings without these managers (including the Head of the Finance Unit) being present.

3.3.The Internal Audit Committee will consider the work of the Internal Audit Unit comprising audit reports that have been submitted, the schedule of work (Work Programmes) and other matters as appropriate.

3.4The operation of the Internal Audit Committee will be reviewed by the Accounting Officer, the Chairperson of the Committee and the Head of the Internal Audit Unit after a three-year period. 

3.5The Internal Audit Committee should ensure &lsquo;Quality Assurance Reviews&rsquo; of the Internal Audit Unit on a regular basis, i.e. at least once every five years.



4.0Responsibilities

4.1The Internal Audit Unit operates as an independent advisory service and outside of this has no operational role.  Responsibility for internal control rests with managers who, without regard to audit activity, ensure that appropriate and adequate control arrangements exist in their areas of responsibility.  The role of internal audit is to appraise the adequacy and effectiveness of those arrangements and to make recommendations for improvements as appropriate.

4.2It is for managers and Departmental management to decide upon the appropriate response to reports and recommendations of internal audit.

4.3The Internal Audit Unit will liaise, as necessary and appropriate, with external auditors, including the Office of the Comptroller and Auditor General.

4.4The Internal Audit Unit is authorised to have full access to Departmental records (manual and electronic), physical properties and personnel relevant to the carrying out of a review.  It will be responsible for affording to records and other materials entrusted to its care, the same protections afforded by staff in whose care they normally are retained.</p><p>5.0Scope

5.1The Internal Audit Unit will, in general, adopt a systems-based approach to its audits supplemented, where appropriate, by the use of traditional transaction-testing, vouching and verification methods .

5.2The Internal Audit Unit will be responsible for reviewing and appraising the following: -

5.2.1the design and operation of all systems and procedures (financial, managerial etc.) which are intended to control the Department's operations, including those used by management to measure the effectiveness of programmes and other activities of the Department;

5.2.2the adequacy, reliability and integrity of the information systems used to monitor the Department&rsquo;s activities and to ensure accountability;

5.2.3the degree of compliance with (a) legislation (domestic and international) and other requirements laid down centrally (e.g. by the Department of Finance) and (b) management plans, procedures and policies;

5.2.4the acquisition and disposal of assets and the safeguarding of assets and interests from losses, including those arising from fraud, malpractice and irregularity;</p><p>6.0Reporting Accountabilities

6.1The Head of the Internal Audit Unit will report to the Internal Audit Committee on a regular basis, as agreed in the context of the Annual Work programme, and in particular circumstances, as requested by the Accounting Officer/Internal Audit Committee.

6.2.Audit reports prepared by the Internal Auditor will be submitted to the Accounting Officer by the Head of Internal Audit.  A copy of the reports will also be circulated to the Internal Audit Committee which in turn will submit its observations on reports to the Accounting Officer.

6.3The Internal Audit Committee will submit an annual report to the Accounting Officer.  A copy will be provided, for information, to the Taoiseach.



7.0Resourcing

7.1The Expenses of the Internal Audit function shall be met from the Vote of the Department of the Taoiseach.



8.0Conflict of Interest

8.1.In view of the relatively small size of the Department and the need to make the most efficient use of resources the Head of the Internal Audit Unit will be assigned on a part-time basis.  However, to ensure an appropriate level of access within the Department and that particular concerns and recommendations are acted upon,  he/she shall be at Principal Officer level and will perform the audit role in addition to his/her Divisional duties within the Department.  

8.2.Should for any reason a matter arise relating to the Principal Officer&rsquo;s dual roles where a potential conflict of interest might arise then he/she should advise the Chairman of the Audit Committee accordingly who will ensure that appropriate steps are taken.



Martin Fraser

Secretary General

7 July 2012</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.116" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB03400">Department of Social Protection</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.115" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB03375">Public Sector Pensions</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.116.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1051" speakername="Brendan Griffin" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB03400"><p><i>134.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Social Protection if a retired civil servant (details supplied) in County Kerry will be permitted early access to their retirement lump sum; and if she will make a statement on the matter. <b>[30444/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.117.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB03500"><p>The officer in question retired from the Civil Service on 4<sup>th</sup>September 2009 under the Incentivised Scheme for Early Retirement.</p><p>In line with the terms of the Scheme, the officer was paid the pension along with 10% of the retirement lump sum without actuarial reduction.  The 90% balance of the lump sum will be payable when the officer reaches preserved pension age (i.e. 60 years of age). </p><p>While there is no provision under this Scheme to pay the balance of the lump sum to the officer before preserved pension age, preserved lump sums may be paid early on grounds of incapacity, i.e. if the officer satisfies the criteria for ill-health retirement from the civil service.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.118" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB03550">Youth Unemployment Measures</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.119.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1050" speakername="Tom Fleming" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB03600"><p><i>135.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Social Protection the strategy to address the 30.02% youth unemployment as per statistics reported in summer 2015 by the Central Statistics Office; and if she will make a statement on the matter.  <b>[30816/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.120.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB03700"><p>The Government&rsquo;s primary strategy to tackle youth unemployment is through policies to create the environment for a strong economic recovery by promoting competitiveness and productivity.Economic recovery will underpin jobs growth and the availability of productive employment for young people.  This strategy has been succeeding, with an increase of over 80,000 in employment over the last two years. </p><p>Youth unemployment continues to fall (with a rate of 22.4% in Q2 2015, as compared to 26.9% in Q2 2014).  These figures are not adjusted for seasonality; the seasonally-adjusted rate published by the Central Statistics Office as of August 2015 was 20.7%.</p><p>The number of young people who are long-term unemployed has fallen from 35,000 in mid-2012 (46% of all the young unemployed at that time) to 13,000 (31% of all the young unemployed) in mid-2015.</p><p>However, the Government recognises that as the recovery takes hold, there is a need for additional measures to ensure that as many as possible of the jobs created are taken up by jobseekers and young jobseekers in particular.  This is the rationale behind the Government&rsquo;s <i>Pathways to Work</i>strategy and the Youth Guarantee.</p><p>The Youth Guarantee sets a medium-term objective of ensuring that young people receive an offer of employment within four months of becoming unemployed.  The main plank of the guarantee is assistance to young people in finding and securing sustainable jobs.  For those who do not find employment, additional offers are provided for.  Most such offers (over 70%) are in further education or training.  Others are in community-based employment programmes such as CE, Gateway and T&uacute;s, or through the JobsPlus employment subsidy for private employment.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.121" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB03725">Community Employment Schemes Operation</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.122.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1054" speakername="Se&aacute;n &Oacute; Feargha&iacute;l" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB03800"><p><i>136.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Social Protection her views that the imposition of PRSI charges on community employment scheme participants receiving more than &euro;352 per week, constitutes an unfair and unreasonable burden on those with a number of dependants, particularly those in community employment projects; if she will support amendments to rectify this issue; and if she will make a statement on the matter.  <b>[30882/15]</b></p></ques>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.123.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1054" speakername="Se&aacute;n &Oacute; Feargha&iacute;l" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB03900"><p><i>172.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Social Protection if she will provide a PRSI exemption for participants in community employment schemes who are in receipt of payments in excess of &euro;352 and who are currently finding that there is no financial incentive to participate in such a scheme; and if she will make a statement on the matter.  <b>[30881/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.124.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB04000"><p>I propose to take Questions Nos. 136 and 172 together.  </p>  <p>  Participants in certain employment schemes, including community employment schemes (CE), receive a weekly payment which is equal to the social welfare payment appropriate to their family size, plus a top up of &euro;20, subject to a minimum payment of &euro;208 per week.  This income has been for many years treated in the same manner as earnings from employment for PRSI purposes and accordingly is subject to Class A PRSI.  Therefore participants on CE schemes, similar to other private sector employees who pay Class A, can establish entitlement to the full range of short term benefits including jobseeker&rsquo;s benefit, illness benefit, and maternity benefit and to long term benefits including State pension (contributory).</p>  <p>  As of 31 August 2015, there were 1,957 CE participants in receipt of payments in excess of &euro;352 per week and who would therefore be liable to make an employee PRSI contribution.  For over 98% of these CE participants there is a financial incentive to participate in the scheme as the net amount of their CE payment exceeds their underlying social welfare entitlement.</p>  <p>  Any proposed PRSI exemption for CE participants paying PRSI would have to apply to all workers similarly paying PRSI and with access to the same level of social insurance benefits.  This would have to be considered in a Budgetary context.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.125" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB04050">One-Parent Family Payment Eligibility</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.126.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB04100"><p><i>137.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Social Protection the steps she has taken since changes to the one-parent family payment came into effect on 2 July 2015, to ensure that persons who qualified previously or were eligible for this payment have not been negatively impacted or affected.  <b>[31092/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.127.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB04200"><p>The final phase of the one-parent family payment (OFP) scheme reforms took place on 2 July 2015, when the maximum child age threshold of the scheme was reduced to 7 years.  On that date, approximately 25,500 affected customers were supported by the Department to transition to a range of alternative income support payments.</p>  <p>  In the months in advance of the implementation of the final phase of reforms to the one-parent family payment scheme, the Department contacted all affected lone parents and invited them to attend information seminars.  At these seminars lone parents were advised of the best possible options available to them depending on their circumstances.</p>  <p>  Of the affected 25,500 customers, approximately 96% transitioned to another social welfare payment, of which 13,500 transitioned to the jobseeker&rsquo;s transitional payment (JST), 2,500 transitioned to the jobseeker&rsquo;s allowance payment (JA), and 8,100 transitioned to the family income supplement (FIS).  The 8,100 customers who transitioned to the family income supplement are also eligible for the back to work family dividend (BTWFD) and a large proportion of these customers have already availed of the dividend.</p>  <p>  Since the changes came into effect the Department has written to affected lone parents and invited them to participate in a meeting with a case officer with a view to improving their employment prospects.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.128" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB04225">Child Benefit Data</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.129.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/994" speakername="Jim Daly" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB04250"><p><i>138.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Social Protection the position regarding the savings accrued to the Exchequer from the budgetary change made in 2010, terminating child benefit payments at 18 years of age, regardless of whether the person has completed second level education or not; and if she will make a statement on the matter.  <b>[31591/15]</b></p></ques>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.130.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/994" speakername="Jim Daly" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB04300"><p><i>139.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Social Protection the estimated cost of reversing the budgetary decision made in 2010 to terminate child benefit payments at 18 years of age, regardless of whether the person has completed second level education or not; if she will consider doing so in the upcoming budget; and if she will make a statement on the matter.  <b>[31592/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.131.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200061#WRB04400"><p>I propose to take Questions Nos. 138 and 139 together. </p>  <p>  Child Benefit is a monthly universal payment to assist with the costs associated with raising children.  It is paid to around 616,000 families in respect of some 1.17 million children, with an estimated expenditure of around &euro;1.9 billion in 2014.  Child Benefit continues to be paid in respect of children up to their 18th birthday who are in full-time education or who have a disability.  I am conscious that Child Benefit is an important source of income for all families and in Budget 2015 the Government increased child benefit by &euro;5 per month, at a cost of &euro;72 million. </p>  <p>  Budget 2009 provided for the reduction of the age for which Child Benefit is paid from under 19 years to under 18 years.  This measure was implemented in full in 2011 and has resulted in savings of &euro;79 million on an annual basis.  A value for money review of child income supports undertaken by the Department of Social Protection in 2010 found that participation patterns in education support the 18 year age limit for Child Benefit. </p>  <p>  The estimated cost of reversing the budgetary decision made in 2010 to terminate Child Benefit payments at 18 years of age and to extend the upper age limit for those in education to 19 years would be in the region of &euro;58 million in a full year.  Any changes to the eligibility criteria for Child Benefit could only be decided in a budgetary context. </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.133" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC00150">Social Welfare Code</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.134.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1049" speakername="Michael Healy-Rae" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC00200"><p><i>140.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Social Protection the action she will take on the commitment to protect persons with disabilities by implementing a number of the ten points recommended by the Disability Federation of Ireland relevant to her Department, namely increasing disability payments by &euro;20 per week as an interim measure to offset the cost of disability; restoring the respite grant to pre-austerity levels by increasing it by &euro;325 per annum; making all employment activation programmes eligible to persons with disabilities; and if she will make a statement on the matter. <b>[32289/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.135.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC00300"><p>Any increases in social welfare rates can only be considered in the context of the Budget and estimates process. </p><p>A &euro;20 increase per week in the rate of disability payments would cost approximately &euro;254 million in a full year, while in relation to the respite care grant (RCG), the estimated cost of increasing the RCG by &euro;325, from &euro;1,375 to &euro;1,700, is &euro;29.4 million in a full year. </p><p>The Government recognises the importance of increasing participation in employment for persons with a disability, and its commitment in this regard will be reflected in the forthcoming Comprehensive Employment Strategy for people with disabilities.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.136" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC00350">Community Employment Schemes Eligibility</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.137.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1071" speakername="Dara Calleary" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC00400"><p><i>141.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Social Protection if any community employment schemes exist for a person (details supplied); and if she will make a statement on the matter. <b>[30437/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.138.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC00500"><p>Eligibility for the Community Employment (CE) scheme can be ascertained by the individual contacting their local Intreo Office or Employment Services Office (contact details on the website). The Department&rsquo;s public website also lists all the eligibility criteria for the Community Employment scheme.</p><p>A person of 18 years of age or over, who is currently in receipt of illness benefit for 6 continuous months or more, is eligible for Community Employment. The person in question will still need to contact their local Intreo Office to have their eligibility confirmed and to register their interest in the scheme. This will allow their name to be submitted to CE employers for interview. CE vacancies are advertised on the website.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.139" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC00550">Invalidity Pension Applications</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.140.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1069" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC00600"><p><i>142.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Social Protection the reason a person (details supplied) in County Meath was refused an invalidity pension; if the application will be reviewed; and if she will make a statement on the matter. <b>[30467/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.141.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC00700"><p>The person in question is currently in receipt of means tested disability allowance.</p>  <p>  Invalidity pension (IP) is a payment for people who are permanently incapable of work because of illness or incapacity and who satisfy the pay related social insurance (PRSI) contribution conditions. </p>  <p>  To qualify for IP a claimant must, inter-alia, have at least 260 (5 years) paid PRSI contributions since entering social insurance and 48 contributions paid or credited in the last complete contribution year before the date of their claim.  Only PRSI classes A, E or H contributions are reckonable for IP purposes.  </p>  <p>  The department received a claim for IP from the person concerned on 22 June 2015.  The person concerned was refused IP on the grounds that the contribution conditions for the scheme are not satisfied.  He was notified on 1 July 2015 of this decision, the reason for it and of his right of review and appeal.  On foot of this enquiry, a review of all the information available has been carried out and it has been decided that there is no change to the original decision. The person concerned was notified on 17 September 2015 of the outcome of the review and of his right to appeal the decision to the independent Social Welfare Appeals Office within 21 days.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.142" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC00750">Social Welfare Appeals</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.143.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/950" speakername="Jack Wall" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC00800"><p><i>143.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Social Protection further to Parliamentary Question No. 195 of 30 June 2015, if a person (details supplied) in County Kildare can appeal the decision cited; and if she will make a statement on the matter. <b>[30475/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.144.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC00900"><p>When the original decision in this case was made on 28 October 2014, the client was advised of her right of appeal to the Social Welfare Appeals Office within 21 days of receiving the decision.  As notified to the Deputy on 9 January 2015, as the appeal was not received until 18 December 2014 the Appeals Officer decided the client&rsquo;s right to appeal had expired.  </p>  <p>  As correct procedures were followed at the time of award of this claim, a request to review the original decision was refused on 3 September 2015.  Accordingly, there is no recourse to a further appeal at this stage.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.145" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC00950">Invalidity Pension Applications</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.146.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1101" speakername="Barry Cowen" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC01000"><p><i>144.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Social Protection when a person (details supplied) in County Offaly may expect a decision on an application for a disability allowance.  <b>[30504/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.147.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC01100"><p>The person concerned has been awarded invalidity pension with effect from the 09 July 2015.  The first payment issued to his nominated Post Office on 17 September 2015.  The person in question was notified of this decision on the 11 September 2015.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.148" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC01150">Carer's Allowance Applications</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.149.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/950" speakername="Jack Wall" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC01200"><p><i>145.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Social Protection the position regarding an application for a carer's allowance by a person (details supplied) in County Kildare; and if she will make a statement on the matter. <b>[30521/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.150.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC01300"><p>The Social Welfare Appeals Office has advised me that an appeal by the person concerned was referred to an Appeals Officer on 25 August 2015, who will make a summary decision on the appeal based on the documentary evidence presented or, if required, hold an oral hearing.  </p>  <p>  The Social Welfare Appeals Office functions independently of the Minister for Social Protection and of the Department and is responsible for determining appeals against decisions in relation to social welfare entitlements.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.151" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC01350">One-Parent Family Payment Application Numbers</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.152.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/983" speakername="Billy Kelleher" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC01400"><p><i>146.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Social Protection the number of families whose one-parent family payment was discontinued from July 2015, and who transferred to other social welfare benefits; and if she will provide, in tabular form, a breakdown, by county. <b>[30541/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.153.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC01500"><p>The latest data collated by the Department on the numbers of customers who transitioned out of the one-parent family payment (OFP) as a result of the reform on 2 July, 2015, show that some 25,500 customers transitioned out of the scheme on that day.  Of those customers approximately:</p><p>- 13,700 moved to the jobseeker&rsquo;s transitional payment;</p><p>- 2,500 moved to the jobseeker&rsquo;s allowance (JA) scheme, and</p><p>- 8,100 moved to the family income supplement (FIS) scheme.</p><p>The remainder of customers transitioned to a broad range of other income support payments such as the jobseeker&rsquo;s benefit (JB), the disability allowance (DA), illness benefit (IB), as well as to various back-to-work schemes. </p><p>A tabular breakdown of these figures by County is presently not available in the Department.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.154" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC01550">Meabhr&aacute;n M&iacute;nithe</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.155.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/969" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC01600"><p><i>147.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Social Protection an bhfuil aon dul chun cinn d&eacute;anta maidir leis na meabhr&aacute;in mh&iacute;ni&uacute;ch&aacute;in a bheith ar f&aacute;il as Gaeilge, &oacute;s rud &eacute; gur luaigh s&iacute; gur mhaith l&eacute;i go mbeadh f&aacute;il orthu 'i nGaeilge ag an am c&eacute;anna leis an leagan B&eacute;arla' ar an D&eacute;ardaoin 16 I&uacute;l 2011 agus &iacute; ag caint ar an Acht Leasa Sh&oacute;isialaigh agus Pinsean, 2011, ag c&eacute;im an choiste; agus an nd&eacute;anfaidh s&iacute; r&aacute;iteas ina thaobh. <b>[30542/15]</b></p></ques>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.156.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC01700"><p><i>148.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Social Protection an bhfuil aon dul chun cinn d&eacute;anta maidir leis na meabhr&aacute;in mh&iacute;ni&uacute;ch&aacute;in a bheith ar f&aacute;il as Gaeilge, &oacute;s rud &eacute; gur luaigh s&iacute;, D&eacute;ardaoin an 16 I&uacute;il 2011 agus &iacute; ag caint ar an Acht Leasa Sh&oacute;isialaigh agus Pinsean, 2011 ag c&eacute;im an choiste, gur mhaith l&eacute;i go mbeadh f&aacute;il orthu 'i nGaeilge ag an am gc&eacute;anna leis an leagan B&eacute;arla; agus an nd&eacute;anfaidh s&iacute; r&aacute;iteas ina thaobh. <b>[30547/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.157.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC01800"><p>Bearta&iacute;tear chun ceisteanna 147 agus 148 a fhreagairt lena ch&eacute;ile.</p><p>I gcaitheamh dh&iacute;osp&oacute;ireacht Ch&eacute;im an Choiste ar an mBille Leasa Sh&oacute;isialaigh agus Pinsean, 2011, bh&iacute; m&eacute; ar aon intinn leis na Teachta&iacute; D&aacute;la sa mh&eacute;id gurbh fearr, m&aacute;s f&eacute;idir, aistri&uacute;ch&aacute;in Ghaeilge Bill&iacute; agus Meabhr&aacute;in Mh&iacute;nithe ghaolmhara a chur ar f&aacute;il ag an tr&aacute;th c&eacute;anna a fhoils&iacute;tear leaganacha B&eacute;arla de na Bill&iacute;.</p><p>Chun leagan Gaeilge den Mheabhr&aacute;n M&iacute;nithe a fhoilsi&uacute;, &aacute;fach, theast&oacute;dh go mbeadh an leagan Gaeilge den Bhille ar f&aacute;il ag tr&aacute;th foilsithe an Bhille, chomh maith.  Is amhlaidh at&aacute; an c&aacute;s, go h&aacute;irithe i gc&aacute;s Bill&iacute; casta teicni&uacute;la, &aacute;it a bhfuil g&aacute; le comhsheasmhacht sa t&eacute;arma&iacute;ocht a &uacute;s&aacute;idtear sna haistri&uacute;ch&aacute;in Ghaeilge ar th&eacute;acs an Bhille agus ar na Meabhrach&aacute;in Mh&iacute;nithe ghaolmhara chun mearbhall a sheachaint. </p><p>&Oacute;s rud &eacute; go bhfuil Seirbh&iacute;s Aistri&uacute;ch&aacute;in Thithe an Oireachtais freagrach as leagan Gaeilge na mBill&iacute; a fhoilsi&uacute;, chuir m&eacute; in i&uacute;l do na Teachta D&aacute;la&iacute; gur ceist &iacute; seo arbh fhearr a mbeadh na Teachta&iacute; D&aacute;la, n&oacute; b&rsquo;fh&eacute;idir Pr&iacute;omh-Aoir&iacute; Thithe an Oireachtais in ann d&eacute;ile&aacute;il l&eacute;i.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.158" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC01850">Family Income Supplement Eligibility</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.159.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1102" speakername="Brian Stanley" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC01900"><p><i>149.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Social Protection if she will approve family income supplement payments for Garda recruits (details supplied) in Templemore, County Tipperary as they are employees of the State; and if she will make a statement on the matter. <b>[30571/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.160.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC01950"><p>The family income supplement (FIS) is an in-work income support for employees on low earnings who have families.</p><p>To qualify for payment of FIS a person must be engaged in full time paid employment as an employee which is expected to last for at least 3 months and be working for a minimum of 38 hours per fortnight.  A couple may combine their hours of employment to meet the qualification criteria. </p><p>Student Garda&iacute; attend full-time day education at the Garda College as well as periods of on the job training over a period of 72 weeks while studying for their BA degree in advanced policing. They receive a weekly allowance of &euro;184 per week while studying for this degree.</p><p>Attendance on a full-time day education course is not considered full-time employment and consequently students cannot qualify for FIS.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.161" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC01975">Carer's Allowance Eligibility</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.162.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1049" speakername="Michael Healy-Rae" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC02000"><p><i>150.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Social Protection her views on a matter (details supplied) regarding the operation guidelines for carer's allowance; and if she will make a statement on the matter. <b>[30577/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.163.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC02100"><p>The Department endeavours to keep all information on its website accurate, complete and up-to-date.  The Department is arranging for the carer's allowance operational guidelines to be updated to reflect any changes that have occurred in the BTEA since 2012 and appreciates your drawing of this oversight to its attention.</p>  <p>  Entitlement to the back to education allowance (BTEA) is dependent on an applicant being in receipt of certain social welfare payments.  Although each scheme&rsquo;s guidelines may contain some reference to BTEA, there are comprehensive guidelines on the BTEA scheme available on the Department&rsquo;s website. These were last updated on 11 June 2015. </p></reply>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.164" nospeaker="true" ><p>Question No. 151 withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.165" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC02250">Carer's Allowance Appeals</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.166.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1049" speakername="Michael Healy-Rae" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC02300"><p><i>152.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Social Protection the position regarding the appeals process for carer's allowance-benefit (details supplied); and if she will make a statement on the matter. <b>[30628/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.167.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC02400"><p>Appeal processing times peaked in 2011 when the average processing time for an appeal of carers allowance was 38.8 weeks.  In 2012 the average processing time reduced to 33.8 weeks.  Further improvements were achieved in 2013, when the average appeal processing time reduced to 28.5 weeks.  As at the end of August 2015, the average time taken to process a carer&rsquo;s allowance appeal has reduced further to 21.3 weeks, a reduction of 17.5 weeks since 2011. </p>  <p>  The average processing time for carers benefit appeal in 2011 was 29.3 weeks.  In 2012 the average processing time reduced to 24 weeks.  Further improvements were achieved in 2013, when the average appeal processing time reduced to 18.7 weeks.  As at the end of August 2015, the average time taken to process a carer&rsquo;s benefit appeal has reduced further to 16.4 weeks, a reduction of 12.9 weeks since 2011. </p>  <p>  The reduction in processing time reflects the significant resources which have been invested in the Social Welfare Appeals Office over the last number of years.</p>  <p>  In addition the Department has undertaken a process of reform in many of its scheme areas aimed at reducing the time taken to respond to requests for submissions in relation to appeals. While the Department&rsquo;s response times for carers benefit has increased slightly from 6.2 weeks in 2011 to 8.4 weeks at end of August 2015, the response time to requests for submissions to the Department for appeals of carers allowance has reduced from an average of 17.9 weeks in 2011 to 12.9 weeks at end August 2015.</p>  <p>  Processing times are calculated from the registration date to the date of finalisation and include time spent awaiting clarification from the appellant and time in the Department for review and preparation of its appeal submission, and any further investigation, examination or assessment by the Department&rsquo;s Inspectors and Medical Assessors that is deemed necessary.  While this process carries an inherent delay in terms of finalising an appeal, it also crystalises the flexibility and accessibility of the appeals system. By its nature and because it is a quasi-judicial function, the processing of appeals takes time and reflects the fact that, by definition, the appeal process cannot be a quick one.</p>  <p>  Appeal processing times are kept under continual review in the Social Welfare Appeals Office and every effort is made to reduce processing times.</p>  <p>  The Social Welfare Appeals Office functions independently of the Minister for Social Protection and of the Department and is responsible for determining appeals against decisions in relation to social welfare entitlements.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.168" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC02450">State Pensions Reform</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.169.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1041" speakername="Paul Connaughton" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC02500"><p><i>153.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Social Protection if she is considering changing the contributory pension regime to ensure that persons who have worked for decades and made contributions over many years can access the full contributory pension rate; the mechanisms that are open to those not on a full contributory pension to have the decision reviewed or revisited; and if she will make a statement on the matter. <b>[30631/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.170.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC02600"><p>The State pension contributory (SPC) is a very valuable benefit and is the bedrock of the Irish pension system.  Therefore, it is important to ensure that those qualifying have made a sustained contribution to the Social Insurance Fund over their working lives.  To ensure that an individual can maximise their entitlement to an SPC, all contributions paid over their working life from when they first enter insurable employment until pension age are taken into account when assessing their entitlement and the level of that entitlement. </p>  <p>  Since 1961, when contributory pensions were first introduced, the average contributions test has been used in calculating pension entitlement.  Under this system, the rate of the SPC is related to the average contributions paid (or credited) over their working life.  For example, someone with a yearly average of 52 contributions (i.e. 100%) would generally receive a full rate pension (personal rate &euro;230.30), whereas someone with a yearly average of only 30 contributions paid or credited would have an entitlement, under the SPC, to a weekly personal rate of &euro;207, which is 90% of the maximum rate.  If such a pensioner was paid the same rate of contributory pension as someone who had paid into the social insurance system all their working life, it would mean there was no benefit derived from the much greater contribution made by that person.  As it is, the benefit derived from paying PRSI is greater, in relative terms, for those with limited contribution records and who receive lower rate pensions, than it is for full-rate pensioners.</p>  <p>  Where an older person qualifies for the reduced rate SPC of &euro;207, but they do not have other income (such as a private pension), the State pension system provides alternative methods of support.  In such cases they may qualify for a means tested State pension (non-contributory), the maximum personal rate of which is &euro;219, which amounts to just over 95% of the maximum rate of the SPC.  </p>  <p>  If a person does not believe that my Department has calculated their pension entitlements correctly, they may request that the decision be reviewed in the first instance, or they may appeal it to the independent Social Welfare Appeals Office.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.171" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC02650">Social Welfare Application Forms</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.172.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1194" speakername="Gabrielle McFadden" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC02700"><p><i>154.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Social Protection in view of concerns by post offices, if her Department has reviewed application forms for Department payments and updated them to ensure that a more neutral wording in relation to payment options is provided; and if she will make a statement on the matter. <b>[30634/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.173.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC02800"><p>My Department updates and reviews its application forms on a regular basis, to take account of evolving requirements.  Recently revised application forms reflect a more neutral wording of the payment options section of the forms.  The revised forms have been distributed and are also available on the Department&rsquo;s website .</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.174" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC02850">Social Welfare Payments Administration</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.175.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1093" speakername="Ciara Conway" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC02900"><p><i>155.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Social Protection the cost per individual transaction incurred by the State for each cash social welfare payment collected at the post office, as opposed to the cost per transaction incurred by State for each welfare payment paid electronically into a claimant's bank account; and if she will make a statement on the matter. <b>[30642/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.176.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC03000"><p>The estimated average total cost to the Department of Social Protection per individual transaction for social welfare payments made in cash at the Post Office is &euro;1.70 at current volumes.  The estimated average total cost to the Department per transaction in respect of social welfare payments direct to bank accounts is 26c.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.177" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC03050">Carer's Allowance Payments</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.178.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1049" speakername="Michael Healy-Rae" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC03100"><p><i>156.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Social Protection the position regarding the payment of carer's allowance for a person (details supplied) in County Kerry; and if she will make a statement on the matter. <b>[30693/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.179.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC03200"><p>The Social Welfare Appeals Office has advised me that an appeal by the person concerned was registered in that office on 4 August 2015.  It is a statutory requirement of the appeals process that the relevant Departmental papers and comments by the Deciding Officer on the grounds of appeal be sought.  When these papers have been received from the Department, the case in question will be referred to an Appeals Officer who will make a summary decision on the appeal based on the documentary evidence presented or, if required, hold an oral appeal hearing.</p>  <p>  The Social Welfare Appeals Office functions independently of the Minister for Social Protection and of the Department and is responsible for determining appeals against decisions in relation to social welfare entitlements.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.180" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC03250">Community Employment Schemes Operation</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.181.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1049" speakername="Michael Healy-Rae" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC03300"><p><i>157.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Social Protection her views on a matter (details supplied) regarding the community employment scheme; and if she will make a statement on the matter. <b>[30701/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.182.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC03400"><p>Community Employment (CE) is an active labour market programme designed to provide eligible long-term unemployed people and other disadvantaged persons (including lone parents, recovering drug misusers and persons with a disability) with an opportunity to engage in part-time work and training within their communities on a temporary, fixed-term basis. </p><p>The A8/A9 PRSI stamp paid by Community Employment (CE) participants is effectively the same as a full rate A stamp in terms of the benefits that can be obtained. The reduced rate of jobseeker's benefit on CE exit reflects the rate of weekly earnings from CE as this is used to determine the rate of jobseeker's benefit, as set out below: </p><p><b><font color="#2F2F2F">Weekly Jobseeker's Benefit payment in 2015</font></b><table><tr><th>Average weekly earnings</th><th>Personal rate </th><th>Increase for a qualified adult</th><th>Increase for a qualified child</th></tr><tr><td>Less than &euro;150 </td><td>&euro;84.50</td><td>&euro;80.90</td><td>&euro;29.80</td></tr><tr><td>&euro;150 - &euro;219.99</td><td>&euro;121.40</td><td>&euro;80.90</td><td>&euro;29.80</td></tr><tr><td>&euro;220 - &euro;299.99</td><td>&euro;147.30</td><td>&euro;80.90 </td><td>&euro;29.80</td></tr><tr><td>&euro;300 or more</td><td>&euro;188 </td><td>&euro;124.80</td><td>&euro;29.80</td></tr></table></p><p>If a person is only entitled to a reduced rate of jobseeker's benefit, it may be financially more beneficial for them to claim jobseeker's allowance. However, jobseeker's allowance is means-tested and household means must be below a certain level to qualify.</p><p>With respect to the participants exhausting their time on the programme, all CE sponsors and participants are aware of the time limits for participation, and the fact that sponsors will only have the participants for a limited amount of time based on the published rules of the programme. The participation limits allows for the maximum utilisation of places amongst qualifying persons, to ensure the benefit of the CE placements to the widest possible audience. </p><p>For participants who are fully trained and considered &ldquo;job-ready&rdquo; for the open labour market, the renewed efforts of the sponsoring organisation should be towards assisting them in gaining employment.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.183" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC03450">Momentum Programme</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.184.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1050" speakername="Tom Fleming" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC03500"><p><i>158.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Social Protection if she will extend the eligibility for entry to the Momentum programme which funds free education and training for long-term unemployed, to cater for people on disability and illness payments; and if she will make a statement on the matter. <b>[30713/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.185.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200062#WRC03600"><p>The Government recognises the importance of increasing participation in employment for persons with a disability and provides a wide range of income and work related supports through the Department of Social Protection.  These supports play an important role in facilitating increased participation in the labour force by people with disabilities.</p>  <p>  These supports include the wage subsidy scheme (WSS), the EmployAbility (supported employment) service, the reasonable accommodation fund for the employment of people with disabilities and the disability awareness training scheme.  For those who are in receipt of invalidity pension or illness benefit (for at least six months) and who feel they now have some capacity for work, the partial capacity benefit (PCB) scheme allows them to work and retain a portion of their social welfare payment. People on disability-related payments also have access to activation programmes such as Community employment and Jobbridge administered by the Department of Social Protection.</p>  <p>  Unlike job-seekers where participation in activation measures through the Intreo service is mandatory, in the case of persons in receipt of disability/illness support payments, engagement with the Intreo service is on a voluntary basis and at all times they are free to contact the Intreo service.  The Department has trialled in ten locations provision of full activation supports to people with disabilities who wish to avail of the Intreo service and will consider expansion to other locations on the basis of operational experience. </p>  <p>  The Momentum programme is funded by the  Department of Education and Skills through Solas and is designed on a payments by results basis specifically for long-term unemployed jobseekers. The Department of social Protection, through Intreo, identifies and refers eligible and suitable clients to the Momentum programme. The current phase of Momentum is coming to a conclusion and a decision has yet to be taken on whether or not it will operate again next year. Should it be decided to repeat the programme, the Department will together with the Department of Education and Skills and SOLAS consider if, and if so how, eligibility be extended to people with disabilities.</p></reply>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.186" nospeaker="true" ><p>Question No. 159 withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.188" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD00150">Disability Allowance Payments</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.189.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1049" speakername="Michael Healy-Rae" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD00200"><p><i>160.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Social Protection the position regarding an overpayment of disability benefit in the case of a person (details supplied); and if she will make a statement on the matter.  <b>[30742/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.190.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD00300"><p>I confirm that the person concerned was in receipt of disability allowance (DA) from 2002 to 2013.  </p><p>A review of her entitlement was carried out recently and it was established that the person concerned had means not previously disclosed to this department.  These means are derived from a United Kingdom State Pension which was awarded to the person in question in 2007.There is no evidence that the person concerned notified this department of the pension in 2007. </p><p>On 27 July 2015, a deciding officer, decided that  the person concerned had a reduced entitled to DA from 8 August 2007 to 6 August 2013, because of the means from their UK State Pension.  This resulted in an overpayment.  </p><p>The person concerned was given the right to appeal this decision within 21 days to the Social Welfare Appeals Office.  No appeal was received in this case.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.191" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD00350">Jobseeker's Allowance Payments</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.192.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1049" speakername="Michael Healy-Rae" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD00400"><p><i>161.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Social Protection the position regarding the payment of jobseeker's allowance in the case of a person (details supplied) in County Kerry; and if she will make a statement on the matter. <b>[30746/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.193.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD00500"><p>I am advised by the Social Welfare Appeals Office that an Appeals Officer, having fully considered all of the available evidence, has decided to allow the appeal of the person concerned by way of a summary decision.  The person concerned has been notified of the Appeals Officer&rsquo;s decision.</p><p>The Social Welfare Appeals Office functions independently of the Minister for Social Protection and of the Department and is responsible for determining appeals against decisions in relation to social welfare entitlements.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.194" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD00550">Child Benefit Payments</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.195.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/957" speakername="Bernard Durkan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD00600"><p><i>162.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Social Protection when child benefit will be paid for a person (details supplied) in County Longford; and if she will make a statement on the matter. <b>[30748/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.196.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD00700"><p>A claim for child benefit was received in respect of the child concerned from his mother in May 2015.  She had previously applied for child benefit in respect of this child in June 2014; however the earlier claim was withdrawn as she failed to reply to correspondence issued.  Child benefit has now been awarded from July 2014, the month following receipt of the earlier claim.  Payment of child benefit including arrears issued to the bank account of the person concerned on 4 August 2015.</p>  <p>  The Department is investigating a possible entitlement to child benefit for an earlier period, prior to July 2014.  This involves establishing the date of the child&rsquo;s arrival in the State; further correspondence will issue to the person concerned as soon as these enquiries are complete.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.197" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD00750">Invalidity Pension Appeals</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.198.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1070" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD00800"><p><i>163.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Social Protection the status of an appeal against the refusal of an invalidity pension by a person (details supplied) in County Mayo; if it will be expedited; and if she will make a statement on the matter. <b>[30751/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.199.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD00900"><p>I am advised by the Social Welfare Appeals Office that an Appeals Officer, having fully considered all the evidence, disallowed the appeal of the person concerned by way of summary decision on the 10 April 2014.</p>  <p>  Under Social Welfare legislation, the decision of the Appeals Officer is final and conclusive and may only be reviewed by the Appeals Officer in the light of new evidence or new facts.  I am advised that the person concerned subsequently submitted additional evidence and that the Appeals Officer agreed to review the person concerned appeal on foot of this additional evidence.  Regrettably the Appeals Officer did not find any new facts or fresh evidence which warranted a revision of his earlier decision.  The person concerned has been notified of the Appeals Officer&rsquo;s decision.   </p>  <p>  The Social Welfare Appeals Office functions independently of the Minister for Social Protection and of the Department and is responsible for determining appeals against decisions on social welfare entitlements.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.200" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD00950">Jobseeker's Allowance Appeals</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.201.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/957" speakername="Bernard Durkan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD01000"><p><i>164.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Social Protection when an application for jobseeker's allowance will be awarded in the case of a person (details supplied) in Dublin 7; and if she will make a statement on the matter. <b>[30779/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.202.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD01100"><p>The person concerned recently made a claim for jobseeker&rsquo;s allowance which was disallowed on the grounds that he is not habitually resident in the State. He has submitted an appeal against this decision which has been processed and is being forwarded to the independent Social Welfare Appeals Office (SWAO) by the Deciding Officer involved in the case. The SWAO will be in contact with the person concerned in relation to developments on the Appeal.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.203" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD01150">Carer's Allowance Applications</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.204.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1049" speakername="Michael Healy-Rae" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD01200"><p><i>165.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Social Protection the position regarding an application for carer's allowance by a person (details supplied) in County Kerry; and if she will make a statement on the matter. <b>[30787/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.205.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD01300"><p>The application for carer&rsquo;s allowance in respect of the person concerned was awarded on 11 August 2015 and the first payment was issued to the person&rsquo;s bank nominated bank account on 20 August 2015.  </p><p>Arrears of allowance due from 30 April 2015 to 12 August 2015 were also issued to the bank</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.206" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD01325">State Pension (Contributory) Appeals</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.207.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1049" speakername="Michael Healy-Rae" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD01400"><p><i>166.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Social Protection the position regarding an application for a contributory pension appeal by a person (details supplied) in County Kerry; and if she will make a statement on the matter. <b>[30790/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.208.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD01500"><p>The Social Welfare Appeals Office has advised me that an appeal by the person concerned was registered in that office on 16<sup>th</sup>April 2015  It is a statutory requirement of the appeals process that the relevant papers and comments by or on behalf of the Deciding Officer on the grounds of appeal be sought from the Department of Social Protection  These papers have been received in the Social Welfare Appeals Office on 9 September 2015 and the case will be referred to an Appeals Officer who will make a summary decision on the appeal based on documentary evidence presented or, if required, hold an oral hearing.</p><p>The Social Welfare Appeals Office functions independently of the Minister for Social Protection and of the Department and is responsible for determining appeals against decisions in relation to social welfare entitlements.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.209" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD01550">Youth Unemployment Measures</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.210.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1050" speakername="Tom Fleming" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD01600"><p><i>167.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Social Protection the action that she is taking to address the extremely high level of youth unemployment, which in summer 2015, the Central Statistics Office reported was at a level of 20.02%, which is the current percentage of youth unemployment for over one year; and if she will make a statement on the matter. <b>[30812/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.211.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD01700"><p>The Government&rsquo;s primary strategy to tackle youth unemployment is through policies to create the environment for a strong economic recovery, by promoting competitiveness and productivity.Economic recovery will underpin jobs growth and the availability of productive employment for young people.  This strategy has been succeeding, with an increase of over 80,000 in employment over the last two years. </p><p>Youth unemployment continues to fall (with a rate of 22.4% in Q2 2015, as compared to 26.9% in Q2 2014). These figures are not adjusted for seasonality; the seasonally-adjusted rate as of August 2015 was 20.7%.</p><p>The number of young people who are long-term unemployed has fallen from 35,000 in mid-2012 (46% of all the young unemployed at that time) to 13,000 (31% of all the young unemployed) in mid-2015.</p><p>However, the Government recognises that as the recovery takes hold, there is a need for additional measures to ensure that as many as possible of the jobs created are taken up by jobseekers and young jobseekers in particular. This is the rationale behind the Government&rsquo;s <i>Pathways to Work</i>strategy and the Youth Guarantee.</p><p>The Youth Guarantee sets a medium-term objective of ensuring that young people receive an offer of employment within four months of becoming unemployed.The main plank of the guarantee is assistance to young people in finding and securing sustainable jobs.  For those who do not find employment, additional offers are provided for.Most such offers (over 70%) are in further education or training.  Others are in community-based employment programmes such as CE, Gateway and T&uacute;s, or through the JobsPlus employment subsidy for private employment.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.212" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD01750">Social Welfare Benefits</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.213.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/957" speakername="Bernard Durkan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD01800"><p><i>168.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Social Protection the allowances available to a person (details supplied) in County Kildare who is a widow, living alone and receiving widow's pension; and if she will make a statement on the matter. <b>[30815/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.214.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD01900"><p>In addition to their widow&rsquo;s contributory pension, the person concerned is in receipt of fuel allowance, free electricity allowance and free television licence.</p><p>The person&rsquo;s application for living alone increase was disallowed on the basis they had not reached the qualifying age of 66.  The decision to disallow the application for living alone increase has been appealed and the appeal has been forwarded to the independent Social Welfare Appeals Office. The person concerned will be contacted directly by that office regarding the outcome of their appeal.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.215" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD01950">Jobseeker's Allowance Payments</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.216.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/957" speakername="Bernard Durkan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD02000"><p><i>169.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Social Protection the correct amount of jobseeker's allowance being received in the case of persons (details supplied) in County Kildare; and if she will make a statement on the matter. <b>[30820/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.217.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD02050"><p>As outlined in reply to the Deputy&rsquo;s question number 29976-15 on 16 July 2015, the person concerned is in receipt of Jobseeker&rsquo;s Allowance at the appropriate rate (for the client, her partner and one child dependant).  Means, which have been reviewed since the reduction in the work pattern, are assessed against this payment in respect of her partner&rsquo;s income.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.218" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD02075">Carer's Allowance Applications</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.219.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD02100"><p><i>170.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Social Protection if she will provide an update with regard to an application for carer's allowance by a person (details supplied) in County Cork; and if she will make a statement on the matter. <b>[30826/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.220.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD02200"><p>I confirm that the department received an application for carer&rsquo;s allowance from the person in question on the 7 May 2015.  Some additional information in relation to the person&rsquo;s employment was required and has been requested by the deciding officer.  </p><p>Once this information is received, the application will be processed and the person concerned will be notified directly of the outcome.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.221" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD02250">Widow's Pension Applications</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.222.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/957" speakername="Bernard Durkan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD02300"><p><i>171.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Social Protection if she will review the level of widow's contributory pension in the case of a person (details supplied) in County Kildare; and if she will make a statement on the matter. <b>[30878/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.223.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD02400"><p>Entitlement to widow&rsquo;s contributory pension is based on either the social insurance record of the widow or that of their deceased spouse.  Their social insurance records cannot be combined to establish entitlement.</p>  <p>  The social insurance record of the person concerned consists of 129 paid and credited insurance contributions in respect of the period between 1974 and 1976.  This record is not sufficient to qualify the person for pension in their own right.  The Department has contacted the Department of Work and Pensions in the UK requesting the person&rsquo;s UK social insurance record.  When received, pension entitlement based on a combination of Irish and UK social insurance contributions will be examined.</p>  <p>  The person concerned was awarded a widow&rsquo;s contributory pension, under EU Regulations, with effect from the 3 April 2015, based on the combined social insurance contributions paid and credited by the person&rsquo;s late husband in Ireland and in the United Kingdom.</p>  <p>  Payment of this pension has not yet commenced because the person concerned has not yet notified the Department of their preferred payment method which was requested in June of this year. A reminder has recently issued to the person concerned.</p></reply>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.224" nospeaker="true" ><p>Question No. 172 answered with Question No. 136.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.225" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD02475">Community Employment Schemes Operation</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.226.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1054" speakername="Se&aacute;n &Oacute; Feargha&iacute;l" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD02500"><p><i>173.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Social Protection if she will provide funding for a gratuity or lump sum payment to community employment supervisors and assistant supervisors who retire on age or other grounds in advance of the possible introduction of a pension scheme for such workers; and if she will make a statement on the matter. <b>[30885/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.227.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD02600"><p>The Department of Social Protection has indicated that it is not in a position to provide funding for a gratuity or lump sum payment to Community Employment Supervisors on their retirement.  This has been advised and has been detailed in numerous responses to Parliamentary Questions on this topic.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.228" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD02650">Services for People with Disabilities</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.229.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1050" speakername="Tom Fleming" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD02700"><p><i>174.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Social Protection the number who participated in the WALK PEER pilot programme for young persons with disabilities; in view of the success of the scheme in providing employment opportunities, if she will roll-out this scheme nationwide; and if she will make a statement on the matter. <b>[30888/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.230.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD02800"><p><b></b>I should clarify at the outset that the WALK Peer initiative was not a &ldquo;pilot programme&rdquo;.  It was one of 14 disability activation projects (DACT),in the Border, Midlands &amp;amp; West region, which were jointly funded by the European Social Fund (ESF) and the Department.  WALK Peer supported a total of 119 participants during the lifetime of the project, with 12 participants remaining in education or some form of employment after 12 months.</p><p>The objective of the DACT project was to explore a variety of routes towards ensuring that people with disabilities were enabled to avail of progression, education and development opportunities within the world of work.  A key criterion applied when selecting projects was that any learning from the projects should be capable, where appropriate, of being mainstreamed in the future.</p><p>The Department commissioned Indecon International Economic Consultants to undertake an independent evaluation of the DACT project as a whole.  This report is now being finalised and the Department will in the near future be convening a working group, comprising the relevant Departments with responsibilities under the upcoming Comprehensive Employment Strategy for people with disabilities, to consider the findings and next steps.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.231" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD02850">Domiciliary Care Allowance Appeals</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.232.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1050" speakername="Tom Fleming" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD02900"><p><i>175.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Social Protection if she will examine and expedite a domiciliary care allowance appeal by a person (details supplied) in County Kerry; and if she will make a statement on the matter. <b>[30897/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.233.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD03000"><p>An application for domiciliary care allowance was received from the person concerned on the 20th January 2015.  This application was not allowed as the child was not considered to satisfy the qualifying conditions for the allowance.  A letter issued on the 29th April 2015 outlining the decision of the deciding officer to refuse the allowance. </p>  <p>  An appeal of this decision was registered on 3 June 2015 and additional information on this child&rsquo;s condition/care needs has been supplied.  The application together with the new information supplied was examined by another medical assessor who did not consider that the child met the medical criteria for the allowance.  Having reviewed the application in its entirety, the deciding officer considered that a revision of the original decision was not warranted and confirmed this in writing on the 7 September 2015.  The file has been forwarded to the Social Welfare Appeals Office for their consideration of the appeal.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.234" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD03050">Back to Work Allowance Applications</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.235.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1207" speakername="Billy Timmins" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD03100"><p><i>176.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Social Protection the position regarding a back to work allowance application by a person (details supplied) in County Wicklow; and if she will make a statement on the matter. <b>[30898/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.236.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD03200"><p>The Back to Work Enterprise Allowance (BTWEA) scheme supports people receiving certain social welfare payments who wish to pursue self-employment, allowing them to retain 100% of their social welfare entitlement in year one and 75% in year two. </p><p>There is no record of the person concerned having any current social welfare claim or of having made an application for BTWEA.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.237" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD03250">Social Welfare Appeals</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.238.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1049" speakername="Michael Healy-Rae" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD03300"><p><i>177.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Social Protection her views on correspondence (details supplied) regarding allowances; and if she will make a statement on the matter. <b>[30899/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.239.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD03400"><p>I am advised by the Social Welfare Appeals Office that an Appeals Officer, having fully considered all of the available evidence including that adduced at the oral hearing, had decided to disallow the appeal of the person concerned on 5 August 2015.  Under Social Welfare legislation, the decision of the Appeals Officer is final and conclusive and may only be reviewed by the Appeals Officer in the light of new evidence or new facts, or where there has been a change of circumstances which has come to notice since the date of the Appeals Officer's original decision.  </p>  <p>  I am advised that the person concerned has submitted additional evidence and that the file has been recalled from the Invalidity Pension section. The file will be submitted to the Appeals Officer for further consideration.  The person concerned will be contacted when the review of his appeal has been finalised.</p>  <p>  If the person&rsquo;s means are insufficient to meet his needs, he should contact his local Community Welfare Service regarding his possible entitlement to Supplementary Welfare Allowance.</p>  <p>  The Social Welfare Appeals Office functions independently of the Minister for Social Protection and of the Department and is responsible for determining appeals against decisions in relation to social welfare entitlements.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.240" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD03450">Illness Benefit Payments</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.241.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1034" speakername="Eoghan Murphy" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD03500"><p><i>178.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Social Protection if a person (details supplied) is only entitled to a reduced social welfare payment; and if there has been a change in policy regarding a person in this position. <b>[30908/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.242.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD03600"><p>Since January 1993 in accordance with the Social Welfare (Miscellaneous Social Insurance Provisions), (No. 2) Regulations 1992, (S.I. 448 of 1992) the rate of Illness Benefit payable is dependent on the claimant&rsquo;s earnings in the governing contribution year.  Where the average weekly earnings are &euro;300.00 or more the full rate is payable.  Where the earnings are less than this amount a graduated rate is payable.</p>  <p>  The person concerned claimed Illness Benefit from 5 June 2015 and, as his average weekly earnings in the 2013 governing contribution year were &euro;208.00 weekly, he was paid Illness Benefit at the graduated rate of &euro;121.40 weekly.  He has since opted to become a dependant on his spouse&rsquo;s Invalidity Pension, the dependent rate increase being &euro;138.10 weekly.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.243" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD03650">Data Protection</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.244.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD03700"><p><i>179.</i> To ask the Tnaiste and Minister for Social Protection the additional safeguards she has in place in her Department to safeguard against the illegal elicitation of personal data, in the wake of the recent revelations that a rogue private investigator is suspected of using illegal tactics to obtain data belonging to hundreds of credit union customers from officials in her Department. <b>[30909/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-09-22a.245.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015092200063#WRD03800"><p>The Department takes its responsibilities in relation to data protection very seriously. Every effort is made to ensure that personal customer data is used solely for business purposes and that it is not compromised in any way.  The Department has data protection and information security policies, standards, procedures and guidelines in place governing the use of its computer systems and customer data.  </p>  <p>The Department is very aware of the threat posed by all forms of bogus callers, including those that could be described as rogue Private Investigators and others who utilise social engineering to attempt to illegally elicit personal data.  A range of specific measures are in place to strengthen data protection governance and compliance within the Department.</p>  <p>  All members of staff of the Department are regularly reminded of their data protection obligations and the consequences of not adhering to policies such as loss of increment, loss of entitlement to enter promotional competitions and dismissal.  Staff members are required to sign annual undertakings that they have read, and will act in accordance with, data protection policies and guidelines.  </p>  <p>  A number of alerts have issued to all staff notifying them of bogus calls to the Department and giving information on modus operandi and persona adopted by the bogus callers.</p>  <p>  A high-level working group is in place to examine, and progress, all aspects of data protection compliance in the Department.  </p>  <p>  In June the Department ran its annual Data Protection Awareness Week for staff.  Activities this year included a very effective short video on social engineering which was developed in-house and made available to all staff; a data protection newsletter issued to all staff; presentations were made to hundreds of staff nationwide which included a section on &lsquo;blagging&rsquo; and posters were exhibited in headquarter and local offices drawing attention to the importance of securing customers&rsquo; personal data.</p>  <p>  Oversight is maintained by logging data accesses which are subject to audit.  All allegations of data breaches are fully investigated and the Department cooperates fully with the Office of the Data Protection Commissioner in all its investigations.</p></reply>
</publicwhip>