<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.3" nospeaker="true" ><p>The following are questions tabled by Members for written response and the ministerial replies as received on the day from the Departments [unrevised].</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.4" nospeaker="true" ><p>Questions Nos. 1 to 9, inclusive, answered orally.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.5" nospeaker="true" ><p>Questions Nos. 10 to 105, inclusive, resubmitted.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.6" nospeaker="true" ><p>Questions Nos. 106 to 114, inclusive, answered orally.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.8" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA00600">Department of Children and Youth Affairs</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.7" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA00550">Child Protection Services</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.8.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1052" speakername="Catherine Murphy" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA00600"><p><i>115.</i> To ask the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs the number of children that are currently waiting to be allocated a social worker; the number of these that are high priority and emergency; if he will provide a breakdown in tabular format of the number of each of these that have been waiting for less than six months, between six months and one year, between one year and 18 months, between 18 months and two years and longer than two years; the number of social workers that are employed at present; the number of these that are on maternity leave; his plans to address the shortfalls; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2189/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.9.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA00700"><p>As of November 2014, the Child and Family Agency has advised that a total of 19,988 children were in receipt of a dedicated social work service.  A further 8,451 cases did not have an allocated social worker.  <br/><br/>Of these 8,451 cases, 2,844 were deemed to be high priority.  Of the 8,451 children who do not have an allocated social worker, 5,347 have been waiting longer than three months for a social worker to be allocated to them.  Of these 1,774, are deemed to be high priority.  These cases represent a mix of new referrals that need further assessment and social work input, as well as children known to the Agency who need a continuing social work service.  I am assured by the Agency that emergency cases continue to be dealt with immediately, for instance a child who has been abandoned or is in immediate physical danger or at immediate risk of sexual abuse and that high priority cases are kept under review.<br/><br/>At the end of November, 2014 there were 1,403 whole time equivalent social workers employed by the Agency representing 40% of its overall workforce.  A total of 84 social workers were on maternity leave.  The impact of vacancies on service provision is risk-assessed on an on-going basis to ensure that social work team numbers do not fall below what is considered necessary to provide a safe service. <br/><br/>The Child and Family Agency is taking a number of initiatives to address staff shortfalls:<br/><br/>- Continuing recruitment, with 155 social workers recruited since the Agency was established, and a further 193 posts currently in the recruitment process;<br/><br/>- The introduction of a pilot Maternity Leave Scheme whereby temporary staff can be offered a 12 month contract to cover maternity leave;<br/><br/>- In recognition of the challenging nature of this work, new entrants and graduates have a reduced workload for their first year, with opportunities for regular supervision with experienced practitioners;<br/><br/>- The roll out of a caseload management system to ensure caseloads are manageable and prioritised appropriately.<br/><br/>For the Deputy's information, I have set out in tabular format, the total number of children in receipt of social work services broken down by those who have been allocated a social worker, those who are awaiting allocation to a social worker and their associated priority levels as at November 2014.  Also included are details of the length of time children have been waiting for allocation to a social worker and their associated priority level. <br/><br/>The Agency has advised that it collects the relevant data in a standardised manner and not in the format as requested by the Deputy.  <br/><br/><b>Breakdown of Allocation by Priority</b><table><tr><th>Open Cases by Priority</th><th>Allocated</th><th>Unallocated</th><th>Total</th></tr><tr><td>High</td><td>8,767</td><td>2,844</td><td>11,611</td></tr><tr><td>Medium</td><td>6,852</td><td>3,977</td><td>10,829</td></tr><tr><td>Low</td><td>4,369</td><td>1,630</td><td>5,999</td></tr><tr><td>TOTAL</td><td>19,988</td><td>8,451</td><td>28,439</td></tr></table><br/><br/><b>Breakdown of Unallocated cases by Length of time and Priority</b><table><tr><th>Open Cases Unallocated at the end of the Month</th><th><div>High Priority</div></th><th><div>Medium Priority</div></th><th><div>Low Priority</div></th><th><div>Total</div></th></tr><tr><td>&amp;lt;1 week</td><td><div>103</div></td><td><div>91</div></td><td><div>17</div></td><td><div>211</div></td></tr><tr><td>1-2 weeks</td><td><div>129</div></td><td><div>127</div></td><td><div>44</div></td><td><div>300</div></td></tr><tr><td>2-3 weeks</td><td><div>174</div></td><td><div>199</div></td><td><div>64</div></td><td><div>437</div></td></tr><tr><td>3-4 weeks</td><td><div>179</div></td><td><div>296</div></td><td><div>83</div></td><td><div>558</div></td></tr><tr><td>1-2 months</td><td><div>272</div></td><td><div>483</div></td><td><div>127</div></td><td><div>882</div></td></tr><tr><td>2-3 months</td><td><div>213</div></td><td><div>303</div></td><td><div>200</div></td><td><div>716</div></td></tr><tr><td>&amp;gt;3 months</td><td><div>1,774</div></td><td><div>2,478</div></td><td><div>1,095</div></td><td><div>5,347</div></td></tr><tr><td>TOTAL</td><td><div>2,844</div></td><td><div>3,977</div></td><td><div>1,630</div></td><td><div>8,451</div></td></tr></table></p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.10" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA00750">Mother and Baby Homes Inquiries</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.11.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1195" speakername="Ruth Coppinger" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA00800"><p><i>116.</i> To ask the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs the reason there is no provision for archaeological research to take place within the remit of the Commission of Investigation into Mother and Baby Homes and Certain Related Matters. <b>[2182/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.12.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA00900"><p>The Commissions of Investigation Act 2004 provides an effective, prompt and transparent mechanism to investigate complex and sensitive matters while also respecting fair procedures and natural justice. The 2004 Act gives the Commission robust powers to conduct investigations within its terms of reference in the manner it considers appropriate while adhering to the rules and procedures contained within the Act. </p>  <p>  The primary focus of this investigation is on the experiences of women and children who lived in Mother and Baby Homes over the period 1922-1998. While the Terms of Reference provide for a comprehensive investigative framework, the Commission is independent in the performance of its investigations and in deciding how best to approach its work.  </p>  <p>  The Deputy may wish to note that Section 8 of the 2004 Act provides that the Commission may, with the consent of the Minister, appoint persons with relevant qualifications to advise and assist the Commission.  Given the range and scale of the discrete issues to be examined, it is anticipated that the Commission may require the assistance of additional professional expertise and specialists for particular tasks, and funding is available for this purpose. Therefore, it is ultimately a matter for the Commission to consider whether it requires archaeological research and there is ample discretion in the Commission of Investigations Act for the Commission to pursue such methods if it so determines.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.13" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA00950">Early Years Strategy Publication</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.14.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1065" speakername="Robert Troy" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA01000"><p><i>117.</i> To ask the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs when the early years strategy, originally promised for 2012, will be published; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2203/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.15.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA01100"><p>The objective of Ireland's first Early Years Strategy is to create an innovative and dynamic blueprint for the future development of Ireland&rsquo;s early years sector and a coherent approach to seeking to improve the lives of children from birth to 6 years. <br/><br/>The Early Years Strategy will address a range of issues affecting children in their first years of life such as child health and well-being, parenting and family support, learning and development and play.<br/><br/>Considerable work has been done on the development of the Early Years Strategy.  The work of the Expert Advisory Group, <i>Right from the Start</i>, has greatly informed the work to date.  I have signalled my intention to conduct focused consultations with relevant parties across the early childhood care and education sector before concluding my own deliberations on the Strategy.  I am also mindful of the importance of other work which is being undertaken in parallel in respect of the future investment priorities in respect of childcare.  Taking account of these developments, I expect to be in a position to publish the Strategy once my own consultations have concluded in the coming months.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.16" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA01150">Social Workers Recruitment</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.17.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1017" speakername="Finian McGrath" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA01200"><p><i>118.</i> To ask the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs if he will provide an update on the major shortfall of social workers dealing with child support services; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2162/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.18.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA01300"><p>Staffing vacancies arise for a variety of reasons, including retirements, career breaks, paid and unpaid leave (including maternity and other family related leave) and resignations. The Child and Family Agency (TUSLA) has advised that there were 1,403.46 whole time equivalent social workers employed at the end of November 2014 and that they are currently recruiting an additional 193 social workers to meet existing vacancies. They have also advised that 155 social workers have already been recruited during 2014 and that 102 social workers left employment due to retirement and for other reasons.</p>  <p>  There are currently 84 social workers on maternity leave and in order to address priority gaps in service resulting from maternity leave, a pilot Maternity Leave Cover scheme has been introduced whereby maternity related vacancies in each region can be filled by way of a temporary contracts. The Pilot Scheme involves the allocation of 100 posts between each region, 80 of which relate specifically to social workers. </p>  <p>  The impact of vacancies on service provision is risk-assessed on an ongoing basis to ensure that social work team members are never allowed to fall below what is considered necessary to provide a safe service. Such risk-assessments take account of issues such as case loads and referral numbers. Where necessary, temporary staff  are brought in immediately to cover vacancies until such vacancies are filled on a permanent basis.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.19" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA01350">Child Poverty</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.20.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1003" speakername="Richard Boyd Barrett" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA01400"><p><i>119.</i> To ask the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs his Department's plans for measures to tackle child poverty here in 2015; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2180/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.21.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA01500"><p><i>Better Outcomes, Brighter Futures: the National Policy Framework for Children and Young People 2014 - 2020 (BOBF),</i>which was published and launched by Government in 2014, provides the overarching framework for the development and implementation of policy and services for children and young people. As provided for in the Framework, the Department of Social Protection is the lead department on child poverty and has lead responsibility for the commitment to lift over 70,000 children out of consistent poverty by 2020, a reduction of at least two-thirds on the 2011 level.  The Department of Social Protection also has lead responsibility for the National Action Plan for Social Inclusion.<br/><br/>My Department is working on a number of initiatives which are relevant in addressing issues related to children poverty.  For example, in terms of other provision, my Department is spending &euro;260 million annually on childcare support programmes which provide childcare to 100,000 children. A number of these programmes are targeted at those on lowest incomes. The CCS programme provides subvention support to parents on low incomes and parents in receipt of certain social welfare payments, whose children are enrolled in community childcare facilities. Additionally, the 3 Training and Employment Childcare (TEC) programmes - the Childcare Education and Training Programme, the Community Employment Childcare programme and the Afterschool Childcare Programme - provide childcare supports to eligible parents returning to work or to education. <br/><br/>It is leading the implementation of the Area Based Childhood (ABC) Programme (2013-2016).  The ABC Programme is being co-funded by Atlantic Philanthropies and will have a total funding allocation of up to &euro;29.7 million.  The ABC Programme draws on best international practice to break the cycle of child poverty where it is most deeply entrenched, and improve the outcomes for children and young people and existing services.<br/><br/>My Department also provides targeted support for disadvantaged, marginalised and at risk young people are provided through the Special Projects for Youth Scheme, the Young People's Facilities and Services Fund, Rounds 1 and 2, Local Drugs Task Force Projects.  In addition, some 31 national and major regional youth work organisations are supported under my Department's Youth Service Grant Scheme and other schemes include the Local Youth Club Grant Scheme and Youth Information Centres.  In 2015, current funding of &euro;49.93m will be provided to my Department for these schemes.<br/><br/>The outcomes of the recent European Commission/Departmental of Social Protection/Department of Children and Youth Affairs national seminar will inform the development of an implementation plan for tackling child poverty.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.22" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA01550">Illegal Adoptions</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.23.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1192" speakername="Clare Daly" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA01600"><p><i>120.</i> To ask the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs in view of the Adoption Authority's recent acknowledgement that thousands of illegal adoptions took place here, the steps he will take to have these matters investigated, and/or prosecuted criminally. <b>[2127/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.24.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA01700"><p>The Adoption Act 1952 provided a legal basis for adoption in Ireland and for the establishment of the Adoption Board. This brought order to what had been the system of ad-hoc arrangements in lieu of formal adoption procedures up to this point. Prior to the commencement of the 1952 Adoption Act it would be inaccurate to describe these informal adoptions as illegal. However, it is recognised that many adoptions were never formalised even under the transitional arrangement available for some such informal adoptions following the commencement of the Act.  Historic private arrangements operated in conditions of great secrecy and in many cases there are no written records of these events. </p>  <p>  Post 1952, there is some evidence that such ad-hoc arrangements may have continued. It should be noted that there was no barrier to the private placement of a child until the Act of 1998, although such adoptions were required to be legally formalised. In addition, there is some evidence that such private placements may have concealed the true parentage of the child and been registered as a child born to persons with whom the child was placed. Any such registration is a breach of the Civil Registration Acts.  Those affected by illegal registrations, are now unable to access personal records and information.  </p>  <p>  While my Department is not in a position to confirm the actual extent of such registrations, I am advised by the Adoption Authority that a review of the National Adoption Contact Preference Register in 2010 found that there were 100 cases and a further 20 since then, where no adoption took place. The Authority has advised me that, in the first instance, any person seeking information on adoption, or an illegal registration of a birth, should contact the Authority or the Child and Family Agency&rsquo;s Community Services. They are also advised that if any person believes that their birth was illegally registered they should inform the General Registrations Office (GRO) as the body responsible for registration of births, who in turn may refer cases of illegal registrations to the Garda&iacute; Siochana for investigation of criminal wrongdoing. </p>  <p>  The Deputy will be aware that the proposed Terms of Reference for the Commission of Investigation into Mother and Baby Homes were announced recently and Article 1(VII) specifically requires the Commission to investigate the nature of the relationship between Mother and Baby Homes and other key institutions including children&rsquo;s homes; orphanages; and adoption societies. The Commission will investigate evidence relating to patterns of referral, relationships and cooperation with other entities and intermediary organisations, and any systematic arrangements for the placement of children. I believe that this will allow the Commission sufficient scope to examine both the issue of placing such children for adoption abroad, as well as to examine situations in which the child&rsquo;s parentage was concealed, either by omission or sometimes, by illegal means. If the Commission's reports reveal issues of concern which are potentially criminal in nature, these will be referred to the appropriate investigative and prosecution authorities.</p>  <p>  My Department is continuing to work on the Heads of Bill for the Adoption (Information and Tracing) Bill and I hope to be in a position to seek Government approval to publish the Heads of Bill as soon as possible. I can say that, the issues in relation to illegal registrations are being considered as part of the drafting process.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.25" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA01750">Mother and Baby Homes Inquiries</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.26.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1193" speakername="Joan Collins" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA01800"><p><i>121.</i> To ask the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs the reason the inquiry into the mother and baby homes does not include Westbank Orphanage, County Wicklow. <b>[46774/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.27.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA01900"><p>In developing the Terms of Reference for the Commission of Investigation into Mother and Baby Homes and certain related matters, due regard has been given to the clear emphasis on &ldquo;Mother and Baby Homes&rdquo; in the motion approved by D&aacute;il Eireann on the 11th June 2014. The investigation will thoroughly examine a broad range of matters in relation to the experience of mothers and children who were resident in a Mother and Baby Home over the period 1922-1998. As the Deputy will be aware these Homes have not been the central focus of previous statutory investigations.</p>  <p>  The approach taken to ensure the requisite level of specificity has been to identify Mother and Baby Homes for the purposes of this investigation. The criteria used include having the main function of providing sheltered and supervised ante- and post-natal facilities to single mothers and their children, including both board and lodgings; and an ethos which those running the institutions considered to promote a regime of work, training or education as part of an overall approach to either rehabilitating single mothers, or to give them training for living independently. On the basis of the available information, the institution raised by the Deputy did not provide this type of service for mothers and babies. </p>  <p>   However, it is not accurate to describe these institutions as being excluded from the Commission's work. During the course of consultations, it became clear to me that the issue of entry and exit pathways of both women and children to these Homes raised further questions which needed to be examined. For this reason, the Commission is tasked with examining the extent to which other entities, including children&rsquo;s homes, orphanages and adoption societies, were part of these pathways. This examination will identify patterns of referral, and the practices and arrangements for placing children, including where an intermediary organisation was involved in arranging a subsequent placement. It is certainly open to the Commission to examine the role played by the institution raised by the Deputy in this strand of its investigations. Issues to be examined by the social history module also include the role and interrelationships of a range of institutions, including homes for infants or children. </p>  <p>  I do appreciate that since the decision to establish this investigation was announced there have been calls for the inclusion of a broad range of matters. At least some of these issues are unrelated to the intended remit of this investigation. In addition, and in the interests of maintaining the required focus and specificity on Mother and Baby Homes, it must be recognised that previous inquiries have already examined some related issues. This includes the comprehensive investigation into historical child abuse already conducted by the Commission to Inquire into Child Abuse. Its remit was to inquire into the abuse of children in a broad range of care settings, including childrens' homes, during the period 1940 to 1999.</p>  <p>  The Government is satisfied that the proposed Terms of Reference Government provide an ambitious and appropriately focused set of tasks which can be accomplished by this Commission within a realistic timeframe.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.28" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA01950">Child Care Law Reporting Project</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.29.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1192" speakername="Clare Daly" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA02000"><p><i>122.</i> To ask the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs if changes have been made, or are planned, as a result of the findings to date of the Child Care Law Reporting Project, including an indicative timeframe of when any changes might be implemented. <b>[2128/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.30.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA02100"><p>The Child Care Law Reporting Project (CCLRP) is an independent project established with the support of the Department of Children and Youth Affairs, the One Foundation and Atlantic Philanthropies.<br/><br/>The aims and objectives of the project are to:<br/><br/>- Provide information to the public on child care proceedings in the courts;<br/><br/>- Conduct research on these proceedings in order to promote debate and inform policy-makers;<br/><br/>- Make recommendations to address any short-comings in the child care system identified by the research;<br/><br/>- Assist in the implementation of these recommendations;<br/><br/>- Promote confidence in the child care system.<br/><br/>The project pursues its aims and objectives by attending the courts where child care cases are heard in order to report on those proceedings while protecting the anonymity of the children and their families.<br/><br/>The project provides a measure of the effectiveness of current systems and policies in the area of child protection and of court administration. Ultimately it is assisting the Department in gaining a greater depth of knowledge and understanding of child care cases and is increasing the evidence base on which future policy formulation is based.<br/><br/>The Child Care Law Reporting Project publishes reports of child care cases before the courts. It collects and analyses data from the proceedings on the nature and outcomes of the child care proceedings and seeks to promote a public debate on the issues raised through seminars and conferences. This includes small round-table sessions with key policy makers and practitioners. To date, the project has published four volumes of case reports each year in 2013 and 2014 as well as two interim reports, published in November 2013 and October 2014. This work informs Tusla practice and policy on an ongoing basis. Issues raised are also informing the Department's policy and legislative programme. This includes a proposed review of the Child Care Act 1991 which is currently being scoped.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.31" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA02150">Youth Justice Strategy</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.32.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/956" speakername="Mick Wallace" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA02200"><p><i>123.</i> To ask the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs if he has had any discussion with the Department of Justice and Equality in relation to the use of detention on remand for child offenders, in view of statistics from the Irish Penal Reform Trust which found that only approximately 45% of children detained on remand actually go on to receive a detaining order indicating a possible overuse of detention on remand; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2192/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.33.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA02300"><p>There is ongoing cooperation between my Department and the Department of Justice and Equality in relation to all aspects of the youth justice system.  The Irish Youth Justice Service is based in my Department and has responsibility for leading and driving reform in the area of youth justice.<br/><br/>The focus of the <i>Youth Justice Action Plan 2014-2018</i>, which was launched by the Minister for Justice and Equality and the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs on 3 February 2014 is to achieve better outcomes for children who get into trouble with the law, to reduce crime leading to safer communities and to use detention only as a last resort.  The issue of the nature and pattern of remands in custody for children has recently been the subject of discussions involving the Irish Youth Justice Service and Tusla, the Child and Family Agency which will feed into the development of policy priorities for the Youth Justice Action Plan for 2015.  <br/><br/>Under Section 88 of the Children Act 2001, a court may remand a child in custody who is charged with or found guilty of an offence, who is being sent forward for trial, or in respect of whom the court has postponed a decision. The judiciary are independent in the performance of their functions and the discretion as to whether or not to remand a child in custody is solely for the judge to decide.  The figure of 45% of children quoted by the Deputy is contained in the 2013 annual report of the Irish Penal Reform Trust.  The methodology for this figure is not stated and this may relate to both the detention schools and also 17 year old boys who are currently detained in the adult prison system.  I am advised that in 2013, there were 96 individuals remanded in custody to the children detention schools of whom 26 received a detention order, which equates to 27% of the children concerned.  The comparable figures for 2011 and 2012 were 35% and 31% respectively.  <br/><br/>In many cases, there may be a range of factors affecting the decision of a court on the remand of a child in custody.  As well as a pattern of criminal behaviour, this may also include identified service needs in areas such as mental health supports, substance abuse or educational welfare.  Section 88(10) of the Children Act states that the court shall not remand a child in custody if the only reason for so doing is that the child is in need of care or protection or the court wishes Tusla to assist it in dealing with the case.  The court may also request Tusla to be represented in the proceedings under section 76B of the Children Act.  Children are legally represented in court and the courts also have the authority to require the attendance of parents or guardians to assist the court in dealing with any individual case involving a child.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.34" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA02350">Youth Services</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.35.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1182" speakername="Terence Flanagan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA02400"><p><i>124.</i> To ask the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs the position regarding his Department's national youth strategy; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2194/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.36.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA02500"><p>The National Youth Strategy will focus on the youth-related policy commitments outlined in Better Outcomes, Brighter Futures, the National Policy Framework for Children and Young People. It will be a universal strategy for all young people aged 10 to 24. It will have a particular focus on those who are most disadvantaged or at risk and who have the poorest outcomes and therefore in most need of support.</p>  <p>  A National Youth Strategy Task Group, convened by my Department, is overseeing the development of the new Strategy. This Task Group comprises statutory youth interests and voluntary agencies and organisations working with young people.</p>  <p>   I am keen that all stakeholders have a role to play in the development of the new National Youth Strategy and a comprehensive consultation process is underway at present. This consultation process includes online surveys of young people and those working with young people and three major stakeholder events planned for later this month. These events are for young people, the youth sector, NGOs working for and with young people, Education and Training Boards, Government departments, agencies, business and academia and other youth interests. The events will also include consultation on the new Strategy and the findings of the recently completed Value for Money and Policy Review of Youth Programmes. The Review makes recommendations for the future operation of youth funding schemes and their development in the years ahead to ensure effective, value for money services that will be evidence based and improve outcomes for young people. </p>  <p>  The consultation will run into February 2015 and I anticipate that the Strategy will be completed promptly thereafter.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.37" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA02550">Mother and Baby Homes Inquiries</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.38.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1195" speakername="Ruth Coppinger" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA02600"><p><i>125.</i> To ask the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs the reason the Magdalen laundries are not included in the Commission of investigation into Mother and Baby Homes and Certain Related Matters. <b>[2183/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.39.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA02700"><p>I announced the proposed Terms of Reference for the Commission of Investigation into Mother and Baby Homes and certain related matters on Friday, 9th January. While due regard has been given to the emphasis on &ldquo;Mother and Baby Homes&rdquo; in the motion approved by D&aacute;il Eireann on the 11th June 2014, the terms of reference also reflect a much wider agenda of directly related matters than was evident at the initiation of this process.</p>  <p>  The approach taken provides a clear and deliberate emphasis on the experiences of women and children who spent time in Mother and Baby Homes over the period 1922-1998. As we know these institutions have not been the central focus of previous investigations. Clear criteria have been used to identify Mother and Baby Homes for the purpose of this investigation, including having the main function of providing sheltered and supervised ante and post-natal facilities to single mothers and their children. The Terms of Reference do include the former Magdalen Home at 8 Lower lesson Street, Dublin 2, as a Mother and Baby Home, although the information available indicates that the Magdalen Laundries did not provide this specific type of service. </p>  <p>  During the course of my consultations with advocacy groups and political colleagues across the spectrum, it became clear to me that the issue of entry and exit pathways of both women and children raised further questions which needed to be examined. In this regard, the Deputy may wish to note that the Commission is tasked with examining the extent to which other entities were part of the entry or exit pathways for single mothers and children into or leaving these specified Homes. It is certainly open to the Commission to give consideration to the Magdalen Laundries in this significant strand of its investigations. The issues to be examined by the social history module also explicitly cite the Magdalen Laundries in this regard. </p>  <p>  I believe that both the Commissions of Investigation Act 2004, and the Terms of Reference themselves, provide adequate opportunity for the Commission to take an independent view of the adequacy of scope, given its task. The Deputy may also wish to note that the proposed arrangements, in particular Article 6 of the Terms of Reference, require the Commission to make recommendations in respect of any matters which is not covered by the existing scope, but which it considers may warrant investigation in the public interest.</p>  <p>  Details in respect of the Commission are available on my Department&rsquo;s website including a number of explanatory documents.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.40" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA02750">Child and Family Agency Staff</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.41.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/969" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA02800"><p><i>126.</i> To ask the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs the details of the high turnover of social workers employed by Tusla, in view of the fact that they are more than twice as likely to resign their positions when compared to other employments in the health and social services generally; the actions being taken to ensure that this does not occur; the further action being taken to ensure that any child at risk and not currently under the care of a social worker will be catered for; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2197/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.42.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA02900"><p>There have been some recent media reports around HSE data which shows a social work turnover rate of 15% from 2010 to 2013. I understand that this relates to social work across all services including Primary Care, Disabilities, Mental Health, Older Persons and Children and Families. While the Agency is experiencing some staff retention issues, the turnover of social workers in the Agency&rsquo;s first year of operation (2014) was 6.7% &ndash; less than that experienced in many neighbouring countries. At the end of November 2014, there were 1,403.46 whole time equivalent social workers and the Agency is currently recruiting an additional 193 posts to meet existing vacancies. </p>  <p>  The area of child protection and welfare social work is one of the most challenging areas of work for any professional and involves working closely with some of the most vulnerable and marginalised individuals and groups in society. The Agency is committed to producing a Workforce Development Plan by the end of June 2015, which will provide an opportunity to improve resource deployment and take account of the need to support and develop staff who work in this critical area.</p>  <p>  The impact of vacancies on service provision is risk-assessed on an ongoing basis to ensure that social work team members are never allowed to fall below what is considered necessary to provide a safe service. Such risk-assessments take account of issues such as case loads and referral numbers. Where necessary, temporary staff  are brought in immediately to cover vacancies until such vacancies are filled on a permanent basis.  The Deputy should note that if a child does not have an allocated social worker it does not mean that there is no oversight from social work professionals. Cases awaiting allocation are reviewed regularly by the principal social worker/team leaders and are managed by duty social work teams.  Depending on the circumstances and priority level, the child could be visited regularly by the social worker on duty and/or other professionals, such as teachers, may be contacted daily if necessary.  The purpose of the oversight is to establish if the child&rsquo;s circumstances have changed and to monitor the risk to their well-being. An example could be where an initial assessment has established a child is at high risk due to their parent&rsquo;s abuse of alcohol, however, the child then goes to live with their grandparents, and so immediate risk decreases although the case will require further attention.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.43" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA02950">Child Poverty</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.44.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1017" speakername="Finian McGrath" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA03000"><p><i>127.</i> To ask the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs the supports for children living in disadvantaged communities; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2165/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.45.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA03100"><p>Responsibility for addressing disadvantage is a matter for all Departments and Ministers and indeed for wider society. The provision of intervention and supports to target the particular needs of children will be dependent on the type of disadvantage, be it social, financial, educational, health etc. Responsibility for the identification and provision of those interventions will fall to my Ministerial colleagues as appropriate to the type of disadvantage. For example, the Department of Education and Skills have lead responsibility for issues concerning educational disadvantage, the Department of Social Protection has lead responsibility for addressing child poverty.<br/><br/>Notwithstanding this, I am fully convinced of the need for a whole-of-government approach in addressing such issues.<i>Better Outcomes, Brighter Futures: The National Policy Framework for Children and Young People (2014-2020)</i>takes such an approach in addressing disadvantage for children, emphasising an integrated and evidence informed approach to working across government, on horizontal and vertical levels, which transfers to all sectors and settings working with children and young people.<br/><br/>While my Department has overall responsibility for the framework, individual Departments will continue to take lead roles on matters within their remit.<br/><br/>My Department has lead responsibility for a range of funding schemes which target disadvantage across the areas of services and supports for children and young people.<br/><br/>My Department supports a range of education support services for children in disadvantaged communities. Tusla, the Child and Family Agency has a statutory remit to support children and young people to participate in and benefit from the education system. Tusla has responsibility to ensure that each child attends a recognised school or otherwise receives a certain minimum education<br/><br/>Tusla delivers an integrated approach to educational welfare services through the continued reform of work practices to provide an enhanced response to the needs of children, families and schools. Three service strands &ndash; the statutory Educational Welfare Service and the School Support Programme services under the Department of Education's DEIS Action Plan (namely, the Home-School Community Liaison Scheme and the School Completion Programme) collectively form the Educational Welfare Services (EWS) of the Agency. <br/><br/>I am advised by Tusla that the statutory Educational Welfare Services worked with over 20,000 children in 2013. Some 2,434 cases involved intensive intervention and a multidisciplinary approach and the provision of sustained support by an Education Welfare Officer to address the child's needs and support school attendance. During this period the School Completion Programme provided targeted support to approximately 36,000 children and young people at risk of early school leaving across 124 community based programmes.<br/><br/>Tusla also provides a range of services that offer advice and support to families.  This includes over 100 family resource centres.  The aim of the Family Resource Centre Programme is to combat disadvantage and improve the functioning of the family unit. The Programme emphasises involving local communities in tackling the problems they face, and creating successful partnerships between voluntary and statutory agencies at community level. <br/><br/>The main focus of these services is on early intervention aiming to promote and protect the health and well-being and rights of all children, young people and their families.  At the same time particular attention is given to those who are vulnerable or at risk.<br/><br/>I recently issued the Performance Statement 2015 to the Tusla. This Performance Statement provides Tusla with specific policy guidance, direction, and prioritisation and resource parameters to inform the preparation of its Business Plan for 2015.<br/><br/>As part of the Performance Statement, I have asked that in the area of family support, Tusla should provide a clear framework for action to expedite and enhance their capabilities in the area of early intervention and protection through supporting parents and families in accordance with relevant Government policy.  Key elements of this framework are to be developed during 2015.<br/><br/>My Department administers a range of funding schemes and programmes to support the provision of youth services to young people throughout the country, including those from disadvantaged communities.  Targeted support for disadvantaged, marginalised and at risk young people are provided through the Special Projects for Youth Scheme, the Young People's Facilities and Services Fund, Rounds 1 and 2, Local Drugs Task Force Projects.  In addition, some 31 national and major regional youth work organisations are supported under my Department's Youth Service Grant Scheme and other schemes include the Local Youth Club Grant Scheme and Youth Information Centres. The funding schemes support national and local youth work provision to some 380,000 young people and involve approximately, 1,400 youth work staff in 477 projects and 40,000 volunteers working in youth work services and communities throughout the country. In 2015, current funding of &euro;49.93m will be provided to my Department for these schemes.<br/><br/>My Department also assists children experiencing deprivation by taking the lead in implementing the Area Based Childhood (ABC) Programme. The ABC Programme is being co-funded by Atlantic Philanthropies and will have a total funding allocation of up to &euro;29.7 million.  The ABC Programme draws on best international practice to break the cycle of child poverty in communities where it is most deeply entrenched, and improve the outcomes for children and young people and existing services.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.46" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA03150">Child Abuse Prevention</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.47.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1065" speakername="Robert Troy" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA03200"><p><i>128.</i> To ask the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs the role his Department is playing in combatting online child grooming, cyber bullying and abuse; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2205/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.48.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA03300"><p>Combatting online child grooming is a matter for my colleague the Minister for Justice and Equality. As part of a wide-ranging package of measures aimed at the reform of Ireland&rsquo;s criminal law on sexual offences, including online grooming, child abuse, child exploitation and child pornography, Minister Fitzgerald recently published the General Scheme to the Criminal Law (Sexual Offences) Bill.</p>  <p>  The Office for Internet Safety, an executive office of the Department of Justice and Equality, has previously published guidance related to cyber bullying and filtering technologies for parents. </p>  <p>  My Department has actively engaged with the Department of Education and Skills on the dangers associated with bullying, including online activity. The anti-bullying agenda has been a recurring element in my Department&rsquo;s consultations with young people. Notably, the majority of the 34 Comhairle na n&Oacute;g initiatives funded by my Department have identified mental health services, cyber bullying and homophobic bullying as priority issues for young people. This has led a number of targeted measures being adopted by service providers across the country.</p>  <p>  Tusla, the Child and Family Agency, produced a Child Protection and Welfare Practice Handbook, intended for social workers and other professionals who refer child welfare and protection cases. The Handbook contains advice in respect of online safety and online child sexual abuse in order to heighten awareness of same. </p>  <p>  It is my view that each Government Department is responsible for how child protection obligations should be met in its own sector, reflecting the Government&rsquo;s position that best safeguarding practice should become a cultural norm. My Department is represented on an Implementation Team formed in response to the 2014 report of the Internet Content Governance Advisory Group, commissioned by the previous Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources. The Implementation Team is considering the report's recommendations and how best to address them.</p>  <p>  I would encourage any individual who has concerns about activities that may constitute grooming, to make contact directly with An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.49" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA03350">Child and Family Agency Staff</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.50.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1177" speakername="Denis Naughten" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA03400"><p><i>129.</i> To ask the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs the steps he is taking to address the number of resignations of social workers within Tusla; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2186/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.51.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA03500"><p>There has been some recent media reports of a social worker turnover rate of 15%. I understand that this relates to HSE figures for the period 2010 to 2013 and relates to social work across all services including Primary Care, Disabilities, Mental Health, Older Persons and Children and Families. While the Child and Family Agency is experiencing some staff retention issues, the turnover of social workers in the Agency&rsquo;s first year of operation (2014) was 6.7% &ndash; less than that experienced in many neighbouring countries. </p>  <p>  The Child and Family Agency (TUSLA) have advised that there were 1,403.46 whole time equivalent social workers employed at the end of November 2014 and that they are currently recruiting an additional 193 social workers to meet existing vacancies. They have also advised that 155 social workers have already been recruited during 2014 and that 102 social workers left employment due to retirement and for other reasons.</p>  <p>  Stability, experience and capacity of staff working in the area of child protection and child welfare is extremely important. The Agency is committed to producing a Workforce Development Strategy by end of second Quarter 2015. This is to ensure that strategic and operational workforce development plans and processes are established as key activities in the Agency. This development presents the Agency with a significant opportunity to improve resource deployment, skill and grade mix and staff motivation to the benefit of the children and families. The workforce development plan will consider issues around recruitment, retention and turnover of key staff. This will also include further developing supports through structured professional and career development.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.52" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA03550">Juvenile Offenders</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.53.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/957" speakername="Bernard Durkan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA03600"><p><i>130.</i> To ask the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs the extent to which juveniles have been incarcerated in adult prisons over the past three years; his plans to address this issue and where possible provide rehabilitative and custodial care in lieu of such practices; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2185/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.54.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA03700"><p>On a sample date of 30 October 2012, there were a total of 31 children detained in the adult prison system.  The comparable figure for the same date in 2013 was 14 children and the same number also applied on 30 October 2014.  The reduction of approximately 50% in the number of children detained in the adult prison system between 2012 and 2013 reflects the transfer of responsibility for 16 year old boys to the children detention schools, which was put in place in May 2012.  On 16 January 2015, there were a total of 16 boys detained in the adult prison system, comprising 6 boys remanded in custody in St Patrick&rsquo;s Institution and 10 boys serving a sentence of detention in Wheatfield Place of Detention. <br/><br/>There is a commitment in the Programme for Government to end the practice of detaining<b></b>children in adult prison facilities.  Significant progress has been made and this commitment will  be fully met when the extension of the Oberstown campus results in the transfer of responsibility for 17 year old boys from the adult prison system to the children detention schools. The Oberstown capital development project, which commenced on site in September 2013, will enable the extension of the child care model of detention, which focuses on education and rehabilitation in order to minimize re-offending, to all under 18 year olds ordered to be detained by the courts on criminal justice charges.<br/><br/>The first 3 units of residential accommodation, which will prioritise the transfer of responsibility for 17 year old boys from adult prison facilities, were formally handed over to the Oberstown campus on 27 November 2014, following the required inspection of works and technical approval of the Office of Public Works, managing the project on behalf of my Department.  I am advised that, in order to ensure safe and secure custody of children in the new buildings and that the appropriate health and safety standards are met, a further period of training and orientation for staff and for the fitting out of the new units with furniture and equipment is required.  This process is ongoing at present and will be completed in the first quarter of 2015.<br/><br/>Other issues impacting on the operational date for the transfer of responsibility for 17 year old boys are the recruitment of the required complement of new care staff to work in the expanded facilities, and the passage of necessary legislation to ensure that all legal issues relating to the detention of children up to the age of 18 are fully addressed.  Following a recruitment programme carried out in 2014, 38 new care staff have commenced employment on the Oberstown campus and completed the training and orientation process.  However, the recruitment programme had a target of 60 additional care staff and an additional  process for a further phase of recruitment is currently underway.  It is intended that the required staff complement will be reached in the second quarter of 2015 for the operation of all of the new residential units.  <br/><br/>My Department is also progressing the necessary legal changes required in order to transfer responsibility for 17 year old boys from adult prison facilities.  Heads of a Bill to amend the Children Act, 2001 were approved by Government in September 2014 and it is intended that the Bill will be published this quarter and enacted as soon as possible thereafter. <br/><br/>My Department is reviewing these matters on an ongoing basis and it is my intention that the practice of detaining children in adult prison facilities will cease as early as possible this year.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.55" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA03750">Child Care Services Funding</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.56.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1017" speakername="Finian McGrath" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA03800"><p><i>131.</i> To ask the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs if he will support facilities for child care in the Darndale/Belcamp area, Dublin 17; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2163/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.57.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA03900"><p>The Darndale Belcamp Integrated Childcare Service continues to be in receipt of significant funding from a number of State bodies, including Tusla (the Child and Family Agency) and my Department.  The centre also receives income by way of fees from parents. Tusla has worked closely with the centre last year in developing a sustainability plan.  I am advised by Tusla that the centre is successfully implementing this plan. Tusla management in North Dublin will continue to meet on a monthly basis with the management of the centre to monitor progress in this regard.  The centre will continue to provide monthly progress reports and quarterly financial statements during 2015.</p>  <p>  I am further advised by Tusla that in 2014 it provided &euro;489,000 in direct funding to Early Years services in the Darndale/Belcamp area and an additional &euro;828,000 to Early Years Services within the geographical area of Edenmore, Kilbarrack/Raheny, Donaghmede and Bonnybrook.  This funding was in addition to per capita funding from Pobal and the Early Childhood Care and Education Schemes (ECCE). </p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.58" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA03950">Mental Health Services Provision</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.59.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/957" speakername="Bernard Durkan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA04000"><p><i>132.</i> To ask the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs the extent to which he remains satisfied that adequate resources remain available to child psychology services with particular reference to early intervention and identification of the relevant and appropriate supports thereby making available an adequate suite of services to meet the growing requirements evenly throughout the country; if analysis has been undertaken to identify possible weaknesses in the services over the past number of years; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2184/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.60.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA04100"><p>The Child and Family Agency was established on 1 January, 2014.  It involved bringing together nearly 4,000 staff from three separate organisations, the Health Service Executive, the Family Support Agency and the National Educational Welfare Board.  The establishment of the new Agency with a budget of over &euro;600m represents one of the most ambitious and far reaching public sector reforms undertaken by the Government.  The Agency, in discharging its functions, is placing a strong emphasis on prevention, early intervention, family support, therapeutic and care interventions, all of which are key to the provision of integrated, multi-disciplinary services for vulnerable children and families. </p>  <p>  Psychology services for children are currently being provided by the HSE. The Agency and the HSE have in place both a Memorandum of Understanding and a Joint Protocol for inter-agency collaboration which underpins the provision of these services for children. The purpose of the Memorandum of Understanding is to set out the partnership agreement between the HSE and the Agency to continue pre-establishment levels of service across both organisations. The objective of the Joint Protocol is to specify a pathway and associated responsibilities for children and families whose needs cross between Health Service Divisions and the Agency. </p>  <p>  Both the Memorandum of Understanding and the Joint Protocol are subject to regular monitoring and review to ensure that they are working effectively in the best interests of children and families. Additionally, the Agency and the HSE are working to finalise a service level agreement to underpin the provision of psychological services by the HSE which will assist the Agency in fulfilling its statutory obligations.  The service level agreement with the HSE will determine the quantum of service needed to meet the Agency's requirements and will be an interim arrangement pending the Agency providing the service directly.  </p>  <p>  Clinical psychology services are directly provided by the Child and Family Agency within multi-disciplinary teams deployed by the Assessment, Consultation and Therapy Service (ACTS). Services provided include assessment and focused interventions for children and young people with complex clinical needs and high risk behaviours. They also provide support to other professionals in order to guide interventions to children and families.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.61" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA04150">Child Care Services Provision</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.62.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1065" speakername="Robert Troy" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA04200"><p><i>133.</i> To ask the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs the details of his proposed child care plan; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2202/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.63.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA04300"><p>There is clear evidence that investing in childcare services which provide quality care and education for children in their early years has significant dividends for both the children themselves and for society as a whole.  Ensuring the best possible outcomes for children in their early years is therefore an important element in future economic planning. </p>  <p>  The case for investing in children and young people on both social and economic grounds is supported by a body of international evidence.  As the Minister with responsibility for this key area, I propose to establish a cross-Departmental group at senior level to develop a whole-of-Government approach to future investment in early childhood care and education and after-school care. The group will undertake an economic and cost benefit analysis of policies and future options for increasing the supply, accessibility and affordability of quality childhood care and education services. </p>  <p>  It is clear that accessibility, affordability and high quality childcare can play a critical role in achieving a number of Government priorities, including improving educational outcome for children, reducing poverty and increasing parents' participation in the labour market. The importance of this area is reinforced by continuing economic improvement and job growth and an increased focus on activation for those currently outside the labour market.</p>  <p>  To ensure that all the potential benefits can be realised, future public investment in childcare must be evidence-based and strategically coordinated. It must look at the provision right across the 0 to 6 age group as well as consider the after-school needs of older school-going children. It is crucial, therefore, that we develop a coherent cross-Government approach to investment in childcare services.</p>  <p>  The group which I propose to establish will include representatives of the Department of Education and Skills, the Department of Social Protection, the Department of Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform, the Department of Finance and the Department of the Taoiseach and will be led and supported by my Department.  I will be asking that the work of this group be carried out within a relatively short time frame and I expect that the group will be in a position to report to me in the Summer.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.64" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA04350">Mother and Baby Homes Inquiries</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.65.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1186" speakername="Lucinda Creighton" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA04400"><p><i>134.</i> To ask the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs in view of the announcement of a commission of investigation into mother and baby homes, his views that a compensation or redress scheme should be established for affected persons; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2188/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.66.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA04500"><p>I announced the proposed Terms of Reference for the Commission of Investigation into Mother and Baby Homes and certain related matters on Friday, 9th January.  The investigation will thoroughly examine the experience of the many mothers and children who were resident in a Mother and Baby Home over the period 1922-1998. </p>  <p>  In the course of this announcement, I indicated my view that it would be premature to consider the issues of compensation or redress in respect of any matters within the scope of this investigation. Given that theses issues have not been central to any previous inquiry, this Commission must be given the opportunity to advance its investigation and to establish the facts of what happened in and around these homes.  In the absence of relevant information it would be difficult to make determinations on issues as potentially complex as the question of redress.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.67" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA04550">Child and Family Agency Staff</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.68.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1177" speakername="Denis Naughten" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA04600"><p><i>135.</i> To ask the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs the steps he is taking to investigate allegations that social worker numbers were temporarily increased within the child welfare services in advance of the Health Information and Quality Authority inspections; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2187/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.69.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA04700"><p>I have been assured by the Agency that this practice is not employed in advance of HIQA inspections. At the end of November 2014 a total of 1403.46 WTE social workers were employed by the Agency around the country. The Agency's Employment Control Group has a national remit and decides whether agency workers are to be employed. Agency workers are only employed when it is determined that the provision of a safe service has been compromised because of a fall in staffing levels. These agency staff are only stood down when permanent staff are recruited or when staff return from absence. The Agency is actively addressing the staff shortfalls with continuing recruitment. 155 social workers recruited since the Agency was established, and a further 193 posts currently in the recruitment process.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.70" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA04750">School Completion Programme</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.71.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1054" speakername="Se&aacute;n &Oacute; Feargha&iacute;l" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA04800"><p><i>136.</i> To ask the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs the funding to be provided for the school completion programme in 2015; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2190/15]</b></p></ques>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.72.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1054" speakername="Se&aacute;n &Oacute; Feargha&iacute;l" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA04900"><p><i>141.</i> To ask the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs his plans for the school completion programme in 2015; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2191/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.73.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000058#WRA05000"><p>I propose to take Questions Nos. 136 and 141 together.</p>  <p>  The School Completion Programme aims to retain young people in the formal education system to completion of senior cycle and to generally improve the school attendance, participation and retention of young people who are risk of educational disadvantage. The Programme is a targeted intervention aimed at school communities identified through the Department of Education and Skills&rsquo; DEIS Action Plan for Educational Inclusion. It provides targeted supports annually to approximately 36,000 children.</p>  <p>  Since 1 January 2014, the Child and Family Agency has operational responsibility for the School Completion Programme, including the allocation of funds to local projects. In 2014, an allocation of &euro;24.756 million has been provided for the School Completion Programme. The Agency has approved local projects' school retention plans for the 2014/2015 academic year. The first instalment of 2014/15 funding issued to local projects last September. Further payments totalling approximately &euro;9.5m have issued over the past month, with a third instalment in May 2015.   </p>  <p>  The estimate for the Child and Family Agency for 2015 is &euro;631 million, a 4.3% increase on its 2014 allocation. My Department has recently issued a Performance Statement to the Agency under Section 45 of the Child and Family Agency Act, 2013. This includes my priorities for consideration in the development of the Agency's 2015 Business Plan. The Business Plan will set out the Agency's proposed activities, programmes and priorities for 2015, including provision for the School Completion Programme, in the light of the monies available.</p>  <p>  A review of the School Completion Programme has commenced. It is being carried out by the ESRI following a procurement process managed by the Agency. The programme has been in operation since 2002 and I believe that it is timely that a review be carried out.  The Review is an important initiative to plan for the future development of this Programme.  It is envisaged that the review will be completed during the 2014/2015 academic year.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.75" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000059#WRB00150">Children in Care</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.76.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1065" speakername="Robert Troy" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000059#WRB00200"><p><i>137.</i> To ask the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs his views on a Health Information and Quality Authority report indicating that children at a care centre in the southern region routinely engage in illegal drug use and criminal activity during frequent absences from the facility; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2206/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.77.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000059#WRB00300"><p>The Health Information and Quality Authority (HIQA) has a statutory responsibility to inspect the Child and Family Agency's children residential centres under Section 69 of the Child Care Act 1991.  I view these independent inspection reports as an essential component of quality improvement for children's residential centres, which work alongside internal processes within the Agency.  Residential care accounts for a very small proportion - less than 5% - of children in care (316 of 6,454).  During 2014, HIQA focused its inspections of residential centres on how staff manage children - usually older teenagers - who have behaviour described as challenging and difficult.</p>  <p>  Last week there were concerning reports in the media regarding a children's residential care unit in the southern region following the publication of an inspection report on 12th January 2015.  HIQA's inspection found that the three teenagers living in the centre at the time were taking risks primarily in the form of taking illegal substances when outside the centre.  The inspection report notes that the staff and managers tried to make sure that these young people were safe but weren't able to prevent them from leaving the centre without permission or taking drugs.  I am advised by my officials that Ireland is somewhat unusual in that we have quite a number of 16 and 17 year olds coming into care.  Latest figures from the Agency indicate that 14% that is, 258 of young people received into care in 2013 were over the age of 16.  Some of these young people had very difficult lives before coming into care including histories of emotional and behavioural difficulties and substance misuse.  Agency staff and those working in HSE mental health and addiction services engage with these young people to try and help them overcome their problems - but helping young people with such complex backgrounds is challenging work.</p>  <p>  I take the care and safety of all children and young people in care very seriously indeed, as do the Agency's staff, and I recognise that the job of helping troubled young people to resolve their difficulties is key to keeping them safe.  This includes referring young people to specialist addiction counsellors in the HSE when required.</p>  <p>  The Agency has advised me there is one young person living in the centre now - he is doing well and has a good relationship with the staff.  Another young person was discharged home and the third is in a private residential centre (following a period of detention in the criminal justice system).  Since the inspection, the Agency has advised that it is carrying out a management review of the centre and that no further children are to be admitted pending its outcome.  I have asked the Agency to keep my Department appraised and look forward to learning the outcome of the review.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.78" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000059#WRB00350">Social Workers Recruitment</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.79.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1182" speakername="Terence Flanagan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000059#WRB00400"><p><i>138.</i> To ask the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs the position regarding his Department's plan to recruit more social workers for Tusla; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2195/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.80.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000059#WRB00500"><p>Staffing vacancies arise for a variety of reasons, including retirements, career breaks, paid and unpaid leave (including maternity and other family related leave) and resignations. The Child and Family Agency (TUSLA) has advised that there were 1,403.46 whole time equivalent social workers employed at the end of November 2014 and that they are currently recruiting an additional 193 social workers to meet existing vacancies. They have also advised that 155 social workers have already been recruited during 2014.</p>  <p>  In addition to the above, there are currently 84 social workers on maternity leave and in order to address priority gaps in service resulting from maternity leave, a pilot Maternity Leave Cover scheme has been introduced whereby maternity related vacancies in each region can be filled by way of a temporary contracts. The Pilot Scheme involves the allocation of 100 posts between each region, 80 of which relate specifically to social workers. </p>  <p>  The impact of vacancies on service provision is risk-assessed on an ongoing basis to ensure that social work team members are never allowed to fall below what is considered necessary to provide a safe service. Such risk-assessments take account of issues such as case loads and referral numbers. Where necessary, temporary staff are brought in immediately to cover vacancies until such vacancies are filled on a permanent basis.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.81" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000059#WRB00550">Children First Guidelines</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.82.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1058" speakername="Patrick O'Donovan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000059#WRB00600"><p><i>139.</i> To ask the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs his views on the introduction of protocols that would require political parties to put in place child protection policies in line with other voluntary organisations that have a youth element; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2126/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.83.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000059#WRB00700"><p>Children First: National Guidance for the Protection and Welfare of Children [2011] is the current national policy which sets out the non-statutory child protection requirements which are in place for all sectors of society. This would include the youth element of political parties.  Any person, or persons, who run an organisation which provides services to children and young people should be aware of, and comply with, their child protection obligations as set out in Children First. Section 4.7.2 of the Guidance provides that all statutory, voluntary and community organisations working with and in direct contact with children should have procedures and guidelines derived from and consistent with the current <i>Children First: National Guidance</i>. <i>Our Duty to Care: The Principles of Good Practice for the Protection of Children and Young People</i>, published in 2002, offers specific guidance to the community and voluntary sectors on the promotion of child protection and welfare practices.<br/><br/>The Children First Bill, 2014, which is currently progressing through the Oireachtas, will place key elements of the Children First National Guidance on a statutory basis once it is enacted and commenced. In effect, this means that providers of relevant services will acquire a number of statutory obligations. Under the Bill, providers of relevant services are defined as organisations which employ one or more persons. Relevant services are listed in Schedule 1 of the Children First Bill and include educational, research, training, cultural, recreational, leisure, social and physical activities. Once the Bill is commenced, a provider of relevant services will be required to undertake a risk assessment of the potential harm which could come to a child while availing of the services, and to then prepare a Child Safeguarding Statement which outlines the policies and procedures which are in place to mitigate the risks identified. Furthermore, certain persons who are mandated persons under the Bill, will be required by the legislation to report child welfare and protection concerns. These would include persons employed as safeguarding or child protection officers in organisations providing services to children. <br/><br/>In parallel to the legislative process, my officials are currently revising and updating the existing Children First National Guidance. This is to ensure that the Guidance, which will continue as the basis for all citizens to report concerns, reflects the new legislative obligations and provides, in one place, a complete reference resource for individuals and organisations.  This will provide clarity and ensure consistency between the proposed legislation and the existing non-statutory obligations which will continue to operate administratively for all sectors of society.<br/><br/>Requirements in relation to the vetting of persons who work with children are a matter for the Department of Justice and Equality. The Deputy should refer to the website of that Department for further information, including in relation to the National Vetting Bureau (Children and Vulnerable Persons) Act, 2012.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.84" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000059#WRB00750">Child Detention Centres</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.85.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/956" speakername="Mick Wallace" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000059#WRB00800"><p><i>140.</i> To ask the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs if he has had any discussion with the Health Information and Quality Authority regarding the next report on child detention conditions in view of the fact these reports are supposed to be carried out on an annual basis but the most recent one was published in November 2013; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2193/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.86.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000059#WRB00900"><p>In accordance with section 185 of the Children Act 2001, the Health Information and Quality Authority have been authorised to undertaken inspections of the children detention schools, which are required to be undertaken at least once every 12 months. HIQA is independent in the exercise of its functions.</p>  <p>  I can confirm to the Deputy that HIQA conducted their last inspection of the children detention schools in Oberstown between 28 October and 3 November 2014.  Following on from these inspections, HIQA will issue a report in accordance with the agreed protocol entitled &ldquo;Protocol for Health Information and Quality Authority Inspections of Children Detention Schools". The protocol is outlined in Appendix A of the Standards and Criteria for Children Detention Schools, which is available on the Irish Youth Justice Service website and I have asked my officials to forward this material to the Deputy.  I am advised that the HIQA report on this recent inspection is expected in the near future.</p></reply>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.87" nospeaker="true" ><p>Question No. 141 answered with Question No. 136.</p></speech>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.89.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/969" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000059#WRB01100"><p><i>142.</i> To ask the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs the details of the 16 boys reportedly being held in adult prisons; when these boys will be placed in more age-appropriate settings; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2196/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.90.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000059#WRB01200"><p>On 16 January 2015, there were a total of 16 boys aged 17 years detained in the adult prison system, comprising 6 boys remanded in custody in St Patrick&rsquo;s Institution and 10 boys serving a sentence of detention in Wheatfield Place of Detention.<br/><br/>There is a commitment in the Programme for Government to end the practice of detaining<b></b>children in adult prison facilities and significant progress has been made in this area.  Responsibility for 16 year old boys was transferred from the adult prison system to the Oberstown campus in May 2012 and this commitment will be fully met when the extension of the Oberstown campus results in the transfer of responsibility for 17 year old boys from the adult prison system to the children detention schools. The Oberstown capital development project, which commenced on site in September 2013, will enable the extension of the child care model of detention, which focuses on education and rehabilitation in order to minimize re-offending, to all under 18 year olds ordered to be detained by the courts on criminal justice charges.<br/><br/>The first 3 units of residential accommodation, which will prioritise the transfer of responsibility for 17 year old boys from adult prison facilities, were formally handed over to the Oberstown campus on 27 November 2014, following the required inspection of works and technical approval of the Office of Public Works, managing the project on behalf of my Department.  I am advised that, in order to ensure safe and secure custody of children in the new buildings and that the appropriate health and safety standards are met, a further period of training and orientation for staff and for the fitting out of the new units with furniture and equipment is required.  This process is ongoing at present and will be completed in the first quarter of 2015.<br/><br/>Other issues impacting on the operational date for the transfer of responsibility for 17 year old boys are the recruitment of the required complement of new care staff to work in the expanded facilities, and the passage of necessary legislation to ensure that all legal issues relating to the detention of children up to the age of 18 are fully addressed.  Following a recruitment programme carried out in 2014, 38 new care staff have commenced employment on the Oberstown campus and completed the training and orientation process.  However, the recruitment programme had a target of 60 additional care staff and an additional process for a further phase of recruitment is currently under way.  It is intended that the required staff complement will be reached in the second quarter of 2015 for the operation of all of the new residential units.<br/><br/>My Department is also progressing the necessary legal changes required in order to transfer responsibility for 17 year old boys from adult prison facilities.  Heads of a Bill to amend the Children Act, 2001 were approved by Government in September 2014 and it is intended that the Bill will be published this quarter and enacted as soon as possible thereafter. <br/><br/>My Department is reviewing these matters on an ongoing basis and it is my intention that the practice of detaining children in adult prison facilities will cease as early as possible this year. </p></reply>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.92" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000059#WRB01300">Department of An Taoiseach</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.91" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000059#WRB01250">Employment Data</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.92.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/968" speakername="Pat Deering" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000059#WRB01300"><p><i>143.</i> To ask the Taoiseach if he will provide a breakdown in tabular form on a county basis of the number of persons at work between February 2012 and December 2014. <b>[2295/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.93.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1098" speakername="Paul Kehoe" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000059#WRB01400"><p>The exact information requested by the Deputy is not available. The Quarterly National Household Survey (QNHS) is the official source of estimates of employment in the State. Estimates of employment are produced by NUTS2 and NUTS3 regions.<font color="#FF0000"> </font><br/><br/>Due to methodology and sample size it is not possible to produce reliable county level estimates from the QNHS. In addition, data is only available from the QNHS on a quarterly basis.The latest figures available from the QNHS are for Quarter 3 of 2014. The table below shows the number of persons aged 15 years and over in employment classified by NUTS2 and NUTS3 regions in each quarter from Q1 2012 to Q3 2014.<br/><br/><b>Table 1 Persons aged 15 years and over in employment (ILO) classified by NUTS2 and NUTS3 regions, Q1 2012 to Q3 2014</b><br/><br/>'000<table><tr><th><b>-</b></th><th><b>Q1 12</b></th><th><b>Q2 12</b></th><th><b>Q3 12</b></th><th><b>Q4 12</b></th><th><b>Q1 13</b></th><th><b>Q2 13</b></th><th><b>Q3 13</b></th><th><b>Q4 13</b></th><th><b>Q1 14</b></th><th><b>Q2 14</b></th><th><b>Q3 14</b></th></tr><tr><td><b>Border, Midland and Western </b></td><td><b>456.4</b></td><td><b>459.3</b></td><td><b>459.7</b></td><td><b>458.1</b></td><td><b>467.8</b></td><td><b>476.5</b></td><td><b>478.6</b></td><td><b>482.9</b></td><td><b>476.4</b></td><td><b>476.8</b></td><td><b>485.4</b></td></tr><tr><td>Border</td><td>174.5</td><td>174.6</td><td>172.4</td><td>171.5</td><td>176.8</td><td>183.1</td><td>181.8</td><td>185.8</td><td>183.8</td><td>185.00</td><td>190.7</td></tr><tr><td>Midland</td><td>104.8</td><td>105.2</td><td>105.3</td><td>105.7</td><td>106.9</td><td>109.7</td><td>111.2</td><td>111.1</td><td>110.2</td><td>113.5</td><td>112.8</td></tr><tr><td>West</td><td>177.1</td><td>179.5</td><td>181.9</td><td>180.9</td><td>184.0</td><td>183.7</td><td>185.6</td><td>185.9</td><td>182.4</td><td>178.3</td><td>181.9</td></tr><tr><td><b>Southern and Eastern</b></td><td><b>1,368.7</b></td><td><b>1,376.9</b></td><td><b>1,381.6</b></td><td><b>1,390.8</b></td><td><b>1,377.8</b></td><td><b>1,393.4</b></td><td><b>1,420.7</b></td><td><b>1,427.0</b></td><td><b>1,411.9</b></td><td><b>1,424.8</b></td><td><b>1,441.5</b></td></tr><tr><td>Dublin</td><td>541.5</td><td>547.4</td><td>548.4</td><td>556.3</td><td>547.1</td><td>555.1</td><td>570.1</td><td>572.1</td><td>572.9</td><td>576.4</td><td>576.5</td></tr><tr><td>Mid-East</td><td>228.8</td><td>222.7</td><td>223.5</td><td>225.5</td><td>220.6</td><td>219.0</td><td>216.7</td><td>225.9</td><td>225.1</td><td>228.5</td><td>229.6</td></tr><tr><td>Mid-West</td><td>150.4</td><td>150.1</td><td>150.9</td><td>150.1</td><td>146.5</td><td>150.9</td><td>153.1</td><td>151.3</td><td>144.5</td><td>148.0</td><td>155.6</td></tr><tr><td>South-East</td><td>181.3</td><td>186.0</td><td>183.8</td><td>181.8</td><td>186.5</td><td>187.7</td><td>193.8</td><td>197.1</td><td>195.8</td><td>198.5</td><td>202.6</td></tr><tr><td>South-West</td><td>266.6</td><td>270.7</td><td>274.9</td><td>277.0</td><td>277.1</td><td>280.7</td><td>287.1</td><td>280.6</td><td>273.5</td><td>273.3</td><td>277.2</td></tr><tr><td><b>State</b></td><td><b>1,825.0</b></td><td><b>1,836.2</b></td><td><b>1,841.3</b></td><td><b>1,848.9</b></td><td><b>1,845.6</b></td><td><b>1,869.9</b></td><td><b>1,899.3</b></td><td><b>1,909.8</b></td><td><b>1,888.2</b></td><td><b>1,901.6</b></td><td><b>1,926.9</b></td></tr></table>Data may be subject to sampling or other survey errors, which are greater in respect of smaller values or estimates of change.';<br/><br/>Reference period: q1=Jan-Mar, q2=Apr-Jun, q3=Jul-Sep, q4=Oct-Dec.<br/><br/>Source: Quarterly National Household Survey, Central Statistics Office.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.94" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000059#WRB01450">Job Creation Data</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.95.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000059#WRB01500"><p><i>144.</i> To ask the Taoiseach if he will provide in tabular form the total number of jobs created and lost in County Limerick in the years 2011, 2012, 2013 and to date in 2014; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[48526/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.96.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1098" speakername="Paul Kehoe" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000059#WRB01600"><p>The exact information requested by the Deputy is not available. The Quarterly National Household Survey (QNHS) is the official source of estimates of employment in the State. The most recent figures available are for Q3 2014. Estimates of employment are produced by NUTS 3 Regions. The NUTS 3 Mid-West region includes Clare, Limerick City, Limerick County and North Tipperary. Due to methodology and sample size it is not possible to produce reliable Limerick City estimates from the QNHS. <br/><br/>Table 1a below shows the number of persons aged 15 years and over in employment classified by NUTS3 Mid-West region in Q3 of each year from 2011 to 2014.<br/><br/>Table 1b shows the annual change in the numbers of persons aged 15 years and over in employment classified by NUTS3 Mid-West region in Q3 of each year from 2011 to 2014. <br/><br/>As Table 1a shows the overall stock of persons employed at given points in time, the annual changes which are calculated using these stock figures depend both on the number of jobs lost and jobs created over the period in question.<br/><br/>The QNHS does not record whether a job is newly created.<br/><br/><b>Table 1a Persons aged 15 years and over in employment (ILO) classified by NUTS3 Mid-West region, Q3 2011 - Q3 2014</b><br/><br/>'000<table><tr><th></th><th>Q3 11</th><th>Q3 12</th><th>Q3 13</th><th>Q3 14</th></tr><tr><td>In employment</td><td>154.0</td><td>150.9</td><td>153.1</td><td>155.6</td></tr></table>Data may be subject to sampling or other survey errors, which are greater in respect of smaller values or estimates of change.<br/><br/>Source: Quarterly National Household Survey, Central Statistics Office.<br/><br/><b>Table 1b Persons aged 15 years and over in employment (ILO) classified by NUTS3 Mid-West region, Q3 2012 - Q3 2014 - Annual change </b><br/><br/>'000<table><tr><th></th><th><div>Q3 12</div></th><th><div>Q3 13</div></th><th><div>Q3 14</div></th></tr><tr><td>In employment</td><td><div>-3.1</div></td><td><div>2.2</div></td><td><div>2.6</div></td></tr></table>Data may be subject to sampling or other survey errors, which are greater in respect of smaller values or estimates of change.<br/><br/>Source: Quarterly National Household Survey, Central Statistics Office.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.97" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000059#WRB01650">Employment Data</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.98.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/957" speakername="Bernard Durkan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000059#WRB01700"><p><i>145.</i> To ask the Taoiseach the total number of jobs lost in the services sectors in each of the past five years to date; the number of new jobs created in the same period; the degree to which a positive trend has been established; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[48693/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.99.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1098" speakername="Paul Kehoe" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000059#WRB01800"><p>The Quarterly National Household Survey (QNHS) is the official source of estimates of employment in the State. The latest figures available from the QNHS are for Quarter 3 of 2014. <br/><br/>Table 1a below shows the number of persons aged 15 years and over in employment in the Services sectors, classified by NACE Rev. 2. in Quarter 3 of each year from 2010 to 2014. <br/><br/>Table 1b shows the annual change in the number of persons aged 15 years and over in employment in the Services sectors, classified by NACE Rev. 2, in Quarter 3 of each year from 2011 to 2014.<br/><br/>As Table 1a shows the overall stock of persons employed at given points in time, the annual changes which are calculated using these stock figures depend both on the number of jobs lost and jobs created over the period in question. The QNHS does not record whether a job is newly created.<br/><br/><b>Table 1a Persons aged 15 years and over in employment (ILO) classified by NACE Rev. 2 Economic Sector, Q3 2010-Q3 2014. </b><br/><br/>'000<table><tr><th></th><th><div><b>Q3 10</b></div></th><th><div><b>Q3 11</b></div></th><th><div><b>Q3 12</b></div></th><th><div><b>Q3 13</b></div></th><th><div><b>Q3 14</b></div></th></tr><tr><td><b>Total Services</b></td><td><div><b>1,426.9</b></div></td><td><div><b>1,412.1</b></div></td><td><div><b>1,420.8</b></div></td><td><div><b>1,439.2</b></div></td><td><div><b>1,460.2</b></div></td></tr><tr><td>Wholesale and retail trade; repair of motor vehicles </td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td>and motorcycles</td><td><div>278.1</div></td><td><div>276.5</div></td><td><div>272.7</div></td><td><div>273.3</div></td><td><div>275.2</div></td></tr><tr><td>Transportation and storage </td><td><div>92.8</div></td><td><div>96.7</div></td><td><div>90.3</div></td><td><div>88.2</div></td><td><div>87.5</div></td></tr><tr><td>Accommodation and food service activities</td><td><div>128.9</div></td><td><div>121.1</div></td><td><div>123.1</div></td><td><div>137.7</div></td><td><div>139.8</div></td></tr><tr><td>Information and communication</td><td><div>75.8</div></td><td><div>77.1</div></td><td><div>78.2</div></td><td><div>82.0</div></td><td><div>79.3</div></td></tr><tr><td>Financial, insurance and real estate activities</td><td><div>100.6</div></td><td><div>99.1</div></td><td><div>102.3</div></td><td><div>101.5</div></td><td><div>103.1</div></td></tr><tr><td>Professional, scientific and technical activities</td><td><div>97.4</div></td><td><div>96.6</div></td><td><div>100.4</div></td><td><div>111.3</div></td><td><div>116.9</div></td></tr><tr><td>Administrative and support service activities</td><td><div>62.3</div></td><td><div>69.4</div></td><td><div>66.6</div></td><td><div>64.7</div></td><td><div>65.2</div></td></tr><tr><td>Public administration and defence; compulsory social security</td><td><div>104.0</div></td><td><div>99.3</div></td><td><div>99.7</div></td><td><div>96.1</div></td><td><div>98.1</div></td></tr><tr><td>Education</td><td><div>149.0</div></td><td><div>137.2</div></td><td><div>140.6</div></td><td><div>140.8</div></td><td><div>144.1</div></td></tr><tr><td>Human health and social work activities</td><td><div>240.3</div></td><td><div>243.5</div></td><td><div>245.0</div></td><td><div>243.6</div></td><td><div>249.5</div></td></tr><tr><td>Other NACE activities </td><td><div>97.7</div></td><td><div>95.5</div></td><td><div>101.9</div></td><td><div>99.9</div></td><td><div>101.6</div></td></tr></table>Data may be subject to sampling or other survey errors, which are greater in respect of smaller values or estimates of change. <br/><br/>Source: Quarterly National Household Survey, Central Statistics Office.<br/><br/><b>Table 1b Persons aged 15 years and over in employment (ILO) classified by NACE Rev. 2 Economic Sector, Q3 2011-Q3 2014 - Annual change</b><br/><br/>'000<table><tr><th></th><th><div><b>Q3 11</b></div></th><th><div><b>Q3 12</b></div></th><th><div><b>Q3 13</b></div></th><th><div><b>Q3 14</b></div></th></tr><tr><td><b>Total Services</b></td><td><div><b>-14.8</b></div></td><td><div><b>8.7</b></div></td><td><div><b>18.4</b></div></td><td><div><b>21.1</b></div></td></tr><tr><td>Wholesale and retail trade; repair of motor vehicles</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td>and motorcycles</td><td><div>-1.6</div></td><td><div>-3.8</div></td><td><div>0.6</div></td><td><div>1.9</div></td></tr><tr><td>Transportation and storage </td><td><div>3.8</div></td><td><div>-6.3</div></td><td><div>-2.1</div></td><td><div>-0.8</div></td></tr><tr><td>Accommodation and food service activities</td><td><div>-7.8</div></td><td><div>2.0</div></td><td><div>14.7</div></td><td><div>2.1</div></td></tr><tr><td>Information and communication</td><td><div>1.3</div></td><td><div>1.1</div></td><td><div>3.8</div></td><td><div>-2.7</div></td></tr><tr><td>Financial, insurance and real estate activities</td><td><div>-1.5</div></td><td><div>3.1</div></td><td><div>-0.7</div></td><td><div>1.6</div></td></tr><tr><td>Professional, scientific and technical activities</td><td><div>-0.7</div></td><td><div>3.8</div></td><td><div>10.9</div></td><td><div>5.6</div></td></tr><tr><td>Administrative and support service activities</td><td><div>7.1</div></td><td><div>-2.9</div></td><td><div>-1.9</div></td><td><div>0.5</div></td></tr><tr><td>Public administration and defence; compulsory social security</td><td><div>-4.7</div></td><td><div>0.5</div></td><td><div>-3.7</div></td><td><div>2.0</div></td></tr><tr><td>Education</td><td><div>-11.8</div></td><td><div>3.4</div></td><td><div>0.2</div></td><td><div>3.4</div></td></tr><tr><td>Human health and social work activities</td><td><div>3.2</div></td><td><div>1.5</div></td><td><div>-1.4</div></td><td><div>5.9</div></td></tr><tr><td>Other NACE activities </td><td><div>-2.2</div></td><td><div>6.4</div></td><td><div>-1.9</div></td><td><div>1.7</div></td></tr></table>Data may be subject to sampling or other survey errors, which are greater in respect of smaller values or estimates of change. <br/><br/>Source: Quarterly National Household Survey, Central Statistics Office.<br/><br/>The Central Statistics Office (CSO) compiles information on jobs created and jobs lost by linking P35L returns from the Revenue Commissioners with the CSO Business Register.  The most recent data available is for the reference year 2013.<br/><br/>Job creation for an enterprise in a given reference year is measured as the positive difference in the number of paid employees recorded with non-zero reckonable pay in the reference year compared with the previous year. Job creation in the business economy as a whole is the sum of all enterprise job creation.<br/><br/>Jobs lost for an enterprise in a given reference year is measured as the negative difference in the number of paid employees recorded with non-zero reckonable pay in the reference year compared with the previous year.  Jobs lost in the services sectors as a whole is the sum of all enterprise jobs lost.  It should be noted that when interpreting figures, jobs lost for a particular year means that these jobs were identified in the previous year but not in the reference year, that is some of these jobs may have disappeared sometime during the previous year.  Net job creation is calculated as the difference between job creation and jobs lost.<br/><br/>The calculation of rates for a given year is based on the average number of jobs counted in the given year and the year previous to the given year.<br/><br/>Considering the services sectors as Business Economy services excluding activities of holding companies (G to N,-642)<b>,</b>jobs lost rates fell from 27% in 2009 before stabilizing at 12% from 2011 onwards.  Job Creation rates rose from 8% in 2009 to fluctuate between 11% and 14% in the years 2010 to 2013.</p></reply>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.100" nospeaker="true" ><p>Table 2 Employment records, job creation, jobs lost and net job creation for the Business Economy services excluding activities of holding companies (G to N,-642), 2009 &ndash; 2013Job Churn Components by Activity NACE Rev 2, statistical indicator and Year20092010201120122013Business economy services excluding activities of holding companies (G to N,-642)Employment records (Number)1,218,4421,172,3401,195,4821,215,7871,222,122Job creation rate 8%12%14%13%11%Jobs lost rate 27%17%12%12%12%Job creation (Number)113,490148,285165,909157,789133,473Jobs lost (Number)358,036203,000144,848138,816146,152Net job creation (Number)-244,546-54,71521,06118,973-12,679Wholesale and retail trade, repair of motor vehicles and motorcycles (G)Employment records (Number)402,920386,564388,272387,260390,911Job creation rate 7%10%11%11%9%Jobs lost rate 28%14%11%11%13%Job creation (Number)29,63237,88143,35542,06637,561Jobs lost (Number)125,39354,48042,17243,34152,924Net job creation (Number)-95,761-16,5991,183-1,275-15,363Transportation and storage (H)Employment records (Number)94,17788,50588,53285,39484,658Job creation rate 5%9%9%9%8%Jobs lost rate 16%14%11%10%9%Job creation (Number)4,9888,0788,1627,4006,953Jobs lost (Number)16,39812,2479,3938,9487,689Net job creation (Number)-11,410-4,169-1,231-1,548-736Accommodation and food service activities (I)Employment records (Number)220,305210,140217,271226,839227,663Job creation rate 10%14%17%17%13%Jobs lost rate 30%19%14%13%13%Job creation (Number)25,01530,38536,29837,26830,399Jobs lost (Number)73,85939,89829,56127,96729,575Net job creation (Number)-48,844-9,5136,7379,301824Information and communication (J)Employment records (Number)85,09885,61285,62792,20092,358Job creation rate 13%18%16%19%14%Jobs lost rate 25%19%15%12%14%Job creation (Number)12,03315,36713,72316,94013,371Jobs lost (Number)22,68016,05012,94310,43513,213Net job creation (Number)-10,647-6837806,505158Financial and insurance activities excluding activities of holding companies (K-642)Employment records (Number)103,374110,741114,568116,665114,828Job creation rate 4%12%13%9%7%Jobs lost rate 14%6%9%8%8%Job creation (Number)4,01512,82814,21310,8947,974Jobs lost (Number)15,6686,87710,3759,4089,811Net job creation (Number)-11,6535,9513,8381,486-1,837Real estate activities (L)Employment records (Number)17,09015,62017,90618,16418,610Job creation rate 14%19%30%18%16%Jobs lost rate 36%28%17%13%13%Job creation (Number)2,6933,0964,9643,1912,903Jobs lost (Number)6,9634,5422,7972,3792,457Net job creation (Number)-4,270-1,4462,167812446Professional, scientific and technical activities (M)Employment records (Number)117,607114,531118,859120,599122,160Job creation rate 8%13%17%15%12%Jobs lost rate 26%21%14%15%11%Job creation (Number)10,92715,30520,24018,53215,038Jobs lost (Number)33,80425,53416,07318,29513,477Net job creation (Number)-22,877-10,2294,1672371,561Administrative and support service activities (N)Employment records (Number)177,871160,627164,447168,666170,934Job creation rate 12%15%15%13%11%Jobs lost rate 32%26%13%11%10%Job creation (Number)24,18725,34524,95421,49819,274Jobs lost (Number)63,27143,37221,53418,04317,006Net job creation (Number)-39,084-18,0273,4203,4552,268</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.101" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000059#WRB01850">Commissions of Investigation</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.102.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1057" speakername="Niall Collins" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000059#WRB01900"><p><i>146.</i> To ask the Taoiseach when the Fennelly commission of investigation will be completed; when he will publish the report; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[49355/14]</b></p></ques>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.103.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1057" speakername="Niall Collins" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000059#WRB02000"><p><i>147.</i> To ask the Taoiseach if he or his Department has been requested to extend the terms of reference of the Fennelly commission to include illegal eavesdropping through illegal devices; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[49511/14]</b></p></ques>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.104.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1057" speakername="Niall Collins" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000059#WRB02100"><p><i>148.</i> To ask the Taoiseach if he is satisfied that the terms of reference for the Fennelly commission are broad enough to take into consideration all concerns regarding bugging; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[49512/14]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.105.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1072" speakername="Enda Kenny" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000059#WRB02200"><p>I propose to take Questions Nos. 146 to 148, inclusive, together.</p>  <p>  Following a formal request from the Fennelly Commission of Investigation under section 6 (6) of the Commissions of Investigation Act 2004, I have extended the timeframe for the Fennelly Commission of Investigation to report until 31 December 2015.</p>  <p>  Under its terms of reference the Commission had been due to report by the end of 2014, subject to section 6(6) of the Commissions of Investigation Act 2004, which provides for an extension of the timeframe for reporting at the Commission's request.</p>  <p>  Following consultation with the Commission, I have also published on my Department's website the Interim Report submitted by the Commission requesting an extension of its timeframe for reporting.  Submission of such an Interim Report is a requirement under Section 33(3) of the Act when an extension of the timeframe for its final report is being requested.  It outlines the work completed to date by the Commission since its establishment and the work that remains to be done with a view to identifying as accurately as possible the time required to complete its task.</p>  <p>  As I previously informed the D&aacute;il, I have also requested the Commission to submit a separate Interim Report in respect of paragraphs 1 (n) and (o) of its terms of reference provided it is satisfied it is feasible and appropriate to do so.</p>  <p>  When the Commission's final report is received it is my intention to publish it as soon as possible afterwards, subject to the relevant provisions in the Commission of Investigation Act.</p>  <p>  The Commission's terms of reference were appended to the Order that provides for its establishment, the Commission of Investigation (Certain matters relative to An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and other persons) Order 2014, Statutory Instrument Number 192 of 2014, which was debated and approved by the Dail and Seanad in April 2014.  I am not aware of any requirement to extend the Commission's terms of reference.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.106" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000059#WRB02250">Emigrant Support Services</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.107.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/969" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000059#WRB02300"><p><i>149.</i> To ask the Taoiseach if he will provide an update on the &euro;1 million fund announced in the budget for diaspora projects; the criteria for funding under the scheme; when the scheme will be open for applications; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[1605/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.108.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1072" speakername="Enda Kenny" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000059#WRB02400"><p>Mr Jimmy Deenihan TD was appointed as Minister for Diaspora Affairs in the Department of the Taoiseach and the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade in July, 2014.  In Budget 2015 &euro;1 million was allocated for new diaspora projects and initiatives in the Vote of the Department of the Taoiseach - this is additional to the &euro;11.595 million allocated to the Emigrant Support Programme in the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade for 2015.</p>  <p>  The Minister for Diaspora Affairs is working to finalise a new Diaspora Policy that will build on the important work that has been done to support emigrants and with the additional funding will invest in new projects and initiatives designed to further broaden and deepen Ireland&rsquo;s engagement with its global Diaspora.  This funding will have a particular focus on supporting local communities to develop relationships with their diasporas.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.109" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000059#WRB02450">Departmental Meetings</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.110.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1186" speakername="Lucinda Creighton" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000059#WRB02500"><p><i>150.</i> To ask the Taoiseach further to Parliamentary Questions Nos. 108 and 109 of 16 December 2014, the number of meetings with the MAC for the years 2011 to 2014, inclusive, which were attended by him, special advisers, a Minister of State at his Department or their special advisers; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2461/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.111.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1072" speakername="Enda Kenny" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000059#WRB02600"><p>There are frequent meetings in many different formats attended by me, Ministers of State in my Department, special advisors and members of the MAC on an ongoing basis. These meetings include Cabinet Committees, the Economic Management Council and briefings on matters related to the work of my Department.</p>  <p>  The details of attendance at each meeting of my Department's Management Advisory Committee (MAC) in 2011, 2012, 2013 and in 2014 were given in the written question number 132 on 2nd December 2014.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.112" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000059#WRB02650">Departmental Staff Career Breaks</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.113.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1101" speakername="Barry Cowen" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000059#WRB02700"><p><i>151.</i> To ask the Taoiseach if he will provide in tabular form the number of staff in his Department currently on a sabbatical or career break, broken down by zero to six months, six to 12 months, one to two years, two to three years, four to five years and more than five years; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2480/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.114.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1072" speakername="Enda Kenny" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000059#WRB02800"><p>There are 10 staff from my Department currently on career break.  The information sought is set out in the table beneath.<table><tr><th><div>Number of staff on career break for <br /><br />0-6 months</div></th><th><div>Number of staff on career break for <br /><br />6-12 months</div></th><th><div>Number of staff on career break for <br /><br />1-2 years</div></th><th><div>Number of staff on career break for <br /><br />2-3 years</div></th><th><div>Number of staff on career break for <br /><br />4-5 years</div></th><th><div>Number of staff on career break for <br /><br />5 years plus</div></th></tr><tr><td><div>1</div></td><td><div>1</div></td><td><div>1</div></td><td><div>2</div></td><td><div>2</div></td><td><div>3</div></td></tr></table></p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.115" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000059#WRB02850">Departmental Expenditure</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.116.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1101" speakername="Barry Cowen" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000059#WRB02900"><p><i>152.</i> To ask the Taoiseach if he will provide, in tabular form, the total photography costs for his Department since he came to office, including costs incurred from the use of the ministerial allowance; the list of occasions for which photographers were booked; the photographers used; the breakdown of costs associated with each occasion that a photographer was used; if there is a policy regarding the booking of photographers within his Department; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2481/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.117.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1072" speakername="Enda Kenny" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000059#WRB03000"><p>The total expenditure by my Department on photography from 9th March 2011 to 16th January 2015 is provided in the table below:<table><tr><th><b>Year</b></th><th><b>Amount spent on photography</b></th></tr><tr><td>2011 (9th March to December )</td><td>&euro;28,069</td></tr><tr><td>2012</td><td>&euro;13,449</td></tr><tr><td>2013</td><td>Department  &euro;6,778.00<br /><br />EU Presidency  &euro;38,172.26</td></tr><tr><td>2014</td><td>&euro;12,749.90</td></tr><tr><td>1 - 16 January 2015</td><td>&euro;124.85</td></tr></table><br/><br/>Photography costs in my Department have reduced by 85% from &euro;83,398 in 2008 to &euro;12,749.90 in 2014. <br/><br/>The use of local photographers on international trade missions is required to distribute images to the domestic media to accompany the coverage of domestic journalists who are travelling on behalf of their organisations. Utilising local agencies is cost efficient and costs are kept to a minimum.  Increasingly my Department utilises its own staff to take photographs in-house, thereby reducing costs.<br/><br/>In relation to the EU Presidency costs - as is standard for all Presidencies there is a host photographer to capture the images for the Presidency and to distribute them around the world. <br/><br/>The table below lists the occasions for which photographers were used and costs associated with each occasion:<br/><br/>Photography Costs from 9th March 2011 to 16th January 2015:<br/><br/>2011<table><tr><th><b>Vendor Name</b></th><th><b>Description</b></th><th><b>Cost</b></th></tr><tr><td>The Press Association</td><td>The Press Association, Nottingham</td><td><div>&euro; 139.30</div></td></tr><tr><td>Hackett's Reprographics </td><td>Visa photos for 1 of the Taoiseach's delegation for USA Mar 2011, 10 Mar 2011</td><td><div>&euro; 20.25</div></td></tr><tr><td>Maxwell Photography</td><td>1916 Commemoration 24/04/2011</td><td><div>&euro; 502.45</div></td></tr><tr><td>Maxwell Photography</td><td>SDLP 14/04/2011</td><td><div>&euro; 371.17</div></td></tr><tr><td>Maxwell Photography</td><td>Launch of Census 10/3/2011</td><td><div>&euro; 357.25</div></td></tr><tr><td>Maxwell Photography</td><td>Newly appointed Ministers 15/03/2011</td><td><div>&euro; 478.25</div></td></tr><tr><td>Maxwell Photography</td><td>Visit of Jesse Jackson 21/03/2011</td><td><div>&euro; 409.58</div></td></tr><tr><td>Maxwell Photography</td><td>Book of Condolence - Japan 22/03/2011</td><td><div>&euro; 401.42</div></td></tr><tr><td>Maxwell Photography</td><td>US Ambassador Dan Rooney 28/03/2011</td><td><div>&euro; 401.42</div></td></tr><tr><td>Maxwell Photography</td><td>Jpegs 1916 Commemoration 04/04/2011</td><td><div>&euro; 60.50</div></td></tr><tr><td>Maxwell Photography</td><td>Mass New Dail 09/03/2011</td><td><div>&euro; 508.50</div></td></tr><tr><td>Maxwell Photography</td><td>Taoiseach Office Photo Call 09/03/2011</td><td><div>&euro; 538.75</div></td></tr><tr><td>Maxwell Photography</td><td>Reception New Ministers 09/03/2011</td><td><div>&euro; 391.13</div></td></tr><tr><td>Maxwell Photography</td><td>New Cabinet Meeting 10/03/2011</td><td><div>&euro; 492.17</div></td></tr><tr><td>Maxwell Photography</td><td>New Ministers Appointments 09/03/2011</td><td><div>&euro; 780.75</div></td></tr><tr><td>Maxwell Photography</td><td>The Late Dr. Garret Fitzgerald's Funeral 21-22 May 2011</td><td><div>&euro; 2,359.50</div></td></tr><tr><td>My Photobook.ie</td><td>27 May 2011 - My PhotoBook.ie</td><td><div>&euro; 140.80</div></td></tr><tr><td>Maxwell Photography</td><td>President Obama Visit 23 May 2011 </td><td><div>&euro; 4,537.50</div></td></tr><tr><td>Maxwell Photography</td><td>Taoiseach Enda Kenny &amp;amp; Church Leaders on 19 May 2011 at Government Buildings</td><td><div>&euro; 409.58</div></td></tr><tr><td>Maxwell Photography</td><td>British PM Visit to Gov. Buildings on 18 May 2011.</td><td><div>&euro; 629.50</div></td></tr><tr><td>Maxwell Photography</td><td>US Congressman on 16 May 2011. assignment covering attendance, taking colour, processing, digital contact sheet.</td><td><div>&euro; 280.42</div></td></tr><tr><td>Maxwell Photography</td><td>Hungarian Prime Minister 01-06-11</td><td><div>&euro; 409.58</div></td></tr><tr><td>Maxwell Photography</td><td>Excellence Awards 09/06/2011</td><td><div>&euro; 857.59</div></td></tr><tr><td>Maxwell Photography</td><td>North South Ministerial Council 10-6-11</td><td><div>&euro; 812.21</div></td></tr><tr><td>Maxwell Photography</td><td>President of European Council 17/6/11</td><td><div>&euro; 562.04</div></td></tr><tr><td>Maxwell Photography</td><td>President Obama Visit 23 May 2011 </td><td><div>&euro; 260.15</div></td></tr><tr><td>Maxwell Photography</td><td>Obama and Cabinet Ministers 23 May 2011 </td><td><div>&euro; 740.52</div></td></tr><tr><td>Maxwell Photography</td><td>New Ambassadors 30-6-11 </td><td><div>&euro; 332.75</div></td></tr><tr><td>Maxwell Photography</td><td>Chinese Delegation</td><td><div>&euro; 357.25</div></td></tr><tr><td>Maxwell Photography</td><td>Saudi Minister 14 June 2011 </td><td><div>&euro; 280.42</div></td></tr><tr><td>Maxwell Photography</td><td>Richard Haass meets Taoiseach Enda Kenny on 01/04/2011</td><td><div>&euro; 371.17</div></td></tr><tr><td>LK Photo</td><td>Costs relating to St. Patricks Day Visit to Washington 2011 </td><td><div>&euro; 2,106.14</div></td></tr><tr><td>Maxwell Photography</td><td>New Sec Gen and Ian Paisley on 26/07/2011.</td><td><div>&euro; 318.84</div></td></tr><tr><td>Maxwell Photography</td><td>Meeting EU Parliament President 12 July 2011.</td><td><div>&euro; 696.05</div></td></tr><tr><td>Maxwell Photography</td><td>Strategy for International Services Industry 14-7-2011</td><td><div>&euro; 349.08</div></td></tr><tr><td>Hackett's Reprographics </td><td>7x5 Digital Prints</td><td><div>&euro; 30.76</div></td></tr><tr><td>J. Higgins Photos</td><td>Photos Taoiseach 4/5 May 2011 visit to New York</td><td><div>&euro; 303.30</div></td></tr><tr><td>Maxwell Photography</td><td>Arvato meeting with Taoiseach 21 Sept 2011.</td><td><div>&euro; 560.84</div></td></tr><tr><td>BANK OF IRELAND</td><td>19 November 2011 - </td><td><div>&euro; 212.96</div></td></tr><tr><td>Maxwell Photography</td><td>Photocall TAOISEACH &amp;amp; New SDLP Leader 09/11/2011.</td><td><div>&euro; 340.92</div></td></tr><tr><td>Maxwell Photography</td><td>Presidential Inauguration on 11/11/2011.</td><td><div>&euro; 3,956.70</div></td></tr></table></p></reply>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.118" nospeaker="true" ><p>2012Maxwell PhotographyTaoiseach signs Book of condolence 20 Dec 2011.&euro; 371.17Maxwell PhotographyTaoiseach - Christmas Media Meeting 22 Dec 2011.&euro; 296.75The Press Association 12 January 2012 - Photos of Prime Minister David Cameron with Taoiseach Enda Kenny 10 Downing Street.&euro; 122.01Maxwell PhotographyBritish Irish Council 13/01/12&euro; 531.05Maxwell PhotographyTaoiseach meeting with Deputy PM Nick Clegg&euro; 377.30Maxwell PhotographyBlue Star Programmes on 07/02/2012.&euro; 539.36Maxwell PhotographyEU Presidency Job winning logo on 02/02/2012.&euro; 687.26Maxwell PhotographyTaoiseach &amp;amp; T&aacute;naiste attend 'Progress to date' launch 07/03/2012.&euro; 195.57Frank Fennell Photography LtdLaunch of the Stability Treaty Website, 19 April 2012.&euro; 409.63Frank Fennell Photography LtdOlympic Torch Photocall at Govt Buildings on 06/06/2012.&euro; 268.45QiLaiPhotographer for Taoiseach's visit to China 25/28 March 20122,817.49Maxwell PhotographyCarers Strategy Launch in the Italian Room on 19th July 2012.&euro; 439.11LK PhotosTaoiseach's visit to US 19-21 March 2012.&euro; 1,774.78Lafayette Photography LtdNSMC in Farmleigh on 15/06/2012&euro; 174.24Lafayette Photography LtdNational Day of Commemoration 08/07/2012 &euro; 555.75Lafayette Photography LtdOlympic Reception at Farmleigh 15/08/2012 - CD of photographs&euro; 330.16Lafayette Photography LtdOfficial Photography services for visit of Secretary of State Northern Ireland on 01 Oct 2012.&euro; 87.66Michael Hudson PhotosTaoiseach's Visit to Chicago, 17 March 2012&euro; 302.35Lafayette Photography Ltd18hrs of photography over 4 days for the JPEGs for Whos Who on the Irish Presidency Website&euro; 3,168.51</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.119" nospeaker="true" ><p>2013Frank Fennell Photography LtdEU Conference of Presidents, Dublin Castle on 31 December 2012&euro; 116.85Frank Fennell Photography LtdPresidency meeting of European Parliament Leaders, Dublin Castle 29th Nov 2012&euro; 430.51Maxwell PhotographyPhotography Prints for Constitutional Convention Inaugural Meeting on 1st Dec 2012.&euro; 1,763.46Mac Innes Photography LtdFamily photo shot, post production touch up + prints (36 copies) for the EU Directors General Informal meeting (13-14/1/2013)&euro; 512.62Maxwell Photography2 JPEG images of the Taoiseach/Cyprus President Nov 2005 - 28 Jan 2013.&euro; 34.44Lafayette Photography LtdEucharistic Congress Reception Dublin Castle 1st July 2012&euro; 171.01Lafayette Photography LtdVisit of Secretary of State Northern Ireland on 01 Oct 2012, 18 images sent to media&euro; 19.43Mac Innes Photography LtdPhotocall for 40 years in the EU, Art Exhibition, 25 February 2013.&euro; 318.54Mac Innes Photography LtdInformal Justice and Home Affairs meeting, Dublin Castle, 18/01/13&euro; 1,471.99Mac Innes Photography LtdEU Council President Herman Van Rompuy visit, Dublin Castle, 9/1/2013&euro; 1,645.47Mac Innes Photography LtdInformal Justice and Home Affairs meeting, session 2, Dublin Castle, 17/1/2013&euro; 1,449.89Mac Innes Photography LtdInformal EU Affairs meeting, Dublin Castle 21/01/13.&euro; 1,564.62Mac Innes Photography LtdInformal meeting of Employment 8th Feb. 2013 Dublin Castle.&euro; 817.91Mac Innes Photography LtdInformal meeting of Employment 7th Feb. 2013 Dublin Castle.&euro; 1,573.31Levon Biss Photography LtdPrints of Taoiseach's Time Magazine cover 26/11/2012&euro; 111.95Mac Innes Photography Ltd31st Dec 2012 for EU Flag Raising Ceremony attended by Taoiseach at Dublin Castle.&euro; 669.09Mac Innes Photography LtdVisit of Presidents Barroso &amp;amp; Schulz at Government Buildings on 28/2/2013. - Post Production Fee&euro; 257.43Mac Innes Photography LtdInformal meeting of Defence Ministers 13/2/2013, Dublin Castle.&euro; 817.91Mac Innes Photography LtdInformal meeting of Development &amp;amp; Co-operation Ministers 12/2/2013, Dublin Castle.&euro; 1,559.45M McNally PhotographerTaoiseach's visit to Downing Street on 11 March 2013.&euro; 335.03E Hill PhotographyTaoiseach's visit to Enniskillen, 11 November 2012.&euro; 700.60Peter Cavanagh PhotographyWhos Who for Presidency. 27/28 Sept. 2012 &amp;amp; 16 Oct 2012.&euro; 1,600.00Magnum ComputersPhotos of Taoiseach's visit to Cleveland, Ohio. October 2012.&euro; 192.41Mac Innes Photography LtdGymnich meeting - 23rd March 2013.&euro; 484.58Mac Innes Photography LtdPrints, Presentation Folders, Envelopes relating to Host Photography for Informal Meeting of Energy Ministers at Dublin Castle 24 April, 2013&euro; 1,181.62Mac Innes Photography LtdPrints, Presentation Folders, Envelopes relating to Host Photography for Informal Meeting of Environment Ministers at Dublin Castle 23 April, 2013&euro; 1,307.04Mac Innes Photography LtdInformal Meeting of Environment Ministers at Dublin Castle on 22nd April 2013&euro; 821.57Mac Innes Photography LtdPrints, Presentation Folders, Envelopes relating to Host Photography for Informal Meeting of Ministers for Trade at Dublin Castle 18 April, 2013&euro; 1,535.67Mac Innes Photography LtdHunger-Nutrition Conference at Dublin Castle 15 April,2013&euro; 968.41Mac Innes Photography LtdECOFIN Ministerial Informal meeting on 13/4/2013&euro; 1,870.49Mac Innes Photography LtdPrints, Presentation Folders, Envelopes relating to Host Photography for Informal Meeting of ECOFIN Ministerial Informal 12 April 2013.&euro; 4,126.55Mac Innes Photography LtdHunger-Nutrition &amp;amp; Climate Change at Dublin Castle on 16th April 2013.&euro; 817.91Mac Innes Photography LtdCommission College meeting Dublin Castle on 10 Jan 2013 - Prints &amp;amp; Digital Imaging&euro; 2,042.61Mac Innes Photography LtdHealth Informal Ministerial Meeting 4th March, Dublin Castle attendance&euro; 276.75Mac Innes Photography LtdEU Presidency Team Group Shot on 01 May 2013.&euro; 302.58Mac Innes Photography LtdHealth Informal Ministerial Meeting 5th March 2013- Dublin Castle.&euro; 1,134.33Mac Innes Photography LtdGymich meeting 22nd March 2013, Photography &amp;amp; high resolution imaging&euro; 1,570.00Mac Innes Photography LtdMinisterial Informal, Agriculture Ministers on 27th &amp;amp; 28th May 2013 &euro; 2,453.74Mac Innes Photography LtdMinisterial Informal - Competitiveness [Dept. DJEI ] 2nd May 2013&euro; 817.91Mac Innes Photography LtdInformal meeting of Competitiveness - Council day on 03 May 2013.&euro; 1,134.34Mac Innes Photography LtdFamily photos of Presidency team at Government Buildings on 01 May 2013.&euro; 31.38Mac Innes Photography LtdPresidency Liaison Officers Photos at Dublin Castle on 27 May 2013.&euro; 162.01Marty Katz Photography &amp;amp; James Higgins PhotographySt Patrick's Day Visit, New York - 16-17 March 2013&euro; 2,235.66Maxwell PhotographyNorth South Ministerial Meeting on 05/07/2013 at Dublin Castle Sundays F.T.P. images to Media outlets&euro; 706.02Maxwell PhotographyEU Presidency staff event on 05/07/2013 at Dublin Castle - Upload of images to online gallery&euro; 292.74Maxwell PhotographyRound table discussion with the Taoiseach and on Online Retailers on 06 Sept 2013.&euro; 292.74Maxwell PhotographyTaoiseach's meeting with Bill Clinton at Government Buildings - 09/10/2013&euro; 249.69</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.120" nospeaker="true" ><p>2014Maxwell PhotographyExtra copies of prints of the Queen &amp;amp; President Obama's visit, May 201177.18Maxwell PhotographyPhotography assignment, Taoiseach's Address of the Nation, 15th December 2014956.94Maxwell PhotographyPhotography Services for the Convention on the Constitution final plenary meeting 22nd &amp;amp; 23rd February 2014511.68DNP ServiceTaoiseach's visit to Japan, 3-4 December 2013.244.23Maxwell PhotographyPhotography assignment for the visit of the Spanish Prime Minister on the 6th March 2014519.06Maxwell PhotographyPhotography assignment for the visit of the German Prime Minister on the 7th March 2014396.06Maria PhotographyTaoiseach's visit to Abu Dhabi &amp;amp; Dubai, January 2014.2695.8Dan Hallissey PhotographyTaoiseach's visit to Boston, 16 March 2014.506.77Marty Katz Photography Photography for Taoiseach's visit to Washington DC on 13 &amp;amp; 14 March 20141740.64Maxwell PhotographyOfficial Photography at State Funeral of the late Albert Reynolds 23rd Aug 2014 at Mansion House and Donnybrook Church2841.3James Higgins PhotographyPhotographs of the Taoiseach's visit to New York on 17 March 2014.252.71Dowlings PharmacyPassport photos for Official 04 Sep 20146Boots ChemistPhoto's for Official 13 July 20142.1Getty Images InternationalEU, All About Jobs campaign, purchase of iStock photo subscription for 3 months, 7th Oct 2014207.87Maxwell PhotographyPhotography for North South Ministerial Council on 3rd Oct 2014, Dublin Castle.547.35CreativeShot PhotographyUnited Irish Cultural Center - San Francisco 4 June 2014.753.07Mac Innes Photography Ltd#AllAboutJobs: photography of key local industries and visit by Minister Nash to Carlow, 26 November 2014'491.141 January to 16 January 2015Mac Innes Photography LtdEU - 10 Low Resolution images from Minister Ged Nash events in Carlow 26th November 2014124.85</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.121" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000059#WRB03050">Consultancy Contracts Data</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.122.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1101" speakername="Barry Cowen" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000059#WRB03100"><p><i>153.</i> To ask the Taoiseach if he will provide, in tabular form, the use of external public relations firms employed by his Department since he came to office; the list of uses of the external public relations firms; the internal departmental policy with regard to employing external groups; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2482/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.123.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1072" speakername="Enda Kenny" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000059#WRB03200"><p>The table below provides details of external public relations firms employed by my Department since 9 March 2011: <table><tr><th><b>Name of Firm</b></th><th><b>Purpose </b></th></tr><tr><td>Caroline Erskine, Media and Public Affairs Consultant<br /><br /></td><td>To assist in the implementation of the communications plan for Ireland&rsquo;s Presidency of the Council of the European Union and Associated Projects</td></tr><tr><td>Q4 Public Relations</td><td>Support for the Convention on the Constitution</td></tr></table>My Department ensures that it gets best value for money in the procurement of all goods and services and keeps to a minimum the engagement of public relations firms.  In the cases set out above, the use of external public relations firms was limited to work carried out for Ireland's EU Presidency in 2013 and the Constitutional Convention.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.125" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000060#WRC00200">Consultancy Contracts Expenditure</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.126.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1101" speakername="Barry Cowen" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000060#WRC00300"><p><i>154.</i> To ask the Taoiseach the total amount spent on external IT consultants by his Department in 2010 to 2014, inclusive; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2483/15]</b></p></ques>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.127.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1101" speakername="Barry Cowen" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000060#WRC00350"><p><i>155.</i> To ask the Taoiseach if his Department has renegotiated external IT consultancy contracts and costs since March 2011; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2484/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.128.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1072" speakername="Enda Kenny" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000060#WRC00400"><p>I propose to take Questions Nos. 154 and 155 together.<br/><br/>The total amount spent on external IT consultants by my Department in 2010, 2011, 2012, 2013 and 2014 is as follows:<table><tr><th>2010</th><th>2011</th><th>2012</th><th>2013</th><th>2014</th></tr><tr><td>&euro; 11,711</td><td>&euro; 18,679</td><td>&euro; 0</td><td>&euro; 2,560</td><td>&euro; 0</td></tr></table><br/><br/>My Department does not have any ongoing IT consultancy contracts in place.  When IT consultancy is required the practice in my Department is to select an appropriate competitive process such as seeking quotations, using a centrally negotiated framework agreement or issuing a Request For Tender.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.129" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000060#WRC00800">Appointments to State Boards</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.130.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1101" speakername="Barry Cowen" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000060#WRC00900"><p><i>156.</i> To ask the Taoiseach if he will provide, in tabular form, the number of appointments to State boards under his Department's remit made since March 2011 to date; the number of vacancies in State boards under his Department's remit since March 2011 to date; the number of vacancies in State boards under his Department's remit publicly advertised since March 2011 to date in 2014; and the number of appointments to State boards under his remit drawn directly from the public advertisement process. <b>[2485/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.131.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1072" speakername="Enda Kenny" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000060#WRC01000"><p>Tabular statement follows.<table><tr><th>-</th><th>Number of appointments to State boards under his Departments remit made since March 2011 to date</th><th>Number of vacancies in State boards under his Department's remit since March 2011 to date</th><th>Number of vacancies in State boards under his Department's remit publically advertised since March 2011 to date in 2014</th><th>Number of appointments to State boards under his remit drawn directly from the public advertisement process</th></tr><tr><td>National Economic and Social Development Office</td><td><div>2</div></td><td><div>2</div></td><td><div>N/A</div></td><td><div>N/A</div></td></tr><tr><td>National Statistics Board</td><td><div>9</div></td><td><div>9</div></td><td><div>4*</div></td><td><div>4</div></td></tr></table>* Other appointments were made in an ex-officio capacity or were nominated by representative organisations.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.132" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000060#WRC01100">Freedom of Information Requests</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.133.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1101" speakername="Barry Cowen" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000060#WRC01200"><p><i>157.</i> To ask the Taoiseach if he will provide, in tabular form per annum from 2009 to 2014, the total number of freedom of information requests received by his Department; the total refused; the total granted; the total part granted; the total appealed; the total successful appeals; the total part successful appeals; the total refusals; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2486/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.134.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1072" speakername="Enda Kenny" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000060#WRC01300"><p>The information requested in relation to requests received by the Department of the Taoiseach under Freedom of Information from 2009 to 2014 is set out in tables.<table><tr><th>-</th><th>Total FOI Requests</th><th>Granted</th><th>Part Granted</th><th>Refused</th><th>No Records</th><th>Withdrawn</th></tr><tr><td><div>2014*</div></td><td><div>173</div></td><td><div>36</div></td><td><div>76</div></td><td><div>13</div></td><td><div>16</div></td><td><div>16</div></td></tr><tr><td><div>2013</div></td><td><div>91</div></td><td><div>20</div></td><td><div>40</div></td><td><div>9</div></td><td><div>11</div></td><td><div>11</div></td></tr><tr><td><div>2012</div></td><td><div>153</div></td><td><div>43</div></td><td><div>61</div></td><td><div>14</div></td><td><div>15</div></td><td><div>20</div></td></tr><tr><td><div>2011</div></td><td><div>98</div></td><td><div>28</div></td><td><div>52</div></td><td><div>3</div></td><td><div>11</div></td><td><div>4</div></td></tr><tr><td><div>2010</div></td><td><div>110</div></td><td><div>41</div></td><td><div>44</div></td><td><div>5</div></td><td><div>12</div></td><td><div>8</div></td></tr><tr><td><div>2009</div></td><td><div>99</div></td><td><div>52</div></td><td><div>30</div></td><td><div>4</div></td><td><div>9</div></td><td><div>4</div></td></tr></table>*16 requests are ongoing<table><tr><th>-</th><th>Requests for Internal Review </th><th>Affirmed</th><th>Varied</th><th>Annulled</th><th>Withdrawn</th></tr><tr><td><div>2014</div></td><td><div>6</div></td><td><div>5</div></td><td></td><td></td><td><div>1</div></td></tr><tr><td><div>2013</div></td><td><div>4</div></td><td><div>4</div></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td><div>2012</div></td><td><div>5</div></td><td><div>2</div></td><td><div>2</div></td><td><div>1</div></td><td></td></tr><tr><td><div>2011</div></td><td><div>6</div></td><td><div>4</div></td><td><div>2</div></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td><div>2010</div></td><td><div>4</div></td><td><div>2</div></td><td><div>2</div></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td><div>2009</div></td><td><div>3</div></td><td><div>2</div></td><td><div>1</div></td><td></td><td></td></tr></table></p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.135" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000060#WRC01400">Consultancy Contracts Data</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.136.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1101" speakername="Barry Cowen" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000060#WRC01500"><p><i>158.</i> To ask the Taoiseach if he will provide in tabular form per annum all external consultant reports commissioned by his Department since March 2011; the cost per report; the company involved; the title of the report; and the publication date. <b>[2487/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.137.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1072" speakername="Enda Kenny" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000060#WRC01600"><p>A table details the external consultant reports commissioned by my Department since March 2011.<table><tr><th>Year</th><th>Name</th><th>Details</th><th>Cost</th></tr><tr><td>2011</td><td>QTS</td><td>Health and Safety Statement 2011</td><td><div>&euro;1,270.50</div></td></tr><tr><td>2012</td><td>QTS</td><td>Health and Safety Statement 2012</td><td><div>&euro;1,270.50</div></td></tr><tr><td>2013</td><td>QTS</td><td>Health and Safety Statement 2013 and Risk Assessment</td><td><div>&euro;1,783.50</div></td></tr><tr><td>2014</td><td>QTS</td><td>PEEP Assessment and Disabled Access Review</td><td><div>&euro;307.50</div></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td><div>&euro;4,632.00</div></td></tr></table></p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.138" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000060#WRC01700">Departmental Staff Allowances</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.139.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1101" speakername="Barry Cowen" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000060#WRC01800"><p><i>159.</i> To ask the Taoiseach if he will provide in tabular form the total amount spent per annum in 2011 to 2014, inclusive, on staff subsistence payments and staff taxi payments; if his Department has been audited for tax compliance on these payments and other benefits in kind; if these processes have been revised in view of the Revenue Commissioners' concerns over practices in other State bodies; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2488/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.140.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1072" speakername="Enda Kenny" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000060#WRC01900"><p>The total amount spent per annum by my Department on subsistence payments to staff and on taxi costs from 2011 to 2014 is provided in a table: <table><tr><th>Year</th><th>Subsistence</th><th>Taxi</th></tr><tr><td>2011</td><td>&euro;27,487.01</td><td>&euro;41,174.93</td></tr><tr><td>2012</td><td>&euro;38,803.34*</td><td>&euro;30,273.37*</td></tr><tr><td>2013</td><td>&euro;46,802.27*</td><td>&euro;28,609.89*</td></tr><tr><td>2014</td><td>&euro;45,636.17</td><td>&euro;24,828.37</td></tr></table><i>* Note: this includes impact of EU Presidency</i><br/><br/>My Department has not been audited for tax compliance on these payments.  However, my Department's Appropriation Account is audited annually by the Comptroller and Auditor General.<br/><br/>In March 2014, following a review by my Department, an unprompted voluntary disclosure was made to the Revenue Commissioners which included a liability for benefit in kind in relation to the use of taxis to and from home of &euro;24,506 (including penalties and interest). This reflected a long-standing practice where staff are sometimes required to work outside normal office hours in order to carry out their official duties, in most cases due to Oireachtas sittings.  Revenue guidelines state that benefit in kind is due on the costs of taxis from home to headquarters and vice versa.  My Department has put in place revised arrangements to ensure compliance with Revenue Guidelines in respect of benefit in kind on taxi journeys to and from home.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.141" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000060#WRC02000">Legal Costs</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.142.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1101" speakername="Barry Cowen" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000060#WRC02100"><p><i>160.</i> To ask the Taoiseach the total legal costs incurred by his Department in 2011 to 2014, inclusive. <b>[2489/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.143.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1072" speakername="Enda Kenny" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000060#WRC02200"><p>The total legal costs incurred by my Department from 2011 to end 2014 is provided in a table:<table><tr><th>Year</th><th>&euro;</th></tr><tr><td>2011</td><td>&euro;43,535.00</td></tr><tr><td>2012</td><td>*&euro;241,676.00</td></tr><tr><td>2013</td><td>Nil</td></tr><tr><td>2014</td><td>&euro;22,909.00</td></tr></table><br/><br/>The table does not include any costs that have been incurred in relation to the Tribunal of Inquiry (Moriarty) or the Commission of Investigation (Fennelly).<br/><br/>*In 2012 my Department paid &euro;241,676 in legal costs, incurred in respect of the applicant's costs in proceedings taken against the previous Government about the holding of a by-election in Donegal South-West.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.144" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000060#WRC02300">Public Relations Contracts Expenditure</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.145.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1101" speakername="Barry Cowen" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000060#WRC02400"><p><i>161.</i> To ask the Taoiseach the total external public relation costs incurred by his Department in 2011 to 2014, inclusive. <b>[2490/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.146.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1072" speakername="Enda Kenny" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000060#WRC02500"><p>The total external public relations costs incurred by my Department from 2011 to end December 2014 is detailed in a table:<table><tr><th><b>Year</b></th><th><b>&euro;</b></th></tr><tr><td>2011</td><td>Nil</td></tr><tr><td>2012</td><td>26,631*</td></tr><tr><td>2013</td><td>49,054*</td></tr><tr><td>2014</td><td>8,408</td></tr></table>*The majority of this expenditure was in relation to the EU Presidency and the Constitutional Convention.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.147" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000060#WRC02600">Programme for Government Priorities</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.148.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1182" speakername="Terence Flanagan" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000060#WRC02700"><p><i>162.</i> To ask the Taoiseach the priorities in his Department for the remainder of the term of this Government; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2491/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.149.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1072" speakername="Enda Kenny" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000060#WRC02800"><p>In accordance with its Strategy Statement, the Department of the Taoiseach will continue to support the work of the Taoiseach and the Government to ensure a cohesive approach to the development and implementation of the priorities set out in the Programme for Government and the recent Statement of Government Priorities.</p>  <p>  An updated Statement of Strategy setting out the key objectives for the Department of the Taoiseach will be submitted to Government and published shortly.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.150" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000060#WRC02900">Departmental Reports</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.151.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1100" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000060#WRC03000"><p><i>163.</i> To ask the Taoiseach if his Department has published its annual report for 2013. <b>[2492/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.152.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1072" speakername="Enda Kenny" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000060#WRC03100"><p>The Department of the Taoiseach annual Report for 2013 was published on the departmental website and laid before the Houses of the Oireachtas on 9 May 2014.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.153" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000060#WRC03200">International Agreements</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.154.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1057" speakername="Niall Collins" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000060#WRC03300"><p><i>164.</i> To ask the Taoiseach the actions his Department has taken to allow for the implementation of the Istanbul convention; if his Department has any engagement with the Department of Justice and Equality on this matter; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2494/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.155.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1072" speakername="Enda Kenny" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000060#WRC03400"><p>The Taoiseach's Department has no role in the implementation of the articles or issues in the Istanbul Convention and therefore has not engaged with the Department of Justice and Equality. The implementation of the Convention is a matter for the Minister for Justice and Equality, who along with a number of otherDepartments hold functional responsibility.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.156" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000060#WRC03500">Consultancy Contracts Data</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.157.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1050" speakername="Tom Fleming" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000060#WRC03600"><p><i>165.</i> To ask the Taoiseach if he will provide details of all consultancy firms engaged by his Department during 2014; if he will also provide details of all the relevant fees paid to those firms during the period; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2495/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.158.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1072" speakername="Enda Kenny" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000060#WRC03700"><p>A table details all consultancy firms engaged by my Department during 2014 and the relevant fees paid to those firms.<table><tr><th>Company Name</th><th>Fees Paid</th></tr><tr><td>Q4 Public Relations</td><td><div>&euro;8,408.29</div></td></tr><tr><td>QTS Limited</td><td><div>&euro;2,091.00</div></td></tr><tr><td>RA Consulting</td><td><div>&euro;9,298.80</div></td></tr><tr><td>Total</td><td><div>&euro;19,798.09</div></td></tr></table></p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.159" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000060#WRC03800">EU Directives</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.160.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/970" speakername="Brendan Smith" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000060#WRC03900"><p><i>166.</i> To ask the Taoiseach if he will provide in tabular form the number of EU directives that remain to be implemented within his Department; the titles of these directives; the timeframe for the implementation of these directives; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2496/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.161.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1072" speakername="Enda Kenny" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000060#WRC04000"><p>Responsibility for transposing EU measures into Irish law rests with individual Departments with responsibility for the relevant policy area.<br/><br/>The Department of the Taoiseach has no EU Directives awaiting transposition.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.162" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000060#WRC04100">Ministerial Advisers Remuneration</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.163.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/989" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000060#WRC04200"><p><i>167.</i> To ask the Taoiseach the amount spent by his Department on special advisers for each of the past four years; the way this compares to the four years 2007 to 2010; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2513/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.164.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1072" speakername="Enda Kenny" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000060#WRC04300"><p>The expenditure by my Department on special advisers is detailed in a table:<table><tr><th>Year</th><th>Amount</th></tr><tr><td>2014</td><td>&euro;596,548.29</td></tr><tr><td>2013</td><td>&euro;579,734.87</td></tr><tr><td>2012</td><td>&euro;582,258.55</td></tr><tr><td>2011*</td><td>&euro;755,525.42</td></tr><tr><td>2010</td><td>&euro;886,569.27</td></tr><tr><td>2009</td><td>&euro;974,182.76</td></tr><tr><td>2008</td><td>&euro;667,516.03</td></tr><tr><td>2007</td><td>&euro;676,682.65</td></tr></table>* &euro;390,399.97 of this relates to expenditure on the special advisers of the previous Government.</p></reply>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.165" nospeaker="true" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000060#WRC04400">Ministerial Transport</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.166.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/989" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000060#WRC04500"><p><i>168.</i> To ask the Taoiseach the amount spent by his Department on ministerial drivers and associated travel expenses for each of the past four years; the way this compares to similar expenditure for the four years 2007 to 2010; and if he will make a statement on the matter. <b>[2529/15]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/answers/2015-01-20a.167.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1072" speakername="Enda Kenny" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2015012000060#WRC04600"><p>The total expenditure on Ministerial transport by my Department from 2011 to 16th January 2015 was &euro;68,959.74.  This relates to Government Chief Whip and Minister of State Paul Kehoe.<br/><br/>Prior to March 2011, the Government Chief Whip was supplied with a State car and two Garda drivers.  This facility was removed in 2011.<br/><br/>My Department does not maintain records of the travel costs for each Minister. However, at the time the change was made in March 2011 it was estimated that the annual savings from Cabinet Ministers using their own cars rather than using State ones would be of the order of &euro;4 million.</p></reply>
</publicwhip>