<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.1" nospeaker="true" time="11:00:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.2" nospeaker="true" time="11:00:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Leas-Cheann Comhairle i gceannas ar 10 a.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.3" nospeaker="true" time="11:00:00" ><p>Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.4" nospeaker="true" time="11:00:00" ><p>Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.5" nospeaker="true" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600003#A00100">Cemetery Management Bill 2013: Second Stage [Private Members]</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1038" speakername="Eamonn Maloney" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600003#A00200"><p>I move: "That the Bill be now read a Second Time."</p><p>  I welcome the Minister, Deputy Hogan.  The purpose of the Bill is to provide a comprehensive framework for the management of cemeteries to avoid any distortion of competition where cemeteries are managed in a non-transparent manner and where cemetery authorities engage in commercial activity at their cemeteries in a manner which disadvantages commercial entities in competition with the authorities.</p><p>  On the issue competition, I would like to add to that, because it will become part of this debate, and say that there is a need not only to end the distortion of competition in regard to cemeteries but to address the issue of Dublin city and county arguably having the most expensive burial costs in Europe.  Some have made the case, whether it is entirely correct or not, that it is more expensive to have a burial in Dublin than in the cities of London and Paris.  The lack of competition which exists in regard to burials in this city has influenced the high cost.</p><p>  In regard to the provisions of the Bill, section 1 provides for the establishment of a cemeteries regulator.  Section 2 provides that each cemetery authority, other than a local authority or an ecclesiastical authority, may not manage a cemetery without a licence from the regulator.  The licence should only be issued if the authority complies with specialised management requirements such as that it does not engage in commercial activities other than internment at its cemeteries or, if it is a charity, in other places.  Section 3 makes any trust or private Act subordinate to this Act.  Sections 4 and 5 contain standard provisions.  In regard to financial and regulatory implications, there are possible financial implications in that the Act would disallow cemetery authorities from charitable status if carrying on commercial activity.  Furthermore, the Act will provide competition in the cemetery sector.  </p><p>  On the issue of competition, or lack of, all of us are familiar with the fact that historically church bodies or local authorities have provided burial facilities in this country, as in most of our neighbouring countries.  However, private entities or charities are not excluded, an issue which pertains in other jurisdictions.  I have no objection to that in principle provided there is accountability and a licensing framework.  I appeal to the Minister to ensure that if private commercial bodies engage in burial services, they are licensed in this jurisdiction.  As I said, that is the practice nationally, that is, it is either a local authority or a church bodies, with one exception in the city and county of Dublin.  </p><p>  In 1846, during the reign of Queen Victoria, a committee was established to maintain Glasnevin and Goldenbridge cemeteries.  I am happy to say it was a very worthwhile committee given the particular problems at the time.  Set up during the Victorian times, it was a trust with very special powers.  Not surprisingly, the original trust was all male but what is more interesting, and was a feature of the time, was that the committee was based on perpetual succession - in other words, certain named persons and their successors.  Effectively, it was a closed shop or, to put a stronger slant on it, a secret society.  If someone died, the existing members decided who would replace them.  All of their business, financial or otherwise, was exclusively private.  That aside, it served a very useful purpose and I do not wish to take anything from the work it did.</p><p>  Interestingly, the status of having perpetual succession, which was introduced in 1846, continues to this day.  It might have been a feature of Victorian times but it should not be a feature of modern Ireland that we have a body or an authority which can exercise perpetual succession because of the secrecy attached to it.</p><p>The 1846 Act did its job in the 124 years until 1970 when a Private Bill came to the House.  I do not question the usefulness or the cause of the subsequent Act because the situation had very much changed in the intervening years.  There were many aspects to the trust.  For instance, it was allowed to take donations.  The Act was one of the very few Private Bills that came to the House, in other words, it was a Bill written not by a legislator or Deputy, but by a body.</p><p> I will deal briefly with two or three aspects of the Act.  The Act was passed unanimously.  The changes that resulted from the 1970 Act gave the committee - sometimes referred to as the 1846 committee, at other times as the Dublin Cemeteries Committee or the Glasnevin committee - powers to borrow money, which it did not have previously, and powers to invest and employ.  It also gave the committee powers to accept grants, subscriptions, donations, devises and bequests for all or any of the purposes of the committee.  Given the secret nature of the committee, to this day, we do not know the assets of the committee and we do not know how much property it has.</p><p> The matter should be of concern to all legislators in a modern democracy such as this.  It is a legacy of the past which should be changed.  Despite what was in the 1970 Act, I argue that it did not confer the Glasnevin cemetery committee with the power to engage in commercial activity.  The Act does not allow the entity to go into direct competition with those providing monument works &ndash; stonemasons providing headstones and sculptures.  In the 1980s the cemetery committee first established a subsidiary company, Glasnevin Works Limited, with limited liability.  I argue that was not proper because the status of the parent committee is a charity.  We have recently had discussions about charities, much of it unpleasant, but that is not to infer that charities do not do good work.  Most charities do good and important work but that cannot be said for all of them.  In the case of the cemetery committee, it was a charity with tax-free status and it engaged in setting up a private enterprise without authority, as the 1970 Act did not give any such power, and went into direct competition with companies in the city and throughout the county in the manufacture and sale of headstones and monumental works.  By that stage the parent company had ownership, or in one case in south Dublin, the lease of a burial ground.  That bestowed great advantages on the new company that was set up to make and sell headstones, to the detriment of all the other companies, most of which were family owned.</p><p> In the period from the 1980s to date, from the setting up of the private entity by the charity, 16 firms in the city and county of Dublin went out of business.  That is proof of the need for the legislation.  Further proof of the privileges enjoyed by the new monument companies is that none of the 16 companies was bought out by anyone because business was in decline as one company was taking the lion&rsquo;s share of manufacturing headstones and selling them.  I refer to companies such as Egans and Crowes among others.  Their closure was one of the consequences of a charity setting up a private entity with all the advantages it had over other companies.  In the autumn of last year three monument companies ceased trading and no one bought them due to the lack of competition in the sector in this city and county.  Hilary Monuments ceased trading in the autumn of last year.  Emerald Monuments of Palmerstown ceased trading in September 2013 and Farrells of Glasnevin ceased trading in October 2013.  I mention the latter specifically because many people are familiar with the company, which was established in 1829.  The site was a landmark one for anyone familiar with the city.  If one was passing the area of Glasnevin one could not but notice the monument works there and the granite and marble pieces of work.  After three generations in business the company closed down.  It was on the doorstep of Glasnevin Works Limited.  Despite the fact that Farrells existed since 1829 the company could not compete with the new regime and ceased trading.</p><p> I use the example as an illustration of the need for the Bill.  We must have regulation because if we do not deal with the issue there will be a monopoly in the city and county, namely, a company operating under the auspices of a charity.  I appeal to the Minister to consider the Bill.  It is not perfect but I urge him to give the Bill serious consideration and to accept it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.8" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/967" speakername="Phil Hogan" time="11:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600004#B00200"><p>I thank Deputy Maloney for publishing this Bill, availing of the Friday facility for Private Members' Bills and for providing the opportunity to discuss important matters such as this one.  The provisions of Deputy Maloney's Bill have been closely examined by the Department.  It presents an earnest attempt to deal with the issues he has discussed.  The Deputy has raised other issues as well with which I will deal. The Government does not propose to oppose the Bill.</p><p>  Deputy Maloney is correct that the financial expenses in the Dublin area for funerals and matters relating to burials are far too high.  In spite of various investigations by the Competition Authority, it is difficult to get evidence of collusion between funeral undertakers or anti-competitive arrangements to the detriment of the consumer, but there is scope for investigation into those matters in the context of the consumer given that the Dublin area is becoming the most expensive place to have a family burial.</p><p>  There are a number of shortcomings in the Bill which I will outline, with a view to being constructive and to improve the proposed legislation earnestly put forward by Deputy Maloney.  The main point made by him is that the Glasnevin Trust is engaged in commercial activities and competing in an unfair way with existing companies in the monument business and thereby contributing to what he perceives as a monopoly.</p><p>The Bill may not be able to deal with these issues but nevertheless the Deputy has raised important issues in the context of competitiveness or, in the Deputy's view, anti-competitive practices.</p><p> I draw the attention of the House to a number of issues about the Bill.  It does not fully provide for the establishment, operation and powers of a new cemetery regulator.  For example, there is no reference in the Bill to allow a Minister give directions to the regulator on policy matters.  There is no provision for financing or staffing the regulator.  We are trying to reduce the number of agencies and devolve more functions to local authorities.  The Bill does not refer to offences, fines or other penalties that would arise if an operator of a cemetery operated without the approval of the regulator.  These are not major issues of principle but are details of the Bill I wish to bring to the attention of Deputy Maloney before we proceed.</p><p> Perhaps local authorities should be represented on all cemetery boards dealing with matters of burial because of issues relating to planning which affect local authorities, and the HSE should also be represented in the context of public health.  It is important to have assurances on these matters from the point of view of the public good.  Perhaps strengthening these provisions should be examined.</p><p> There are no specific requirements to be met for an operator's establishment to be approved by a regulator.  The Bill makes no reference to guidelines or further regulations which would or should be produced to ensure the consistent and effective operation of such establishments.  There is no provision in the Bill for a regulation-making power to set out the standards which must be complied with.</p><p> The Deputy spoke at length about matters relating to Glasnevin and he detailed the history of its establishment going back to 1846.  As the Deputy rightly pointed out, those were different times and there is a need to reform the manner in which we deal with issues, particularly given the increasing number of people opting for crematoria.  Approximately 50% of people in the Dublin area opt for cremation rather than traditional burial.</p><p> A notable difficulty with the Bill is the ownership of cemeteries which are also national monuments, for example, Clonmacnoise, the Rock of Cashel and the Hill of Tara.  For the purposes of this legislation these are owned by the Minister for Arts, Heritage and the Gaeltacht, Deputy Deenihan, while the Minister for Finance has a statutory duty under the National Monuments Acts to maintain them through the Office of Public Works.  As my two ministerial colleagues are neither local authorities nor ecclesiastical authorities, and I would not say they themselves would subscribe to the view of being ecclesiastical - they would come within the definition of &quot;cemetery authority&quot; as set out in this Bill.  I am informed the two Ministers are corporations sole constituted under the Ministers and Secretaries Acts and clearly could not reconstitute themselves to meet the requirements the Bill would impose for eligibility to obtain a licence to operate as a cemetery authority.  I am using these examples to show it is not all as straightforward as we would like, but this does not cut across the principle of what Deputy Maloney is trying to do in the legislation.</p><p> I have made these observations in the context of not opposing the legislation.  I thank Deputy Maloney for bringing forward this important legislation and the opportunity to discuss the Bill which we have carefully analysed.  While it is clear there are some legal and other shortcomings, we look forward to improving the proposals to meet our objectives.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1057" speakername="Niall Collins" time="11:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600005#C00200"><p>Fianna F&aacute;il is opposed to the Bill.  Establishing an additional quango while local authorities already have the capacity to undertake this role is a duplication of scarce resources.  However, the proposals hit upon important issues in managing burial grounds and ensuring adequate space is provided for them.  The high costs of funerals place pressure on families at a deeply sensitive time.  The Government's heartless decision to remove the bereavement grant has made this even worse.  Local authorities taking the lead in reducing burial plot costs is an important step in driving down the price of funerals.</p><p>  The creation of a new quango in the shape of a cemetery regulator is an unnecessary additional expense to the consumer and taxpayer.  This work should be given to local authorities who have on the ground knowledge and are adequately placed to carry out the duties included in the Bill.  The core aim that must underpin end-of-life management, including cemetery oversight, is the right to a dignified burial.  End-of-life management is a costly industry in Ireland.  Approximately 30,000 people pass away each year in Ireland with approximately 3,000 being cremated.  This means 27,000 are buried in cemeteries.</p><p>  Burial plots in Ireland are very expensive.  The average cost in the State is approximately &euro;1,100, with an additional administrative fee of &euro;120.  There is a wide disparity of prices throughout the country, with a plot in Glasnevin costing up to &euro;20,000 for a premium space and a local authority plot in Offaly costing &euro;400.  Despite the significant expense involved, the Government ruthlessly scrapped the &euro;850 bereavement grant payment that alleviated the financial pressure of funerals on vulnerable families.  There is significant pressure in urban areas with regard to acquiring suitable additional land for burial.  Local authorities are in charge of cemetery oversight and have to identify and negotiate land purchases for future burials.</p><p>  Fianna F&aacute;il welcomes the opportunity to discuss this issue, which ultimately affects all citizens in the State.  Cemeteries are an important part of the local infrastructure that require management and supervision to ensure a dignified burial for all citizens who chose this option.  The proposal for a new regulator is an overly bureaucratic response to the problems involved.  Establishing a new quango amid the Government's broken promises on its so called quango cull is an unnecessary expense to the taxpayer and consumer.  The Government has steadily eroded the powers of local authorities in its local government reform agenda.  Its needs to give local authorities responsibility over local issues that are best suited to their on-the-ground knowledge.  Cemetery supervision should remain as part of the local government remit, and licensing of cemetery operations by other bodies should be included in its powers and responsibilities.  This would help encourage competition while keeping down costs to the taxpayer and avoiding further fees being levied on the families of the bereaved.</p><p>  Local authorities have to take the lead in identifying suitable graveyard sites for future burials.  This is particularly acute in urban areas where scarcity of land is driving up plot costs.  Establishing a regulator detracts from the responsibility of the local authority in ensuring there is sufficient land provision.  The promotion of competition in the sector is a welcome step that will help drive down the escalating costs of funerals and help make passing a more manageable process for the bereaved.</p><p>  Funeral costs in Ireland have risen over recent years, with the average price in the country approximately &euro;3,000 to &euro;5,000, but this can rise to up to &euro;10,000 in Dublin.  The significant rise in costs associated with funerals and burials has put major pressure on vulnerable families at a deeply sensitive time.  The Government's heartless decision to abolish the bereavement grant exacerbated the pressure faced by families.  The bereavement grant of &euro;850 was paid to an average of 22,000 families per annum who were eligible for help to deal with funeral expenses.  The Government is now chasing the elderly with cuts all the way to the grave.  This final cut in budget 2014 was the deepest for bereaved families.  The bereavement grant was paid to people who made PRSI contributions over their working life and was vital to help ease the burden of a close family member passing on.  This modest grant gave many families peace of mind and was a welcome respite at a time of grief and stress.</p><p>By abolishing it, the Government again demonstrated its ability to measure the cost of everything and the value of nothing.</p><p> One of the major drivers of the cost increase is scarce burial grounds.  This has also encouraged the ever-increasing switch to cremation as a form of final rest.  Increasing competition in the provision of burial grounds will help address this problem with new operators coming on stream in providing and maintaining cemeteries.  This should be conducted under the auspices of the local authorities' planning powers and overall responsibility for cemetery management.  The hidden expenses of funerals demand a response led by local authorities in addressing burial space issues and the re-introduction of the bereavement grant by the Government to families who need targeted support to help in distressful situations.</p><p> Ultimately, the underlying goals behind policies toward cemeteries and end-of-life issues are simple.  They should enable people to celebrate and commemorate the lives of the departed loved ones in a respectful and meaningful way.  Reasonable costs, suitable space and appropriate location are a key part of that.  Proper planning, fair competition and adequate land will help to enable this and ensure the protection of people's right to a dignified departure from the world.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1021" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kenny" time="11:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600006#D00200"><p>I support the Cemetery Management Bill 2013 being proposed by Deputy Maloney and commend him on its introduction.  I have been contacted by a number of businesses in my constituency that have been involved in the erection of headstones and monuments.  They have outlined to me how the 1970 Act places them at an unfair disadvantage in respect of the provision of headstones and monuments and how many of them have been obliged to let people go recently.  Deputy Maloney has outlined some of the companies that went out of business because of the operation of the 1970 Act, which confers an advantage on one particular business that is involved in this activity.   I support the proposal in Deputy Maloney's Bill to provide a regulator who would regulate this area, which is common sense.</p><p>  I also wish to refer to the question of the cost of burials, which has been raised by other Members, as it also is relevant to the subject matter of the Bill.  It is well known that funeral costs in the city of Dublin are four or five times what they are throughout the rest of the country.  This is a problem for families, particularly those with low incomes, who are obliged to borrow substantial sums of money to pay for funeral costs.  In many cases, they must approach the HSE to get an exceptional needs payment to meet some of these costs.  The question of the withdrawal of the bereavement grant has been raised but, in effect, that grant went directly to the funeral undertaker in most cases.  There is a strong argument to drive down the cost of the funeral undertaking business within the city of Dublin.  In the past, there was a number of firms of undertakers that were household names but they all have changed.  There is an allied funeral undertaker company, I cannot recall its precise name, but there now is a company that encompasses the previous businesses that were providing funerals in Dublin.  In some ways, it is almost like a cartel and this is a matter that must be looked into and is an issue a regulator could examine.</p><p>  The Minister also mentioned the changes in the patterns of funerals in recent years, which is true.  It was the custom - this is particularly noticeable in Dublin - that the remains were brought to the church the evening before and then there was a mass and burial the next morning.  That is not happening, perhaps because the churches no longer have the clergymen to handle it, but in most cases, the remains stay in a funeral parlour overnight and then go to the church the next morning for a ceremony and burial.  This is increasing the cost and it is noticeable that a number of undertakers have opened funeral parlours in areas where they never existed previously such as, for example, one in Kilbarrack and another in Edenmore.  These funeral parlours are being used overnight whereas in the past, the remains would have been in a church and this is a matter that should be considered.</p><p>  As has been stated, a burial is a traumatic occasion through which a family must go.  There is an Irish saying, &quot;He was buried decently&quot;, and people like to bury their relatives decently.  People sometimes go overboard in this regard and one might see a number of limousines at a funeral leading one to wonder why it is necessary to go to such an extent.  Perhaps this is an Irish characteristic and funerals are something we have celebrated the past.  Perhaps they sometimes were over-celebrated but, nevertheless, this Bill addresses this issue of the cost, as well as the lack of competition, which is another matter.  As some of my colleagues have asked me to share time, including Deputy Eric Byrne, I will conclude.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1030" speakername="Eric Byrne" time="11:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600006#D00300"><p>Can the Leas-Cheann Comhairle confirm that I would have been next on the list with ten minutes in any event?  I ask in order that I can share.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1040" speakername="Michael Kitt" time="11:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600006#D00400"><p>If the Deputy is sharing time, that is fine.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1030" speakername="Eric Byrne" time="11:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600006#D00500"><p>So will I have the five minutes from my colleague and then ten minutes to share among my dear friends?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1040" speakername="Michael Kitt" time="11:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600006#D00600"><p>I should note that I will call Deputy Stanley after this but there is plenty of time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1030" speakername="Eric Byrne" time="11:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600006#D00700"><p>I will get on with my five minutes and see what is left.</p><p>I congratulate my colleague on going to the trouble of putting this Bill before the House.  I have been a long time in politics and while I appreciate the Minister is not opposing the Bill, I imagine I might be well and truly cremated up in Mount Jerome cemetery before anything happens.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/967" speakername="Phil Hogan" time="11:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600006#D00800"><p>That is not regulated either.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1030" speakername="Eric Byrne" time="11:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600006#D00900"><p>It is a very popular method of burial in Mount Jerome, where there are two crematoria.  However, to cut a long story short, I was also spoken to by some craftsmen who traditionally designed, carved and erected the headstones for deceased people.  A lovely memorial stands at the northern corner of Harold's Cross Park to commemorate the members of the fourth battalion of the Old IRA.  My grandfather was from Harold's Cross and was a member of that particular Old IRA unit, which is commemorated there by a Celtic cross.  That cross was built by a traditional family of monumental sculptors from Harold's Cross called Broe.  That family is long gone and as has been pointed out already, more than 16 traditional monumental sculptures are now gone.  I appreciate that technology is moving into the field and I understand one can now use computers to carry out much of the design work and that the beautiful handwork on the granite at the Harold's Cross memorial commemorating my grandfather's Old IRA unit probably is becoming a thing of the past.  I do not see many such examples around the place.</p><p>  However, in the brief time available to me, I wish to emphasise it is wrong that cemeteries which receive charitable status can engage in commercial activity much to the detriment of traditional monumental sculptors.   Whatever about the burial costs and other aspects of the Bill, I emphasise that in thinking through what was happening, I contacted my colleague, Senator Bacik, who, as the Leas-Cheann Comhairle is aware, has an intelligent, bright legal mind.  I did so because I was convinced that some item of legislation must be wrong and that the competition must be fundamentally flawed that could allow companies with charitable status to engage in commercial activities in an open market, thereby distorting competition in the market and putting traditional craftsmen and women out of business.  The only appropriate approach I could think to take was that something could be prepared to take to Europe on behalf of these monumental sculptors.  However, the Bill was introduced before Senator Bacik had been able to put together the necessary approach to Europe.  Nevertheless, I ask the Minister to consider this point.</p><p>That element completely distorts the market, so to speak.  It disadvantages the traditional monumental sculptors and artists.  I am concerned about that element of competition and I hope the Bill would be used to deal with it.</p><p> Mount Jerome cemetery was in rag order for many years.  Gay Mitchell was a famous MEP and he also represented Dublin South-Central.  He highlighted the disgraceful conditions prevailing in the cemetery.  When he became a Minister of State, he arranged for F&Aacute;S workers to clean it up.  At one stage Mount Jerome, a place of tremendous historical importance, was in danger of closing but it was rescued at the last moment.  However, it is not good enough that burial grounds can be allowed to deteriorate to the extent that they are obnoxious, with weeds and trees growing through the vaults.  This is not the situation in Mount Jerome today but it has proved the weakness of the system that Mount Jerome almost closed.</p><p> I hope the Minister will agree to elements of this Bill in order to maintain the long-term sustainability and protection of the historical context of these older graveyards.  I hope he will take seriously the intent of the Bill.  Its proposer, Deputy Maloney, has suggested it is not perfect and he acknowledges it needs to be fine-tuned.  Before it is too late for those traditional family monumental sculptors, I ask the Minister to address the question of the unfair competition created by those who run cemeteries and also produce headstones commercially.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1102" speakername="Brian Stanley" time="11:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600007#E00200"><p>I thank Deputy Maloney for proposing this Bill, which is an attempt to deal with the cost of funerals and burials which is an issue in Dublin in particular.  I know that the costs are very significant for families, many of whom are burdened with large credit union or bank loans.  However, in my view the appointment of a regulator to oversee the administration of cemeteries would be a duplication of the supervisory role of local authorities.  Some 950 councillors are taking their seats in local authorities around the country and the Minister plans to devolve power to those councils.  I am not often at one with the Minister but I agree with him about local authorities having the main role in local administration of cemeteries.  There is an issue with how much another quango and regulatory board would cost when money is scarce.  The 34 local authorities are in place and they can do that work.</p><p>Section 4 of the Bill defines a cemetery authority as &quot;any company, committee or body (other than a local authority or a town or borough council or an ecclesiastical authority)&quot;.  I ask what are the functions of these new bodies other than commercial activity.  I presume the Bill does not propose that cemeteries would be competitive, rather that the ancillary services would be competitive.  Other than in a few isolated instances, cemeteries are generally administered by the local authority, by the churches or by committees and that is as it ought to be.  We do not want a situation as is found in some other countries where cemeteries become a private industry and funeral companies engage in often lurid attempts to attract business.</p><p>I refer to a recent planning application in Cork by an individual seeking to open a private cemetery for the reason that the local graveyard was full and that local people were being forced to bury their deceased relatives a long distance away from their home place.  The application sought to have the cemetery on part of the person's own land was turned down by An Bord Plean&aacute;la on the grounds that it would constitute a threat to the local water supply and constitute a traffic hazard.</p><p>One of the reasons for the refusal of planning permission, although this was not stated by An Bord Plean&aacute;la, could be that there is a major resistance on the part of Irish people to the idea that burial grounds should become privately owned.  It could be regarded as profiting from the dead as well as profiting from the living.  </p><p>I refer to the cost of burials.  In Portlaoise, a double burial plot costs &euro;600 and a single plot costs &euro;300 while the costs in Dublin are shocking.  My relatives in Dublin inform me that the cost of a funeral is a significant burden for families.  This Bill does not include provisions about the funeral grant but that grant of &euro;850 was vital for bereaved families.  Many constituents have asked me for advice about how to pay for a family funeral.  They have to go to community welfare officers and do a round of begging.  I ask the Minister to reverse the cutting of the funeral grant which was made to approximately 20,000 families every year and it is a huge loss.</p><p>As Deputy Maloney explained well, the Bill is specifically attempting to prevent cemeteries or companies allied to cemeteries from engaging in the sale of headstones, flowers, ornaments or other goods or services.  This measure in the Bill is to prevent cemeteries from engaging in unfair competition, as outlined by Deputy Maloney.</p><p>Section 2(3)(<i>f</i>) proposes that if a cemetery enjoys charitable status, it should not be allowed to engage in commercial activity other than selling grave plots.  I can see the argument in favour of allowing competition for those whose livelihood is based on selling flowers or making gravestones, for example.  Businesses have gone out of business, such as a firm in the Glasnevin area.</p><p>There is also an argument to be made against cemeteries being allowed to sell flowers within the cemetery itself.  These matters can easily be addressed by the local authority.  Some of the larger cemeteries sell flowers and such like inside their gates but I have not heard of cemeteries actually selling headstones.  Deputy Maloney has explained very well that umbrella companies attached to the cemeteries are selling the headstones.  This presents a challenge to legitimate companies.  I question whether this legislation, if passed, would stand up under competition legislation.  Would the fact that a cemetery was selling headstones and flowers be considered to be unfair on other businesses seeking to provide the same?  It may be an unfortunate comparison but Croke Park sells food and drink in its grounds but this is not considered to be unfair competition with pubs and takeaways in the vicinity.  Is there a need to examine the legal basis for preventing cemeteries engaging in commercial activity within their own precincts?  Perhaps that is something that could be examined if this Bill proceeds to the next Stage and is subject to closer examination.</p><p>While I question the need for a cemeteries regulator and new cemetery authorities, I support practical measures in relation to cemeteries, in particular the obligation on cemeteries to ensure the sanctity of the graves under their responsibility and the safety of visitors.  There have been numerous reports of cemeteries being used for drinking and drug-taking and also incidences of vandalism and people being mugged in graveyards or mourners' cars being stolen.  There is an obligation on the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, local authorities, cemetery bodies and the public in general to ensure that cemeteries do not become centres of such activities.  Unfortunately, criminal elements have identified cemeteries as targets so the problem needs to be faced.  Given that the Bill proposes to set up what in my view would be another quango to duplicate the functions of local government, I will vote against it.  I recognise that the Bill is an earnest attempt to address a particular problem.  It proposes a licensing system and the basis for another quango in order to halt commercial activity.</p><p>In some counties graveyards are administered by the churches, the local authority or by burial boards known as joint bodies.  I suggest that cemeteries not administered by local committees allied to a church body should be brought under local authority control.  During my time on a local authority, we passed by-laws relating to cemeteries, some of which were controversial, such as by-laws preventing kerbstones being used in lawn cemeteries, to provide for easy maintenance.  County councils have significant powers in this regard and the Minister sitting across the way can give them more powers.  It is a significant problem in Dublin.</p><p>People in country areas also have problems in this regard.  We had a cemetery mass in my locality last Sunday.  Issues need to be addressed in the main cemetery in Portlaoise town, which is in great condition and operates under the control of the local authority.  The council provides a local committee that helps run the facility with some staff to assist it.</p><p> The buck should stop with local authorities, which should be empowered to manage cemeteries.  Local authority members would then have a vested interest in ensuring cemeteries were managed properly.  Constituents become exercised about the places in which where dead relatives are buried and how well cemeteries are looked after and regulated.</p><p> The costs of burial have become a major issue.  As Deputy Se&aacute;n Kenny noted, people like to give their relatives a decent burial.  Working class families, in particular, spend large amounts of money burying relatives because they feel they have an obligation to give their loved ones a good and decent burial.  I can understand this attitude but the flipside is that families incur large debts which take years to repay.  I ask the Minister to raise with his Cabinet colleagues the issue of the funeral grant.  While the grant can be as large as one likes, it is of little value if action is not taken to prevent the costs of funerals from increasing.  The cost of a funeral in Dublin and certain other areas has spiralled out of control and the issue is not being addressed.  </p><p> While I understand Deputy Eamonn Maloney's reasons for introducing the Bill, the solution to the problem rests with the new local authorities and municipal districts, which will meet for the first time in the coming weeks.  The Minister's party and the Labour Party have the numbers required to ensure the matter is addressed and Sinn F&eacute;in will work with them to achieve this.  This will require bringing cemeteries under the control of local authorities.  Under the 2001 Act and older legislation, local authorities already have the power to pass effective by-laws, as some have done.  The way forward is to have by-laws introduced democratically in order that they can be stood over.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1011" speakername="Robert Dowds" time="11:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600008#F00200"><p>I thank Deputy Eamonn Maloney for introducing the Bill.  I also thank the previous speakers for their contributions, with the exception of the Fianna F&aacute;il Party spokesperson who dealt with the matter very unsympathetically, and the Minister for his response.  While Deputy Maloney and I accept that certain improvements are required in the Bill, the important issue is that the broader issue it raises is tackled.</p><p>  I first became interested in this issue when a constituent, a woman whose husband had died suddenly in his early 60s, had to quickly purchase a plot in which to bury him.  While she understood it would cost her approximately &euro;3,000, the final cost to emerge was approximately &euro;9,000.  As a result, the lady in question had to deal not only with her bereavement, but also a substantial financial weight around her shoulders.  The most distressing part of her story was that she was not presented with the full picture and the facts emerged only gradually.</p><p>  When I started to inquire into the matter and, having discussed it with Deputy Maloney and others, I realised there was much more to the issue than first meets the eye.  Previous speakers noted that restrictive practices have resulted in businesses closing down.  I do not propose to rehearse the arguments they made, which I support, and will instead concentrate on an important element of the Bill, namely, the provisions dealing with The Dublin Cemeteries Committee Act 1970.  The 1970 Act should be repealed and I ask the Minister to carefully consider doing so.  The Act makes the Dublin Cemeteries Committee, which controls several large Dublin cemeteries, including Glasnevin, Newlands, Palmerstown and Dardistown cemeteries, both a corporate body and a charity, which is a contradiction in terms if ever there was one.  It is apt that the D&aacute;il is discussing this issue at a time when the entire charitable sector is under scrutiny.  As previous speakers noted, it is important to recognise that the majority of charities do extremely good work and operate in a perfectly acceptable manner.  Unfortunately, unacceptable practices have been identified in a number of cases, including in this particular case.  </p><p>  Under that 1970 Act, 20 members of the Dublin Cemeteries Committee hold positions for life.  They are paid and have their expenses covered and the Act explicitly provides that they may enter into contracts with the committee, for example, for the provision of headstones.  What we have, therefore, is a charity providing lucrative employment for its members.  Similar practices were revealed in the cases of the CRC and Rehab.  The Act also provides for the functions of the committee.</p><p>  I will put a series of questions to the Dublin Cemeteries Committee, also known as Glasnevin Trust, and it is vital that I receive answers to them.  What are the sources of the committee's finance?  Why should it have charitable status?  Who are its members and how are they chosen?  What is each member paid and what functions does he or she carry out?  How does the committee decide who can or cannot work in the cemeteries for which it is responsible?  Why does it not publish annual accounts and when will it do so?  Does the committee receive bequests and, if so, for how much and for what are they used?  Does the committee own land other than cemeteries and, if so, where is this land and for what purpose is it used?  Will it make charges for all burial services absolutely clear to those burying loved ones?  I also ask the Minister for a response because these are serious questions on which clarity is needed, especially in light of the general focus on the charitable sector.  Light must be thrown on this issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1075" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="11:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600008#F00300"><p>I am pleased to have an opportunity to speak to this Bill and thank Deputy Eamonn Maloney for introducing it.  The purpose of the legislation is to address serious anomalies in The Dublin Cemeteries Committee Act 1970.</p><p>The death of a loved one is undoubtedly the most traumatic experience any of us will ever encounter.  While the ways in which we say goodbye to members of our families have drastically changed in recent years, unfortunately the rules that apply to burials have not.  It is glaringly obvious that in the areas of local government, business and charity law the management of cemeteries has been unregulated, uncompetitive and, in the case of Dublin, completely non-transparent.</p><p>People who lose a family member take great consolation from visiting the graveyard.  The location and organisation of cemeteries, way in which they are kept, inscriptions and shape and size of grave markers are all important in remembering and respecting loved ones who have died.</p><p>The purpose of the Bill is to provide a framework for the management of cemeteries, which will bring transparency to the operation of cemeteries and prevent distortion of competition among commercial suppliers in the cemetery sector.  Such distortions are evident in the sector today, particularly in Dublin. </p><p>Deputy Robert Dowds noted the existence of a committee of what I can only describe as salubrious gentlemen.  Despite enjoying charitable status, the committee blatantly carries out commercial operations that provide its members with distinct benefits and advantages <i>vis-&agrave;-vis</i>other people who are trying to run family businesses, some of which have been operating for generations.  It is outrageous that it is not possible to ask questions of this group of gentlemen, as is the fact that they are not responsible to either a Minister or the Oireachtas.  The committee appears to have <i>carte blanche</i>to continue to operate as it has done for many years.  This must stop immediately. </p><p><i>11 o&amp;rsquo;clock</i></p> <p> The Bill provides for the establishment of a cemeteries regulator.  This will mean that it will be necessary for cemetery authorities to obtain a licence to operate from the regulator.  The licence will only be issued if the cemetery authorities comply with specific management obligations, for example, that they will not engage in commercial activities other than interments in their own cemetery.</p><p> As Deputy Stanley alluded to, the Bill also obliges the board of management of cemetery authorities to have at least one third of the members of the board nominated by members of the local authority for the area in which the cemetery is situated.  The Bill will lead to greater competition, an overall reduction in burial costs, which is important given the economic circumstances in which the country finds itself, and, most important, greater transparency and accountability.</p><p> The proposed reforms will bring the laws up to date to meet the modern Irish experience of death without over-regulating, which would stop funerals being able to adapt to cultural changes and diversity within this country.  Like most things, the art is to strike that balance.</p><p> The recent increasing commercialisation of the funeral and burial sector has brought with it increasing concern about cost, with the average price of a funeral now at &euro;6,000.  In some areas, it is far higher.  In Dublin, the price for opening a new grave, including the interment fee, monument application fee and foundation costs, is usually in excess of &euro;4,000.  Of course, these costs can be significantly higher depending on where or how one is laid to rest.</p><p> With burial plots in Dublin costing as much as &euro;16,000 each, it is no wonder charities such as the Society of St. Vincent de Paul state they encounter a high number of people getting into financial difficulties arising from funeral expenses.  The cost of a burial plot is usually the single biggest funeral expense, particularly in Dublin, with plots in Deans Grange Cemetery costing up to &euro;16,000, and even those in Glasnevin costing &euro;4,500.  On top of that, there is the cost of interment, which is typically between &euro;900 and &euro;1,000.  Many Dublin cemeteries discourage advance purchase or set the scene so that one physically cannot do so because it makes it more difficult to manage the graveyards.  Glasnevin, for example, charges double for advance purchase grave and interment.  This means the advance purchase of a grave could soar to more than &euro;9,000, with burial costs of an extra &euro;2,000.</p><p> At any other time in a person's life, the norm, if one is making large purchases, is to seek out a couple of quotes, perhaps gather recommendations from friends and family, and think about it.  However, funeral purchases are made under emotional, stressful circumstances.</p><p> It is clear we need to introduce modern management structures to provide greater transparency in the operation of cemeteries.  The Bill should deny charitable status to those cemetery authorities who are engaging directly in commercial activities, and it will also modernise the legal infrastructure under which cemeteries operate.</p><p> These combined reforms will provide greater choice and make the task of bereaved family and relations easier and clearer at a time when they are at their most vulnerable.  I hope the Bill will help make one of the most difficult times in people's lives a little easier.  I commend the Bill to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1190" speakername="Tommy Broughan" time="11:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600009#G00200"><p>I am delighted to have the opportunity to contribute to this debate.  I warmly commend Deputy Eamonn Maloney's initiative in bringing forward this much-needed Bill.  It is typical of Deputy Maloney's original and thoughtful contributions to this House.</p><p>  I firmly agree with the core element of the Bill, that is, the establishment of a cemeteries regulator.  I also proposed the establishment of an independent regulator dealing with funeral services in my Private Members' Bill, the Burial and Cremation Regulation Bill 2011.  The regulator I proposed, however, would also have had a remit in the regulation of the operation of crematoria.  It was also proposed that the regulator would be independent in its functions and would be self-financing.  It is laughable when one hears Fianna F&aacute;il talking about quangos, given that in government it set up dozens of unnecessary quangos, whereas in this area we are talking about one of the most important elements of society and human existence - the way we treat citizens who have passed away.</p><p>  It is exasperating that the legal position is exactly the same as when I proposed my Bill in December 2011 and when it was debated in this House in April 2012.  There is still an absence of a specific regulatory framework clearly governing the sustainability, planning, building and operation of cemeteries and crematoria in Ireland.  Most cannot understand why there is still a dearth of regulation in the area.</p><p>  A number of organisations have raised serious concerns about the gaps in the legislative framework.  For example, the National Council of the Forum on End of Life in Ireland produced an interesting document in April 2011, entitled The Funeral Industry in Ireland: the case for reform and regulation, which made an unanswerable case that there should be a Bill, such as Deputy Maloney's, brought through this House and implemented.  Separately, the Irish Hospice Foundation and the Irish Association of Funeral Directors have made recommendations concerning the Coroners Bill 2007, and it is shocking that Bill has still not been enacted.  The recommendations made by all these organisations related also to the cremation certification process.  Section 5 of my Bill related to this specific issue and it stipulated the conditions under which cremations were allowed and stated a cremation could not take place unless an application for cremation had been made to and approved by the relevant authorities - a new regulator.</p><p>  As the Minister stated, cremation is an increasingly popular form of funeral in Ireland.  In 2012, according to the figures I had, cremation accounted for 15% of funerals nationally.  The Minister's figure could be correct.  In the United Kingdom and countries such as Denmark, cremation accounts for 75% of funerals.  Then, of course, there are countries for which cremation is part of their culture, such as Japan, where virtually everybody is cremated.  Research carried out by my office for the period 2010 to 2012 showed grave concerns about the lack of a licensing and regulatory authority for cremation, including the care and maintenance of columbarium memorial walls in graveyards.</p><p>  Treating deceased citizens with the dignity and respect they deserve is imperative, and when there is a failure in this regard, it reflects poorly on society.  Today's debate is all the more timely in light of the publication of reports last week of the circumstances surrounding the burial of almost 800 babies in Tuam, County Galway, and the disgraceful manner in which these human remains were treated.  I listened carefully to the Leas-Cheann Comhairle's important contribution on this matter in the House yesterday.</p><p>  From the point of view of crematoria, the Edinburgh baby ashes scandal recently also highlighted the difficulties raised by the lack of regulations covering the disposal of human remains.  For many decades, staff at the crematorium in question in Edinburgh buried ashes of dead babies in a garden of remembrance where they were swept up with the ashes of adults.  The recent report into this scandal raised concerns about a hands-off approach to the crematorium in question at Mortonhall in Edinburgh.</p><p>  As recently as April of this year, I asked the Minister, Deputy Hogan, if he had any plans to create a licensing regulatory authority for the establishment and operation of cemeteries and crematoria, and he informed me in responses to parliamentary questions that he had no plans to create such a new authority.  He stated: &quot;The establishment and operation of such services and businesses are currently subject, where applicable, to the provisions of legislation dealing with planning and development, environmental protection and air pollution.&quot;  However, the thrust of Deputy Maloney's contribution and Deputy Dowds's contributions over the years clearly shows that we need a regulatory framework in this area, regardless of whether local authorities would be closely involved in its operation.</p><p>  The other major problem brought to my attention in 2011-2012 was the soaring cost of funerals.  My colleagues have also covered that extensively over the years and brought it to public attention.  Constituents referred to the long list of costs for plot openings, interment fees, foundation fees and application fees, and a host of other charges, especially across the four Dublin counties.  Funeral costs seemed to range from more than &euro;4,000 to &euro;10,000 and above.  I recall Deputy Dowds referring in the previous debate in this House to a funeral which cost &euro;16,000 - an incredible figure.</p><p>  In my own constituency, I have noted over recent years the increasing popularity of using funeral directors from north Fingal, Meath, Louth and even Armagh and Down, which seems due directly to escalating costs in Dublin.  The training for and invigilation of embalming of remains was an issue about which many were concerned when I was last trying to address this matter.  On cost grounds and the licensing of funeral directors and embalmers alone, it seemed clear then that a regulatory system is crucial for the planning, licensing and operation of graveyards, crematoria and the undertaker-funeral director sector.</p><p>I have already referred to the Association of Funeral Directors but the great majority of funeral directors are not members of that association.</p><p>Over the years, my colleague, the former outstanding councillor Peter Coyle of Fingal, has also highlighted deficiencies in the planning process for cemeteries, citing in particular the very bad drainage problems at Fingal-Balgriffin cemetery and in Dardistown.  Councillor Coyle and I had one battle over a planning situation where somebody wanted to have a graveyard and crematorium just beside a nursing home.  It was an incredibly crass development idea but, fortunately, Fingal County Council did not accept the proposal.  It demonstrated, yet again, the necessity for regulation in that regard.</p><p>I welcome the contents of Deputy Maloney's Bill.  As well as establishing a cemeteries regulator in section 1, it also deals in section 2 with the key issue of licensing cemetery authorities.  In addition, section 2 includes a number of important safeguards by proposing that cemeteries cannot operate without a valid licence.  Another integral and well-thought-out feature of Deputy Maloney's Bill is section 2(3)(<i>e</i>).  This addresses an ongoing issue highlighted by members of the Irish Monumental Firms Association, IMFA, concerning the difficulties posed by the operations of the Glasnevin Trust.  Other Deputies have almost unanimously referred to that matter earlier in the debate.  Members of the IMFA have provided me and other Deputies with a briefing on their key concerns about what they maintain is an abuse of a dominant or monopoly position by Glasnevin Trust in its operations of providing services ancillary to interments, particularly gravestones and monumentals.</p><p>I raised this specific competition issue with the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, Deputy Bruton, and he referred the organisation to the Competition Authority.  I understand that the IMFA has been informed by the Competition Authority that, unfortunately, there is nothing it can do about this situation and legislative change - led by the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government - is required.  On 30 April last, I raised this specific issue with the Minister, Deputy Hogan, and asked him if he had any plans to reform The Dublin Cemeteries Committee Act 1970.  At the time, the Minister told me that it is a private Act and he has no role or function in relation to same.  That seems incredible, however.  This is the Republic's Legislature and surely it is our business to regulate this important aspect of our culture.</p><p>Section 3 of Deputy Maloney's Bill seeks to get around this difficulty by making cemetery authorities managed by trusts submit proposals to the High Court to amend the trust and ensure it operates in conformity with the Act.  That is an excellent proposal.  The Minister has highlighted some of the deficiencies.</p><p>When Deputies attempt to bring forward Bills, we often find that the implementation structures are difficult to put together if one has not been a Minister.  I do not think that would be a major failing of this legislation.  I warmly commend my colleague, Deputy Maloney, on his outstanding work on this Bill.  It is typical of his tremendous contribution to this House and to politics generally.</p><p>When my own Bill was discussed a few years ago, it was argued by Deputy Brian Stanley and other Deputies that regulation of cemeteries was best left to existing cemetery trusts and local authorities.  We heard the same refrain from a Fianna F&aacute;il Deputy this morning.  Clearly, however, the record shows that this is not the case.  The treatment of people's remains after death is a key measure of a society's culture and involves respect for all our citizens.  Like other aspects of Irish life, regulation of the sector in a small State like ours requires a national response.</p><p>The Minister has argued the opposite concerning Irish Water, even though the four Dublin counties and the mid-Leinster region looked after the water supply pretty well over the years.  With limited support from Government, we kept the water flowing.  We did the business.  The Minister is saying that it has to be national, but one could argue the same in reverse.  Counties now operate under Uisce &Eacute;ireann and are delivering what the Minister says is his vision for a water supply.  While I am grateful that the Minister has accepted the Bill, I urge him to legislate in this area.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1040" speakername="Michael Kitt" time="12:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600010#H00200"><p>The Minister is entitled to make a short speech of five minutes duration, if he so wishes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/967" speakername="Phil Hogan" time="12:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600010#H00300"><p>I thank Deputies for their contributions.  I remind Deputy Broughan that Irish Water is not a regulator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1190" speakername="Tommy Broughan" time="12:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600010#H00400"><p>No, but it is the same idea.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/967" speakername="Phil Hogan" time="12:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600010#H00500"><p>No.  It is a commercial semi-State body.  I thought the Deputy would be in favour of a commercial semi-State body.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1190" speakername="Tommy Broughan" time="12:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600010#H00600"><p>It is the same.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/967" speakername="Phil Hogan" time="12:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600010#H00700"><p>It is not in private ownership.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1190" speakername="Tommy Broughan" time="12:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600010#H00800"><p>It is about regulation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/967" speakername="Phil Hogan" time="12:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600010#H00900"><p>I can understand why the Deputy would have a problem if it were in private ownership.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1190" speakername="Tommy Broughan" time="12:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600010#H01000"><p>Irish Water regulates local authorities.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1040" speakername="Michael Kitt" time="12:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600010#H01100"><p>We can come back to this again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/967" speakername="Phil Hogan" time="12:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600010#H01200"><p>If Deputy Broughan thinks that the water quality and other water issues in Dublin are good, he has a problem.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1190" speakername="Tommy Broughan" time="12:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600010#H01300"><p>We did the business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/967" speakername="Phil Hogan" time="12:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600010#H01400"><p>I thank Deputy Maloney for bringing forward this Bill.  It gives everybody an opportunity to have a look at where we are.  I agree with Deputy Broughan that we have been slow in dealing with some of the issues that have been raised over the years.  I will certainly take a personal interest in trying to bring forward some of the issues.  I have a problem with quangos being established and a new regulator for this purpose.  However, I am prepared to examine how we can strengthen the accountability, permits, licensing and responsibility of charitable trusts or local authorities in meeting a fundamental requirement for people to get value for money in funeral arrangements.  It is an expensive undertaking in anybody's life, apart from the trauma of losing a loved one.</p><p>  Deputy Broughan has outlined competition issues which are quite complex and difficult to overcome legislatively.  We will examine that matter also in the context of concerns that have been raised here by Deputies.  As various speakers have said, the monuments industry has suffered a lot in recent years.  If that problem arises from a monopoly position, it should be investigated.</p><p>  The local authority system and the HSE have a role to play in dealing with some of the issues that have been outlined by speakers in the House.  I will examine the by-laws in that respect.  I understand from the Office of the Attorney General that a private Act is difficult to amend, so we may need new legislation to deal with this matter.  Deputy Maloney acknowledged that in his legislative proposals currently before the House.</p><p>  I agree in principle with what Deputy Maloney is trying to do in regulating all aspects of funerals.  I acknowledge that this is a very expensive matter.  I am prepared to examine the issues the Deputy has raised about the monuments industry.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1038" speakername="Eamonn Maloney" time="12:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600010#H01600"><p>I sincerely thank those Members on all sides of the House who have made contributions in support of the Bill and for taking the time to endorse it.  Like some others, I was aghast at the initial comment from the Fianna F&aacute;il spokesman.  Times have changed so much that someone from Fianna F&aacute;il, the republican party, can defend the oldest quango in Ireland.  It is 168 years old.  Above all, I am aghast that a man from the county of Se&aacute;n South would find himself in agreement with Queen Victoria.  My God, where are we?</p><p>  I am not in agreement with Victoria, although I am sure she was a very good person.  She did not do much for Ireland but nevertheless we will leave that for another occasion.  It is not Victoria's fault that the oldest quango in Ireland still exists and, according to the Fianna F&aacute;il spokesman, it will continue to exist.  Will the remaining individual monument works companies that have managed to survive in this city and county also continue to exist?  If I am to take as read what the Fianna F&aacute;il spokesman said in opposing this concept, in five or ten years there will be very few independent monument works in Dublin city or county.  I am certain there will be a monopoly, given the track record of the past 25 years.</p><p>  There is a link between Ireland's oldest quango and the commercial entities it has established.  I am referring to the Glasnevin Monument Works and Glasnevin Florists, which are private limited liability entities.</p><p>It will be no surprise to anybody that a scan of the directorships of the charity and the two private entities shows that they are almost one and the same.  Deputy Dowds referred to the status of charities and how they have been punched around in recent times - for very good reasons, although not all of them.  This charity is under scrutiny for bad practices including anti-competitive practices that make it almost impossible for the existing monument companies to earn a decent living and get a full week's work.  Across the Chamber we agree on the principle of it.</p><p> The only way to rectify the problem is through a regulator.  As Deputy Broughan said, it is a serious enough matter to be the responsibility of an appointed regulator.  I do not suggest the formation of another quango.  This is a very small country and there is no need to open a great office in Harcourt Street or Merrion Road.  Can we not learn from past mistakes?  The regulator could operate alone with no need for large amounts of staff and great appointments.  There are enough gifted people around to take on the additional minor responsibility of monitoring the cemeteries of Ireland.  It is ridiculous for people to make such an argument because it is not about that.</p><p> I thank the Leas-Cheann Comhairle for his stewardship of the debate and the Minister for his willingness to take the Bill.  Hopefully we can work together and resolve both the anti-competitiveness and the high cost of burial in Dublin.  I hope also there are enough of us sufficiently interested in it to work with the Minister to bring about a resolution.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.43" nospeaker="true" time="12:15:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.44" nospeaker="true" time="12:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600011#J00300">Cemetery Management Bill 2013: Referral to Select Committee [Private Members]</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1038" speakername="Eamonn Maloney" time="12:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600011#J00400"><p>I move:<blockquote>That the Bill be referred to the Select Sub-Committee on Environment, Community and Local Government pursuant to Standing Orders 82A(3)(<i>a</i>) and (6)(<i>a</i>) and 118 of the Standing Orders relative to Public Business.</blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.46" nospeaker="true" time="12:15:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.47" nospeaker="true" time="12:15:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 11.25 a.m. and resumed at 11.45 a.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.48" nospeaker="true" time="12:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600012#L00100">Reform of Judicial Appointments Procedures Bill 2013: Second Stage [Private Members]</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/998" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="12:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600012#L00200"><p>I move: &quot;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&quot;</p><p>The Reform of Judicial Appointments Procedures Bill 2013 was published in January last year and it seeks to increase transparency and accountability in judicial appointments.  Confidence in the justice system is contingent on a Judiciary which is free from political control and political or other bias.  It is essential that there is an independent and impartial Judiciary which is representative of the community it serves.  I acknowledge that the overwhelming majority, if not all, of the members of the Judiciary who have served down through the years see themselves in that light.  Although I appreciate that, because of the way we have carried out the appointments, it has left the perception of political appointment, which is very unfortunate and must end.</p><p>A truly representative Judiciary would enhance confidence in the justice system and promote the development of a non-partisan Judiciary and a culture of judicial independence.  Future judicial appointments should be drawn from a wide pool of qualified candidates that fully represent the community as a key step towards the eradication of the corrosive and unaccountable system of patronage.  We must not allow a &quot;jobs for the boys and girls&quot; attitude to permeate something so fundamentally important as the administration of justice in the State.  As well as increasing transparency and accountability in the appointment of judges, we also want a judicial council and complaints body that will hold judges to account, along with a code of ethics by which they should abide.  This Government should be the last to make political appointments to the Judiciary.</p><p>We would like to see a sentencing council based on the system in England and Wales, with clear sentencing guidelines given to the Judiciary.  I admire the system in place in England and Wales, as it has engagement with the public about what are appropriate sentences for particular categories of criminal offences.  On the basis of what is agreed, guidelines are passed to the Judiciary.  It is quite a flexible framework and judges still have a degree of discretion according to the circumstances of the individual case, although judges are expected to record the reasons for their decision regarding the sentencing for an offence.  I hope the system will be implemented in Ireland.</p><p>I understand the judicial council Bill is on the way and when the time arises, on behalf of my party I will submit detailed amendments incorporating a sentencing council into the judicial council framework.  I have been advised by a number of non-governmental organisations that this is the best way to proceed, although I had intended to submit a sentencing council Private Members' Bill in order to implement the model in Ireland.  We want a position where the perception of political appointments to the Judiciary can be brought to an end.  We can then clearly state that this is an independent and accountable system, with sentences and practices that are equally accountable.  We hope to get that in the next few years through legislation.</p><p>When we published the Bill last year it was part of Sinn F&eacute;in's campaign to end the political cronyism that had been embedded - some would argue it is still there - in Irish society.  For too long we have all been aware of stories from across the State of judges being appointed after their loyalty has been demonstrated to Government parties.  The days of the old boys and girls club which has dominated the legal and political spheres in Ireland must come to an end.  An investigation by Ms Dearbhail McDonald of the <i>Irish Independent</i>in November 2011 highlighted that a third of the country's judges had personal or political connections to political parties before being appointed to the Bench.  Of the 168 judicial appointments made since 1995, 56 had such connections, and they were appointed after the introduction of the Judicial Appointments Advisory Board, JAAB, an agency designed to take judicial nominations out of the political arena.  In the majority of cases, the judge's links were to one or other of the parties who were in Government at the time the appointment was made, and in other cases, the judges were relatives of leading political figures.</p><p>Sinn Fein believes judicial independence is undermined by the current appointment process in this State.  The JAAB was established in the wake of the controversial appointment of Harry Whelehan as President of the High Court in 1994 and was meant to remove sole discretion for judicial appointments from Government.  However, there is still too much political involvement in the appointment of the Judiciary as the JAAB merely provides a list of seven qualified candidates to the Government, which in turn make the appointments of judicial office holders.</p><p>Sinn Fein believes that there should be as little political involvement in the appointments process as possible.  We have proposed in our Bill to make the following changes to the constitution of the Judicial Appointments Advisory Board.  The chair of the Irish Human Rights Commission shall be the chairperson of the board.  Other members will include the Chief Justice, the President of the High Court, the President of the Circuit Court, the President of the District Court and the Attorney General.  The board would also include a practising barrister who shall be nominated by the chairman for the time being of the Council of the Bar of Ireland; a practising solicitor who shall be nominated by the president for the time being of the Law Society of Ireland; and not more than four persons appointed by the Minister who shall be persons engaged in, or having knowledge or experience that the Minister considers appropriate of commerce, finance, administration or persons who have experience as consumers of the services provided by the courts that the Minister considers appropriate.</p><p>It is notable that the number of lay representatives on the board is increased from three to four in order to ensure there is meaningful lay representation, in keeping with the equivalent obligations under the Good Friday Agreement.  We have also sought to define the criteria for appointments more fully as what we have is somewhat ill-defined and overly subjective.  Sinn F&eacute;in believes the criteria must be transparently meritocratic.</p><p> Section 10 of the Sinn F&eacute;in Bill also obliges the Government to make public the reasons for appointing an individual to a position within the Judiciary.  Key to all our considerations in drafting the Bill were transparency and the restoration of public confidence in the system.  We have moved from the model of a short list of seven to one of three. </p><p> I recognise the work of the judicial appointments review committee led by the Chief Justice, Ms Susan Denham.  This was a very important contribution.  At the end of last January she spoke out on behalf of that committee.  The judges want a new system of judicial appointment.  She called on the Government to de-politicise Ireland&rsquo;s unsatisfactory, to use her word, judicial appointments process and to introduce new laws to ensure judges are appointed on merit.  She also called for the establishment of an independent judicial council to oversee issues such as appointments, pay talks, complaints about judges and judicial education, warning that the absence of such a body is causing great damage.</p><p> She went on to say political allegiance should have no bearing on appointments to judicial office.  The committee's proposals for a remedy to the perception of political appointments are identical to those in my Bill.  It calls for a short list of three and for the reasons for an appointment to be given clearly.  Everybody in this House agrees that Ms Justice Susan Denham is one of the most respected members of the Judiciary.</p><p> I accept that there is no question about the independence of the overwhelming majority of judges.  Having an allegiance to, being a member of, or adviser to, a political party, should not exclude one from holding judicial office because people should be active in political life and are entitled to pursue political interests in their early life.  There needs to be a clear, published meritocracy in the appointment process.  There should be no question that any member of the Judiciary is appointed because of his or her political allegiances.  That is the challenge we face.  The Judiciary wants this to happen, as does the public.  If the Government has the will we can achieve that.</p><p> I lean on the findings of the judicial appointments review committee and the intervention by one of the most respected members of the Judiciary, the Chief Justice Ms Susan Denham.  I have submitted this Bill as part of the Government review of this process.  The Chief Justice's comments were almost identical to our suggestion.  When I and my colleagues in Sinn F&eacute;in drafted this Bill we consulted with people who have much more wisdom in these matters to reach a model that struck the right balance.  I hope the Government will support the progress of this Bill to Committee Stage where it can amend it, if it has issues with it.  If the Government supports the Bill today that would send a clear signal that the Government is ready for change and will engage in that process.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1057" speakername="Niall Collins" time="12:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600013#M00200"><p>Fianna F&aacute;il welcomes the opportunity to contribute to the debate on the mechanisms used to appoint personnel to the Judiciary.  It supports the principles of this Bill which seeks to reform the way in which individuals are selected for appointments to the judiciary by the Judicial Appointments Advisory Board, JAAB.  The legislative provisions including a weight on the principle of non-discrimination, promotion of diversity and safeguarding against improper motives for appointment are to be welcomed.</p><p>  As a third branch of government, the Judiciary has a pivotal role to play in the stability and continuity of the State through the application of the rule of law.  Ensuring we have the best and brightest wielding the gavel, independent of political or personal pressure, is vital to the proper administration of justice in the State.  The JAAB was established under the Courts and Court Officers Act 1995.  Under its remit, the board invites candidates to submit applications for judicial vacancies when those vacancies arise, assesses the applications it receives, and then submits the names of a maximum of seven suitably qualified candidates to the Government for its consideration.</p><p>  The JAAB was established in the wake of previous appointments which caused controversy and threatened the stability of the Government.  The intention behind its creation was to have taken sole discretion for judicial appointments out of the hands of Government and give it to an independent body.  Unfortunately, the JAAB in its current role and with its current prescribed procedures has not fulfilled the original intention of its creation.  The State's judges have called for a radical overhaul of the judicial appointments process stating that a merit-based system that limits the Government's scope to reward political allies is vital to retain public confidence in the justice system.  Since this Government came to office, with a promise of a so-called &quot;democratic revolution&quot;, we have seen a litany of appointments which are overtly political in nature.</p><p>  So blatant were these appointments that in a rare intervention in January 2014, the judges, through a committee chaired by Chief Justice Ms Susan Denham and including representatives of all court jurisdictions, were sharply critical of the &quot;demonstrably deficient&quot; system and said wide-ranging changes are needed to attract high calibre applicants to the bench.  They felt the need to state that political allegiance should have no bearing on appointments to judicial office.  This was a direct response to this Government's approach to filling the benches with its political supporters.</p><p>  The body that represents 90% of Ireland's judges felt the need to chastise this Government by stating, &quot;It is increasingly clear that the relative success of the administration of justice in Ireland has been achieved in spite of, rather than because of the appointment system&quot;.  The sentiments expressed here are a stunning rebuke to this Government's hypocrisy in the area of judicial appointments.</p><p>  We need to get back to a system where appointments made are clearly without reproach.  The rule of law is the bedrock of democracy in our society.  It means all citizens can rely on a set of predictable, stateable rules to govern society that can be independently interpreted.  This Government has continuously undermined the administration of justice in this country, by refusing to listen to whistleblowers about the maladministration of justice; the closure of Garda stations leaving rural Ireland without police protection and the undermining of the Judiciary through a series of measures to undermine its independence and ignore matters of concern raised by it.</p><p>  There are real concerns about how we appoint judges that need to be addressed.  With regard to judicial powers, the Judiciary is far from non-political.  Article 40.3&deg; of the Constitution allows judges to take an active approach to interpreting the Constitution.  Their decisions have direct political consequences.  The establishment of the existence of unenumerated rights in the seminal 1965 Ryan case has transformed the evolution of our Constitution.  It has meant the fundamental law of the land has been able to adapt to a rapidly changing country as judges are empowered to find rights in the Constitution that are not explicitly enshrined.  It also means the Judiciary has wide discretion to interpret the spirit of the Constitution, not simply what is explicitly written in the document.  This gives judges real political power.  The establishment of rights, such as the right to privacy in the 1974 McGee case, legalised contraception in Ireland or the controversial 1992 X case that found for the right to travel, have all been deeply political decisions.</p> <p><i>12 o&amp;rsquo;clock</i></p> <p> It is also worth noting that the Constitutional Convention debated whether to endorse the enshrining of socioeconomic rights in the Constitution and found they should be.  This would expand the powers of the Judiciary to cases beyond the civic and political rights contained in the Constitution as it stands.  This level of political influence on the type of society we have and the rules that govern it underlines the need for this debate and for transparency in regard to whom we appoint to these highly sensitive and influential positions.</p><p> The Bill put forward today would represent a first step in reforming the appointment process.  Fianna F&aacute;il's view is that we can take a constructive approach to changing the system without the need for a referendum.  To that end, we have introduced legislation to tackle the long-standing problems in the judicial appointments process.  Our Bill is based on the declaration of the European Network of Councils for the Judiciary on judicial recruitment and appointments.  At present, the law simply requires the Judicial Appointments Advisory Board to recommend to the Minister for Justice and Equality at least seven persons for appointment to a particular judicial office.  The Minister may or may not accept its recommendation.  Under our Bill, a new judicial appointments board would be established and the existing Judicial Appointments Advisory Board abolished.  Instead of recommending seven persons for appointment to judicial office, the judicial appointments board would recommend candidates whom it would certify as the best candidates for that particular office.  This would ensure high calibre candidates are drawn upon to fill judicial vacancies.  This process would be fully open and transparent, in contrast to the behind-the-door approach taken to date in regard to the Judicial Appointments Advisory Board.</p><p> The Judiciary is a vital part of our system of government and the cornerstone of the rule of law.  Having a genuinely independent Judiciary free from political pressure is central to a functioning democracy where citizens have recourse to justice.  Judicial posts are deeply powerful positions with real political consequences.  We must construct an appointments system that reflects this pivotal role.  Fianna F&aacute;il has put forward its proposals based on European best practice with a view to creating an open, transparent and reliable system of appointments.  Our Bill will not require constitutional change and can be legislated for by the Government immediately.</p><p> As I have said before in this House, the challenge is to balance the independence of the appointments process with the need for accountability.  It is a difficult balancing act.  One of the largest sectors in society is the local government sector, and the most powerful people within that sector are the local authority managers, who are appointed by an independent commission.  They have huge reserved executive powers, which local authority members, who are directly elected by the people, cannot challenge.  That is wrong.  Local authority managers are appointed by a body that is answerable to nobody.  We need an appointment system for the Judiciary which ensures its members can be held politically accountable and answerable.  We will not get that if we have a system which operates behind closed doors and locks out public representatives.</p><p> Public representatives, on the Government side and otherwise, must have a say in the appointment of judges.  Governments are mandated by the people to govern, not to be mere bystanders in a process of formalities.  This is particularly the case with regard to the administration of justice.  There has been criticism of the current Judicial Appointments Advisory Board but, to its credit, only two judges have been removed, Brian Curtin and Heather Perrin - in both cases, for obvious reasons.  No screening appointments process could have foreseen the activities in which those individuals would engage and which led to their removal from the bench.  That must be said in the defence of the Judicial Appointments Advisory Board.</p><p> This is a welcome debate.  We must have accountability of Government and independence in the appointment of the Judiciary.  I do not support dismantling the current system entirely and handing the appointment of senior positions over to persons who cannot be held accountable if something goes wrong.  Accountability is what being in government is all about.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1024" speakername="Alex White" time="12:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600014#N00200"><p>The Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Frances Fitzgerald, has asked me to convey to the House her regret at not being in attendance for this debate.  She is in Luxembourg today at a meeting of justice and home affairs Ministers, a matter of considerable importance in the context of her work as Minister.  The issue of reform of the judicial appointments process is one in which she has very considerable interest and is the focus of intensive work at present.</p><p>On behalf of the Minister, I thank Deputy P&aacute;draig Mac Lochlainn for preparing and tabling the Reform of Judicial Appointments Procedures Bill 2013 and thereby providing an opportunity to debate this important issue.  The introduction of the Bill comes as a significant review of the entire spectrum of issues around the topic of judicial appointments is under way in the Minister's Department, a review which has already been well signalled to the House.  The legislative context for judicial appointments in Ireland is a highly complex one, and any appraisal of that system encompasses an extremely wide range of issues for consideration.  For example, the role of the Government and the Judiciary itself and of others in the process, the relevant practice and eligibility criteria and international benchmarks are all worth reflecting on in making an assessment of the current arrangements and signposting changes that should be considered.</p><p>It was with this in mind that the Minister's predecessor embarked on a major review of the judicial appointments process and initiated a consultation process in December last as a first step.  The Minister, Deputy Fitzgerald, is most anxious, as a key priority in her new role, to see this worthwhile process through.  It is her view that it is vital, if reforms applicable to this area are to be made, that they derive from a considered consultative process, public debate and debates in this House.  Pending the consideration of the conclusions of the review by the Government, I do not propose to express a view on behalf of the Minister as to the approach that should be adopted with regard to judicial appointments.  It is a very important and multifaceted issue that requires detailed examination.  Moreover, I am very conscious that the Judiciary and the courts, as the key organs of the justice system, are constitutionally independent in their operation.  That is a very basic principle within which we must continue to work.</p><p>I will return again to this review process and to the detail of Deputy Mac Lochlainn's Bill.  Before doing so, however, it is useful to summarise the key provisions of the Courts Acts that govern the appointment of judges.  Under the Constitution, judges are appointed by the President on the advice of the Government.  The current process for the appointment of judges is set out in the Courts and Court Officers Act 1995, sections 12 to 17, which established the Judicial Appointments Advisory Board.  In particular, section 16 provides that a person who wishes to be considered for appointment to judicial office shall so inform the board in writing and shall provide the board with such information as it may require to enable it to consider the suitability of that person for judicial office, including information relating to education, professional qualifications, experience and character.</p><p>The board must recommend a minimum of seven candidates for each vacancy and submit to the Minister the name of each person who has applied to the board.  Where there are fewer than seven applicants or if the board is unable to recommend seven, it must forward all names to the Minister and recommend such of those as it considers suitable for appointment.  The Government, in advising the President to make an appointment, must first consider names recommended by the advisory board.  The Act also requires that a notice of appointment to judicial office shall be published in <i>Iris Oifigi&uacute;il</i>, with a statement, where applicable, that the appointment was recommended to the Minister by the board.  Certain positions are excluded from the board's remit, such as the appointment of the president of a court or the Chief Justice, or the elevation of a serving judge.  Therefore, it is the Judicial Appointments Advisory Board that identifies persons and informs the Government of their suitability for appointment to judicial office.  The establishment of this arrangement dates back almost 20 years, and that passage of time alone would suggest that a review of operations and the process is timely.</p><p>It is worthwhile synopsising the process today as the reality is that all the fundamental arrangements that underpin the system have been highlighted in one way or another across the contributions received as part of the public consultation process.  Much of the comment is generated around the issue of the Judicial Appointments Advisory Board itself, including its composition.  The board is composed of the Chief Justice, who is chairperson, the presidents of the High, Circuit and District courts, the Attorney General, a Bar Council nominee, a Law Society nominee and up to three lay members appointed by the Minister.  The 1995 Act prescribed that these three persons shall be engaged in or have knowledge or experience of commerce, finance, administration or as consumers of services provided by the courts, as considered appropriate by the Minister.  Appointments of the nominees of the legal professional bodies and lay persons are for a period of three years and such persons may be reappointed.</p><p> Before introducing any reforms in this area, the then Minister was anxious to encourage public debate on statutory changes that should be considered in the public interest in regard to the appointment of members of the Judiciary.  In December 2013, the Minister's predecessor initiated a public consultation process.  This was to involve not only members of the Judiciary and the legal profession generally but also to engage the broader public and interested stakeholders who benefit daily in innumerable ways from the protection of an independent Judiciary.  Submissions were invited on the judicial appointments process including in respect of such matters as: eligibility for appointment; the need to ensure and protect the principle of judicial independence; promoting equality and diversity; and the role of the Judicial Appointments Advisory Board, its membership and its procedures.</p><p> The Department received 27 submissions earlier this year, running to more 250 pages.  I take this opportunity, on behalf of the Minister, to acknowledge and thank the many contributors, including the Judiciary, the Bar Council, the Law Society, the Free Legal Advices Centres, the Irish Council for Civil Liberties, individual constitutional officeholders, many other individuals and groups and public representatives.  I do not think Deputy Mac Lochlainn will mind me noting his input into that process on behalf of his party in the form of the Bill before the House which is just one of very many constructive and helpful contributions received.</p><p> A report on the outcome of consultations signalling key emerging issues and options for legislative reform is at an advanced stage of preparation in the Minister's Department.  It is inevitable that this report will become the focus of a further consultative process with all relevant stakeholders.  It can be anticipated that this process will take place in the second half of this year and with a resulting outline of legislative proposals towards the end of 2014.  This is a challenging timeframe for progressing significant reform that is likely to encompass several fundamental aspects of the judicial appointments process.</p><p> I turn now to the Deputy's Bill, which as mentioned is one of many very useful and thought-provoking submissions received as part of the review process.  Key elements of the Deputy's Bill seek to reform the judicial appointments process by setting out criteria for nomination; linking the appointment process into equality law; changing the composition and the chair of the Judicial Appointments Advisory Board; limiting to three the number of persons to be recommended by the board for a judicial vacancy in given circumstances; and including the promotion of serving judges within the remit of the board.</p><p> While there is no doubt that these themes feature quite centrally in the submissions received on the current appointment arrangements and that the Deputy's proposals give food for thought, I point out that the Bill does not address many relevant issues emerging from the consultations process.  For example, the need for a comprehensive assessment of all criteria for appointment, the need for a complete reappraisal of the structure and functioning of the Judicial Appointments Advisory Board and the need to consider the eligibility of employed legal professionals, academic lawyers and others.  Other questions arise, and will be responded to under the review, which the Deputy's Bill does not adequately address.  The following are just a flavour of them.  Should the selection process be much more multi-layered, including detailed reviews of applications, preliminary testing, panel interview, professional references and peer review?  The Bill makes no such provision.  Should a thorough merit-based model be developed, publicised and used by the  Judicial Appointments Advisory Board?  Even more fundamentally, should the advisory board be completely reconstituted as an independent statutory and expert body?  Should District Court judges be eligible for appointment to the High and Supreme Court, on a similar basis as are Circuit Court judges currently?  The Bill does not address that issue.  </p><p> Are the existing qualifying practice requirements for barristers and solicitors adequate or should they be varied upwards or onwards? The Bill is silent on this issue.  Should promotion - what we really mean is the elevation of judges - of judges from one court to another or, indeed, as Presidents of the Courts or Chief Justice come within the remit of the appointments body, which they do not currently?  The Deputy's Bill in section 9 provides that so-called promotions should come under the advisory remit of the board but any such provisions, if proceeded with, would require considerable precision as to the specific arrangements.  </p><p> To what extent should information about given appointments be made public?  The Deputy's Bill in section 8 would require the board to make public the names being recommended for appointment and why they are being recommended while section 10 requires that the Government would publish a report within 14 days in advance of appointment as to why a person is to be appointed.  The publication arrangements to do with appointments are subject to review and while the Deputy's suggestion will be looked at, it is not entirely clear to me why such information would be put into the public domain in advance of appointment.  </p><p> Should the advisory board submit a minimum, maximum or fixed number of names for recommendation to Government and what should that number be and should such recommendations be ranked in order of merit?  This matter comes up for consideration in almost every submission, and this is perhaps the central issue and one that needs careful weighing in the context of a range of views obtained.</p><p> In posing these questions I am not suggesting the answers to them but I can say that on all these issues the consultations process has revealed a remarkable range of views with strong support shown for often opposing takes on the best way forward on many of these emerging issues.  I have no doubt too that there will be many ready-made answers from different sources to the types of questions that arise but the diversity of views coming forward, and it must be said in some cases the convergence of such views, clearly demonstrates the need for a comprehensive analysis of all such matters.</p><p> A central tenet of the review is the need to ensure and protect the principle of judicial independence as enshrined in Article 35.2 of the Constitution.  Since 1922 we have had a robust and independent Judiciary appointed under the current constitutional arrangements.  Ireland was ranked second in the 2014 EU justice scoreboard for perceived judicial independence.</p><p> I have mentioned that the current system is almost 20 years in existence and, in many respects, while innovative at the time, it is in some respects very much of its time.  There are doubtlessly reforms and improvements that can be made to render the system more transparent and accountable while also ensuring that the independence of our Judiciary is rigorously protected and the Judiciary continues to be respected by the Irish people and internationally.</p><p> While the decision as to who should be nominated to the President for appointment to judicial office rests with the Government, it has been the practice of this Government to nominate to the President for appointment only persons who have been recommended as suitable for appointment to judicial office by the board.  The only exception to this is where existing members of the Judiciary have been elevated to a higher court - a matter currently excluded from the remit of the Judicial Appointments Advisory Board, as I have explained.</p><p> It is important to state that Government decisions on judicial appointments take only competence and merit into consideration.  The system we have is a considerable defence against any notion of political control or patronage.  However, if that can be strengthened further through the process of review, then that should be done.  </p><p> In respect to certain specific provisions in the Deputy's Bill, key provisions include the appointment of the chair of the Irish Human Rights Commission to be the chairperson of the Judicial Appointments Advisory Board, and a rebalancing of the advisory board to allow for more lay members than Judiciary members.  While such an arrangement may well be for consideration in the context of the review, the Minister is not prepared to accept that this will be an inevitable conclusion or outcome of the review and wishes all of the complex arguments around this point to be very carefully analysed before any aspect of the composition of the advisory board is determined.</p><p> The Bill appears to make no new provision for the filling of a single judicial vacancy which may well be a drafting anomaly in it.  Section 8 inserts a new subsection (5) in section 16 of the Courts and Court Officers Act 1995.  This would have the effect of allowing the advisory board to recommend three names for appointment where there is more than one vacancy - for example, six names per two vacancies - but would leave the existing provision whereby at least seven names would be furnished in respect of a single vacancy and that appears to be inconsistent with the aims of the Bill.  I would be interested to hear the Deputy's thinking on this.</p><p> Other provisions in Deputy Mac Lochlainn's Bill raise questions, appear unclear or require significant analysis of implications and I can assure the Deputy and the House that these will be addressed in the context of the review of judicial appointments.  To take one example, section 4 seeks to go beyond the existing nine equality grounds in the equality legislation with inherent duplication and it would appear inadvisable to do so either in equality legislation or in other legislation without careful thought.</p><p> The Government has decided to oppose the Deputy's Bill as it is currently conducting a wide-ranging review of all matters concerned with judicial appointments that will allow the necessary full assessment of all relevant matters in respect of the issue and the Government will bring forward legislation to reflect the outcome of the consultations process as a priority.</p><p>Many of the issues that arise for consideration in that context are not addressed in the Bill, as I have set out.  In addition, as I have mentioned, some of the provisions are somewhat unclear in terms of their effect and open to question as to implementation.  That said, I think it is important to say that the new Minister will have the opportunity to fully consider the Deputy's Bill as part of the review process along with a significant volume of other contributions and I would take the opportunity today of thanking the Deputy again for his very constructive input to that process and to the formulation of policy in this area.  I very much look forward to today's debate and the deliberations and insights of Deputies on this issue.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1190" speakername="Tommy Broughan" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600016#P00200"><p>I am pleased to get an opportunity to speak on the Reform of Judicial Appointments Procedures Bill 2013 today.  I congratulate Deputy Mac Lochlainn for the great work he has done in this area and for bringing these very important proposals before us to finally democratise our Judiciary because it is fair to say that the public is deeply and profoundly unhappy with the political nature of the appointment of judges, the perceived selection of judges from a tiny elite of Irish society and what appears when one looks at court records to be one law for the wealthy and another for the poor.  It appears that some people who, having committed what most constituents would consider to be very major crimes, walk away virtually scot-free while others receiving very lengthy sentences for stealing a bicycle or a coat, so there is grave disquiet.</p><p>  In the first instance, I acknowledge the work of the former Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Alan Shatter.   I thought he was right to resign but his efforts to reform the legal system and the establishment of the consultation process were very valuable initiatives.  Unfortunately, the pace of reform has been very slow.  We have been waiting at length for the Legal Services Regulation Bill 2013.  Again, there is grave public disquiet in that area.  </p><p>  There are different systems of appointing judges throughout the democratic world.  Like Ireland, many countries use political institutions.  Appointments are made through the judiciary itself in some countries.  The judicial council system is also used and Deputy Mac Lochlainn has referred to the Judicial Appointments Commission in England and Wales as template we could emulate.  Under this system, there are up to seven lay people on the commission if one includes the lay magistrate and five judges.  There is a variety of models.  What is most interesting for many people is the electoral system used in the US.  It is possible to run for election to be a judge even up to the Supreme Court.  This reform was introduced in the 19th century to try to get judges who were more representative of society.</p><p>  Over the years, I have been concerned about the lack of transparency in the area of judicial appointments.  While the enactment of the Courts and Court Officers Act 1995 did address some concerns about the political nature of many judicial appointments, most people felt that it did not create the transparency we need.  As ordinary citizens, we are familiar with looking at the court records and the performance of judges.  The Acting Chairman and I closely observed the magisterial performance of Mr. Justice Nicholas Kearns in respect of the delivery of law and justice respect of the Priory Hall debacle.  On the other side of the scale, I have been exasperated in recent years when some District Court judges around the country have not ensured that the will of this House is carried out in respect of the Road Traffic Acts of 2010 and 2011.  Instead of ensuring that errant drivers get their penalty points, they have allowed people to escape or gone back to the old common law function of the poor box.  This is unacceptable because it is not the will of the people as we have expressed it here in respect of tightening up traffic regulations and law.</p><p>  In many respects, people are deeply unhappy that we still have such an outrageous system of political appointment of judges in this country and it is something we need to get away from.  As Deputy Mac Lochlainn has said, senior members of the Judiciary feel that we need an independent and transparent system where we get the best people and the best legal minds for the job.  Under Article 35.1 of the Constitution, judges of the Supreme Court, the High Court and all other courts established in pursuance of Article 34 are appointed by President and the role of the President will remain regardless of whatever reforms are introduced in respect of judicial appointments.  The manner in which a new commission has been set out in this Bill would be a much representative and democratic system, which is what the public wants.  </p><p>  One issue that has been raised over the years in respect of the appointment of judges is the necessity to consider the appointment of leading members of the academic legal community.  There are some outstanding legal minds throughout our seven universities and senior colleges and it would be right that those distinguished lawyers and teachers would have the opportunity to serve on the bench.  I know the Minister agrees with me in respect of that.  </p><p>  I made a submission to the consultation process.  One of the issues I considered, and one area where I would have gone further than Deputy Mac Lochlainn, concerns lay members of a judicial appointments commission.  Perhaps there could be scope for electing these lay members as is the case in the UK.  If there were a half a dozen members, they could be elected with the rest of us at general, local or European election times.  People have a great interest in the law and following legal matters.  Perhaps senior solicitors or barristers who do not want to be judges would have an input on our behalf.  I ask the Minister to examine if there is some way direct democratic accountability could be brought into the process.  </p><p>  In my submission to the consultation process, I echoed the legal formulations of Deputy Mac Lochlainn in respect of non-discrimination in section 4, diversity in the judiciary in section 5 and the rest of the Bill.  It is critical that all sections of society are represented.  Gender equality in the Judiciary, particularly in the upper echelons, remains a matter of concern.  I note that the two most recent appointments to the Supreme Court were female but perhaps we should have a quota system.  The Labour Party has a great tradition in that regard going back decades.  It was the general principle to try bring forward 50% men and 50% women in these areas.  Certainly the aim should be to ensure that neither gender would have less than 40%.  </p><p>  Other issues are the growing diversity of the population in terms of ethnic origin, particularly the arrival of the new Irish in the past decade, and people from those communities who might be training in law.  It is early days yet but there is a requirement for more accountability to reflect the growing diversity of our society either through Deputy Mac Lochlainn's Bill or whatever template is hopefully based on it that the Government might employ.   </p><p>  I strongly support major reform in the area of judicial appointments.  It will be good to receive the report of the consultation process.  Perhaps the Minister of State might tell us how soon we will know because it would be interesting to read the contributions of the different parties and Members of this House and other people, including those in the legal profession.</p><p> This is a very important Bill and I commend Deputy Mac Lochlainn.  One of the fundamental principles of a free society is an independent Judiciary which is independently and transparently appointed.  The Minister of State quoted a review which puts us second on the planet in terms of judicial independence, but the ordinary citizen feels the perceived political nature of appointments is an outrage and should end and we should have independence in this area.  If it is possible to give the people a say, at least for the commission or council, we should consider it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/953" speakername="Shane Ross" time="13:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600017#Q00200"><p>I very much welcome the Bill.  I am disappointed with the Government's response because it is quite obviously a very constructive effort to reform a system which is generally acknowledged to be in dire need of reform.  My only criticism of the Bill is that it is not radical enough.  It is a very good effort to highlight the real problems we have in the judicial system, particularly in the appointment of judges.  I was struck by several aspects of the Minister of State's reply.  It appears nothing will be done very soon.  Anybody who acknowledges the problem and then reads the Minister of State's speech will be staggered when they see the extraordinary process which apparently must be gone through for a reform which everybody knows is vital.  The Minister of State spoke about the need for a review, then a consultation process, then a further consultation process, a considered consultative process and then we will have some sort of legislation which needs detailed examination.</p><p>  I do not know what Governments have been doing on this issue for the past 50 or 60 years but there has been something wrong with the appointment of judges ever since the foundation of the State because there is a certain unanimity, certainly on these benches and apparently on the Government side.  I was very struck by one sentence the Minister of State said and I presume it is a reflection of the views of the Minister for Justice and Equality.  The Minister of State said, &quot;It is important to state that Government decisions on judicial appointments take only competence and merit into consideration.&quot;  This is nonsense.  Nobody in the land believes the only considerations in the appointment of judges are merit and competence.  The most important considerations should be merit and competence, but the defining consideration is far too often the political colour of the applicant.  The cases of this are so numerous it is indisputable.</p><p>  I suspect it is against the rules of the House to name judges and state they are members of political parties, but I could document them one by one and make an overwhelming case, and will do so if I am allowed, for the fact it is of immense benefit, regardless of which party one is in, to be a member of or have served well the party in power.  I will not name the person, but a Fine Gael trustee who ran as a colleague with the Taoiseach in his constituency but did not get elected and has a Fine Gael pedigree second to none was appointed to the District Court when the Government came to power.  The same person had made many applications under the previous Government but did not get a job.  Suddenly whoever makes the appointments saw the light and he was appointed.  There are so many cases which are similar to this that the Minister of State's statement that all appointments are made on merit really does not hold any water.</p><p>  The fact of the matter is the Government has been as bad as the previous Government in using this political patronage at its disposal in appointing to the bench those who have served the parties well over the years.  This is the way we do it.  It means the appointment of judges and the judicial process is a political cesspool.  It is well disguised and well camouflaged by what has been pointed out so well by previous speakers, namely, the Judicial Appointments Advisory Board.  It is a joke.  It is well dressed up and has people with big titles, such as the President of the High Court, Supreme Court judges and the Attorney General, but at the end of the day it has absolutely no power.  It does not even take its own role particularly seriously.  The Minister of State will know that since its foundation in 1997, although it has the power to hold interviews, it has not held a single one.  It has the power to recommend seven people to the Government, but if the Government does not like the list, it does not have to take anybody from it.  The fig leaf is there and there is apparently a process which means there is no direct contact between the Minister for Justice and Equality of the day, who is the principal player although the Government ultimately makes the recommendation, and the applicants.  We have this layer which itself is full of political appointees, including the various judges.</p><p>  We need to take two elements out of judicial appointments.  One is the Government in power, so judicial appointment is not a power of patronage, and the other is the legal profession itself.  Far too often these appointments are made by insiders and politicians in cabals together who come up with solutions which inevitably mean either insiders in the Law Library or Leinster House are appointed to these positions.  This is not acceptable and it is absurd to pretend this is not the way it is done.</p><p>  I was going to state the wrong Minister of State is in the House today, but it is appropriate he is here because he is a barrister and I respect what he states and what he knows about this.  He knows from the Law Library that barristers tell each other whose turn it is this time and who has no chance because of not being in the right party.  This is what they say inside and outside the Law Library.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1024" speakername="Alex White" time="13:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600017#Q00300"><p>I have never heard such a discussion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/953" speakername="Shane Ross" time="13:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600017#Q00400"><p>I do not know where the Minister of State has been because I have heard barristers say very little else and they say it in here also.  They know perfectly well how the world works.  There is no point in pretending innocently this is not how things happen.  It is how things happen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1017" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="13:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600017#Q00500"><p>I think he is a northsider.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/953" speakername="Shane Ross" time="13:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600017#Q00600"><p>I am not particularly fussy about how it happens but the principles are very important.  I would like to see the initial selection process being made by outsiders but allowing, as Deputies Broughan and Mac Lochlainn stated, people with legal expertise to be involved.  It would be appropriate, of course, that wider society gets involved.  I do not know whether the groups identified by previous speakers are necessarily the right ones and I do not particularly mind, but at least a broader section of society should get involved in the initial selection process.  When one goes beyond this, of course, as Deputy Broughan stated, it would be more than appropriate if people with legal expertise were involved, but this does not mean it must be people who are practising lawyers.  It does not mean it must be politicians who are practising lawyers, or politicians at all.  Why would one not include in the process people from academic institutions with legal expertise?</p><p>Why would one not include people - who know who are the experts on law, who would be suitable judges and would be slotted appropriately into such places - at least to make the initial recommendations?  One would have a politician-free zone and a judge-free zone in this regard.</p><p> The Minister of State's remarks are contradicted by a point to which previous speakers have referred, which is the judges themselves are deeply embarrassed by the process at present.  The judges themselves issued a report earlier this year stating they did not wish to see a process that allows such blatant naked political interference in the selection of judges.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1017" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="13:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600018#R00200"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/953" speakername="Shane Ross" time="13:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600018#R00300"><p>If a politician is to state this is not the way it works, at a time when the judges themselves are blushing at the process, it simply beggars belief.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1017" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="13:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600018#R00400"><p>First, I welcome the Reform of Judicial Appointments Procedures Bill 2013 and commend my colleague, Deputy Mac Lochlainn, on bringing forward this new legislation because it is important, particularly in the current climate.  All Members were elected in 2011, when they made commitments on change and reform of the political system and this is an example from Deputy Mac Lochlainn today of bringing forward legislation to introduce new ideas and reforms into the judicial system and into the wider justice system.  It is important to make that point because speaking as a member of the Joint Committee on Justice, Defence and Equality, and regardless of whether Members like it, the justice system has taken a major hit over the past six or 12 months with regard to a major lack of trust and lack of confidence on the part of the public.  All Members have been inundated with cases of allegations of miscarriages of justice and have witnessed the shenanigans regarding the former Minister for Justice and Equality, the former Garda Commissioner and the Secretary General in the Department of Justice and Equality.  While these issues are being dealt with through a commission of inquiry and through the Guerin report, the theme I hear constantly from the public is there must be reform and change.  Moreover, in the context of this legislation in particular, trust must be restored in the judicial system and unless Members do that, they will be doing a great disservice to the public.  As the Title of this Bill suggests, the subject of discussion is reform, as well as change, a meritocracy and accountability.  It is important to make this point and I intend to discuss individual sections of the Bill in a couple of minutes.</p><p>  However, when discussing this subject, there is another side of the justice system to which everyone appears to be turning a blind eye because Members are so busy beating up one another over procedures, what went on, what was said and for how long the letter was held up in the Department of Justice and Equality.  Meanwhile, young men are being shot in the streets and bodies are being dumped on islands.  There were two such cases concerning people from my constituency recently and nobody batted an eyelid.  More than 1,500 people attended a funeral in Coolock this week and it did not get a mention anywhere.  People are being shot in gangland killings and Members should be focusing on these issues as well.  Although 26% of violent crime in this State arises from the gangland sector of criminality, Members are not also discussing these issues but are being distracted.  My point is that while Members seek reform of the judicial system, they should never take their eyes from the slaughter going on the streets.  Kids are dying in the streets, young people are dying in gang-related deaths and their families are mourning because of the scourge of drugs within Irish society.  It is important to make these points within the context of this broader debate.  Again, it goes back to the issue of public trust.  The public want to trust the justice system and, as I mentioned earlier, all Members have been inundated with complaints and allegations of miscarriages of justice.</p><p>  To return to the Bill itself, it amends the procedures used by the Judicial Appointments Advisory Board to nominate individuals for positions within the Judiciary to end the practice of political appointments to the Bench.  That is the purpose of the legislation and I strongly endorse and agree with my colleague, Deputy Ross, in this regard.  He has been talking about this issue for many years and has presented legislation on it in the House.  He has the full support of the Independent group with regard to this reform because it is important.  Confidence in the justice system is contingent on a Judiciary that is free from political control or political or other bias.  It is essential that there is an independent and impartial Judiciary that is representative of the community it serves.  This is also an important point.  As far as I am concerned, judicial appointments should be made on the basis of merit from a list of qualified candidates who are representative of the community.  Let us bring in equality, a meritocracy and good judgment on behalf of the citizens of this State.  When one considers the legislation more closely, it proposes that any potential candidates should satisfy the Judicial Appointments Advisory Board that they have relevant legal experience.  They of course must have the qualifications to enable them to make judicial decisions with integrity, fairness and impartiality.  Members should focus on those three words, namely, &quot;integrity&quot;, &quot;fairness&quot; and &quot;impartiality&quot; and how, sadly, they have been missing in recent months in this House in particular with regard to many issues.</p><p>  If one digs further into the Bill, section 4 sets out that in the appointment of judicial officeholders, there should be no discrimination on any of the prohibited grounds.  Section 5 is part of a move to work towards a policy of affirmative action to increase judicial diversity.  I consider sections 4 and 5 to be excellent provisions.  Section 6 deals with an extremely important issue and aims to ensure that the practice of hiring political appointees for the Bench is ended.  This is a point Deputy Ross made strongly in his speech earlier.  Members must root out the insiders.  There are many people of high quality with legal expertise in this country, many of whom sadly are out of work at present.  My point is that many young people are coming through the system who in the future would make excellent judges but this should be based on their ability, not on being a political hack, on hanging out with a Minister or dropping leaflets for a Government backbencher.  Members are aware this is going on and Deputy Ross is 100% correct this regard.  I have witnessed this myself over the 12 years in which I have been a Member of this House and, consequently, it is important to make this point.</p><p>  Section 8 amends the number of candidates on the list that the board may provide.  At present, the board must nominate a list of up to seven candidates, from which the Government is not obliged to choose, and this will be reduced to three candidates.  Section 9 will enable the board to provide advice on the promotion of members of the Judiciary and section 10 obliges the Government to make public the reasons for appointing an individual to a position within the Judiciary.  Again, I consider sections 8 to 10, inclusive, to be strong and decisive provisions in this legislation.  However, the entire theme and ethos of the Bill is about reform of the system.</p><p>  In conclusion, I welcome warmly the legislation and again commend Deputy Mac Lochlainn on his magnificent work on this legislation.  I also commend my colleague, Deputy Ross, on his work on this issue in recent years.  This legislation is about reform and change and hopefully, it will be about bringing back trust into the justice system in order that the public can trust the entire process in this State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1040" speakername="Michael Kitt" time="13:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600018#R00500"><p>If he wishes, the Minister of State now is entitled to make a five-minute contribution before the proposer responds.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1024" speakername="Alex White" time="13:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600018#R00600"><p>I thank all Deputies for their contributions to the Second Stage debate.  I especially wish to acknowledge the contribution of Deputy Mac Lochlainn and have listened very carefully to all the remarks and insights from Deputies in the course of the debate.  It has been a worthwhile and constructive engagement and many points that have been made today are extremely valuable,  While they are points that have been raised previously in the House in debates on this important question, this is not to suggest they do not remain important and they will be considered carefully.  I have taken careful note of what has been said.</p><p> The matter we have debated today is a complex one - it touches off concerns about equality, diversity, eligibility, judicial independence, resources issues, qualification criteria and many other issues in an area of great importance to the administration of justice in the State.  I have explained to the House that the Government is tackling the issues covered by Deputy Mac Lochlainn's Bill in a comprehensive and consultative manner.  The precise extent of any measures that are needed to deal with the issues we have discussed will be shaped by the outcomes of the consultations process which is at the heart of the current review.</p><p> Deputy Ross expressed concerns about delay or the length of time of the process.  He caricatured the consultation process in a sense that it was something so rooted in bureaucracy and delay, as he sees it, that nothing would ever happen.  I assure the Deputy and the House that the Minister has every intention of addressing this question and she is currently addressing it through the process I have outlined.  The Minister intends to address the issues raised and the issues of which she is aware.  As I said in my contribution, I anticipate that the process will continue through the summer and that a resulting outline of legislative proposals should be available towards the end of this year, it is hoped.  We are heading towards that prospect of bringing forward an outline of legislative proposals towards the end of 2014.  This is a real commitment which the Minister has given in the context of the consultation process and it is not a case of it being said for the purposes of ending the debate or fobbing people off; it is a statement of a clear intention of the Minister and which I have repeated today on her behalf.  The Minister expects to be in a position quite soon to bring forward a full assessment of all the relevant elements of the matter, and she intends to develop these further in the manner I have described.</p><p> In so far as the Deputy's Bill is concerned, I have opposed the Bill on the specific grounds that its provisions do not provide an adequate framework to address all the issues that I believe require to be considered and to some degree it also lacks key elements that almost inevitably will feature in the comprehensive reform planned in this area.  The best and indeed, the only way, to guard against any of the concerns of Deputies or members of the public about the appointments process to the Bench, is that the system of appointment is clear, transparent and is properly balanced.  Deputy Mac Lochlainn made the point about a person applying for judicial office who has, in the past, had an association with a political party.  This fact cannot of itself, cause somebody to be excluded from the process, just by reason of the fact that he or she has had a previous political association.  The challenge, however, is to ensure that the system of appointment of that person is sufficiently robust and transparent to reassure those who might have a suspicion, even a remote suspicion, that a political background may have entered into the equation as a basis for the appointment of that person.  I agree with that motivation of the Deputy, that the system should be sufficiently robust and sufficiently clear and transparent to guard against any such risks that might exist, now or in the future.  That is what we are all trying to achieve.</p><p> The extent to which it has been suggested by some speakers that people are appointed wholesale on the basis of a political background rather than on the basis of merit and competence, I reject and I do not believe it is so.  To the extent that we need to be absolutely clear that I am correct in this view and that this or future Governments are also correct to hold such a view, the system of appointment deserves and merits a review.  It is being currently reviewed, with a view to the bringing forward of changes as the Minister and the Government may deem appropriate and ultimately that the Oireachtas will be asked to consider and about which the Oireachtas will have the final say in any change to the legislation in this area.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1040" speakername="Michael Kitt" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600019#S00200"><p>I call on the proposer of the Bill, Deputy P&aacute;draig Mac Lochlainn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/998" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600019#S00300"><p>I am disappointed that the Government will vote against this Bill but we have had a constructive debate and it has been a helpful opportunity to examine these issues.  I reiterate that the intervention by the Chief Justice, Susan Denham and her committee was very timely.  It sent a clear message that the Judiciary wants to see a change to the appointments procedure.  Whether we like it or not, there is a long-held perception that the men and women of the Judiciary are often appointed on their political allegiances.  The first question that many people - in particular those who practise law - ask about a recent judicial appointment is to find out who has been appointed and what are his or her political affiliations.  This has been the case and is well known in this House.  We need to remove that perception of any political interference in the process.</p><p>  Another important point to consider is the importance of the Supreme Court decisions.  It is the highest court in the land and its responsibility is to interpret the Constitution on behalf of the people.  Its members must often make difficult decisions when interpreting the Constitution.  We need to ensure that the Supreme Court is representative of all the Irish people, of all the ideologies in Irish society, including conservative, liberal and reforming ideologies.  It is not satisfactory to have an entire Supreme Court based on a conservative tradition, as is the case in some countries.  In my view, such a Supreme Court will interpret the Constitution in a conservative fashion.  That is the reason these matters are so important; it is a case of achieving a balance in a Judiciary that is representative of all the people in order to achieve balanced, fair decisions.</p><p>  I do not wish to impugn the character of our Judiciary.  I accept that we have, in the main, an independent Judiciary which has performed a very proud service to this State.  However, I am reassured and supported in my view by the intervention of the Chief Justice, Ms Susan Denham, which shows that the Judiciary believes the process needs to be changed.  I believe the Minister of State, like me, as well as Members of this House, wish to achieve that change.  I have to accept that the Minister of State does not intend to support the Bill and I accept that the Bill does not provide the full panacea but is instead my humble contribution and I agree that there are many other issues which I have not raised in this Bill.  I accept the premise of the arguments made by the Minister of State about the wider range of issues that need to be addressed.  I ask that the review process should not be prolonged unnecessarily and that it should be time-limited - I am sure it is -  and that the decisions be made quickly.  It is in everyone's interest to have a judicial appointments process that is beyond challenge or any suggestion of political interference, even though this may not be the only challenge.  We also need to progress the Bill dealing with the judicial council as soon as possible.  I suggest the incorporation in that Bill of a model based on the sentencing council in England and Wales which gives clear sentencing guidelines to the Judiciary.</p><p>  We want to achieve an accountable and transparent judicial appointments process with no question about the reasons for the appointment of any individual to the Judiciary - which is a great honour for the individual and his or her family.  We need a judicial council to hold the Judiciary to account and puts in place a clear code of ethics and standards.  I know the Judiciary would welcome such a regulation.  We ask for the establishment of sentencing guidelines to achieve accountability and consistency in judicial decisions.  Some decisions have been controversial, in particular those related to sexual offenders being released by the payment of a fine.  Such a decision is not in the public interest.</p><p><i>1 o&amp;rsquo;clock</i></p> <p> In other cases, individuals have received very long sentences for tax evasion.  While tax evasion is a serious crime for which an appropriate sentence is required, one must compare the sentences handed down in such cases to those handed down in cases involving sexual attacks, which members of the public regard as much more serious offences.  The public must be involved in the process, although not by engaging in some kind of town hall raid, as depicted in "The Simpsons" with crowds of people bearing torches descending on a suspect's home.  We need to have a mature debate about what types of sentences are appropriate for particular categories of offence.  Consistency is required throughout the judicial system if full public confidence is to be retained. </p><p> I am pleased to have had this opportunity to propose this Bill and I accept that the Government wishes to address this issue in wider legislation.  It should introduce a Bill within the current term to address the two issues I have raised, namely, judicial appointments and a judicial council.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.73" nospeaker="true" time="13:40:00" ><p>Question put.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1040" speakername="Michael Kitt" time="13:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014060600020#T00200"><p>In accordance with Standing Order No. 117A(4), the division is postponed until immediately after the Order of Business on Tuesday, 10 June 2014.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-06-06a.75" nospeaker="true" time="13:40:00" ><p>The D&aacute;il adjourned at 1 p.m. until 2 p.m. on Tuesday, 10 June 2014.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>