<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-11-07a.1" nospeaker="true" time="10:00:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-11-07a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:00:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Leas-Cheann Comhairle i gceannas ar 10.00 a.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-11-07a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:00:00" ><p>Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-11-07a.4" nospeaker="true" time="10:00:00" ><p>Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-11-07a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014110700003#A00100">Social Welfare Appeals Bill 2013: Second Stage [Private Members]</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-11-07a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014110700003#A00200"><p>I move: "That the Bill be now read a Second Time."</p><p>This is a very short Bill with one purpose, which is to expedite the social welfare appeals system.  I propose that the maximum period for an appeal should be 60 working days, which is 12 weeks, except in very exceptional circumstances.</p><p>  The Minister of State is aware of the 2012 report of the Free Legal Advice Centres, FLAC, which examined the social welfare appeals system in detail.  It highlighted a number of difficulties with the existing system, of which delay was just one.  In its report FLAC pointed out that in 2011 the success rate of social welfare appeals was 43%.  I understand this figure has since crept up to more than 50%.  The information available to me is that in the period from October 2013 to September 2014 34,000 cases were taken, of which 19,000 cases succeeded, which is approximately 56%.  This means more than half the decisions taken by the deciding officer at first instance were incorrect.  The latest figures available to me also state that at present the average length of time to process an oral hearing is 29.3 weeks, which is approximately seven months, and a summary decision takes 21.8 weeks, which is approximately five months.  These are the average figures; individual cases can take much longer.  I know of cases that have taken a year or longer.</p><p>  Taken together, these delays, along with the high rate of incorrect decisions at first instance, mean that many people may be deprived of their legitimate social welfare entitlement for a very lengthy period.  In certain instances a person may apply for a supplementary welfare allowance to tide him or her over.  The way it is supposed to work is that somebody who makes an appeal shows evidence of this to the community welfare officer, who is supposed to make a payment to tide the person over.  My experience is that this is not automatic.  I have come across several instances in which people have been refused supplementary welfare allowance for one reason or another.  If a case centres on habitual residence, a supplementary welfare allowance will automatically be refused.</p><p>  During the lengthy waiting period, people are affected in two ways.  Some of them are literally destitute and depend on the assistance of family and friends to tide them over.  In many cases these family and friends can ill afford the payments themselves.  It has also been my experience that while people are waiting for an adjudication on their entitlement to social welfare they experience great anxiety and distress.  I have come across cases in which people's health was affected by the delay encountered on an adjudication of entitlement.  With this Bill, I am seeking to shorten this period of uncertainty and, sometimes, destitution.</p><p>  Changes could be made within the system itself which would alleviate the situation.  If 56% of appeals are successful - I acknowledge that some of these successes were as a result of a review by the deciding officer - what does this say about the decision-making process at first instance?  I have some familiarity with the courts system.  If a particular judge was being overruled 56% of the time there would be consternation.  Surely it is not beyond the capacity of the Department to improve the decision-making process at first instance.  If my figures are correct, they show that the number of successful appeals is increasing, which indicates that the position is getting worse rather than better.</p><p>  A common experience of Members who phone the appeals office is to hear that the file has not yet been handed over by the deciding officer.  This accounts for a considerable portion of the delay.  We are speaking about individual human beings who may be kept waiting, so it is difficult to speak about averages, but I understand that on average it takes a deciding officer approximately three months to hand over a file to enable the appeals office make a decision.  This is indefensible.</p><p>  It is no exaggeration to state that the 2012 FLAC report is a brilliant piece of work and a model of lucidity.  Recently I read an interview with the novelist Ken Follett, who extolled simplicity in writing.  He stated that if anybody had to read one of his sentences twice he had failed in his task.  We can say this about the FLAC report.  It is clear, comprehensive and compelling.  It examines the social welfare appeals system in detail and signposts very clearly the need for a number of changes.  Some of the changes proposed certainly would involve a cost to the Exchequer, but others are simple and straightforward, could be done at no cost to the Exchequer and would immensely improve the system.</p><p>  When the Minister of State responds, will he indicate how aware the Department is of the report and what, if any, action has been taken on foot of its recommendations?  The evidence suggests that not much action has been taken.</p><p> Among the proposals made is that the appeals office be put on an independent statutory basis so as to remove the view that it is simply part and parcel of the Department of Social Protection.  Another allied recommendation is that appeals officers be recruited through the general recruitment process rather than from within the Department as this reinforces the image of the Department adjudicating on itself.</p><p> Another recommendation is that the appellant be automatically given a copy of his or her social welfare file.  Currently, an appellant whose appeal progresses to an oral hearing must, if he or she wishes to know the deciding officer's submission, request his or file under FOI legislation.  In my opinion and the view of FLAC, appellants should be automatically entitled to this information. </p><p> Another recommendation is that urgent cases be prioritised or, alternatively, that an interim payment be made to persons experiencing destitution in the event of excessive delay.  While free legal advice is available to social welfare appellants, FLAC recommends that civil legal aid also be available, which obviously would result in a cost to the Exchequer.  FLAC also recommended that terms of reference be drawn up for appeals officers.  I am not aware if this has been done.  </p><p> A number of other, largely procedural, proposals are made, including that the appeals officer carry out an audit of his or her procedures to ensure optimum use of resources and that staff in the Department of Social Protection, where appropriate, direct people presenting with problems to organisations that can help them such as citizens' advice centres and NGOs.  It is also recommended that an appellant be given access to any previous decision which may be relevant to his or her case, with, of course, the appropriate anonymity.  In terms of precedent, such a system operates in the courts.  </p><p> Another recommendation is that oral hearings be granted when requested unless there is a compelling reason to the contrary.  In my experience - I am not aware of statistics in this regard - while this was previously the case, the number of cases in which oral hearings are being refused is increasing, which is a serious matter.  By way of statistics, the number of successful appeals decided by way of oral hearing far out-numbers the number of successful appeals decided by way of the summary process.  </p><p> Other recommendations include that appeals officers, similar to deciding officers, hold quarterly meetings and that regular training be provided for appeals officers.  All of these are simple and straightforward recommendations, the vast majority of which would not result in an additional burden on the Exchequer but would immensely improve the system for the benefit of appellants.  We are speaking in this instance about people whose circumstances are such that they have applied for social welfare benefits and are, therefore, among the poorest in society.  In many cases, they will experience several months of anxiety and uncertainty and, in some cases, great poverty, while awaiting a decision on their case.  The system should be as user-friendly as possible for the people concerned who are a disadvantaged sector of society.</p><p> I look forward to hearing the Minister of State's response on shortening the appeals system or, at least, the provision of some certainty for the unfortunate people stuck in the appeals system awaiting a decision on their cases and also on the recommendations contained in the FLAC report of 2012.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-11-07a.8" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014110700004#B00200"><p>I welcome the opportunity to discuss the social welfare appeals system.  I acknowledge that there has been an understandable level of concern about appeal processing times in the past few years and appreciate that this is what prompted Deputy Willie O'Dea's proposals.  Appeal processing times are always a matter of concern, particularly when they impact on those who are most vulnerable in society.  I hope that in setting out the very significant progress made in this area in the past two years I can allay Deputies' concerns.</p><p>  First, I would like to speak about how the appeals system works and why, by its very nature, it takes time to finalise an appeal.  The process has a statutory basis in primary and secondary legislation; appeals officers are required to be quasi-judicial in performing their functions, and the office operates independently of the Department, which is one of the proposals made by  Deputy Willie O'Dea.</p><p>  The processing times, as reported by the appeals office, include all stages of the process, including the time taken by the Department in reviewing a decision.  It is worth spelling out how the process works.  </p><p>  When an appeal is received in the appeals office, it is registered and the processing time is measured from that date.  As required by regulations, the appeals office then notifies the Department that the appeal has been lodged.  This notification requires that any file or document relevant to the appeal be forwarded to the appeals office and also requires a submission from the deciding officer on the extent to which the facts advanced by the appellant are admitted or disputed.  At this point in the process the Department reviews the original decision.  </p><p>  Social welfare legislation provides that where a decision is on appeal, a deciding officer may only revise the decision if the revision favours the appellant.  Therefore, at this stage of the appeals process, the decision is reviewed to decide whether it should be revised in favour of the appellant.  This part of the process can take some considerable time.  However, it also demonstrates the flexibility of the overall system.  For example, in the case of schemes which relate to illness, disability or caring, the time taken by the Department will almost always include a review of the case by a different medical assessor from the one who initially examined that case.  In many cases, there may even be a third review, in respect of which additional information is submitted.  In cases where the issue involves a means test or other conditionality requiring investigation, a further visit by a social welfare inspector may be warranted.  All of this activity takes time, but it also affords the appellant many opportunities to strengthen his or her case.  By way of example, 21% or 8,062 of the 38,421 appeals finalised in 2013 were revised by the Department in favour of the appellant during this stage of the process.</p><p>  Where a decision is not revised, the file with the relevant appeal submission is returned to the appeals office and added to the files awaiting assignment to an appeals officer.  To be fair to all appellants, the assignment of appeals and the arranging of oral hearings are dealt with in chronological order.  The only exception is in respect of the supplementary welfare allowance scheme.  Deputies will be aware that where a claimant has been refused a claim for social welfare and is appealing that decision, it is open to him or her to apply for supplementary welfare allowance in the interim.  If the application for supplementary welfare allowance is subsequently refused, the appellant can also appeal that decision and the supplementary welfare allowance appeal will be prioritised for attention within the appeals office as soon as the appeal file and submission are received from the Department.</p><p>  When a case is assigned to an appeals officer, he or she will examine the documentary evidence presented in order to determine if the appeal can be properly and fairly decided on a summary basis.  Where it is considered that an oral hearing of the case is required, it is estimated that the logistics alone involved add a further six weeks to the process.  The venue must be booked; the case must be scheduled with other cases to be heard at the same location, and sufficient notice must be given to the appellant and witnesses.  At any time during this process, up to and including the hearing of the case, an appellant may submit additional information, which, as I said, affords him or her the opportunity to strengthen his or her case.  </p><p>  I would now like to turn to the issue of processing times.  The Bill was initiated by Deputy Willie O'Dea on 13 March 2013.  As I said, I appreciate that during the years 2010 to 2012, inclusive, and into early 2013 there were unacceptable delays in the appeals process.</p><p>The background to this was the dramatic and unprecedented increase from late 2008 in the number of appeals received in the appeals office.  Prior to 2009, the average number of appeals received per year was in the region of 15,000, but by 2012, annual appeal receipts had more than doubled, peaking at 35,500.</p><p> The number of appeals received remains high.  In 2013, the appeals office received 32,777 appeals, or the second highest annual number of appeals received since the office was established in 1990.  The dramatic scale of this increase placed considerable pressure on the appeals office.  However, significant effort and resources have been devoted over the last few years to reforming and improving the overall effectiveness of the appeals system and improving appeal processing times for appellants.  An extra 15 appeals officers were appointed and ten former community welfare service appeals officers joined the appeals office in 2011, bringing the total number of appeals officers to 41.  In addition, a new operating model was introduced in the appeals office aimed at improving the efficiency and effectiveness of the appeals system and eliminating delays at various stages of the appeal process.</p><p> On the basis of these reforms and the increase in resources, there has been a dramatic improvement in the processing times for appeals.  For example, the time taken for an appeal involving an oral hearing has dropped from 52.5 weeks in 2011 to 29 weeks at the end of October 2014, which is a reduction of nearly six months.  The time taken for an appeal determined by way of a summary decision has decreased from 25.1 weeks in 2011 to 21.6 weeks in 2014.  These times are still improving.  For example, the average time taken for an oral hearing last month was down to 26.4 weeks and the time taken for a summary decision was down to 18.7 weeks.  By way of comparison, the time taken for an oral hearing in 2007 was 30.3 weeks and the time for a summary decision was 14.2 weeks.  Nonetheless, there can and will be further improvement at every stage of this process.  However, it is worthwhile to consider the comparable processing times for the Social Security and Child Support Tribunal in the UK.  Appeals in that process took an average of 30 weeks to clear as at June of this year.  This measurement does not include the time spent with the Department for Work and Pensions in reviewing the case.  If the time spent with the Department in this jurisdiction is discounted, the figure for the time taken to process an oral hearing in 2014 falls to 17.3 weeks, while a summary decision takes 11.6 weeks.  It is worth noting that the English appeals system is more inflexible in that the tribunal deals only with the decision that was made at a point in time and based on the evidence that was submitted at that point in time.  This demonstrates that we compare very favourably with the UK with regard to processing times.</p><p> Deputy O'Dea proposes that where appeals are not processed within the specified 12-week deadline, a decision allowing the appeal would be deemed to have been met.  This timeframe simply does not take account of the fact that it is a two-stage process, which includes the initial review by the Department and consideration of the appeal by an appeals officer either on a summary basis or by means of an oral hearing.  As I mentioned earlier, the logistics alone of setting up an oral hearing adds six weeks to the process.  Further, the proposal would mean that even where the underlying conditions for receipt of the social welfare payment were not met, an appeal would be allowed simply on the basis of elapsed time.  This would clearly not be tenable and would be a misuse of public funds.  The proposal would lead to a situation in which it may be in an appellant's interest to delay an appeal beyond the statutory deadline in order to achieve this result.</p><p> Significant progress made in the past two years means that the time taken for completion of the process has now decreased considerably.  As of October this year, we are now below the norms that existed before 2010.  As I have outlined, the appeals system in place in Ireland has a number of stages and allows for reviews, appeals and further information to be submitted at any stage of the process.  This favours the appellant, who would otherwise have to repeat the application process unnecessarily.  This process carries an inherent delay in terms of finalising an appeal but it is also a very flexible and accessible system.  For all the reasons outlined, a statutory timeframe for the completion of the appeals process is not tenable, and I will be opposing Deputy O'Dea's Bill.</p><p> We must try to achieve a quicker turnaround time.  I want to maintain a process in the system whereby additional information can be added at any stage, as it would be wrong to have to push people back to the beginning.  There may be a disadvantage to the proposal in this respect.  I can see the very strong justification for the introduction of the Bill, especially if we recall the waiting times that have occurred.  I will certainly take on board the report of the Free Legal Advice Centres and the issues raised by the Deputy with respect to terms of reference and oral hearings.  The office acts independently.  I thank the Deputy for raising the issue today, as it has been an opportunity for Deputies to contribute to the debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-11-07a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="10:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014110700005#C00200"><p>I support the intention of the Bill, but the Minister of State is opposing the timeframe, which is too narrow.  Nevertheless, the intention is to address a problem within the social welfare appeals section.  It is not just a problem with social welfare appeals, as the issue is with the initial decision in many cases.  For example, consider the number of appeals upheld, especially in medical cases.  These would include applications for carer's and disability allowance, as well as invalidity benefit.  There is a range of social welfare payments on which an assessment is made by a deciding officer based on medical evidence.  Considering that the number of appeals upheld can be 40% or more in these cases, we know there is a problem in the system.  Other social welfare applications that go to appeal might see 10% or 15% upheld.  The problem lies in medical assessments and the examination of documentation produced by an applicant.  When the application is made, not all the medical documentation might be present or clear.  I know this because I have seen some documentation supplied by doctors to clients.  If the information is unclear, rather than making a decision of refusal, a deciding officer would be better served by asking an applicant to get his or her doctor to fully explain the issue.  In medical cases, the deciding officer would be a medical practitioner in the Department.  These officers must go on the documents in front of them, but they are not stupid; if somebody has had a body part amputated, he or she will know the condition will not get better.  There have been strange decisions concerning visible medical problems whose existence has not been accepted by a deciding officer.  In such cases, the person involved would experience the stress, strain and turmoil that is often involved in making an appeal, as well as the subsequent delay.</p><p>That is the biggest problem with medical appeals.  Often, the allowance is needed quickly.  This is particularly true of people who will be dependent on a carer.  It is not necessarily the carer's allowance that is in question.  In order for a carer to be granted carer's allowance, the person being cared for must be in receipt of disability allowance or an invalidity pension.  Where somebody has been struck down by an illness that is not properly explained by a doctor, God forbid, there may be a delay in granting these allowances to him or her.  If the person appeals, it can take more than six months before a decision is made by the Social Welfare Appeals Office.  If it is granted at that stage, the carer may then apply for carer's allowance and end up in the same rigmarole.  There is a need for a more linked-up approach to medical documentation.  It is not always the fault of the Department of Social Protection or the Social Welfare Appeals Office.</p><p> I acknowledge the major progress made in recent years.  The length of time for appeals has been cut in half in the past five or six years.  Some of this is related to the letter sent out in the first instance.  I have made this point to the Minister on a number of occasions.  The letter refusing an allowance in the first instance is not very clear on what &quot;review&quot; means.  When better documentation or other facts that could change the decision can be provided, the case can be reviewed rather than ending up in the Social Welfare Appeals Office.  If that were made clearer in the letter, it would be better.  The review is buried in the third paragraph, telling people that they can apply for a review if there has been a change in circumstances or if further documentation is available.  The same paragraph deals with how people can deal apply for a social welfare appeal and sets out the deadline.  People do not understand what a review means.  It must be made clearer to the applicant.  This might cut down the number of appeals and the length of time people are without payments.  In many cases, they have the documentation and can go back to the doctor or consultant or tell the Department of Social Protection that the problem is that there is a waiting list to get a letter from a consultant.  It is one of the biggest scandals that people must wait five, six or seven months for a letter stating their condition.  A press of a button in the hospital is all that is required.  I know the pressure that outpatient units are under, but if they could issue a letter to support a person with a disability it would serve the cause of the hospital because it would relieve some of the stresses and strains that people are under, and this might make their recovery quicker.</p><p> I understand the intention of the Bill and support its progression to Committee Stage, where we can tease out this legislation, rather than having a back-and-forth debate today.  At the very least, we should consider a timeframe.  With regard to the asylum seeker process, which is a debacle, the Minister of State at the Department of Justice and Equality, Deputy Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in, is examining whether a timeframe can be implemented so that people have their human rights respected and an early decision can be made.  If decisions are put off, people do not have the right to a proper service.  It is not yet at that level in the Social Welfare Appeals Office, but sometimes it is due to a complication of the system or the fact that an applicant does not have access to documentation or does not understand all of the forms.</p><p> I presume other Deputies have had the same experience of being asked what people should do with social welfare appeal forms.  One of the initiatives undertaken by FLAC is a guide to the social welfare appeals system.  We can tell people that this is the mechanism of how to make an appeal or ask for a review.  It is framed in this way so that it is clear to people what is sought and what conditions apply.  If people think there have been hard done by, they should have access to the social welfare file through a freedom of information request.  They can then check to see whether account was taken of all of the documents supplied.  It is an extra burden on the Department of Social Protection, but people are entitled to their files.  Perhaps many people do not understand this point, but they are also entitled to their medical files.  If they apply for the medical files at the same time as the social welfare file under freedom of information, they might be able to speed up the appeal.  Perhaps this can be addressed by allowing the Bill to go to Committee Stage for a more detailed perusal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-11-07a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014110700006#D00200"><p>I thank both Deputies for their contributions.  I will re-examine the useful suggestions made by the Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh.  Deputy Willie O'Dea spoke about training.  A total of 13,000 individual training days were delivered to staff in 2013.  We are actively working on this.  He also suggested that examples of the Department's decisions be published to provide a better understanding of the process.  I do not have the note to hand but, as far as I know, examples are published in the annual report.  I am saying that off the top of my head so I will need to go back and look at it.</p><p>  Although over 50% of cases are overturned on appeal, this does not mean the original decision was wrong in each case.  The Deputies know there are many occasions on which people come to our offices and we find out that information was left out of the appeal submission.  That shows the flexibility of the system.  There is no cut-off date for information to be submitted and it will be accepted at any stage.  That can add to the length of the decision.</p><p>  The Department is working hard to make improvements.  We are trying to implement better information gathering at the initial claim stage, which will lead to better decisions.  There should also be better explanations for the reasons behind decisions, which will make it easier for customers to understand the decisions and reduce unnecessary appeals.  We are actively working on that point.  Improvements in review processing times will be examined.  Decisions made and notifications to the citizen could be in better or clearer English, because people have different levels of literacy.  Official forms can be quite challenging for all of us.  I will look at that.</p><p>  Oral hearings are always granted when requested unless there is a compelling reason not to do so.</p><p>Applicants are always told they may get their file from the Department.  Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh touched on that in his contribution that people are aware of it but that sometimes even when they get the file, it is of no great assistance.  That was pointed out in the FLAC report also.  There are regular meetings of appeals officers to try to ensure continuity across the system.</p><p> It is in all our interests that we drive down the length of time this takes as much as possible.  Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh suggested that this go to a committee.  I do not think the proposal needs to go to Committee Stage but an exchange, possibly at a committee, would be interesting because many Deputies have experience, sometimes much more than myself, because of the volume of constituency queries received.  There is a wealth of experience which could be tapped into by the Department and sharing those experiences could mean a better and faster decision for the applicant.</p><p> I pay particular credit to the staff who work in the appeals office.  Since the recession, there has been an unprecedented increase in the number of appeals - I gave the figures earlier - and that reflects the high unemployment rate.  The number of appeals has reduced and the length of time it takes for an appeal to be heard has reduced significantly.  That is due to the civil servants who work in the Department.  I did not want to finish without mentioning the trojan work done by, and the level of change and reform in, the Department to bring the figure down by more than 50%, which Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh rightly pointed out.  That is exceptional at a time of grave economic difficulty.  I thank Deputy O'Dea for raising the issue and the Deputies for their contributions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-11-07a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014110700007#E00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his response and Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh for his support.  I join with the Minister of State in complimenting the staff in the Department of Social Protection and the appeals office, with whom it is always a pleasure to deal.  They are very courteous and helpful people.</p><p>  I will make a couple of general observations, none of which is directed personally at the Minister of State.  There was a reference in his speech to what is happening in the UK.  We are coming up to the 100th anniversary of 1916 and we have been an independent country for almost 100 years.  I think it was the late John Kelly who described this constant tendency to look at what is happening in the UK, of emulating the UK and of measuring ourselves against the UK as malignant &quot;Paddyism&quot;, with which I agree.</p><p>  The Minister of State was correct in saying the Bill was initiated on 13 March 2013 and that the situation was worse then.  I acknowledge the improvements that have been made and the extra staff who have been appointed but it highlights something else.  I recall in the run-up to the general election and during the preparation of the programme for Government great play being made of the so-called democratic revolution and how this D&aacute;il would be revolutionised.  One of the central parts of that revolution was that Deputies would be able to bring in their own legislation.  Normally, when a Deputy brings a Private Members' Bill before this House, it is to deal with a fairly immediate problem.  This Bill was proposed 20 months ago in a particular situation and it is now being introduced.  That says more about the claims that this particular parliamentary reform would be revolutionary than anything I could add.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-11-07a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014110700007#E00300"><p>In fairness, it reflects the hard work of Deputies in bringing forward Bills.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-11-07a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014110700007#E00400"><p>Of course it does but the point is that when they are introduced 20 months after they were produced, it says something about how the system has changed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-11-07a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014110700007#E00500"><p>A huge number of Bills have been brought in not only by the Deputy's party but by many others.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-11-07a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014110700007#E00600"><p>Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh made the point that 60 days may be too short a timeframe.  With the resources etc. available to the Department, that may very well be correct.  I am not caught up with 60 days.  What I am trying to deal with is the situation of some unfortunate who has been turned down for social welfare.  The statistics from the Department show that in more than 50% of cases, he or she may have been wrongly turned down.  If he or she goes to appeal, he or she will go to his or her local public representative to say that he or she was months applying for carer's allowance, disability allowance or whatever but now he or she has gone to appeal.  He or she will ask how much longer he or she must wait.  What I want to do is to give the person some element of certainty and that we can say it will not go beyond a certain period of time.  I still think that is valid.  Some of these people do not get supplementary allowance, so they will be literally living from hand to mouth.  What is being adjudicated on is whether the person is entitled to social welfare in this country.  That will be a very big thing for the person, probably the most important thing in his or her life.  We want some element of certainty to reduce that worry and stress and that a person will know that a decision will have to be made within a particular timeframe.</p><p>  The Minister of State mentioned that there are various steps in the process, with which I agree.  Perhaps the Department, as an alternative or on its own initiative, will produce a circular which fixes a maximum period of time for each process, for example, the process whereby the deciding officer must prepare his or her observations and send them on to the appeals office.  If there was a specific timeframe for each of those processes, it would certainly help.</p><p>  The Minister of State said that when somebody looks for an oral hearing, he or she will automatically get one but that has not been my experience.  I ask the Minister of State to look at that because if somebody requests an oral hearing, it should be automatic.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-11-07a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014110700007#E00700"><p>Will the Deputy send us an example?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-11-07a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014110700007#E00800"><p>I will do that.  I also ask the Minister of State to take on board Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh's very good suggestion that the right to a review be clearly set out because people have come to me who think they must go straight to the appeals office and they are amazed to hear they can actually go back to the deciding officer to have their case looked at again.  That is not clear on the form.  I am glad some of the administrative changes proposed by FLAC have taken place.</p><p>  While I will press the Bill, I nevertheless acknowledge the improvements that have been made.  I seriously urge the Department - this is not political - from the point of view of the people we represent, on whose behalf we speak, who are the poorest section of society and who are waiting for their social welfare entitlement to be adjudicated on, to continue the improvements made and to try, if at all possible, to bring some element of certainty for those people.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-11-07a.21" nospeaker="true" time="10:40:00" ><p>Question put.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-11-07a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1040" speakername="Michael Kitt" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014110700007#E01000"><p>In accordance with Standing Order 117A(4), the division is postponed until immediately after the Order of Business on Tuesday next, 11 November 2014.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-11-07a.23" nospeaker="true" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014110700008#F00100">Report of Joint Committee on Public Service Oversight and Petitions: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-11-07a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014110700008#F00300"><p>I move:<blockquote>That D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann shall consider the report of the Joint Committee on Public Service Oversight and Petitions entitled, Report on the Design and Layout of Ballot Papers used in the Seanad Referendum, October 2013, copies of which were laid before D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann on 12 June 2014.</blockquote>I apologise on behalf of Deputy P&aacute;draig Mac Lochlainn, Chairman of the committee, for not being present to begin the debate.<br/><br/>This is an interesting topic.  People do not take a lot of time to consider the issue of ballot papers and usually only see a ballot paper when it is put in front them when they go to cast their vote at an election or in a referendum.  However, a number of complaints were made to the committee about the Seanad referendum.  These complaints suggested the ballot papers had caused confusion.  One of the principles of democracy is clarity and the notion that people should be given a clear choice.  Therefore, the committee undertook to examine the ballot paper used in the referendum.  Expert witnesses came before the committee and explained how the ballot paper had been laid out, why the question had been framed in the way it was and offered alternatives that could have been used.  This is all laid out in the report.<br/><br/>I recall the debate we had prior to the referendum.  When I went to vote, I knew the decision I had taken and how I intended to vote.  However, as soon as I looked at the question on the ballot paper, I did a double take and had to ask myself if I was right and if I was voting in support of the Seanad or voting to abolish it.  It should have been simple to decide this, but the question had been framed in such a way that one had to ask oneself what one was voting for if one voted &quot;Yes&quot;.  Voting &quot;Yes&quot; meant one that was voting to abolish the Seanad and was not an affirmation of support for it.  The way the question had been framed caused me difficulty, but I was able to overcome that difficulty easily because I was a member of a political party and had a certain view and knew our slogan and choice.  However, the question caused confusion for many.  <br/><br/>What is even more confusing, not only in the referendum, is that the language used is complicated.  It is not plain English but gobbledygook.  It is even worse in Irish.  The language used is not the type used daily by people.  I am a fluent Irish speaker and know how to frame a question, but the question on the referendum papers was framed in such legalistic terms that people could not make head nor tail of it, unless they had a copy of the Constitution or another document in front of them which made it clear that the answer to the question was in the negative rather than the positive.<br/><br/>The report of the committee makes a number of suggestions, not in an argumentative but a helpful way.  I hope they will be taken on board by the Minister and an electoral commission that will consider how we frame questions on and the layout of ballot papers.  Ballot papers should be laid out clearly and if, as we had previously, we have two or three referendums on the same day, they should be in different colours.  People may remember that the headline on the ballot paper in the Seanad referendum was confusing.  <br/><br/>The Constitutional Convention also dealt with the issue of the electoral process and recommended having a permanent electoral commission.  I hope that when the Government takes the convention's report on board, it will fast track the establishment of an electoral commission, whether it needs to be included in the Constitution or if can be done otherwise.  Perhaps this recommendation might be implemented for any referendum we may have next spring.  I hope we will have learned the lessons to be learned from the Seanad referendum by the spring.  If, for example, we have the promised referendum on marriage equality next year, the proposition to be put must be made very clear in order that the public will be able to make an informed decision.  Often, the difficulty and inaccessibility of the language used in the Constitution cause people to shy away from turning out to vote in a referendum.  This may also be the reason there were so many spoilt votes previously.  The number of spoilt votes in the Seanad referendum is referred to in the report of the committee and perhaps it can be put down to people not understanding the question put or being confused by the language used.  However, in every election or referendum a spoilt vote is a way for people to make a political charge or express their dissatisfaction with the political system as a whole.  <br/><br/>Another issue is the failure of people to turn out to vote.  This is a serious concern in the case of referendums where it is proposed to change the Constitution which would bind the whole country for the future.  It is a concern that citizens are not as engaged as they should be.  <br/><br/>I encourage the Minister of State to take on board the points made in the report of the Joint Committee on Public Service Oversight and Petitions.  He should give a commitment that the next referendum process will be accessible.  The electoral commissions set up for referendums should ensure the language contained in the documentation is clear and simple.  Also, the type of print used should be larger.  Recently, the print used has been smaller, clearly because it is costlier to produce more pages.  The functional literacy level in the country is higher than in many other European Union countries, but if the print used on information documentation is reduced to 10 point or smaller, people will just throw it in the bin because it is just a block of text.  This makes no sense.  The documentation used is important.  Democracy should never be about cost; democracy costs money.  If it means an extra &euro;1 million to produce documentation that is clear and legible, so be it.  We must also put more thought into how ballot papers are laid out, their colour, the question put and the language used.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-11-07a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014110700008#F00400"><p>I apologise on behalf of the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government, Deputy Alan Kelly.  He had intended to take this debate.</p><p>However, unfortunately, due to a heavy diary commitment today, he could not make it.  Anyway, he will be taking on board the views made by Deputies as things progress.  I welcome the young people in the Gallery who are looking down at this debate.  Certainly, the future of democracy is important.  I accept the point made by Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh that democracy costs and that we have to put the information in a clear manner.</p><p> The joint committee report raises important issues that are of concern to all sides of the House.  I welcome the opportunity provided by today's debate to hear the views of Deputies on the recommendations of the committee.  These views will inform the future consideration of the issues raised in the report by my colleague, the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government, Deputy Alan Kelly, particularly in respect of the wording of the ballot paper for referendums.</p><p> The background to this report is the reported confusion of the electorate when they went to the polls in last year's referendum on the abolition of the Seanad.  When Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh was talking I pulled out the ballot paper to examine it.  It is clear more thought needs to be put into the ballot paper because it is easy to get confused, especially if a person is rushing in early or late in the evening and there are other referendums, European polls or local elections.  There is a need for clarity and the work the committee has done is welcome.</p><p> The joint committee received correspondence raising concerns about confusion among the electorate.  The committee agreed to examine the reported confusion in respect of the ballot paper, resulting in the report under consideration today.  Post-campaign research undertaken by the referendum commission reflected similar concerns.  This was the first occasion on which the referendum commission asked questions designed to probe possible voter confusion and ease of understanding of the ballot paper.  The commission recommended that further research in this area would be worthwhile and I acknowledge the work the committee has done in this regard.</p><p> Before reflecting on the recommendations in the report it would be useful to remind Deputies of the legal requirements in respect of ballot papers at referendums and the information that is available to voters as they head to the polls.  Section 24 of the Referendum Act 1994 provides that a referendum proposal must be stated on the ballot paper by citing the Short Title of the Bill, as passed by both Houses.  In addition, the ballot paper must comply with the format set out in Part 1 of the Second Schedule to the Act.  These requirements were met in the case of the Seanad referendum.  Section 24 also provides that the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government may, by order, following a resolution of both Houses, approve the order providing for the inclusion on the ballot paper of a heading indicative of the referendum proposal.  This was done on several occasions for referendums.  For example &quot;British-Irish Agreement&quot; and &quot;Treaty of Amsterdam&quot; were on the ballot papers for the two referendums held together in 1998.  In these cases the Titles of the respective Bills did not include any reference to the referendum proposals.  In the case of the Seanad referendum, however, the need for such a heading did not arise.  The Short Title of the Bill included a clear reference to the referendum proposal.  It read: Thirty-Second Amendment of the Constitution (Abolition of Seanad &Eacute;ireann) Bill 2013.  This has been the style of all constitutional amendment Bills passed by both Houses since 2009.</p><p> Provision of information to voters about the subject matter of referendums is crucial.  There is a sequence in the availability of information.  This starts with the publication of a constitutional amendment Bill and the debates in the Houses of the Oireachtas on the Bill.  The proposal for the amendment of the Constitution is final when the Bill is passed by the Oireachtas.  The debate and the Bill are accessible on the website.  Following that, information is provided by the independent referendum commission and a statement for the information of voters prescribed by the Oireachtas is sent to voters with their polling information card.  This relates to the point Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh made.  The information that came out was in block print.  This did not encourage people to read it and we need to reflect on that.  It would be interesting if Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh wrote to the commission to explain that.  We will have further debates next year.  Solid examples need to be shown because on occasion we can forget the lessons of the past because of the gaps between referendums.</p><p> Section 2 of the Referendum Act 1998 provides for the establishment of a referendum commission once a constitutional amendment Bill has been initiated in the D&aacute;il.  A commission has been established for every referendum held since 1998.  The statutory role of the commission includes the preparation and publication of one or more statements explaining the subject matter of the referendum and the text of the relevant Bill.  An independent guide drawn up by the commission is sent to each householder.  This was done, as usual, for the two referendums held in autumn 2013.  Research commissioned by the commission indicated that 72% of the public claimed to have read at least some of their guide for the 2013 referendum.  Some referendum commission reports over the years have drawn attention to the short period that was at the disposal of the commissions to carry out their functions.</p><p> Section 23(1) of the Referendum Act 1994 provides that a statement on the referendum proposal may be prescribed for the information of voters by resolution of each House.  A statement for the information of voters has been prescribed for every referendum held on the Constitution, including those held in autumn 2014.  This statement is sent to every person entitled to vote at a referendum in advance of voting.  It is also displayed in poster format at polling stations.  These information sources are the formal or official sources of information for constitutional referendums.  They are additional to the campaigns that might be run by political parties and third parties with an interest in the subject of the referendum.</p><p> The recommendations of the joint committee are set out in pages 14 and 16 of the report.  I will comment first on the recommendations concerning the modernisation of the legislation and the format in which a referendum question is put to the electorate.  Although the ballot paper at the Seanad referendum was in line with legal requirements, the reported confusion is of concern.  No one wants a situation where people are confused when they go to mark a ballot paper.  However, we need to take into account a number of factors when reflecting on changes or on the scope for improvement.  The committee's report recommends that the Minister examine the legislation with a view to modernising how a question is posed.  The committee noted that the ballot paper for referendums has remained largely unchanged since 1963 and that, in the same period, there have been significant changes to ballot papers for general elections.  The point that we should review the legislation to ensure that it is fit-for-purpose is accepted.  However, we need to guard against change for the sake of change.  In his foreword to the report the Chairman indicated that 14,335 people spoiled their vote in the Seanad referendum and that this was a matter that could cause great concern.  This is a concern but the evidence would seem to suggest that confusion about the ballot paper was not the only factor at play.  For example, the report also refers to the 45,424 invalid votes in the European elections.  This amounts to 2.67% of the poll compared to 1.16% in the case of the Seanad referendum and there was no reported confusion over the European Parliament ballot papers.  Likewise, the rate of invalid votes on the Court of Appeal referendum which was held on the same day as the Seanad referendum was 1.62%.  It is also noteworthy that statistics on referendum polls show that the rate of invalid votes rises when the electorate are asked to vote on more than one issue on the same day.  This has been the case where more than one referendum poll is taken on the one day or where a referendum poll is taken with a presidential election or with local or European elections.  The committee suggest that the legislation be examined with a view to modernising how a question is posed.  In this regard, we need consensus on Article 46.2 of the Constitution.</p><p>This article requires that every proposal for an amendment of the Constitution shall be initiated in D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann as a Bill and shall, having been passed, be submitted by referendum to the decision of the people.  It is a formal process.  We should not lose sight of the gravity of the decision voters are being asked to make in referendums.</p><p> Proposals to amend the Constitution can have far-reaching and profound consequences.  Voters are not simply being asked their opinion on a particular subject.  They are being asked to decide on amendments to the written Constitution that are set out in the relevant constitutional amendment Bill.  They are being asked to say &quot;yes&quot; or &quot;no&quot; to the proposal to amend the Constitution that is set out in the Bill passed by the Houses of the Oireachtas.</p><p> At a more general level, we also need to be aware that seeking a formula of language that eliminates the scope for any possible confusion is not an easy one.  The language is not very clear.  There is confusion between English and Irish.  We need to remove that kind of confusion.  We need to consider what has happened in other jurisdictions and how they have framed their referendums for example, the Scottish referendum on independence and how the language was framed on that ballot paper.  We also need to consider &quot;plain English&quot; and consult with literacy groups.</p><p> This was reflected in the July 2014 statement of Government priorities.  A similar recommendation made by the Convention on the Constitution was accepted by Government in April of this year.  The Government legislative programme for autumn 2014 provides for the publication of an Electoral Commission Bill in 2015.  I have been informed that work has started on that and it is on schedule.  I look forward to debating that with the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Public Service Oversight and Petitions.  We want to make this an inclusive democracy, to reduce the barriers that exist for various reasons, and ensure that when a referendum is put to the people the ballot paper is as clear and simple as possible, that the information supplied prior to the referendum is simple, clear and efficient, that the block text that Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh mentioned is done away with, and the information is accessible to everybody.  We must consider modern technology.  We have developed good websites for previous referendums.  We must consider how to communicate with citizens to ensure they are better informed and better able to make a decision.  It is a simple yes or no on a ballot paper.  Confusion does not help.  Multiple questions do add to the confusion.  I welcome the report.  It will be an important element in the discussion of future legislation.  I thank the committee for its hard work and look forward to hearing Deputies' contributions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-11-07a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/998" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014110700010#H00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his comments and look forward to working with him and the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government, Deputy Alan Kelly on implementing as many of the recommendations as possible.  As I noted in the foreword to this report the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade, Deputy Charles Flanagan, following the Seanad referendum expressed concern about voter confusion at the Seanad ballot paper.  The matter of 14,355 people spoiling their vote in a referendum to abolish the Seanad should cause great concern.  However, we need to recall that there were on that day two referendums, on whether to abolish Seanad &Eacute;ireann and whether to establish a Court of Appeal and make other changes to the courts system.  Was there confusion because we had multi-referendums on the same day?  The joint committee considered Deputy Flanagan&rsquo;s concerns and agreed that apart from the issue of multi-referendums on the same day two other issues could also have had an impact: first, the design, text and language of the ballot paper; and second, the question, was to all intents and purposes, a double negative.</p><p>  The Department of Environment, Community and Local Government is responsible for the various legislative codes dealing with the conduct of elections and referendums.  So in advance of meeting the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government, the joint committee wrote asking him to address the problems in the design, text and language of the ballot papers.  The then Minister, now Commissioner Hogan, replied and included a report prepared by the franchise section at the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government on the questions raised.  The joint committee considered that report which crystallised the issues in four main themes, as follows: that the format of the ballot paper has remained largely unchanged since 1963; the acceptance of the need for research and the type of comparisons used in that research; holding multi-referendums on the same day; the proofing of the wording in advance of its being put on a ballot paper; and whether the question always be put in the positive when the intention is to secure a negative.</p><p>  I have a knowledge of parliamentary procedure and practice and D&aacute;il Standing Orders.  If we as parliamentarians err, we can always rely on the helpful guidance of the Ceann Comhairle.  I am sure, however, that Members have experienced confusion in voting when the decision required is in the negative but the question is always put in the positive.  I still have not figured out how to vote during Committee and Report Stages of a Bill.  It is an archaic legalistic system.  Maybe it is necessary here, and we can get assistance but it can be very confusing.  If this causes confusion to politicians who vote on an almost daily basis it is easy to understand how in the Seanad referendum many of the public were confused.</p><p>  The joint committee was advised that the format of the ballot paper has remained largely unchanged since 1963, the same year that RT&Eacute; television went on air.  If the same pace of change applied to RT&Eacute; as has applied to the format of ballot papers, the Irish public would still be looking at a test card hoping that in the future, or in the new measurement of time when Irish Water is sorted, there would be a one-channel national television service broadcasting for four to five hours per day in black and white and colour TV would be for the next millennium.  Today we are a far cry from 1963: we have the Internet, Twitter, YouTube, facebook and smartphones that can have apps by the million yet the auld ballot paper stays the same.  Are we trying to pretend that the ballot paper is some new media form of Oscar Wilde&rsquo;s picture of Dorian Grey? </p><p>  In this report a number of recommendations are made and there are two key recommendations: first, the members have agreed to revisit this report within the next six to 12 months to invigilate and examine the progress made in the implementation of the recommendations, and second, the joint committee recommends a permanent electoral commission be established with a mandate to conduct research, which is vital.  This report refers to 14,355 people spoiling their vote in a referendum to abolish the Seanad.  However, in the May 2014 European elections there were 17,258 spoiled votes in the Midlands-North-West constituency; 6,368 spoiled votes in the Dublin constituency; and 21,798 spoiled votes in the South constituency.  This is a total of 45,424 spoiled votes in an election for the European Parliament.  In the local elections held on the same day there were over 19,400 spoiled votes.  There should be concern at such a level of spoiled votes.  Research is necessary and must be undertaken within a permanent electoral commission established with a mandate to conduct research and it must be reported on to D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann.</p><p> As practising, professional politicians we should always be pushing for change.  There should always be examination, but one cannot and should not make policy decisions without information, which we get from research.  I thank the Minister of State for his response on behalf of the Government and look forward to developing this.  When we finally get people to the voting booths, they are confused.  The wider issue of voter turnout needs to be examined.  That is another day's debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-11-07a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1038" speakername="Eamonn Maloney" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014110700011#J00200"><p>I thank Deputy Mac Lochlainn and the others who compiled this report.  It is interesting, and nothing much was left out.  It is very specific, given the subject matter, about both ballot papers.  It firmly states, with regard to the level of confusion about the Seanad ballot paper, that 55% of those who voted found it quite or very difficult to understand.  On the Court of Appeal ballot paper, 47% of people who, I presume, cast their votes and were surveyed found the ballot paper quite or very difficult.  </p><p>  The question of what is the correct thing to do about referendums was raised.  I am not the only one who followed what happened in the Scottish referendum.  It is my contention that if what happened in this referendum had happened in Scotland, there would have been a second referendum.  This would and could not have been tolerated.  People who cast their votes on two ballot papers, each dealing with a single issue, are smart enough.  We are not back in the Stone Age.  Irish people have sufficient common sense to be able to work those things out.  The Parliament caused this confusion; about that there is no doubt.  There is no point in pretending otherwise.</p><p>  The Minister of State referred to the young people in the Visitors' Gallery.  They were probably scratching their heads and wondering how the people who are running the country cannot even produce a ballot paper.  We did produce one, but we sent people all over the shop.  Everything about it was wrong.  Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh is perfectly correct about the typesetting and so on.  Mischievous people would say it could have been done deliberately.  I do not wish to end up in jail so I will not express an opinion like that, but a lot of people outside the House have their own opinions.  </p><p>  We have tolerated the outcome of the vote, but the Scots would not have, and I have no doubt whatsoever that Scotland would have rerun the referendum.  I am happy to express my point of view.  Let us be honest.  Some people do not want to hear this, but during the referendum campaigns a lot of people said one thing in public while lobbying in private for the retention of the Seanad.  I have no doubt about that whatsoever.  It happened across all parties, mine included.  The political establishment wanted to retain the Seanad and I do not need to go into the reasons for that.  People can work it out themselves.  </p><p>  With regard to the things that caused confusion among the voters surveyed, I alluded to two figures, but it gets worse than that.  Deputy Mac Lochlainn highlighted the number of spoiled votes.  The figure is unbelievable, given the fact that 61% of the people stayed at home.  Things have changed a lot in terms of the public's perception of politicians in this country.  We still ask what the turnout was, but I do not do so any more.  I talk about the other figure because it is larger.  People say how precious the Constitution and the Upper House are, but if they are so precious why did they not turn out to vote?  </p><p>  The report is very good and a necessary part of the process.  In fairness to Deputy Charles Flanagan, now the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade, he was the first to acknowledge what had happened.  Well, I think he was the first; no doubt Deputy Mac Lochlainn will correct me.  I should have done the same myself.  If you are beaten you are beaten - go on home and have a cup of tea.  Deputy Flanagan was spot on, and he initiated the whole process.</p><p>  Having these discussions is an important part of a democracy.  That is how we learn.  I do not know how much we have learned, but we are not Scots so we will carry on into the future.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-11-07a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1198" speakername="Michael Fitzmaurice" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014110700011#J00300"><p>I concur with what other Members said about referendums, especially the Seanad referendum.  I remember that when I walked out of the booth that day I was not sure whether I had put the tick in the right box.  Something that should have been straightforward was very complicated.  </p><p>  When one fills out the forms to run as an Independent candidate in an election, one is categorised as non-party.  Ballot papers have a blank square beside such candidates in place of a party logo, which confuses many people who must figure out where to put the &quot;X&quot;.  This problem has been brought to my attention by people from all over the country.  We have to have a different system, because some people vote for Independent candidates, party candidates or a mixture of both, but they do not know for whom they are voting.  The current system will cause problems.  There will be a very tight election some day, votes will be queried and some will not be included because people ticked the wrong box.</p><p>  National schools are often used for voting.  When I was on a board of management I had to watch the pounds, shillings and pence.  I understand a school receives &euro;15 for the day, which would not even cover the heating cost.  Changing the voting location needs to be considered.  Most places around the country have community centres, many of which are vacant when elections are held.  </p><p>  The Register of Electors is another problem.  People have been put on or taken off it and do not know how it works.  An accurate register needs to be introduced, because in the last by-election people who should have been on the register were not, while others who had died six months or a year ago were still on it.</p><p>We need a root and branch analysis to make it more efficient.  My first point is that we should consider moving polling stations out of national schools and using community centres instead and my second is that one can still write "Independent" or whatever else in order that the box is filled in order to save confusion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-11-07a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1040" speakername="Michael Kitt" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014110700012#K00200"><p>We need another report to deal with those issues.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-11-07a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014110700012#K00300"><p>I concur with the Deputy in his final remarks.  It is wrong to disturb children during the school week.  We need to move polling stations, if possible.  I acknowledge that this is not the subject of the report, nor can it be dealt with in this debate, but I echo the Deputy's remarks.  It would make common sense to move polling stations out of primary and secondary schools, where possible, because of the impact on the school week and also on parents who need to organise child care for that day.  I am listening to the Deputy's point and concur with him.</p><p>  The Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government has sought legal advice on modernising the language used on the ballot paper.  It has written to the National Adult Literacy Association to seek its views on the current format of the ballot paper from a plain English perspective.  Its views will assist in the consideration of the committee's recommendations.</p><p>  I say to Deputy Eamonn Maloney that I am certain that I put my tick in the right box on the day of the Seanad referendum.  </p><p>  I apologise on behalf of the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government who was unable to attend.  The transcript of the contributions made to the debate will be available.  I will convey to the Minister the spirit of the contributions because it does not always come across when reading it.</p><p>  I agree with Deputy Eamonn Maloney on the question of voter turnout and that there is a job of work to be done in that regard.  It is noticeable that the turnout has been lower at every election.  It is a problem which needs to be examined in detail by others, as well as by Members.  We hold democracy dear, but, increasingly, citizens are not bothering to vote.  We should not blame them; rather, we should examine what we are doing.  These concerns are shared by all parties.</p><p>  I thank Deputies for their contributions and will ensure we will have that discussion with the Minister next week.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-11-07a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1102" speakername="Brian Stanley" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2014110700012#K00500"><p>The recent Seanad referendum showed that people could be confused very easily by the way in which ballot papers were presented.  The survey showed that 13% of those who had voted "Yes" to abolish the Seanad had thought they were voting to retain it.  A total of 6% of those who had voted "No" said they wanted to abolish it.  One could argue flippantly that such errors were balanced out, but there is a case to be made for ensuring clarity in any proposal put.  This could be achieved by including in the ballot paper an explanation of the purpose of the referendum.  I suggest the Seanad referendum ballot paper could have included the simple question: "Do you want to abolish the Seanad?"  The Taoiseach commented after the referendum that the question on the ballot paper had caused confusion among voters.</p><p>  I am not convinced that the layout of the ballot paper was responsible for the number of spoiled votes at 14,255.  Presumably, most of these votes were spoiled by placing an &quot;X&quot; in the two boxes.  However, it is difficult to explain why anyone would do this in a referendum where the choice is between &quot;Yes&quot; and &quot;No&quot;.  A minority of the spoiled votes included personal insults against candidates or their families or other forms of abuse.  I have heard about a ballot paper on which were drawn pictures of characters from &quot;The Simpsons&quot;, but I am unsure how one would decide whether a preference had been expressed between, for example, Mayor Quimby or Mayor Moe.  However, that is another day's work.</p><p>  I refer to the total of 45,424 spoiled votes in the European Parliament elections last May, a very significant number, and 19,400 in the local elections, which seem to indicate that the layout of the referendum ballot paper was not the main factor in the number of spoiled votes in that case.  The proportion of spoiled votes in the Seanad referendum was 1.16% compared to 1.14% in the local elections; they are almost identical.  The anomaly is the much higher proportion of spoiled votes in the European Parliament elections, 2.7%, even though the number of votes cast was only 50,000 fewer than in the local elections.  It could be the case that people do not treat the European Parliament elections as seriously as other elections.  I am interested in knowing the contributory factors, given that thousands were quite capable of filling in properly the ballot papers for the local elections but not the European Parliament elections.  It could be assumed that in the case of the latter the spoiled votes were, in the main, deliberate.</p><p>  There is a case to be made for a change in the layout of the ballot paper, given that it has remained the same since 1963.  I suggest the proposition be printed on the ballot paper rather than citing the relevant section of the Bill.  I commend the positive decision taken ten years ago to put candidates' photographs on the ballot paper.  It was a great idea and has been of assistance.</p><p>  The higher than average number of spoiled votes in referendums is significant.  A random sample of referendums such as the Lisbon One and Lisbon Two referendums, the 2002 referendum on the protection of life and the divorce referendum in 1997, shows that the level of spoiled ballots ranged from between 0.33% to 0.53%.  The only referendum in which there was a higher number of spoiled votes was the one on judges, when the number was 2.11%.  I suggest the layout of that ballot paper should be examined to see what changes are needed.  There is merit in the suggestion that ballot papers be proofed.</p><p>  The report refers to extensive research on the wording used carried out in Scotland prior to the recent referendum on Scottish independence.  I refer to the question which was simple and to the point: &quot;Should Scotland be an independent country?&quot;  This is preferable to quoting sections of a Bill.  It is better to put a straight question.  It is difficult to imagine how such a direct question could be confusing for any voter.  The number of spoiled votes in the Scottish referendum was lower than 0.09%, not even 0.1%.  This evidence supports my proposition that the question on the ballot paper be phrased in a similar manner.  I suggest a question such as: &quot;Should the Seanad be abolished?&quot;  This would require legislative change.  </p><p>  I support Deputy Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh's proposal that there be a permanent electoral commission, which proposal was approved by the committee, with a remit covering how information is distributed and other election issues.  I believe the Government has plans in that regard.  The Constitutional Convention also dealt with the matter.  The way forward is to have an independent commission to deal with all electoral matters.  </p><p>  I reiterate that having a simple, straightforward question on the ballot paper is preferable.  Members exist in a bubble in that we are familiar with legislation and legislative language, but members of the public prefer to be asked straight questions.  These matters need to be reviewed because of the decline in the numbers voting in referendums and elections, which is a concern.</p><p>  Other speakers referred to the need to engage young people in the democratic process.  A number of referendums are planned for next year.  I propose that everyone over the age of 16 years be given the right to vote in future referendums and elections.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-11-07a.36" nospeaker="true" time="11:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2014-11-07a.37" nospeaker="true" time="11:30:00" ><p>The D&aacute;il adjourned at 11.30 a.m. until 2 p.m. on Tuesday, 11 November 2014.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>