<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.1" nospeaker="true" time="11:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.2" nospeaker="true" time="11:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Ceann Comhairle i gceannas ar 11.30 a.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.6" nospeaker="true" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100003#A00100">D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann and Seanad &Eacute;ireann: Sitting in Joint Committee - Exchange of views with Mr. Michel Barnier, Chief Negotiator of the Taskforce for the Preparation and Conduct of Negotiations with the United Kingdom</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.7" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1371" speakername="Se&aacute;n &Oacute; Feargha&iacute;l" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100003#A00200"><p>A Chomhghleacaithe, t&aacute; f&aacute;ilte is fiche romhaibh go l&eacute;ir chuig an gcomhshu&iacute; speisialta seo den D&aacute;il agus den Seanad chun pl&eacute; a dh&eacute;anamh ar cheann de na d&uacute;shl&aacute;in pholait&iacute;ochta is m&oacute; at&aacute; roimh an oile&aacute;n seo i l&aacute;thair na huaire, agus go deimhin, roimh an Eoraip ar fad, is &eacute; sin, an R&iacute;ocht Aontaithe a bheith ag f&aacute;g&aacute;il an Aontais Eorpaigh.  On behalf of both myself and the Cathaoirleach, I wish to welcome the Members of both Houses and Mr. Michel Barnier to this sitting in joint committee.  We are here for an exchange of views with Mr. Barnier, who, as Members will know, is the chief negotiator of the task force for the preparation and conduct of negotiations with the United Kingdom.  We will now go into committee.  Accordingly, I invite Mr. Barnier to take his seat in the Chamber.</p>  <p>  Monsieur Barnier, au nom de tous les Membres du D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann et du Seanad &Eacute;ireann, soyez le bienvenu ici aujourd'hui.  Nous sommes ravis et honor&eacute;s que vous ayez accept&eacute; notre invitation &agrave; vous adresser aux chambres de l'Oireachtas, r&eacute;unies en s&eacute;ance commune.  The decision by the United Kingdom last year to withdraw from the European Union will have a profound effect on Europe and its citizens but it also raises a number of specific and important issues that are unique to Ireland.  For instance, concerns have been raised about its impact on Northern Ireland and the peace process as well as its impact on the common travel area between Ireland and the United Kingdom.  Since the formal notification on 29 March 2017, of the UK&rsquo;s intention to withdraw, preparations for the start of the negotiations have intensified.  As Members will be aware, the European Council agreed guidelines for the first phase of negotiations on 29 April 2017.  Last week the European Commission published its draft negotiating directives.</p>  <p>  Our exchange of views today is therefore very timely and we hope it will contribute positively to the preparations for the negotiations.  Let me also say I firmly believe today&rsquo;s sitting demonstrates how national parliaments can contribute effectively to public debate on matters of concern to the Union, which of course is one of the principal objectives of Article 12 of the treaty.</p>  <p>  Mr. Barnier, we are conscious of the very challenging road ahead.  We wish you and your task force well in your important work and it is our sincere hope that an agreement can be reached that protects the principles of the Union and the interests of its member states while maintaining a strong relationship with the United Kingdom.  With those few thoughts, I invite you now to address us.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.8" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Michel Barnier" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100003#A00300"><p>I thank the Ceann Comhairle for his perfect French.  Mr. Speakers, Taoiseach, Members of the Houses of the Oireachtas, a chairde, I am very happy and honoured to address both Houses of the Oireachtas and to greet you, as the representatives of the people of Ireland, in all your political diversity.</p><p>I take this honour as a responsibility: the responsibility to listen to all those who will be affected by the decision of the UK to leave the European Union; the responsibility to listen to your concerns, build our positions together and negotiate in our common interest; and the responsibility to explain that we need each other - that Ireland is stronger in the Union, and the EU is stronger with Ireland.<br/><br/>Your country has had deep historical, cultural and intellectual ties to continental Europe for many centuries.  In the 16th, 17th and 18th centuries, Irish colleges were set up around Europe - from Madrid, where I was yesterday, to Leuven, Paris, Rome and Prague.  They contributed to writing the history of Ireland and the history of Europe, and they spread Irish culture to the Continent.<br/><br/>Centuries later, in 1972, the people of Ireland massively voted to take part in the European project.  At that time I was 21 - that was the last century.  France had a referendum on the accession of Ireland, the UK, Denmark and Norway.  It was my very first vote.  I campaigned for a &quot;Yes&quot; vote.  For the UK's accession, back then, voting &quot;Yes&quot; was not so easy for a member of the French Gaullist Party.  I did it with my full heart and I never regretted it.  I regret that Brexit is happening now.  I would have liked to have seen the UK staying in Europe, with Ireland and all the 26 other member states, but we are where we are.<br/><br/>Since 1972, we have accomplished great things together.  The European Union has helped Ireland become what it is today, and Ireland has complemented and strengthened our Union.  The Irish people are known as hard-working and open minded.  They saw EU membership as a chance to modernise their economy and society.  We see this now in innovative companies and in the creation of new jobs.  Investors see Ireland as being central in the European market, not peripheral.  We see it across Irish cities, towns and villages.  They have been enriched by fellow Europeans who have come here to work, study, travel and live.  <br/><br/>As Seamus Heaney said to mark the enlargement of the EU in 2004:</p><blockquote>So on a day when newcomers appear<br /><br />Let it be a homecoming and let us speak ...<br /><br />Move lips, move minds and make new meanings flare.</blockquote><p>Ireland has welcomed, like you were welcomed 30 years earlier.<br/><br/>Ladies and gentlemen, for 44 years, Irish people have shaped the Union.  They have helped turn Europe into a more open and innovative Continent.  Ireland's first European Commissioner, Patrick Hillery, played a major role in improving equality between women and men, before serving as your President.  Another Irish Commissioner, Peter Sutherland, supported the creation of the Single Market and he established the ERASMUS programme - bringing young Europeans closer together for 30 years now and showing what free movement of people really means.  Today, Phil Hogan is in charge of developing what is the Union's most complete economic policy, the Common Agricultural Policy.  Speakers, ladies and gentlemen, for my part, I am proud to have been Minister with responsibility for the farmers and fishermen in my own country.<br/><br/>Some, in large countries with imperial pasts like my own, seem to think that the EU makes them smaller.  This is simply not true.  In smaller countries, people are often more aware that being part of the EU increases influence and opportunities, and that being part of a common project and identity does not prevent a country from keeping its own identity and making a name for itself in the world, as Enda Kenny reminded us all in his excellent St. Patrick's Day speech in Washington.<br/><br/>Pooling national sovereignty increases our European sovereignty.  Because they are part of the EU, citizens of all our countries can study, work and settle down in another member state and be treated like nationals.  European consumers can access high quality food and agricultural products from across the EU because they all meet strict standards.  Suppliers do not have to worry about border checks.  Because they are part of the EU, citizens travelling to another EU country will soon be able to call without roaming charges, as if they were calling from home.<br/><br/>Airlines, from whatever member state they come, can offer direct flights between any two EU airports.  They can rely on our open skies agreement with the US.  The EU has made travel easier.  Irish airlines have been among the first to take advantage of these benefits and have profoundly changed the market.  I experienced it first hand myself when I flew to Dublin last night on a rather well known low cost carrier - there was still no coffee but there was a little bit more seat space than before.<br/><br/>Honourable Members, being together makes us all stronger.  Because we are part of the EU, businesses can trade goods without customs duties and documentation requirements are very simple.  As part of the EU's Single Market, companies can rely on fair competition and a level playing field.  Because the EU has consistently put in place high levels of environmental protection, citizens enjoy cleaner air and water.  Governments can resist a race to the bottom and fight climate change more effectively together.<br/><br/>EU companies have privileged access to 60 foreign markets such as South Korea, Vietnam and recently Canada - thanks to the free trade agreements negotiated at EU level.  Banks, insurance or investment funds can provide services throughout the Single Market, based on their establishment here in Dublin - thanks to the so-called passporting rights.  <br/><br/>Because they are part of the EU, judges can rely on the European arrest warrant.  It ensures the rapid treatment of requests for surrendering suspected criminals from another member state to bring them to justice.  Because they are part of the EU, universities receive funding for research and innovation.  They form one of the widest academic networks in the world.  <br/><br/>Speakers and honourable Members, as a Union member, this is what we enjoy, and this is what a member state loses when it leaves the Union; but let me also be clear: Brexit will come at a cost also to us, the 27.</p><p>I am fully aware that some member states will be more affected than others.  As chief negotiator, my objective is to reach a fair deal, one that defends the interests of the entire EU but also of individual member states.  </p>  <p>  Due to its historical and geographical ties with the UK, its shared Border and strong economic links, Ireland is in a unique position.  With the fall of sterling, Brexit is already having an impact on the value of Irish exports to the UK, particularly in the agrifood sector.  Many in Ireland fear the return of tensions in the North.  Today, in front of these two Houses, I want to reassure the Irish people that in these negotiations, Ireland's interests will be the European Union's interests.  We are in these negotiations together and a united EU will be there for Ireland.  </p>  <p>  Tomorrow I will travel to the Border with Northern Ireland and will meet farmers and workers in a dairy co-operative.  I want to learn from them and listen to their concerns about how they are affected by Brexit.  Some might be concerned about exports to the UK or the return of customs checks at the Border while others might fear a return to the instability of the past.  In Northern Ireland, lifting the Border took time and it was only 15 years ago that checkpoints and controls totally disappeared, thanks to the Good Friday Agreement that ended decades of violence.  I was the European Commissioner in charge of the PEACE programme and I have not forgotten my conversations with Mr. John Hume and Mr. David Trimble on that point.  I understand the European Union's role in strengthening dialogue in Northern Ireland and in supporting the Good Friday Agreement.  European integration helped to remove borders that once existed on maps and in minds.  Now, Brexit changes the external borders of the EU but I will work with Ireland to avoid a hard Border.  </p>  <p>  The UK's departure from the EU will have consequences.  Together, we have a duty to speak the truth in that regard.  Customs controls are part of EU border management.  They protect the Single Market, as well as our food safety and standards.  However, as I have said many times, nothing in these negotiations should put peace at risk.  This was recognised by the 27 Heads of State and Government two weeks ago.  They were very clear that the Good Friday Agreement must be respected in all of its dimensions.  I also made it very clear that the Border issue will be one of my three priorities for the first phase of the negotiations, together with citizens' rights and the financial settlement.  We must make sufficient progress on these points before we start discussing the future of our relationship with the UK.  The sooner this happens, the better.  </p>  <p>  If the conditions are right, a close partnership with the UK is in everybody's interests, particularly Ireland's.  Currently, Ireland exports 14% of its goods and 20% of its services to the UK, which is twice the EU average.  The agriculture and energy sectors are fully interconnected on the island of Ireland.  Of course, such facts must be put in perspective.  Before Ireland&rsquo;s accession to the EU in 1973, the UK accounted for over 50% of Irish trade.  Today, Ireland exports much more to the other EU countries than to the UK and the Single Market is a key asset for its financial and pharmaceutical industries.  Nevertheless, the specific issues that Ireland faces deserve all our attention.  Ireland shares a land border with the UK and most of its trade to the EU goes through the UK.  This is why I engaged with the D&aacute;il and Seanad, the Government and its administrators, as well as all the Irish Members of the European Parliament immediately after taking up my position.  Ireland has done remarkable preparatory work and we must use our combined strength and work together to deliver solutions.</p>  <p>  I want to listen to the concerns of the Irish people but I also want to pass on a message of hope and determination.  For all the problems it creates, Brexit also reminds us of what the EU has built together, what each of us enjoys as EU citizens and how we can further improve the European project.  The EU is not perfect; we know that.  President Juncker put it candidly on the occasion of Europe Day this week.  There are lessons to draw from the crisis and not only in Ireland.  There are lessons to draw from Brexit and from the rising scores of populist parties in many countries, including mine.  Let us not confuse public opinion with populism.  We should listen to people's feelings and respond with policy change.  This is how we will fight populism.  I am convinced that Ireland will play a major role in these changes, as a centre for innovation, a strong and sustainable agrifood producer, a bridge across the Atlantic and as a supporter of the future relationship that we need to build with the UK.  </p>  <p>  Our objective is clear - we want these negotiations to succeed.  I want us to reach a deal.  The UK has been a member of the EU for 44 years and it should remain a close partner.  We will need to negotiate a bold, ambitious but also fair free trade agreement.  We will also need the same ambition for our research and innovation networks and for the fight against climate change, as well as in foreign policy, international co-operation and development.  Almost 27 years ago, Nelson Mandela spoke in this very room, just a few months after he was released from jail.  He praised Ireland's leadership within the European Community to maintain strong pressure on the apartheid system in South Africa.  Tomorrow, our international partners should be able to turn to the EU and the UK and find in them strong and united advocates of our shared European values.  We also need the same ambition in the field of our internal and external security, whether it is the fight against terrorism, the exchange of information, the fight against hybrid threats or cybersecurity. </p>  <p>  If we put things in the right order, if we negotiate with mutual respect, without any aggression or naivety and are open to finding solutions, there is no reason our strong Europe cannot maintain a strong relationship with the UK.  </p><p>Dear Speakers and honourable Members, I have been a national parliamentarian for more than 17 years, both in the National Assembly and the French Senate.  I will now listen carefully to the views of the Taoiseach and of all party leaders.  In these negotiations and the public debate that now starts you have, as a national parliament, an essential role to play together with the European Parliament and civil society.  That is why I have been so honoured by your invitation to address the two Houses of the Parliament of Ireland.  Go raibh m&iacute;le maith agaibh.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1371" speakername="Se&aacute;n &Oacute; Feargha&iacute;l" time="11:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100006#D00200"><p>Merci, Monsieur Barnier, and thank you for that valuable overview of the major challenge that lies ahead for us all.  I call the Taoiseach.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1245" speakername="Enda Kenny" time="11:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100006#D00300"><p>I am pleased to address the Houses today in the presence of Michel Barnier.  Thank you for your fine contribution, Michel.</p>  <p>  I thank him for his statement in which he outlined the complexities of the Brexit negotiations and for his acknowledgement of their importance for Europe and of course for Ireland.</p>  <p>  Michel Barnier is a longstanding friend of this country, not just as a leading French politician and Minister, but also as a European Commissioner.  Indeed, his time as Commissioner for Regional Policy gave him a particular insight into the unique circumstances on the island of Ireland, which will be central to the talks ahead.</p>  <p>  I also want to thank him sincerely for his willingness to engage with Ireland since his appointment as head of the Commission Brexit task force last July.  This is his second visit to Dublin since that appointment but we have also met on other occasions, including on my visits to Brussels in February and March, and at the European Council.</p>  <p>  Michel and his colleagues in the Brexit task force have been more than co-operative and accessible to our Ministers and our senior officials.  I know that he has also been open to a range of other important stakeholders from Ireland.  I thank him for this engagement.  The challenges for this country arising from Brexit are extremely serious; and it is essential that all those affected have the opportunity to make their voices heard.</p>  <p>  This has also been the approach of the Government here.  Along with ongoing sectoral analysis across Departments, we have engaged widely with industry and civic society, holding almost 280 separate meetings.  The all-island civic dialogue, which I convened with the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade, Deputy Flanagan, has included 16 sectoral events and two plenary meetings, with more than 1,200 delegates representing industries and organisations from across the country.  This kind of consultation has informed our positions on the negotiations, and enabled us to publish our thinking in a comprehensive Government document last week.</p>  <p>  Events have moved on quickly since Prime Minister May formally notified the European Union of the UK's intention to leave.  The European Council agreed the EU negotiating guidelines on 29 April and on 3 May, the European Commission proposed its draft negotiating directives, which build on the guidelines and provide more detail on the issues to be addressed.</p>  <p>  The extensive preparation by member states, the EU institutions and Mr. Barnier's task force meant that the guidelines were agreed very quickly.  This was by no means a given.  We know just how complicated and serious the issues are for Europe as a whole and particularly for Ireland.</p>  <p>  For over two years, the Government has been analysing the issues and engaging with sectors across this island to identify our main areas of concern and to develop our priorities.  Some of these have been referred to here by Michel Barnier.  These are the protection of the Good Friday Agreement and the peace process, including by avoiding a hard Border; to retain the common travel area; to minimise the impact on our economy and to work for a positive future for the European Union.</p>  <p>  We have also been extremely active at political and official level in engaging with our EU partners and the EU institutions, with a view to highlighting and explaining the significant implications for Ireland arising from Brexit, and the need to take account of our particular concerns in the negotiations ahead.  Indeed, since the UK referendum last June, we have had over 400 engagements on Brexit with our EU partners.</p>  <p>  In all these meetings, we have explained the background and context of the Northern Ireland peace process and emphasised the need to avoid the re-imposition of a hard Border on the island of Ireland.  As I have stated previously, this is a political challenge and we will have to be both flexible and imaginative to deal with it.</p>  <p>  Thanks to this strategic and patient work, and the understanding and support of our European partners, I am pleased that Ireland's specific concerns - Mr. Barnier has mentioned this specifically - and the unique circumstances that apply here are fully acknowledged in these guidelines.  Supporting and protecting the achievements, the benefits and commitments of the peace process; avoiding a hard Border; and protecting the common travel area will now be addressed as part of the withdrawal negotiations.  The guidelines provide an excellent basis for the negotiations.  It was crucial that we got this right from the start and again, I would like to thank Mr. Barnier for his role in making that happen.</p>  <p>  In more general terms, we are pleased with the tone of the guidelines which is open and constructive, while nevertheless clearly and firmly outlining the EU's objectives and principles.  They highlight the importance of getting clarity in respect of EU citizens' rights, a key issue across member states and important in terms of providing certainty for people and for families.</p>  <p>  The approach to the sensitive question of the United Kingdom's financial liabilities is also welcome.  It is only reasonable that the United Kingdom be asked to honour the commitments it entered into as a member state of the European Union.  Mr. Barnier's approach to this is sensible, to focus first on the principles and methodology before considering the numbers or the structure of payments that might be involved.</p>  <p>  Importantly from our perspective, the guidelines acknowledge the need for transitional arrangements.  This will be crucial in order to provide a level of continuity and certainty for our citizens and businesses.  As Ireland stands to be more affected than any other member state by the departure of the UK, we believe it is necessary to begin work as soon as possible - and I am glad you referred to this - on scoping out the future EU-UK relationship.  I am pleased therefore that the guidelines acknowledge that the shape of the future relationship can be considered once the European Council, that is, the Heads of State and Government of the 27 member states, agrees that "sufficient progress" has been made on the withdrawal issues.  This phased approach is also a sensible and pragmatic way forward.</p>  <p>  From Ireland's perspective, our objective is for a close and positive future relationship with the UK, and we are pleased therefore that the guidelines indicate the EU wants an ambitious agreement, not just in economic terms but also in areas such as security.  We will continue to work with partners to achieve such an outcome.</p>  <p>  Consequently, I welcome the European Council guidelines from a substantive perspective and that their principles and approach have been carried forward into the draft negotiating directives.  I appreciate the thorough preparatory work carried out by Mr. Barnier and his task force, as well as the European Council team and other EU partners, whose willingness to listen to us, to listen to our story and to acknowledge our unique and special circumstances has brought us to this point.  The outcome is an endorsement of the approach by Government and a clear recognition of the specific challenges we face.</p>  <p>  The Government has robustly defended the Good Friday Agreement process throughout these negotiations so far, making clear that, as a legally-binding, international treaty, it provides a unique political and constitutional framework on the island of Ireland.  We know that it was vital to provide reassurance that Brexit does not in any way undermine any provision of the Good Friday Agreement.</p><p>In that context, we secured an acknowledgement that, in the event of change in the constitutional status of Northern Ireland, brought about in accordance with the principles of the Good Friday Agreement and the principle of consent, the entire territory of such a united Ireland would be part of the EU.  I have been consistent in my view that now is not the time to have such a referendum on Irish unity and that the conditions set out in the Good Friday Agreement for the calling of a Border poll do not currently exist.  However, the statement agreed by the Heads of State and Government of the 27 EU member states, which will be recorded in the minutes of the European Council, was hugely important in order to dispel any doubt or uncertainty that the UK exit from the EU would negatively impact on this crucial constitutional provision of the Good Friday Agreement.</p> <p> With the EU guidelines now adopted, including the language about our unique concerns, the Government last week published a comprehensive document which reflects the findings of our extensive preparatory work and consultations on the island of Ireland and at EU level, and outlines the positions and priorities that will underpin our engagement in the Brexit process over the next two years.  At EU level, the more detailed draft negotiating directives are now being discussed at ministerial and official level with a view to agreement at the General Affairs Council on 22 May.  These are again broadly positive from Ireland&rsquo;s point of view.  Mr. Barnier and his team have shown that, in addition to being open to meet with us, they are also listening very closely to what we have to say, which is why I welcome the Ceann Comhairle's decision today.  This is vitally important if the negotiations are to proceed in a calm and ordered way, and end up at a point which is as good as possible for all sides.</p> <p> As I said in my statement to the D&aacute;il on Tuesday, it became very clear at an early stage of our analysis that the economic impacts of Brexit would be severe.  With the EU guidelines now adopted and work under way on the directives, the Government will intensify its focus on the economic implications of Brexit, including on domestic policy measures to protect it from the potential negative impacts of Brexit, to reinforce the competitiveness of the Irish economy, which is so important, and also to pursue all opportunities that might arise.  In this context, I should also mention Ireland will bid, along with other countries, for the two EU bodies currently located in London - the European Medicines Agency and the European Banking Authority.  I believe that Ireland offers an excellent opportunity as a location for these.</p> <p> As I have said before, and in conclusion, Brexit is a British policy.  It is not an Irish policy and it is not an EU policy.  For its part, Ireland remains committed clearly to the European Union and its future.  Indeed, a poll published on Europe Day this week showed that 88% of Irish people agree that Ireland should remain a member of the European Union.  Participation and membership have transformed our country, as Mr. Barnier is well aware, over the last 40 years.  We are committed to playing a strong and active role as a member of the EU 27.  We are well prepared and will continue to ensure that our concerns and priorities are reflected in the European Union negotiating position as it evolves, and that we work closely with our EU partners, the EU institutions and Mr. Barnier and his task force, towards a strong and constructive future relationship with the United Kingdom.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1224" speakername="Miche&aacute;l Martin" time="11:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100007#E00200"><p>On behalf of the Fianna F&aacute;il Party, I would like to thank Mr. Barnier for taking the time to address this session today in such an effective and comprehensive manner.  His eagerness to listen and respond to the concerns of Ireland continues an approach seen during the many important roles which he has held in the French Government and in the European Commission.</p>  <p>  This is not an occasion where we can or should get into the deep specifics of the negotiations.  I am confident that Mr. Barnier's team and the European institutions will continue to be accessible for constructive discussions.  Fianna F&aacute;il sees this exchange of views as an opportunity to link our approach to these negotiations with the fundamental issue of Ireland&rsquo;s place within Europe.  This is not just about the outcome of the Brexit process but also about how we see the long-term future of relations on this island, with our neighbour and with our partners in the European Union.  No one underestimates the scale and complexity of the task which Mr. Barnier faces.</p>  <p>  Last year&rsquo;s referendum was an ugly and negative affair.  No amount of warm words and earnest statements can cover this up.  There was no strategy for implementing Brexit, there was just a strategy for winning the vote through a combination of bluster and aggression.  It was not a positive assertion of sovereignty; it was the culmination of 30 years of an increasingly corrosive scapegoating of Europe and immigrants for the home-grown divisions in British society.  Those false prophets who promised an economic bonanza are now claiming that they have defied the critics and Britain is booming.  This is nonsense.  Public borrowing and taxes have already risen since the vote and the long-term damage to employment and standards of living is becoming ever more certain.  Fundamentally, the narrow Brexit majority represented a rejection of strong rule-based co-operation between states.  It asserted a narrow vision of sovereignty which developed in the 19th century and directly led to the two bloodiest wars in history.</p>  <p>  Let there be no doubt about where Ireland stands.  We want nothing to do with a backward-looking idea of sovereignty.  We remain absolutely committed to the ideals of the European Union.  We see the Union for what it is - the most successful international organisation in world history.  While the extremes of right and left join together to attack it, they have no credible response to the fact that every member state has secured a significant rise in living standards and a Continent once defined by conflict is today defined by co-operation.  The Union is flawed, but its successes are undeniable.  There are certainly different views here.  There are those who buy into the anti-EU narratives, but the overwhelming majority of the Irish people are determined that Ireland&rsquo;s future will remain a European future.</p>  <p>  It is important for Mr. Barnier to understand that Ireland&rsquo;s approach to Europe and to international commitments is deeply intertwined with our national identity.  Last year, we marked 100 years since the most important founding event of our Republic.  The nationalism of the Rising of 1916 and the Proclamation of Independence is a generous one.  It defines the Irish nation as having diverse elements and seeks a State which works with others.  Our republican Constitution, adopted in 1937 at a dark moment in world affairs, goes even further and explicitly recognises the role of international law and co-operation.  We have no nostalgia for a lost empire and no wish to assert superiority over others.  We have never sought to stand apart from the world, jealously guarding the right to say no to everything.  We fully understand that only when states work together they can secure peace, progress and prosperity for their people.  That is why we will remain active and constructive members of the European Union.</p>  <p>  The most basic challenge for the agreement which Mr. Barnier will negotiate is to protect the essential contract which underpins the European Union.  This essential contract is that all members must have the opportunity to achieve progress.  When new circumstances arise, new responses must be possible.  If Europe ceases to be a vehicle of hope then it ceases to have a purpose.  Brexit represents a dramatic disruption which poses permanent challenges which are unevenly spread within the Union.  The referendum result and the British Government&rsquo;s decision to opt out of both the Single Market and the customs union are deeply destructive for businesses and communities on this island.  The only long-term option for us is to take a more ambitious and urgent approach to diversification and innovation.  Even more importantly, we must now find a way of fixing the damage caused to the agreed approach to building a lasting reconciliation in the place of sectarian division.</p>  <p>  I remember well that when a Government of ours approached Mr. Barnier concerning EU support for the peace process, he was active, engaged and generous.  We have no doubt that he will do everything possible to honour the clear support for the Good Friday Agreement contained in the negotiation guidelines.</p><p>It is important to emphasise that the Good Friday Agreement establishes structures and policies which are intended to evolve over time.  It is not a question of having either the <i>status quo</i>or reunification.  In fact, the real spirt of the Agreement is to be found in provisions which facilitate greater shared action over time in important practical matters.  The text incorporated in our Constitution permits this Parliament to delegate functions to bodies which are not solely under its direction.  Tourism, trade and European Union funding programmes are three of the areas already covered.  Whatever is agreed in the negotiations, it must do nothing to undermine the ability to permit shared cross-Border institutions and action to develop.<br/><br/>On the issue of wider trading arrangements, Fianna F&aacute;il considers that the maintenance of a close trading relationship with the United Kingdom is in Europe's best interests.  Given the scale of disruption Brexit will cause even with a soft border, a form of special status should be considered in the negotiations.  There are many models of special economic zones across the world which could be adapted here.<br/><br/>The rights of long-term residents of and persons born in Northern Ireland to Irish and therefore European citizenship must be protected fully in the final agreement.  We welcome the reassurances provided in this regard as well as the commitment to maintain the common travel area.  As Mr. Barnier knows, the commitment is referenced currently in Protocol 20 of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union.  The protocol is, in essence, meaningless once the UK leaves the EU because Ireland's rights are defined in terms of its relations with another contracting partner to the treaty.  This raises what may be a fundamental practical issue in the negotiations, namely, the status of the agreement which emerges.<br/><br/>The guidelines limit what measures can be agreed to those which conform to the existing European Union order and laws.  It is, frankly, very difficult to see how issues having to do with Northern Ireland or the common travel area, as well as essential economic adjustments, can be addressed without some new EU legal measures.  We hope Mr. Barnier will be willing to recommend new legislation where it is necessary.  However, where a doubt exists in relation to the treaties, the final agreement should provide a means to adopt new measures, following Council unanimity, such as an enabling provision to facilitate new North-South arrangements.<br/><br/>The ratification process for the British agreement is similar to the one adopted for accession treaties.  It should be possible to agree minor treaty provisions at the same time where such provisions are essential to meeting basic objectives.  This session does not allow me to go into more detail, but my party will forward to Mr. Barnier specific proposals once the negotiations are under way.<br/><br/>On this very day 45 years ago, the votes were counted in our accession referendum.  An overwhelming 83% voted in favour of membership.  The campaign saw the promotion of many scare stories about how Europe would reduce Ireland to a barren wasteland, build nuclear plants at every crossroads and parade missiles down our main streets.  The people, however, chose to place their faith in the positive vision of Ireland growing and prospering within the European community of nations.  Our European path was, in fact, the final public contribution of our great revolutionary generation.  As a 16 year old boy, Se&aacute;n Lemass escaped from home in order to fight in the 1916 Rising.  As a politician a decade later, he read and was inspired by the idea of a united Europe proposed by the great French statesman, Aristide Briand.<br/><br/>When Se&aacute;n Lemass became Taoiseach at the end of the 1950s, he called for our country to open itself up.  His Governments laid the foundations for sustained progress, central to which was securing agreement to apply for membership of the then European Economic Community.  He told us that while there would be challenges, the opportunities would be far greater.  This father of our European path and of modern Ireland died on 11 May 1971, exactly one year before the result of our accession referendum was announced.  His legacy is as important today as it has ever been.<br/><br/>Europe faces a moment of great uncertainty and, in many ways, of fear.  There is no positive side to Brexit.  If, however, we look to our shared history, we will see that we have come through many difficult times before.  If we remember the core ideals of the Union, we will get through this process and secure for another generation the promise of shared progress and prosperity among the nations of Europe.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1330" speakername="Gerry Adams" time="12:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100008#F00200"><p>C&eacute;ad m&iacute;le f&aacute;ilte, cuirim f&aacute;ilte - bienvenue - roimh an Uasal Barnier go h&Eacute;irinn, go dt&iacute; Baile &Aacute;tha Cliath, agus chuig an Oireachtas.  T&aacute; s&uacute;il agam go mbeidh cuairt fhaisn&eacute;iseach agus suimi&uacute;il agat.  Is mise an Teachta Gerry Adams agus is uachtar&aacute;n Shinn F&eacute;in m&eacute;.  On behalf of Sinn F&eacute;in, I welcome Mr. Barnier's presence and his remarks and I would like to tell him a wee bit about the party.  Sinn F&eacute;in is an Irish republican party.  It is an all-Ireland party and it has the largest group of Irish MEPs in the European Parliament.  Sinn F&eacute;in members include TDs, MLAs, Senators, MPs, MEPs and local authority members.  It has a significant mandate and is the only party which is substantially organised across the entire island.</p><p><font color="#222222">  Sinn F&eacute;in is opposed to the partition of Ireland.  Ours is a united Ireland party and we want an end to British Government involvement in Irish affairs.  We are working for the unity of all the people of the island based on equality, respect and reconciliation.  We believe absolutely in the core values of equality, liberty and fraternity and that the foundation of these values is in the 1916 Proclamation.  Like others, Sinn F&eacute;in has played a central role in the development of the peace process, the Good Friday Agreement and subsequent agreements.  We helped to bring about and engaged in the international efforts which ended conflict on this island, not least those of the European Union which has been a critical partner for peace over the past 20 years.  For those who were previously denied the right to work peacefully for a united Ireland, the Good Friday Agreement commits the governments to legislate for that if the people consent.</font></p><p><font color="#222222">  Sinn F&eacute;in campaigned against Irish membership of the EEC in 1973.  Since then, every European treaty has taken further powers from the Irish State.  Sinn F&eacute;in wants a different type of European Union.  We want a social Europe which promotes peace, demilitarisation, economic and social justice, international solidarity and greater democratic accountability.  Today's European Union is wedded to neoliberal policies which have created widespread hardship as austerity, deregulation and privatisation have undermined the social function of states and the rights of citizens and workers.  As Mr. Barnier acknowledged in his remarks, people across the EU are increasingly uncomfortable with this state of affairs and this discomfort has assisted the growth of far right parties which exploit people's fears.  Brexit is a consequence of that.</font></p><p><font color="#222222">  During the Brexit referendum, Sinn F&eacute;in campaigned for a remain vote in the North.  It is clearly not in the interests of the people of this island, whatever their background or views, to have one part of the island outside the EU while the other part is inside.  Mr. Barnier values the peace process and the Good Friday agreement.  He has worked for peace going back to the time of John Hume and David Trimble.  I am sure he is aware that any EU agreement which violated an international treaty, which is what the Good Friday Agreement is, would contravene EU treaty obligations.</font></p><p><font color="#222222">  Brexit is not only an issue for the North.  It will adversely affect the entire island if we let it.  As such, it is vital that its challenges are met on an all-island basis.  As Mr. Barnier and the Taoiseach acknowledged in their remarks, it is clear that Brexit will have a serious and detrimental effect.  It is already having this effect on Irish jobs and businesses, in particular in the agriculture and agrifood sectors.</font></p><p> The aim of the European Union, if I may say so, should be to prevent a land frontier between the European Union and Britain on the island of Ireland.  That should be the key objective and the priority.  To achieve this, we have advocated that the North be afforded designated special status within the European Union.  We also believe that Ireland should have a veto on any agreement reached between the European Union and the British Government that does not include this position.  Designated status is the best and only way to ensure that the entire island of Ireland will remain within the European Union.  I commend this proposal to Mr. Barnier.  It is an imaginative solution that addresses the complexities of the problem.  It does not affect the constitutional status of the North.  That will be changed only by a referendum.</p> <p> Designated special status within the European Union is the position endorsed by this D&aacute;il.  It is the position of this Parliament.  It is endorsed by the majority of MLAs in the Northern Assembly.  It recognises that the people of the North voted to remain part of European Union.  Is that just going to be placed to one side, ignored and driven over?  It is a solution being advocated by representatives of Border communities, some of whom are here in the Visitors Gallery.  I welcome them.  The Tory Government in England should not be allowed to reject the vote in the North and set aside the decision of people there.  It should not be allowed to drive the North out of the European Union against the democratic wishes of citizens.</p> <p> Designated special status for the North within the European Union is not about a hard Brexit or a soft Brexit; it is about the best interests of our economy, our peace process and our people.  It is also a democratic imperative.  It is about retaining the freedom of movement of goods, people and services on the island of Ireland.  Any restriction whatsoever on freedom of movement would represent a hardening of the Border.  Believe me, this will severely damage social and economic cohesion.  It would be unacceptable to those who live in Border communities but also to people right across our island.  Special status would ensure the North's trading relationship with the rest of Ireland and the European Union, particularly in the context of business, tourism, the all-Ireland energy market, agriculture and the agrifood sector.  All the relationships in this regard would be maintained.  It is about allowing all of Ireland to remain in the customs union and the Single Market and under the jurisdiction of the European Court of Justice.  It is about maintaining the European Convention on Human Rights and it is about protecting the rights of citizens in the North who have a right to Irish citizenship and, therefore, to citizenship of the European Union.  Access to EU rights and services across employment, workers' conditions, social security and health care must also be protected.</p> <p> None of this is beyond our collective wisdom or ability.  It will require political flexibility from the European Union.  Of course, the little Englanders may object.  Let me remind Mr. Barnier and them that they are looking for special arrangements with the European Union for themselves.  There are already unique arrangements in place for other states.  Therefore, the European Union has been flexible on these matters.  There are different forms of integration and relationships for member states and non-member states.  These include overseas countries and territory status, the European Free Trade Association and the separate customs union.</p> <p> In light of the provisions for Irish unity in the Good Friday Agreement, the European Union should not diverge from these norms.  Sinn F&eacute;in, unlike the Taoiseach, would like to see a referendum on Irish unity within the next five years.  The immediate challenge facing the European Union and the people of Ireland, however, is how to meet the threat of Brexit.  This is all about what kind of Ireland will emerge after Brexit.  The only way to shape that positively is through special designated status for the North within the European Union.  Merci beaucoup, Monsieur Barnier.  I thank you for your presence.  Go raibh m&iacute;le maith agat.  Go n-&eacute;ir&iacute; an t-&aacute;dh leat.  M&iacute;le bu&iacute;ochas.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1353" speakername="Brendan Howlin" time="12:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100009#G00200"><p>I am standing very close to our guest.  I add my welcome and that of my Labour Party colleagues to Monsieur Barnier.  Although my speaking time is very brief, I will use my proximity to him to emphasise the points I want to make.  Mr. Barnier and I met many years ago.  We were both environment Ministers.  I know his commitment to the ideals of Europe.  I also know he appreciates that the Brexit negotiating mandate is about our vital national interests and the vital interests of this island as a whole.</p>  <p>  We have many concerns.  We are an island off an island off the mainland of Europe.  Inevitably, our geography must dictate our policies and our priorities.  The negotiating guidelines, with their insistence on an orderly first-things-first approach, postpone until later consideration of what for us will be, in fact, most vital interests.  To be specific, while the guidelines do recognise the special position of Northern Ireland, albeit with the real challenges that others have already underscored, they do not sufficiently recognise the unique challenges that would be faced by us south of the Border.  For us, Brexit means that the idea of achieving the European Single Market has been set back a generation.  That is the undeniable truth.  To put it bluntly, once the United Kingdom leaves, it will no longer make any real, practical day-to-day sense for us to talk about membership of a true single market in regard to the goods and services that we import and export.  Talk of the Single Market will, from our perspective, revert from being almost a practical reality that we almost had fully achieved towards something more closely resembling an aspiration.</p>  <p>  As I stated earlier, the basic reason is one of geography.  There will, in future, be a large chunk of non-Europe between us and the rest of the Union.  Brexit will impact on every aspect of our economic, social and cultural lives.  It will impact on every network to which we are already connected.  This includes, in physical and infrastructural terms, our transport, energy and telecommunications networks.  Therefore, it will impact on Ireland's ability to adhere to EU law.  It will affect, for example, our ability to comply with the EU directive requiring a single EU market in electricity since our only power connections are with Northern Ireland and Britain.  Another directive requires EU-wide television without frontiers when most of our external television programming comes from Britain.</p>  <p>  EU directives are based on internal markets, common markets and interconnectedness.  They are designed to cover enormous territories and immense distances and to bring them together as one.  They are not designed to leapfrog over other countries operating completely distinct and separate rules, to which we in Ireland will nonetheless remain truly tied in terms of geography, infrastructure, networks and trade.  Our challenge after Brexit, therefore, is for Ireland to adhere to policies and laws that were designed for an internal EU market when we will find ourselves removed from direct access to that market, having few direct infrastructural connections and remaining connected instead to a country outside the Union.</p><p>All these factors make Ireland's case unique in the negotiations Mr. Barnier is about to lead on our behalf.  I hope the views expressed by Members in the few short minutes we have here and in the ongoing dialogue we will have with him will make sure that he will bring as effective as possible a conclusion in our interests.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1238" speakername="Richard Boyd Barrett" time="12:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100010#H00200"><p>As a representative of the People Before Profit alliance and a socialist, I am a thorough internationalist, an implacable supporter of international solidarity and an implacable opponent of the racist and far-right forces that are now rising in Europe.  I ask in all sincerity if we can trust Mr. Barnier with the issues of international solidarity or free movement of people as they pertain to Europe or to this country.</p>  <p>  This week, 250 desperate refugees fleeing north Africa drowned in the Mediterranean because of the EU's fortress Europe policies.  These are not free movement policies, rather they deny free movement to desperate people.  Can we trust Mr. Barnier with international solidarity when Jean-Claude Trichet threatened to let off a financial bomb in Dublin if our Government even suggested burning the gambling bondholders who crippled our economy and whose activities inflicted cruel and vicious austerity on hundreds of thousands of our citizens?  This has left us today with the legacy of the worst housing and homelessness crisis in the history of the State, a health service which has been savaged and incredible hardship imposed on some of our most vulnerable citizens.  Even now the EU fiscal rules, of which Mr. Barnier was a significant architect, cripple our ability to deal with those problems.  I do not trust the European Union to do a deal that will vindicate the needs and aspirations of the citizens of this country because it has failed to do so in recent years.  Indeed, it has imposed similar hardships on countries like Greece, Spain and Italy.  </p>  <p>  If we are to give Mr. Barnier any credibility in his commitments today I would like answers to a few simple questions.  Will Mr. Barnier guarantee - not consider - that Europe will not try to break up the free travel area between Ireland and the UK?  Will Mr. Barnier guarantee that the European Union will not impose a hard Border between the North and South of this country?  If the EU believes in democracy as it professes to do, will it give us a vote on the final deal in the negotiations between the EU and the UK in order that we can decide democratically whether we believe the best deal has been done?  If Mr. Barnier cannot give those guarantees, frankly all the noble aspirations mean very little indeed.  It is the failure to give guarantees and promises on democracy and rights and to vindicate genuine international solidarity that has caused the existential crisis the EU is now facing.  The EU should address itself very quickly to that issue, if the dangerous forces that are rising in Europe are not to gain further advance.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1371" speakername="Se&aacute;n &Oacute; Feargha&iacute;l" time="12:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100010#H00300"><p>Deputy Pringle.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1238" speakername="Richard Boyd Barrett" time="12:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100010#H00400"><p>Deputy Coppinger is to speak.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1371" speakername="Se&aacute;n &Oacute; Feargha&iacute;l" time="12:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100010#H00500"><p>Deputy Boyd Barrett consumed all the time, I am afraid.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1238" speakername="Richard Boyd Barrett" time="12:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100010#H00600"><p>Everybody else went over their time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1371" speakername="Se&aacute;n &Oacute; Feargha&iacute;l" time="12:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100010#H00700"><p>They did, and so did Deputy Boyd Barrett.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1367" speakername="Br&iacute;d Smith" time="12:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100010#H00800"><p>That is very unfair.  The Labour Party went over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1371" speakername="Se&aacute;n &Oacute; Feargha&iacute;l" time="12:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100010#H00900"><p>The Deputies should organise the time amongst themselves.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1367" speakername="Br&iacute;d Smith" time="12:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100010#H01000"><p>We timed everyone and they all went over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.27" nospeaker="true" time="12:20:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1371" speakername="Se&aacute;n &Oacute; Feargha&iacute;l" time="12:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100010#H01200"><p>Let us not have a scene.  Deputy Coppinger for a second then, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1434" speakername="Ruth Coppinger" time="12:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100010#H01300"><p>I thank the Ceann Comhairle.  Solidarity also must stand against the consensus expressed by Mr. Barnier and most of the other parties.  The growing alienation against the EU - which Mr. Barnier has labelled "populism" - is actually largely a reaction to years of a neo-liberal agenda within the EU that has favoured the interests of big business and banks against those of workers and the poor.  EU directives, state aid rules and fiscal compact treaties are continually cited in this country to our successful anti-water charges movement, to striking Bus &Eacute;ireann workers and to the thousands on the housing waiting lists here as reasons nothing can change.  What Mr. Barnier represents actually has more in common with the Tories that he would have us believe.  Both camps want bargain basement societies.</p>  <p>  The issue of a hard Border is causing huge uncertainty and anxiety in Northern Ireland and we should just put an end to the idea.  Nobody wants, and there is no requirement or need for, a hard Border.  Speaking of borders, the Mediterranean has become a graveyard for thousands of people thanks to fortress Europe, which Mr. Barnier favours.  It is a migration policy of which Donald Trump would be envious.  </p>  <p>  The big business-dominated agenda of the EU consistently undermines the standards of living of the majority in the EU.  Today's attempt at a neatly packaged consensus will be challenged by those of us on the left who seek to create a society where the needs of the millions, not the millionaires, are fundamental.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1366" speakername="Thomas Pringle" time="12:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100010#H01400"><p>I welcome Mr. Barnier to the Chamber today to engage with this committee of the D&aacute;il and Seanad and to hear directly about our concerns surrounding the UK's decision to leave the European Union and the negotiations that are about to take place on the future relationship with the UK.  I believe the EU does not have a history of having at heart the interests of the Irish people in dealing with us in the past.  Hopefully, through the negotiations around Brexit, an outcome can be achieved that will change that.</p>  <p>  I represent the constituency of Donegal, which is the most northerly part of Ireland.  Donegal has a land border of approximately 15 km with the rest of the Republic of Ireland.  We stand therefore to be the most impacted region of Ireland from Brexit.  My county has suffered from its isolation since the partition of Ireland after independence in 1921, and has only in recent years started to recover from that isolation.  A hard Brexit, if it comes, will have a huge impact on the county.  There are three main areas that could particularly be affected, which are the economy - and the fishing industry in particular - cross-Border workers and students, and the provision of health care.  While an arrangement for trade will probably dominate the negotiations, access to fishing stocks is vitally important for the entire Irish fishing industry but particularly for the industry in County Donegal.  Unfortunately, the EU does not have a good record when it comes to the treatment of Irish fishing, going back to when we negotiated to join the EEC, as it then was in the 1970s.  It will be vitally important that access to fishing grounds is negotiated alongside the trade negotiations that will take place.  This is the only way to ensure the survival of communities that depend on fishing.  As more than 35% of the Irish quota that Irish fishermen catch is caught in UK waters, the continued access for fishermen to the fishing grounds is vital.  Indeed, the value of fish caught in UK waters is higher than the percentage would suggest, being almost 50% of the total value of our catch.  The importance of a fair negotiation and outcome cannot be over-stressed for us.  </p>  <p>  There is a compelling case for special status for Northern Ireland after Brexit that will recognise that we will have the only land border with a UK jurisdiction and that the possibility of a future reunification, as has already been outlined, has been provided for in the Good Friday Agreement.  Approximately 30,000 people cross the Border to work every day, and many more thousands of students are studying in the North.  Maintaining the common travel area in order that these workers and students can continue to participate is vitally important for us.</p><p>Donegal's isolation has meant we have suffered from under-developed health services and neglect in provision from successive Governments that have had a totally Dublin-centred model for the provision of services such as health.  Just last year, a radiotherapy centre was opened in Derry city, part-funded by the Irish Government, to give access to cancer patients from Donegal within a reasonable journey time from their homes for treatment.  The future relationship with Northern Ireland has to ensure bilateral arrangements such as these can continue to be developed for the betterment of all our citizens, North and South.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1275" speakername="Michael Harty" time="12:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100011#J00200"><p>I will not speak in French as it is not as polished as the Ceann Comhairle's.  I want to say <i>bonjour,</i>Mr. Barnier, and welcome him to our Parliament, D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann, on behalf of the Rural Independent Group.</p><p>This is a landmark occasion for this country as we, together with our European Union colleagues, enter negotiations on the UK's exit from the EU.  These negotiations are as profound to Ireland today as those when we applied to join the European Economic Community almost 50 years ago.  For Ireland, disentangling from our closest neighbour will be more difficult than for any other member state due to our common border and our common economic and cultural connections.  Mr. Barnier's presence here today is a tangible recognition of the unique difficulties we face.</p><p>Our main concerns relate to the still delicate nature of the peace process underpinned by the Good Friday Agreement, the nature of the border between the UK and the EU on this island, the close trading relationships between Ireland and the UK and the free passage of people, goods and services.  These are all critical to Ireland.</p><p>Our farmers tell us that Brexit presents the most serious economic threat to our agricultural sector, such is the large percentage of our high-quality exports which go to the UK.  Border tariffs and customs, border checks and regulatory changes will cause serious restrictions on these exports.  The negotiators must make every effort to secure favourable trading relationships between Ireland and the UK to avoid direct negative impact on our farm incomes.  We must also find alternative markets in Europe and beyond for these goods and we request that Mr. Barnier assist us in that regard.</p><p>As we will have a new land border with the EU, this needs special attention from Mr. Barnier in his negotiations with the UK.  Ireland needs to know what this future border will look like in every scenario of British withdrawal.  Economics may well dictate if a united Ireland will be the best option for all on this island.  Only time will tell.  We are a resourceful people and we must not be sacrificed to a hard Brexit because of our geography or because of our small size.  Brexit makes us think of new opportunities and new potentials and there are new potentials in relation to developing our maritime and deep-sea ports.  For instance, we have the asset of a number of uncongested deep-sea ports in the Shannon Estuary which should act as a trans-shipment location for the distribution of goods throughout Europe and should offer freight and cargo companies shipping to the United States preclearance facilities similar to those enjoyed by air passengers flying from Shannon.</p><p>From a Brexit point of view, this is an opportunity to attract industry from right across Europe which is exporting into the United States and would benefit companies throughout the region.  United, we will negotiate the best strategy for both the EU and the UK.  There is nothing to be gained by making life difficult for everybody.  After all, the UK will still be our nearest neighbour after these negotiations have been completed.</p><p>We must appeal to people's hopes and not to their fears, and in adversity there is also opportunity.  A united Europe can deliver a more prosperous Union where Ireland plays a prominent role.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1371" speakername="Se&aacute;n &Oacute; Feargha&iacute;l" time="12:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100011#J00300"><p>We now move to Deputy R&oacute;is&iacute;n Shortall who is sharing time with Deputy Eamon Ryan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1222" speakername="R&oacute;is&iacute;n Shortall" time="12:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100011#J00400"><p>On behalf of the Social Democrats, I warmly welcome Mr. Barnier to our Parliament today.  In regard to Ireland's geography and small population, our big fear is that our voice will not be heard clearly at the negotiating table.  Our fate is inextricably linked to that of the UK and for that reason it is essential that our concerns and interests are kept to the fore.  Many Irish people continue to have to endure the cruel reality of austerity arising from the bank bailout.  Ireland was forced to carry a burden for Europe on that occasion and we have no desire to do so again.  If there is one message that might be taken back from today's engagement, I hope it is that the preservation of unrestricted free movement across the island of Ireland and between Ireland and the UK for people, goods and services must remain.  This is vital to Ireland's national interest but it is also vital to the success of the European project, a project which must encompass all citizens of Europe working together to achieve a strong, equal, fair, economic and social Europe.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1294" speakername="Eamon Ryan" time="12:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100011#J00500"><p>Nous vous souhaitons bonne chance dans votre travail.  Je suis avec les Verts.  I am with the all-island Green Party, proud, united, part of the European Green Party and best of mates with our Green Party colleagues in Scotland, England and Wales.  We are very glad that in the first phase of these talks, Mr. Barnier has agreed that one of the three conditions we have to work on is the border issues, particular to Ireland and Gibraltar, but we are concerned about our Border issues here.  I am glad that is front and centre stage.  I have one request about how Mr. Barnier might approach the work that he has to do.  As Mr. Barnier said, we are in a unique position that we are very close to Britain.  We are closely connected to Whitehall and as a country we are well-regarded in each capital and in every European council, that is my experience.  We should use this position, this place we have that is close to Berlin as well as Boston.  Let us use this position.</p><p><i></i>Mr. Barnier said today that one of the things we should seek in these negotiations is ongoing co-operation in innovation, research and particularly on climate change.  I agree.  We can play a role in this.  I ask Mr. Barnier to start straight away, perhaps in informal but flexible, safe space talks, which we can provide here in Ireland, to start working with the British immediately.  What are the regulations on which we can agree in order that we make this necessary great climate change leap?<i></i>What are the digital rights that we have to agree in the information revolution that is taking place?  What are the standards in the transport revolution that we need to do to improve our urban system and our quality of life in every way?  Those three issues are not contentious.  They are some of the critical issues that we will have to get right here.  Do not wait until the Brexit bill or all the other citizens' rights are all sorted.  Let us start straight away on those areas of co-operation.  Doing that will be good for all of Europe.  We can test it here, as Mr. Barnier said, in the first phase when we think about the Border relations between Ireland and the UK.  That is what is good and strong about the European Union, that is against the race to the bottom, and that will raise all our spirits in the Union and set a future of which we can be proud.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1371" speakername="Se&aacute;n &Oacute; Feargha&iacute;l" time="12:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100011#J00600"><p>We now move to the illustrious members of Seanad &Eacute;ireann.  I call Senator 	.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="12:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100011#J00700"><p>Monsieur Barnier est vraiment bienvenu en Irlande aujourd'hui.  He has pointed out that the issues Ireland faces call for imaginative and flexible solutions.  Many things have been said here today with which I agree, and others with which I disagree, but it is up to the Irish now, North and South, to participate in the process of devising imaginative and flexible solutions and coming up with models for consideration by Mr. Barnier.  Some people here have impugned the good faith of the European Union institutions and perhaps Mr. Barnier himself.  I have trust and confidence that he does appreciate our needs and that he will be open to imaginative and flexible solutions which address the real problems in Ireland if we come forward with them to him.</p><p>No institution or politician has a monopoly on imagination or flexibility.  What we need in Ireland is a coalition of the willing, North and South, including all aspects of civil society and all economic interests, to try to ensure the implementation of Brexit is done in a manner which is least harmful to all the people of Ireland, North and South, over the next few years.  We in the Senate are conducting an examination of these issues.  We think the common travel area will survive and is no threat to general principles of European law such as freedom of movement but there are other issues, as Mr. Barnier mentioned.  There is a need to have, as far as possible, free trade in goods with Britain, as a close partner of the EU after its exit, as well as the need to have, as far as possible, the free movement of goods on this island and between these islands.  </p> <p> I draw to the attention of Mr. Barnier that prior to the reunification of Germany, East Germany was given a special status for the export of goods to West Germany.  It was regarded as inside the customs union in the days of the European Economic Community.  That is the kind of flexible arrangement we should aspire to if we can.  It has been suggested, in particular by Deputy Adams here today, that Northern Ireland should effectively remain within the European Union.  It is not a practical possibility but there is a great opening to explore special status for the island of Ireland and its two parts without going that far.  I agree with the Taoiseach that we do not need a Border poll now as part of the process of sorting out where Ireland should be in the short or medium term.  I agree with Deputy Martin very strongly that the all-Ireland institutions contemplated by the Good Friday Agreement provide a framework, for instance, for a new agrifood dispensation on this island and a new cross-Border body to deal with all of those kinds of things.  I will finish on that note.</p> <p> Mr. Barnier has said there is a need for flexible and imaginative institutions.  The Irish people have to play their part in developing those responses to Mr. Barnier's challenge.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.39" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Senator Alice Mary Higgins" time="12:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100012#K00300"><p>On behalf of the Civil Engagement group in Seanad &Eacute;ireann, I thank Mr. Barnier for his presence here today and for the special and appropriate consideration he has given to Ireland in advance of the forthcoming negotiations.  The four fundamental freedoms must be protected, in particular the freedom of movement, which is of great importance for Irish citizens and all those who live on this island.</p>  <p>  Although the question of the Border has already been discussed, I will raise one further point on it.  Can Mr. Barnier assure us the EU will not lead to any militarisation of Ireland's Border with the UK, as we have seen in other EU external borders, or attempt to press ahead with any further development of an EU military that could risk or compromise Ireland's neutrality, something of deep and valuable importance to our State and citizens and to our international role in peace building?  Others have spoken about the importance of our peace process.  One crucial pillar of the Good Friday Agreement was the co-guaranteeing of human rights. The Human Rights Act in the UK was brought in alongside the Good Friday Agreement to underpin that commitment.  It is therefore of great concern to see the UK recently speak of repealing that Act.  Will Mr. Barnier, in his negotiations, seek to protect this important Act, ideally linked to the European Court of Human Rights, or, at a minimum, demand a commitment to full and ongoing equivalence on human rights standards?  </p>  <p>  On the wider question of standards, it is vital that European and international principles and policies that have been agreed in areas such as employment, equality and the environment do not face a roll-back in this process.  A race to the bottom is a race nobody wins.  On the environment, the prospect of the UK moving away from common rules and commitments could seriously endanger collective progress in this area and could risk direct environmental damage for those of us in Ireland.  How does the Commission see negotiations with the UK proceeding in the area of environmental regulation and what leverage can be employed to secure them?  How, for example, will we guarantee that any deal with the UK preserves the principles and measures of sustainability which currently underpin the Common Fisheries Policy?  Access to and transit through UK territorial waters will also be vital for Irish fishermen.  It is an area Mr. Barnier understands with great depth.  Others have spoken of transport, telecommunications and energy but there are other areas of important co-operation between the two parts of the island, as well as between Ireland and the UK more broadly.  There are areas of practical co-operation, many of which predate or operate outside and alongside the EU's remit.  Practical co-operation in areas such as education, health and social protection, particularly pensions, is of immense importance to the real lived lives of our citizens and must not be lost in these negotiations.  </p>  <p>  We, in Ireland, will be watching the forthcoming negotiations with great attention.  They will also be watched by many across Europe and across the world at a time of great difficulty following periods of austerity and conflict.  The nature and tone of the negotiations will send an important message about Europe and about what Europe is.  It is vitally important the message is not simply of a Europe that is strong or a Europe of the economy but that it is a Europe grounded in social rights and social cohesion and which works for peace, values all its members, values democracy and listens to civil society.  The message should be of a Europe committed to all its citizens, all who live in it and to positive leadership and partnership in our shared world as we face the challenges ahead.  We entrust Mr. Barnier to convey that message.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1371" speakername="Se&aacute;n &Oacute; Feargha&iacute;l" time="12:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100012#K00400"><p>I thank all Members for their considered contributions.  I now call on the Cathaoirleach of the Seanad, Senator Denis O'Donovan, to make the concluding remarks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.41" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="An Cathaoirleach" time="12:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100012#K00500"><p>Gabhaim bu&iacute;ochas le Monsieur Barnier as an aitheasc a thug s&eacute; don d&aacute; Theach anseo inniu.  I thank Mr. Barnier for his address today to the D&aacute;il and the Seanad.  The potentially adverse political, economic and social consequences of Brexit for Ireland have been highlighted by the Houses and by the Irish Government both before and after last summer's referendum in the United Kingdom.  Mr. Barnier's presence here today has afforded a valuable opportunity to hear directly the concerns of the Members of the Houses of the Oireachtas.  His direct engagement with the Members of a national parliament of the EU also speaks to the strength of his commitment to the spirit of treaty principles.  The outcome of the Brexit negotiations will very much set the framework for the foreseeable future for decision-making for Ireland and for all of our fellow member states of the European Union.  We, in Ireland, fully appreciate the enormity of the task Mr. Barnier and his team face as they negotiate the withdrawal of the United Kingdom.  We wish him well in his work and we hope he will be strengthened in his endeavours by the goodwill of the Members of these Houses.  We look forward to continued engagement with Mr. Barnier on this crucial issue in the period ahead.  As he conducts the negotiations and seeks to achieve the best outcome for the European Union we ask him to keep in mind the particular situation we have here in Ireland.  Merci beaucoup.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1371" speakername="Se&aacute;n &Oacute; Feargha&iacute;l" time="12:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100012#K00600"><p>That brings our special sitting to a conclusion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.43" nospeaker="true" time="12:40:00" ><p>Sitting adjourned.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.44" nospeaker="true" time="12:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100013#Q00200">Leaders' Questions</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1296" speakername="Jim O'Callaghan" time="12:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100013#Q00300"><p>It will not come as a surprise that I will ask the T&aacute;naiste questions about An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and her political management of the force.   However, before I do, I wish to say something that I think is important.  I acknowledge and commend the work that is done every day in this country by members of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na who protect our communities and enforce our law.  I also commend and recognise the role that has been played in the past by members of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na who have served this country proudly.  I say that at the outset because, unfortunately, recent controversies have significantly damaged the reputation of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  It is unfortunate, to say the least, that we are now in a situation where we are expecting to hear scandal after scandal in respect of the force.  This is having a significant impact on the morale of the force.  More seriously, it is having an impact on the good relationship that has historically existed between An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and members of the public.  As politicians, we have a responsibility to ensure we rectify that relationship and rebuild the status of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na in our community.</p>  <p>  It is seven weeks to the day since senior members of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na told the public that there were 937,000 false breath tests on the PULSE system and 14,700 wrongful convictions as a result of Garda error.  At the time, my party stated that we needed answers and accountability.  Regrettably, from the force to date, we have not got answers or accountability.  Neither have we got political answers or accountability from the Government, which is responsible for An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.</p>  <p>  After the breath tests scandal, we had another scandal in respect of what was happening down in Templemore.  An audit, which displayed considerable financial irregularities, was conducted.  Last week, the Committee of Public Accounts was informed of a litany of financial irregularities in respect of the Garda College at Templemore.  More worrying, there was open disagreement in An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na between civilian members of senior management of the force and the Commissioner, who is a member of the officer band of the force.  This has caused significant concern.</p>  <p>  The issues in respect of Templemore were only brought to the T&aacute;naiste's attention by the Commissioner 14 months after she was apprised of them.  Under section 41 of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na Act, there is a legal duty on the Commissioner to bring to the Minister for Justice and Equality's attention "significant developments that might reasonably be expected to affect adversely public confidence in the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na".  It is unquestionably the case that the issues concerning financial irregularities in Templemore have affected public confidence in An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  Is the T&aacute;naiste satisfied that she was told about this 18 months later?  Why is it that when she was told, she did not ask the Commissioner the reason she was not told about it earlier?  The T&aacute;naiste needs to answer those questions and explain this to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1214" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="12:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100013#Q00400"><p>I agree with the point that the Deputy makes regarding the work of the members of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na day in, day out throughout the country tackling crime.  We should do everything in this House to support the work they do, which is extremely challenging at this time.  We should do everything possible to restore morale in An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  That has been my goal and aim since I became Minister for Justice and Equality.  Every action I have taken has been to support the reform that is necessary and to support the work of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  It had been starved completely of resources due to the lack of investment, the closure of Templemore and the lack of investment in the fleet and so on.  This is what I inherited from the Government previous to the last.  That was the situation I had to deal with.  That is the reality of the situation An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na was faced with when the Deputy's Government went out of power.</p>  <p>  I would not want to underestimate in any way the seriousness of the finding of the interim internal audit report on the finances of the Garda College in Templemore.  While it is an interim report, it paints a disturbing picture of the manner in which the college's finances were run, including the existence of a large number of bank accounts and investment accounts linked to the college, staffing issues and issues relating to the ownership and non-use of certain lands.  In short, it found that the financial controls in place could not be stood over.  While the report did not identify misappropriation as such, the question of whether any criminality might be involved is now being examined, and has to be examined, separately by an assistant commissioner of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.</p>  <p>  As the House will be aware, the Garda Commissioner is the Accounting Officer for An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  As such, she is liable to account to the Committee of Public Accounts on the Garda Vote.  The Committee of Public Accounts plays a vital role in ensuring there is proper accountability with regard to public moneys.  It is quite clear that the committee is determined to protect the interests of the taxpayers and to examine fully the facts behind what happened at the college.  I am aware from its meeting this morning - I saw some of it - that the committee is determined to proceed with this examination.  It spent a lot of time discussing precisely how it should proceed, the documentation that is needed and the ambit of its discussions.  Many members of the committee emphasised the need for fair procedures to be followed.  This should be borne in mind by all Members of the House.  Very particular responsibilities lie with Accounting Officers, and the House will appreciate that I must be careful not to interfere in any way with the work of the committee.  I can tell the House, however, that I will pay careful attention to the proceedings of the committee and, in particular, any report it may make.  If action is required on my part as a result, I will not hesitate to take it.</p>  <p>  As I stated yesterday, I cannot have a running commentary on these proceedings.  There is a danger.  Some people want the examination of these issues to proceed but to reach conclusions before it has been concluded.  Some people want to reach verdicts before all the evidence has been heard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1289" speakername="Pat Gallagher" time="12:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100013#Q00500"><p>Go raibh maith agat, a Th&aacute;naiste.  T&aacute; t&uacute; thar am.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1214" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="12:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100013#Q00600"><p>We cannot do that.  There is a process in place.  We need to get to the end of that process.  I got an interim report.  There was further work to be done by the auditors.  When I got the final report in March, I published it shortly afterwards and immediately referred it to the Policing Authority.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1289" speakername="Pat Gallagher" time="12:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100013#Q00700"><p>The T&aacute;naiste will have a second opportunity.  We have to have some discipline.  I call Deputy Jim O'Callaghan.  From now on, is will be no latitude day.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1296" speakername="Jim O'Callaghan" time="12:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100013#Q00800"><p>My party does not want a running commentary.  We want political responsibility in respect of this matter.  I asked the T&aacute;naiste a straightforward question.  It concerned the legal obligation of the Commissioner under section 41 of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na Act.  Is the T&aacute;naiste satisfied that she was notified in adequate time about these significant issues of public concern affecting confidence in An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na?</p><p>That is the question I asked and I would like the T&aacute;naiste to answer it.  Our concern on this side of the House is that it appears to be the case that the Government is allowing the Garda to drift from one scandal to another - the scandals are simply being identified, with no one accepting political responsibility for them.  More important than accepting political responsibility, someone in Government must come forward with a plan as to how we will rectify the position regarding public confidence in An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  The force has done too much for this State for us to abandon it politically by saying we cannot come up with a solution.  The T&aacute;naiste and the Cabinet have that responsibility, so I ask her again: is she satisfied with the notification she received under section 41, or does she think it was delayed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1289" speakername="Pat Gallagher" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100014#R00200"><p>I thank the Deputy for observing the time.  The T&aacute;naiste has one minute to respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1214" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100014#R00300"><p>I take that responsibility very seriously and I am very happy for anyone to examine my record.  The reality is that we now have a Policing Authority-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1335" speakername="Dara Calleary" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100014#R00400"><p>The T&aacute;naiste should answer the question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1214" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100014#R00500"><p>-----and a strengthened GSOC.  These issues are emerging.  They did not emerge before under any previous Administration.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1311" speakername="John Lahart" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100014#R00600"><p>Deputy O'Callaghan asked the T&aacute;naiste a straight question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1214" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100014#R00700"><p>Section 41 of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na Act places a requirement on the Garda Commissioner to report certain matters to me.  In practice, it is a matter for the judgment of the Commissioner as to when to make reports specifically citing section 41 of the Act.  It is a decision for her as to when she-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1296" speakername="Jim O'Callaghan" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100014#R00800"><p>Is the T&aacute;naiste satisfied?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1214" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100014#R00900"><p>It is not just a question of legal judgment; it is a question of determining whether a particular set of circumstances fall within the criteria set out in the Act.  There are issues too-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1353" speakername="Brendan Howlin" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100014#R01000"><p>The T&aacute;naiste is satisfied.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1214" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100014#R01100"><p>-----about the stage at which the Garda Commissioner might consider it appropriate to make a report citing section 41.  They are used rarely enough.  I can also refer a section 41 matter to the Commissioner.  Most contacts between the Garda and me do not involve the citation of that specific legal provision, as it happens.  Whether a report regarding particular circumstances is made and when it might be made are clearly not straightforward issues-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1250" speakername="Robert Troy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100014#R01200"><p>Is the T&aacute;naiste satisfied with the timeframe?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1214" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100014#R01300"><p>-----as has been indicated by some people.  It is also worth making the point-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1289" speakername="Pat Gallagher" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100014#R01400"><p>I have to stick to Standing Orders.  The T&aacute;naiste was allowed two extra minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1250" speakername="Robert Troy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100014#R01500"><p>She does not answer the question in any event.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1289" speakername="Pat Gallagher" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100014#R01600"><p>I have no responsibility in that regard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1239" speakername="Mary Lou McDonald" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100014#R01700"><p>Yesterday and again today, the Taoiseach and the Minister for Social Protection, Deputy Varadkar, expressed continued confidence in the Garda Commissioner.  The T&aacute;naiste does so in the wake of damning documentation presented by the head of Garda human resources, Mr. John Barrett, to the Committee of Public Accounts.  This documentation substantiates Mr. Barrett's contradiction of Commissioner O'Sullivan's statement to the committee last week.  It details his concerns about how his efforts to raise financial irregularities at Templemore were frustrated.  In fact, he expresses the very real worry that the approach of senior garda&iacute; could be perceived as a cover-up.  The documentation reiterates the fact that the Commissioner ignored her legal advice and her legal obligation to inform immediately the T&aacute;naiste of the financial irregularities at Templemore.  Now we discover that the T&aacute;naiste is, it seems, happy to be left in a state of blissful ignorance in this regard.  Worse still, she suggests that the happenings at Templemore were not serious enough to merit a report under section 41.  This is quite incredible.</p>  <p>  The leadership of the Commissioner has become a conveyor belt of crises, each scandal flying in the face of the central mission of the Garda, that is, to uphold the law and protect the people.  Since public confidence in the Commissioner has been torn to ribbons by persistent malpractice, corruption, arrogance and a blatant lack of accountability, it is now the T&aacute;naiste's responsibility to act.  It is a disgrace that she refuses to hold this Commissioner to account.  The T&aacute;naiste is the Minister for Justice - she is the Commissioner's boss - yet she has done nothing.  Deputy Enda Kenny is An Taoiseach - for a few more weeks at least.  He is the T&aacute;naiste's boss and he, in turn, has done nothing.  Is it any wonder the Commissioner refuses to do the right thing and resign?  The Commissioner knows full well that the T&aacute;naiste and the Taoiseach will both keep their heads firmly stuck in the sand in an attempt to wish all of this away, but it will not go away.  The T&aacute;naiste's handling of the scandals surrounding the Commissioner's leadership of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na is a scandal in and of itself, and the story is now wider than the Commissioner's intransigence.  We are in the throes of a serious crisis of governance that fundamentally undermines the credibility of the T&aacute;naiste's Government and the rule of law.  This has been brought about by her refusal to act and her incredible insistence that Commissioner O'Sullivan remains the best person to lead An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  The position of Fianna F&aacute;il, Fine Gael's partners in government, is equally nonsensical on this score and on the test of accountability.</p>  <p>  The Commissioner needs to go.  Her position is completely untenable.  In no other walk of life, in no other job, would a person so compromised be allowed to stay in her position.  The T&aacute;naiste's approach to this crisis has made a laughing stock of the political process within and outside this institution, and her continuing refusal to do her job will only ensure that ordinary people become more angry, more alienated and more cynical.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1289" speakername="Pat Gallagher" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100014#R01800"><p>Go raibh maith agat.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1239" speakername="Mary Lou McDonald" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100014#R01900"><p>The T&aacute;naiste talks a great deal about reform.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1289" speakername="Pat Gallagher" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100014#R02000"><p>I call the T&aacute;naiste.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1239" speakername="Mary Lou McDonald" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100014#R02100"><p>She talks about raising morale but she does not mean it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1289" speakername="Pat Gallagher" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100014#R02200"><p>The Deputy has exceeded her time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1239" speakername="Mary Lou McDonald" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100014#R02300"><p>She is bluffing.  When will the T&aacute;naiste stop bluffing?  When will she remove the Commssioner and begin that process of reform?  That is what she must do.  Will she do it?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1214" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100014#R02400"><p>I suggest to the Deputy that what the public will find extraordinary is that she, as a member of the Committee of Public Accounts, which this morning discussed for two and a half hours how it would approach an examination of this issue, has already made up her mind on the issue of Templemore while it is still before the committee.  I suggest to her that what the public will find quite extraordinary is that, without waiting for the evidence regarding the issue, she, as a member of the committee, has given an opinion on the final outcome.</p>  <p>  Quite clearly, the issues that have arisen at Templemore underline the need for the reform to which everyone in this House is committed and to which the last Government was committed, which was shown by the establishment of the Policing Authority.  This was the first time there has been such oversight, the first time there have been public hearings regarding An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and the first time appointments have been made independently of Government - assistant commissioners appointed already and chief superintendents being appointed.  No other Government except this one set that in place, so do not talk to me about not being committed to reform.  No other Government has supported An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na with the resources as this Government and the previous one has done.  We are determined to ensure the reform takes place.  A modernisation programme is in place for the first time-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1274" speakername="Timmy Dooley" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100014#R02500"><p>Led by the old guard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1214" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100014#R02600"><p>-----and it is being monitored by an outside body.  The first report regarding the implementation of that reform has already been published by the Policing Authority.  I do not believe there is anyone in this House who does not have trust in the work done by Josephine Feehily and the Policing Authority.  We set up the Policing Authority.  We made those appointments to ensure there would be the kind of oversight to ensure that these issues emerged and that the Garda would be held publicly accountable instead of doing things in private.  That is what I am committed to, namely, public accountability, procedures in place to ensure oversight, acting on the recommendations that come to me and the Government and ensuring that budgetary provision is made so that instead of people not having the management they need, not having the civilian staff in place and not having recruitment, that is all now in place.  That is what this Government is doing, that is what the previous Government did and that is what the commitment is - to support members of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na to go about their daily work, to give them the resources to do so, and absolutely to have accountability and to call them to task when there is not accountability.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1239" speakername="Mary Lou McDonald" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100014#R02700"><p>The T&aacute;naiste's response is ironic.  She talks of accountability but she resolutely refuses to take the first action of accountability, which is to hold the boss - the Commissioner - to account.  She will not do that.  Let me say, as a member of the Committee of Public Accounts, that we are well conversant with our role and our responsibilities.  Let me reiterate: we will get to the bottom of all of this.  Let me also tell the T&aacute;naiste that we and, more importantly, the internal audit function of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na have already established the facts.</p><p>These facts, which are accepted by the Garda Commissioner, are that 50 bank accounts were opened by An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na without the sanction of the Department of Justice and Equality, that An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na entered illegally into land leasing arrangements and took the benefit of the revenues that accrued and that the Commissioner was advised of her obligation under section 41 to inform the Minister of the shenanigans in Templemore and refused that advice.  These are not matters of contention but established facts.  All of the T&aacute;naiste's hot air about accountability amounts to very little.  She is not serious about accountability because if she were, she would call Commissioner N&oacute;ir&iacute;n O'Sullivan to account and relieve her of her duties.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1214" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="13:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100015#S00200"><p>The Deputy seems to think that calling people to account means asking them to resign.  What I mean by accountability is having in place procedures and organisations, such as the Policing Authority, where there is that accountability.  What I mean by accountability is that all of the facts are brought out into the public arena.  The Garda Commissioner of the day does not hold office on the basis of political expediency.  I am not free to decide the fate of a Garda Commissioner on the basis of a headline or expressions or confidence or otherwise by Members of the Oireachtas.  There are very specific legal provisions in place in respect of these matters.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1239" speakername="Mary Lou McDonald" time="13:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100015#S00300"><p>The T&aacute;naiste is correct and those provisions enable her to act.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1214" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="13:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100015#S00400"><p>In fairness to Deputy O'Callaghan, he highlighted publicly the specific legal provisions relating to the tenure in office of the Garda Commissioner.  My only concern is to have an effective and accountable police service which keeps our communities safe and preserves our national security, which is what garda&iacute; do must do in their day-to-way work.  They protect our communities.  I have to support the actions that I believe will ensure the safety of our communities.  That is what guides my decision-making.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1239" speakername="Mary Lou McDonald" time="13:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100015#S00500"><p>The T&aacute;naiste is failing in that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1353" speakername="Brendan Howlin" time="13:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100015#S00600"><p>I find the T&aacute;naiste's strident response to the critical issues raised by other Deputies depressing.  That there is a growing level of crisis in and about An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na is undeniable.  It is not conjecture or fanciful thought.  Perhaps the most concerning development of recent days is the clear division opening up between senior civilian members and other members of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  The intention behind civilianisation of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and giving civilians senior roles was twofold, namely, to bring additional expertise that the Garda did not have into the heart of the force and to open up and change the closed culture that I, the T&aacute;naiste and others know exists within the force.</p>  <p>  In the past week, three senior civilian officers have sharply disagreed with the stance of senior Garda officers.  Mr. Gurchand Singh, the civilian head of analysis, made clear to the Policing Authority that the report on mistakes in the homicide figures were not his work.  He also made clear that he did not even get to read the report submitted to the Policing Authority, although he is the head of analysis.  Mr. Niall Kelly, the civilian head of audit, told the Policing Authority that the review of breath test figures repeatedly referred to by the most senior members of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na as an audit could not be regarded as an audit and was not done by him.  Then we had Mr. John Barrett, the civilian head of human resources, whose detailed recollection of meetings with the Commissioner regarding profoundly disturbing matters in Templemore clearly and flatly contradicted the assertion of the Garda Commissioner that their meeting was a short encounter over a cup of tea.</p>  <p>  The leadership of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na is in crisis management mode or, more accurately, crisis reaction mode.  It is staggering from one emergency to another.  It is clear that the ability of the Garda and its leadership to respond effectively to the cascade of crises is bringing this matter to a critical mass.  I am trying to use objective and dispassionate language.  I do not want to apportion blame, let alone seek to blame all of this on one individual, namely, the Garda Commissioner.  When the Commissioner was appointed, I hoped that she could bring about the fresh start the policing service required.  I also want to use objective language because the law requires the T&aacute;naiste, as Minister for Justice and Equality, to apply an objective test in this case.  There has been much talk of whether the T&aacute;naiste has confidence in the Garda Commissioner and barely a day goes by that she - or one of her colleagues - responds to that question.</p>  <p> There has been a learned but unnecessary intervention from the other side of the House claiming it is for the T&aacute;naiste rather than the House to decide whether she has lost confidence in the Garda Commissioner.  That intervention was unnecessary because it misses the essential point.  Section 11 of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na Act 2005 does not refer to whether anyone has confidence in the Commissioner but sets out a different, much simpler test in objective terms, that is, whether the continued role of the Garda Commissioner is in the best interests of the force.  My question is very simple and the T&aacute;naiste should apply that test now.  Does she believe the continuation in office of the Commissioner of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na is in the best interests of the force?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1214" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="13:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100015#S00700"><p>The Deputy raised a number of issues, the first of which relates to civilians who work in An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  The Government is committed to increasing the number of civilians who hold senior posts in An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1353" speakername="Brendan Howlin" time="13:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100015#S00800"><p>That was not the question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1214" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="13:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100015#S00900"><p>I will come to the Deputy's question.  It is absolutely essential that we have increasing civilianisation in An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and it is essential that those civilians have a constructive, positive working relationship with members of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  I am absolutely committed to ensuring there are more civilians in the Garda.  Part of the modernisation, renewal and change that is needed is to ensure this happens.</p>  <p>  I am very aware of the issues that have emerged at the Committee of Public Accounts and in evidence before the Policing Authority regarding the differences between some civilian members.  One of the issues the Deputy mentioned was addressed at the Policing Authority's most recent meeting in respect of one of the examples that he cited.  Both of these issues are before the Policing Authority and Committee of Public Accounts because that is where the documentation Mr. Barrett supplied was given.  This documentation has to be dealt with and I am sure it will be further explored.  The committee will want to find out what other people have to say about it.  I understand that it is not a minute of the meetings that were held but a personal note.  It would be very helpful if there was a minute of the meeting that took place but I have no doubt the committee will examine that matter.</p>  <p>  In the context of the Garda Commissioner and the ongoing work she is doing, she is implementing the recommendations of the Garda Inspectorate's report.  A range of initiatives and changes have taken place already.  It is in the interests of the force that this work continues and that we, in this House, do everything to ensure it continues with the oversight bodies we have set up.  That is the way forward and the right thing to do in terms of the public interest, An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and morale.</p>  <p>  I would like to see less politicisation of these issues and the oversight bodies being allowed to get on with their work.  I want to see the Committee of Public Accounts finishing its work on these issues.  As I said, I will take very serious note of the findings of the committee when its report is published.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1353" speakername="Brendan Howlin" time="13:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100015#S01000"><p>Every crisis, scandal and issue is carefully boxed off to an inquiry by GSOC or the Committee of Public Accounts - somewhere, anywhere - and things carry on.  Every Member can clearly see that the best interests of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na are not served by the <i>status quo</i>.  That the T&aacute;naiste cannot see this is a matter of great concern.  She and I have known each other for a long time and I believe her to be compassionate and a very capable politician.  I ask sincerely that she does not make herself an obstacle to doing what the people and vast majority of Members believe is clearly the right and essential thing to do.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1214" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="13:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100016#T00100"><p>I will do what I believe is the right thing to do.  That has been my guiding principle in politics - to support the right actions that need to be taken in my portfolio in the Department of Justice and Equality and the reform that we are committed to as a Government.  The work that is being led by the Commissioner is important.  The work being done by the oversight bodies needs to be supported.  As a Government and a House, we need to continue giving the resources to the Garda that it was starved of, making it impossible for it to do its job-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1311" speakername="John Lahart" time="13:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100016#T00200"><p>That has nothing to do with it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1214" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="13:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100016#T00300"><p>-----for six or seven years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1311" speakername="John Lahart" time="13:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100016#T00400"><p>Resources are not the issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1353" speakername="Brendan Howlin" time="13:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100016#T00500"><p>The question of resources is never an excuse for not doing a proper-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1289" speakername="Pat Gallagher" time="13:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100016#T00600"><p>The T&aacute;naiste without interruption, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1214" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="13:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100016#T00700"><p>I am not suggesting that it is an excuse.  Rather, some of the cultural and imbedded issues in terms of management that we are now seeing were not helped by a starvation of resources to An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  I ask the House to support the work of the oversight bodies.  Deputies have said time and again that they do not want to see political interference in the work of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  We have a proper and important job to do in terms of oversight and I have an important job to do in terms of policy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1353" speakername="Brendan Howlin" time="13:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100016#T00800"><p>Let us do it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1214" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="13:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100016#T00900"><p>As the Deputy will recall, motions in the House some weeks ago were not passed, but we had a detailed discussion on the issues that he has raised.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1240" speakername="Michael Lowry" time="13:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100016#T01000"><p>This House is convulsed by the proposed sacking of one individual, the Garda Commissioner, but I draw the T&aacute;naiste's attention to the fact that a decision of Bord na M&oacute;na last week effectively sacked 122 workers in Tipperary.  The decision of Bord na M&oacute;na's board of directors is having a major impact on the local community.  We do not agree with the decision or the justification for it that has been put forward, but we have been told emphatically that the decision will not be changed and we must work with it.</p>  <p>  It is in this spirit that, last Friday, we met the unions representing the workers at Littleton.  As one would expect, it was a highly charged and, at times, emotional meeting.  The five Tipperary Deputies attended the meeting and agreed to take a unified approach to the strategy to be employed.  We requested a meeting with the Minister for Communications, Climate Action and Environment, Deputy Naughten, which was held yesterday.  I thank him for being accessible and open and for showing a genuine concern for the plight of the workforce and community at Littleton.</p>  <p>  During the meeting, we had a useful and constructive exchange of views on the actions required.  We all came to the conclusion that there first needed to be a renegotiation of the redundancy package.  Second, we requested an extension to the closure date of April 2018.  Third, we asked that an alternative use for the remaining peat be examined.  Fourth, we asked for a plan for the utilisation of the existing bog, plant and facilities.</p>  <p>  A number of issues arise, one of which is the need to commence negotiations.  I call on the management of Bord na M&oacute;na and the unions to enter into negotiations without preconditions on the understanding that the Minister and the board are not averse to the idea of holding discussions on redundancy packages and a time extension.  I ask that the Government take responsibility in the matter, given that a cost would be involved in any time extension.  That cost should be considered in the context of Bord na M&oacute;na's payment of a &euro;10 million dividend to the State every year.  It should be possible for the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform to reduce that amount by the cost, or &euro;3 million, which should be set aside to ease the burden on the workforce at Littleton.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1214" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="13:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100016#T01100"><p>I thank Deputy Lowry for raising this important issue.  I recognise the difficulty, stress and challenge posed by the recent decision for everyone involved.  Having received the review conclusions, the company has begun a process of engagement with the group of unions and employees.  It has also confirmed that no redundancies are being contemplated in the current year.  That is an important point.</p>  <p>  I note the Deputy's comments about my colleague, the Minister, Deputy Naughten.  The Deputy accepts that the Minister is monitoring the situation closely and is acutely conscious of the decision's impact on Bord na M&oacute;na's employees.  The Minister has urged Bord na M&oacute;na to consider all opportunities for redeployment, a phased reduction in employment numbers and any other renewable technology opportunity that may arise in respect of Bord na M&oacute;na investments.</p>  <p>  As part of Bord na M&oacute;na's general strategy to move towards sustainable businesses based on renewable sources, pilot trials for the production of a biomass briquette have been conducted in the past 12 months.  This is a significant investment by Bord na M&oacute;na, which has confirmed its plan to begin large-scale production of the briquette.  It will soon seek planning and other approvals in that regard.  This will be a critical step in future-proofing the fuels business, as it offers the potential of sustainable and quality regional employment.</p>  <p>  The Minister held a series of meetings with the Bord na M&oacute;na group of unions and staff representatives as well as Tipperary's Deputies.  He will continue with those discussions.  He has called for engagement and imagination by all sides on devising a range of solutions and different outcomes for employees.  I do not doubt that he will take on board the particular points that Deputy Lowry has raised, but Bord na M&oacute;na is a major employer across the middle of the country and is exploring new opportunities for growth, particularly in renewable energy.  I hope that this will help the company not just keep current levels of employment, but grow it in a part of the country where, although there have been some successes, attracting foreign direct investment has traditionally been challenging.</p>  <p>  The Minister will bring a memo to the Government soon on establishing a new semi-State entity, BioEnergy Ireland, which will focus on the development of the biomass sector and exploit those skills currently available to Bord na M&oacute;na and Coillte.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1240" speakername="Michael Lowry" time="13:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100016#T01200"><p>Our first priority is to make the case for a time extension.  A ready argument for this relates to the 260,000 tonnes of peat that are piled up at various points around the bog.  The factory uses approximately 7,000 tonnes per week, which means that enough peat is available to keep the plant running for another 37 weeks.  That should be possible, as should a third harvest.</p>  <p>  The redundancy package for employees, especially those who are long serving and wish to exit the company, is not strong enough and needs to be renegotiated.  One employee has 40 years of service and is 63 years of age.  He would receive &euro;31,200 in redundancy.  This is a person who has given a lifetime of service, commitment and dedication to Bord na M&oacute;na.  The package must be renegotiated.  It includes a clause to the effect that, the longer one's service, the more one is penalised.  The current agreement is not fair or just and needs to be re-examined.  Will the Government play a part in ensuring that happens?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1214" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="13:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100016#T01300"><p>I recognise Deputy Lowry's concern for the individuals who are caught up in this situation.  The Minister has stated that he is examining the recommendations of the unions, Deputy Lowry and other Deputies and is open to exploring a range of options.  The suggestions that the Deputy is making today will be taken on board by the Minister.</p>  <p>  Regarding redundancy, I expect the Minister will discuss the matter with the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform with a view to examining the precise circumstances of the individuals involved.  The Minister, Deputy Naughten, will be familiar with the matter, but it is one for the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.101" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100017#U00100">Questions on Promised Legislation</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1289" speakername="Pat Gallagher" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100017#U00200"><p>We have only 15 minutes for questions on promised legislation so if Members observe the time limit, it will give others a chance.  I call Deputy O'Callaghan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1296" speakername="Jim O'Callaghan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100017#U00300"><p>Yesterday, the D&aacute;il Select Committee on Justice and Equality met to consider amendments to the Coroners Bill 2015.  We never got a money message in respect of it but that is an issue for another day.  However, we were informed by the Chairman, Deputy &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in, that the T&aacute;naiste had informed him she intends to bring forward issues concerning maternal deaths in a civil law and courts (miscellaneous provisions) Bill.  When will that Bill be published so we can know it will come before the committee?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1214" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100017#U00400"><p>I had given a commitment to Deputy Clare Daly recognising the importance of this issue she had highlighted, as had Deputy O'Callaghan and other members of the committee.  I am very keen that it would be passed before the summer.  There are a variety of legislative mechanisms or Bills I could use but I might also consider a stand-alone Bill.  I am meeting Deputy Daly later this afternoon to discuss that issue.  I emphasise I want to work with the committee to ensure that legislation is passed before the summer.  I recognise there are many families who have a very deep and serious concern around this issue and would like to see it being brought into law.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1289" speakername="Pat Gallagher" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100017#U00500"><p>We might be able to include all if we make the questions and replies short and snappy.  I call Deputy McDonald.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1239" speakername="Mary Lou McDonald" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100017#U00600"><p>We will see what we can do.  Yesterday, the Taoiseach indicated the T&aacute;naiste would be more than happy, in fact delighted it seems, to come before the House and make a statement on the matters surrounding Templemore and some of the issues we touched on during Leaders' Questions.  He also indicated the T&aacute;naiste would be quite happy to take questions in that regard.  I want to know when she proposes to do that.</p>  <p>  When she takes to her feet on that occasion, she also should shed some light on the case of Dara Quigley, a young woman who died by suicide on 12 April.  She had been detained by garda&iacute; some days previously under the Mental Health Act.  She had been walking naked in a Dublin street when detained.  Garda CCTV footage of this detention was posted on Facebook, a really deplorable and revolting turn of events, and something that has brought great hardship to her family and which clearly brought very great distress to Dara.  We mark her passing.  When we talk about Garda culture, reform and accountability, I suppose this is the rawest end, the sharpest end, of a deplorable culture of humiliation and disregard for human beings.</p>  <p>  I hope the T&aacute;naiste will, as the Taoiseach promised, come before the House to make her statement and take questions.  I hope also that she might shed some light on the accountability that will be held for the life of Dara Quigley.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1214" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100017#U00700"><p>In regard to the individual case the Deputy mentioned, everybody will be totally disturbed and appalled by the story that has been reported in the media and actions are following on from that.  As the Deputy knows, that has been reported and there is an investigation and a GSOC inquiry.  Of course, our thoughts are with that young woman's family, given the appalling and very sad sequence of events.</p>  <p>  No doubt, the Business Committee can discuss the question of Ministers appearing before the D&aacute;il.  I just want to make the point that I do not want to in any way cut across the work the Committee of Public Accounts is doing in regard to Templemore.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1253" speakername="Joan Burton" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100017#U00800"><p>I want to raise the issue of bogus or phoney self-employment whereby, as a condition of getting work, somebody is forced to become self-employed or to form a company.  It means the person's employer does not pay social insurance and that the person has very little protection in terms of labour law.</p>  <p>  When I was Minister and T&aacute;naiste, I set up a group drawn from the Departments of Social Protection and Finance to look at the issue.  My understanding is that the work on that has been complete for some time.  There was a public consultation process which ended well over a year ago and I understand the information is to hand.</p>  <p>  This issue of phoney self-employment involves a very significant number of people, including many low-paid and poor people.  I want to know why both the Minister for Finance and the Minister for Social Protection are refusing to publish this report.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1432" speakername="Mick Barry" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100017#U00900"><p>Time.  This is ridiculous.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1289" speakername="Pat Gallagher" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100017#U01000"><p>Thank you, Deputy Burton.  We want to give others a chance.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1253" speakername="Joan Burton" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100017#U01100"><p>When the Revenue Commissioners did a study of it about three years ago, it resulted in large amount of extra tax being recovered by the State because of the bogus self-employment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1214" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100017#U01200"><p>I will ask for the information in regard to that report to be sent to the Deputy.  While I do not have details as to when it will be published, I will ask both Ministers to liaise with the Deputy.  I am not familiar with the publication date.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1253" speakername="Joan Burton" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100017#U01300"><p>I have raised it with both Ministers-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1289" speakername="Pat Gallagher" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100017#U01400"><p>Sorry, Deputy.  There are others who want the opportunity to speak.  I call Deputy Troy.  I ask Deputies to consider their colleagues and make it short and snappy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1250" speakername="Robert Troy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100017#U01500"><p>The An Post network and its mail distribution centres face uncertain times.  The Bobby Kerr report is with the Government and the McKinsey report is currently under way.  There is huge anxiety and worry among the employees of An Post in the mail distribution centre in Athlone and in other areas of the An Post network.  The Minister with responsibility might update the House on when we can expect these reports to be published and debated in the D&aacute;il and on when we can expect a clear roadmap for the future of the An Post network and the mail distribution centres.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1214" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100017#U01600"><p>I will ask the Minister, Deputy Naughten, to respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1234" speakername="Denis Naughten" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100017#U01700"><p>I thank Deputy Troy for his questions. As he knows, this is something very close to my heart.  First, in regard to the post office network, I am one of the five Deputies who made a submission to initial review for the Bobby Kerr report and it is something I articulated when I was on the other side of the House in regard to constructive reform of the network.  The issue of the mail centres is also close to my heart, given there is one in my home town of Athlone.  No decision has been made in regard to any of these.  The board is considering reports that are being produced by the company.  The board has discussed some of these issues to date but no decisions have yet been made and there will have to be extensive engagement with the group of unions and with the IPU.  I understand the IPU has already commenced engagement with management.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1324" speakername="Frank O'Rourke" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100017#U01800"><p>The Planning and Development (Housing) and Residential Tenancies Act, which was passed in December 2016, introduced rent caps in rent pressure zones.  I am the representative of a rent pressure zone in Kildare North.  A number of rent reviews have been with the Department for nearly three months.  While the T&aacute;naiste might not be able to answer me, she might get her colleague or departmental officials to revert to me in this regard.  It has taken nearly three months to have a review carried out, which is causing a lot of stress and hardship for families and putting pressure on them.  Can the Government have this speeded up?  It is unacceptable that a review of a rent pressure zone would take nearly three months.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1214" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100017#U01900"><p>When the Minister introduced that initiative, he made it clear that there could be reviews.  I will ask him to correspond with the Deputy directly to see when that review in regard to Kildare will be finalised.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1232" speakername="Brian Stanley" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100017#U02000"><p>I want to ask about the commitment in the programme for Government regarding the cost of housing rents.  There are many people caught in the middle who cannot get on a local authority waiting list because they are over the &euro;25,000 or &euro;26,000 threshold and they cannot get a mortgage.  These are low to middle-income workers who are caught in that bind.  We know there is a huge housing crisis, that it is difficult to get private rented accommodation, that people have no security of tenure and that rents are sky-high, as demonstrated by the report this week by <i>www.daft.ie</i>.</p><p>What I want to highlight for the T&aacute;naiste is the fact that the Nevin Institute has put forward a proposal.  There is money with the credit unions, namely, &euro;8 billion in deposits.  There is money in pension funds which is earning 0.5% interest.  There is European Investment Bank, EIB, money.  There is money available.  I am not saying that there is a magic wand, but most Members agree with the cost-to-rent scheme contained in the programme for Government.  There is significant political support for it.  Such a scheme is badly needed.  What progress has been made in bringing that scheme into being in order that we might have developments of cost-to-rent apartments and housing built?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1214" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="13:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100018#V00200"><p>The Minister for Housing, Planning, Community and Local Government has announced a series of initiatives to increase housing supply and to make every effort to ensure that we can make rents more affordable and manageable and make social housing available.  He will be making further announcements in the coming weeks on a number of housing initiatives-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1232" speakername="Brian Stanley" time="13:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100018#V00300"><p>I asked about the cost-to-rent scheme.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1214" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="13:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100018#V00400"><p>-----and no doubt he will be considering the points the Deputy makes in respect of that initiative.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1289" speakername="Pat Gallagher" time="13:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100018#V00500"><p>With a little co-operation, we might get through all those who are offering.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1336" speakername="Lisa Chambers" time="13:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100018#V00600"><p>A Programme for a Partnership Government contains a commitment to increase access to safe and timely care close to patients' homes.  Recent figures from the National Treatment Purchase Fund, NTPF, show that, at the end of April, there were 2,281 people waiting for outpatient appointments at Mayo University Hospital.  These are people who were referred for necessary care and treatment by their GPs.  The length of the waiting list is leading to increased stress, anxiety, further medical complications and increased illness among those patients.  Clearly, the Government is failing in its commitment to provide timely access to care.  Another related issue is the fact that patients who choose to go north of the Border for treatment are having it paid for by the HSE.  Patients in my constituency of Mayo are availing of treatment across the Border.  When will the Government address the delays relating to the NTPF?  When will we see full and proper roll-out of that fund?  Is serious action being taken to address the delays being experienced by patients languishing on waiting lists?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1214" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="13:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100018#V00700"><p>As the Deputy will be aware, there is a budget again for the NTPF.  I indicated previously that hundreds of appointments would be made for patients so that they can benefit from treatment.  Notice of those appointments has begun to issue.  Over 300 patients have received appointments.  The process in this regard will continue and accelerate in the coming weeks and months.  In the meantime, as the Deputy will be aware, other initiatives are being taken by the Minister for Health.  He has access to the largest budget ever in the history of the State.  Of course, there is increasing demand on health services but it is important to note that almost 1.69 million patients received inpatient or day-case treatment in our hospitals in 2016, an increase of almost 40,000 on the previous year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1289" speakername="Pat Gallagher" time="13:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100018#V00800"><p>Deputy Martin Kenny is next.  Brevity, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1345" speakername="Martin Kenny" time="13:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100018#V00900"><p>The fracking Bill was brought through by my constituency colleague, Deputy Tony McLoughlin.  It is a magnificent Bill and there is progress being made steadily as it moves through the Oireachtas.  I seek an assurance.  The Bill has been changed or adjusted slightly to become an amendment to the Petroleum and Other Minerals Development Act 1960.  Will the Government set time aside to have it progressed through the Houses before the summer recess?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1234" speakername="Denis Naughten" time="13:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100018#V01000"><p>We are proceeding with Deputy McLoughlin's Bill on fracking.  My understanding is that, with the consent of the Business Committee, the intention is to take Report Stage in the House the week after next.  I intend to bring the legislation to the Seanad as quickly as possible and to have it enacted before the summer.  That was the commitment I gave to the House at the end of last year when the Bill was brought forward.  I gave a commitment that I am determined to have the legislation enacted.  It is my intention to have it enacted without undue delay.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1342" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="13:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100018#V01100"><p>On numerous previous occasions, I have asked questions about work on flood relief measures.  As the Minister, Deputy Naughten, will be aware, Roscommon and the surrounding counties have suffered terribly as a result of flooding.  I acknowledge and admit that work has been done in respect of flood defences.  My problem, as I have stated time and again, is that there is no dredging programme in place.  As a result, there is no real cleaning up of rivers being done.  We need to get this work done.  The T&aacute;naiste will have heard the adage, "Make hay while the sun shines."  It certainly is appropriate.  We have had six months of outstanding weather and I do not see diggers working on the rivers.  I do not see the programme that was promised for the River Shannon being put in place.  Members will know that rivers everywhere are choked up with peat and silt.  I am aware that this is not the T&aacute;naiste's area.  The Minister, Deputy Naughten, is pushing for this.  I implore the T&aacute;naiste to use the fine weather to get this work done.  We cannot wait for further floods to cause destruction to people's lives, as they have right along the Shannon.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1289" speakername="Pat Gallagher" time="13:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100018#V01200"><p>Four more speakers are offering.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1214" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="13:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100018#V01300"><p>I ask the Minister, Deputy Naughten, to answer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1289" speakername="Pat Gallagher" time="13:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100018#V01400"><p>I ask the Minister to be brief.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1234" speakername="Denis Naughten" time="13:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100018#V01500"><p>Deputy Eugene Murphy is correct.  This is most frustrating.  The previous maintenance on the Shannon was carried out under a different authority in a different Parliament.  This is a complex issue.  All of the semi-State companies are now sitting down with the Minister of State with responsibility for the OPW.  There is significant engagement ongoing.  A number of those semi-State companies come under the control of my Department and I have instructed each of them to facilitate the OPW in progressing this matter.  I reiterate that this is a complex issue .  It is not only a matter of the physical removal of the material; where that material subsequently goes also needs to be addressed as part of this process.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1432" speakername="Mick Barry" time="13:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100018#V01600"><p>In recent days, there has been media comment on the circumstances leading up to the death of the journalist and blogger, Ms Dara Quigley.  Very serious questions have been raised about the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and its treatment of the most vulnerable in society.  I will leave those questions for another day.  Today, I want to ask the T&aacute;naiste about the question of dual diagnosis.  Dara suffered from and struggled with mental health problems and addiction.  She received help from many agencies but what was available was not sufficient.  A particular problem was the lack of dual diagnosis services where psychiatric and addiction problems are treated together in a professional and properly-funded manner.  My question to the T&aacute;naiste is as follows.  Does she see a legislative pathway to addressing this problem?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1214" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="13:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100018#V01700"><p>I ask the Minister of State, Deputy McEntee, to answer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1337" speakername="Helen McEntee" time="13:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100018#V01800"><p>I offer my condolences to the late Ms Quigley's family and friends.  This was a terrible situation and what happened consequently was deplorable.  The issue of dual diagnosis is something that we have not dealt with in the past.  We know that in a significant number of suicides there is a link between drug or alcohol use as well.  We are developing a clinical programme on the issue of dual diagnosis.  We have appointed a national clinical lead who will work to develop a programme whereby if somebody is suffering from either a drug or alcohol problem that is leading on to a mental health problem, there will be a clear clinical pathway for our doctors and nurses, both within the acute hospitals and in primary care settings.  There is work well under way and we would be hoping to continue that during the year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1289" speakername="Pat Gallagher" time="13:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100018#V01900"><p>Following Deputy Durkan, we will have Deputies Mitchell and McConalogue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1322" speakername="Bernard Durkan" time="13:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100018#V02000"><p>The insurance (amendment) Bill is promised legislation, the purpose of which is to implement the report, Review of the Framework for Motor Insurance Compensation in Ireland.  I ask the T&aacute;naiste when the Bill is likely to come before the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1214" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="13:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100018#V02100"><p>Work is under way in relation to that Bill.  At this time, I do not have a date in relation to its publication.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1362" speakername="Denise Mitchell" time="13:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100018#V02200"><p>I want to refer to the general scheme of the social welfare and pensions Bill 2017.  Elements of the proposed Bill intend to deal with abuse in the welfare system.  However, I note the inaction to date of the Department in chasing up more than &euro;450 million owed to the State by companies the liabilities of which had to be covered by the taxpayer.  Will there be provisions in the proposed Bill which will lead to the Department getting tough in the context of recouping the moneys owed to the State by such companies?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1214" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="13:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100018#V02300"><p>The heads of that legislation were cleared by Cabinet on Tuesday and it is now going for pre-legislative scrutiny.  Hopefully, the Bill will be published after that.  There will be an opportunity to raise that issue in committee.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1244" speakername="Charlie McConalogue" time="13:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100018#V02400"><p>The programme for Government contains a commitment to encourage young farmers to take up careers in farming.  However, unlike its predecessor, the young farmers scheme relating to the national reserve, which was announced a few weeks ago by the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine, does not accommodate farmers who are currently undertaking agricultural courses.  The deadline for basic payment scheme returns and for making applications in respect of those schemes is Monday next.  I ask the T&aacute;naiste to liaise with the Minister to ensure that the conditions are changed in order to accommodate - as was the case previously - those young farmers who are pursuing courses and make sure that they are given time to apply.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1214" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="13:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100018#V02500"><p>That is a very tight deadline.  I assume there was a reason to change it.</p><p>I will ensure the Deputy's concerns on the matter are brought to the attention of the Minister today and I will ask him to link with the Deputy to discuss the matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1221" speakername="Niall Collins" time="13:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100019#W00200"><p>I wish to raise an issue which came to my attention recently in my constituency office.  I appreciate it does not come under the direct supervision of the Minister in her Department but she may be able to furnish us with some clarity.  A person came to me whose business failed and they find themselves in mortgage arrears.  The banks are moving on them.  They are also in arrears with the Revenue Commissioners.  The Revenue Commissioners have an attachment order on their bank accounts.  Recently, in order to survive and subsist, the person applied for and was granted family income supplement.  Upon receiving the first payment of the family income supplement and the arrears due from the application date, the Revenue reached into their bank account and took the payment.  As I understand it, the payment is an income supplement for the family to allow them to live day to day.  Through her good offices, could the Minister please get clarity on whether the Revenue Commissioners are allowed to take the family income supplement payment from a person's bank account in cases where they have an attachment order on the bank account?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1214" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="13:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100019#W00300"><p>I suggest that the Deputy would raise the issue with the Minister for Social Protection, but I will have it brought to his attention as well.  I suggest also that Deputy Collins would inform the person who came to see him that it would be worthwhile contacting Abhaile given the financial support, information and advice that is available.  It could well be that the person could get support for the situation they face and have such queries answered.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.149" nospeaker="true" time="13:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100019#W00400">Companies (Amendment) Bill 2017 [Seanad]: Second Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1272" speakername="Pat Breen" time="13:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100019#W00500"><p>I move: "That the Bill be now read a Second Time&rdquo;.</p>  <p>  A copy of my speech together with a short information note is being circulated to Members present in the House, which give will them additional useful information to what I will outline in my speech.  I am pleased to bring the Companies (Amendment) Bill 2017 before the D&aacute;il today.  This is a very short Bill, with just two sections, dealing with a very specific issue in the law on financial reporting by companies.</p>  <p>  The issue is the application of section 279 of the Companies Act 2014.  That is the section that permits certain companies to prepare and file Companies Act financial statements using the American accounting standard, known as US generally accepted accounting principles or US GAAP.  As things stand, that section will no longer apply after December 2020.  As Deputies will be aware, the provisions of the Bill before the House today were originally proposed as part of the general scheme of the Companies (Statutory) Audits Bill 2017, which was published by the Government earlier this year, in February.  While drafting of that Bill is well under way and publication is planned for the summer, it has become apparent to the Government that the issue dealt with in today's Bill may require more immediate attention.  Indeed some Deputies have raised this issue and called for those provisions in the general scheme of the statutory audits Bill that relate specifically to section 279 to be taken out of that proposed Bill and brought forward as a matter of urgency.  Accordingly, I am pleased to say today that the Government has responded to those calls for urgency and given the relevant provisions their own stand-alone Bill, which is before the House now.  I hope Members will welcome it.</p>  <p>  The history of this issue dates back to the Companies (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act 2009, when the Oireachtas first enacted the possibility for some companies to use US GAAP.  Under Irish company law, companies are generally required to prepare and file their financial statements using one of two sets of accounting standards, namely, international financial reporting standards, IFRS, as adopted by the European Union, or Irish generally accepted accounting practices, Irish GAAP, in accordance with EU law.  With the 2009 Act, an exception to this rule was introduced allowing particular types of companies to prepare their financial statements using US GAAP.  Those provisions were later amended in the Companies (Amendment) Act 2012 and then re-enacted as section 279 of the Companies Act 2014.</p>  <p>  In short, section 279 permits companies that are not listed on a regulated market in the EU and that meet certain other criteria to prepare and file their financial statements using US GAAP rather than using either IFRS or Irish GAAP.  This provision was intended to facilitate companies that are registered in Ireland but are listed in the US.  Once a company is listed in the US, it is subject to the rules of the Securities and Exchange Commission and is obliged to prepare and file financial statements in the US in accordance with US GAAP.  Without section 279, that company would also have to prepare and file a separate set of financial statements using IFRS or Irish GAAP.  It would have to prepare two very different sets of financial statements in respect of the same financial year.  At the time the provision was introduced, the Oireachtas accepted that this would be an administrative burden on those companies that was not merited.</p>  <p>  The Oireachtas also framed the provision as a temporary measure, with an end point after which it could not be used.  That was due to an expectation that the Securities and Exchange Commission would permit the use of IFRS for the relevant companies.  There were also international efforts toward convergence between US GAAP and IFRS.  The Securities and Exchange Commission still does not permit IFRS for companies known as US domestic issuers and it seems unlikely it will do so in the near future.  Furthermore, the discussions on convergence have not come to a conclusion.  Given that the considerations which gave rise to the provision are still relevant, it is appropriate to review the end date before it passes.  In the event that this date is not extended beyond the current deadline of 31 December 2020, companies will have to prepare and file two different sets of accounts according to two different accounting standards for financial years ending after that date.</p>  <p>  Last September, the Department conducted a public consultation on the impending deadline in section 279.  It received 23 responses from a range of stakeholders, and all are available on the Department's website.  Virtually all the submissions were in favour of extending the deadline beyond 2020.  While some respondents advocated an extension with no end date, most other respondents felt a ten year extension would be appropriate.  The Department also spoke to the Irish Auditing and Accounting Supervisory Authority.  The views of the Minister for Finance were also sought.  As a result, the Government has decided that it is appropriate to extend the deadline by a further ten years.  The main reasons for this decision include, first, the fact the public consultation showed support for an extension among stakeholders such as members of the accounting profession and representative bodies of business.  It is important to point out there were no objections.  Second, the circumstances that gave rise to the deadline in section 279 have not improved.  Third, the relevant companies have been using US GAAP for several years now, so it is easier to compare historical figures if the format remains the same in future.  Moreover, neither the Department nor the Irish Auditing and Accounting Supervisory Authority is aware of any complaints with the use of US GAAP in Ireland.  Therefore, section 1 of the Bill provides that section 279 will continue to apply to financial years ending no later than 31 December 2030.</p>  <p>  Apart from the deadline, one of the other conditions that is currently in section 279 is that the financial statements must comply with all the financial reporting requirements of Part 6 and its associated Schedules in the Companies Act.  The financial statements must be in line with our national law.  That important obligation will remain unchanged by today's Bill.  As well as extending the deadline, the Bill has a second function, which is to address the fact that the use of section 279 is not entirely without concern.  Some of the companies that qualify to use US GAAP are companies that came to Ireland from the US following a so-called inversion process.</p><p>Many of these companies have brought or grown their investment in Ireland.  In some cases, their businesses in Ireland are substantial.  I have met representatives of some of those companies myself when I was doing trade missions to the United States.</p> <p> Nevertheless, inversions can be damaging to Ireland&rsquo;s international reputation.  As Deputies may be aware, they have received negative attention in the US.  Ireland&rsquo;s standing abroad must also be borne in mind.</p> <p> The availability of section 279 for companies has been suggested as a potential factor in attracting US companies that are inverting to Ireland.  In that light, the proposal in the Bill to extend the deadline in section 279 could be seen as a measure to encourage more company inversions in future.  Accordingly, the Government is proposing to close off section 279 at this time to any new companies.  Therefore, section 1 of the Bill introduces a new criterion for qualification.  That new criterion is the requirement that a company has been registered in Ireland before the commencement of this Bill.  That point has to be made quite clear, particularly in an international context.</p> <p> In summary, section 1 of the Bill extends the deadline for companies using US GAAP for a further ten years, bringing that deadline to the end of 2030.  Section 1 also provides that any company that forms after the Bill comes into operation will not be eligible.</p> <p> Section 2 of the Bill is technical and provides for the commencement of the Bill.  It is intended to commence the Bill as soon as possible after enactment.</p> <p> I would like to mention the timing of the Bill and the reason for some urgency.  The existing deadline of 2020 may be over three years away, but companies that rely on section 279 are requesting certainty on the issue well in advance of this date.  They have made representations to the Government and Members of this House asking that the Oireachtas reconsider that deadline at this stage, rather than in a few months as originally intended.</p> <p> This is for two reasons.  First, the companies would need to introduce new accounting systems to prepare financial statements in either IFRS or Irish GAAP.  Second, both IFRS and Irish GAAP require comparative information in respect of the preceding financial year.  This information must be restated in terms of IFRS or Irish GAAP, as the case may be, when IFRS or Irish GAAP is first used.  In effect, this requires restatement of two earlier balance sheets.  If the current deadline of 2020 stands, the companies are clear that they will need to start their preparations straight away.</p> <p> The Government accepts that companies need clarity now as to whether the deadline in section 279 is to be extended.  For that reason it has agreed to introduce the provisions that are now in section 1 of this Bill earlier than was originally planned.  For the same reason, the Government has also placed a priority on the enactment of this Bill.</p> <p> The Bill is pragmatic, timely legislation that addresses the needs of businesses while taking long-term reputational issues into consideration.  It respects the importance of transparency for third parties.  They will continue to have access to financial information in a format that is comparable with the information that is already available on these companies.  Finally, it respects the policy of proportionate regulation.</p> <p> I commend the Bill to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1221" speakername="Niall Collins" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100020#X00200"><p>Fianna F&aacute;il supports the swift transposition into Irish domestic law of the Companies (Amendment) Bill 2017.  The Bill will extend the current expiry date of 31 December 2020 to enable qualifying companies, incorporated in Ireland, to prepare and file financial statements using US Generally Accepted Accounting Principles, US GAAP, rather than International Financial Reporting Standards, IFRS.  The extension is for ten years to December 2030.</p>  <p>  In 2009, under a Fianna F&aacute;il-led government, a temporary exemption was introduced that enabled companies to prepare their financial statements in accordance with US GAAP.  This was subsequently referenced under section 279(2) of the Companies Act 2014.  The Bill will give long overdue legal certainty and clarity to the companies concerned by strengthening the regulatory competitiveness of Ireland in this area and secure jobs into the medium term.  This is more salient than ever with Brexit on the horizon and a more competitive business landscape likely in the US under the new administration.</p>  <p>  There was an impending requirement for SEC-listed and Irish incorporated companies to file accounts under both US GAAP and IFRS.  However, a previous convergence project between both standards has stalled.  Fianna F&aacute;il has pressed for this expiry extension over the last 18 months and on Committee and Report Stages of the Companies (Accounting) Bill 2016 in the D&aacute;il, in order to safeguard the 8,000 high skilled jobs regionally located by these companies in Ireland.</p>  <p>  Legal certainty was urgently needed by these companies who in the absence of any extension to the 2020 expiry date would have had to start making extensive preparations to meet the standards required by IFRS guidelines.  The deadline for the 2020 expiry date would effectively have been 2018.</p>  <p>  It has been estimated that the cost of introducing and implementing this IFRS requirement would be a minimum of $20 million before the end of each company&rsquo;s financial year in 2017, due to the reallocation and introduction of extra resources and staff training, while streamlining the systems required to meet these compliance obligations.</p>  <p>  It is therefore a damning indictment of successive Fine Gael-led governments in failing to do everything within their power to safeguard these high quality jobs, which number approximately 8,000 in this case.  It was only after Fianna F&aacute;il indicated on Report Stage of the Companies (Accounting) Bill 2016 in the D&aacute;il that we were going to introduce an amendment in the Seanad to extend the current expiry date that the Minister - magically at the eleventh hour - was able to fast forward legislative proposals at Cabinet last week to show cause on this issue.  This amendment flagged by Fianna F&aacute;il has expedited the legislative process for this issue and has thankfully awoken the Government.</p>  <p>  Fine Gael has constantly kicked this issue to touch, showing tacit prioritisation and publishing the heads of another Bill, the Companies (Statutory Audits) Bill, in February to address this issue.  However, this would have kicked the can further down the road until the second half of 2017 at the earliest, as companies continue to incur costs due to inaction.  This is all the more astounding considering that similar exemptions are currently in place in a number of European countries, including Switzerland, France, the UK, the Czech Republic and Germany.</p>  <p>  In conclusion, we are happy to support the Bill in its entirety.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1327" speakername="Maurice Quinlivan" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100020#X00300"><p>Sinn F&eacute;in supports the introduction of the Companies (Amendment) Bill 2017.  The Bill is short, technical legislation which will have a positive impact on certain companies doing business in Ireland.  This amending legislation will extend the current expiry date of 31 December 2020 to enable qualifying companies incorporated in Ireland to prepare and file financial statements using US Generally Accepted Accounting Principles, commonly known as GAAP, rather than International Financial Reporting Standards, IFRS.  The extension provided for in the Bill is for ten years to December 2030.</p>  <p>  This continued exemption provides for an ease of doing business in Ireland and spares some companies the costs associated with switching systems.  The Bill also contains a new requirement that only companies registered in Ireland before the commencement of the Bill will benefit from its provisions.  Sinn F&eacute;in welcomes the insertion of that requirement in the Bill.  This is being included to prevent future inversions which have a damaging effect on Ireland's international reputation.</p>  <p>  With this extra criteria, extending the deadline until 2030 cannot be seen as Ireland encouraging further inversions.  Any measure that benefits Ireland's international reputation is welcome.</p>  <p>  I have met with the coalition for Irish international companies on a number of occasions, most recently last week, and they were anxious to get this Bill passed to avoid unnecessary financial expenditure if it were to be delayed.  The companies concerned, as Deputy Niall Collins said, employ over 8,000 people in high quality skilled jobs across the State.</p><p>Should the current deadline of 2020 stand, they will need to start preparations for an alternative strategy straight away.  I understand the Bill passed through the Seanad quickly last month with cross-party support.  I hope it can proceed as quickly as possible.  The Minister of State has our full support in this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1272" speakername="Pat Breen" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100021#Y00200"><p>I thank Deputies Collins and Quinlivan for their and their party's support for this Bill.  They certainly understand the urgency of it.  I thank the Deputies as well for their contributions to this afternoon's debate.</p>  <p>  The Bill, as I said, may be technical, but its impact will be practical.  That is the important thing about it.  I believe it is an appropriate and measured response to the needs of business at this point in time.  We need to respond to those needs.  It also represents a balanced approach, as it takes into account the needs of those who rely on financial statements for information.  It is heartening to see that there is general support across the House for this Bill.  Given that level of general support there is good reason to hope that we will be able to make progress on the Bill in an efficient manner.  I look forward to further debate as we progress through the various Stages in this House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.156" nospeaker="true" time="14:10:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.157" nospeaker="true" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100021#Y00400">Companies (Amendment) Bill 2017 [Seanad]: Referral to Select Committee</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1272" speakername="Pat Breen" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100021#Y00500"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That the Bill be referred to the Select Committee on Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation pursuant to Standing Orders 84A(3)(<i>a</i>) and 149(1) of the Standing Orders relative to Public Business.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.159" nospeaker="true" time="14:10:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.160" nospeaker="true" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100021#Y00700">Topical Issues Matters</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1289" speakername="Pat Gallagher" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100021#Y00800"><p>I wish to advise the House of the following matters in respect of which notice has been given under Standing Order 29A and the name of the Member in each case: (1) Deputy Charlie McConalogue - the report into defective concrete blocks in Donegal; (2) Deputy Niamh Smyth - waiting times for needs assessments; (3) Deputy Thomas P. Broughan - HSE funding withheld from the Irish Wheelchair Association and pay scales in section 39 organisations; (4) Deputy Donnchadh &Oacute; Laoghaire - intensive care for young adults who are seriously ill at home; (5) Deputies Eoin &Oacute; Broin and Brian Stanley - the issue of rent increases; (6) Deputy David Cullinane - development on the north quays in Waterford; (7) Deputy Thomas Byrne - delays in provision of occupational therapy for children in Meath; (8) Deputy Ruth Coppinger - the delay in processing maternity benefit payments; (9) Deputy Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in - Coeliac Awareness Week, 8-15 May; (10) Deputy Carol Nolan - the use of private ambulances in the midlands region; (11) Deputy Clare Daly - primary school places for Swords in September 2017; (12) Deputy Fiona O'Loughlin - second level school places for children with special needs in the Newbridge area; (13) Deputies Br&iacute;d Smith and Richard Boyd Barrett - the provision of an update on the plight of Ibrahim Halawa; and (14) Deputy Jackie Cahill - funding to address the shortfall from the Irish Cattle Breeding Federation, ICBF, levy.</p>  <p>  The matters raised by Deputies Charlie McConalogue, Eoin &Oacute; Broin and Brian Stanley, Thomas P. Broughan, and Jackie Cahill have been selected for discussion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.162" nospeaker="true" time="14:10:00" ><p>Siting suspended at 3.25 p.m. and resumed at 3.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.164" nospeaker="true" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100022#Z00200">Ceisteanna - Questions - Priority Questions</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.165" nospeaker="true" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100022#Z00250">Aftercare Services Provision</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.166.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1231" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100022#Z00300"><p><i>1.</i> To ask the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs the number of young persons under and over 18 years of age that were on a waiting list to access an aftercare worker at the end of 2016 by area, in tabular form; the average length of time a young person spends on the waiting list before gaining access to an aftercare worker; and if she will make a statement on the matter.  <b>[22522/17]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.167.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1231" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100022#Z00400"><p>I wish to ask the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs about the number of young persons under and over 18 years of age who were on a waiting list to access an aftercare worker at the end of 2016 by area, in tabular form, and the average length of time a young person spends on the waiting list before gaining access to an aftercare worker.</p></reply>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1358" speakername="Katherine Zappone" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100022#Z00500"><p>Tusla has informed me that in 2016, a total of 605 young persons left care that year - the reason for this being that they had reached 18 years of age.  At the end of 2016, Tusla has indicated that 1,055 young persons in care were aged 16 or 17 years of age.  Of these 432 - 41% - had been allocated an aftercare worker.  Tusla has advised that it does not collate data on the waiting periods before an aftercare worker has been assigned.  I have made the tabular data requested by the Deputy available for inclusion in the record of the House.</p><p>Each year, between approximately 500 and 600 young persons will turn 18 years of age while in care.  In recent times, I understand that about 75% of 17-year-olds in care were in foster placements while a further 20% approximately were reported to be placed in residential settings.  The remaining 5% are in other settings, for example, a disability setting or supported lodgings.  </p><p>I am conscious that the transition to independent adulthood can be challenging for many young people.  This is particularly true for children and young people in care.  Planning for leaving care needs to begin in the years prior to leaving care and continue as part of the care planning process.  This preparatory work is facilitated by a social worker and is based on collaboration with the young person, their carers and partner agencies.  It is specific to the individual young person's needs.  During the preparation for leaving care an aftercare worker is introduced to the young person.  They are involved in the preparation for the leaving care process.  Tusla prioritises children in residential care and short-term foster care for the early allocation of an aftercare worker.  Children in long-term foster care with an allocated social worker have their aftercare plan developed with the social worker.</p><p><i>Additional information not given the floor of the House.  </i></p><p>If their plan is to remain living with their foster carers, on a case-by-case basis, it may be considered best practice that they would be allocated an aftercare worker when they are in their 17th year.  I believe this is a pragmatic approach which matches needs to available resources.  </p><p>Children 16 and 17 years with an allocated aftercare worker at end December 2016:<table><tr><th><b>Area</b></th><th><b>Number of 16 and 17 year olds in care</b></th><th><b>Number with allocated aftercare worker</b></th></tr><tr><td>Dublin South East-Wicklow</td><td>48</td><td>33</td></tr><tr><td>Dublin South West-Kildare-West Wicklow</td><td>91</td><td>31</td></tr><tr><td>Dublin South Central</td><td>62</td><td>8</td></tr><tr><td>Midlands</td><td>63</td><td>49</td></tr><tr><td>Dublin North City</td><td>121</td><td>26</td></tr><tr><td>Dublin North</td><td>56</td><td>27</td></tr><tr><td>Louth-Meath</td><td>70</td><td>39</td></tr><tr><td>Cavan-Monaghan</td><td>19</td><td>10</td></tr><tr><td>Kerry</td><td>24</td><td>17</td></tr><tr><td>Cork</td><td>143</td><td>52</td></tr><tr><td>Carlow-Kilkenny-South Tipperary</td><td>70</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td>Waterford-Wexford</td><td>59</td><td>20</td></tr><tr><td>Donegal</td><td>29</td><td>19</td></tr><tr><td>Sligo-Leitrim-West Cavan</td><td>22</td><td>22</td></tr><tr><td>Mayo</td><td>20</td><td>20</td></tr><tr><td>Galway-Roscommon</td><td>63</td><td>24</td></tr><tr><td>Midwest</td><td>95</td><td>29</td></tr><tr><td><b>National Total</b></td><td><b>1,055</b></td><td><b>432</b></td></tr></table></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1231" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100022#Z00600"><p>I thank the Minister for her response.  The goal of aftercare was to introduce a statutory duty on Tusla to prepare an aftercare plan for young people.  I have been spokesperson for children and youth affairs for 12 months and in those 12 months, I cannot say that I have been convinced that it is being delivered.  I have to hand last year's Empowering People in Care, EPIC, report, which spoke about how young people do not get access to aftercare.  We do not even collate the data and do not have a proper system for understanding who is being identified as needing these social care workers.  There are huge gaps and anomalies.  While I appreciate that Tusla is doing its best to organise planning, there is no connectivity between social care workers.  Some young people might only meet for the first time the social care worker who is writing their aftercare plan.  This sort of engagement is leading to children ending up on council housing waiting lists straight after leaving residential care.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1358" speakername="Katherine Zappone" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100022#Z00700"><p>On the Deputy's comments about moving forward, particularly entitlements to aftercare plans for children in care, as she is aware, there are pending amendments to the Child Care Act 1991 that will place a statutory obligation to provide an aftercare plan before the young person leaves care.  I intend that this provision will be commenced with effect from 1 September 2017.  I have secured the funding needed to recruit additional aftercare workers to enable Tusla to deliver this new commitment in full.  In some situations, the child's social worker may continue in the role of an aftercare worker when the child reaches 18 years.  My Department working to implement the changes that are needed.  There is no doubt that improvements are needed and I intend to ensure that they happen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1231" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100022#Z00800"><p>Hearing that funding has been secured is welcome but could we look at this in a different way?  When I hear about Youth Advocate Programmes, YAP, Ireland Ltd, the wonderful work it does and how it is trying to source funding for advocates, I wonder why we are not investing in the groups that are already there.  Why do we not give funding to EPIC and YAP?  We know there is a shortage of social care workers and that we are struggling to recruit them but we know we have good agencies that can work with and empower young people.  We do not need to reinvent the wheel.  What these organisations are looking for is funding.  Why do we not get behind these organisations and give them the support they need?  They are on the ground and know this system and how it works.  The fact that we do not have the personnel to fill the posts shows that it is one thing giving funding but, regrettably, when we cannot hire the personnel, we are still left with the same problem so we are not moving forward and I have a huge concern about this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1358" speakername="Katherine Zappone" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100022#Z00900"><p>I appreciate the work of EPIC and organisations like it.  We are supporting them.  In terms of our statutory and legal responsibilities relating to children in care and in aftercare, I have been informed by Tusla that 18 aftercare managers will be recruited.  Each manager will manage one of the 18 teams across the country.  The composition of each team will be based on Tusla's analysis of the requirements of the area.  For example, it may be appropriate, particularly in rural areas, to retain the social worker allocated when the young person was in care on the aftercare team.  I know Tusla has given aftercare a high priority in respect of its business plan, which I have requested.  Among the plans to improve outcomes in the area are the implementation of the national aftercare policy through area-based dedicated aftercare teams, as well as the continued roll out of a inter-agency aftercare steering committee in all areas, which will be there to work with and in collaboration with the groups identified by the Deputy.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.173" nospeaker="true" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100023#AA00050">Child Detention Centres</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.174.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1287" speakername="Donnchadh &Oacute; Laoghaire" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100023#AA00100"><p><i>2.</i> To ask the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs the expected date for the publication of the review into Oberstown juvenile detention centre; and if she will make a statement on the matter.  <b>[22486/17]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.175.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1287" speakername="Donnchadh &Oacute; Laoghaire" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100023#AA00200"><p>Baineann s&eacute; seo leis an ionad i mBaile an Oibricigh.  This question regards the report on Oberstown juvenile detention centre, a matter which has been raised by many Deputies in the House and at committee meetings.  The report is now substantially overdue.  It was due to be published on 20 December 2016.  I ask the Minister to make a statement on the status of the report.</p></reply>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1358" speakername="Katherine Zappone" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100023#AA00300"><p>I understand the Deputy's question relates to the report on the operational review that was commissioned by the Oberstown board of management.  It is one of a series of reports commissioned by Oberstown with the aim of improving services and ensuring good practice for the children and young people.  </p>  <p>  Four independent reviews have been commissioned by the Oberstown board of management, including the operational review and reviews of security, behaviour management and health and safety.  The security and health and safety reviews have issued reports to the Oberstown board of management, while the behaviour management review is expected to report in the near future. </p>  <p>  The operational review was a snapshot study undertaken within a particularly short timeframe and designed to help the campus to constructively move forward.  I want to ensure that the report's recommendations are implemented as appropriate as soon as possible.  The chair of the board has indicated to me that many of the recommendations have already been implemented, that they mirror recommendations from the other reports and are very much in keeping with the approach advocated by the board of Oberstown, national policy and my own views.  An action plan adopted in January 2017 continues to drive improvements on the Oberstown campus.</p>  <p>  In considering the operational review report, it is important to guard against any potential legal risks and unintended consequences of publication.  The board commissioned independent legal advice which it is currently considering.  A decision on publication will be made as soon as possible. </p>  <p>  To ensure full consideration of recommendations made in all of the reviews I have established an implementation group chaired by Professor Kilkelly with representation from Oberstown staff and management, my Department, the IMPACT trade union and a child development expert.  The group is tasked with analysing the recommendations of each of the reviews with a view to their implementation while taking account of resource and policy implications.  The implementation group regularly reports on progress to the board of management and to my Department.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.177" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1287" speakername="Donnchadh &Oacute; Laoghaire" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100023#AA00400"><p>I thank the Minister for her response.  Last Tuesday there was due to be a conference in Smock Alley on the future of Oberstown to which many Members were invited.  That event was cancelled.  I had expected that in that context and close to that date, the Minister might publish the independent review or at least make a statement on the matter.  The Minister is correct that I am referring to the operational review.  It would also be of value to be updated on the other reports.  </p>  <p>  The operational review was first due to be published on 20 December 2016.  Next week, there will have been a six-month delay in its publication.  That is not good enough.  I understand that there are legal consequences and things that need to be taken into account.  However, this was a matter of considerable public debate, concern and interest.  Oberstown staff and management also have a considerable interest in the report.  While there has been some progress, the Minister has not even given a ballpark timeframe for publication.  She has said publication will be after legal advice has been considered and all issues have been dealt with.  We need a sense of when the report will be published.  It is already six months overdue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1358" speakername="Katherine Zappone" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100023#AA00500"><p>I appreciate the Deputy coming back to me with that question.  The report and its recommendations have been produced.  The implementation group which I put together is considering them in the context of the recommendations made by the two other reports which have been completed and the fourth report, which is expected in the near future.  </p>  <p>  The event to which the Deputy referred has been rescheduled and will take place on 29 May.  At that stage there will be an opportunity to hear about the progress made and the implementation of the key recommendations of the various reviews that are promoting improvement in Oberstown.  I hope that there will then be an opportunity to see the recommendations of the operational review.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.179" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1287" speakername="Donnchadh &Oacute; Laoghaire" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100023#AA00600"><p>We need a more concrete commitment to when this report will be published.  This process cannot go on indefinitely.  I ask the Minister, if she can, to give a more specific indication of when it will be published.</p>  <p>  The cessation from 30 March onward of the practice of putting persons under the age of 18, whether on remand or on committal, in adult prisons was a welcome development.  It is a very welcome step.  In the context of issues in regard to facilities and buildings in Oberstown, we need to know that everything is in place to allow that cessation to happen.  Mercifully, the current number of detainees in Oberstown is lower than it was several months ago.  It has fallen from the mid-30s to the mid-20s.  If that number were to change and were there to be a full cohort of 17 year olds in the facility, all units would have to be open to ensure that the facility could work to the best of its ability.  Can the Minister ensure that all units will be open as soon as possible and all required resources will be available to Oberstown to ensure that this additional cohort and all children in such a situation are kept and educated in Oberstown and that the facility is capable of doing so?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1358" speakername="Katherine Zappone" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100023#AA00700"><p>The report is with the Oberstown board of management, which is seeking legal advice.  It is not my place to step into that process but I hope and expect that the board will soon make decisions on the report.  It is in everyone's interest to await legal advice before proceeding.  As the Deputy has indicated, there has been much positive news in regard to youth justice and Oberstown, such as the ending of the practice of children being sent to adult prisons.  There is also a new bail supervision scheme that is contributing to the reduction in the number of detainees in Oberstown.  It is difficult to say that this indicates a trend.  There have been improvements to the units in Oberstown and an increase in its perimeter security.  Part of the work of the implementation review group has to do with ensuring the required units will be put back in place in Oberstown.  The number of detainees there is considerably lower than previously.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.181" nospeaker="true" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100023#AA00750">Child Care Costs</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.182.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1231" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100023#AA00800"><p><i>3.</i> To ask the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs her views on widespread forecasts that child care fees will increase in September 2017 as a result of increased demand under the single affordable childcare scheme, in view of the fact that up to 9,000 households that were initially promised targeted levels of subsidy will now receive the universal level of subsidy.  <b>[22523/17]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.183.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1231" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100023#AA00900"><p>I ask the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs her views on widespread forecasts that child care fees will increase in September 2017 as a result of increased demand under the single affordable childcare scheme in view of the fact that up to 9,000 households that were initially promised targeted levels of subsidy will now receive the universal level of subsidy.</p></reply>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.184" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1358" speakername="Katherine Zappone" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100023#AA01000"><p>I do not anticipate widespread increases in child care fees as a result of increases in subsidies this September.  There is no evidence of plans to increase fee levels.  Fees charged to parents are at the discretion of child care providers, who operate independently of the State.  There are many factors that influence the fees charged, including a range of cost pressures and market forces.  There are many reasons why a child care provider may raise its fees, in particular if child care fees have changed very little in recent years.  While I do not expect a widespread increase in fees, my Department will actively monitor the trends over time.</p>  <p>  The policy paper on the affordable childcare scheme, ACS, which the Government approved last October examined the option of imposing price caps on child care providers to prevent the erosion of subsidies through fee inflation.  The policy paper noted that among the potential benefits of price caps would be preventing fee inflation and providing certainty for and equity between parents.  However, it also noted problems that might arise.  The introduction of price caps would represent economic regulation of the market.  That would raise legal and economic questions as to what constitutes a fair price for child care.  The policy paper recommended that there should be no initial price cap but the option of price caps should be considered following the independent review of costs and an examination of the initial market response to higher subsidies.  The independent review to be commissioned later this year will include an examination of variation in costs and fees.  It will be a key input into any future consideration of the potential benefits and risks of introducing price caps.</p></speech>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.185.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1358" speakername="Katherine Zappone" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100024#BB00100"><p>Estimates of take-up of the September 2017 measures suggest that up to 70,000 children will benefit from the improvements I am making.  The fact that so many children will benefit from subsidies this September is a very positive development and represents a significant precursor to the affordable child care scheme when even more families will benefit.  I am hopeful that the Bill on the affordable child care scheme will be published before the summer recess.  I cannot guarantee this but we are working very hard to make this a reality before mid-July.</p></reply>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.186" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1231" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100024#BB00200"><p>I thank the Minister for her response.  The reason I asked the question, in light of the fact the scheme would be in before September 2017 and the fact that people were led to believe what their entitlements might have been, is that there will be a gap between the qualifications for certain families.  There are approximately 9,000 families more or less who will not qualify but who will get the subsidy.  Fees are not publicly displayed and are quite hard to get.  There is no databases as to what the standard is throughout the country for fees.  Given that there is so much talk about the sector around wages and the difficulties of recruitment and retention of staff in the sector, this might have been seen as an opportunity by some employers or cr&egrave;ches to pass it on directly to staff.  My concern is around the numbers of people who will not be receiving anything other than the 50 cent per hour.  If the subsidy is passed on directly to the staff then the parents would have the shortfall, leaving them worse off than they would have been in the previous year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.187" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1358" speakername="Katherine Zappone" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100024#BB00300"><p>The Deputy highlights the point that not all families will receive subsidies.  This, in itself, will be a factor that child care providers must take into account when setting their fees and in deciding to raise or not raise the fees.</p>  <p>  The Deputy spoke of the numbers of families who may not benefit right away in September because we not have the full affordable child care scheme that we had hoped and intended to have by then.  We are estimating that it is possible that up to 9,000 children and their families may not be eligible for some subsidy this September, but these are families who are really closest to the threshold of the affordable child care scheme.  It is, however, an estimate because it is impacted by fees and whether or not families choose to engage in the use of child care providers who are registered so they can access the subsidies.  It must be stressed that the potential number of children and families in this regard is an estimate and we cannot be more precise in advance.  We will monitor that, as I have indicated, for any possible chance of increase in fees.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1231" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100024#BB00400"><p>This all hinges on when the ICT infrastructure is up and running - in 2018 or whenever the Minister can indicate that it will be up and running.  Will those parents then be in a position to get payments backdated if there was a difference in the fees during the year?  They have been disenfranchised in the 12 months from 2017 to 2018.  I know they will receive the universal level of subsidy, but it was announced in Budget 2016.  Will the Minister say if it will be backdated?  If they thought they were going to be treated equally it would be a comfort for the parents.  The 9,000 families I speak of, and the Minister has hinted at this, are in the gap between those who have the medical card and those who have the GP visit card.  Is there going to be any retrospective payback for these families?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.189" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1358" speakername="Katherine Zappone" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100024#BB00500"><p>Most of those 9,000 families that may not benefit, and who we had anticipated could benefit, would have incomes that are near the maximum income threshold for the affordable child care scheme.  They would have received low levels of subsidy under the affordable child care scheme.  It is not possible to specify the precise income levels that may be affected as the means test for the GP visit card takes into account not just the family's income but also the amount the family spends on housing costs and child care costs and other expenses.  Based on the HSE data on the typical family incomes of GP visit card holders it is estimated that on average this group may have received in the region of &euro;12 per week subsidy.  That is on the basis that they have full-time child care so it is not necessarily the case that everybody is going to lose that amount.  What we will do in September 2017 is a massive improvement and a very big first step.  I am not going to say "Never say never" to taking a look at the possibilities of the retrospective issue, but it is really important to accept and acknowledge that this is a huge leap forward and we are moving towards it.  It is not just about getting the IT right: obviously we must pass the legislation also.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.190" nospeaker="true" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100024#BB00600">Social Workers Recruitment</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.191.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1325" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100024#BB00700"><p><i>4.</i> To ask the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs the status of the recruitment of social workers for children in care who still have not been allocated a social worker; the actions she will take to ensure that such children are allocated a social worker without delay; and if she will make a statement on the matter.  <b>[22524/17]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.192.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1325" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100024#BB00800"><p>My question relates to children in care who have not been allocated a social worker and I have raised this issue with the Minister before.  These are obviously very vulnerable children and there seems to be a real difficulty in meeting targets for recruitment of social workers.  Perhaps the Minister could give an update on that situation.</p></reply>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.193.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1358" speakername="Katherine Zappone" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100024#BB00900"><p>This is an important issue.  It is a continuing priority of mine to address the problem of children in care who do not have an allocated social worker.  I am informed by Tusla that 99% of children in residential care and 100% of children in special care have an allocated social worker.  However, I am concerned to note that 7% of children in foster care do not have an allocated social worker.  When social workers are being allocated, children recently received into care and those with mental health issues, a disability or challenging behaviour, are prioritised.  Tusla is also focusing on intervening at an early stage of a family difficulty through social care and family supports.</p>  <p>  When a child who has not been allocated a social worker is placed in foster care, the placement is closely monitored and supported by the duty social work team.  In addition, I have been informed that the child's foster family will be visited by a link social worker.  This link worker will have oversight of the child's welfare until a social worker can be allocated.</p>  <p>  I place a high priority on addressing the number of children in care who are without an allocated social worker.  I secured additional funding for this purpose in 2017, and Tusla is now in the second year of a three year plan to ensure the allocation of a social worker to all children and young people who need one.  The recruitment environment for social workers is very challenging.</p>  <p>  My Department will continue to monitor progress closely in this regard.  I will continue to engage directly with the Tusla board and senior management team over the course of the year to review the progress being made in reducing the numbers of children in care who do not have an allocated social worker.</p></reply>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.194" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1325" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100024#BB01000"><p>I thank the Minister.  I note that we have been invited to the launch of Tusla's new child protection and welfare strategy on Monday week.  I do not know if measures will be announced then.  I believe they need to redouble their efforts.  I do not know what methods they use to recruit social workers but I have made the point before that there are many people in the State who are qualified social workers but who do not work in social work.  Some of these would be relatively mature people.  There is a very big turnover of people, some very young, working in this very challenging area.  I hope Tusla will look at other ways of recruiting.</p>  <p>  There is an article in today's media about the report of the independent national review panel in respect of children who died while in State care or who were known to social services.  The chair of the panel, Helen Buckley, said "Some of these reviews reveal the level of pressure being experienced by social work departments due to increased reporting and shortages of staff."  Clearly it is a real concern and I know it is a concern also for the Minister, but we need to see a sense of urgency about ensuring we have enough social workers in the system.  They are dealing with really vulnerable children.  I ask that the Minister draws this question to the attention of Tusla.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.195" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1358" speakername="Katherine Zappone" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100024#BB01100"><p>Yes.  Of course I am aware of the national review panel report.  It adds to the motivation and the need to ensure a redoubling of efforts in recruitment and retention.  I am indicating that I also do not find it acceptable and I agree with the Deputy in this.  In addition I acknowledge, and may have previously pointed out, the aspects of the actions Tusla is taking to recruit and retain staff.</p><p>I may refer to some of those actions later in response to another question.  It is important to recognise that all children in care are risk assessed.  Those at the highest risk are allocated a social worker.  We also have duty social work teams carrying out monitoring, as well as link social workers.  It is not as if the children are without social workers.  It is part of the effort to ensure the children who are in care without a specifically allocated social worker are not at risk in respect of their care.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1325" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100025#CC00200"><p>I understand the efforts that are being made and that there is a team in place.  However, we are talking about extremely vulnerable children.  The targets would not exist if there were not an understanding that they are required.  When people who work in this particularly stressful and difficult job are contending with understaffing, their work becomes more stressful.  It becomes a vicious cycle in respect of being able to retain staff when they are dealing with such pressurised work along with inadequate staffing.  I urge the Minister to consider whether there may be other ways of recruiting.  The recruitment efforts may need to be rejuvenated in some way.  We have to ensure we have an adequate number of social workers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.198" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1358" speakername="Katherine Zappone" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100025#CC00300"><p>I agree with the Deputy.  Relatively recently, I met the Irish Association of Social Workers, a professional organisation.  I examined many of these issues and the suggestions they put forward.  In respect of the ability to recruit, Tusla is implementing a national transfer policy.  To assist retention and the attractiveness of Tusla as an employer, it has put in place a transfer mechanism to facilitate social workers wishing to relocate to another part of the country.  If a post is offered for an area other than the one in which the person lives, the possibilities at regional level are being considered in order for him or her to take a post where he or she lives.  Tusla is also providing continuing professional development according to the 2017 business plan, which expects to deliver more than 650 courses by the end of the year.  There are efforts being made by Tusla in respect of retention as well as recruitment to support the children in care.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.199" nospeaker="true" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100025#CC00400">Child and Family Agency Services</minor-heading>
    <ques id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.200.q" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1231" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100025#CC00500"><p><i>5.</i> To ask the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs the number of cases relating to adult retrospective disclosures that have been referred to Tusla since 2011; the number which remain unallocated; and the number of these that are deemed high risk. <b>[22525/17]</b></p></ques>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.201.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1231" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100025#CC00600"><p>This is to ask the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs the number of cases relating to adult retrospective disclosures that have been referred to Tusla since 2011, the number which remain unallocated and the number of those that are deemed to be at high risk.</p></reply>
    <reply id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.202.r" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1358" speakername="Katherine Zappone" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100025#CC00700"><p>A historical or retrospective disclosure is where an adult discloses abuse experienced in childhood.  I understand that the overwhelming majority of such disclosures are about sexual abuse.  Tusla has advised me that there were 1,895 historical and retrospective cases on hand at the end of March 2017.  Tusla has also indicated that, included in these cases and during the first three months of this year, it received 354 reports from adults about past abuse.  Of the cases on hand, 1,141 were allocated to a social worker and 754 were awaiting allocation.  All these referrals have been reviewed by a social worker and 120 have been categorised as high priority.  While this is a very complex and worrying situation, the safety of children now is my top priority.</p>  <p>  It is very important to point out that all child protection referrals which allege current or past criminal activity are referred to An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  Tusla's focus is to screen historical and retrospective disclosures for any indication of current risk to children.  In cases of urgent need, the disclosure is acted on immediately.  Tusla has a limited role where there is no evidence of a current risk to children.  In respect of the adult making the disclosure, Tusla may assist him or her in accessing HSE counselling services.</p>  <p>  Tusla's policy in assessing risk relating to an adult about whom an allegation of sexual abuse has been made is strictly guided by the principles set out in the Barr judgment.  In such cases, the person must be informed of the nature of the allegation and the identity of the person who is making the complaint.  Tusla must adhere to the practice of due process and fair procedure.</p>  <p>  Tusla has put in place a service improvement plan, with experienced social workers dealing with the high priority cases.  Medium and lower priority cases will be dealt with by social workers drawn from other services and provided with training and supervision.  I have asked Tusla to report to me monthly on the progress it is making.</p></reply>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.203" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1231" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100025#CC00800"><p>I thank the Minister for her response.  I, too, acknowledge that it is a very complex issue.  Although I have a script in my hand, I feel compelled to depart from it.  People do not realise the gravity of this matter.  It is about what happens when a person makes a disclosure in adulthood about an incident that happened during childhood.  The person has found the courage to come forward, yet we are saying it is a matter for An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and that Tusla has dealt with it fully in recording the disclosure.  Having made that first step, the person has to come forward again to ask An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na to take up the mantle.  Although the person about whom the disclosure has been made could still be actively involved in the community, childminding, working in the local GAA club or whatever, Tusla has done its job, dotted its i's and crossed its t's, and sent the discloser on to the Garda.  The discloser has been kicked back again and may lose his or her courage.</p>  <p>  We need to tighten up on the roles and responsibilities between Tusla and An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  There should be a bridging period in terms of people's age, for example, if somebody aged 18 or 19 has gone to college and sought independent counselling and support outside the family for the first time.  We should be encouraging such people.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.204" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1358" speakername="Katherine Zappone" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100025#CC00900"><p>I take Deputy Rabbitte's points.  It is important to have ongoing collaboration between Tusla, An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and, in terms of counselling services, the HSE.  My response focuses on the legal responsibility of Tusla in this regard and on identifying where there are other responsibilities there too.  In her follow-up question, the Deputy suggested that the ways in which these responsibilities are defined may leave those who have taken the decision to contact a statutory agency and make a disclosure feeling that they may not get the proper supports and services.  My understanding is that there is a process that people go through when contacting Tusla.  They are supported in that regard.</p>  <p>  From Tusla's perspective, the most important thing is to identify whether there are any children currently at risk.  Tusla also provides referrals where HSE counselling supports are required, as well as support for the person to go to An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  That is not to say that the systems are perfect.  I am trying to indicate clearly what Tusla's responsibilities are.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/dail/2017-05-11a.205" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1231" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/dail2017051100025#CC01000"><p>I thank the Minister.  Adult disclosure referrals are being categorised as low priority.  I asked the chief executive of Tusla when he was before an Oireachtas committee recently how adult disclosures are categorised, and they are low priority.  That set off alarm bells for me.  I still think about the children who are at risk.</p>  <p>  We need a strategy that seeks to educate, create awareness and encourage adults who have experienced abuse to come forward and thereby reduce child sexual abuse.  We also need to use the information to protect further generations of children and young people from abuse.  This is one of the dark parts of our history.  The Minister and I and all Members of the Oireachtas will be defined by how we address these matters.  We must bring all agencies together to clear the retrospective and historical cases as quickly as possible.  I have requested that we have a section within Tusla that is singularly responsible for retrospective cases in order that we can clear the backlog.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>