<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.2" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00"><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 14:30</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00"><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.4" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00"><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.5" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300002#A00050">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300002#A00100"><p>I have received notice from Senator Kathryn Reilly that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, she proposes to raise the following matter:<blockquote><br />The need for the Minister for Health to outline the reasons a promised podiatry post at Cavan hospital, sanctioned in April 2012, will now not be filled because of the HSE recruitment embargo, given that the post was planned as part of the national foot care programme.</blockquote>I have also received notice from Senator Tony Mulcahy of the following matter:<blockquote>The need for the Minister for Social Protection, arising from her reply to the Adjournment debate of 23 October 2012, regarding domiciliary care allowance, to outline the qualification of each assessor without identifying the assessor; and if she will further outline whether he or she carries out any other role for her or any other Department.</blockquote>I have also received notice from Senator Trevor Ó Clochartaigh of the following matter:<blockquote>The need for the Minister for Justice and Equality to discuss the announcement in October of an additional 170 vehicles for the Garda Síochána; to provide a breakdown by county and district of the allocation of these vehicles; if these vehicles have been allocated and, if not, the timescale for their distribution.</blockquote>I regard the matters raised by the Senators as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment and they will be taken at the conclusion of business.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.7" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300003#B00100">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.8" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300003#B00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, statements on the new children's hospital, to be taken at 3.45 p.m. and conclude not later than 4.30 p.m., with the contributions of group spokespersons not to exceed five minutes and the contribution of the Sinn Féin Member not to exceed two minutes, with the Minister to be called on to reply not later than 4.25 p.m.; and No. 2, statements on the economy, to be taken at 4.30 p.m. and conclude not later than 6 p.m., with the contributions of group spokespersons not to exceed six minutes and those of all other Senators not to exceed three minutes, with the Minister to be called on to reply not later than 5.50 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300003#B00300"><p>I welcome the passing of the children's rights referendum.  We all have many lessons to learn from the referendum.  The low turnout was, whether we like it, an indictment of the political system and how all of us in all parties and none - I will not apportion blame - worked towards the referendum.  The result was not a resounding "Yes" but I still firmly believe the changes to be brought forward in the Constitution will be important to protect children.  When the dust settles the House should examine and debate in a calm and clear way the advice the Attorney General gave the Government on the publication of the Government's booklet to ensure we do not make again the mistakes we made in this referendum.  I believe the turnout was low for various reasons and I will not apportion blame in any way, shape or form.  We must look back and wonder why only 32% of our people voted in the referendum.  We must look with a critical cold eye at what we can do differently and how we can represent and present a referendum in future.</p><p>I wish to follow up on several issues which I have raised on a number of occasions.  The Minister for Health will come to the House this afternoon, and I am sure our health spokesperson will also raise this matter with him.  Where stand the cuts to home help with regard to the 950,000 hours which have been taken out of the system this year?  A cut of 450,000 home help hours was signed off by the Minister in mid-October for a paltry €8 million saving.  All of us receive letters, telephone calls and e-mails from families about home help hours being arbitrarily cut.</p> <p>I asked Senator Bacik if she had raised the issue with the Minister for Health last week and she said that she had.  I am sure Fine Gael Senators have also raised the issue with him.  I have written to him as many of my colleagues in Fianna Fáil have done.  Will the cuts stand or will the Government reverse what I am sure we all agree, if we leave politics at the door, are the most unfair and unjust cuts to people who badly need assistance and want to be cared for at home?  The financial argument for the cuts simply does not stand up.  The less care people receive in their homes will mean that more of them, mainly elderly people, will end up in hospitals.  They do not want to be there.  They do not want to be cared for in hospitals and we all know this.</p><p>Will the Government reverse the cut of 950,000 hours introduced this year?  I remind Senators that, on page 38 of the programme for Government, Fine Gael and the Labour Party signed up to not only maintaining home help, carers' allowances and home care packages, but to increasing them.  Savage cuts have been made in the sector that affect people throughout the 26 counties of the Republic of Ireland.  I believe the Minister will take the opportunity today to clarify once and for all whether he will proceed with the cuts and whether he will admit that a mistake has been made and decide to reverse these utterly unjust cuts.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300004#C00200"><p>I join in Senator Darragh O'Brien's welcome for the result of the children's rights referendum and agree that lessons must be learned.  There is a concern for us as politicians and wider civil society that a large portion of civil society could support such a measure, yet there was a low turnout.  I suspect that the last couple of days of the campaign brought about a change of heart on the part of some persons who would have voted for the referendum.  I strongly agree that we need to reflect.</p><p>I also agree with the Senator about the cuts to the home care package.  The House needs a wider debate on the budget and budgetary measures.  Perhaps we could have a full session, in the same way that committees have done, where Members of all parties could express their full and informed thoughts on various aspects that are under consideration for the upcoming budget.  I believe the House has something to say on the subject.</p><p>I welcome Ireland's appointment to the United Nations Human Rights Council.  It is a great achievement for the country and is an endorsement of our history of human rights advocacy.  I congratulate the Tánaiste, Deputy Eamon Gilmore, on the part he played in bringing about that appointment.</p><p>I also welcome the Tánaiste's comments on gay marriage and the need for a constitutional referendum in this regard.  We have made progress in the recognition of non-formal couples in recent years.  As the Tánaiste rightly pointed out, however, it is merely a halfway house and does not represent equality.</p><p>I note that eight Irish authors have been longlisted for the IMPAC awards.  It is a great achievement for a country of this size that our mark on the world of literature is so strong.  I hope the eight authors who have been longlisted will be shortlisted.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" speakername="Jillian van Turnhout" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300004#C00300"><p>I congratulate the Tánaiste and Minister for Foreign Affairs, his Department, the permanent missions of Ireland to the United Nations in Geneva and New York, and everyone else involved in Ireland's successful bid to secure a seat on the UN Human Rights Council in Geneva.  It will be an interesting three years and I look forward to Ireland's renewed focus on the implementation of the Human Rights Council's universal periodic review recommendations now that we have member status.</p><p>With very warm wishes I say &quot;well done&quot; to everyone involved in the successful passage of the referendum on children's rights, especially to the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs, Deputy Frances Fitzgerald.  This is a gratifying time for me personally and professionally.</p> <p>I have campaigned for many years for this referendum and I anticipated the margin to be much more narrow as this is a difficult issue involving profound social change.  Much comparison has been taking place in the media with previous referendums and I note this referendum pertained to social change.  As this was a major difference from previous referendums, it is difficult to make comparisons.  I believe this referendum will be transformative and the full extent of its impact is not yet known.  A case will appear before the Supreme Court in ten or 20 years time, after which people will know that on Saturday, 10 November 2012, they made a difference.  However, I also urge caution in dismissing the &quot;No&quot; vote.  I spoke at many meetings throughout the country and some of that &quot;No&quot; vote reflected a real fear of the social services and this is something to which Members must listen.  One cannot simply dismiss the &quot;No&quot; vote by suggesting they all were anti-government.  People have had negative experiences, in the current period or previously as children or as family or friends.  Consequently, the Leader should facilitate the appearance in the House of the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs at the earliest opportunity to discuss in particular the report of the task force on the child and family support agency, which was published in July.  Members must play a role in shaping that new agency and they should address the fears people have raised.  In addition, they also could discuss the fifth report of the special <i>rapporteur</i>on child protection and the Ryan report implementation plan, on which a three-year progress report was published earlier today.  I also ask the Leader to ask the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs to introduce the adoption Bill to this House first.  This issue is intricate and some of the relevant concerns were raised ensuring the debate.  This legislation will require timely and well thought out debate.</p><p> I ask the Leader to schedule a debate in a timely manner after the Supreme Court judgment is given on 11 December.  As the date on which the Supreme Court will give its detailed judgment is known, Members should have a timely debate to discuss the full implications.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="Rónán Mullen" time="14:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300005#D00400"><p>I also congratulate the Government on the passage of the children's rights referendum and acknowledge Senator van Turnhout's particular role.  I also congratulate and wish well those on the different sides who brought the benefit of their life experience and expertise to sincere contributions on the debate.  Unfortunately, I cannot congratulate the Government on the manner in which it treated taxpayers' money.  The Government must have been in some kind of cocoon of unreality in which it deluded itself into thinking it could spend taxpayers' money in whatever way it wished.</p><p>I also was struck by the comments made this morning by the Tánaiste and Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade, Deputy Gilmore, on his hopes for a referendum on redefining marriage in effect because there also appears to be an air of unreality about that.  One must be clear about a couple of points.  The Tánaiste claims that gay marriage is a human right and while that might be what he thinks, it is not what the Universal Declaration on Human Rights says about marriage.  It is not what the International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights says about marriage and it is not what the European Convention on Human Rights states about marriage because each of the aforementioned human rights documents understands marriage to be the union of a man and a woman.  Moreover, each of these documents is many times more important than is Deputy Eamon Gilmore's declaration on human rights.</p><p>That said, I am not afraid of a debate.  Bring it on and let us have a full and open debate about this.  One could call it the second children's rights referendum because central to that debate will be the right of a child to be brought up by two biological parents in a low-conflict marriage and that the State shall not do anything to lessen the preference for that situation in the laws that apply.  I make this point with full regard of course to people's rights to protections of various kinds that already have been passed in the law, in however flawed a way notwithstanding.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="14:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300005#D00500"><p>What about the rights of children of these arrangements?  They have no rights at all.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300005#D00600"><p>Senator Mullen to continue, without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="Rónán Mullen" time="14:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300005#D00700"><p>However, the Tánaiste appears to have learned very little from the children's rights referendum debacle.  The history of referendums dealing with social and ethical issues is interesting because there is a pattern.  The political elite convince themselves of the necessity of liberalising stupid old traditional Ireland.  Opinion polls appear to heavily support them in the early days and the media all are onside.  Two months before the referendum polling, opinion polls are even more emphatic in suggesting the constitutional change will go through.  Thereafter however, there is debate and the final result is either a terrible shock to the political and media elite or an almighty scare, such as was evident last weekend.  If the Supreme Court has adjudged the Government of the day to have acted unconstitutionally, no matter, because even if the referendum had not succeeded the other day, we probably would have a second bite of the cherry in due course.  The Government should brush up on its social history before running in blithely with naive claims about what constitutes authentic human rights, as it certainly is not a version supported by the international human rights instruments.</p> <p> On the subject of children's rights and children's welfare, it is astonishing that although 12 Senators raised the issue of the illegal and dangerous advice being given by counselling clinics to women seeking abortion, the Minister has still not seen fit to come into this House to make a statement, or to go into the other House to which he is even more accountable under the Constitution.  On five occasions, women were told to hide their abortions from their doctors.  One woman was told twice that if abortion complications arose after her surgical abortion, she needed to tell medical staff in the hospital that she had a miscarriage.  In the HSE service, the woman was told that in the case of any future pregnancies after abortion, she could tell her doctor that this was her first pregnancy.  I am afraid that I, and I think other Senators, will not be able to let this go until the Minister faces up to his responsibilities and makes a statement about his concern on this issue.  I will ask the Leader again what I asked him last week, namely, for the Minister to come to the House on the matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300006#E00200"><p>I support Senator Mullen's last point that the Minister owes this House an explanation on what is going in regard to the Irish Family Planning Association clinics, which are funded by the State, the health and pregnancy of pregnant mothers and the advice they are getting.</p><p>  Congratulations are due to the public who voted children's rights into the Constitution.  We have done something good for society and we can stand proud on that.  We must await the Supreme Court decision, as others have said, but the Government faced a terrible dilemma in the past few days.  The question arises as to why we need a Government booklet.  Are we now saying the Referendum Commission's booklet would have been adequate?  Perhaps that is the case but we must recognise the Government has a duty to inform and clarify.  From the start, it was clear to everybody that the Government was recommending a &quot;Yes&quot; vote.  That is something which needs to be teased out.  I do not want to see &#8364;1 million thrown away if the Referendum Commission booklet will do.  Let us have that debate in mid-December, as Senator van Turnhout said.  It would be very welcome if the Leader put it on the agenda.  </p><p>  The public is seething about pensions to bankers in banks bailed out by the taxpayer.  Given the fear about home help cuts, mortgage and household debt issues, the Government must find a way around this.  Will the Leader ask the Minister for Finance, Deputy Noonan, to look at this because together we must act for the people?  We should put a surtax on everyone in receipt of a pension above &#8364;100,000 or we must have preconditions to bailout money.  Anyone who is getting a hand-out of that nature, which is taxpayers' money, should not be getting it free<i> gratis</i> and there should be conditions to prevent it being used for pensions for bankers who let us down.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300006#E00300"><p>We should have a debate after 11 December when the decision of the Supreme Court is made known and we see exactly what went wrong.  There is no question but that the Government made a hames of this referendum because the booklet sent was costly, unnecessary and biased and it caused so many people to stay away from the polls last Saturday.  The reaction to it was unbelievable.  People felt they were being misled by the document sent by the Government and, in the circumstances, voted "No" or stayed way.  Fortunately, enough people went to the polls - roughly 33.5% - and voted "Yes".  It is a vital amendment of the Constitution and it is has been a success from the point of view that it has passed.</p><p>The Government has learned lessons.  One lesson it has learned is that in the next referendum it holds - there have been approximately 80 proposed amendments of the Constitution - it may be beaten but so be it.  That is another day's work and we will debate that again.  </p><p>I commend the country for getting a seat on the UN Human Rights Council, which is very worthwhile.</p> <p>I commend the efforts of people in the Government like the Tánaiste and Minister for Foreign Affairs, as well as Bono, who secured it.</p><p>I resent the fact that the Tánaiste and Minister for Foreign Affairs has stated that we are restoring our good name around the world.  There is nothing to restore and our position regarding human rights is second to none as far as we are concerned.  We won a seat on the UN Security Council on 1 January 2001, when Fianna Fáil was in power and Mr. Brian Cowen was Minister for Foreign Affairs.  The Tánaiste has gone on television and radio to say that &quot;our reputation is being restored.&quot;  How can a reputation for human rights be restored when it has not been damaged?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1143" speakername="John Whelan" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300007#F00200"><p>With great difficulty.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300007#F00300"><p>Did we ask for the Senator's advice?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300007#F00400"><p>It is a very important decision for the United Nations that Ireland has a seat on this body.  I also reject the criticism of Trócaire by the chairman of the Fine Gael Party, Deputy Charles Flanagan-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300007#F00500"><p>The Senator is way over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300007#F00600"><p>He criticised the excellent work of Trócaire in the Middle East and its very honest approach-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300007#F00700"><p>The Senator is way over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300007#F00800"><p>------to the intrusion of Israel into Palestinian lands.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300007#F00900"><p>I call Senator Moloney.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300007#F01000"><p>I hope members of the Fine Gael Party will bring this up at the meeting this evening and tomorrow.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300007#F01100"><p>The Senator is way over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300007#F01200"><p>Is Senator Leyden leading for Fianna Fáil today?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Maloney" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300007#F01300"><p>I raise the issue of analysis of death by suicide figures, which indicate an alarmingly high rate of suicide in Kerry, Cork city and Offaly, at 50% above the national average.  I also commend our colleague in the House, Senator John Gilroy, who has been travelling around the country, meeting interested parties and collating information on suicide.  He is a <i>rapporteur</i> on suicide for the Oireachtas health committee and doing some great work.</p><p>  It is a pity it has taken so long to fill the post of director of the National Office for Suicide Prevention following the resignation of Mr. Geoff Day.  I call for the formation of a task force to probe the issue and determine why rates of suicide are so high in these areas.  I know the answers are difficult to find and neither I nor other Members in the House have them.  We should at least try to do something to determine those answers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300007#F01400"><p>As the Cathaoirleach was not here last week, he may be glad to hear for the first time-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300007#F01500"><p>He will take up the Senator on her remarks last night.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300007#F01600"><p>I was standing up for the Leader last night.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300007#F01700"><p>The Senator did it very well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300007#F02000"><p>I thank the Senator very much.  I have said that if we are to play and beat the banks at their own game, we must possibly take our business elsewhere.  I suggest to the Seanad we start with the post office and credit unions.  As a Senator, I cannot accept that the Government is unable to do anything about the pensions of the great, the good and the Gods.  Why are we part of a Government that is unable to do anything?  It seems to be a massive contradiction, as the purpose of a government is always to do the right thing and bring about the right type of action.  There was plenty that could be done to the ordinary worker, such as the introduction of the universal social charge at the stroke of a pen.  I suggest the Government should introduce the solidarity social conscience claw-back, SSCCB, or a moral duty.  If we cannot do anything, we should not be part of the Government.  Banks are what they are because they get what they want from people and use it as they wish.  Are we to say that the Government should have the same privilege?</p><p>Senator John Whelan is entirely right in saying that if the cap fits, we should wear it.  There are unctuous payments and handshakes for incompetence.  Obscene payments, whatever the job, organisation or quarter, must be challenged, particularly when made outside the retirement age.  I would like the Minister for Finance to come to the House to explain exactly how we will act, especially if we are to call ourselves part of the Government or Members of the Upper House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" speakername="Jim D'Arcy" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300007#F02100"><p>Like others, I congratulate the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs, Deputy Fitzgerald, on the magnificent success she has had with the recent referendum.  The people, particularly the children of Ireland, will forever be in her debt.</p> <p>We have talk of another referendum but there should be a moratorium on referenda for four years because referendum fatigue is setting in.</p><p>Will the Leader inquire from the Minister for Education and Skills whether he intends to urge Student Universal Support Ireland, SUSI, to speed up the grant application process for third level students?  Students and their families are reaching the end of their tether on this issue, which is leading to great distress.  Members of the Joint Committee on Education and Social Protection met SUSI officials this morning and while I appreciate there was a large number of applications this year, with more than 65,000 first-time applications, and it takes a long time to get through them, of the 20,000 determined so far, more than 9,000 have been refused, which leads me to the conclusion that with the centralisation of the system everyone is trying to secure a grant.  It is difficult but it is imperative that students receive their grants before Christmas.  Will the Leader ask the Minister about this because, otherwise, students will have to leave the third level system?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300008#G00200"><p>I add my voice to those welcoming the historic election of this country's representatives to the human rights council of the UN.  The Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs and Trade urged this to every incoming delegation and perhaps that played some small role in this.</p><p>  I also very much welcome the result of the referendum on children's rights and draw attention to the fact that this House played a significant role.  Last Thursday, a large number of Members changed their arrangements to take part in an historic debate to give the first opportunity for the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs to put the Government's position clearly before the public, which was important.</p><p>  Both of these developments make it opportune for us to have a debate on human rights and what exactly they are.  There are some in this House, such as my colleague, Senator Mullen, who feel that they are either static or can be rolled back.  I take a different view.  My opinion is that human rights are something that are capable of continual expansion as our understanding of the human personality grows.  Within my lifetime, a referendum on children's rights was seen as impossible and regarded as outlandish.  Children were supposed to be seen and not heard.  Gay rights certainly were not as part of human rights and they certainly are now, whatever the technical definition that mean-minded people will seek to impose upon and to limit human rights.  Human rights should be expanded as far as possible.  Legislation is needed to flesh out the children's rights referendum.  We need it to be resourced properly.  At the time of the Roscommon incest case, we had the guardian<i> ad litem</i> programme which I was involved in through this House.  It was not properly resourced, and, therefore, it did not operate properly.</p><p>  Taking into account the business of human rights, what about the issue of suicide, which was so correctly and courageously raised on the other side of the House?  Where is the national suicide prevention officer?  Nothing has been done about this for the past year.  The Government motion tabled about suicide does not mention the post; it just congratulates the Government here and there.  I will table an amendment asking for this officer to be appointed.  As a European and not just an Irishman, I am bitterly ashamed that we see today that in the wake of yet another suicide in Spain, this time of a prominent political figure, it has been acknowledged for the first time that Spanish banks have put 400,000 people out of their homes.  Where are the human rights in this when people on a mass scale all over Europe are being ejected from their homes while in this country, where we fought for centuries against eviction, we are having evictions?  Let us have a stop to this and let us confront the banks-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300008#G00300"><p>Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300009#H00100"><p>Let us confront the banks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300009#H00200"><p>Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300009#H00300"><p>I seek a debate on human rights and would like this included in it.  As the IRA said in the old days, "We have not gone away."  The money has not gone away either.  It has gone into the pockets of billionaires in America and Europe and it should be taken back from them to rehouse the people who have been evicted.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" speakername="John Kelly" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300009#H00400"><p>I support my colleague, Senator Jim D'Arcy, with regard to the delays in processing third level grants.  I can only describe it as scandalous that, at this stage, between 25% and 28% of the grants have been approved.  What is annoying is that Student Universal Support Ireland, SUSI, is blaming the applicants, suggesting they did not dot the i's and cross the t's.  As a result, SUSI kicks the can down the road and sends the applications to an appeals process when applicants do the smallest thing wrong.  The appeals process works on the basis that the file will be parked for one month before someone looks at it.  That is wrong and we seem to have learned nothing about centralising anything.  We should have learned from the centralisation of medical card applications at the primary care reimbursement service, PCRS, that it does not work.  We have proved that centralising third level grants does not work.  I agree with Senator Jim D'Arcy that students are being deprived of services in colleges.  Some of them are considering leaving college because the grants have not been approved.  This morning I listened to the representative of SUSI clapping herself on the back and saying SUSI is doing a great job, with only 28% of students having received approval for grants as we approach Christmas.  The Minister for Education and Skills needs to step in and set a deadline for when all grants will be approved.  I ask the Leader to progress that matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor Ó Clochartaigh" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300009#H00500"><p>Ba mhaith liom iar-úair teachtarach a thuairt go dtí an seanad inniú.  Bhí mé ag criunniú poibli i nGaillaimh leis na draonn a bhíonn sa phlé le cursaí pobal agus cursaí deonach.  At a public meeting in Galway last night, we were asked to draw to people's attention that everything is not hunky-dory in Galway, even though it has a great reputation for festivals, celebrations, the arts and culture.  A budget submission entitled "Protect Communities-Protect Galway", about the community and voluntary sector sinking under the cuts, outlines the difficulties the sector faces.  I would welcome any Senator reading the submission in the run-up to the budget.  Representatives of all areas, from the disability sector, older people and the LGBT community, said they are under immense pressure and want Senators and the Government to take on board their concerns.</p><p>We might be able to do so by examining the regime of oil and gas licensing in the State following the wonderful find of oil off the coast of Ireland.  On a number of occasions, I have called for the Minister to come to the Chamber and give us his thoughts on the proposal by the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Communications, Energy and Natural Resources on the licensing regime.  By international standards, the regime is very favourable to oil companies.  Although the Minister told us finding oil off the coast of Ireland was like looking for a needle in a haystack, we have had two big finds over the past couple of months.  It is more important than ever that we discuss the licensing regime and see what tax revenues we can get from the resources and how the moneys can be used to offset problems in the State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" speakername="Terry Brennan" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300009#H00600"><p>I support the call for grants to be issued to students more quickly.  The delay in processing grant applications beggars belief.  Thousands of students throughout the country have been waiting for so long that such delays are unacceptable.  I listened to the SUSI spokesperson say this morning that 20,350 applications have been approved but only 3,010 students, 5% of those who applied, have been paid.  Students and families are encountering hardship.</p> <p>We have had delays in the past - we have had 32 concerns dealing with applications prior to this.  Surely before issuing or accepting a tender from a single VEC all aspects should have been thoroughly covered to establish what could and could not be done.  The VEC has now outsourced this to a private company.  Was it involved in the tendering process?  Did it envisage the number of applications?  It is unacceptable that students waiting for their applications to be processed telephoned only to find that the application had not been received and they were asked to submit a second one.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.50" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="A Senator" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300010#J00200"><p>The same thing happened with medical card applications.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" speakername="Terry Brennan" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300010#J00300"><p>Where am I going as a Senator?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300010#J00400"><p>Is the Senator seeking a debate?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" speakername="Terry Brennan" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300010#J00500"><p>I want the Minister to come to the House to tell me if this is a sign of things to come for many years ahead.  We appear to be going backwards.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300010#J00600"><p>I call Senator MacSharry.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300010#J00700"><p>Excuse me, a Chathaoirligh, I wish to raise a point of order, which is of significance to all Members of this House.  I submitted an amendment to No. 15, the motion on suicide.  My office was informed that it could not be accepted because it had missed the deadline because it had to go to the Cabinet.  Since when do Members' individual amendments to Government motions have to go to the Cabinet?  I do not seek or request or want the permission of the Cabinet to put a resolution before this House or to amend the Government's business.  That is my right attaching to my position as an elected Member of this House.  It does not need to go to the Cabinet.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300010#J01000"><p>Senator Norris-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300010#J01100"><p>I resist that and would like a ruling from you on this, a Chathaoirligh.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300010#J01200"><p>I have ruled on it.  The Senator's notice should have been submitted by 11 a.m. yesterday and it was late.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300010#J01300"><p>I wish to ask whether this was because it was a Cabinet matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300010#J01400"><p>It was late.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300010#J01500"><p>I find that very difficult to believe.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300010#J01600"><p>I join others in expressing grave concern at the incompetence of SUSI and whatever officials are involved at organising this process.  The older analogue version organised on a regional basis was much more effective.  We were all given an undertaking last year that it would be much quicker this year and that it was in students' interests.  We now have anecdotal evidence that students are packing in courses as a result of not being able to secure the necessary finance to go on.  I join other Senators in expressing dismay at the attitude of SUSI and the witnesses who appeared before the committee this morning.  They outlined how they were doing their best.  With an appeals mechanism now open to people, how many months will it take for appeals to be processed?  Appeals in the case of, for example, carer's allowance and farmers' payments, can take nine months to a year.  Is it the intention of SUSI and the Government that if my student grant is declined, provided I can get money from banks - which apparently have no money to lend and only have money to give for pensions and so on and will not give anything to students - I will not be able to continue with my education?  If, somehow, the money is to come out of thin air while my appeal is to be adjudicated on I might find myself in second or third year of studies.  There are many reasons for failure but there are no excuses.  Effectively the Minister and whichever of his colleagues can best assist with this will need to manage this personally.  He needs to make a statement on when funding will be made available and how quickly appeals will be heard.  He needs to ensure this process is completed expeditiously because it has been an unmitigated disaster, as was seen from the contributions at today's committee meeting.</p><p>I seek a debate - this is close to the Leader's heart - in advance of the Minister's announcement of the hospital groupings nationally.  There is a suggestion that the Leader's local hospital, Waterford Regional Hospital, will be linked to Dublin and I do not know how the hospitals in the north west will be linked.  I have serious concerns as to the criteria being used.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300011#K00100"><p>The Senator is way over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300011#K00200"><p>I appreciate that but I am conscious that others were afforded-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300011#K00300"><p>I call Senator Higgins.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300011#K00400"><p>If the Cathaoirleach would not mind, I will not be a moment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300011#K00500"><p>We have a rule that Senators may raise only one issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300011#K00600"><p>I appreciate that but others were afforded these opportunities.  This is an issue close to the Leader's heart.  The criteria being used to match these hospitals have more to do with saving money and medical politics than preserving what are the best pathways for outcomes for patients.  It is very important that we have a debate in this regard in advance of the Minister's announcement of the groupings.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1173" speakername="Lorraine Higgins" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300011#K00700"><p>I call on the Minister for Agriculture, Fisheries and Food to come to the House to discuss an issue relating to the single payment scheme application form and its associated terms and conditions.  There appears to be a degree of ambiguity in the application of the law referred to in the form.  This ambiguity relates to farm inspections.  Page 22 of the form states that in submitting a single payment scheme application applicants agree to permit officials or agents of the Department to carry out on-farm inspections with or without prior notice at any reasonable time.  This gives the impression to farmers that inspectors can carry out inspections at any time without giving notice to the farmer.  However, we all know departmental officials must abide by requisite time periods and notice periods.  For example, 48 hours notice must be given for inspections to be carried out on cattle and sheep tagging and inspections on land eligibility require up to 14 days notice.  I have raised the issue of the inspection regime in Ireland previously and I have highlighted the fact that the law is being flouted by some, but I stress not all departmental officials.</p><p>Understandably, there is a huge element of fear throughout the community.  Often farmers are afraid to stand up for their rights for fear of detrimental action being taken against them.  It is unacceptable to have such a reign of fear over the farming community, and for the State to collude in it by allowing this ambiguity on the single payment scheme form.  In the interests of doing what is right and informing farmers of their rights, it is imperative we clarify the position and have no grey area.  We owe farmers a duty of care to enforce the law of the land and any EU laws and regulations in a fair, reasonable and unambiguous manner.  To achieve this I call on the Minister to clarify the position and accordingly change the wording on page 22 of the form to reflect the law as it applies to each of us.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300011#K00800"><p>Like other Senators, I add my voice to welcoming the outcome of the children's rights referendum.  The outcome was much closer than I thought it would be and there are a number of reasons for this.  We need to interpret the results, including the reasons so many people voted "No" and ensure their concerns and issues are addressed.  Somebody mentioned a lack of trust in social workers.  What also came across was a lack of trust in the Government.  This was well defined by the Tánaiste today when he spoke about redefining marriage.  This is one of the concerns which affected people who voted "No".  They questioned whether the Government was genuine in its approach to protecting children.  A plethora of international reports and research and analysis conducted in this country clearly show the best interests of the family lie within the married family.  The Minister acknowledged the importance of a father and a mother both playing a role in the development and rearing of children when we debated the issue.  I call on her to return to the House soon to debate the issue again.</p><p>Concerns were also raised about the assurances of the Minister for Health, Deputy Reilly, to Deputy Mick Wallace that he would introduce abortion based on the X case, which would be very liberal.  This concerns many people.  I have asked in the House previously whether the children's rights referendum was about some children or all children.  We need to focus on these issues.</p><p>With regard to the €1.1 million misappropriated by the Government in spending on the referendum, I will not criticise Ministers of Fine Gael or the Labour Party for campaigning strongly, but like other parties, they should fund it themselves.  I call on the Minister to come to the House to give us an assurance that the €1.1 million will be refunded to the Exchequer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300011#K00900"><p>Fianna Fáil would have an awful lot to refund.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300011#K01000"><p>We funded the "Yes" campaign ourselves.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300011#K01100"><p>It resonates with the €1.1 billion misappropriated-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300012#L00100"><p>What about all of the money that was misappropriated when The Senator's party was in government?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300012#L00150"><p>----with the knowledge and acquiescence of the officials in the Department of Finance and put into a pension fund.  The moneys could have been used to assist distressed mortgagees.  That would have been a much better way to use the money.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300012#L00200"><p>I welcome the result of the referendum.  I thank the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs for introducing it after 20 years of debate and a number of reports, including by the Oireachtas.  I also pay tribute to Senator van Turnhout.  She has been involved in the area for a long number of years and has made a great contribution to moving the campaign forward.  I also thank every Member for participating in the campaign.</p><p>It is important to note that the people who voted &quot;No&quot; had genuine concerns.  In my area of Cork North-Central one box of ballot papers showed that 90 people voted &quot;No&quot; and 12 people voted &quot;Yes&quot;.  People have genuine concerns about dealing with the social services and we need to deal with the issue.  Social services provide the best service they can within their remit and we must send out a positive message about that work.  I shall touch on the issue that relates to the Supreme Court.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300012#L00300"><p>It is irrelevant.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300012#L00400"><p>Let us remember that the High Court approved the Government's decision on the challenge made.  The High Court favoured the Government in that decision but the Supreme Court made a different decision.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300012#L00500"><p>On a point of order, the Senator has brought the Supreme Court into disrepute.  He has questioned the Supreme Court's decision.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300012#L00600"><p>That is not a point of order and I ask the Senator to resume his seat.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300012#L00700"><p>It is.  Senator Colm Burke referred to the separation of powers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300012#L00800"><p>The Senator has said nothing about the Supreme Court yet.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Caít Keane" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300012#L00900"><p>The Senator is stating the obvious.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300012#L01000"><p>Senator Colm Burke has only mentioned the High Court.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300012#L01100"><p>He mentioned the Supreme Court.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300012#L01200"><p>I ask the Senator to resume his seat.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300012#L01300"><p>The Supreme Court is the highest court in the land and he discussed it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300012#L01400"><p>If the Senator does not want to hear the truth, then that is fine.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300012#L01500"><p>Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300012#L01600"><p>My question relates to future referenda.  Under the Constitution there is a mechanism that when a Bill is passed by the Oireachtas, the President has a right to refer it to the Supreme Court to be tested.  The last time that happened was for the nursing homes Bill.  I want to make a similar proposal for future referenda.  Before a referendum is held I want the Government to refer documentation to be used for a referendum to the Supreme Court for adjudication.  That would mean there would be no outstanding issues to be dealt with and would prevent what happened on this occasion.  The same mechanism is in place for legislation and there is no reason we cannot do the same for a referendum.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300012#L01700"><p>I welcome the comments made, particularly by Members on the other side of the House, on the bungling incompetence by Student Universal Support Ireland, SUSI.  Senator Whelan's contribution was particularly good and I agree with him.  Many Senators could not wait to get out the door to criticise local authorities and VECs on what they deemed to be the incompetent handling of student grants over the years.  The proof has been laid bare.  Where is the incompetence now?  The buck stops with the Minister and he should come here to answer my query.</p><p>  Members will also be aware that in the past few days there have been a series of parliamentary investigations into the payment or non-payment of tax by multinationals in Britain.  The matter is of particular importance to this country because some of the companies seem to operate successfully here yet pay very little tax.  Amazon, Starbucks and Google have been the subject of parliamentary investigations in the UK primarily because they have paid no tax.  Corporation tax is a sacred cow and one never hears it being raised by politicians in either House.  The defence used is that they create a large number of jobs in this beleaguered economy and contribute tax domestically due to their large workforces.  I applaud that but I do not want my remarks to be misinterpreted.  Storm clouds are gathering in Europe while the Government attempts to get a <i>modus vivendi</i> from its European partners in order to reduce an unsustainable bank debt.  In the past few weeks during discussions with the Minister for Finance, Ireland's corporation tax has been raised again.  That pressure will continue.  There has been a deafening silence, not only from these Houses, but by the Irish media on the question that was asked by Deputy Boyd Barrett which revealed that the multinationals do not pay 12.5% in corporation tax.</p> <p>They are paying as little as 4% or 5% tax.  Were I asked the question----- </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300013#M00200"><p>We are stuck for time today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300013#M00300"><p>The question I am putting to the Leader is that the Minister for Finance or the Minister of State should come to this House to provide some clarity, in light of the investigation that is going on at Parliament level and the discussions that are under way in Europe to try to get our European partners to reduce our unsustainable bank debt, as to exactly what is the reaction of the Government to the 4% or 5% tax that is being paid by multinationals.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300013#M00400"><p>The Senator is eating into the time of other Senators.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300013#M00500"><p>Were I asked the question as to whether I should take the money from those in receipt of home help or who are disabled-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300013#M00600"><p>The Senator is way over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300013#M00700"><p>----- or should I take another couple of bob from multinationals, I know what the answer would be.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" speakername="John Gilroy" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300013#M00800"><p>Senator Rónán Mullen called for a debate on marriage equality in this Chamber this afternoon and while his call was reasonable, the words he used were not.  Members should have a debate on this issue at the earliest possible opportunity because during such a debate, the intolerance at the heart of Senator Mullen's argument will be exposed.  However, that is not the reason I speak today.  I welcome the news this morning that Bank of Ireland has returned successfully to the markets with a bond sale of more than €1 billion.  It secured three-year money at 3.2%, which is a full ten points lower than the level of interest we were being charged 12 months ago.  This is a small but significant step and signals a returning of confidence to the market and the economy.  Notwithstanding the presence of the Minister for Finance in the House today, the Leader might organise a debate about banking, banking debt and banking practices in Ireland.  While the news from Bank of Ireland today is very welcome, I very much doubt whether it will do anything to reduce the level of arrogance of that same organisation, as evinced in the buildings of Leinster House in the past week.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1115" speakername="Labhrás Ó Murchú" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300013#M00900"><p>It would be helpful for Members to have a debate at an early stage on the recent referendum.  When all the congratulations have evaporated, there will be much soul-searching and analysis of the conduct and outcome of that referendum.  To change the Constitution at any time is a momentous occasion and it is a momentous decision for the citizens as well.  The recent amendments had the support of each political party in the State, yet the bottom line is that 80% of those entitled to vote did not support the referendum.  This means that only approximately 20% did so.</p><p>As for the Supreme Court decision, I am disappointed at the casual response to that decision.  I always understood that as legislators, when a decision came forward, Members not only accepted it but did so magnanimously.  While I do not refer to any speaker today, references to the High Court in that context are not correct.  The bottom line is the Supreme Court made a unanimous decision. </p><p>The second point I find worrying - again I make no reference to anyone who spoke on the issue today because it has been on the public airwaves up to now - is the suggestion the Government should be allowed to spend money on a &quot;Yes&quot; vote.  This is exceptionally worrying, because it misunderstands and misinterprets what sovereignty means when it comes to a change in the Constitution.  In this case, it would have meant that one would have been spending €1.4 million on behalf of 20%, because one certainly could not state one was spending it on behalf of the 80% who did not support it.  I hope that particular debate does not gather any weight.  However, in a positive sense - I do not say this in a confrontational way - an early debate would be important.  Very important messages, as distinct from the result, are emerging.  If I may conclude on this point-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300013#M01000"><p>The Senator is out of time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1115" speakername="Labhrás Ó Murchú" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300013#M01100"><p>Many people have been saying in recent times that many more referendums should be held to give the people an opportunity to speak.  In light of what happened in the last referendum, we now must find out why that has not been taken on board by the people.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300013#M01200"><p>I have no difficulty in supporting Senator Ó Murchú's call for a debate in the aftermath, when the dust settles, on the referendum.</p> <p>I congratulate the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs, Deputy Fitzgerald, on successfully steering through the referendum.  It is the culmination of 20 years hard work on the part of many Members in all parties and all-party Oireachtas committees.  I also acknowledge the work and support of Senator van Turnhout.</p><p>There are many lessons to be learned from the referendum.  One of them is whether our methods of communication to the public are adequate or effective.  I was surprised to hear the vox pop on radio yesterday and over the weekend in which many people indicated that they did not have a clue what the referendum was about.  They decided to either vote &quot;No&quot; because they did not understand what it was about or they decided to stay away, and that was despite the fact two booklets were sent to every household.  Either people had a lazy attitude to finding information or they were disinterested and used the excuse that they did not know what it was about; therefore, they did not bother to vote.  We need to analyse all of those issues.  I might be wrong, and Senator Ó Murchú might correct me if I am, but I think a previous Government spent money on the second Lisbon treaty referendum; therefore, there is a precedent for doing so.  The McKenna judgment and all of those other issues need to be debated.</p><p>I have a final comment on the SUSI debacle, and there is famous song with the lyrics, &quot;If you knew Susie like I know Susie.&quot;   I was one of the Senators who warned that it was a bad idea to take the processing of those grant applications away from the local authorities and the VECs.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300014#N00200"><p>The Senator is out of order in mentioning SUSI.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300014#N00300"><p>I am disappointed the assurances we were given of a better system have not come to fruition.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300014#N00400"><p>I pay tribute to the 15,000 people from the south east who marched over the weekend in defence of Waterford Regional Hospital and services at the hospital.  There were a number of meetings today between Oireachtas Members, consultants and clinical directors across the south east, the Minister for Health and the Secretary General at the Department of Health.  It is very clear opposite views are being expressed by all parties.  The Minister and the Secretary General said Waterford Regional Hospital will not be in any way downgraded and that tertiary services, such as cancer care, cardiology and trauma, will not be affected by changes which will, effectively, break up the region, yet people who work in the hospital and in other hospitals in the region, including a cardiologist in Wexford and consultants and others who work in Waterford Regional Hospital, are saying that is not true.</p><p>In that environment, I am sure the Leader would agree that the best thing to happen would be for the Higgins report to be published in order that we can all see exactly what is in it and make up our own minds about how all of this will play out for the patients of the south east.  We all want to ensure that at the end of this process, we get the best structure for the people of the south east and not just Waterford.  Given that opposite views are being expressed by people who work in those hospitals and by the Minister for Health and the Secretary General, it only adds weight to the view that the report should be published.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300014#N00500"><p>We are way over time and five Senators have indicated that they wish to contribute.  I will take Senators Jimmy Harte, Paul Coghlan, Martin Conway, Mary Moran and Eamonn Coghlan first tomorrow.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300014#N00600"><p>Senators Darragh O'Brien and van Turnhout and many other Senators commented on the children's rights referendum.  The result is a momentous one and it reflects many years of work on the part of the Oireachtas and others.  What is clear is that the electorate has endorsed the proposition that children's rights and protections be expressly recognised in the Constitution.  This is part of a wider change in the process being led by the Government which recognises the failures of the past and puts in place more robust child protection laws and services.</p> <p>The Criminal Justice (Withholding of Information on Offences against Children and Vulnerable Persons) Bill 2012 has been enacted and the National Vetting Bureau (Children and Vulnerable Persons) Bill 2012 will be brought before the House soon.  The heads of a Children First Bill have been published and debated by the Oireachtas committee dealing with health matters.  An amending adoption Bill has been published to inform referendum deliberations.  In the coming week the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs will publish the child and family support agency Bill to provide for the establishment of a dedicated child welfare and protection agency early next year.  That is what will happen in the future.</p><p>I agree with Members who have called for a debate on the Supreme Court judgment when it is published and I will have no problem in facilitating such a debate.  There is no question that it is regrettable that only 32% of the electorate voted.  People have spoken about Saturday voting and the jury is still out on the issue.  When the Supreme Court judgment is published, I will facilitate a debate in the House on the matter.</p><p>The issue of home help has been raised for the past three weeks by Senator Drragh O'Brien and others.  As I stated in the past three weeks, the Government is committed to supporting older people to live in dignity and independence in their own homes and communities for as long as possible.  It has invested approximately €320 million in home help and home care packages this year.  A review of individual needs is ongoing.  I have spoken at length on the subject in recent weeks but the position has not changed.  The process will be reviewed in the new year and it is the Government's position that people should be supported with dignity and independence in their own homes.  That is the way to go.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300015#O00200"><p>Will the cuts be reversed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300015#O00300"><p>That will be reflected in the budget for 2013.  Senator Hayden spoke about budgetary debates, of which we have had a number of these on areas such as social welfare.  There will be a debate on the economy this afternoon.  The Senator and others complimented the Government on receiving a seat on the executive of the Human Rights Council in the United Nations, which should be welcomed by all.</p><p>I take Senator van Turnhout's point on the referendum and compliment her on the part she played during that campaign.  I note her points on the periodic review.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="Rónán Mullen" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300015#O00400"><p>She was the only good turn-out on the occasion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300015#O00500"><p>I have already addressed the point on the adoption Bill.  Senator Mullen spoke about human rights and marriage equality, which is a debate for another day.  With regard to the alleged information on family planning clinics, the Senator has mentioned that the matter is in the hands of the Garda.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="Rónán Mullen" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300015#O00600"><p>Some of it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300015#O00700"><p>Any malpractice in clinics must be investigated by the Garda, which is charged with investigating any such malpractice.  As I stated last week,I have the utmost confidence in the Garda in the matter.</p><p>Senator Healy Eames spoke about banker pensions and there is no doubt that there is anger and resentment among the public and politicians about the matter.  I am confident a way will be found in next month's budget to address the issue.  </p><p>Senator Moloney spoke about the report on people dying by suicide, mentioning in particular those in the Cork, Kerry and Offaly areas.  It makes for very hard reading.  We have had many debates in the House on the subject and I am sure there will be similar debates in the future.</p><p>With regard to Senator O'Donnell's comments, we should await the budget on 5 December for a response by the Government on the issue of bankers' pay and pensions.</p> <p>The Minister of State at the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform will be in the House later and I am sure any question that needs to be asked of him can be asked during that debate.</p><p>I was disappointed by the number of Members who contributed last week when the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform attended the House.  Some Members obviously tried to ruin it for others but there were not many in the Chamber for the debate which had been sought by between 15 and 20 Members in the past number of weeks.  A total of 11 took part in the debate.</p><p>Senator Jim D'Arcy called for a moratorium on referenda for the next number of years.  I am sure he will have almost the full support of Members for that proposition.</p><p>The issue of student grants was raised by Senator Jim D'Arcy and many other Senators.  We all agree with the Minister for Education and Skills that the delays many students face in the processing of their applications are unacceptable.  The Minister has requested that City of Dublin VEC which operates SUSI, the new single grant awarding authority, increase its staffing to deal with the backlog.  As of yesterday afternoon, the position of 66,000 applications was as follows: 20,000 had been completed, awarded, provisionally awarded or refused; SUSI was awaiting documentation on almost 21,000 applications, for which 15,000 applicants had provided no documentation whatsoever; and 26,000 were awaiting processing.  I agree with Members that this is too many but we should not rule out centralisation of this system.  We had 66 local authorities and VECs and some of them were excellent at processing applications, while others were not as good and students would still be waiting if that system was still in place.  Let us give the system a chance.  I am as critical as anybody else of the centralisation of services when they do not work.  This is not working as we want it to but let us give it a chance.  Having one authority deal universally with grant applications is the way to go but I accept it must be done in a more professional and efficient manner, which is what the Minister is trying to ensure.</p><p>Senator Norris commented on human rights issues and the children's rights referendum.  We owe a debt of gratitude to him for the debate we had last Thursday at short notice about the Supreme Court's decision on the referendum.  It was an excellent debate which was a great advertisement for this House.</p><p>Both Senator Norris and Senator Moloney raised the issue of the national suicide prevention officer.  The position has been filled and the person concerned will start in the coming weeks.  That will be welcomed by all.</p><p>Senator Ó Clochartaigh raised the issue of the funding of community and voluntary bodies.  We have had debates with various Ministers on the budgetary process and this matter can be raised in that context.  With regard to oil, we still have not brought anything ashore.  When we bring something ashore, we can begin to generate revenue at that stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor Ó Clochartaigh" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300016#P00200"><p>It will be too late.  The licences should be put in place.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300016#P00300"><p>The Senator is a gas man for raising the issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300016#P00400"><p>What about bringing gas in off the Mayo coast?  Has the Senator forgotten about that?  We will be waiting years with all his party's punters stopping gas coming ashore.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor Ó Clochartaigh" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300016#P00500"><p>The Government will be pumping out the profits.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300016#P00600"><p>The Leader to continue, without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300016#P00700"><p>If Sinn Féin had anything to do with it, there would be nothing coming into the country at all.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300016#P00900"><p>Senators MacSharry and Cullinane called for a debate on the hospital groupings report when it is published.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300016#P01000"><p>Before would be better.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300016#P01100"><p>How can we have a debate on a report before it is published?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300016#P01200"><p>I am sure views have been articulated to Members on how they should be formed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300017#Q00100"><p>We cannot debate something that has not been published and put before us but I assure the House that when Professor Higgins's report is published, we will have a debate on it.</p><p>Senator Higgins raised the issue of inspections by officials of the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine.  I will bring the matter to the attention of the Minister if she provides me with the details she outlined.</p><p>Senator Walsh referred to the rights of the family.  They are clearly enshrined in the Constitution and will be protected by the Supreme Court.</p><p>Senator Mooney raised the issue of corporation tax.  The Government has made its position clear on this issue for many years.  That remains the position.  The issue of companies or individuals not paying sufficient corporation tax could be raised with the Minister of State at the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform when he attends the House later.</p><p>Senator Gilroy commented on Bank of Ireland being back in the markets.  This is encouraging but it is only a first step and we have a long way to go in that regard.</p><p>Senator Cullinane mentioned the march by 15,000 people in Waterford on Saturday last.  I was among those who marched.  We will have a debate on the hospital groupings as soon as the Higgins report is published.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300017#Q00200"><p>The Leader should have been on television.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.130" nospeaker="true" time="16:05:00"><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.131" nospeaker="true" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300018#R00100">National Children's Hospital: Statements</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300018#R00200"><p>I was delighted to announce that the Cabinet had accepted my recommendation to develop the new national children's hospital at the campus of St. James's Hospital in Dublin.  The rejection by An Bord Pleanála earlier this year of the proposal to develop a children's hospital on the site of the Mater hospital was very disappointing, particularly given the many real strengths of that location.  In response, I established a review group, chaired by Dr. Frank Dolphin, to advise me on the best way forward and the group presented its report to me in June.  Unfortunately, after consideration and further detailed analysis, the Government decided it could not proceed with a site with such a significant planning risk.  In identifying the new site we have carefully considered the report of the Dolphin group along with detailed supplementary information on cost, time and planning issues.  I again express my thanks and praise to Dr. Dolphin and his group for the key role they played in helping us to reach our conclusion.  I take the opportunity to say that not for the first time the good will of people towards this project was shown in abundance.  On the previous occasion we asked four international experts to give us their opinion and they did quite a body of work <i>gratis</i>.  Similarly, the Dolphin group also worked <i>gratis</i>.</p><p>  The report of the group reiterates what all previous reports on the national children's hospital have stated, which is that any decision must be based first and foremost on clinical considerations.  Both the Mater hospital and St. James's Hospital have the necessary clinical mass and both are at the cutting edge of Irish health care.  However, the Dolphin report and subsequent work undertaken by members of that group made it very clear that the planning risks associated with the Mater hospital are still significant.  The decision on where the new children's hospital should be situated was not an easy one.  Over the summer officials in my Department and I looked closely at all the proposals submitted, each of which had its own particular strengths.  I thank all the hospitals that took part in the review process for their hard work and dedicated enthusiasm.  In the end, however, the decision had to be made.  As Senators will know there can never be a perfect site, but as we said previously we cannot let perfection be the enemy of excellence.</p><p>  This decision has been made in the best interests of children with clinical considerations being paramount.  It is essential that the new children's hospital can deliver best clinical outcomes for our children.  Co-location with an adult hospital has been deemed essential in the Dolphin report and in all previous reports on the issue, while tri-location with a maternity hospital is optimum.  Co-location and ultimately tri-location with a maternity hospital on the St. James's campus will support the provision of excellence in clinical care that children deserve.</p><p>  I now intend to move quickly to put in place all the necessary arrangements to enable the delivery of this project as quickly as possible and to the highest quality.  The Government regards the building of the new national children's hospital as a key priority and no effort will be spared in expediting its completion.  We must now get on with building this hospital to the highest quality with best value for money as quickly as possible so that we can continue to provide the best of care, but now in the best of environments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300018#R00300"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House and thank him for taking the time out of his busy schedule to always come himself to talk with us.  On balance Fianna Fáil welcomes the progress on the national children's hospital.  I wish to mention a number of issues and I have some personal reservations.</p> <p>I know the process transcends a different Administration.</p><p>When one reads the objections to the Mater Hospital proposal - I am not a trained planner but a humble auctioneer with some common sense - one could have written them in advance as being issues which would be raised by An Taisce and the Irish Georgian Society.  They were the main objections which carried the day with An Bord Pleanála.  I hope this time all of the ducks can be put in a line very quickly and that the Minister, or those in the Department who will manage the project, will proactively engage with Ian Lumley, the chief executive of An Taisce, members of the Irish Georgian Society and other stakeholders.  They may hold the view we should be able to retrofit Georgian buildings to facilitate all possible wishes with regard to hospitals, which is obviously not practical, workable or cost effective.</p><p>We need to move much more quickly than we have.  The Dolphin report was available in June and if we believe what we read in the media, we have had a five month wait since then.  The Tánaiste was checking out the process to ensure he was happy with it before we could move forward.  Serious doubts about the site have been raised.  We all agree we want the hospital, and if St. James's Hospital is the site then so be it, let us get on with it and build it as quickly as we can.  The official zoning of the site is unclear because of the court ruling.  Earlier today I looked at some maps and it is very much a brownfield site rather than a greenfield site and this raises all types of issues.  It is notionally possible that some brownfield sites may have listed buildings.  If this were the case all of a sudden we would have far more interest from An Taisce, the Irish Georgian Society and other interest groups which can hold up processes.  People may wish to pursue an agenda rather than facilitate the overall ambition of getting the hospital built as quickly as possible to start delivering the outcomes for which all of us yearn.  It is a potential problem if the site is not sufficiently zoned.</p><p>In recent days the media reported the OPW highlighted in advance of the selection that serious challenges from a planning perspective and that the zoning was no longer clear.  This puts a serious doubt over the timeframe.  Presumably the project will go directly to An Bord Pleanála, which will be guided by the zoning of the day.  Assuming Dublin City Council zones it appropriately to facilitate the building of the hospital as quickly as possible it may be open to challenge because the court judgment states it must go to public consultation.  While the application will go directly to An Bord Pleanála it will consider it in line with the development plan of the day.  If the development plan is amended to apply the relevant zoning, while it will not involve the planning authorities in Dublin City Council they will be cognisant of the development plan.  The density to plot ratio of the project would be 4.5:1, but this is in contravention of the development plan for the area.  Any potential objectors will have significant ammunition to shoot it down before we even start.</p><p>In putting his ducks in a line the Minister may not be able to consider the zoning issue only.  He may also have to examine the possibility of Dublin City Council adjusting the density in the development plan for the area to progress the project.  Otherwise it could be delayed for a significant period.</p> <p>Building costs have changed in recent years.  I have anecdotal evidence that the starting place for the HSE, when it considers the cost of building, is €200 per sq. ft. but from an auctioneering point of view, and my untrained view, it ought to be about €120 per sq. ft.  Costs may be higher for a specialist build such as a hospital but it should not be 120% higher.  Perhaps the Minister will reflect on the points that I have made.  I wish him well in making a decision as quickly as possible. </p><p>Obviously leaving the maternity hospital on the never, never is not good enough.  As the Minister has said, trilocation was mooted 19 years ago.  If we put the maternity hospital on the never, never then my children will be grown by the time we realise the ambitions that the Minister and his predecessors have for the hospital.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1152" speakername="Imelda Henry" time="16:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300020#T00200"><p>Senator Colm Burke wishes to share time with Senator Eamonn Coghlan.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="16:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300020#T00300"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House and thank him for making a decision on the matter.  It is welcome. The McKinsey report dates back to 2006.  At present three hospitals in Dublin provide child care.  It is important that we make the necessary changes because children require specialist treatment.  In 2006 the report accepted that one children's hospital would look after children from the greater Dublin area and provide specialist care for children from around the country.  It is important that we provide the best facility for children and at the earliest possible date.</p><p>  It is interesting how medicine has improved in the past ten years and the specialist work that is now carried out in hospitals.  It is important that children do not have to leave the State for medical treatment.  There have been a number of reports since the McKinsey report and it is unfortunate that the original Mater project was unable to proceed.  As recently as 15 May 2012, An Bord Pleanála responded to a suggestion to scale down the Mater project by stating:<blockquote>In the case of this pre-application consultation, whilst the information before the Board is of an outline nature, the Board notes that a reduction in the height of the proposed building from 16 to 9 storeys plus plant is proposed.  Whilst such a reduction in height is likely to reduce the visual prominence on the city skyline the Board advises that the reduction may, however, have other significant impacts in respect of the design, massing, bulk and functionality of the proposed hospital building and have the potential for consequent planning impacts which, together with the issue of visual impact, will be important considerations for the Board in determining any future application.  </blockquote>An Bord Pleanála made it quite clear, no matter what new application came forward about the Mater Hospital, that there was still going to be difficulties even with a reduction in height.  </p><p>  The site at St. James's Hospital is good.  It will be a trilocation and will provide an adult facility.  The Coombe Hospital is quite close plus we will have a new facility.  We will be able to provide a comprehensive service when they are all working together.</p><p>  It is important to have a maternity hospital close by.  A lot of difficulties can be identified before a baby is born and a pregnant woman can be transferred to the new facility once her baby is born.  Tri-location is crucial and I thank the Minister for making the proposal. </p> <p>I agree with Senator MacSharry that it is important that the planning and consultation processes be expedited and that we build at the earliest possible date.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" speakername="Eamonn Coghlan" time="16:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300021#U00200"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House.  Last week, 6 November was a great day when the announcement was made that the new national paediatric hospital would, at last, go ahead.  Whichever site was chosen, there were always going to be disagreements as to the right location.  The hospital in Crumlin was designed in 1936 and opened, eventually, 20 years later.  It took 18 years from the time Tallaght hospital was designed until it opened.  This debate has been going on for ten years.  I hope it will not take another eight or ten years before the hospital is finally constructed.</p><p>A few moments ago, we heard how the children's rights referendum took 20 years to get this far and that there are lessons to be learned from what happened last weekend.  Let us hope the lessons we have learned to date can be applied to what is going to happen in the new paediatric hospital on the St. James's Hopsital site and that we get it right this time.</p><p>The McKinsey report indicated that it was important for the paediatric hospital to be co-located with an adult hospital.  From my experience as a fund-raiser for Our Lady's Children's Hospital in Crumlin for more than 20 years, I can emphasise that it is more important to have a maternity hospital located with a children's hospital.  More than 500 emergencies go by ambulance from the maternity hospitals to Crumlin and Temple Street hospitals every year.  A direct physical link from a maternity hospital to the children's hospital is most important to deal with these emergencies.</p><p>With regard to planning permission, is a maternity hospital included in the planning application?  If not, will it be included in phase 2?  I hope it is not left until phase 2, because no construction included in phase 2 of a hospital plan has ever been built.  Planning permission for this hospital must include permission for a maternity hospital at exactly the same time in order that we know exactly where we stand now, not 20 years down the road.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="16:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300021#U00300"><p>With the permission of the House, I will share my time with Senator Marie Moloney.</p><p>I take some credit for my own party in saying the national children's hospital was a key Labour Party commitment in the general election and in the programme for Government.  Funding for the project has been ring-fenced by the Government and it will represent the single biggest piece of infrastructure to be given the green light in the lifetime of the Government.  It is a very important development.</p><p>As a parent, I welcome the development.  I have had reason to use two of the three hospitals concerned, and irrespective of how wonderful the staff are, the hospitals are not fit for purpose.  I welcome the decision, on foot of the Dolphin report, to proceed with the national children's hospital.</p><p>I know there are many who are dissatisfied with the decision.  Spokespeople for the Mater Hospital, for example, have said its proposed changes would now satisfy the planning requirements.  The Children's Hospital Alliance accepts the decision but considers the choice of St. James's Hospital to be a poor one.  The alliance favours the greenfield site at Connolly Hospital and wants the Minister to mothball that site for future development.  The Minister might bear that in mind.</p><p>The McKinsey report, which supported trilocation, has been dealt with by other colleagues.  As I presume the Minister will deal with this matter in his reply, I will not go into it.  I am concerned, however, that the Minister has indicated that the 2016 deadline for the construction of the hospital will not be met.  I ask him to pull out all the stops to ensure it is.  In the late 1990s, the Bacon report on housing indicated that it might be possible to expedite the planning process.  It is shocking that it took five years from the initial choice of the Mater site to the submission of a planning application.  That must not happen on this occasion.  The McKinsey report was issued in 2006.</p> <p>There were many debates before the McKinsey report was issued on a national paediatric hospital.  For the sake of argument, I am thinking of when childhood leukaemia services were moved from Tallaght hospital to Crumlin hospital.  That resulted in a very significant national debate.  It is important we learn from what can only be described as a debacle in the past few years and ensure it does not happen again.</p><p>I am concerned about what will happen in the meantime to the existing children's hospitals, namely, Our Lady's Hospital for Sick Children in Crumlin, Temple Street hospital and Tallaght hospital.  It is critical the services in these hospitals are maintained in the interim.  There is always a temptation, even if it is unintentional, to downgrade services when it is known that a service will be moved to another site.  In fact, I think a certain amount of downgrading has gone on over the past number of years in anticipation of the building of a national children's hospital.</p><p>In terms of the design of the new national children's hospital, I would like the Minister to take two specific things into account.  There should be adequate accommodation for parents of children who require hospitalisation.  Children do better when their parents are around but, more importantly, it is assumed in the medical services that family will be there to take over part of the care of children.  The second point I would like to make is that there must be adequate parking.  The parking charges in some of our hospitals are a disgrace and many parents and others are paying exorbitant amounts of money in parking fees which they cannot afford.  </p><p>Senator Coghlan mentioned that Tallaght hospital took 18 years from initiation to construction even though in 2007 we built 98,000 housing units in this country.  Many of our current hospitals are not really fit for purpose.  I was in St. Vincent's Hospital recently and the Minister might turn his attention to some of the other hospitals in the country.  If it is going to take this amount of time to build a national children's hospital, we should start to move on some of the other hospitals.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Maloney" time="16:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300022#V00200"><p>I welcome the Minister.  I will be very brief because Senator Hayden touched on the subject I was going to speak about.  In the wake of the children's rights referendum last Saturday, it is paramount that we protect the welfare and well-being of every child in this State and a world class national children's hospital is key to that.  In the development of the new site, as Senator Hayden said, I hope the families of sick children will be considered and catered for because it is a very traumatic time for families when they have a very sick child.  As a rural Senator coming all the way from Kerry, I know many families struggle financially to afford accommodation in Dublin.  The Ronald McDonald House in Crumlin is an invaluable and affordable service for families having to travel to Dublin with sick children.  Have negotiations taken place with the Ronald McDonald service in regard to the new site?  In the development of a world class hospital, we must cater for the needs of families as well as children.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1147" speakername="John Crown" time="16:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300022#V00300"><p>I welcome an Aire.  I begin by saying, unambiguously, well done and congratulations to the Minister.  It was a good decision.  In a country with six medical schools for 4.5 million people - twice the European average and three times the North American average - it was pretty obvious that people were going to be unhappy no matter which affiliated institution was chosen for this.  There really was a necessity to pick the best place.  There were a number of good places but this clearly was one of the best ones.  St. James's Hospital, in the Irish context, is a very fine hospital and it has a full range of support and high quality services and high quality academic connections, again in the Irish context, and I have no doubt it will make a very fine fist of it.</p><p>There were a number of arguments to be made in favour of alternative sites and the Minister may still hear some of the disgruntled adherents of other sites still making arguments at this stage.  I beg and beseech for ciúnas among my colleagues, regardless of their institutional affiliation at this stage.  The decision has been made and let us support it.</p> <p>There is still the hurdle of what I have, rather uncharitably, termed "An Bord Faulty Pleanálty" to overcome.  We should not give any ammunition to any argument from a group that feels there is still a viable alternative.  Any other decision at this stage will just cause delays, and as there are no manifestly superior sites, we should proceed with this one.</p><p>I draw the Minister's attention to two problems.  There will inevitably be a tendency for a freeze to occur on much-needed first aid measures in the existing children's hospitals with a mantra of waiting until the new place is built.  There will be deficiencies affecting the health of living children and the services must formulate creative ways to deal with the issue.  We understand that it would not be wise to make major infrastructural investments in any of the existing institutions that will close but we must ensure that some of the appalling waiting list issues in children's medical and surgical services are not just put on the long finger until the arrival of the nirvana of the opening of the new national children's hospital.</p><p>There may be some apparently regrettable duplicate investments in the short term to ensure waiting lists are dealt with.  I am sure the Government is considering whether, in the short term, certain specialist surgical services with unacceptable waiting lists can be outsourced from the country temporarily until the new hospital is built.</p><p>Concentration facilitates quality but does not ensure it.  The fundamental reform of the health system and how the hospital system is paid for will have a much bigger effect on the quality of health care in this country than any reorganisation of either hospital networks or integration into solitary specialist hospitals.  I urge the Minister to ensure he keeps his eye very firmly on that prize because until we get fundamental reform of the way we pay and finance the health service, our system will be mediocre, and there is no other interpretation in that regard.</p><p>I am a little newer to the political arena than the Minister but I am a fast learner.  While he is in the House, I will shamelessly tack on some questions for his consideration.  Ireland will assume a senior role in Europe in January as the country takes on the European Union Presidency and I hope the Minister will use the opportunity to seriously advance some anti-smoking initiatives that we are considering.  Our legislation banning smoking in cars in which children are present appears to be stuck between Departments.  In the health committee on Thursday we will introduce a motion that Leinster House, in its entirety both inside and out, will be made a smoke-free zone like HSE hospitals.</p><p>In the past week we have begun a major initiative targeted at Europe and the Government to get the European Commission and the European Parliament to agree to the notion that by 2030, it would be illegal to do any commerce in tobacco in the European Union.  With 17 years to lead into this process, this quixotic ideal is possible.</p><p>Will the Minister determine if appropriate inquiries are being made into the circumstances of the resignation of the former Commissioner Dalli?  I attended the European Parliament last week wearing my European oncology hat rather than my Seanad hat and there is substantial speculation that Mr. Dalli, who had a very firm anti-tobacco agenda in his position, found himself in rather surprising circumstances being forced to step down.  It has been suggested, although we do not know if there is a basis to the claim, that he may have been the victim of dirty tricks by those with a vested interest in opposing attempts to rein in the tobacco industry.</p><p>I congratulate the Minister on the decision made on the national children's hospital and look forward to a very productive six months when the Minister is in charge of Europe's health initiatives.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300023#W00200"><p>I learned today that the Minister is not in favour of shotgun or forced marriages and I agree with him on the site chosen and that we should get on with building the hospital, which we all want.  It is a welcome development that the site has finally been chosen and we will now see the building of a new top quality national children's hospital, which will be an enormous addition to the health care infrastructure on this island.</p> <p>I commend the Minister for the review carried out by him when he took up office and on the confirmation that the Mater Hospital site was the appropriate choice before the refusal of planning permission by An Bord Pleanála in February 2012.  It seems clear that this process and the delay it caused in delivering a key project was less than ideal at the time.  We have moved on and we now have a new site.  The genuine question people have relates to the ring-fencing of capital funding for the project to ensure there is no issue about funding going forward.  We all accept there has been too much delay.  We can continue to engage in the blame game or we can move on and work together to ensure the hospital is built.  In that context, the Minister will have my party's support to ensure that happens.  I seek an assurance that the funding will be ring-fenced.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" time="16:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300024#X00200"><p>I thank all the Senators for their comments and support.  There is unanimity in the House that this project is worthy of a modern State.  Many countries are judged by how they treat their most vulnerable and sick children fall into that category.  Senator MacSharry alluded to a parallel process being run.  There was no parallel process.  There was a clear sequential process in that we had the Dolphin group report, then we had a member of the group do a further report on the relative costings because all the bidders put their best foot forward and in their enthusiasm some of the information might not have been as accurate as they believed and this had to be verified.  There was a planning exercise given the risks and what had happened previously, where the focus was on the clinical primacy needs of co-location.  This is the benefit we are seeking to achieve.  A small country of 4.6 million people does not have the cohort of children to support the specialties that a country such as the UK does with a population of 60 million.  Members have referred to Great Ormond Street as a stand-alone hospital.  It can justify that because there is such a huge cohort of children.  The hospital's chief executive officer was a member of the international group who kindly gave of her time freely and even she agreed unanimously with the other three members that co-location was by far the most preferable way to go.</p><p>I have walked the site and the planning issues have been mitigated considerably because it is much bigger than the Mater site.  It is in excess of 6 hectares, which is much bigger than the 2.4 hectare site originally offered by St. James's Hospital.</p><p>This also provides a wonderful opportunity to rejuvenate part of old Dublin and lift that area of the city with the possibility of a new medical quarter in the city to rival the best in the world.  Meetings have been held since the decision was made on the hospital regarding governance issues.  I attended a meeting in this regard before I attended the Chamber with members of the national paediatric hospital board.</p><p>I highlighted in the other Chamber a number of issues that could not be addressed until the site was chosen and they primarily related to governance, information technology, which was a big miss in the planning process for the Mater Hospital site, and the ambulatory urgent care centres.  Clearly until the site was chosen, I could not adjudicate on how many of these centres might be needed and I believe we need more than one.</p><p>Several Senators mentioned the need to maintain a safe environment in the interim while the hospital is under construction and I am acutely aware of this.  This is a recurring theme.  When I served on the Eastern Health Board years ago, I witnessed what happened at St. Ita's Hospital, Portrane, while we awaited the new psychiatric admission unit in Beaumont Hospital, which only opened a year ago.  Reference was made to waiting 20 years for the children's hospital but we waited even longer for the unit in the Beaumount Hospital.  Dreadful conditions pertained in the admission unit in St. Ita's Hospital for both the patents and the staff, which I highlighted in the past.</p> <p>I am grateful we are moving ahead.  Unfortunately, we do not have a capital budget that allows us to build all the hospitals we would like.  I am acutely aware of the situation in our maternity hospitals and the difficulties there.  We are looking at innovative ways to allow us to increase our capital fund to address the issues.</p><p>I refer to the issues raised by Senator Hayden in respect of parental accommodation and parking.  These issues will be addressed.  I thank Senator Crown for his support.  I have some positive news in respect of children.  This year, there are 800 fewer children on the list awaiting inpatient treatment than last year.  Too many people are awaiting treatment still but we are moving close to achieving our goal of ensuring everyone in the childhood population is looked after within 20 weeks.</p><p>With regard to tobacco legislation, I share the concerns expressed by Senators Crown and Eamonn Coghlan.  I have spoken to John Dalli directly to offer my personal support.  I have spoken to several of the ministers in Europe and the interim Commissioner about the need to ensure the tobacco directive is progressed.  It is a key part of our EU Presidency and we want to move it on.  Everyone knows my view on tobacco, it robs children of a full life and the industry seeks to make addicts of young children.  That is to be discouraged at every opportunity.  Many people in Europe are very concerned at the manner of the Commissioner's resignation.  In due course, I hope he gets to clear his good name.  He was a great champion of tobacco control.</p><p>With regard to the point raised by Senator Cullinane, who has just left the Chamber, I assure Members that capital funding is secure for this project.  Lottery funding of €200 million has been made available to us and the remainder is available in the capital budget.  I have been very slow to say how much the hospital will cost because we are going to tender and the last thing I want to do is give those who will submit a tender the opportunity to take advantage of the information.  Everyone knows that if there is a certain amount to be spent and we let people know the amount, that is what it will cost.  We are looking for value for money.</p><p>Senator Eamonn Coghlan referred to the maternity hospital, as did others.  The reports are quite clear that the optimal is bi-location if we can manage it but the most important thing is co-location with an adult hospital.  Tri-location is our plan and the site will accommodate it.  This is an important point when referring to the site at St. James's Hospital.  It is large enough to accommodate not only the new national paediatric hospital but also a new maternity hospital and other developments.  I hope I am not talking out of turn but I am given to understand that, in respect of education and research facilities, another area on the site is acceptable to Our Lady's Children's Hospital, Crumlin.  That may remove the need for one floor in the new hospital, which mitigates further planning issues.  St. James's Hospital has a long history in Dublin and has good relationships with its neighbours.  It is part of the community and people feel it is their hospital.  I went out to walk the site and meet management and I was at pains to point out that the local community should be engaged with to ensure there was full information in order that the plans did not intrude on local people too much.  Obviously there will be some inconvenience during construction but I have absolute faith in the hospital's ability to do this in a manner that will minimise inconvenience.</p><p>I thank Senators for their support and assure them this will receive my serious attention.  I expect to be given weekly updates and have monthly meetings to ensure this is expedited.  We are looking at every legal and proper way to cut through red tape with regard to EU tendering, which causes so many delays.  We will run as many matters as we can in parallel in order to avoid delays.</p> <p>We need to be realistic - it could be late in 2017 or early in 2018.  However, nothing would please me more than to surprise people by coming in much earlier and obviously well within budget.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.150" nospeaker="true" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300026#Z00200">The Economy: Statements</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300026#Z00300"><p>I am grateful for the opportunity to address the House on the theme of where the economy stands.  The Government's policies are beginning to bear fruit and the economy is showing signs of growth, which is the first step towards our national recovery.  The aim of Government policy is to improve living standards for all.  A growing economy and an improved jobs market are essential prerequisites.  That is our focus and objective, and that is what we intend to obtain.</p><p>Before discussing the Government's response to the opportunities and challenges facing us, I will provide Senators with a brief overview of the economic situation.  Last year's 1.4% expansion in GDP followed three successive years of annual declines.  Growth has continued into this year, rising modestly at 0.5% in the first half of this year compared with the same period last year.  The recovery is being led by the external sector.  Exports of goods and services are now well in excess of pre-crisis levels.  This demonstrates that the improvement in competitiveness, which has been evident in recent years, is now yielding benefits.  It highlights the inherent flexibility of the Irish economy given the significant improvements in relative prices and costs.  Strong export performance means that our balance of payments with the rest of the world moved into surplus in 2010 for the first time in more than a decade.</p><p>More recently, a surplus of €3.2 billion was recorded on the current account of the balance of payments in the second quarter of this year.  This is the largest nominal surplus recorded since records began in 1981.  While the figures can be volatile, it is notable that in the past four quarters the current account balance has averaged 3.3% of GDP.  In the second quarter of the year services exports recorded an 8% annual increase.  This again reflects the competitiveness improvements of recent years.  It also reflects the continuing willingness of foreign and domestic multinationals to locate new business in Ireland.  The pipeline for more foreign direct investment is strong and IDA Ireland has secured 77 foreign direct investments to date this year.</p><p>Notwithstanding these positive developments, the Government is acutely aware that the greatest fallout from our economic difficulties is in the labour market.  The October unemployment estimate at 14.8% is simply too high.  However, the only reliable way to bring down unemployment is to secure economic growth.  I repeat that is the main focus of the Government's economic policies.</p><p>On the budgetary front, the gap between revenue and expenditure remains large despite the reduction in the underlying deficit to an estimated 9.1% of GDP last year - well within the limit set under the EU-IMF programme.  The Government is committed to reducing the deficit further.  The latest available data are consistent with achieving this year's target of 8.6% of GDP.  Aggregate tax receipts for the 12 months to the end of October are up 6.3% on the same period last year on a headline basis and are 0.3% ahead of target with three of the four main sources of revenue outperforming expectations.</p><p>The majority of Departments continue to manage within their agreed limits.  That said, spending is somewhat higher than planned in the social protection and health areas, which is a serious cause for concern.  First, in order to achieve budgetary targets and, second, to restore confidence in the sound management of the public finances, the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, Deputy Howlin, is working with ministerial colleagues in these areas to ensure that allocations are managed effectively.</p> <p> The Government continues to meet the quantitative fiscal targets set out as part of the EU-IMF programme, most recently for the end of September.  Compliance with these targets has helped a great deal in restoring Ireland's reputation as we seek to return the public finances to a more sustainable path.  Our recent return to the bond markets is a clear measure of the progress Ireland has made towards emerging from the programme.  Success here illustrates that the strong programme implementation by the Government is recognised by investors and that Ireland's recovery is on track.</p><p> As a small, open economy, Ireland's prospects are inextricably linked to wider global developments.  Concerning our main trading partners, GDP in the euro area contracted by 0.2% in the second quarter of this year following a flat first quarter.  UK GDP grew by 1% in the third quarter, following three successive quarters of negative growth.  The United States figures are a little more encouraging, with GDP increasing by 0.4% in the second quarter.  The IMF recently revised downwards its global growth projections for 2013, including for Ireland's main trading partners, in particular the UK and euro area.  Thus demand for our exports in 2013 will not be as high as had been anticipated when the Department of Finance last published its growth forecasts in April.</p><p> The Government is acutely aware that many in our society who have been negatively affected by the economic difficulties of the past four years are under immense strain.  I repeat that job creation is our key objective in this regard, and putting in place the right policies to encourage growth in employment is at the centre of the policy action.</p><p> I wish to go into detail on some issues, particularly mortgage arrears, as colleagues have requested that this be done during the debate.  The Government is aware of the significant difficulties homeowners face in meeting their mortgage obligations.  The Government is committed to advancing appropriate measures to assist those mortgage holders experiencing real and genuine difficulty.  The Government is now actively implementing the main report recommendations of the interdepartmental working group on mortgage arrears, and significant milestones have been achieved.</p><p> The Personal Insolvency Bill passed Report Stage last week in Dáil Éireann.  The Minister of State with responsibility for housing and planning formally launched the mortgage to rent scheme on a nationwide basis.  Lenders have provided the Central Bank with details of their proposed forbearance and loan modification options.  Some forbearance measures have been introduced on a pilot basis and are being further rolled out.  The Minister of Social Protection has put in place an extensive independent mortgage advice framework.  This comprises an enhanced website, <i>www.keepingvourhome.ie</i>, a mortgage arrears information helpline, and the provision of free, independent, one-to-one professional financial advice to borrowers considering a long-term forbearance or resolution offer from their lender.</p><p> The Government remains committed to progressing these measures to assist genuine mortgage holders in difficulty.  These are in addition to existing supports such as the protections offered by the Central Bank's code of conduct on mortgage arrears.  The Government sub-committee on mortgage arrears, chaired by the Taoiseach, continues to ensure this issue receives priority attention.</p><p> In terms of the labour market, the Government's Action Plan for Jobs 2012 was launched earlier this year by my colleague, the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, Deputy Bruton, and builds on work throughout Government to deliver reform and create economic growth.  We will build on the progress made on economic reforms to accelerate jobs growth and get the economy working again.</p><p> Action Plan for Jobs 2012 is the first instalment in an ambitious multi-year process.  It aims to create, by 2016, the environment where the number of people at work will increase by 100,000 people net to approximately 1.9 million and reach 2 million people by 2020.  Its success will depend on whether it fosters greater job retention and creation.  The latest progress report shows that in the third quarter of 2012, Departments and agencies had delivered on schedule.  This equates to an 87% completion rate of the 67 measures due.</p> <p> That said, structural unemployment is a key concern, and is reflected in the regrettably high share of long-term unemployed.  This remains in part a legacy of the aftermath of the construction boom and the decline of associated sectors.  To combat this the Government has prioritised job creation and retention through the action plan on jobs and Pathways to Work which is the Government's jobs activation programme.  We have also successfully negotiated with our programme partners that some of the receipts from the sale of State assets will be directed to support job creation.</p><p> Ireland must maintain its position as an attractive destination for inward investment.  We must position our economy to take advantage of the global recovery when it emerges.  While the sustainability of the public finances is paramount, the Government has taken, and will continue to take, steps to support competitiveness.  These include the Government's commitment to the 12.5% rate of corporation tax and to maintaining and enhancing our pro-business tax policies.  As a result, Ireland continues to attract inward foreign direct investment.  Almost 1,000 companies, including Google, eBay and Facebook, have chosen Ireland as their European hub.  Equally encouraging are recent investment decisions by Irish companies to locate new business at home.</p><p> Since 2011 the Government has introduced and enhanced a number of pro-business tax measures.  The 2012 Finance Act introduced the special assignee relief programme<i></i>to attract key talent and innovators to Ireland.  We have also introduced the foreign earnings deduction to support companies looking to expand into the emerging BRIC markets of Brazil, Russia, India and China, and also South Africa.  Significant enhancements to the research and development tax credit scheme have been internationally recognised as best in class.  Improvements in the three-year tax exemption for start-ups<i></i>now ties the value of the relief to employment creation.  Furthermore, the jobs initiative introduced a reduction in the VAT rate on certain employment intensive industries such as tourism, while a reduced rate of PRSI payable by employers supports wage competitiveness.</p><p> Given Ireland's labour costs contribution to total costs, its competitiveness significantly impacts on overall competitiveness.  Unit labour costs, relative to the euro area, have improved substantially in recent years and are forecast to continue to converge in the coming years.  Exchange rate movements also benefit our competitiveness.  Last year's euro depreciation against the dollar and sterling has been of great benefit given our greater exposure to trade outside of the euro area.</p><p> Despite the challenges we face, the Government will spend &#8364;17 billion on the 2012-16 capital programme.  That level of expenditure is based on what we can afford and targeted at where it is needed most.  The programme is designed to facilitate economic growth and build our social infrastructure.  An increasing share of our scarce capital resources will be allocated to schools and health care facilities.  These areas will benefit the construction industry in terms of stimulating increased demand and the consequent jobs that will follow. </p><p> Last July my colleague and Minister, Deputy Howlin, announced the Government's plan for an additional &#8364;2.25 billion investment in jobs-rich public infrastructure projects in Ireland.  Intensive efforts were made to identify projects that are realistic, credible and deliverable.  The bulk of project funding will come from a combination of the National Pensions Reserve Fund, the European Investment Bank and Council of Europe bank, domestic banks and other potential private investment sources.   Phase 1 of our public private partnership programme is estimated to generate up to 13,000 jobs.  Phase 1 will focus on projects valued at up to &#8364;1.4 billion in the education, health, transport and justice sectors.</p><p> The importance of ensuring a sustainable public finance position is clear to all.  The Government must demonstrate, nationally and internationally, that the public finances are gradually returning to a sustainable level.  Our debt-to-GDP ratio must be put on a downward path and the ratio is expected to peak next year and will fall thereafter.<br /><b></b>With regard to the medium term, the external environment is expected to strengthen from 2014 onwards, as is our export growth.  As stronger exports start to feed through to investment and employment, consumer confidence is expected to improve and the savings rate should start to fall.  I expect to see economic activity beginning to gradually firm up and broaden out from being externally driven to domestic demand beginning to make a modest contribution. </p> <p>The strong performance of foreign direct investment points to the fact that many of the underlying strengths of our economy remain, including a well educated workforce, favourable demographics, an open and flexible economy and a pro-enterprise environment.</p><p>Much, however, remains to be done and I reiterate that addressing the difficulties in the labour market remains our biggest challenge.  Recent figures point to signs of stabilisation in the labour market.  The next task is to get unemployment on a downward path.</p><p>While the Government is taking every step to support economic recovery, there are no quick fixes.  We must continue to deliver on our commitments under our EU-IMF programme and, in so doing, ensure that the programme is working for us.  The Government's main priorities, to restore order to the public finances, repair the banking system and improve competitiveness, reflect the scale of the challenge we face.</p><p>We are on track to bring the deficit below 3% of GDP by 2015. The banking system has been recapitalised and the economy returned to growth last year following three successive years of annual declines.  The Government is delivering a return to sustainable growth that plays to the underlying strengths of the economy.</p><p>Tomorrow, the Department of Finance will publish its revised forecasts for 2012 and later years.  These will take account of more recent information and the outlook for the international economy.</p><p>The Government is reacting decisively and in a timely manner to address our economic challenges.  This is widely recognised internationally by those who objectively assess our performance.  Hard decisions have been taken and these have helped reposition our economy on a more sustainable, export-led growth path.  The return to modest growth demonstrates that these hard decisions are now beginning to bear fruit.  While this has not yet had a positive impact on the labour market, as momentum builds in the economy we can expect further positive dividends, particularly in the labour market.</p><p>I look forward to the debate that will follow my contribution.  I assure Senators that the Government has an open mind when it comes to listening to the contributions of colleagues on all sides and considering sensible suggestions that will help us all to get the economy working again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="17:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300029#CC00200"><p>I apologise to the Cathaoirleach and the Minister of State for my absence for the early part of his speech.  I had thought a colleague would be here in my stead.  I thank the Minister of State for outlining the Government's position and thank him for coming to the Seanad, as he so frequently does.</p><p>The picture the Minister of State and the Government paint of the economy, however, is more rosy than the reality.  The gross national product for the second quarter of this year was flat.  The economy avoided slipping back into recession by just €3 million.  This shows the difficult position the country and the Government are in.  The overall figures show the familiar story that has been continuing for the past few years.  Companies that are selling outside the country are doing well, and in some cases very well, but domestic demand continues to fall.  The massive expansion on the export front, which the Minister of State graciously acknowledges goes back to at least 2010, is not making up for the depressed demand in the domestic economy.  In the last year, consumer spending was down about 2.5% and investment spending was down 18%.  For our economy to recover properly we need more than exports, although we are grateful for them.  We also need consumer spending and internal business investment to increase.</p><p>Unfortunately, there has been a fall of about 24,000 at work this year and 34,000 fewer people are employed full time than at the end of 2011.  The fall in the second quarter of this year was the highest since 2010.  Broader measures of unemployment would show that about a quarter of the workforce are not working to the extent they would like.  This presents a severe challenge, not just for the Government but for the entire political system.  It presents a challenge for us in opposition not just to criticise and castigate, as was the practice for many years, but also to provide some alternatives and constructive suggestions, which the Minister of State invited today.</p><p>The Government should scrap the pension levy it imposed on private pensions last year to pay for a spin led jobs initiative which made no impact whatsoever on the jobs numbers.  I debated this expenditure of money with the Minister of State at the time.</p> <p>I suggested to him that there should be a jobs target and that we would actually see where the money was being spent and what the results were.  I also suggested I would be the first to congratulate the Government if unemployment was reduced as a result of all that spending, but it did not happen.  We took a tax out of people's pensions which, in some cases, resulted in a 10% reduction in their pension payments, in particular those of the Tara Mines workers, although it also had an impact on schemes such as the Aer Lingus one, but there was no direct result except a positive PR spin that the Government was doing something about it.  We are not careful enough about how we spend our money.  That was a huge problem for many years and it is about time we learned the lesson.  Instead of that pension levy, we should mandate pension funds to invest in job creation schemes.  There has been a tiny bit of progress on that from the Government but not enough to make a difference.</p><p>Since coming into office, the Government has undertaken the jobs initiative, a jobs friendly budget and an action plan for jobs but the number of people at work continues to fall.  The burden of rates is becoming intolerable for many small businesses while large multiples pay a much smaller proportion of their turnover on rates.  Serious concerns have been brought to the Department's attention in regard to the Valuation (Amendment) Bill and to the dangers for business which it presents.  In fact, that Bill is a jobs shedding one and it is time the Government took a serious look at the concerns expressed.  Many of the business associations have not been on the case in regard to this Valuation (Amendment) Bill but the few that have hit the nail on the head in regard to certain provisions of the Bill and how it will kill jobs.</p><p>We need to reverse the cuts made to home insulation grants.  In budget 2012, grants for internal wall insulation were slashed by 64% for apartments and mid-terraced houses and by 46% for semi-detached houses and end of terrace houses.  There were cuts of 55% in the grants available for external wall insulation, which is more expensive, and the grants for attic insulation were cut by 20%.  That is unfortunate and it is short-sighted, it will cost jobs and it will make it extremely difficult for Ireland to meet its retrofit and energy reduction targets.  Not only will it cost those jobs, but people will spend more of their money on utility bills rather than in the productive sector of the economy. </p><p>We have to tackle the black economy.  One suggestion I ask the Minister to take seriously is that in every commercial transaction, there should be a requirement to give and receive a receipt.  As I understand it, there is no such requirement in Ireland while in many continental countries, if one leaves a shop without taking a receipt, one is technically guilty of an offence.  It is not a requirement here and the contractors federation is looking for something similar to that.  If there was a legal obligation to give and receive a receipt in every commercial transaction, it could help tackle the black economy.</p><p>I have a number of concerns about the mortgage situation.  It is completely germane to the whole issue of the economy.  I was not expecting the Minister to address it relatively comprehensively and I am glad he did, but I have a number of concerns.  The mortgage-to-rent scheme is not working.  It is simply a pilot scheme.  The Minister's former colleague, Olwyn Enright, and I produced a joint report for the former Oireachtas Joint Committee on Social and Family Affairs and we recommended that as one of a number of solutions.  I thought one would rent the property from the bank but instead the Government has to give the bank money to pay off the mortgage.  It seems that cannot work without significant expenditure by the Government.  </p><p>The mortgage arrears resolution procedures within the banks are starting to kick in with banks actually dealing with these cases.  The result is the banks are now moving to get rid of people.  For the past few years, this was not organised and it gave people breathing space but that is now gone and people are getting letters from the banks saying there is nothing more they can do for them.  The banks are now judge and jury in regard to individual cases.  We will have to look at that because I do not think it will work for the benefit of the individual and we are only starting to get experience of how that system works.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1160" speakername="Michael D'Arcy" time="17:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300030#DD00200"><p>I have sometimes been very critical of Senator Byrne but I thought his contribution was sharp and on the ball.  I do not give positive praise to the Senator very often but on this occasion, it was deserved.  I want to start where Senator Byrne finished in regard to household debt.  The increase in the ratio of debt to disposable income from 2002 to 2012 has been astonishing.  It has gone as high as 2,013%, peaking at €214 billion which is an incredible figure.</p> <p>Taking the adverse scenario, in five years the figure will still be 150% of disposable income, effectively meaning that between now and then we will maintain that high ratio, which is where the ratio is in the UK today.  This means people will have a poor spending power, leading them to save and become more careful with money.  If they do not spend money, it is taken from the economy.</p><p>The predominant fear to spend in Irish society is a major issue for the Government to crack.  People are determined not to spend.  If they go shopping they may have a meal but not have a coffee, and if people have lunch they may not get their kids a soft drink.  This is why, as Senator Byrne noted, the second quarter was practically flat, with only €3 million in the difference stopping us reversing into recession.</p><p>When there were major credit booms and busts in the past, the issues were rectified through the likes of inflation, which gobbled some of the cost; growth, which took more of it; and write-downs.  As inflation is a little over 1% now, it will not gobble much.  The figures for growth will be out tomorrow and most people will be surprised if the growth prediction for 2013 is 1%, which means it will not be helpful.  We are left with reducing the debt burden through a write-down.  From the discussions we have had about usage of what we hope will be a personal insolvency Act, it seems we do not know what will be the attitudes of banks.</p><p>I welcome the Personal Insolvency Bill, which will come before us on 21 November.  A crucial aspect of the legislation will be the agreement between banks and individuals.  This will take in hundreds of thousands of cases and I wonder if banks will have the capacity to deal with hundreds of thousands of cases on a one-to-one basis.  A valuation Bill is ahead of us and we should take this opportunity to improve the system of rates.  The silliest aspects of this comes from case law.  For example, if somebody is in business and leaves a premises, the rates burden, if unpaid, stays with the premises even if some other party occupies it.  That is crazy as it means premises are normally left without occupants.  Money would be spent on a premises that should be used for business but instead it is left idle.</p><p>I will provide an example of the cost of living for a citizen.  I was recently told that when a person filled a tank of heating oil three years ago, the cost was €430.  It now costs €1,100 to fill the same tank.  People are not spending elsewhere because the cost to fill a heating oil tank has nearly trebled.  Spending power in other areas has been removed.  People commuting to work are in a similar boat.  My own town is a commuter area for this city, despite being 50 or 60 miles away, and people do not have spending power because of the cost of the commute.</p><p>I am not saying we should slaughter some of the sacred cows but we should analyse their cost.  For example, there should be a reasoned debate on corporation tax.  Some will say that this would scare corporations out of the country but I am not arguing for this.  Nevertheless, we should analyse the effects of a very modest increase of 1% and see if this would scare companies.  I do not know if these firms would run if our rate was 13.5% instead of 12.5% but we should analyse the figures.</p> <p>The burden arising from our current deficit should not fall completely on the taxpayer citizens of this country.</p><p>A property tax will be implemented and people are satisfied to pay more in taxes that they know and understand.  People know and understand the property tax, as almost 70% of people have paid the household charge, which will evolve into the property tax next year.  If people are given certainty about the figure for a fixed period such as five years, some of the sting may be taken from the process.  People need certainty and if the Government gives it to them, they will accept some of the burdens more easily than if it just tells them what is happening without a long-term view.  A longer perspective will make these issues more saleable.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" speakername="Feargal Quinn" time="17:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300032#FF00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State and, in general, the speech is welcome as well because it contained positive news.  It is fair to say that some developments have been very worthwhile.  I disagree entirely with Senator Michael D'Arcy, who said that people need certainty while indicating that we should play with corporation tax.  If we are to give investors certainty, we must make it very clear that the 12.5% corporation tax rate will stay and that we will not fiddle with it.</p><p>IBEC's new report indicates that 2012 will likely be the last year of falling employment because cuts to the public sector numbers are receding and the rate of decline in the domestic economy is slowing.  However, since 2010, budgetary measures have added €660 million per annum to the labour costs of Irish employers, and we must consider reducing those costs.  In the World Bank's ranking of ease of doing business, which was published recently, Ireland fell from 10th to 15th; Singapore remains in first place, as it takes just three days and three procedures to start a business there.  New Zealand is approximately our size and it is even better in some areas, as it takes just one day and one procedure to start a new business.  Why should we not aim to cut red tape, as it still takes ten days and four procedures to start a business in Ireland?  We should make it even easier to attract investment and do business in the country as it would be some help to the economy.  There are steps we can take in that direction.</p><p>We still have closed minds in many areas that could grow the economy.  Why are we not debating the possibility of extracting shale gas through fracking, for example?  I know there are some who are afraid to touch the subject but it would be worthwhile.  By approximately 2020, the United States is projected to become the world's largest global oil producer, overtaking Saudi Arabia.  The result will be a continued fall in US oil imports, currently at 20% of its needs, to the extent that North America will become a net exporter of oil.  It is worthwhile considering the matter.</p><p>IBEC has indicated there is still a skills gap in Ireland and we can do much in that area.  The financial services and ICT sectors need many extra skills, for example.  Some estimates have more than 2,500 urgent vacancies and approximately 5,000 current job vacancies across the entire web and Internet sector in Ireland.  Some of the key areas of shortage include web and mobile developers and designers, as well as project managers for application development.  The Minister for Education and Skills should consider teaching web coding to schoolchildren.  That may seem excessive when we have difficulty teaching them French, German or some other language but there are vacancies that can be filled if we only teach the required skills.</p><p>The Government is examining pensions and the last time I spoke about releasing a portion of the pensions to stimulate the economy, the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, Deputy Howlin, said he understood the case made and &quot;thought would have to be given to whether such an exercise would result in the diminution of people's capacity to pay their own way and not be a burden on the State&quot;.  I would like to open the debate.  People in great need due to mortgage or credit card debt could get some money now to help them survive.  People need cashflow now and we can go a long way working on that.  South Africa offers access to pension savings, and research by a consultancy, Alexander Forbes International, indicated that 70% of members there take their benefits in cash before retirement.  It is also believed that allowing people early access to a portion of their pension offers encouragement to sign up to a pension scheme.</p><p>Australia's pension scheme requires compulsory enrolment but members are allowed to take all the benefit as a lump sum at 55.  A similar measure would help many people who may be three months in arrears on a mortgage or have €1,000 in credit card debt.  Any remaining money would go back into the economy.  There is an estimated €100 billion in Irish savings in pension funds, 90% of which are outside the country.  Money would flow back here if the Government allowed my proposal.</p><p>Senator Barrett will speak later and he recently mentioned how Denmark issues mortgages.  That country is also progressive in its treatment of pensions, having introduced a pension release initiative in 2009, with higher than anticipated take-up because householders opted to dip into pension savings in order to offset the worst effects of the economic crisis.  I hope the Senator touches on the issue, which was regarded as an effective response to very difficult economic circumstances.  When this was carried out in Denmark, 94% of the people with such funds chose to access them, resulting in a stimulus of 1.4% of GDP and an Exchequer windfall of something like €2 billion.</p><p>There is much we can do.  The six minute speaking time limit may be forcing us to squeeze in some of the thoughts reaching uppermost in our minds.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" speakername="John Gilroy" time="17:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300032#FF00300"><p>I welcome the Minister of State's return to the Chamber and always look forward to him coming here because he has a particular fondness for engagement.  His contributions are always very informative.  There are so many issues facing the economy that it is almost impossible to think of how we could even address one of them in the six minutes allocated to us.  I will speak to some of the many aspects of debt.</p><p>One of the many important elements to our economic difficulty is the fiscal deficit, which will approach 120% of GDP next year.  That is extremely worrying.  Figures are changing all the time in discussing what is a dangerous level of debt.  It was traditionally thought 80% of GDP was very dangerous, and this figure has moved to 90% or even a third higher than that again.  It represents a significant drag on the economy and everything we try to achieve.  If we do not close the fiscal deficit, we will not take control of our own affairs.  It is not possible to close the fiscal deficit easily with a mixture of inflation, reduction in spending and tax increases.  The economy would not be capable of sustaining such measures.  There has been much comment about the level of indebtedness in the country, of which public debt is only one element.  Senator Michael D'Arcy referred to household debt, which is of a similar magnitude to public debt.  Non-financial corporate debt has also been mentioned.  I have heard a Member from the other House quoting combined figures leaving the economy on the hook for approximately €850 billion.  That is not right as at least €300 billion of that is multinational corporation debt and there is no possibility of the State being responsible for it.  Nevertheless, €550 billion in debt is substantial on its own and we must achieve some success in negotiating this figure down.</p><p>There are some welcome aspects to the direction in which the economy is going.  This morning held a good example, as Bank of Ireland returned to the capital markets and secured €1 billion of money over three years at 3.2%.  That rate is not great but it is a big improvement on the figure 12 months ago, which could have been ten percentage points above today's figure.  On the European Union's response to the financial problems in the interbank and financial markets, they have seemingly stabilised, perhaps only temporarily, with €1.1 trillion of long-term refinancing options in two tranches, which is welcome.</p> <p>However, this is not the solution because unless the intra-European financial markets work properly, we will not make the impact needed.  The only way that can be done is to restore confidence, as Senator Quinn said.  Restoring confidence at European level is important because the only way to fix the markets is to get private money flowing where public money is now flowing.  Until that is done, there will not be a solution to this crisis.  While it seems to have stabilised, a crisis, for example, if the Greek austerity budget had not passed on Sunday evening, would put the eurozone back in the melting pot again, which would have major knock-on effects for Ireland.  It is important that what we do as a Government must first and foremost and single-mindedly be about restoring confidence.</p><p>The target 2, T2, liability against the Central Bank of Ireland is approximately €150 billion and while T2 is not harmful or worrying, it might point to continued underlying weaknesses in the economy.  The Minister of State noted in his contribution that our balance of payments is positive and is not adding to our T2 liability.  Is capital still flowing from the country through the banks?  In what way are the T2 liabilities increasing?  If these liabilities begin to reduce, that will be one indication that everything is heading very much in our direction at a macro level.  The banks have reduced their dependence on the ELA to €45 billion this year from €130 billion last year, which is also promising.  In addition, the return of Bank of Ireland to the markets is encouraging and these changes show the Government’s strategy is heading in the right direction in many ways.</p><p>Many challenges still face us, the greatest of which is securing a deal on the bank debt.  Anything else we do will not make much difference if we do not secure a deal.  What progress has been made in the negotiations on securing a deal on the Anglo Irish Bank promissory notes?  They offer the best opportunity to secure a deal on the debt.  While negotiations are taking place, I will be critical of the Government in one sense.  There seems to be a lack of information or a lack of leadership on this.  Commentators in all sectors of society and among the Government and Opposition parties are pointing to different strategies we should pursue.  Should we burn the notes?  Should we pay them in full?  Should we restructure them?  As a Government, if we offered a little more certainty about the direction we are taking on this, it might make the route towards financial independence for the State a little easier.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="17:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300033#GG00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State.  As my party colleagues have said, we have given the Government parties a fair wind.  The public has a positive attitude towards the Government&#8217;s efforts in trying to get us back to where we were.   While I do not think we will ever get back to that position, we can at least get to a point where we will have reduced our deficit and met all the economic targets the Government has set.  I wish the Government parties continued success in their efforts in that regard.</p><p>  I would like to focus on competitiveness, an issue I raised on the Order of Business.  The Minister of State said this included the Government&#8217;s commitment to the 12.5%  rate of corporation tax and maintaining and enhancing its pro-business tax policies.  He referenced a number of multinationals.  The Government is correct to maintain the line that we stick solidly and rigidly to the 12.5% rate and there is an all-party consensus in this regard.  We are under increasing pressure again, particularly as we seek a <i>quid pro quo</i> from Europe to review the rate again.  The tax policy pursued by the Government and previous Administrations going back over many decades has been correct.  It is the right strategy and it has shown that Ireland, as the Minister of State rightly pointed out, is a proactive location for multinationals.</p><p>  However, an investigation in the past few days by a parliamentary committee in the UK has highlighted anomalies in the UK's tax policies relating to multinationals and pointed out flaws.  Companies such as Google, Amazon and Starbucks allegedly are not paying any tax.  Starbucks, amazingly, said it had been operating at a loss for 15 years in the UK.  This is a tax avoidance rather than a tax default issue.  Deputy Richard Boyd Barrett received a reply to a parliamentary question a few weeks ago from the Minister of Finance which stated companies were paying a corporation tax rate of 4% or 5% and not 12.5%.  When the Government tries to balance the books and is searching for money, inevitably vulnerable people will suffer as a result of budgetary measures.  Has the Minister of State a response to the real corporation tax take at a rate of between 4% and 5%?  How will the Government address this?  If the Government tried to ensure it extracts more tax revenue from the multinationals, will they walk away?  Is there is a belief in government that this is a sacred cow, which cannot be touched?</p><p>  This issue should be reviewed because if the rate is 12.5%, then that is the rate that should be levied.  The multinationals are operating tax avoidance measures, including the Dutch sandwich and another which relates to Bermuda, where they hive off their profits to separate companies on the basis that their royalties can be set against their tax liabilities.  All this is legal and I do not wish to give the impression that I am bashing them but in the current climate with the Government trying to find &#8364;3.5 billion, the Minister of State referred to 1,000 multinationals.  I do not know how many are paying 4%, 5%, 10% or 12.5% but it would be interesting to know.  There is anger among the people about bankers' pensions of &#8364;400,000 and so on yet multinationals are generating billions of euro.  Recently, Google announced it made an &#8364;8 billion profit, yet it only paid a measly few million euro under the corporation tax regime.  Its response was to ask people to look at what it is contributing in other areas to the Exchequer.  I accept that and believe it is right and proper to pursue the strategy of attracting more multinationals to the country.  They are contributing to a reduction in unemployment and they generate economic activity wherever they are located.  They are good for the country but the question remains as to how the Government will square the circle.  If the rate is 12.5%, that is what companies should pay, not 4% or 5%.  I am sure if the Government knew it would be able come up with a few hundred million euro more from the multinationals, it would spare those who will be in the firing line next month, particularly those reliant on the Department of Social Protection whose budget must be reduced.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="17:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300033#GG00300"><p>I welcome the Minister of State. I would like to raise three issues relating to mortgages, unemployment and the cost of living.  I was aware that our debt-to-GDP ratio is 120% but I was struck hard when I heard recently that our household debt-to-GDP ratio is 130% because this means there is little room for cuts.  It is something to bear in mind when the axe falls.</p><p>The Minister of State made a substantial contribution on mortgage debt and I acknowledge the work we are doing as a Government in this area but a unique group is not being helped and has not become a statistic yet.  This group comprises people where more than 35% of their net income monthly goes on paying their mortgage.  They are managing but they are being screwed in terms of spending power and this is unsustainable.</p> <p>They are cutting back on fuel, heating and food.  They are good people.  If they could get some relief, they have the money to spend in the domestic economy.  They need relief.  Legislation in the US suggests mortgage payments above 37% of net income are unsustainable.  I met a family last week paying 70% of its net income on a mortgage.  How long can the family keep going?  We have lost trust in the banks.  The way to help these people is not through the banks, it is through mortgage interest relief.  We have made a decision but I ask the Minister of State to think again about particular subgroups, such as the cohort to which I referred.</p><p>Last week a Nobel laureate economist, Professor Pissarides, spoke on youth unemployment and said some interesting things.  He said we had a massive opportunity during the EU Presidency to persuade the powers that be, the troika, to split the budget between recurrent spending and investment spending.  It is not right to include recurrent spending, like civil servants' salaries, with investment spending.  He strongly advocated investing in job creation projects, which is the view of the Government, such as green tech, ICT and the health sector.  We have received €50 million from the European Investment Bank for schools and we should do more of that.  He advocated that made better sense than the youth guarantee, which is a programme we are considering.  He said the youth guarantee is too expensive for so little return.  It amounts to four months in employment or in training.  When one thinks about the criticism we suffered for the internships, which ran from six to nine months, we should re-examine what he is saying.  He also made a valid point about subsidies for employers.  He said it is better to give subsidies that offer work experience than unconditional unemployment compensation.  Perhaps the Minister of State can comment on splitting the troika budget between recurrent spending and investment spending.</p><p>My final question is on the cost of living.  What are we doing about it?  The price of electricity has gone through the roof.  I know families spending €200 a month on electricity, which is a huge bill yet it is a modest spend.  Senator Quinn referred to fracking, which is controversial.  Diesel remains an issue and is driving up the cost of goods and food.  How are we addressing it?  What are we doing with semi-State bodies to make them more competitive in the delivery of services?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="17:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300034#HH00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State and he always has our good wishes in the reforms he is trying to implement.  In response to the speech of the Minister of State, we have some growth but GNP was down 2.5% in 2011.  The domestic economy remains in trouble, as the Minister of State knows.  He also referred to tax receipts having increased by 6.3% in the year end to October.  It may be higher as the months progress but that is raising extra taxation out of a flat economy.  It is a problem I have with the strategy in the April 2011 IMF statement.  We are in the process of raising taxation from €34 billion to €44 billion and current expenditure is reducing from €49 billion to €48 billion.  Virtually all of the adjustment is being done on the tax side and current expenditure has increased this year.  No newspaper believes it and their headlines would be redundant if they actually read the numbers.  The so-called cutbacks are counterbalanced in other areas of Government activity by expenditure increases but all of the burden is being borne on the tax side.  That has created all sorts of problems in retail and tourism because that is how the economy is adjusting.  More should be done on the expenditure side, a point I will address presently.</p><p>Reforms are needed in government.  The Wright report was critical that only 7% of the staff in the Department of Finance had qualifications in economics.  Mr. Wright comes from Canada, where the proportion is 60%.  The Government needs a Government economic service, with economists in the spending Departments as well as in the Department of Finance.  When spending Ministers speak in the Chamber, it is rather obvious they do not evaluate alternatives.  Each Department tries to maximise its budget rather than deliver measures of outputs where we could judge whether programme A is good at poverty alleviation and is achieving its goals.  We must tackle that problem and we need proper public expenditure appraisal.</p><p>On the capital side, the Minister of State mentioned some projects but the danger with infrastructure is that we end up with empty roads, empty airports, empty hotels and empty houses.  There was an edifice complex in capital expenditure in this country in the past.  I propose a central office of project evaluation, publishing evaluations in advance and allowing people to evaluate them over the course of a year.</p><p>Ireland has a strong culture of political lobbying, which reflects the structure of public expenditure.  Lobbyists will be at the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Finance, Public Expenditure and Reform tomorrow and a large number of submissions would spend the imaginary surplus if there was any danger we will ever have a surplus.  No one is addressing the problem that the country is living far beyond its means and has developed an entitlement culture that has exhausted not just the taxable capacity of the country but also our borrowing capacity.  We have a bureaucracy problem.  An bord snip noted that the number of senior civil servants expanded far more rapidly than the number of civil servants as a whole.  Bureaucracy maximises its own budget.  We also have a lobbyist problem, which we must get a grip on because it will bankrupt the country again.</p><p>We also have a moral hazard problem in that most of the people who caused the crisis from 2008-10 are still walking around enlarging their incomes.  The Government must face up to that problem.  I love moral hazard being described by bankers as people who cannot afford a mortgage.  Bankers are the greatest exhibits of moral hazard.  They took €64 billion out of the Exchequer, which is not bad work for one evening.  We will not take any lectures from bankers, or IBEC more widely, about the dangers of moral hazard.  Bankers are the illustration of regulatory capture.  We have far too many useless regulators.  Senator Healy Eames mentioned energy.  All of the regulators are captured by the producers and do not act in the public interest.  I will not trod on the patience of the Cathaoirleach anymore.  Anything this side of the House can do, we will be delighted to do.  The Minister of State has an important national task.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1144" speakername="Jimmy Harte" time="17:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300034#HH00300"><p>The Minister of State is welcome to the debate on this important subject.  Last week was armistice week in Europe and one of the epitaphs on the Menin Gate in Ypres is "For your tomorrow, we gave our today."  The epitaph for the latter part of the 20th and the early part of the 21st century could be "For our today, we took your tomorrow".  We owe it to the next generation, which has yet to be born, and the children starting school, to fix the economy.  We are now in a debt war and it is hanging over every family throughout most of western Europe.  Unless we sort out debt, the generation that is yet to be born will look back on us and say that we left it with nothing.</p><p>The Government is moving in the right direction and the domestic economy is the secret.  We must generate credit in the domestic economy.  Today I met Mr. John Trethowan of the Credit Review Office and spoke about the issues and progress he is making.  I am confident the work he is doing with his staff in getting small businesses finance, with the assistance of the Government, is a positive development.  At the same time, he is under-resourced and could do more with greater resources.  With the help of the Minister for Finance, the Minister of State should seek to strengthen the staffing levels of the Credit Review Office so that, working with the county development boards, small businesses can be helped to get off the ground and businesses that are surviving but unsure of the future can be helped to get access to finance.  The Credit Review Office also has a function in respect of large employers employing hundreds of people.</p> <p>The evidence is that the banks, when they can, are still holding back on providing finance.  There is a role for us, therefore, in promoting the credit guarantee scheme and the microfinance loan schemes that have been put in place.  Many small business are not aware of these schemes.  Accountancy firms and bodies must also promote the schemes and engage more with the Credit Review Office.  It has said that any case it deals with where there is a satisfactory outcome helps to preserve and create jobs.  Therefore, it has an important function.</p><p> Senator Feargal Quinn<b></b>made an important point when he said that pension funds should be released for the purpose of clearing debt.  I would hold the opposite view having spoken to people in that field.  The pension funds were put aside by people in business to ensure they could live in comfort during retirement.  That is an important point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="17:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300035#JJ00200"><p>I fully agree.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1144" speakername="Jimmy Harte" time="17:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300035#JJ00300"><p>There was a recent court case where a financial institution tried to call in the pension fund of an individual and was unsuccessful.  If we tamper with pension funds and seek to have them released early or to take partial payments out of them, the courts might say that if they are to be used for purposes other than one's pension, we may end up letting the institutions grab them, as it were.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor Ó Clochartaigh" time="17:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300035#JJ00500"><p>Cuirim céad fáilte arís roimh an Aire Stáit.  Díospóireacht iontach tábhachtach é seo agus is mór agam deis a bheith agam mo chuid tuairimí féin agus tuairimí mo phairtí a roinnt leis.  We are approaching two years since Fine Gael and the Labour Party won the election and formed the Government.  At that time people undoubtedly voted for change but, I believe, they have been let down and an increasing number of people realise that the Government has no interest in bringing about a change in economic policy.  It has not been an easy time in government because the Fianna Fáil and Progressive Democrats economics had brought the country to its knees.  Fine Gael and the Labour Party took over a state with 14% unemployment and tens of thousands emigrating each year.  It was a State whose sovereignty had been surrendered and which had taken on an unsustainable banking debt.</p><p>Unfortunately, all those facts remain true because there has been no real change in policy.  To continue with the failed policies of Fianna Fáil and the Progressive Democrats and expect a different result is crazy.  Still, the banks - our banks - are not lending to small and medium-sized enterprises.  The education and health sectors are under constant pressure fearing for the next round of cuts.  It is not an easy time to be in government but the Government is fond of saying it is making hard choices.  Is it, however?  Is it not taking the easy way out by blindly following IMF diktats by doing things the Fianna Fáil way?  What would be a brave choice would be to commit the State and its resources to a stimulus plan such as the one Sinn Féin has proposed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" speakername="John Gilroy" time="17:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300035#JJ00600"><p>Is that the fantasy one?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.173" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor Ó Clochartaigh" time="17:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300035#JJ00700"><p>I told the Minister of State recently that we had just launched our draft plan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.174" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="17:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300035#JJ00800"><p>I got a copy of it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor Ó Clochartaigh" time="17:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300035#JJ00900"><p>Good man.  I am very grateful.  I hope to see the fruits of that on budget day.  By using the National Pensions Reserve Fund, the European Investment Bank and private pension funds we would create more than 150,000 jobs.  That is not an easy choice but it is the right one.</p><p>It is not, despite the Government's claims, the hard thing to do to tax the lower and middle income earners to balance the books or to impose flat taxes, such as property and water taxes, on struggling working families.  What would be the harder and right approach would be to introduce a higher third rate of tax on high earners and to introduce a wealth tax where the assets of the very wealthy are taxed.</p><p>Last night at a meeting of the community and voluntary sector in Galway, which has arranged a lobby, I was asked to bring a message to the Seanad today because the sector to which I referred is at breaking point owing to the cuts that have been introduced.  The representatives showed a graph from the EU-SILC report which indicates that, through the austerity of recent years, those on higher incomes have made more money and are better off than those on lower incomes, whereas more of the burden has been piled on to the lower income families.  I suggest that report be taken on board because those groups are finding it very difficult.</p><p>By cutting rather than investing and by taxing those who are struggling to pay, the Government is preventing economic growth by killing off domestic demand in the economy.  People have less money in their pockets and less confidence to spend it.  I note that the United Nations Committee on Trade and Development and the IMF have recently issued reports stating that austerity is not working.</p><p>I ask the Minister of State to take on board the suggestions that have been made by ourselves and others in this sphere.  The suggestions are made in good faith in order that the community and voluntary sector and all the people in society who cannot afford to take more of the burden will not be lumbered with it.  I hope he will take the suggestions on board in the pre-budget deliberations.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" speakername="Terry Brennan" time="17:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300035#JJ01000"><p>Ba mhaith liom fáilte ar ais go dtí an Seanad a chur roimh an Aire Stáit.  As the Minister of State said, last year saw an expansion in gross domestic product of some 1.4%.  This followed three years of successive decline in GDP and marked a positive first step on the road to recovery.  Growth has continued into this year, rising at the modest rate of 0.5% in the first half of the year compared with the same period in 2011.  It is a start.  The recovery is being led by the external sector, with exports of goods and services well in excess of pre-crisis levels.  The strong export performance also means our balance of payments with the rest of the world moved into surplus in 2010 for the first time in more than a decade.  This is welcome.</p><p>As the Minister of State said, in the second quarter of the year, services exports recorded an 8% annual increase.  Our aim is to win more foreign direct investment.  I note that IDA Ireland has secured 73 foreign direct investments to date this year.  That is no mean achievement.  IDA Ireland, the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, Deputy Richard Bruton, and the Minister of State must be complimented on this significant investment in additional jobs in the country.  However, unemployment was estimated at 14.8% in September, which is still far too high.  The only reliable way to reduce unemployment is to secure economic growth.  That is, and no doubt will remain, the main focus of the Government's economic policies.</p><p>It is good to note that aggregate tax receipts so far this year to the end of September are 1.5% ahead of target, with three of the four main sources of revenue performing better than expected.  I hope this will be borne in mind at the forthcoming December budget.  I note the Government successfully negotiated with the troika that some of the receipts from the sale of State assets will be used for job creation.  I ask that strategic infrastructure, be it the ESB, gas pipelines or whatever, would not be for sale and would be held as State assets for future generations.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.177" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" speakername="Jillian van Turnhout" time="17:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300035#JJ01100"><p>The Senator's time has expired.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" speakername="Terry Brennan" time="17:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300035#JJ01200"><p>The three-year tax exemption for start-up companies, the value of the relief for employment creation and the jobs initiative are welcome.  I read somewhere that the NAMA investment plan proposes to invest €2 billion between 2012 and 2016.  Perhaps the Minister of State can provide an update on when it is likely to start.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.179" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" speakername="Jillian van Turnhout" time="17:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300035#JJ01300"><p>The Senator is well over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" speakername="Terry Brennan" time="17:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300035#JJ01400"><p>Tá an tAire Stáit ag déanamh a dhícheall agus tá sé ar an mbóthar ceart.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.181" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1173" speakername="Lorraine Higgins" time="17:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300035#JJ01500"><p>I raise an issue which has been raised by several colleagues, that is, the banking sector in Ireland.  If the Irish banks are reluctant to reverse their current rule of thumb and associated trends of having a loan rejection rate second only to Greece in the eurozone of 24% of all loan applications to the SME sector, I ask the Minister of State to consider setting up a special working group in his Department to explore the possibility and feasibility of establishing a new bank or make efforts to encourage licence applications from banking institutions with similarities to that of the former ICC and ACC banks which targeted the very important sectors of Irish businesses as a way of generating significant economic growth.</p> <p> We need proper banking competition in this country if we are to make any real achievements in the economy and we need to encourage new institutions to set up here.  At present we have the same old banks with the same old legacies.  Let us take some inspiration from what the UK has done where the Bank of England has recently granted a licence to a new bank called Metro Bank.  This bank targets more than half of its lending to the SME sector and commercial enterprises.  This is exactly the kind of statistic of which I would like to see Ireland boast next year.</p><p> The crux of the problem is that all the banks currently operating in the market are retail banks.  There is no properly focused business bank and it is high time for one to enter the market and the Government needs to make efforts to allow this to happen.  We need to ensure banks are financing cash-flow businesses.  We also need to ensure that officials get the proper training  <i>vis-à-vis</i>consideration of business plans so that viable business plans are approved for finance and not let slip through the net.  We are missing the opportunity to finance Irish businesses and entrepreneurs.  If we do not correct this trend and take remedial action, we will face paralysis.  We owe it to the country to avoid this.</p><p> Without a proper functioning banking system we will not be able to rebuild Ireland.  We must recognise how critical SMEs are for economic development and we must do everything to address the conditions which have been inflicted upon them in recent times.  Therefore I urge the Minister of State to earnestly consider the proposals my colleagues and I have made with regard to the banking sector.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.183" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="18:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300036#KK00200"><p>I thank my colleagues for their very informed and constructive contributions to this very important debate.  Senator Harte summed it up very well when he spoke about the economic war through which we are living.  This is an economic war and is about the survival of the country.  When I studied economics the people who taught me made it clear that when an economy has a debt to GDP ratio of more than 90% it is in major trouble and a country with a current budget deficit of more than 10% is also in major trouble.  On the latter issue we are making steady progress, but it is still an enormous deficit that needs to be rectified over a period of years.  The key task the Government faces, as Senator Harte and others mentioned, is the need to bring that deficit down to a manageable 3% by 2015.  Of course that is made easier if we see economic growth re-emerge.  We are seeing some tentative signs of that at the moment.  Last year was positive whereas in the previous three years effectively 14% of GDP was knocked out.  That was an extraordinary cliff over which the entire economy fell.</p><p>While we must do that, we must also make the correction through tax increases and reductions in expenditure.  We need to get that balance right.  Based on all the international evidence, if we are to correct a deficit while trying to resuscitate an economy, we need to do more on the public expenditure side than the tax side.  We will not encourage entrepreneurship and investment, and get people back to work by taxing the hell out of people either on the corporate side or on the individual side.  We need to get that balance right.</p><p>Of course much of the heavy lifting will need to be done by way of GDP growth.  For every 1% of GDP growth, we get €1.6 billion into the economy through new jobs, more investment and revenue coming in.  While we must continue on the taxes consolidation side and reduce expenditure in circumstances when more children are coming into our schools, there is more pressure on our hospitals and there are so many people out of work who need to be paid, that is not easy but we need to get that balance right.  We need to do that in a way that is fair for everyone.  I echo what the Minister for Finance said to our party and externally, that we need to do this in a fair way.  Those with the broadest shoulders will need to bear the brunt of this.</p><p>We should not forget from where we have come.  Since 2008 some €24 billion has been taken out of the Irish economy and we were told that if we did that, we would never see growth again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.184" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="18:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300036#KK00300"><p>The Minister of State and his colleagues told us that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.185" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="18:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300036#KK00400"><p>We have shown that by taking money out of the economy in a fair way and getting the balance right between tax and expenditure, we can still resuscitate the economy.  The good news - if there is any good news - is that there is only €8.5 billion to go, but arguably it is the most difficult €8.5 billion because so much of the low-hanging fruit has been taken out already.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.186" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="18:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300036#KK00500"><p>What does the Minister of State consider as low-hanging fruit - pay cuts and welfare cuts?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.187" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" speakername="Jillian van Turnhout" time="18:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300036#KK00600"><p>The Minister of State to continue, without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="18:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300036#KK00700"><p>I did not interrupt the Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.189" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="18:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300036#KK00800"><p>There is all this nonsense that it was only low-hanging fruit that we cut in the €24 billion, every penny of which the Minister of State's party opposed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.190" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" speakername="Jillian van Turnhout" time="18:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300036#KK00900"><p>Can we hear the Minister of State without interruption, please?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.191" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="18:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300036#KK01000"><p>This is old rubbish.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.192" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="18:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300036#KK01100"><p>I thought the Senator realised his party lost the election, but it has still taken him nearly two years to realise it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.193" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="18:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300036#KK01200"><p>We thought the Government would introduce different policies after the public rejected our policies, but it has brought in the same policies.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.194" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="18:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300036#KK01300"><p>I want to make something clear to the Senator because he is a very slow learner in this regard.  We will ensure that the economy comes out of the negative territory in which his party left it.  We will ensure the economy grows in so far as we can.  As I have repeatedly said, the economy is a bit like a cork bobbing up and down on a huge ocean.  More than any economy in western Europe we are very exposed to the international markets.  We have a thriving economy and a well trading economy.  We have an economy that is highly deleveraged and highly privatised.  It is not like the Mediterranean example.  We actually have a smallish public sector <i>vis-à-vis</i> many other economies in Europe.  As the world comes out of this difficulty and as we get some stability back into the eurozone, the economy will come back quicker than most.  That is the view of the Minister for Finance and the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform.</p><p>  Let us consider the issue of VAT.  When we increased VAT last year from 21% to 23%, the Opposition advised that the total take in that area would reduce.  However, since then there has been an increase in the amounts of money coming into the economy from VAT.  We have made it absolutely clear that there is nothing more to give in this regard, particularly in the area of indirect taxation.  We did it deliberately to ensure that last year we did not increase income taxation.</p><p>  I do not agree with Senator Michael D'Arcy on corporation tax.  When there is such uncertainty the last thing to do is to have further doubt.  One of the great advantages of the 12.5% corporate tax rate is that it creates absolute certainty on which there is political consensus.  It sends a clear signal to international investors that Ireland will not change its 12.5% rate and that is the right message to send in circumstances where up to 250,000 direct and indirect jobs are related to foreign direct investment - the kinds of jobs that can move very quickly overnight.  Of course they are not only coming here for the 12.5% corporate tax rate, as the Senator and others know.  They are coming here because we have a well-educated workforce, we speak English, our currency is the euro, the demographics are good, and our workers are excellent in their flexibility and productivity.  One of the great stories from this recovery is the way in which we have still managed to obtain very significant investments from US and other companies coming to Ireland and I believe we should not change the corporate tax rate.</p><p>  I understand that five years ago the amount we were taking in in corporate tax was just over &#8364;7 billion.  The amount this year will be &#8364;3.6 billion.  I do not believe it makes sense to increase the corporate tax rate when the yield has reduced by almost half.  At the height of the boom we were taking in &#8364;59 billion in taxes - corporate taxes, personal taxes, VAT etc.  That reduced in 2008 to &#8364;31 billion.  During that period of time, as Senator Barrett rightly pointed out, we have not seen a significant reduction in expenditure.  We have seen a slight reduction, but the amounts have not radically reduced.  We face an enormous challenge where the entire economy fell off a cliff and tax receipts, one third of which were predicated on a hyped up property boom, collapsed.  We have to repair that tax system by broadening the tax base, which is the Government's policy.</p> <p> Senator Quinn spoke about reducing the cost to employers and I very much agree with him.  It makes no sense to increase taxes on employers in circumstances where we are trying to ensure they create the jobs of tomorrow.  I also agree we need to do much more on reducing red tape and bureaucracy and make it easier for people to employ within our economy.  We have done some very positive things in this regard.  In the jobs budget we reduced PRSI where employers hire new employees.  This made a difference and I very much reject what Senator Byrne stated.  The advantage of the jobs strategy pursued by the pension levy was that we saw substantial growth in the numbers employed in the hospitality and tourism sectors.  This happened as a result of the measures we introduced, particularly reducing VAT from 13.5% to 9%.</p><p>We are examining how to utilise the pension savings in the economy.  The Minister for Finance made very clear in his Budget Statement last year that this year he would engage in consultations with the Irish pensions industry to examine ways in which the upcoming budget could get the pensions industry to invest in Ireland were traditionally it has not.  This is under active consideration by the Minister.  Consultation has been concluded and I expect that in the upcoming budget, or through other measures, the Minister will reflect these discussions.</p><p>I thank Senator Gilroy for his remarks, particularly with regard to the fiscal deficit.  I agree with him that the issue of 120% of GDP is a very difficult challenge facing the country and our task is to make this more sustainable.  The way this can be obtained is through a much better deal on our national debt through the promissory notes and opportunities provided by the ESM and recapitalisation.  Senator Gilroy asked whether we need to be more publicly engaged in explaining our strategy.  This is a challenge and a dilemma.  People need to understand the Government is working on this, which we are, but many of these discussions take place behind closed doors because once a position on the objective of talks is made public and known, it becomes the only position and one cannot row back from it.  We must get the balance right between continually explaining to the public our objectives while also doing much of the work behind the scenes and winning friends internationally, as the Taoiseach and Tánaiste have done in such an exemplary way through their work in trying to rebuild the country after the collapse.</p><p>It is worth stating that in 2012 one fifth, or 20%, of all taxes we take in will pay interest on our national debt, whereas four years ago the figure was 3.5%.  This is a very difficult position.  As Senator Barrett knows, in the 1980s one third of all taxes taken in paid interest on the national debt.  If we can achieve sustained and substantial economic growth there is no reason this figure cannot decrease.  I am confident this will happen over a period of years.</p><p>The role played by the president of the ECB, Mr. Draghi, in giving three year money to the banks at 1% and introducing bond buying on the sovereign markets has been hugely significant in creating incremental progress.  The Senator also asked about the inflows and outflows of money to Irish banks and I will get the exact figures later.  From my knowledge I understand the flow out of the Irish banking sector has stopped and it is now going in the right direction.  As we get more confident and progress is made we will see more deposits.  The news today that Bank of Ireland has returned to the capital markets is very encouraging because no interbank lending has taken place for at least two and a half or three years since the crisis began.  The only source from which the banks could obtain funding was through the emergency liquidity fund.  We are watching the news from Bank of Ireland today very closely.</p><p>When we came into government, the cost of buying nine year or ten year Irish debt was 15.5%.  Last night it was 4.6%, which is lower than Greece, Portugal, Spain and Italy.  We are moving in the right direction.  We will soon be in a position where the cost of buying nine year or ten year money on the international markets will be close to the blended rate we are charged from the EU-IMF programme, which is approximately 2.5% or 3%.  I put it to colleagues in a fair and objective way this is a measure of progress with regard to re-entering the market.  Already this year €5.5 billion has been raised by the NTMA - in short-term money admittedly - and I know more will happen in this regard.  This is the type of incremental progress we need to see happen in a considered way.</p><p>I thank Senator Mooney for his very constructive remarks.  He asked why the 12.5% rate decreased to 6%.  This is largely due to companies investing in research and development who can write off a proportion of their expenditure for this purpose.  This is very important.  If Irish multinational businesses invest in research and development, not only does it reduce their tax bill but it also provides another opportunity for Irish people to grow their ideas and export potential.  I agree with the Senator's assessment that in times of crisis one does not change this but rather one sends out a positive signal.  It is important to state also the tax credit on the research and development side is one reason people can reduce their 12.5% liability to 5%, 6% or 7%.</p><p>Senator Healy Eames spoke about mortgage debt.  I do not disagree with her, but I must state that at the highest levels of Government the Taoiseach, the Tánaiste, the Minister for Finance and the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform deal with this on a weekly and monthly basis.  We need to see the banks get on with the job they have been asked to do.  They have been given the funds to write down this debt where appropriate on a case-by-case basis.  I know the engagement they have with the Central Bank and there is some frustration in this regard.  We have all seen comments on this.  The banks need to get on this task and the sooner they can do so the better.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.196" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="18:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300037#LL00200"><p>They are not doing so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="18:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300037#LL00300"><p>I have referred to some of the remarks made by Senator Barrett.  I do not disagree with him.  My personal view is that more needs to be done on expenditure than tax but we must get the balance right.  With regard to capital expenditure we had many vanity projects in the past 15 years.  At one point we spent €9 billion a year on capital projects.  What value did we obtain from these?  The great majority of capital expenditure this year and next year will be on schools and primary health care centres, ensuring the Government's plans for health are fulfilled and that the huge bulge in population coming into our primary and post primary schools is adequately dealt with.  I do not regard these as vanity projects.  They make good sense and will give good value.</p><p>I want to nail the issue that no savings have been made.  Let us be clear, three years ago the totality of the public sector pay and pension bill was €20 billion and now it is €17.5 billion.  The previous Government and this-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.198" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="18:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300037#LL00400"><p>No, we saved it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.199" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="18:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300037#LL00500"><p>The previous Government and this one-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.200" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="18:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300037#LL00600"><p>Fine Gael voted against it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.201" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="18:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300037#LL00700"><p>The previous Government and this one over a period of three years have reduced by €2.5 billion the amount we spend when public salaries and pensions are summed up.  We do not sing about this and we need to.  We need to explain to the public the enormous reductions in public sector pay and pensions of €2.5 billion made over a three-year period.  It is enormous.  When we speak internationally about this people ask us how we managed to do so.  It is to the credit of the public sector that this level of adjustment has occurred.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.202" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="18:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300037#LL00800"><p>Fine Gael did not assist in any way in opposition.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.203" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="18:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300037#LL00900"><p>It has been done with the support of Fianna Fáil.</p><p>On the question Senator Harte asked about the Credit Review Office, I agree we need to do more but some very important things are happening in the micro-finance area.  I have seen cases in my constituency of people who could not get money from the banks obtaining micro-funding for very small businesses.  The temporary loan guarantees are being rolled out and the big idea is that the State would act as guarantor to help businesses get funds in place.  The pillar banks have been told by the Government that over a three-year period they must invest €21 billion in Irish businesses, big and small.</p> <p>People say to me - I know that Senator Higgins made the point and I shall return to her - that a lot of that money is not going to SMEs but to restructure existing businesses.  Without restructuring, those businesses would be dead and gone.  I have continually made the point that this is not just about creating jobs but protecting the 1.8 million people who are in work.  We want to make sure they are protected too.  A lot of the funding provided by the pillar banks relates to the restructuring of existing loans from existing viable businesses but that fact is frequently ignored.  </p><p>I note the comment made by my colleague from Galway, Senator Ó Clochartaigh.  He mentioned the industrial policy proposed by our colleagues in Sinn Féin and that he had not seen our pre-budget submission.  We have not seen his party's pre-budget submission but we shall be all ears when it comes out.  As last year Sinn Féin produced it 12 hours before the budget, I ask his party to give it to us a few days earlier.  We are prepared to examine any positive and realistic proposals made by Opposition parties.  </p><p>Senator Brennan referred to NAMA and he made an important point.  NAMA has said that it is prepared to invest over €2 billion in investment projects through viable businesses that it is working its way through.  That could be a source of additional employment across the country, particularly outside Dublin, and the Government would welcome the measure.  I can assure the Senator that the only assets that will be sold are non-strategic State assets.  We have no intention of selling strategic State assets.  </p><p>I agree with Senator Higgins that we need a new SME lending culture, not just by the pillar banks but niche banks.  The Minister for Finance holds the view that the more banks the merrier but it is difficult to get them.  There is an opportunity to start Islamic banking which has been successful in the UK.  I understand that 40,000 people who have come to this country in the past decade bank with the Islamic bank in the UK and they are all involved in small business.  They can see that there is a future for a niche banking market and we need to get into that space.  The Government will closely examine any proposals that it receives.  There is nothing to prevent such banks being established in Ireland.  Our difficulty is the sovereign risk and threat which makes it more difficult to get the funds in to match it.  </p><p>I hope that I have replied to everyone and I thank Senators for their suggestions.  We have made it clear that the forthcoming budget will be difficult.  If we can get through it and there is a sustained path towards economic growth then that will help the economy to recover and get people back to work.  There is always a lag between a turn in the economy and improved employment opportunities.  Traditionally, that has been the case.  Our primary objective is to get as many people back to work and to create the right conditions so that investment can come in.  I shall outline one case.  Recently, I met a man from my constituency and I asked him how he was doing.  He said that his business was gone and that he had employed 45 people at one point.  He said that he is back on his feet again because he is selling carpets in London.  He employs three people there but he hopes to return to selling carpets here by the middle of next year.  He said that the one big difference between the 1980s and now is that there are a lot of people like him who know how to make money.  When we get back on our feet again we will make money again.  An entrepreneurial spirit did not exist in the 1980s but it does now.  I have every confidence that if we get the banking sector right, get the general position of the economy right in terms of the deficit and get our competitiveness and pricing right then those people who have made money - the people who created employment opportunities for so many people in the past decade and a half - will be back on their feet and will ensure that the economy is a success.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.205" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" speakername="Jillian van Turnhout" time="18:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300038#MM00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  When is it proposed to sit again?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.206" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1160" speakername="Michael D'Arcy" time="18:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300038#MM00250"><p>At 10.30 a.m. tomorrow.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.207" nospeaker="true" time="18:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300038#MM00300">Adjournment Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.208" nospeaker="true" time="18:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300038#MM00400">Hospital Staff</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.209" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1155" speakername="Kathryn Reilly" time="18:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300038#MM00500"><p>I am sorry to inform the House, at short notice, that I must withdraw my matter on the Adjournment but I will resubmit it tomorrow.  I hope that the Minister for Health or Minister of State at the Department of Health will be present then.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.210" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" speakername="Jillian van Turnhout" time="18:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300038#MM00600"><p>I note the Senator's disappointment that there was no Minister available to answer her question.  I shall ask the Cathaoirleach to allow her to table the matter on the Adjournment tomorrow.  I hope that a Minister or Minister of State can be provided at that point.  I call Senator Mulcahy.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.211" nospeaker="true" time="18:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300038#MM00700">Domiciliary Care Allowance</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.212" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1134" speakername="Tony Mulcahy" time="18:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300038#MM00800"><p>I welcome the Minister of State.  Last week I raised an issue on the domiciliary care allowance with the Minister for Social Protection.  When I received her reply I then sought the qualifications of relevant medical assessors that work in the domiciliary care allowance section.  I sought to identify which applications it dealt with and asked if it dealt with domiciliary care, disability benefit and a raft of other applications.  I was told that there were a total of 27 medical assessors.  This evening I want a list, in tabular format, that clearly states the qualifications of each one.  I do not need to know their names but I do need to know their qualifications.</p> <p>Those dealing with domiciliary care allowance are dealing with the cases of many young children with an intellectual disability.  It is appropriate that people with relevant qualification deal with their applications.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.214" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1074" speakername="Michael Ring" time="18:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300039#NN00200"><p>The Department of Social Protection has 22 medical assessors, including the chief medical adviser and the acting deputy chief medical adviser.  A further three medical assessors have been appointed recently by the Public Appointments Service and two commenced work in the first week of November and the third will commence on 21 November.</p><p>To be appointed to the role of medical assessor, candidates are required to be fully qualified and experienced medical practitioners and be on the general register of medical practitioners while holding an appointment.  It is a necessary requirement that, on appointment, they have at least six years satisfactory experience in the practice of medicine since registration.</p><p>While many of the medical assessors have specialist postgraduate qualifications, including occupational medicine, psychiatry, surgery and general medicine, a specialist postgraduate qualification is not a requirement for appointment as a medical assessor.  Consequently details of such postgraduate qualifications pertaining to individual medical assessors are not collated as a matter of routine and as a result, details of what postgraduate qualifications each and every individual medical assessor may have are not readily available.</p><p>All medical assessors have received special training in human disability evaluation.  The medical assessors are committed to continuing medical education to ensure that standards are maintained and enhanced.  Ongoing medical education is provided by national and international experts in the evaluation of disability.  There are also regular meetings and seminars under the direction of the chief medical adviser where a range of medical issues and developments in the occupational medicine field are discussed.</p><p>It should be noted that medical assessors are not specifically assigned to one particular scheme.  All of the medical assessors complete desk assessments of medical evidence submitted on customer claims, appeals and reviews on all of the Department's disability and illness related schemes.</p><p>Following their appointment as medical assessors for the Department, medical assessors undertake contractually to not engage in private practice or be connected with any outside business which would interfere with the performance of their official duties.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.215" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1134" speakername="Tony Mulcahy" time="18:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300039#NN00300"><p>That reply answers my question.  I rest my case.  They are not qualified and therein lies the whole problem.  They are dealing with children with severe intellectual disability on whom extensive clinical assessments have been carried out by a range of therapists, clinical psychologists, child psychologists, occupations therapists and more.  We have people who are not qualified adjudicating on those applications.  I see that two medical assessors have been lost since I received a reply last week stating the number was 27.</p><p>I cannot stand over the fact the State is not addressing the needs of our most needy children.  I have sent in rafts of forms and supporting documentation.  Today proves that doing so is not worth the paper the forms are written on.  These applications have been assessed by those who are clinically qualified in the HSE and in the early intervention services in the country.  We need medical staff who are clinically qualified to assess those applications.  I know the Minister of State cannot answer that question but I appreciate that he came to the Seanad to reply to my question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.216" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1074" speakername="Michael Ring" time="18:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300039#NN00400"><p>To be fair, there are 22 medical assessors and three new people have been appointed, bringing the number up to 25.  In the first week of November a further two commenced employment bringing the figure to 27.  I will relay the Senator's concerns to the Minister and I am sure the Senator will raise the issue again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.217" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" speakername="Jillian van Turnhout" time="18:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300039#NN00500"><p>I thank the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.218" nospeaker="true" time="18:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300039#NN00600">Garda Transport</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.219" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor Ó Clochartaigh" time="18:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300039#NN00800"><p>Cuirim fáilte roimh an Aire.  Tá brón orm go bhfuil mé beagáinín as anáil tar éis dom rith suas an staighre ón gcoiste.  I welcome the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Alan Shatter, and I am glad to see that he is in fine form again.  I raise on the Adjournment the announcement made by the Minister that an extra allocation of approximately 196 additional Garda cars would be made available.  Will he give a breakdown of the number and location of the additional cars and how soon they will be made available?  We have seen a spate of minor robberies in the Connemara area in the past couple of months.  One of the concerns is that there is only one Garda car available in the whole of south Connemara.  We hope that area will benefit from the additional allocation.  I would welcome any clarification the Minister may be able to give me.</p><p>I apologise that I am out of breath but I got caught at a committee meeting.  Between the Minister for Justice and Equality and the Minister for Arts, Heritage and the Gaeltacht, Deputy Deenihan, they have me on the run.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.220" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1025" speakername="Alan Shatter" time="18:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300039#NN00900"><p>I have just sprinted over from the other side of the House.  The lesson is that I am fitter than Senator Ó Clochartaigh.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.221" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor Ó Clochartaigh" time="18:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300039#NN01000"><p>I will not disagree with the Minister on that point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.222" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1025" speakername="Alan Shatter" time="18:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300039#NN01100"><p>We should have a jogging party in the Oireachtas.</p><p>I thank the Senator for raising this issue which I am very pleased to discuss.  Arrangements have been put in place with special funding being made available to An Garda Síochána to allow the Garda authorities to purchase a significant number of new vehicles.</p><p>We anticipated the possibility of making such a purchase last spring and went to tender in regard to identifying the motor company from whom motor vehicles could be purchased.  We effected saving in the justice section of my Department which effectively made available €3 million for the purchase of Garda cars.  The savings were crystalised in the early autumn and as I state in my script, this funding is being made available at a time of severe budgetary constraints and it represents a substantial investment in Garda transport.  It will provide for an additional 170 new Garda vehicles.  This is in addition to the 42 vehicles which have already been provided this year and means that the Garda Síochána has placed total orders for some 212 new vehicles in 2012.  This is very beneficial.</p><p>The Garda Commissioner is making arrangements for the provision of the additional transport and it is anticipated that it will come on stream in December and January.  The first cars will be allocated during December in accordance with the Garda Commissioner's decision on operational requirements.  They will be rolled out to Garda divisions throughout the country.</p><p>The actual arrangements for the deployment of Garda transport are, of course, a matter in the first instance for the Commissioner in the context of his identified operational requirements.  In turn, at Garda divisional level, the allocation of Garda vehicles is a matter for the chief superintendent who may make and revise arrangements for the deployment of vehicles throughout a division in response to policing demands.  This flexibility in allocating and re-allocating vehicles among stations, so as to best match resources with policing priorities is crucial to the efficient management of the Garda fleet.</p> <p>As a consequence, I am sure the Senator will appreciate that it is not possible to provide a breakdown of the locations to which these vehicles will be allocated. It would be wrong for the Minister for Justice and Equality to decide on where to allocate individual vehicles.  This must be very much an operational decision for the Commissioner and those working under him based on perceived priorities.  The deployment of Garda vehicles is subject to ongoing analysis and review.  This process allows Garda management to allocate available resources within the force in the most appropriate manner to meet existing and emerging operational requirements.</p><p>I am certain that the delivery and commissioning of these 170 new vehicles will serve to enhance the capacity of An Garda Síochána to continue to provide an effective and efficient policing service to communities.  I was anxious that this be progressed as rapidly as possible.  Had we not gone through the tendering process last spring, this would have taken a great deal longer.  If we had waited until we identified what resources we have and then started the tendering process, effectively, we would not have been in a position to acquire the vehicles until next March or April.  We readied ourselves and were in position to do it and when it became clear in mid-October that funding was available, we were then able to give the go-ahead.  This is probably the most rapid purchase of cars that has been authorised in the period from the announcement in October to our having a reasonable number of them in December and the remaining number in January.</p><p>The Estimates process must be completed during November as we approach the budget and there will be details in this respect announced in the budget.  Without giving away any secrets, I advise the Senator that I am optimistic we will have funding to buy additional Garda vehicles in 2013.  It is not the case that this is the purchase of the cars and that is the end of it.  Even though some of these vehicles will not be on the road until January, I anticipate that in 2013 we will be in a position to acquire additional vehicles.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.224" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor Ó Clochartaigh" time="18:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300040#OO00200"><p>That is very welcome news.  It is an issue that has been raised at a number of meetings I have attended.  I appreciate the Minister cannot tell us where the cars will be deployed but he would know from his dealings with the Garda Commissioner the blackspots where the Garda cars are needed most.  Can he clarify that those areas and divisions that have lost Garda vehicles will have those vehicles replaced or are the new vehicles to be deployed differently?  If a certain rural area has lost a number of vehicles, will they be replaced with a number of vehicles adequate to cover the number lost?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.225" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1025" speakername="Alan Shatter" time="18:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300040#OO00300"><p>The deployment of vehicles will be based on decisions made by the Garda Commissioner and those working at divisional level regarding the operational requirements in particular areas.  I want to leave it to those who are expert in policing to make those decisions and to do it with the flexibility necessary because the world changes in a policing context.  We go through periods when particular communities have identifiable difficulties and then when they are addressed, there are difficulties in other communities.  That is a matter for the Garda Commissioner.</p><p>I noted with some interest earlier in the year that dire predictions were being made as to what the position would be regarding the fleet in An Garda Síochána and concerns were expressed that we would not be acquiring additional vehicles that were required.  It was always intended that when we effected savings, we would purchase additional vehicles.  We are in a different resource environment than in the early 2000s when the then Government was flathúlach in throwing money at everything.  We have to do this carefully and in a financially wise way but I am anxious to ensure that the Garda maintains its operational effectiveness, that it has the flexibility it needs to deal with local, petty, organised and subversive crime - the whole range - and that it co-ordinates, interacts and interfaces, especially in rural Ireland with Community Alert schemes that do so much fantastic work.</p><p>Modernising the fleet and acquiring additional vehicles to replace those that are going out of service and getting better vehicles and a greater diversity of vehicles is important.  These are all issues being addressed in the context of the purchase of these 170 vehicles.  I have got the greatest faith in the Garda Commissioner and those working with him to make the appropriate decisions as to where they are deployed.</p><p>It is appropriate to use this opportunity to congratulate the Garda Commissioner and wish him well.  I made an announcement a few hours ago to confirm a Government decision made in Cabinet this morning.  The Commissioner would have completed his term in the Garda force at the end of July or early August next, having been appointed Commissioner in December 2010.   The Cabinet agreed this decision because of the very effective job he is doing, the great insights he brings to it and because of his commitment to reform and to the appropriate and careful use of resources.</p><p>I also point to the great effectiveness of the Garda force in substantially reducing crime levels across a broad range of areas in the past 18 months and to the special operations in which it has been engaged, particularly in tackling burglary which has become an increasing difficulty across parts of the country.  Operation Fiacla has produced an extraordinary result.  Since the beginning of February last there have been 2,500 arrests and more than 1,400 charges taken against individuals engaged in burglaries, some individuals having been engaged in multiple burglaries across the country.  The Garda Commissioner has been asked to stay on for an additional two years from August when he would have otherwise retired.  He will remain heading up the force and I wish him well in continuing to do that.  I thank him for his service and patriotism and look forward to continuing to work with him.  I publicly apologise for giving him an additional two years before he has the opportunity to have a somewhat more relaxed life-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.226" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor Ó Clochartaigh" time="18:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300040#OO00400"><p>No time off for good behaviour.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.227" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1025" speakername="Alan Shatter" time="18:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300040#OO00500"><p>-----than he will have in his current position.  He has not even been granted temporary release.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.228" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" speakername="Jillian van Turnhout" time="18:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2012111300040#OO00600"><p>We join the Minister in wishing him well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2012-11-13a.229" nospeaker="true" time="18:45:00"><p>The Seanad adjourned at 6.30 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Wednesday, 14 November 2012.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>