<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.2" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00"><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 14:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00"><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.4" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00"><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.5" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Mark Daly that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:<ul><br />To ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport to outline the future of the rural transport scheme in County Kerry as the current contracts will cease in July 2013.</ul>I have also received notice from Senator John Kelly of the following matter:<ul>The need for the  Minister for Health to provide funding for a stabilisation unit for Roscommon Hospital where heart attack, stroke and accident victims can be safely treated before being transferred to the most appropriate hospital.</ul>I have also received notice from Senator Mary Moran of the following matter:<ul>To ask the Minister for Education and Skills the reason a school in Dundalk, County Louth, which was added to the Department's list for an extension in 2009, was advised by letter, having completed stage one of the plans for an extension to the Department's satisfaction, that it has not been included on the five year plan for school extensions.</ul>I have also received notice from Senator Marie Moloney of the following matter:<ul>The need for the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government to approve funding for the provision of a sewerage scheme for Kilcummin, Killarney, County Kerry.</ul>I have also received notice from Senator Colm Burke of the following matter:<ul>The need for the Minister for Health, Health Service Executive, voluntary organisations and health professionals to work together to bring forward a comprehensive policy of making the general public aware of the benefits of organ donation.</ul>I have also received notice from Senator David Cullinane of the following matter:<ul>The need for the Minister for Education and Skills to discuss the cuts to further education in budget 2013 and the effect these will have on Waterford College of Further Education and the teacher allocation at the college.</ul>I have also received notice from Senator Averil Power of the following matter:<ul>To ask the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine to respond to the serious concerns that have been raised by local business, community and sporting groups about the proposed plan to introduce paid parking at Howth Harbour.</ul>I have also received notice from Senator Fidelma Healy Eames of the following matter:<ul>To ask the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government to specify where responsibility lies and what action will be taken regarding a dangerous site-large hole in Oranhill, Oranmore, County Galway, belonging to a non-cooperative owner and on which there is a live planning permission; and if the Derelict Sites Act 1990 applies.</ul>I regard the matters raised by the Senators as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment.  I have selected the matters raised by Senators Kelly, Moran, Daly and Moloney and they will be taken at the conclusion of business.  Senators Burke, Cullinane, Power and Healy Eames may give notice on another day of the matters they wish to raise.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.7" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200003#B00100">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.8" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200003#B00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, motion re the arrangements for the address to the House by Ms Phil Prendergast, MEP, on 13 February 2013, to be taken without debate at the conclusion of the Order of Business: No. 2, motion re opt-in under Article 4 of the 21st Protocol to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union to the readmission agreements with the Governments of Macao, Sri Lanka, Albania, Russia, former Yugoslav Republic of Macedonia, Bosnia and Herzegovina, Montenegro, Serbia, Moldova, Pakistan and Georgia, referral to committee, to be taken without debate at the conclusion of No. 1; and No. 3, Taxi Regulation Bill 2012 - Committee Stage, to be taken at the 3.45 p.m. and to be adjourned not later than 5.45 p.m., if not previously concluded.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200003#B00300"><p>I and my colleagues on this side of the House are increasingly concerned and dismayed, as I am sure are many Members on the Deputy Leader's side, by the Minister for Justice and Equality's handling and management of An Garda Síochána.</p> <p>Unprecedented steps have been taken by Garda representative associations in the Dublin north metropolitan area, north County Cork and Cork city, in which members voted no confidence in the Minister.</p><p> Last week, our party tabled a Private Member's motion on policing and justice.  Numerous times, I have raised the issue of Government policy on policing.  I do not just refer to the closure of more than 130 stations, but to the downgrading of further urban and rural stations, the lack of resources provided to gardaí and the absence of new members of the Garda because the Minister will not lift the recruitment ban.  Gardaí rightly have no confidence in the Minister.</p><p> I will explain what this situation entails for the people on the ground, the citizens we are supposed to represent and whom the Garda protects every day.  For four and a half hours yesterday morning, not a single Garda car was operational in the entire north Dublin metropolitan area, including Coolock, Swords and Malahide Garda stations.  The reason was that the Minister would not permit over-time for court appearances.  Gardaí must now drive Garda cars to court.  The area in question comprises more than 150,000 people.  Road traffic accidents and burglaries were left unattended.  This is a crisis in policing.</p><p> Last week, my colleague, Senator O'Donovan, asked the Minister 14 specific questions.  The Minister would only give answers to four.  His attitude to this issue is wrong.  His <i>modus operandi</i>should be concerned with the protection of citizens.  The Government, through his policies, is letting down the people and, as importantly, the gardaí.  The men and women who protect us every day of the week are having the rug pulled out from under them by the Minister.</p><p> With this in mind, I want answers to Senator O'Donovan's ten questions that the Minister would not answer last week.  I want him to explain why not a single Garda patrol car was operational in the north Dublin metropolitan area for four and a half hours yesterday.  To this end, I am tabling an amendment to the Order of Business to the effect that the Minister should attend the House to explain why such a situation was allowed to occur, what contact he has with the normal rank and file of the Garda Síochána and what he will do to win back the confidence of gardaí who, in an unprecedented step, voted no confidence in him.</p><p> This situation will get worse and worse as the days and weeks continue.  In two weeks time, we will be discussing industrial action by the Garda.  I am putting the Minister on notice - he should tell us what he is doing in this regard.  I am formally tabling that amendment to the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200004#C00200"><p>I join with the Taoiseach and Tánaiste in expressing my sincere good wishes to the Holy Father, Pope Benedict XVI, on his declaration yesterday of his intention to retire.  This is something to which he gave much careful consideration.  In common with the views of many others, I believe that his declaration arose from a deep sense of duty to the office he holds.  He provided strong leadership and great service to the church and its people.  He worked tirelessly for world peace and co-operation.  Our thoughts and good wishes are with him in particular, but also with those who will shortly gather in conclave to choose his successor.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200004#C00250"><p>Speak up man.  Do not be ashamed of what you are saying.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" speakername="Jillian van Turnhout" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200004#C00300"><p>It is six weeks since the new year.  The Chinese new year was celebrated last Sunday.  This is the year of the snake.  My first question relates to a report that was promised in the new year.</p> <p>I believe we have qualified on both counts that we are in the new year.  I refer to the report of the Advisory Group on Tax and Social Welfare chaired by Ita Mangan.  The Minister, Deputy Burton, challenged us to examine the facts of this report and gave an undertaking in this House to publish the report early in the new year.  My question is when that report will be published.  Yesterday a report from the Consumers' Association of Ireland showed there has been a 12% rise in the cost of a typical basket of groceries.  We have seen a very brutal cut across the board in child benefit payment.  I am willing to take some tough decisions on child benefit but let us see this report and let the discussion begin.  I do know why it has taken so long for it to be published.</p><p>We were also promised that the child and family support agency Bill would be published in the new year.  Colleagues in the House will know that I have repeatedly asked for us to debate this new agency which has a budget of €545 million and a staff of 4,000, yet we have not had a debate on it.  I have tried every angle to have a debate on it in this House but that has been blocked.  When will the Bill be published?  When will we see it?  This is a very important agency.  My fear is that staff are just being transferred from the HSE.  I question whether any Member of the House would say it is a great idea to transfer staff from the HSE, with all the deals and practices they have, into the agency.  When will that Bill be published?</p><p>A report was commissioned six years ago from the commission of investigation into the Death of Gary Douch.  That commission of investigation was established in April 2007 following the attack and subsequent death of Gary Douch in a cell in Mountjoy Prison.  I ask the Deputy Leader to ask the Minister for Justice and Equality when that report will be published?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="Rónán Mullen" time="14:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200005#D00200"><p>I second Senator Darragh O'Brien's amendment to the Order of Business.  The Senator has raised an issue that will not go away.  Anybody who is in touch with ordinary folk will know how much such a debate matters to them.  People throughout Ireland, especially older people, do not feel the security they deserve to feel in their own country in terms of proper policing in their community.  I realise, as does every other Member, the pressure there is on the Exchequer, but effective policing in terms of the role of the Garda Síochána operating effectively is something we cannot do without and we must not tolerate any failure on the Government's part to ensure we have a proper police service in our country.</p><p>  I note, for example, that in the <i>Galway City Tribune</i> last Friday, Denise McNamara wrote about marauding gangs of thieves creating palpable fear and a growing sense of unease among residents in Galway city despite burglaries levelling off.  At other times I would say that the media is given to exaggeration but we know there is not exaggeration on this issue.  In Salthill recently a gang gathered in a particular area only a 100 yards from the Garda station but no garda was in a position to arrive and investigate when notified.  There is a real problem when we do not have a visible Garda presence and effective Garda patrol in areas.  We need to keep the pressure on the Minister for Justice and Equality.</p><p>  In signalling support for our Garda Síochána, the excellent work its members do and how much we need them, I would like to hear from the Minister about a problem that sometimes occurs when gardaí talk to the media.  I have huge sympathy with our colleague in the other House, Deputy Clare Daly, about the way she was treated recently.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200005#D00300"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="Rónán Mullen" time="14:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200005#D00400"><p>A public representative is not in a different position from any other member of society but the damage to a public representative is particularly severe when there is any kind of suspicion about his or her acting with propriety.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200005#D00500"><p>Has the Senator a question for the Deputy Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="Rónán Mullen" time="14:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200005#D00600"><p>Yes.  I would be grateful if we could have a discussion with the Minister - as this not just a matter for the Garda ombudsman - about what the Department is doing to ensure that gardaí are acting properly.  If there is any kind of nexus, on a financial or other basis, between gardaí or any kind of vendetta mentality towards certain politicians because of certain other things they have done, that will bring our Garda force into disrepute and it would need to be stamped out.  We should stand in solidarity with Deputy Daly about the way she was treated.  It was simply not acceptable.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200005#D00700"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200005#D00800"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="Rónán Mullen" time="14:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200005#D00900"><p>I ask for a date when we will have a debate on the excellent report on the Magdalen laundries by the former Senator, Martin McAleese.</p> <p>As well as discussing the report, we will want to record our thanks to former Senator McAleese for a report that is characterised by fairness and truthfulness.  We should have a further discussion on this matter very soon.  I know the Government has given a commitment in that regard but I would be grateful if we were given a date given for the debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1144" speakername="Jimmy Harte" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200006#E00200"><p>I will be opposing Senator Darragh O'Brien's amendment to the Order of Business regarding the blue flu protest threat by gardaí.  The blue flu was not invented this week or last week.  It is a legacy of a previous Administration.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200006#E00300"><p>That is right.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1144" speakername="Jimmy Harte" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200006#E00400"><p>It is a legacy of a previous Administration which had gardaí scared witless in 2009.  The blue flu took off then.  I do not accuse the Senator of hypocrisy but it is hard to listen to him expressing concern for gardaí.  When his party colleagues were in government, they had the opportunity to negotiate with the Garda, and the blue flu protest was the first time in the history of the State that Garda authorities, or anyone associated with the defence or justice systems-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200006#E00500"><p>Senator, have you a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1144" speakername="Jimmy Harte" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200006#E00600"><p>I ask the Leader to arrange for the Minister or Minister of State to come to the House to explain the situation regarding the Garda and the public service, in general.</p><p>The action of Fianna Fáil in tabling a motion about the threatened blue flu-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200006#E00700"><p>It is not just about that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1144" speakername="Jimmy Harte" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200006#E00800"><p>It is about that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200006#E00900"><p>Senator Harte, have you a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1144" speakername="Jimmy Harte" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200006#E01000"><p>My question is that the Minister would come in.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200006#E01100"><p>Can Senator Harte explain the fact that gardaí have no resources?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1144" speakername="Jimmy Harte" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200006#E01200"><p>The blue flu protest of 2009 was the first time Garda authorities, under Fianna Fáil stewardship-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200006#E01300"><p>What is Senator Harte's point?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1144" speakername="Jimmy Harte" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200006#E01400"><p>The Government at that time was threatened by the Garda.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200006#E01500"><p>I ask the Leader to arrange a debate on the hostile takeover of Aer Lingus by Ryanair, its implications for Cork, Shannon and Knock airports and the fallout from it.  I have no faith in a European Commission which might make a decision at arm's length and without looking at the real problems of this country.  Over the last four or five years there has, for different reasons, been a 40% fall-off in traffic in and out of Cork Airport.  We should not rush into allowing this takeover but look at its full impact and make a full evaluation of it.  It is worthy of a debate in the House.</p><p>I also join other Senators in asking the Leader to arrange a debate on the proposed sale of Coillte.  This could be a retrograde step and could have serious implications for the future of forestry in Ireland.  The various aspects of the sale of Coillte merit a half-day's debate in the House.  It could tie in with the proposed takeover of Aer Lingus by Ryanair.  Given the lessening of the pressure on our financial debts following last week's negotiations, the Government should re-think these strategic developments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" speakername="Jim D'Arcy" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200006#E01600"><p>In discussing matters relating to the Garda Síochána, it is important for us to be aware of the ongoing investigation of the death of Detective Garda Adrian Donohoe.  Media headlines come and go but the death of this young father will be remembered forever in Dundalk, County Louth and throughout the country.</p><p>Speaking at a specially convened press conference in the Garda barracks in Dundalk last Friday, the Garda Commissioner, Martin Callinan, said over 360 statements had been given to the Garda on the matter,1,125 lines of inquiry are being investigated, there are over 300 exhibits relating to the case and 140 separate CCTV recordings are being examined.</p> <p>He also heaped praised on the people of Dundalk, saying there had been a great local response to this vile act and that the people of Dundalk and the Cooley Peninsula were also welcoming to the many gardaí from across the State who were in Dundalk.  We can make political points relating to An Garda Síochána and I accept the right of anyone to support the Garda.  However, will the Deputy Leader invite the Minister for Justice and Equality to the House, as has been requested previously, to outline the additional resources that might be available from the Government to combat criminal elements in the Border region?  I support the Minister but we need that debate.  Will he outline what additional supports are being given to this case?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1169" speakername="Mary Ann O'Brien" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200007#F00200"><p>I wish to restate a call I made before the Christmas recess for a debate on Ireland's foreign aid budget.  On that occasion, many Senators expressed difficulty with my stance on the issue but welcomed the idea of a mature and responsible debate on the topic.  Ireland spent &#8364;639 million in 2012 with a further &#8364;623 million due to be spent this year.  More than 80% of this money will go to Africa, where we have witnessed examples of corruption and waste in recent months.  &quot;Wasteful&quot; and &quot;riddled with corruption&quot; are two statements that come to mind when I think, for example, of Uganda.  Ireland's 0.53% of GDP aid allocation is among the top nine donors in the world in <i>per capita</i> terms.  On the same scale, the US is 19th in development assistance, although this statistic does not reflect what the US spends on emergency aid.  We must debate the reform of our auditing procedures to ensure every euro spent by taxpayers overseas creates economic growth not only for the recipient countries, but also for us in our dealings with them.  We must also debate our strategy on how foreign aid is spent to ensure we embrace change.  It was reported earlier that a report on the Garda has not been done for almost half a century.  I wonder when a policy document was last created on foreign aid and how we spend it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" speakername="Mary Moran" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200007#F00300"><p>I echo the comments of my colleague from my Dundalk.  Yesterday, I met the Garda superintendent for the town who conveyed his thanks and appreciation to the people of Dundalk for their support following the brutal murder of Detective Garda Adrian Donohoe.  He referred to the sense of community spirit that was exhibited throughout the weeks after the incident and how diligently the force is working to apprehend the perpetrators of this crime.  I was shocked when he described cases of robbery and attacks and he mentioned that two 14 year old children were before the court yesterday in the town.  When the Minister for Justice and Equality comes to the House, perhaps we can examine what we can do to combat the increasing incidence of juvenile crime, which is happening all over the country.</p><p>I echo Senator Coghlan's comments about the shock resignation of Pope Benedict yesterday.  While it was courageous of him to admit his frailty and humanity and that he is not in a position to carry out his duties any longer, and many people feel he did not have the charisma and likability factor of his predecessor, Pope John Paul II enjoyed, he showed a personal commitment to the role and he worked tirelessly for world peace, as Senator Coghlan said.</p> <p>However, his successor is taking over the Catholic Church at an extremely difficult time while the church is still reeling from the many clerical child abuse cases that have been brought to light in recent years.  I hope his successor will, perhaps, look at the role of lay people and women in the church as I consider they will be important in leading the Catholic Church in future years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200008#G00200"><p>This is not a day when it would be appropriate to be negative about the pope.  However, my view of that gentleman has not changed.  I understand he is to take up residence at the bottom of the papal garden which may be an inconvenience to his successor but I am profoundly glad that he is not taking up residence at the bottom of my garden.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" speakername="Mary Moran" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200008#G00300"><p>It is an enclosed residence.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200008#G00400"><p>I consider it appropriate that Senator Jillian van Turnhout drew our attention to the fact that this is the year of the snake in terms of the Chinese people.  Yesterday was the opening of the lunar new year for the people of Tibet, the Tibetan Buddhists.  It is horrifying that they have had to cancel the celebration because of the appalling treatment they are receiving at the hands of the Chinese.  We tend to forget human rights in Ireland when a little bit of a purse is jingled in front of our nose and we think of money.  As one of the founders of the Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs I have consistently regretted this change in balance to take in foreign affairs and trade.</p><p>May I also raise a matter - it was mentioned in one of the newspapers that nobody had taken up - a report, Globalising Torture - CIA Secret Detention and Extraordinary Rendition, which has just been published.  We must have time to have a look at it.  It is a matter of shame to all of us that we should be numbered among the countries assisting in the capture and transport of detainees, permitting the use of domestic airspace and airports for secret flights transporting detainees, providing intelligence leading to secret detention and extraordinary rendition of individuals and interrogating individuals who were secretly captured.  We are in that company with Afghanistan, Albania, Azerbaijan, Saudi Arabia, Somalia and Syria.  I raised the issue at the time and I gave information to Members of the other House collected from those very brave people in Shannon who were making notes of the planes.  Everything was denied.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200008#G00500"><p>Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200008#G00600"><p>May we have a debate on the issue, particularly in light of the fact that, to our eternal shame, a committee of inquiry, a special committee of this House, was established and then removed because of pressure from local authorities in the Shannon area?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1121" speakername="Paul Bradford" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200008#G00700"><p>I agree with my colleague, Senator Mary Ann O'Brien, on the need to debate the subject of Irish Aid and how we spend money in the developing world.  We should not be debarred by political correctness from asking hard questions as posed by Senator O'Brien because we must ensure that the money we spend, which is not the Government's but the taxpayer's money, is put to genuine developmental purpose and that there will be a long-term economic spin-off to those in the Third World and the developing world.  Yesterday, the British Minister in charge of international development made the same argument on behalf of the British taxpayer when he expressed concern about British taxes being expended across the globe.  We need a debate in the House to ensure that the money being spent by the Irish Government and Irish taxpayers on Third World development is achieving long-term economic results.</p><p>The second point I wish to raise relates to policing.  The more I hear of and from the Fianna Fáil Party on this matter the more I think back to the 1990s and the promises of zero tolerance.  There was at that stage a deliberate and successful political campaign by Fianna Fáil to frighten the people of the island into believing we were on the verge of social breakdown and that the delivery of John O'Donoghue's policy of zero tolerance would solve every problem.  Of course that did not happen.  If people suggest we need more policing and more gardaí on the beat they must recognise that policing must be paid for.  They must also say where the money is to come from and if they favour the presentation of a supplementary budget and additional taxation to pay for it.  Alternatively, can we have a genuine and mature conversation about policing? </p> <p>Last week, there was a Private Members' motion, but such motions, where the Opposition say "Yes" and the Government say "No" are purposeless and meaningless. I would have said the same when I was on the other side of the House.  The amendment to the Order of Business today is meaningless as well.  Perhaps, if Senator Darragh O'Brien was willing to withdraw his amendment and liaise with the Acting Leader, the Minister could come forward within the next week or two and there could be a mature debate in this House where we could discuss the matter in detail.  The charade of Senators putting down a motion condemning Ministers which they know will be defeated is purposeless and pointless and it adds to the cynicism.  I have seen this fail spectacularly on too many occasions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200009#H00200"><p>Senator Bradford is over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1121" speakername="Paul Bradford" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200009#H00300"><p>Could we have a genuine debate on a genuine topic of policing?  Let us not start with a silly vote here on the Order of Business.  Let us have a mature discussion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor Ó Clochartaigh" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200009#H00400"><p>Ba mhaith liom moladh a thabhairt don Phápa Beinidict as ucht an cinneadh cróga agus ceannródaíoch a ghlac sé inné.  Guím chuile rath air agus ar na cairdinéil a bheidh ag roghnú duine le teacht i gcomharbacht air.</p><p>It also is important that we have a debate on the Magdelen laundries report.  It is clear from the report that the State was complicit in what was happening in those homes.  There was a meeting with the Taoiseach and the Tánaiste yesterday and it is important that we find out what is to come of it.  No doubt an apology is warranted and it is only a question of when it should happen.  Then we need to look at the other series of necessary discussions on recompense for those who were in those institutions, as many of them are elderly.</p><p>There is a report from Accord, the marriage counselling service, reported in the news today, which states that there has been a huge increase in the demand for marriage counselling over the past year.  The service has dealt with 6,536 couples in 2012 and the amount of counselling increased to 50,422 hours.  An interesting part of the report listed the reasons for the increase.  Some 58% of the couples cited financial difficulties as a problem, 82% stated they were suffering from stress and anxiety, 59% stated emotional abuse and 51% stated they were suffering from depression.  An addiction counsellor to whom I spoke recently told me that there has been a huge increase in the number of referrals of persons suffering from alcohol addiction, drug addiction, etc.  It is clear that the austerity imposed on families is having a huge effect and its social  consequences is totally uncosted.  We should have a debate on the social cost of austerity, particularly on families, whether they be married couples or any other type of family unit.  We need to count the cost of the austerity cuts made in budgets in a social sense as well as in pounds, shillings and pence.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Maloney" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200009#H00500"><p>I, too, welcome the talks that are taking place between the Taoiseach and the Tánaiste and Justice for Magdelenes.  It seems that it is women and children who suffer at the hands of the institutions in this country.  For example, the victims of symphysiotomy are still waiting for their report and the Magdelene laundry sufferers are awaiting an apology.  That apology is inevitable.  No doubt we will give one and I cannot see why we are putting it off.</p><p>The reason I rose to speak was similar to that of Senator van Turnhout.  It is nearly two months since the budget debate during which the Minister for Social Protection, Deputy Joan Burton, told us that she had in her possession the report from the advisory group on taxation and social welfare, chaired by Ms Ita Mangan, and that she would lay it before this House in the first instance for debate and discussion before she would take it anywhere else.  I ask the Acting Leader if the matter is on the schedule, if the Minister has given an indication as to when she will present it to the House, and if it is not on the schedule, if the Acting Leader could ask the Minister at her earliest convenience to bring it before the House so as not to have a repeat of last year's budget process where Senators had no time to discuss matters.  Let us discuss the report and see what recommendations are in it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200009#H00600"><p>It is just over three years since, speaking from the other side of the House, I and others first predicted in this House the crisis in mortgage arrears.  Since that time there has been the Cooney report, the Keane report and a superficial code of conduct, but on the ground there are ambivalent banks who engage only in a superficial way.  By way of showing forbearance, they are giving no easement to the families all over the country suffering from the stress of their inability to pay their mortgage bills and the prospect of losing their homes.</p> <p> The Personal Insolvency Bill puts the financial institutions in complete control.  Independent Deputies in the other House have made several attempts, as have I with the Family Home Bill and other initiatives, to bring forward tangible solutions which will help people but nothing has happened.  This week I am glad to welcome into the debate the Governor of the Central Bank, Professor Honohan, who has said he is losing patience with the banks.  I also welcome the troika mission announcing we must achieve sustainability for households and those in distress as a result of mortgage arrears.  No financial institution has put forward the option of warehousing debt, as it seems we as a nation have just been permitted to do.  Nobody from the banks has come forward to say they are prepared to take equity in people's property for a period of time.  Nobody has come forward to suggest intergenerational mortgages.  The level of superficiality is disgraceful.  There has been nothing yet in the crisis for the citizen and I include all Governments over the past three years in this condemnation.  It is time the people in the street see tangible results.  As an intermediary acting on behalf of a couple, I have requested a mortgage to rent option, which is what the family wants, but under no circumstance will the bank consider it.  The bank is thinking of one thing and the bottom line is that the citizen comes last.  The citizen needs to start coming first.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1124" speakername="Michael Comiskey" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200010#J00200"><p>I wish to raise the upgrade of the N4 road from Drumfin to Castlebaldwin.  Sadly, another death occurred on the road last night and I offer my condolences to the family of the young man who lost his life.  I believe 30 people have died on the road.  It is the worst stretch of road between Dublin and Sligo and it is time all efforts were made in this regard.  I call on the NRA and the Minister to make the funding available.  Much work has been done by Sligo County Council on the issue and many studies have been done.  If the money were put in place we could finally see the upgrade of the road, which has been sought for many years.  It is time we move on it and upgrade it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200010#J00300"><p>The Deputy Leader raised the possibility we might complete work today on the Taxi Regulation Bill.  I wish to make the case to the contrary.  The Bill was circulated on 3 December.  Yesterday we were notified of two major amendments, one of which seems to seriously interfere with the rights of part-time workers and with what a person in employment should tell his or her employer; and the other seeks to change how the bus sector is regulated, which certainly will have the bus people hopping mad.  This cannot be allowed to happen.  Serious issues with regard to labour law and employment law arise to be considered.  Introducing these as amendments to taxi legislation indicates the House should not allow Committee Stage to be completed today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200010#J00400"><p>It will be adjourned today at 5.45 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200010#J00500"><p>I thank the Deputy Leader.  As a lawyer she would like to see workers have rights with regard to what they tell employers.  There are many case studies on the rights of part-time workers.  I very much welcome the Deputy Leader's decision and I thank her.</p><p>With regard to the Magdalen laundries, a most interesting work by Eoin O'Sullivan and Ian O Donnell, Coercive Confinement in Ireland, records that at any one stage between the 1920s and the 1950s 30,000 people were locked up in this country.  Former Senator McAleese's estimate is that on average approximately 200 of these were in laundries.  The maximum number of children confined to institutions and held coercively was approximately 6,000.  This has now been reduced to nothing and we all applaud this.  In discussing this we must look at all the aspects of the coercive incarceration of people in which Irish society engaged, including locking up unwanted relatives in mental hospitals.  Elizabeth Malcolm stated families, police, magistrates, clergy and doctors co-operated to take advantage of lax procedures so as to rid their communities of those deemed trouble or troublesome.</p> <p>That happened to 30,000 people.  We need to discuss the matter fully.  It is a bit trivial to ask the Taoiseach to apologise.  All of Irish society, in the past, liked locking up people and we should open up a debate on that horrible period in Irish history.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" speakername="John Kelly" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200011#K00200"><p>I have just been informed of a worrying development from a person who, like me, has raised funds for good causes.  Dunnes Stores has banned all animal charities from collecting in its stores nationwide.  Apparently, it is not willing to discuss its new decision with anybody.  It is also unwilling to talk to Joe Duffy about it and will not give any good reason it has decided to do this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200011#K00300"><p>Does the Senator have a question for the Deputy Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" speakername="John Kelly" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200011#K00400"><p>Yes.  At the same time the company sells dog food, cat food and other pet products but it is not interested in contributing to the welfare of these animals.  I have been in touch with organisations like the Irish Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals, ISPCA, and the ASPCA.  These organisations survive solely on voluntary contributions, donations and fund-raising.  For them to achieve their goals, they need access to stores like Dunnes Stores.  I call on the Deputy Leader to ask the Minister of State with responsibility for small business to find out why the store has taken the decision.  There does not seem to be a logical reason for it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200011#K00500"><p>I support my colleague, Senator MacSharry, in his call for action by the Government on the banking issue.  All we have seen so far is activity portrayed as action.  The sight of the Governor of the Central Bank calling on the Government to do something tells us that even he is frustrated by the lack of action two years on.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200011#K00600"><p>He did not call on the Government, he called on the banks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200011#K00700"><p>I ask the Deputy Leader to organise a debate regarding a specific action and issue related to The Gathering.  We had a debate on it recently but airlines seem to be sabotaging the Government's initiative by price hikes, which in some cases have doubled.  I have been contacted by people in Boston who paid $4,300 for flights and car hire for a family of five less than two years ago but the same package costs $8,000 this year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200011#K00800"><p>That is a lot of money.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200011#K00900"><p>This tells us that the airlines are taking advantage of a great Government initiative.  Events for The Gathering will take place in Kerry and throughout the country.  How will people travel to The Gathering if they will be charged double the fare and rates of a couple of years ago?  I ask the Deputy Leader to arrange the debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200011#K01000"><p>I agree with Senator MacSharry's comments to a large extent except that the Personal Insolvency Act will make a difference.  One of the concerns I have and which I want the Deputy Leader to follow up is that members of the accountancy profession have approached me and advised that they now have difficultly, just like my colleagues in the legal profession, entering into negotiations with the banks.  Some of their clients have been referred to retired bank officials who have set up consultancy businesses and who so not seem to have any difficulty in accessing the banks and can talk to someone in the banks.  I am concerned that some banks have adopted a new policy that they will only talk to people who have previously worked in the banking sector when dealing with people who want to reach a sensible arrangement that would satisfy the bank and the borrower.  I ask for the matter to be clarified.  I want the Minister for Finance to seek clarification from the banks that they are prepared to deal with everyone, whether in the legal profession or accountancy profession, who wants to work with them on behalf of their clients.  I ask that the issue be clarified.  I want to know that negotiations are not solely confined to retired people who have set themselves up as consultants.  It is an urgent matter which needs immediate attention.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200011#K01100"><p>I remind the Deputy Leader that this year is the centenary of the 1913 Lock-out.  A number of weeks ago I asked the Leader whether the Oireachtas would consider marking the centenary in its own way.</p> <p>I put forward a proposal that this House could invite a senior trade union leader from the Irish Congress of Trade Unions to address it on the subject of workers' rights and employment rights.  It would be an important thing to do as we are in a decade of centenaries and there will be many different events that Members should rightly mark in the coming years.  I believe the 1913 Lock-out was a seminal moment in the struggle for workers' rights, and as legislators, Members of the Oireachtas and people who were elected by the people of the State, Members should mark the event in their own way.  It would be remiss of this House not to so do and I ask the Deputy Leader to have discussions with the Leader to ascertain whether this could be done this year in order that Members could pay tribute in their own way to those who were involved in the Lock-out, to remember the sacrifices made and to re-dedicate themselves to ensuring they protect workers' rights at all times. I ask because, unfortunately, many workers throughout this State have been obliged in recent years to engage in sit-in protests to demand even basic rights and entitlements.  I sincerely ask the Deputy Leader to consider this proposal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Caít Keane" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200012#L00200"><p>Like other Senators, I wish Pope Benedict well in his retirement.  When Senator Moloney observed that it usually is women or children who suffer at the hands of institutions, it brought to mind the women in the church, and perhaps the new Pope might look on women in the church in a new light as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200012#L00300"><p>A new Pope who is a woman.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Caít Keane" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200012#L00400"><p>A new Pope who is a woman.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200012#L00500"><p>Some chance.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Caít Keane" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200012#L00600"><p>I will start at the beginning but one never knows.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200012#L00700"><p>The Senator should speak through the Chair.  Many Senators have indicated they wish to speak.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Caít Keane" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200012#L00800"><p>We are always evolving and changing.  As it has been 600 years since the last Pope retired, one never knows.</p><p>However, I did not rise to speak about such an evolution.  I wanted to raise the issue of development levies and the manner in which they are being interpreted differently nationwide.  I refer to manner in which the question of whether the levy follows the developer or the person living in the house is being implemented.  This is an important issue because Members will have noted that people in County Wicklow are being billed by Wicklow County Council for huge sums of as much as €4,000.  While it is important that all development and outstanding levies be paid, it also is important that there should be fairness in how that is implemented.  I refer to scenarios in which, having purchased their houses, people have letters from solicitors regarding the deeds and that a search having been done, there are no outstanding charges on the deed or whatever.  The Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government should issue a statement in this regard because it must be implemented uniformly nationwide.  At present, different statements are coming from different councils and from the aforementioned Department.  One council has stated it is following the developer while another has stated it was thinking about following the purchaser.  The Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government stated it was a matter for each local authority.  It is a matter to be implemented fairly throughout the country and I ask the Leader to request that the aforementioned Department issue a statement on this matter and on how it is to be implemented.  While it is important for local authorities to ensure they get their levies, they must get them fairly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200012#L00900"><p>I wish to support the suggestion that the report by the former Senator, Martin McAleese, into the Magdalen laundries be debated in this House as soon as possible.  I greatly regret that the former Senator has resigned from this House.  Unfortunately, I was absent last week, being at a meeting of the European pro-dialogue group on the Malvinas Islands while Members were debating an extremely important Bill in the Chamber.  I remind Members that in Britain, these islands are called the Falkland Islands but I-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200012#L01000"><p>Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200012#L01100"><p>I was engaged in that last week.  However, I wish the former Senator McAleese the best.  I presume Members already have sent best wishes to him in my absence.  He resides in County Roscommon with his wife, Mary, and is a loss to the county as a Senator.  Will the Taoiseach decide to fill the vacancy or await the outcome of the referendum in October for so doing?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200012#L01200"><p>That is a matter for the Taoiseach.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200012#L01300"><p>Of course it is, and I am sure the Cathaoirleach has no influence whatsoever in that regard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200012#L01400"><p>Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200012#L01500"><p>That was more of a statement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200012#L01600"><p>I wish to support Senator Coghlan's proposal that Members send best wishes to Pope Benedict XVI on his decision to stand down as Bishop of Rome and Head of the Vatican State.  It is a great decision for him in the sense he is 85 years of age.  However, it is very historic from Members' perspective, as this is the first Seanad of which I have been a Member when a Pope has actually resigned.</p> <p>It is certainly-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200013#M00200"><p>We are all in the one boat.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200013#M00300"><p>It has not happened for 500 years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Maloney" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200013#M00500"><p>The last time was 600 years ago.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200013#M00600"><p>On a point of order, I put it on record that Senator Leyden did not call for it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200013#M00700"><p>We are not around for that long - 600 years.  Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200013#M00800"><p>We should not trivialise this important event.  There are 1.2 billion Catholics in the world.  One sixth of the entire population is Catholic and the role of Pope is an important one.  Ageism does not apply in the Vatican, which is refreshing.  Furthermore-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200013#M00900"><p>What about sexism?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200013#M01000"><p>Well said.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200013#M01100"><p>The Senator is over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200013#M01200"><p>I suggest-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200013#M01400"><p>Senator Leyden should be allowed to speak without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200013#M01500"><p>I understand that we will be represented by Cardinal Brady at the conclave, which is good.  Britain has no representative at the moment as there is no cardinal eligible to vote.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200013#M01700"><p>The Senator is over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200013#M01800"><p>I am sorry.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200013#M01900"><p>A lot of Senators have indicated.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200013#M02000"><p>When the new Pope-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200013#M02200"><p>Senator Leyden should be allowed to speak without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200013#M02300"><p>Senator Leyden is interfering between church and State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200013#M02400"><p>When the new Pope is elected I suggest to the Government that we would re-open our embassy in the Vatican as a gesture of solidarity.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200013#M02500"><p>I too, like the vast majority of people, was horrified and disgusted with what I saw on the television programme "Inside Irish Nationwide" last night.  It is a good reminder for people everywhere as to what went on in this country-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200013#M02600"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200013#M02700"><p>------for the past ten to 15 years.  It is also a good reminder of the mess we must clean up as a society, and of the over-indulgence and appalling waste of a valuable commodity, namely, money.  I ask the Leader to again request a banking inquiry in the State.  It is appalling to think that no banker in this State has gone to prison yet for what has happened in terms of the reckless behaviour that has taken place with the valuable commodity of money.  It is also appalling on the other hand to see ordinary householders being hounded by banks-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200013#M02800"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200013#M02900"><p>-----and threatened with eviction and repossession.  On the one hand, there was an exuberant element in society that spent money like it was going out of fashion on champagne, wine and the addition of a million here or there to a sale.  On the other hand, families are being run out of their homes because they are €15,000 or €20,000 in arrears.  We must get real as a society.  Everyone who has a role to play should push for a State banking inquiry headed by a High Court judge.  The truth must come out.  I commend the journalists who worked tirelessly to expose the rot that took place in this country in the past 20 years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1115" speakername="Labhrás Ó Murchú" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200013#M03000"><p>I support Senator Cullinane's suggestion that as part of the State commemoration of the 1913 Lock-out, the Seanad might consider inviting a senior trade union official to address us.  It would be most appropriate.</p><p>I compliment President Michael D. Higgins on the very courteous and generous message of goodwill which he issued on the impending resignation of Pope Benedict.  I join with that the generous message from An Tánaiste, Deputy Gilmore.  He pointed out specifically the work which the Pope had been doing for peace in the world, and never was that more important than it is at the moment.  Our representatives have joined with the President of the United States and the other world leaders in pointing to the work which the papacy and the church itself has been doing throughout the world.  President Obama was exceptionally open in his comment when he talked about the contribution being made by the Catholic Church to the United States.  We could all learn from that.</p> <p>We live in an imperfect world and at times we isolate issues away from the overall attitude we should have to people and organisations that are endeavouring to make society better, more equal and safer.  The current good will that is evident on all television stations might prompt up to seriously consider reopening the Irish Embassy at the Vatican.  If it is genuinely a financial issue I have no doubt we could raise the money throughout the world to pay for it.  With the upcoming election of a new Pope, there is a danger that we might be misrepresented among the nations of the world.  No one wants that and now is a time to revisit that decision and come up with a solution.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200014#N00200"><p>Since we met last week, some significant things have happened in our country.  There was a successful outcome to the promissory note negotiations, which will see the country not having to pay €3.4 billion at the end of March and save the State €20 billion over the coming ten years.  We also saw the successful completion of the ninth review by the EU-IMF, which gave the Government a clean bill of health.  The end of January Exchequer returns showed the income tax take up by 10% and excise duties up by 10%.  This all culminated in the Standard & Poor's ratings agency raising Ireland's outlook from negative to stable.  We now hope and want to see the Government build on that stability over the remainder of the lifetime of this Administration.  The major challenge we face is the curse of unemployment and I welcome the fact that a further €6 billion was committed to fighting youth unemployment at the last meeting of the Council of the European Union.</p><p>In line with Senator Conway's remarks on mortgages, it would be useful to have a review by the Taoiseach or Tánaiste of the progress that is being made with the programme for Government and the objectives that remain to be achieved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200014#N00300"><p>Senator Mullins left one other significant matter off his list.  Once again, according to the latest opinion poll, Fianna Fáil is the largest political party in the State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200014#N00400"><p>Has the Senator a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200014#N00500"><p>It is a very important development for the future of our country.</p><p>I join other colleagues in wishing Pope Benedict well in his retirement.  I wish him a long and peaceful retirement in the Vatican or wherever he decides to reside.  He made a very courageous decision to retire, the first Pope to do so in almost 600 years.</p><p>When is the Education and Training Boards Bill going to arrive into the House?  I join the leader of my party in the Seanad, Senator O'Brien, in calling for the Minister for Justice and Equality to come into the House.  The gardaí are operating in deplorable circumstances.  In Cavan town there are six detectives and they have no unmarked car.  The traffic corps is operating with an almost defunct squad car.  Court houses have been closed and policing districts are being amalgamated, with gardaí being forced to move up to 30 miles from their families without compensation.  I will not mention the mess the same Minister has made of the Defence Forces but I will not allow him to do the same to the honourable and decent people in the Garda Síochána who protect us on a daily basis.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200014#N00600"><p>I also compliment the Pope in his infinite wisdom on realising when it was time to go and on having the courage to break with practice where one went when one died.</p> <p>It is unbelievable how old people are when they are made Pope.  The then Cardinal Ratzinger who was in his late 70s when he became Pope is now in his mid-80s and in ailing health.  Perhaps the Catholic Church should consider this issue in the context of the leadership that is required and job that must be done for the worldwide population of Catholics.</p><p>If there is one common strand in Senators' contributions, it is the need for the House to unite on the banking issue and help people in mortgage arrears.  I agree with Senator MacSharry that the mortgage arrears resolution process, MARP, is a joke.  It is a superficial code that is not working.  I am in close contact with a family that was told after 40 days in the process that it did not qualify for any reduction in payment, despite the relationship manager of the bank in question, Ulster Bank, having recommended that the application for a reduced mortgage repayment be processed.  The family, which is not yet in arrears, has been invited to appeal the decision, a process that is expected to take a further 40 days.  The upshot of this approach is that the bank in question is inadvertently promoting arrears by delaying people who are under extreme financial stress.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200015#O00200"><p>Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200015#O00300"><p>The stress people are under is not properly understood.  For this reason, I was pleased to note the Governor of the Central Bank, Professor Patrick Honohan, intends to switch his energies to focusing on mortgage arrears.  What percentage of decisions taken as part of the mortgage arrears resolution process is going to arrears?  In my view, the MARP is an unacceptable delaying tactic that is placing people under stress.  If Senators stick together on this issue, we will make a difference.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200015#O00400"><p>It is inevitable and appropriate that all sides pay tribute to Pope Benedict XVI following his courageous decision and wish him well in his retirement.</p><p>It is interesting and somewhat salutary that Senator Mullins was the only speaker to highlight seismic changes in the economic and fiscal programme being pursued by the Government.  The Senator will be aware that the Fianna Fáil Party in both Houses applauded the initiative taken last week on the promissory note.  Anyone with common sense must applaud any reduction in the overall national debt.  However, in everything I have read on the issue only one or two people have pointed out that while the deal is perfectly acceptable and welcome, the Government's fiscal policies are having a detrimental effect on confidence and people's pockets.  I advise the Government to tread cautiously in respect of any hype surrounding the events of the past week and not to take its eye off the main focus of its policies, which must be to reduce and, if possible, eliminate austerity measures.  In the next 12 months, upwards of €1,000 will be taken from people's pockets as a result of water charges, the property tax and goodness knows what other budgetary policies the Government decides to pursue from October onwards.  Notwithstanding everything that took place last week, the Government must still address the deficit.  I support Senator Mullins's request to have the Taoiseach or Tánaiste come before the House to give people a little hope for the near future rather than 38 years down the road.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200015#O00500"><p>The three remaining Senators have one minute speaking time each.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200015#O00600"><p>I hope I am given the same time as Senator Leyden who was shown considerable latitude, perhaps because he has not been in the House for some time.</p><p>Senator Wilson referred to the most recent opinion poll.  I am concerned the Senator is starting to believe the fairytale of the past 14 years.  Maybe he still believes in the tooth fairy and Easter bunny as well.  I assure him that the 450 people employed in Stephens Barracks in Kilkenny are very happy with the terms they have in the Army.  The Minister for Defence, Deputy Alan Shatter, is doing a great job. </p> <p> We passed the Equal Status (Amendment) Bill in 2012 to ensure equality in the insurance industry.  Will the Deputy Leader ask the Minister for Finance or the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation to come to the House to discuss the insurance industry?  Ladies' insurance has increased by an average of 30% but there has been no decrease in the amount of insurance paid by men.  This is profit-taking by the insurance companies.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200016#P00200"><p>I agree with previous speakers in regard to the need for an inquiry into the banking sector.  Recently, we saw how inexpensive an inquiry can be.  The inquiry by the former Senator McAleese cost in the region of €11,000, which is a tiny amount compared with what some inquiries over the past number of years cost.  In many cases, young people are in negative equity in respect of their houses and the banks are completely unable to think outside the box.  We now see that there was no expertise in the banks during the boom.  All they did was hand out money - in many cases, far too much money which people could not afford to borrow.  To a large extent, that led to the crisis.  Individual borrowers should not be treated in the way they are being treated by the banks.  Will the Deputy Leader try to convene a debate on the issue as soon as possible so that we might be able to come up a plan in this regard?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" speakername="Terry Brennan" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200016#P00300"><p>We all know small and medium-sized industries are the backbone of the economy given the part they play in many communities.  I read in yesterday's newspaper that they are owed millions of euro by Departments and local authorities.  It beggars belief why Departments and local authorities take so long to pay for works well done.  Like all of us, these small and medium-sized industries need cashflow.  Will the Deputy Leader arrange a debate?  Is there anything we can do to encourage Departments and local authorities to pay their bills more quickly?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200016#P00400"><p>Senator Darragh O'Brien raised the issue of the strength of the Garda force and station closures and proposed an amendment to the Order of Business, to which I cannot agree.  We had a full debate on this issue last week in Private Members' time, which was taken by the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Shatter.  I will certainly provide the Senator with a briefing on it, which I have been given.  As he will be well aware and as was said during last week's debate, the Garda strength is 13,400 and average retirements are 400 per year and it goes without saying that the necessary funding for Garda salaries will be made available even if this means adjustments within the Garda Vote, the wider justice group of Votes or otherwise.  In terms of Garda stations, as Senators are aware, this is about smart policing and the most efficient and effective deployment of Garda resources.</p><p>I have undertaken an interesting exercise which is to look at the number of crimes recorded in individual Garda stations over a number of years and it is an eye-opener to see how small a number of crimes were reported in some Garda stations.  We should also be cognisant that there have been significant advances in modern policing, transport and technology and that the station network must reflect this current situation.  Even after the closure of stations in 2013, we will still have 564 stations throughout the country, comparably more than in Northern Ireland or Scotland.</p><p>Senator Darragh O'Brien raised a very specific issue, of which I am not aware.  I suggest he make the Minister, Deputy Shatter, directly aware of it.  That is probably the most appropriate way to deal with it rather than request the Minister to come to the House for debate, since he has just been here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200016#P00500"><p>It is very serious issue.  The whole north Dublin area is without cars for half a day.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200016#P00600"><p>I accept it is a serious matter and that is why I think the Senator should raise it directly with the Minister.  As I said, he was in the House last week but I will certainly ask about getting him to come here for another debate on policing.  I am very much open to doing that, as I know many Senators on both sides of the House have sought that.  It would be worthwhile having a bigger debate on policing which looks not only at station closures but at smart policing and the effect and impact of policing.</p> <p>If we look at the crime figures, we see that serious crime levels have decreased.  That is not to downplay in any way the serious recent incidents of aggravated burglary that have occurred and caused great concern around the country.  It is none the less worth noting that the launch of Operation Fiacla to tackle mobile gangs and burglary has had a significant effect.  I am told that between April and December 2012, more than 3,500 persons were arrested and approximately 2,000 persons were charged as part of that operation.  Smart policing is having an impact on crime figures.  The picture is somewhat more complex perhaps than is being painted.  We might have a more reflective debate on the issue when the Minister is available rather than deal with it by way of knee-jerk amendment to the Order of Business, in particular given the recent debate on Fianna Fáil's Private Members'-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200017#Q00150"><p>There is nothing knee-jerk about it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200017#Q00200"><p>On a point of order, it is not a knee-jerk reaction.  Fianna Fáil used its Private Members' time last week to-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200017#Q00300"><p>That is not a point of order, Senator O'Brien.  Please allow the Deputy Leader to continue without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200017#Q00400"><p>I take that back.  It sounds like I am dismissing the serious concerns of the Fianna Fáil Party and I am not.  This is a serious issue for me also, as it is for all Senators.</p><p>Senator Coghlan joined the Taoiseach and Tánaiste in sending good wishes to Pope Benedict XVI on his surprise resignation.  Colleagues will be aware that the Taoiseach and Tánaiste made statements in response to the resignation, both of which extended their best wishes to the Pope on his declaration that he intends to step down from office and paid tribute to him, which was shared by colleagues on both sides of the House today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200017#Q00500"><p>The President sent the Pope a letter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200017#Q00600"><p>Yes.  Senator van Turnhout spoke about the Chinese year of the snake.  She also referred to the report by Ita Mangan which was referred to in this Chamber by the Minister, Deputy Burton.  I thank Senator van Turnhout for reminding us about the report of the Advisory Group on Tax and Social Welfare.  I have made inquiries since she last raised it.  An update has been sought.  I understand progress is being made on the report.  I have not yet been told if the report is with the Minister.  We will have a debate on it in early course.</p><p>Senator van Turnhout also sought a debate on the child and family support agency and the legislation in that regard.  The Minister for Children and Youth Affairs, Deputy Fitzgerald, will be in the House tomorrow at 4.15 p.m. to deal with all Stages of the Child Care (Amendment) Bill 2013.  It might be worth the Senator's while raising the matter directly with the Minister at that time.  The Senator also asked about the Consumers' Association of Ireland report, which raises eyebrows in terms of the rising price of goods.  It is worth pointing out that the consumer price index produced by the Central Statistics Office provides a more complete figure and indicates that food and non-alcoholic beverage prices have fallen by 6.3% since 2008.  There is a mixed picture on that issue.  On the Gary Douch report, I am making inquiries on that matter.  I understood there was a publication arising from that appalling death.</p><p>Senator Mullen also raised the issue of policing, which I have dealt with.  He also raised concerns about the treatment of a public representative of the other House in the context of a road traffic offence.  I share the Senator's concern in that regard.  The Senator also asked for a debate on the report on the Magdalen institutions by former Senator McAleese.  I understand the Leader has promised such a debate.  We are continuing in our efforts to secure a date for that debate.  I assure colleagues that we are all keen to ensure there is a full debate on the issue.  We will give notice of the debate so that Senators have time to prepare for it.  I believe we can anticipate a Government response that is more fulsome than that given last week, in particular in light of the meeting yesterday between the Taoiseach, Tánaiste and some of the survivors of the Magdalen laundries.  Many of us firmly believe there must be a State apology on this matter.</p><p>Senator Harte also raised the issue of policing.  Senator O'Donovan spoke about the hostile takeover of Aer Lingus.  The Government position is that it does not support the revised Ryanair bid for Aer Lingus because of concerns about competition, productivity and employment.  On the Government's stake in Aer Lingus, it will be disposed of when the conditions are right.  On the sale of Coillte, which has been raised in the House previously, I will revert to Senator O'Donovan on that matter.</p><p>Senator Jim D'Arcy referred to the tragic death of Garda Adrian Donohoe and the resources put in place to investigate that matter.  I understand extra resources have been put in place.  The Garda Commissioner has made clear that resources will not be an issue in that investigation, which I understand is at an advanced stage.</p> <p> Senator Mary Ann O'Brien referred to the foreign aid budget.  She may be aware that the Minister of State, Deputy Costello, has promised to attend for a comprehensive debate on Irish Aid.  No date has yet been confirmed but he has promised it at an early course.</p><p>Senator Moran also referred to the death of Detective Garda Adrian Donohoe.  I have addressed that point.  She also raised the issue of juvenile crime and the role of women in the church.  As others have mentioned, while ageism may have no place in the church, which is welcome, sexism clearly does.</p><p>Senator Norris discussed Pope Benedict's retirement.  Senator Bradford called for a debate on Irish Aid.  One has been promised.</p><p>Senator Ó Clochartaigh asked for a debate on the report into the Magdalen institutions.  We will have one.  He also asked for a debate on the social cost of austerity but he might need to frame his request in a more focused manner, as I am unsure as to which Minister would attend such a debate in terms of marriage counselling.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor Ó Clochartaigh" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200018#R00200"><p>Maybe a few of them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200018#R00300"><p>We had planned a debate on children, child care and family policies with the Minister, Deputy Fitzgerald, but it needed to be adjourned because of the funeral of Detective Garda Adrian Donohoe.  When that debate resumes, it could be a good opportunity for the Senator to raise these issues.</p><p>Senator Moloney referred to the need for an apology regarding Magdalen institutions.  I agree with her.  She also referred to the Mangan report, a matter on which we need a debate, as the Minister, Deputy Burton, promised us last year.  I agree with Senator Moloney on the need to avoid a rerun of last year's budget.  We need a full debate on the issue as soon as possible.</p><p>Senator MacSharry raised the issue of the mortgage crisis.  He will be aware that the Government has taken steps to address the serious mortgage arrears crisis.  The Cabinet committee on mortgage arrears has driven real change, ensuring the most significant change in insolvency laws in more than a century, which was welcomed by us all, the establishment of the Insolvency Service of Ireland, the strengthening of protections for mortgage holders in difficulty and, working directly with the Central Bank and Governor Honohan, the putting in place by banks of additional restructuring options for those in difficulty.  The Senator will also be aware that the mortgage-to-rent scheme forms part of the package of measures that the Government has developed to deal with this serious issue.  He referred to this scheme.  He also referred to some more creative solutions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200018#R00400"><p>Development and delivery are clearly different.  There is no delivery on the ground whatsoever.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200018#R00500"><p>The Deputy Leader without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200018#R00600"><p>It is a disgrace.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200018#R00700"><p>We can certainly have a further debate on the matter.</p><p>Senator Comiskey mentioned the upgrade of the N4.  We all commiserate on last night's death on that road, but it might be a topic for a matter on the Adjournment.</p><p>Senator Barrett raised the issue of the Taxi Regulation Bill.  That debate is due to adjourn at 5.45 p.m., if not previously concluded.  It will be rolled over if it is not concluded today.  A substantial number of amendments have been tabled.  The Senator also mentioned the excellent book, &quot;Coercive Confinement in Ireland: Patients, Prisoners and Penitents&quot;, by Professors Ian O'Donnell and Eoin O'Sullivan, which I have read.  As the Senator stated, it sets out a full and appalling picture of confinement and incarceration in Ireland, not just in Magdalen institutions, but also in industrial schools, psychiatric hospitals and so on.</p><p>Senator Kelly raised the issue of the ban on animal charities in Dunnes Stores, of which I was not aware.  It might be worth writing directly to the board of the shop in question, a private enterprise,-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200018#R00800"><p>I am sure that Ms Margaret Heffernan will be worried about that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200018#R00900"><p>-----and the Minister of State with responsibility for small business.</p><p>Senator Daly raised the issue of flights.  I have outlined the Government's position on Aer Lingus.</p><p>Senator Burke referred to the issue of employing consultants.  We might discuss it in the context of a fuller debate on the mortgage crisis and banking policy.</p><p>Senator Cullinane mentioned the centenary of the 1913 Lock-out.  Like all Senators, I am well aware of that centenary.  Inviting a senior trade union leader to address the House is a great idea.  Perhaps Senator Cullinane - I believe another Senator also raised the issue - should write to the Committee on Procedure and Privileges, CPP, to ask for a specific consideration.  The CPP considers requests from every Senator who wishes to invite someone to address the House.  Quite a number of guest speakers have visited the House during this term.  In the context of the centenary, trying to do something along these lines might be worthwhile.  Recently, the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Varadkar, debated the centenary issue specifically in the House.</p><p>Senator Keane discussed the issue of a woman pope.  I agree that we might see one some day.  I have a full briefing for the Senator on development levies.  Her issue concerned Wicklow County Council and households charged development contributions.  Some legal action is pending in that regard, but I can share the briefing with the Senator.  Some letters were issued to home owners in Wicklow regarding breaches of planning permission as a result of the non-payment of development contributions, but a separate legal action has been taken against the original developer seeking payment of the full amount of development contributions outstanding of more than €60,000.  That matter will be before the Circuit Court later this month.</p><p>Senator Leyden discussed Dr. McAleese's report.</p> <p>We will have a debate on it and that was promised by the Leader.  </p><p>We all appreciated the comment by Senator Leyden that even in his memory no Pope has resigned.</p><p>Senator Conway raised the matter of the need for a banking inquiry in light of the excellent investigative television programme on Irish Nationwide last night.  We could have a debate on it although a banking inquiry is a somewhat different issue.  It might be worth inviting the Minister, Deputy Howlin, to come to the House to speak to us about how he proposes to set up that inquiry, which I know he is anxious to have established.</p><p>Senator Ó Murchú raised the matter of inviting a senior trade union figure to address the House.  I have said that is a matter for the Committee on Procedure and Privileges and it would be a good idea to put it before that committee.  The Senator referred to the reopening of the Irish Embassy at the Vatican, which another Member raised.  High level diplomacy between the Secretary General of the Department of Foreign Affairs and the Vatican is ongoing and I understand that is going particularly well.</p><p>Senator Mullins referred to the economic situation and welcomed the deal last week on foot of the introduction of the emergency legislation.  Everyone has welcomed the change in the terms on the promissory notes.  It is a significant improvement in our economic situation, perhaps reflected in Standard &amp; Poor's announcement today.  </p><p>Senator Wilson referring to the opinion polls, which were taken before the deal on the promissory notes, as he is aware.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="16:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200019#S00200"><p>They were also taken before the report on the Magdalen laundries.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.153" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="A Senator" time="16:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200019#S00300"><p>That does not matter.  It would have been higher if-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="16:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200019#S00400"><p>Even the people who took those polls said they are only useful now as an indicator of what the mood was-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.155" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="A Senator" time="16:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200019#S00500"><p>What is coming down the road for the Government.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="16:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200019#S00600"><p>-----pre the introduction of the emergency legislation and the deal on the promissory notes.</p><p>I will find out for the Senator when the Education and Training Boards Bill will be taken in the House.  I think it is still on Report Stage in the Dáil.  I checked it last week as I have an interest in it.  I do not think it is due before the House imminently but I will check.</p><p>Senator Healy Eames raised the matter of banking and mortgage arrears and I have given a response on that.  </p><p>Senator Mooney put forward the idea that the Taoiseach or Tánaiste might be requested to address the House on the programme for Government and we could have a reflective review of it.  We can submit a request for the Taoiseach or Tánaiste to come to the House and speak to us on that. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="16:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200019#S00700"><p>That request came from the Deputy's Leader's side; I was just supporting it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="16:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200019#S00800"><p>I like the idea.  It is worth requesting that.  To be fair, another Member also mentioned it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="16:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200019#S00900"><p>Senator Mullen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="16:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200019#S01000"><p>Yes. Senator Mullen.</p><p>Senator O'Neill referred to the Equal Status Bill and the equalising of insurance premia.  He has raised a good point and he has requested that it be brought to the attention of the Minister concerned since that was not the desired effect of the legislation.</p><p>Senator Noone requested a debate on banking, to which I have responded in respect of requests from other Members. </p><p>Senator Brennan raised the matter of small and medium-sized enterprises and their need of cashflow.  There is a code of practice in place and Departments are supposed to pay for work done within a specific time.  If there is a breach in the code of practice, and I have also heard complaints about this, that should be brought directly back to the Departments concerned.  They should be told they are in breach of the code of practice if they do not pay for work done within the requisite time.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="16:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200019#S01100"><p>Senator Darragh O'Brien has proposed an amendment to the Order of Business, "That a debate on the worsening crisis in the operation of An Garda Síochána due to the lack of resources and a lack of confidence by the rank and file of the force in the Minister for Justice and Equality be taken today".  Is the amendment being pressed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="16:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200019#S01200"><p>It is.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.163/1" nospeaker="true" time="16:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200020#T00100"><p>Amendment put:</p><p>The Seanad divided: Tá, 17; Níl, 25.</p><p>Tellers: Tá, Senators Paschal Mooney and Diarmuid Wilson; Níl, Senators Paul Coghlan and Susan O'Keeffe.</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.163/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2013-02-12" time="16:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200020#T00100">
            <divisioncount ayes="17" noes="25" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" vote="aye">Sean Barrett</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" vote="aye">David Cullinane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" vote="aye">Mark Daly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" vote="aye">Terry Leyden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" vote="aye">Marc MacSharry</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" vote="aye">Paschal Mooney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" vote="aye">Rónán Mullen</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" vote="aye">David Norris</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" vote="aye">Darragh O'Brien</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1169" vote="aye">Mary Ann O'Brien</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" vote="aye">Denis O'Donovan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" vote="aye">Trevor Ó Clochartaigh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" vote="aye">Brian Ó Domhnaill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1115" vote="aye">Labhrás Ó Murchú</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1154" vote="aye">Averil Power</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1155" vote="aye">Kathryn Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" vote="aye">Diarmuid Wilson</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" vote="no">Ivana Bacik</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1121" vote="no">Paul Bradford</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" vote="no">Terry Brennan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" vote="no">Colm Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1114" vote="no">Deirdre Clune</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" vote="no">Eamonn Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" vote="no">Paul Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1124" vote="no">Michael Comiskey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" vote="no">Martin Conway</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" vote="no">Jim D'Arcy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1160" vote="no">Michael D'Arcy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1144" vote="no">Jimmy Harte</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" vote="no">Fidelma Healy Eames</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1173" vote="no">Lorraine Higgins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" vote="no">Caít Keane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" vote="no">John Kelly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" vote="no">Marie Maloney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" vote="no">Mary Moran</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1134" vote="no">Tony Mulcahy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" vote="no">Michael Mullins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" vote="no">Catherine Noone</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" vote="no">Susan O'Keeffe</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" vote="no">Pat O'Neill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" vote="no">Feargal Quinn</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1143" vote="no">John Whelan</mpname>
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.163/3" nospeaker="true" time="16:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200020#T00100"><p>Amendment declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.164" nospeaker="true" time="16:35:00"><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.165" nospeaker="true" time="16:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200022#V00100">Address to Seanad Éireann: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="16:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200022#V00200"><p>I move:<ul><br />&quot;That, in accordance with Standing Order 57(2) and the decision of the Committee on Procedure and Privileges, Seanad Éireann agrees that Phil Prendergast M.E.P. shall attend and be heard in Seanad Éireann on Wednesday 13th February, 2013 and that the following arrangements shall apply.  The proceedings, which shall not exceed two hours, shall consist of a contribution which shall not exceed twenty minutes by Phil Prendergast M.E.P. a contribution not exceeding five minutes by the spokesperson of each Group and a contribution not exceeding two minutes from a Sinn Féin Senator at the conclusion of which Phil Prendergast M.E.P. will reply to questions (which shall not exceed one minute in each case) from members in accordance with the Schedule below.<div>Schedule</div>Fine Gael Senators:  2 questions<br />Fianna Fáil Senators:2 questions<br />Labour Senators:2 questions<br />Taoiseach Nominees:2 questions<br />University Senators:2 questions.<br />Sinn Féin Senators:1 question.&quot;.</ul></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.167" nospeaker="true" time="16:40:00"><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.168" nospeaker="true" time="16:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200022#V00400">International Agreements: Referral to Joint Committee</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="16:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200022#V00500"><p>I move:<ul><br />That, the proposal that Seanad Éireann approves the exercise by the State of the option or discretion under Protocol No. 21 on the position of the United Kingdom and Ireland in respect of the area of freedom, security and justice annexed to the Treaty on European Union and to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, to accept the following measures:<ul>(i) Council Decision 2007/341/EC of 19th April, 2007 on the conclusion of the Agreement between the European Community and the Russian   <br />Federation on readmission,<br />(ii) Council Decision 2011/118/EU of 18th January, 2011 on the conclusion of the Agreement between the European Union and Georgia on the                              readmission of persons residing without authorisation, <br />(iii) Council Decision 2007/820/EC of 8th November, 2007 on the conclusion of the Agreement between the European Community and Bosnia and Herzegovina on the readmission of persons residing without authorisation,<br />(iv) Council Decision 2007/817/EC of 8th November, 2007 on the conclusion of the Agreement between the European Community and the former Yugoslav Republic of Macedonia on the readmission of persons residing without authorisation,<br />(v) Council Decision 2005/809/EC of 7th November, 2005 concerning the conclusion of the Agreement between the European Community and the Republic of Albania on the readmission of persons residing without authorisation,<br />(vi) Council Decision 2004/424/EC of 21st April, 2004 concerning the conclusion of the Agreement between the European Community and the Macao Special Administrative Region of the People's Republic of China on the readmission of persons residing without authorisation,<br />(vii) Council Decision 2005/372/EC of 3rd March, 2005 concerning the conclusion of the Agreement between the European Community and the Democratic Socialist Republic of Sri Lanka on the readmission of persons residing without authorisation, <br />(viii) Council Decision 2007/819/EC of 8th November, 2007 on the conclusion of the Agreement between the European Community and the Republic of Serbia on the readmission of persons residing without authorisation,<br />(ix) Council Decision 2007/826/EC of 22nd November, 2007 on the conclusion of the Agreement between the European Community and the Republic of Moldova on the readmission of persons residing without authorisation,<br />(x) Council Decision 2007/818/EC of 8th November, 2007 on the conclusion of the Agreement between the European Community and the Republic of Montenegro on the readmission of persons residing without authorisation, and<br />(xi) Council Decision 2010/649/EU of 7th October, 2010 on the conclusion of the Agreement between the European Community and the Islamic Republic of Pakistan on the readmission of persons residing without authorisation,</ul>copies of which were laid before Seanad Éireann on 10th December 2012, be referred to the Joint Committee on Justice, Defence and Equality, in accordance with Standing Order 70A(3), which, not later than 26th February, 2013, shall send a message to the Seanad in the manner prescribed in Standing Order 73, and Standing Order 75(2) shall accordingly apply. </ul></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="16:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200022#V00600"><p>It would be helpful if we got a minute of explanation as to what each of them were.  That may not be possible in this instance but it would be helpful to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="16:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200022#V00700"><p>To be of assistance to the Senator, I read out the full title for this motion, under item No. 2 at the start.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="16:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200022#V00800"><p>I read it myself but it does not explain what it is.  It just mentions a whole list of countries.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.173" nospeaker="true" time="16:40:00"><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.174" nospeaker="true" time="16:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200022#V01000">Taxi Regulation Bill 2012: Committee Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="16:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200022#V01100"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Alan Kelly, to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.176" nospeaker="true" time="16:40:00"><p>Section 1 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.177" nospeaker="true" time="16:40:00"><p>SECTION 2</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="16:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200022#V01400"><p>Government amendments Nos. 1 and 36 are related.  Amendment No. 37 is an alternative to Government amendment No. 36.  Government amendments Nos. 1 and 36 and amendment No. 37 may be discussed together, by agreement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.179" nospeaker="true" time="16:40:00"><p>Government amendment No. 1:
In page 8, to delete lines 18 to 21 and substitute the following:
&quot; &quot;dispatch operator&quot; means a person who provides for reward a booking service for an intending passenger to contact him or her to arrange for the hire and carriage of the intending passenger in a small public service vehicle operated or driven by another person (other than an employee of the first-mentioned person) but does not include a person employed by the first-mentioned person to take or manage the taking of bookings in the course of that service or a person marshalling in a public place (within the meaning of the Act of 1961) the services of small public service vehicles;&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="16:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200022#V01500"><p>Amendment No. 1 to section 2 provides for a more precise definition of "dispatch operator" who is involved in booking and dispatching taxis.  This definition distinguishes services provided by a "dispatch operator" from other similar services, such as marshalling taxis in a public place, for which a licence under NTA regulations is not required.</p><p>Government amendment No. 36 to section 19 provides for prohibition on acting without a licence as a dispatch operator or as a booking service provider for services requiring a licence under regulations made by the NTA.</p><p>I cannot agree to amendment No. 37 to section 19 which seeks the deletion of subsections (7) and (8).  Subsection (7) prohibits a person from acting as a dispatch operator or providing booking services for small public services vehicles where a licence is required and subsection (8) creates an offence in this regard.</p> <p>This prohibition and offence will enable the NTA to enforce effectively the regulation concerning the licensed operation of these services.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.182" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200023#W00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State and thank him for initiating this legislation here.  The object, we hope, is to improve it if we can or to assist the Minister of State if we can, and if we cannot do so, I am sure it will go forward to the other House.</p><p>My response is to ask what is the point.  A dispatch operator is the person who provides a booking service for an intending passenger.  It is somebody who answers the telephone.  Regulation is expensive and bureaucracy is expensive.  What is wrong with somebody who answers the telephone?  I do not see why it is necessary.  It used be in the literature that this was necessary because persons could achieve monopolies to take control over the sector, but the Goodbody report shows that the dispatch operator share of the market is down, from 51.2% to 38.4%.  The danger of them acquiring a monopoly is not serious.</p><p>Is this regulatory creep?  Is the NTA merely looking for extra functions which really perform nothing?  Does the Minister of State fancy prosecuting persons who answer the telephone?  How persons get taxis these days is by hailing them in the street or by telephoning the taxi driver directly.  That is now the dominant part of the market, where persons leave cards into one's house, etc.  The NTA is in search of extra functions.  I honestly do not see the point of trying to regulate the booking sector.  If somebody can book tickets for functions, etc., and a taxi as well, why do dispatch operators need to be licensed by the National Transport Authority which has a track record of always preventing competition?  This is starting off as relatively nebulous but it can be used to prevent competition because that is the track record of the body which will be administering it.</p><p>I do not see the necessity for it.  It is up to persons themselves how they book a taxi.  They are choosing dispatch operators ever less frequently.  That is the choice they have made.  That is the spirit in which I put forward the amendment.  If the Minister of State thinks it is important and convinces me that it is, I would be pleased to hear that.  I merely wonder.  The Government is trying to cut back on bureaucracy and trying to balance the books of the country.  Commendable strides were made last week and I commend the Minister of State and his colleagues.  What is the point in regulating something that does not need to be regulated?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.183" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200023#W00300"><p>I support Senator Sean D. Barrett.  I use taxis from time to time.  I note, from friends in particular, that there is a mobile phone application where one can push a button and get the closest taxi which will be with one within four minutes.</p><p>  The other point I would make is that amendment No. 36 seems completely redundant, if not fatuous.  It seeks to insert the following in the Bill:<ul>  &quot;(7) A person shall not act as a dispatch operator or provide booking services for small public service vehicles where such services require a licence under regulations made by the Authority unless that person holds a licence in that regard.&quot;.</ul>In other words, one cannot have a job that requires a licence unless one has a licence.  What is the big news?  That is a waste of ink.  If one must have a licence to have a job, then it is perfectly obvious that one needs a licence to get the job.  It seems redundant unless I am missing some legal nicety.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.184" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200023#W00400"><p>I thank the Senators.  I cannot accept the amendment.  For starters, I do not accept that the NTA is over-regulating this.  We are ensuring there is the appropriate licensing of dispatch operators who have an intermediary function which needs to be regulated in some form.</p><p>I accept wholly what the Senators stated on the disintermediation of such dispatch operators.  The different applications, such as the mobile phone applications and the online applications, are changing the face of how one books and interacts with taxis.  More change will happen, some of which I will announce in the coming weeks.  I cannot accept the amendment proposed by the Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.185" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="16:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200024#X00200"><p>If the Minister of State is going down this avenue why does he not license telephone operators?  They often come into contact with sensitive information.  They dispatch not only taxis but ambulances, fire brigades and the police.  As far as I know they are not licensed and anybody can get a job there.  Many of them seem to be poets, certainly at my local exchange.</p><p>The Minister of State has not addressed my comments on amendment No. 36, that it is redundant and simply states one must have a licence because one must have a licence.  I genuinely ask because I may have missed something.  It does not seem to me to make any sense as it states if one must have a licence one must have a licence, unless the person who drafted it was infected by reading the late Gertrude Stein's line that &quot;a rose is a rose is a rose&quot;, and decided for poetic balance to include a licence is a licence is a licence.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.186" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="16:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200024#X00300"><p>Does the Minister of State have a response to this eloquence?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.187" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="16:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200024#X00400"><p>Not really, except to say the section is trying to ensure consistency in approach, in that dispatch operator services are licensed and appropriate licensing arrangements are included in the legislation.  This is what we are trying to achieve.  I accept the spirit in which the Senator tabled the amendment, but we need to ensure consistency in approach, which is why I will not accept the Senator's amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="16:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200024#X00500"><p>I thank the Minister of State and amendments are always offered in this spirit.  The crime we are creating merits a fine of €50,000 for telephoning for a taxi other than through somebody approved by the National Transport Authority.  I know the Minister of State is trying to reform the body, but its record is always one of preventing competition at airports, between bus companies and airlines.  Now one cannot even have competing telephone booking services unless the NTA approves it.  If I ask Senator Norris to telephone for a taxi it will cost him €50,000 according to the section, which I also sought to-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.189" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="16:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200024#X00600"><p>I cannot afford it due to my libel action.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.190" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="16:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200024#X00700"><p>There are elements we need to regulate in transport, and there are others which would be a waste of time to regulate and will probably be overtaken by technology.  I do not want to press the point.  I am concerned about the priority of whoever drew up the Bill which designated a fine of €50,000 for telephoning for a taxi other than through somebody who got a licence from the Minister to do so.  It is "licenceitis" gone out of control.  I will withdraw the amendment because I am sure the Minister of State has many other interesting things to say.  As is the case in other parts of the Bill this indicates a lack of perspective.  The track record of the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport is if it moves try to stop it moving and if people set up in business try to stop them, and I am afraid it shines through in this section just as well.  I cannot imagine anything less worthy of attracting a fine of €50,000 than booking a taxi by telephone through somebody of whom the Minister did not approve.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.191" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="16:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200024#X00800"><p>I thank the Senator for withdrawing the amendment.  I believe dispatch operators need to be regulated.  If the NTA is not aware of who will operate these services one cannot manage quality or ensure certain sensitive information is channelled in the right direction.  Later we will deal with the issue of wheelchair accessible vehicles.  We need certain standards.  I do not accept the NTA is overzealous in this area.  It has been quite moderate in its thinking.  I understand what the Senator stated on the disintermediation effect, which I agree will happen over a period of time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.192" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="16:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200024#X00900"><p>I do not think there is anything at all moderate about a €50,000 fine.  I am pleased by the Minister of State's bashfulness in refusing to answer my repeated requests to address the nonsense of amendment No. 36.</p> <p>I shall take pleasure in voting against it.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.194" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200025#Y00200"><p>Senator Barrett wishes to withdraw his amendment but we must first deal with amendment No. 1.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.195" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200025#Y00300"><p>One cannot withdraw a Government amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.196" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200025#Y00400"><p>Amendment No. 1 is a Government amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200025#Y00500"><p>Then the Leas-Chathaoirleach can do whatever he likes with it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.198" nospeaker="true" time="17:00:00"><p>Amendment put and declared carried.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.199" nospeaker="true" time="17:00:00"><p>Section 2, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.200" nospeaker="true" time="17:00:00"><p>SECTION 3</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.201" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200025#Y00850"><p>Amendments Nos. 2 to 4, inclusive, are related and may be discussed together by agreement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.202" nospeaker="true" time="17:00:00"><p>Government amendment No. 2:In page 9, subsection (2), lines 17 and 18, to delete &#8220;or an order&#8221;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.203" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200025#Y01100"><p>I shall discuss amendments Nos. 2 to 4, inclusive, together.  They are minor technical amendments to section 3 and I wish to delete the term "order".  Matters in the Bill to be prescribed by the National Transport Authority will be by means of regulation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.204" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200025#Y01200"><p>What does withdrawing an "order" mean?  I support the Minister of State and agree that the less of this technical detail the better.  What is the difference, in this context, between a regulation and an order?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.205" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200025#Y01300"><p>It is a provision to make things by order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.206" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200025#Y01400"><p>I accept what the Minister of State had said.  I know that it will not happen and I support his amendments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.207" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200025#Y01500"><p>It is a technical amendment.  It is purely a drafting matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.208" nospeaker="true" time="17:00:00"><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.209" nospeaker="true" time="17:00:00"><p>Government amendment No. 3:In page 9, subsection (2)(a), line 20, to delete &#8220;or order&#8221;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.210" nospeaker="true" time="17:00:00"><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.211" nospeaker="true" time="17:00:00"><p>Government amendment No. 4:In page 9, subsection (2), line 25, to delete &#8220;or order&#8221;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.212" nospeaker="true" time="17:00:00"><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.213" nospeaker="true" time="17:00:00"><p>Section 3, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.214" nospeaker="true" time="17:00:00"><p>SECTION 4</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.215" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200025#Y02300"><p>Amendments Nos. 5 and 12 are related and may be discussed together by agreement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.216" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200025#Y02400"><p>I move amendment No. 5:<ul><ul>In page 9, between lines 37 and 38, to insert the following:<ul>&#8220;(<i>d</i>) the Taxi Regulation Act 2003 (Grant of Taxi Licences) (Amendment) Regulations 2010;&#8221;.</ul></ul></ul>Section 4 listed a number of laws to be repealed such as section 84 of the Road Traffic Act 1961.  I have added, because it is draconian and probably unconstitutional, that we should also repeal SI 250 of 2010.  Professor Paul K. Gorecki of the ESRI has pointed out that the statutory instrument is a prohibition on new entry when what the industry requested was a moratorium.  I have discussed it with my legal colleagues in Trinity College Dublin and elsewhere who said that the attempt to overturn a High Court decision using a statutory instrument or legislation raised serious problems.  The High Court decided in a judgment by Mr. Justice Roderick Murphy, and upheld by Mr. Justice Paul Carney in a judicial review, that one has the right to enter a sector which one has the skills and training for and the public has the right to the services of such persons.  There were also two judgments on these issues made by Mr. Justice Declan Costello and Mr. Justice Hugh <font color="#222222">Geoghegan.  </font></p><p>  There was an attempt in 2010 to subvert that by stopping new entrants which, to the economist, are a vital part of an industry.  When one bans new entrants then industries become fat and the pieces of paper, otherwise called a taxi licence, acquire value and could be worth &#8364;100,000 or more.  They are worth $1 million in New York because the authorities do not let enough people join.  Economically one should not ban new entrants.  However, it is the law to ban them because the courts have decided.  The Government never repealed the decisions made by the two judges in the High Court, in the first instance, and on judicial review to the Supreme Court.  A measure like SI 250 of 2010 must be repealed by the House.  I do not know how it ever got here in the first instance except that statutory instruments are printed in large bundles and are not discussed by the House.  Now we have a chance to discuss the statutory instrument.   </p> <p>It should be repealed on the basis that Members know what the courts have said.  On the last day, the Minister to his credit stated that he would wish to cap the numbers but that it cannot be done because it would be against the law.  That statutory instrument should be taken away from the law as quickly as possible.  If not, someone can challenge it in the High Court but it would be much better were Members to do so here.  I note the Minister wishes to repeal the Act of 2003.  This statutory instrument was purported to be a development of the 2003 Act.  I will be delighted if it falls automatically but if  not, I wish to make sure that it does.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.218" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="17:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200026#Z00200"><p>Senator Norris indicated that he wished to speak.  We are on amendment No. 5 tabled by Senator Barrett.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.219" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="17:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200026#Z00300"><p>Yes, and so am I.  I salute Senator Barrett, who in my opinion justifies the existence of the Senate every day.  He has rooted out something very important in this regard because it looks as though Members are purporting to use a statutory instrument to overrule a judgment that was sustained by two High Court judgments - given by two distinguished High Court judges - and in an appeal to the Supreme Court.  This is not what regulations or orders, which appear to be the alternative to this, are for.  This is endorsing restrictive practices.  I believe that to be a reasonable description of it and such restrictive practices are noxious.  Moreover, they are not welcomed by the taxi group either.  I acknowledge that we rocketed from a taxi industry that was far too restrictive to one that perhaps is overly-liberated but this constitutes restrictive practice.  I remember when these things were very much in view in the legal profession - they probably still are but it is not quite as bad - and attempts were made to keep people out from the professions of solicitor, barrister and so on.  Something significant in this regard has been highlighted by Senator Barrett and were he to call a vote on it, he certainly would have my support.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.220" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="17:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200026#Z00400"><p>Briefly, it is great to see that the Senators from Trinity are so united.  I will reiterate a point I have made previously, which is that Senator Barrett's forensic knowledge of transport economics is something I admire hugely.  In his contribution, Senator Norris referred to the overly-restricted taxi practices before deregulation. and the position in Dublin at that time was an absolute disgrace.  Moreover, deregulation was necessary to deal with that because no agreement on any kind of a more lucid system was forthcoming from the taxi unions at the time.  At the time, any reasonable suggestion put forward by the Fianna Fáil-Progressive Democrats Government was simply rubbished by the taxi unions, which wanted no change whatsoever.  I agree that taxi deregulation as it has happened probably has gone too far and it is pitiful to see the whole of Dawson Street covered in taxis on a Saturday night.  In this section and in the Bill in general, the Minister of State has achieved an attempt to come up with a balance.  However, I suggest that it will be a movable feast in the sense that taxi regulation and legislation will be tweaked depending on needs.  As society evolves and the habits of its citizens evolve over time, we probably will be obliged to address the issue of taxi regulation again and tweak it accordingly.  Consequently, I suggest to my learned colleagues that they should give this legislation a chance.  I am sure the Minister will be more than happy to review it in a couple of years' time, if that is deemed to be necessary.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.221" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="17:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200026#Z00500"><p>While I has intended to await the Minister of State's reply, I will just throw this point  into the mix.  The Minister of State has met representatives of the Taxi Alliance of Ireland, which has been lobbying on this Bill, and much of what I am about to say comes from that organisation.  In the context of regulation, I share fully all the points that have been made about deregulation but for the record, there were 22,964 licences in existence in December 2012, which equates to one licence for every 200 of the country's population.  In the case of Dublin, it equates to one licence for every 103 members of the population, as opposed to the position in County Tipperary, where there is one licence for every 557 members of the population.</p> <p>The representatives suggested that there should be a strategy in existence for the provision of licences on the basis of the current population within each county and that perhaps might go towards explaining why the service can be poor to customers in certain geographic locations.  The taxi alliance argues that it would make more sense for taxi drivers to operate within one county only, and that it should be enforced strongly.  They also make a point about the split on licences between the different categories.  The Minister will have an opinion on it.  They again refer to Tipperary for obvious reasons.  There are 212 hackney licences there compared with 36 taxi licences, and they say it does not seem to be correct.  They recommend that the situation would be examined and that a strategy would be developed before the non-transferability of licences comes into effect so that licences can be purchased for those areas where there is a lack of them, especially in those circumstances where a taxi driver suffers from a long-term illness or death.</p><p>The final point is a stark one, namely, that the Dublin commuter belt accounts for 74% of all taxi licences.  If one includes the cities of Galway, Cork and Limerick, they equate to 89% of all taxi licences across the country.  I am inclined to sympathise with the view of taxi drivers that it is not a fair distribution to the other 16 counties and goes some way to explaining why there is so much illegal taxi activity, which is the point I tried to make on Second Stage.  Illegal activity is taking place as much in rural areas as in urban areas.  I am curious to hear whether the Minister of State has any comments to make in the context of the debate so far.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.223" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="17:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200027#AA00200"><p>Could I add something?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.224" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="17:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200027#AA00300"><p>The Senator will be able to contribute again if he wishes.  I will allow him to speak if it is a short contribution.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.225" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="17:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200027#AA00400"><p>Yes, it is very short.  Far be it from me to chide colleagues who wander, because I am noted for it myself, but a number of contributors have wandered from the essential crux of the amendment, which seems to me to be simply that Senator Barrett objects on a sound democratic principle to the use of a regulation to overrule a judge of the High Court or Supreme Court.  That is a very important point.  It does not relate to whether taxis are available in Laois or Longford.  It relates to the point of democracy and the role of the Oireachtas as opposed to the role of the Judiciary.  Having heard what Senator Barrett said, there may well be constitutional obstacles to any Government purporting to overrule by regulation a decision of the court.  I am grateful to you, a Leas-Chathaoirligh, for giving me the opportunity to speak because I would like to hear the Minister of State address the point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.226" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="17:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200027#AA00500"><p>Amendment No. 5 refers to regulations concerning the issue of licences for wheelchair accessible vehicles, WAVs, only.  The restriction of the grant of new licences to WAVs seeks to ensure that the proportion of such vehicles in the overall fleet is increased.  I am sure we all want that.  The National Transport Authority, NTA, is now considering further measures to promote the use of such vehicles.  For the present, it is appropriate to maintain the existing restriction on new licences.  Therefore, I cannot accept the amendment.</p><p>The statutory instrument was introduced by the Commission for Taxi Regulation under the powers conferred on it under the 2003 Act.  It has never been challenged but it has been judged that it is not a quantitative restriction because new licences are being issued.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.227" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="17:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200027#AA00600"><p>The Minister of State is being disingenuous.  He is erecting a huge barrier to new entrants by requiring that they must have a wheelchair accessible vehicle.  He and his officials know that.  It is a <i>de facto</i> barrier to entry which the High Court told the Department not to do.  That is a serious step.  I will vote against the measure.  We should not be asked to undermine High Court decisions.  The Minister of State knows it is a barrier to entry.  His officials should know that also.  It is massively more expensive to put most of the burden of catering for wheelchairs on new entrants rather than incumbents.  It is discrimination.  The manner in which the officials have operated is cynical.  As they could not say they would ban new entrants outright they just required them to take on the charitable cause which we all share of providing for disabled people.  That is a barrier to entry.</p><p>  In response to the question by my good friend, Senator Conway, on why Nassau Street is awash with taxis on Saturdays, it is because 85% of business takes place between Thursday and Saturday.</p> <p>Why do some counties have more taxis than others?  Presumably that is related to demand but when we opened up the market, the increase in taxi numbers was far greater outside Dublin so the situation beforehand must have been really confined in country areas.  That is why taxi drivers want to restore the situation where the taxi licence would again be worth €100,000, and it would be wrong of the Government to assist in that in any way.</p><p>We are before the troika, trying to make the sheltered sectors of this economy competitive, and invariably a Department is interfering to reduce competition.  What is next?  Will we tell people they cannot open a new shop because there is a surplus of shops?  This is a business for the self-employed that people have entered and left.  Professor Gorecki believes the adjustment is substantially complete so we do not need the NTA or the Department putting up barriers to new entrants, particularly when they have been asked not to do so in a decision of the High Court.  This is an illegal request being made in the Houses by the Minister of State and Department.  I will not be withdrawing this amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.229" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="17:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200028#BB00200"><p>Once again the Minister of State has signally failed to address the point of principle involved.  He has invoked the natural sympathy for wheelchair occupants and while one has every identification with them - I avoid the word "sympathy" because it is patronising - this is a red herring.  Senator Barrett made the point effectively; we are attempting to overturn the judgments of the highest courts in the land by ministerial regulation.  That is not appropriate and that is the principle, no matter if it is to do with whaling and harpoons or public lavatories.  It should not be done, it is not good practice, it is not democratic and it is not contemplated by the Constitution.  Senator Barrett has said it is illegal and I am convinced.  Governments, however, get away with whatever they can, legal or not.  It is the purpose and function of this House to stand up and point out when something is wrong.  Perhaps the Minister of State might deal with that principle because he has not dealt with it so far.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.230" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="17:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200028#BB00300"><p>I thought I had dealt with it.  I said clearly that it is not a quantitative restriction and that is why there is provision for wheelchair accessible vehicles, WAVs.  The National Transport Authority has facilitated and looked at different grant forms to provide more vehicles into the marketplace.  We must get more vehicles like these into the marketplace and it should be the number one priority.  I am not using that as an excuse either and I object to that type of language being used.</p><p>As Senator Barrett said, the criteria for such vehicles are onerous due to cost and higher specifications.  The NTA is looking at those specifications to create a lower cost entry level for such vehicles.  We must address the issue quickly and this mechanism goes some way towards that.  It is something those who use such vehicles feel strongly about.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.231" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="17:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200028#BB00400"><p>I am pressing the amendment because of the level of cynicism here where wheelchair users are being invoked for 1% of vehicles to keep new entrants from the other 99% of the market.  That is wrong and contravenes what the High Court said.  It stands economics on its head, it is devious and underhand and I could not possibly withdraw the amendment in those circumstances.  The Minister of State invoked the National Transport Authority but the NTA is always opposed to competition, be it in the air, at airports or with buses.  That is its track record and I am not surprised in the slightest it told the Minister of State to do this.  It is where it is usually wrong in most economic issues.</p> <p>I regret the authority has chosen this backdoor method of trying to reintroduce quantity licensing in the taxi business.  It did not tell the Minister of State when they last met that waiting time reductions arising from the opening of the taxi market were worth €780 million in time savings each year.  The measure also created 20,000 additional jobs which, based on IDA estimates, were worth €250 million as a once-off sum.</p><p>Government policy on the taxi market, which has been a major success, is being undermined, allegedly on the basis that the Minister of State and his officials care more for people in wheelchairs than Senators on this side do, which is nonsense.  Why is the burden being placed on new entrants?  The reason is the Minister of State was told by the incumbents and his officials to take this approach.</p><p>It is shameful and sets a bad precedent to deliberately flout decisions of the High Court.  If the Minister of State does not like the court's decision, he can appeal it to the Supreme Court but he has chosen not to do so.  When representatives of the taxi industry sought a judicial review the decision was upheld, which means the law that one cannot restrict entry to the taxi business under any guise stands.  I am standing by that position in pressing the amendment. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.233/1" nospeaker="true" time="17:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200030#DD00100"><p>Amendment put:</p><p>The Committee divided: Tá, 12; Níl, 24.</p><p>Tellers: Tá, Senators Sean D. Barrett and David Norris; Níl, Senators Paul Coghlan and Susan O'Keeffe.</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.233/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2013-02-12" time="17:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200030#DD00100">
            <divisioncount ayes="12" noes="24" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" vote="aye">Sean Barrett</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" vote="aye">David Cullinane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" vote="aye">Mark Daly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" vote="aye">Terry Leyden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" vote="aye">Marc MacSharry</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" vote="aye">Paschal Mooney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" vote="aye">David Norris</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" vote="aye">Trevor Ó Clochartaigh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1115" vote="aye">Labhrás Ó Murchú</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" vote="aye">Denis O'Donovan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1154" vote="aye">Averil Power</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1155" vote="aye">Kathryn Reilly</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" vote="no">Ivana Bacik</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1121" vote="no">Paul Bradford</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" vote="no">Terry Brennan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" vote="no">Colm Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1114" vote="no">Deirdre Clune</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" vote="no">Eamonn Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" vote="no">Paul Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1124" vote="no">Michael Comiskey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" vote="no">Martin Conway</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" vote="no">Jim D'Arcy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1160" vote="no">Michael D'Arcy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1144" vote="no">Jimmy Harte</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" vote="no">Fidelma Healy Eames</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1173" vote="no">Lorraine Higgins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" vote="no">Caít Keane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" vote="no">John Kelly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" vote="no">Marie Maloney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" vote="no">Mary Moran</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1134" vote="no">Tony Mulcahy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" vote="no">Michael Mullins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" vote="no">Catherine Noone</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" vote="no">Susan O'Keeffe</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" vote="no">Pat O'Neill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1143" vote="no">John Whelan</mpname>
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.233/3" nospeaker="true" time="17:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200030#DD00100"><p>Amendment declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.234" nospeaker="true" time="17:35:00"><p>Section 4 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.235" nospeaker="true" time="17:35:00"><p>Section 5 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.236" nospeaker="true" time="17:35:00"><p>SECTION 6</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.237" nospeaker="true" time="17:35:00"><p>Question proposed: &quot;That section 6 stand part of the Bill.&quot;</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.238" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="17:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200032#FF00100"><p>I welcome the Minister of State back to the House.  I draw Members' attention to-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.239" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="17:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200032#FF00200"><p>Have we dealt with amendment No. 12?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.240" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="17:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200032#FF00300"><p>Senator Barrett is addressing section 6.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.241" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="17:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200032#FF00400"><p>Amendments Nos. 5 and 12 are being taken together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.242" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="17:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200032#FF00500"><p>Amendment No. 5 was disposed of in the last vote.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.243" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="17:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200032#FF00600"><p>Did we pass section 5?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.244" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="17:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200032#FF00700"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.245" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="17:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200032#FF00800"><p>We are on section 6, to which Senator Barrett has indicated his opposition.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.246" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="17:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200032#FF00900"><p>I want to draw the House's attention to subsection (3), which states: "The Minister may make an order specifying a date from which the Garda Síochána shall cease to be the licensing authority to grant licences to drive small public service vehicles for the purposes of this Act."  To give the Minister his due and if I understand correctly, he does not intend to invoke this subsection yet.  However, if the Government's case is that this industry has more than its share of criminality, a suggestion that I disputed when we last debated this Bill, I cannot think of a better set of people to deal with it than gardaí.  I would be reluctant to remove this authority from the Garda to the National Transport Authority, NTA.  If one is concerned about crime, gardaí are the people who know about it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.247" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="17:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200032#FF01000"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.248" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="17:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200032#FF01100"><p>For this reason, I propose that the subsection should not be invoked.  According to the record, the number of complaints has been decreasing and the level of criminality was seriously exaggerated by those making the case.  There was an example of same last week.  It is not an industry inhabited by social welfare frauds, tax dodgers or people with dodgy vehicles.  In fact, it is a quite well behaved industry.  In the speech given to the world conference on transport in Lisbon, Portugal, on 13 July 2010, Ms Kathleen Doyle, the previous regulator, pointed out that the number of prosecutions and complaints had been decreasing.</p><p>The Garda is doing a good job.  The incumbents are trying to build up a head of steam behind the argument that new entrants will be illegal or, as we have heard, from the &quot;wrong&quot; country.  This sector properly resides with An Garda Síochána.  The evidence is that it has been doing a good job.  The industry has often expressed its confidence in the Garda.  In this regard, the Garda has helped the industry to grow from 4,000 or 5,000 vehicles to 27,000 vehicles without a significant increase in criminality.  This is to the credit of the Garda Síochána.  I ask the House to reconsider allowing the Minister to ever make an order to the effect that the Garda is no longer the licensing authority for this part of the economy.  Gardaí know the people and will know whether fears about criminality are justified.  I have confidence in them, for which reason section 6(3) should not proceed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.249" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="17:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200032#FF01200"><p>I support Senator Barrett.  Will the Minister of State explain why the Garda will be withdrawn in this regard?  My understanding is that the taxi industry supports the retention of the Garda in an enforcement role.  Indeed, the Garda has been called upon a number of times, particularly in cities, to sort out difficulties on various taxi ranks.</p><p>The other aspect of this argument is that the current enforcement structure relies on only nine enforcement officers under the Taxi Regulator's office.  Some 2,552 licences must be checked by each enforcement officer, not taking geographical locations into account.  I see some merit in the taxi industry's preference for the Garda to resume ownership of the enforcement regulations, thereby providing an efficient service that would cut out illegal activity.  I am sure that the Minister of State will have had the same experience as Senators.  Throughout all of the discussions with taxi representatives, the mantra has been &quot;Enforcement, enforcement, enforcement&quot;.  This is the industry's main issue with the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.250" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="17:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200032#FF01300"><p>Can the Minister of State lay before the House any evidence to the effect that the performance of the Garda as licensing authority is unsatisfactory?  It might be a compelling argument in defence of his case, but I am unaware of such evidence.</p><p>The Garda, particularly its traffic section, is in constant contact with the taxi industry and other motorists.  This supports the idea that it is an appropriate licensing body.</p><p>It is a natural and almost inevitable force within bureaucracies like the NTA to build a little empire for themselves.  This measure smacks of empire building more than anything else.  We have seen no evidence that the Garda's performance has been unsatisfactory in this regard.  The Garda is most directly in contact with taxi drivers and the rest of the industry.  I am convinced by Senator Barrett on this matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.251" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="17:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200032#FF01400"><p>On Second Stage, I asked the Minister of State to consider employing more people in the regulatory authority to inspect taxi licences.  We debated a Private Member's motion last Wednesday and, today, we voted on a Fianna Fáil amendment to the Order of Business regarding the Garda.  Gardaí have more to do than checking or issuing taxi licences.  In this smart age, the authority can get information from the Garda on someone's record when determining whether to licence that person.  I ask Senator Barrett not to press the matter.  We have debated the Garda enough.  A better use of Garda time would be patrolling, overseeing road traffic and so on to ensure taxi drivers were not breaking the law under the Road Traffic Acts, not inspecting and issuing licences.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.252" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="17:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200032#FF01500"><p>Before I call the Minister of State, I am sure that Members would like to join with me in welcoming a distinguished former Senator and Deputy Leader of the House, Mr. John Dardis, to the Visitors' Gallery.</p><p>I am sure that Members will also join with me in welcoming Dr. Catherine Woteki, Under Secretary for the United States Department of Agriculture, USDA.  She could not visit Ireland at a more opportune time.  I wish her a happy stay for the next few days.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.253" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="17:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200032#FF01600"><p>Section 6 is required to define a licensing authority for the purpose of the Bill.  The section reflects the current situation, whereby the Garda has responsibility for small public service vehicle, SPSV, driver licensing.  This section also allows for a future scenario whereby it is envisaged that the administration of the SPSV driver licensing functions will be transferred to the NTA in line with action No. 5 of the taxi regulatory review report of 2011, which I am sure that all of the Senators have read.</p><p>It is envisaged that the important vetting function will stay with the Garda.  I take Senator O'Neill's comments concerning recent Seanad debates on board.  I will set the scene.  For months on end, I chaired a review committee, membership of which included the Garda.  The Garda was a component of the decision making process as regards the transfer of functions.  There is no issue concerning what the Garda has done historically, nor are we claiming such.</p> <p>We are looking to the future to see where future resources can be best targeted as regards the administration process, which we believe is with the NTA, and enforcement in which the Garda will have a major part to play.  There will be many qualitative enforcement measures which will support enforcement, and the Garda will have a huge role to play in that.  That is the merit for the change being introduced in the legislation.  I cannot accept the Senator's apparent view that the NTA should not have regulatory powers.  The NTA is central to implementing the regulatory requirements and achieving the right balance between consumer interests and the interests of the industry.</p><p>I might add that, from an enforcement point of view, in conjunction with this legislation, I, as the Minister responsible, am working with the NTA and intend to bring in a large number of qualitative measures and improvements in on the street enforcement levels which I accept must be addressed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.255" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="17:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200033#GG00150"><p>I am glad the Minister of State does not intend to invoke that section.  It is a sword of Damocles in that the Garda might be removed from the area.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.256" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="17:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200033#GG00200"><p>It should not be there.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.257" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="17:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200033#GG00300"><p>I may take up the issue on Report Stage.  I will ask the Garda and those in the industry how they feel about this but the history of regulation by the other bodies in the transport sector is highly discriminatory and unsatisfactory.  The members of the Garda are the most trusted public servants in the country; all opinion polls show that.  I will consider the issue for Report Stage but I do not see the case for removing the Garda from the sector.  I will reserve my position until Report Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.258" nospeaker="true" time="17:50:00"><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.259" nospeaker="true" time="17:50:00"><p>SECTION 7</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.260" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="17:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200033#GG00600"><p>I move amendment No. 6:<ul><br />In page 10, between lines 25 and 26, to insert the following subsection:<ul>&quot;(2) The Authority may not make regulations which reintroduce quantity licensing of small public service vehicles.&quot;.</ul></ul>There are many paragraphs, extending to the letter M in subsection 2 and a number of subsections on what the NTA intends to do about licensing and so on.  I want to call a halt to this direction because this is not to be the reintroduction of quantity licensing.  We saw that in the case of the disabled.  There was a court decision that we cannot have quantitative licensing in this sector.  If we eventually add on that everybody who enters the industry must have two-page D categories in terms of taxi driving and so on, we will effectively keep new entrants out of the industry.  I want an undertaking from the Minister of State that it is not his policy to reintroduce quantity licensing because that has been disallowed by the courts on at least four occasions.  That is the purpose of my amendment.  It is also a warning to the National Transport Authority not to go down that road because I believe its natural inclination is to do that, as it does in all the other sectors for which it has responsibility.  It does not understand the way markets operate and I want to make sure that the opinion of this House is communicated to it in that we support the High Court decision that people are allowed to enter this sector.  Some people may not want to use their services but they carry about 80 million passengers a year and are far more important to the public transport system than buses or trains.  It is not up to a quango to make life more difficult for people who want to enter an industry which added 20,000 jobs since it was deregulated.  I want to make sure of that because the natural inclination of bureaucracies is to end up with a situation where new entrants, vital for the efficiency of the sector, will effectively be banned by red tape.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.261" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="17:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200033#GG00700"><p>I assume in my innocence that the Minister of State will accept this amendment.  I base this on the fact that after a certain amount of obfuscation and prevarication he eventually came around, in response to our arguments about the superiority of judgments of the court and the impropriety that tended to overrule them by regulations, to say that this was a matter of qualitative rather than quantitative measures.  That would lead one to conclude that he accepted that quantitative measures were wrong, imprudent and definitely illegal.  I do not think he should have too much difficulty in absorbing this specific amendment.  I look forward to his enthusiastic acclamation of Senator Barrett's amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.262" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="17:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200033#GG00800"><p>How could one resist that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.263" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="17:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200033#GG00900"><p>The Minister of State cannot; he should say "Yes" to it and we can then move on.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.264" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="17:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200033#GG01000"><p>Unfortunately, I cannot.  I will not be agreeing to the amendment.  The matter of quantitative controls in the taxi market was already addressed in the courts, as we previously discussed, and the outcome was the liberalisation of the taxi market.  The Bill does not provide for any quantitative restrictions on the taxi market in line with the view taken by the review group in the Taxi Regulation Review Report 2011, which I chaired, which recommends that the future approach to the regulation of the SPSV market should involve qualitative improvements to standards and the enforcement of the regulations.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.265" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="17:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200033#GG01100"><p>The Minister of State is rejecting it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.266" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="17:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200033#GG01200"><p>When there are paragraphs extending to the letter M and a few subsections on this area and we are nearly running out of letters in the alphabet to cover measures, my fear is that the bureaucrats are attempting to re-regulate this sector by the backdoor.  I am disappointed that the Minister of State cannot give an undertaking on that.  I am sure this is one of the areas the troika is looking at because it is seriously concerned that the Government is building sheltered sectors in this economy which seriously infringe the ability of the rest of the economy to operate.  That is why we are in our current state and unemployment has increased from 4.8% to 14.8%.  The Minister of State feels unable to give any commitment that this will always be a competitive, contestable industry.  That is all we ask him to do to give a commitment that neither he nor his officials or any of the lobby groups who were in and out of his Department have any intention reintroduce quantity licensing.  I thought he would be glad to give that undertaking but regrettably he is not.</p><p>  I am sure this will not end here.  If there is a build-up of restrictive practices and all the sheltered sectors carry on like this and form clientless relationships with bureaucracies, it will damage the overall Irish economy.  I cannot see why it is such a blow to the Minister of State to have to say that he is favour of the amendment I propose and that he has no intention of introducing quantity licensing.  When we examine the situation, particularly in terms of the Public Transport Regulation Act 2009, many bogus reasons were given by the Department as to why it does not like competition.  It is easy to disprove them but the Department remains committed to preventing competition and will invent the safety argument, one of its favourites.</p><p>  I regret the Minister of State is unwilling to nail his colours to the mast, which economists would advocate and which the High Court has told him to do but the record will speak for itself.  I am sure the IMF and the Competition Authority will note that we could not get an undertaking out of the Minister of State that he will not be influenced by the incumbents to introduce more and more regulations which will have the <i>de facto </i>effect of preventing new entrants who, as we said, are vital for the efficiency of any sector.  Paragraphs (<i>a</i>) to (<i>m</i>) comprise the list he has today and yet he seeks powers to bring in more of them.  They are anti-competitive measures.  The consumer benefits of them are never evaluated.  We know what were the consumer benefits of opening up the market, namely, &#8364;70 million to &#8364;80 million worth of time savings and &#8364;250 million worth in terms of 20,000 new jobs.  They do not count in the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport.  I believe when the Goodbody report was discussed at the transport committee it was disputed.  The report is based on the soundest of economics.  This was a decision by the courts which was hugely beneficial to society and it is being steadily picked at in measures like the one we are opposing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.267" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="17:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200033#GG01300"><p>Once again I must strongly support Senator Barrett.  He has dealt with the economic reasons and I will address myself to what I see as the political reasons.  If these are not controlled it will not be only the Government that will introduce quantity licensing.</p> <p>This is to try to prevent the authority, which lacks the weight or democratic impact of the Government, from making regulations that introduce quantity licensing.</p><p>The Minister of State said the Government will not introduce quantity licensing.  He had made it clear that it is not Government policy.  Nothing in Senator Barrett's amendment, therefore, comes into conflict with the stated policy the Minister of State has reiterated to the House.  Senator Barrett's amendment merely restates a decision of the High Court, supported by the results of a judicial review and by what the Minister of State has told the House today is Government policy.  I do not see there is any difficulty and I am at a loss to understand why the Minister of State cannot accept the amendment.  Senator Barrett's position is clearly aligned with all of those elements and that makes for good government.  I compliment him on producing the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.269" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="18:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200034#HH00200"><p>I have very little to repeat, except to say there is no need for this in legislation.  The market has been fully liberalised, as has already been stated.  I can understand and appreciate the free marketeer approach.  There must be a balance between a <i>laissez-faire</i> approach to regulation, where one believes that all forms of regulation are bad, and establishing a body that can ensure that standards of safety, service provision and everything else, are maintained.  I do not get that sense of balance from Senator Barrett in many of his contributions today on the taxi industry.  This industry needs to change fundamentally.  I am a huge supporter of the taxi industry.  Many people in it cannot make a living.  They need to be supported with regard to standards and to have effective legislation behind that.  While the free marketeer approach, with which Senator Barrett is very much in tune, is something I understand and appreciate, to go so far with a <i>laissez-faire</i> approach as not to require certain standards through regulation is something I cannot accept.  Given the country's current environment, we should have learnt that lesson.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.270" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="18:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200034#HH00300"><p>I am now completely confused.  The Minister of State, having stalwartly maintained that the Government would not introduce quantity licensing, went off on a tangent about Senator Barrett's ideological views on <i>laissez-faire</i> economics and all the rest of it.  If Senator Barrett has those views, I certainly do not share them.  The Minister of State then appeared to be making an argument for quantity licensing, having said he recognised the fact it was illegal.  I do not know what else he could have been doing except making that argument.  The record of the House will show he was at least tending in that direction.  I am left completely bemused.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.271" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="18:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200034#HH00400"><p>When the Minister of State rejected the earlier amendment on SI 250 of 2010, which was using a qualitative argument to restrict new entrants by confining them to 1% of the market, he showed his true colours.  We sought an undertaking that this would not happen again.  The industry is now organised to keep new entrants out.  In tabling this amendment, we sought an undertaking that would not happen.  That is what the High Court intended.  The Minister of State and his officials are here every day.  Parliament is not here every day.  That is why we sought this undertaking.  We are not getting it, and I regret that.</p><p>The Minister of State's arguments have all been heard before.  Are the people satisfied?  They are.  There were 377 complaints to the regulator, which is one tenth of the number of citizens who wrote to the Ombudsman complaining about public servants.  As a percentage of 70 million or 80 million taxi journeys, that number is minuscule.</p><p>The Government has built up a problem which requires a response, allegedly on behalf of quality licensing.  It will not be worth a hill of beans in the end.  Bernard Feeney of Goodbody Economic Consultants looked at the issue of safety.  The insurance rate for taxis, per vehicle mile, is the same as for other vehicles.  The Aunt Sally arguments from the NTA about the need for regulation do not compare with the €780 million worth of time savings benefits and the €250 million worth of jobs created as a result of opening up the market.  I wish official Ireland would accept that it has been a success and stop messing with it.  That is all we ask in the amendment.</p><p>Sometimes we get economic policy right.  I agree with the Minister of State that many of our economic policies are wrong.  In fact, I wonder why some of the provisions against people operating taxis do not apply to bankers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.272" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="18:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200034#HH00500"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.273" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="18:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200034#HH00600"><p>They did &#8364;64 billion worth of damage.  Taxi drivers did &#8364;750 million a year worth of time savings and &#8364;250 million worth of job creation but are continually faced with bureaucrats meddling, as in paragraphs (<i>a</i>) to (<i>m</i>) of this section, and they will not even give the guarantee.  The bureaucrats say they are on the side of the consumer.  They are not setting out to ban new entrants, but that is what they are doing.  Everyone in Irish economics knows that is what they are doing.  The lawyers will know it, when they read the account of what is happening here today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.274" nospeaker="true" time="18:00:00"><p>Amendment put and declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.275" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="18:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200034#HH00800"><p>Amendments Nos. 7, 10, 44 and 47 are related and may be discussed together, by agreement.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.276" nospeaker="true" time="18:00:00"><p>Government amendment No. 7:
In page 11, subsection (2)(l)(ii), line 22, after &#8220;rental&#8221; to insert &#8220;or leasing&#8221;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.277" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="18:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200034#HH01000"><p>Amendment No. 7, to section 7, is to ensure vehicles or equipment under leasing arrangements are included in any regulations made by the NTA under subsection (2) which concerns restrictions on the rental of small public service vehicles, SPSVs.  Similarly, amendment No. 10, which replaces subsection (6), prohibits the contravention of restrictions on rental and leasing arrangements for vehicles and equipment.  A new subsection (7) provides for the offence in this regard.  Amendments Nos. 44 and 47, to sections 30 and 31, respectively, are consequential on the offence under subsection (7), being a specified demerit offence for the purposes of Part 5.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.278" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="18:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200034#HH01100"><p>What is the thinking behind the amendments?  Might it have something to do with the fact that the industry itself has said there is a real problem of illegal taxi drivers?  Representatives of the Taxi Alliance of Ireland to whom I have spoken estimate that as many as 5,000 illegal taxi drivers are operating in this jurisdiction.  I understand some of these illegal drivers operate by using the vehicles of existing licenceholders.  Are these amendments attempting to address this problem?  It had been my intention to wait and speak on the section and cite the wider list of regulations.  I wonder, however, if these amendments are an attempt to address the issue of illegal taxi drivers.  Does the Minister have any views on this?  Is this the thinking behind the amendments?</p><p>I share Senator Barrett's free market views in this regard and would not wish to be identified with any restriction on entry into the market, particularly when people are looking for jobs.  Nevertheless, there must be regulation.  The Minister of State himself mentioned the need for balance.  If there is a real problem of illegal taxi drivers and if they are in such numbers, they will not be subject to normal taxi driver regulations on knowledge of where they are operating, for example, and all of the issues we talked about on Second Stage.</p><p>This takes us back to the view of the Taxi Alliance of Ireland on enforcement.  I do not suggest that we should prevent people getting involved in the industry, but what about those who are currently in the industry and those who wish to enter the industry legitimately and conform with the regulations currently in place?  It appears to me that the Government, in these amendments and in the section, is attempting to address the problem of illegal taxi drivers.</p> <p>That is why I asked whether the Minister of State would clarify his reasons for tabling these amendments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.280" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="18:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200035#JJ00200"><p>The amendments deal with the issues referred to by the Senator in the rental market.  The market needs to change.  Members will have watched the television programmes and read newspaper articles about the way in which the rental market developed willy nilly.  A licence holder could rent out his or her plate and the person driving the car did not have to ensure standards were maintained.  A full package will be put in place under the legislation for those operating in the rental market.  There is a requirement for such a market for many different reasons but standards must be maintained by those renting vehicles under these provisions.  For instance, they will not only rent out the car but they will be responsible for the insurance, signage and equipment in the car.  That is the background to this and we want to ensure a standard is maintained into the future.  Many of the organisations that made submissions to the review committee put this issue at the top of the agenda.  This also drifts into the area of legal requirements.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.281" nospeaker="true" time="18:10:00"><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.282" nospeaker="true" time="18:10:00"><p>Government amendment No. 8:
In page 11, subsection (2), between lines 23 and 24, to insert the following:&#8220;(m) in the case of an application by a company for a licence, the requirement to provide to the Authority details of any director, shadow director, manager, secretary, member entered in the register of the company, other officer or employee of the company, any person who has control of the company or any person purporting to act in that capacity;&#8221;</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.283" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="18:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200035#JJ00500"><p>Taxi licences are held in company names and provision for the grant of further licences to companies is contained in section 9(7).  All applicants for licences are required to meet the suitability requirements set out in section 10.  Section 10(2)(e) contains specific measures relating to the suitability of members of companies.  This technical amendment allows the NTA to make licensing regulations in the case of an application by a company to require that the company provides to the authority details concerning the membership, etc., of the company to ensure the suitability assessment under section 10 can be applied.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.284" nospeaker="true" time="18:10:00"><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.285" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="18:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200035#JJ00700"><p>I move amendment No. 9:<ul><br />In page 11, subsection (4), lines 37 and 38, to delete paragraphs (<i>b</i>) and (<i>c</i>)</ul>The amendment seeks to delete sections 7(4)(<i>b</i>) and 7(4)(<i>c</i>).  The authority in making regulations under these subsections may set different requirements on conditions for different circumstances and different areas of the State.  The High Court applies in all areas of the State and it deregulated the sector.  Why is the Government seeking different regulations in different areas of State?  It is a unitary country and I cannot understand why one would wish to partition it again, as this section proposes.  The High Court's jurisdiction operates in all 26 counties.  Allowing a quango to decide what are the different circumstances is an attempt again to reintroduce quantity licensing through the back door and I have heard no case mentioned as to why that should be necessary.  The reintroduction of area licensing would be utterly contradictory to a High Court decision, which has been shown to have generated &#8364;780 million in time saving benefits per annum by Goodbodys Economic Consultants and &#8364;250 million in job creation according to IDA estimates.  I do not know why any State body should seek to undermine that by saying it wants different rules in different areas of the State.</p><p>  When taxies were controlled by local authorities, we made it a national issue because some local authorities were stingier than others in allowing new entrants.  According to the affidavits and the legislation arising from deregulation, the highest price for taxi licences were in Ennis where American tourists were brought to Shannon Airport and Killarney while Dublin prices were high as well.  Why is the Minister of State returning to area licensing without even the slightest discussion of why we would wish to set aside a High Court decision in this regard yet again?</p><p>  National regulations were decided upon and implemented by the Commission on Taxi Regulation.  Area licensing could only be introduced on foot of a long discussion and not through a subsection such as this.  I would take a great deal of convincing that there is a case for its reintroduction.  It was abolished for good reasons, one of which was to ensure a greater supply of taxis in areas where local authorities had driven up the rental value of taxi plates.  There will always be pressure from those who hold the licences to restrict entry, which would make the licences more valuable.  Revisiting this under area licensing contradicts what the Minister of State has said throughout the debate.  I do not know why this provision is included and I am trying to get it taken out.  I look forward to what he has to say on the virtues, which seem to be small, of area licensing of the taxi sector.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.286" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="18:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200035#JJ00800"><p>I invite the Minister of State to enlighten the House as to what the nature of the different circumstances would entail under section 7(4)(b).  That would help us to make up our minds on that.  With regard to section 7(4)(c), what are the different areas of the State?  Will it be province by province, county by county or city by city?  What would be the intrinsic characteristics of those different areas to justify different treatment?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.287" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="18:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200035#JJ00900"><p>I cannot agree to amendment No. 9.  It allows the NTA to make regulations setting different requirements and conditions relating to different categories and classes of vehicles, SPS drivers and licences as well as-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.288" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="18:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200035#JJ01000"><p>My amendment refers to different circumstances.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.289" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="18:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200035#JJ01100"><p>I understand that.  Section 7(4)(b) enables the NTA to make regulations, if needed, to address issues such as drivers operating in the voluntary sector or in other circumstances while section 7(4)(c) enables the authority to make regulations to address the area restrictions that currently exist in regard to standing or plying for hire.  Some of the issues relate to making provisions to distinguish between taxi and hackney requirements, to deal with the voluntary sector and to address the proposal that emerged distinctively from the review committee to examine the provision of a rural hackney licence in the future.  It has not come into play yet but it is being examined because there are no taxis in certain areas of the country.  In some cases, there is no market but this provision makes it possible for us to consider whether we can provide for such a need in remote rural areas.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.290" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="18:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200035#JJ01200"><p>We could go through this county by county.  First in an open market, if nobody in county X wants to get a taxi, it will not be supplied there. However, before we deregulated, the non-Dublin share of the taxi fleet was 35%.  It then reduced to 32% but, by 2008, it had increased to 41%.  The increase in taxi numbers outside Dublin, therefore, has been greater than elsewhere.  I do not know what market failure is being addressed here.  The market is open to enter unlike in other transport markets such as that for bus services which the Department restricts.  We even have had verbal undertakings from the Minister of State that he would not impose quantitative restrictions on entry but now he is seeking the restoration of area licensing.  I am not at all persuaded by the arguments.</p> <p>That was abolished.  Following its establishment in 2003, one of the first decisions of the Commission for Taxi Regulation was to introduce a system of national licensing which operated throughout the jurisdiction.  I do not see the case that is being made here.  I will oppose the Minister of State on that section.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.292" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="18:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200036#KK00200"><p>I raised the issue previously, and I had a private word with Senator Sean D. Barrett, but we seem to be at variance on our figures.  I do not for one moment dispute his figures.  He showed me the source of the figures he has just put on the record but the source I have, which is the Taxi Alliance of Ireland, states that 74% of all taxi licences are in Dublin and if the cities of Galway, Cork and Limerick are included, this equates to 89% of all licences.  The Taxi Alliance of Ireland makes the point that this is not a fair distribution for the other 16 counties and it goes some way to explaining why there is so much illegal taxi operation and also, as the Minister of State said, why there is not an adequate taxi service in areas of the country.  There is some variance in the figures.  I do not dispute those provided by Senator Sean D. Barrett but perhaps the Minister of State can clarify the issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.293" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="18:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200036#KK00300"><p>In regard to Senator Sean D. Barrett's amendment, he should take the Minister's words in the spirit in which they were meant in respect of the different circumstances and for different areas of the State.  He is trying to provide for regulation of the taxi industry, especially in remote areas, because the cost of a taxi licence and of putting a vehicle on the road will not be a viable proposition in certain parts of rural Ireland, whereas if the Minister of State under this regulation can give somebody a hackney licence to operate his or her own vehicle or a specially adapted vehicle, at least it gives rural areas a chance of being independent, thereby enabling especially elderly people to go to the shops, rural pubs or the church.  He must accept the spirit of the Minister of State's opposition to the amendment.  I ask the Senator to withdraw amendment No. 9, which seeks the deletion of paragraphs (b) and (c) of subsection (4).  The Minister of State has stated the reasons these paragraphs are included in the Bill.  While the matter can be discussed again on Report Stage, it is important not to have a vote on it now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.294" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="18:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200036#KK00400"><p>I thank my friend, Senator Pat O'Neill, for the proposal to debate it on Report Stage.  The phrase "for different circumstances" is too wide.  The Minister of State clarified the issue and I will support him if he wishes, but I do not know what a court case would make of "in different circumstances".  Although I do not have photographic recall, the formulation of words provided by the Minister of State sounded better than what is set down in the Bill.  Perhaps he might think of that on Report Stage.  In respect of paragraph (c) for different areas of the State, that system was tried and failed.  Suppose somebody makes a case to the Minister or the NTA that county X needs special consideration, and if the licence is granted for county X, it will cater for all the problems mentioned by Senator O'Neill.  Before long, however, the holder of that licence will have a monopoly on it and it then becomes an obstacle to further progress.  That is what happened from 1977 until 2000 and eventually the courts threw them out.</p><p>Rather than create local monopolies to solve a shortage of supply of transport in certain areas, I would prefer to have open competitive tendering rather than give somebody a licence and shut out everybody else.  The reintroduction of area licences, on reflection, is something we would all agree did not work the last time.  It is extremely bad to think of reintroducing it and it will create a value for the licence and piece of paper again.  It provides an inferior service as all of the studies show when area licensing is introduced.  That is why there was such a wave of public opinion through the judges and the courts; I sat in on some of the court cases.  People got fed up because the monopolistic practices of the taxi industry led to an inferior service and restricted developments in other parts of the economy.  </p><p>I do not know who in the Department has become converted back to different area licensing systems in different areas of the State, but I hope they reconsider.  When a national licensing system is in place, people can move.  The country is not very big, it is connected up by motorways and people can see a gap in the market and open up their business there.  Why it should be part of the restrictive licensing system escapes me and it is contrary to our experience and the Minister of State's undertaking not to reintroduce quantity licensing.  It contradicts the High Court judgments as well.  This is a country where the entire industry was deregulated by two High Court decisions.  One cannot differentiate in that way.  To encourage supply one would probably have to go the subsidy route rather than the licensing route.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.295" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="18:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200036#KK00500"><p>As it is now 6.45 p.m. I ask Senator Norris to report progress.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.296" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="18:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200036#KK00600"><p>I will be obedient and report progress.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.297" nospeaker="true" time="18:20:00"><p>Progress reported; Committee to sit again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.298" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="18:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200036#KK00800"><p>When is it proposed to sit again?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.299" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="18:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200036#KK00900"><p>Tomorrow at 10.30 a.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.300" nospeaker="true" time="18:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200036#KK01000">Adjournment Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.301" nospeaker="true" time="18:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200036#KK01100">Rural Transport Scheme</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.302" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="18:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200036#KK01200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State.  The issue I wish to raise concerns the rural transport scheme especially in Kerry.  I understand the 12 months contracts have been shortened to six months and I am concerned as to what will happen when the six month contracts expire.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.303" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="18:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200036#KK01300"><p>The programme for Government commits to maintaining and extending the rural transport programme with other local transport services in as much as that is practicable.</p><p>The Government recognises that this programme, which was launched in 2007 following a pilot project between 2002 and 2007, can play a major role in combatting rural isolation and enhancing the mobility, accessibility and community participation of local people, particularly those at risk of social exclusion.  This year, €9.1333 million is being allocated to the rural transport programme corresponding to some 93% of the 2012 allocation.  This represents only a small decrease at a time when very difficult decisions have had to be taken to curtail or postpone other programmes.  Given the limited resources, it is imperative that we deliver the rural transport programme in an efficient and effective way so as to achieve maximum value for the funding while providing a better service to users.</p><p>At present, 35 community transport groups around the country are being funded under the programme of which Kerry Community Transport Limited is one.  I am advised that Kerry Community Transport Limited carried 145,970 passengers in 2012 and covered over 95 towns and villages.  In the period 2003-12 the company has carried 992,964 passengers.  Kerry Community Transport Limited has been allocated €574,859 rural transport programme funding in 2013.</p><p>I am well aware of the very valuable work done on the ground by these groups in ensuring that the transport needs of their local community are being identified and delivered within available resources.</p> <p>However, given the limited resources and the recommendations of the value-for-money and policy review of the RTP published last year, it is essential that the current delivery mechanisms and structures are examined and revised.</p><p>In particular, the VFM review recommended organisational restructuring of the RTP to achieve greater programme efficiencies and beneficial economies of scale.  The review also recommended that better alignment be established between the 35 RTP groups and local authorities.</p><p>Against this background, in January 2012 the Government approved new arrangements for the development and implementation of integrated local and rural transport services.  These new arrangements are aimed at eliminating service duplication, better targeting of services at those with greatest need and the rationalisation of administrative structures relating to service planning.</p><p>The National Transport Authority, NTA, has been assigned national responsibility for local and rural transport services integration, including the rural transport programme, effective from 1 April 2012, putting such services in a broader transport context.  The NTA is working to implement the recommendations of the VFM review.</p><p>A new high-level committee, the national integrated rural transport, NIRT, committee was established in April 2012, comprising key stakeholders and chaired by the NTA, to oversee and manage a partnership approach to implementing integrated local and rural transport in order to achieve greater synergies, better meet identified transport needs and deliver increased value for money for the Exchequer.  I expect the committee to present a number of projects to me over the coming months which will test the level of integration that can be achieved across school, RTP and health services.  The NTA is currently working with the committee to identify suitable projects.</p><p>I should acknowledge that integration measures are already being undertaken by various RTP groups.  A recent survey conducted by the NTA showed that 28 RTP groups are involved at some level in working groups for integrated transport.  In total, there are 23 working groups in place around the country, of which 19 could be deemed &quot;active working groups&quot;.  As a result, some very valuable groundwork is already being done to raise awareness of transport integration opportunities, to establish working relationships with key stakeholders at local level and in a number of cases, to advance integration projects towards implementation of services on the ground.</p><p>In relation to the revised organisational structures, work is under way to determine the optimal structure for the delivery of rural transport from an efficiency and service perspective.  Discussions are taking place with the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government, the County and City Managers Association and the Rural Transport Network in the context of aligning the new structure with the local authority structure.  Any revised structure must be devised having regard to current policy on the public service, including employment and pay policy.  I am hopeful that agreement on the revised structure will be achieved in the second half of this year.</p><p>I must be clear, however, that the current structures of the RTP are not sustainable if the required efficiencies and savings are to be achieved.  If these are not achieved, then with the limited resources available, services will decline.  I do not want this to be the outcome.</p><p>Pending agreement on the revised structure, the contracts of RTF groups, including the Kerry Community Transport Limited contract, have been extended until end June 2013, with an option to roll the contracts over for a further six months if the restructuring programme has not commenced.  While I can understand and fully appreciate that this creates a level of uncertainty for RTF groups, I am hopeful that the outcome will be a better service delivered more efficiently.  I will work with all involved over the coming months to make any transition as smooth as possible.</p><p>Rural transport is a critical component of public transport services that is vital for the development of a fully inclusive society from both a social and economic perspective.  I assure the Senator of my personal commitment to the continuation of appropriate local transport services to those in need in rural areas, while achieving the best value for money for the Exchequer through more efficient delivery structures and integrated services.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.305" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="18:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200037#LL00200"><p>As the Minister of State will be well aware, the rural transport scheme in Kerry is a vital piece of infrastructure, especially in combatting social isolation for those who are living alone and who, except for the scheme, would be isolated not only from their towns and neighbours, but from those of their own age group whom the rural transport scheme manages to bring together.</p><p>I note the Minister of State's answer.  I am not entirely convinced that those involved in the rural transport scheme in Kerry will be comforted by it.  I note he stated it could roll over if agreement has not been reached, but I fear that there are many issues to be ironed out and that if the rural transport scheme is cut back in any way, those benefiting would suffer the most.  That is something with which we would not be happy and would not support.  All I can say to the Minister of State is that as the situation develops and unfolds, I am sure we will have him back in the Chamber.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.306" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="18:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200037#LL00300"><p>I am well aware of the rural transport issues in Kerry.  As Senator Daly will be well aware, I know the area-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.307" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="18:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200037#LL00400"><p>In particular, Waterville.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.308" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="18:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200037#LL00500"><p>-----including his own town, extremely well.  I also visited the group a year or more ago.</p><p>We are stuck in a structure where there is a value-for-money report of which we need to meet certain requirements.  There is a defined amount of funding.  There is a defined requirement that we must meet given the financial circumstances.</p><p>However, I am a committed supporter of rural transport groups and the voluntary nature of what they do.  I do not know whether there has ever been a Minister who has visited as many of them.  I probably have met them all in some way, whether in their own areas or at the various different conferences which I have always tried to attend.</p><p>I believe we must get to a stage where there is greater joined-up thinking between rural transport, non-acute HSE transport, school transport and voluntary transport.  This, in tandem with the rural hackney licence, which is a proposal that has come out of my Department, would help deal with the transport service issues in isolated rural areas and all of their social and economic consequences.  We are making much progress in that regard.  For instance, we are close to issuing tenders on some school routes as they go to and from villages and towns all over the country serving schools and the buses come back, and head out on the reverse routes, empty.  That is an issue that should have been addressed many years ago and it is being addressed.  For many years, the HSE has been spending quite a quantity of funding on non-acute transport, particularly taxis, and we have a working groups looking at that issue.</p><p>All of this is aligned with work with local authorities to ensure that there is consistency in approach.  For example, there is no point in 15-seat minibuses trying to serve areas where there is not joined-up thinking with the local authorities as regards making provision for those buses to be able to go in those areas.  There are also many other areas with which the local authorities can help.</p><p>Lining up all of those areas together, not alone can we negate the fact that due to the economic circumstances there is not as much funding available, but we can free up and create more services for rural Ireland.  We can also align them with national transport services.  For instance, the national journey planner, which is being launched, includes all of the RTP services so that if persons are using national services with Bus Éireann or private bus companies, they can also connect up with RTP services.  All of this helps to enhance the services in rural Ireland.</p><p>I can assure Senator Daly that he will not get somebody who is dug into this as much as I am.  I am hopeful that in the future we will be able to develop more comprehensive services as a result of the approach that I am trying to bring about.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.309" nospeaker="true" time="18:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200037#LL00600">Hospital Services</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.310" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="18:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200037#LL00700"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Alex White, to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.311" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" speakername="John Kelly" time="18:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200037#LL00800"><p>I also welcome the Minister of State, Deputy White, to the House.</p><p>As he will be aware, prior to the last election the issue of Roscommon hospital and Roscommon accident and emergency department was hot on the agenda in the county of Roscommon.  Prior to the election, there were promises given by the Minister for Health, Deputy Reilly, that the accident and emergency department would be retained under his watch, and everybody in the county bought into that.  Anyone who might have considered supporting me at the time decided that the next likely Minister for Health would not let them down and they supported Fine Gael.</p><p>Subsequently, as the Minister of State will be well aware, the consultants in Roscommon were worried that they were short of staff to ensure that the accident and emergency department operated fully within health and safety guidelines and they wrote to the Department of Health to inform it that they needed extra resources.</p> <p>At this point HIQA got wind of it, and without ever calling to Roscommon County Hospital, shut down the accident and emergency department, more or less implying the consultants stated it was an unsafe place to work.  What we have seen in recent weeks, with regard to the hospital in Kilkenny and extra funding for the accident and emergency department in Wexford General Hospital, has re-opened the debate on the accident and emergency department in Roscommon County Hospital.  The people of Roscommon quite rightly feel aggrieved because instead of HIQA shutting down the accident and emergency department, investment could have been made in it to ensure it was up to the required standard.  We must bear in mind an investment of €17 million was made in recent years in the accident and emergency department in Roscommon County Hospital.  It is state-of-the-art and all that was lacking was the support staff sought by the consultants.</p><p>I had received a commitment from the former CEO of the HSE, Professor Drumm, that the accident and emergency department at Roscommon County Hospital would not be closed and that albeit it was under threat by the previous Administration, there was no question of it being closed.  Although this was a HSE agenda with which Fianna Fáil was going to play ball, I had received a commitment from Professor Drumm that the doors of the accident and emergency department would not close until the advanced paramedics were up and running and had proven to the people of Roscommon over a period of six months that their service was every bit as good as, if not better than, an accident and emergency department.  This promise was also reneged upon.</p><p>I have always stated HIQA was established by the HSE to be its chopping block and everything it has done to date has proven me right.  In recent times HIQA was asked whether a health and safety issue would arise if many HSE front-line staff took early retirement and pressure was put on the services.  It answered that it has no role in staffing, but it had a bloody role in staffing when it came to Roscommon County Hospital accident and emergency department.  It stated it was time to close down the department because the staffing was not there.</p><p>I ask the Minister of State to relay back to the Minister, Deputy Reilly, that at this late stage he should consider putting in place a stabilisation unit in the accident and emergency department at Roscommon County Hospital so people in the area who have heart attacks, strokes or accidents can be dealt with, stabilised and moved to an appropriate hospital.  At least they would know there was something behind the doors and would feel safe at night if something unforeseen happened.  People feel let down.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.313" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1024" speakername="Alex White" time="18:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200038#MM00200"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this issue.  In the notice for this Adjournment debate, the Senator used the phrase the "most appropriate hospital" for treatment of those serious conditions which he described and I also note his appreciation that transfer to such facilities is essential.  One of the key functions of pre-hospital emergency care is stabilisation.  On arrival at an incident, paramedics and advanced paramedics assess, treat and stabilise the patient, prior to transporting him or her to the most appropriate, which is not necessarily the closest, facility.  This treatment continues during transit.</p><p>Given this and the fact these types of patient, in particular those suffering cardiac arrest and stroke, are time-critical - which the Senator emphasised and was correct to do so - there is no clinical value in diverting to a stabilisation unit before continuing to a level 3 or 4 hospital, when stabilisation has already been done by the ambulance crew.  It is worth noting also that a bypass protocol, diverting ambulances to level 3 and 4 hospitals for life-threatening cardiac, respiratory and other serious conditions was put in place for Roscommon County Hospital before the emergency department was closed in 2011, in line with national clinical care protocols for best practice and safe management of a patient with a heart attack or stroke.  These protocols require such patients to be treated in a level 3 or 4 hospital as a level 2 hospital does not have a critical care unit.</p><p>Accident victims should only be managed in a hospital with a full emergency department with the necessary available acute care backup, including ICU.  The essence is that patients should go to the hospital best able to treat them.  This is particularly important for heart attack and stroke victims whose survival rate and long-term prognosis is dependent on how quickly they reach an appropriate hospital.</p><p>None of the national clinical care programmes envisages the development of &quot;stabilisation units&quot; in model 2 hospitals.  It is debatable whether these would improve outcomes for patients or whether they would actually delay them from reaching the necessary level of care in an appropriate facility with the necessary clinical expertise and equipment to fully meet their needs.  Having said that, I and the Minister for Health acknowledge that Roscommon County Hospital is leading the way by demonstrating the range of services that can be developed in a smaller hospital.  In July 2011, Roscommon County Hospital commenced a process of reconfiguring services in line with HIQA recommendations.  I respectfully disagree with the Senator's description of HIQA as a chopping block for the HSE.  HIQA does important expert work through its role in our health services and is a very important institution.  It is also a requirement for excellent health services that we have a body such as HIQA doing the type of work it does.</p><p>Roscommon County Hospital now has a medical assessment unit that is open from 9 a.m. to 5 p.m. from Monday to Friday for the assessment of medical patients who are referred by GPs, after initial phone triage with one of the medical consultants to ensure the medical assessment unit is the appropriate care pathway for the patient.  In addition, it has an urgent care centre open 8 a.m. to 8 p.m., 7 days a week, which deals with minor injuries and trauma, as the Senator is well aware.  Developments in 2012 include plastic and reconstructive surgery, sleep studies, urology services, a radiology upgrade, a newly-developed endoscopy suite, dental service, nurse prescribing and re-accreditation for student nurse training.</p><p>Roscommon County Hospital played a key role in the Galway Roscommon hospital group, with more than 520 endoscopy procedures transferred from Galway to Roscommon.  Future plans for Roscommon County Hospital will see increases in elective inpatient care, in particular in endoscopy, plans for which are well advanced with design agreed, site identified, tender documents complete, funding secured and awaiting planning permission.  Roscommon County Hospital is an excellent example of delivering appropriate care in the appropriate setting to maximise patient safety and resources.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.314" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" speakername="John Kelly" time="18:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200038#MM00300"><p>I expected nothing from the Department other than the response given by the Minister of State, because it appears it has a total reluctance to revisit the issue which is so important to the people of Roscommon, bearing in mind Roscommon County Hospital was always considered by virtue of the county's rural nature to be a special case.  I also note that in his response the Minister of State said a stabilisation unit was debatable.  This means it is unclear and that the Department does not know whether it is the right or wrong thing to do, no more than 45 years ago when the Government thought if we took up our train tracks we would never need them again but now we are putting them back down.  The Minister of State said Roscommon County Hospital is leading the way.  No matter what is put into Roscommon County Hospital which leads the way, the people of Roscommon want an accident and emergency department.  This is all they want.  I will not let this issue go and I hope Minister of State will relate this to the Minister, Deputy Reilly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.315" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1024" speakername="Alex White" time="18:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200038#MM00400"><p>I cannot state the matter any further than I have.  I understand the Senator's concern and he has been to the fore on this question and makes his case well, as he has done in the past.  Stabilisation is required to be done at an early pre-hospital emergency care stage, and to the extent to which stabilisation is properly done one then looks for the most appropriate facility for the patient.  In these circumstances it does not follow that the nearest hospital is the most appropriate.  It depends on a clinical assessment.  If stabilisation has already been completed it would not be appropriate for a stabilisation unit to be placed in a hospital, as the job can be done at the pre-hospital emergency stage after which the patient goes to hospital.  I take the points raised by the Senator.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.316" nospeaker="true" time="18:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200039#NN00100">Schools Building Projects Status</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.317" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="18:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200039#NN00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State at the Department of Education and Skills to the House and I call on Senator Moran to commence.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.318" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" speakername="Mary Moran" time="18:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200039#NN00300"><p>I wish to express my sympathy on the death of former Fianna Fáil Senator Jimmy Mulroy who served from 1987 to 1989.  He sadly passed away this afternoon.  As a colleague from County Louth I would like to express my sympathy.</p><p>  I welcome the Minister of State here.  I wish to raise the matter of a primary school in Dundalk who first applied for an extension 20 years ago.  Finally, in 2009 it was added to the Department's list for an extension and the school has already completed stage 1 of the plans for the extension to the Department's satisfaction.  </p><p>  The school personnel, board of management, parents, parents' council, teachers and pupils have reported their dismay to me after they were advised earlier in the year, by letter, that their school had not been included in the five year plan for school extensions and have no guarantee that the project will be completed.  I have many years of teaching experience.  I have taught in old schools, new schools and in several schools that were hundreds of years old.  I can assure the Minister of State that in my experience the environment in which a child is taught is vital to his or her learning experience.</p><p>  The school building to which I refer is several hundred years old.  While the principal and the staff do their utmost to brighten up the classrooms and the best that they can, I know from visiting the school that their job is made much more difficult because of the current state of the building and their limited space.  I find it very difficult to comprehend that in 2013 a school which has no staffroom, no computer room, no staff toilet and no resource room can justifiably be excluded from the Department's list and that they have no guarantee when they will get a badly needed extension.</p><p>  It must be recognised that all schools are vying for students now.  Every school holds an open day to attract students and the numbers of pupils dictates the number of teachers required.  The state of the school is detrimental to its bid to attract pupils to the school because it is not on the same playing field as other schools who have been granted extensions and have the resources that they need.  The school has two classrooms and three prefabs which have greatly reduced the play area.  Despite this there is another building on the site which is hundreds of years old and has now gone into total disrepair.  It is dilapidated.  In my opinion it would have been better to use the dilapidated building rather than pay the astronomical cost to install prefabs.  I appreciate that is not the fault of the present Government and that the prefabs have been <i>in situ</i> for years.  I acknowledge that the Minister for Education has done a great job on ensuring that prefabs are being replaced.</p><p>  On my last visit to the school I had to conduct my meeting with the principal in the schoolyard.  As a teacher I found that unbelievable.  I had to meet her in the schoolyard as all of the classroom space was occupied.  When it began to rain we had to conclude our meeting in her car.  If one read about this in the 1940s and 1950s one would wonder what was going on.  I was dismayed when the principal told me that this is what happens when she needs to conduct meetings and resource teaching is taking place because the school does not have a resource room.  I commend the principal and her staff who do an exceptional job with limited resources.  </p><p>  The school is significant because it caters for a diversity of religions.  As a parent I feel that parents and pupils deserve the right to send their child to a school which they feel caters to their religious preference.  I am concerned that the lack of facilities available at the school could deter parents from sending their children to it.  I ask the Minister of State to convey my concerns to the Minister.  I also ask that the Minister visits the school in Dundalk and reassesses his decision in order to give all children of all religions equal facilities and equal access to education.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.319" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1042" speakername="Ciarán Cannon" time="18:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200039#NN00400"><p>I am taking this Adjournment matter on behalf of my colleague, Deputy Ruairí Quinn, Minister for Education and Skills.</p><p>I thank the Senator for raising the matter of the building project for Dún Dealgan national school, Dundalk, County Louth, as it provides me with the opportunity to outline to the Seanad the Government's strategy for capital investment in education projects over the next five years and to clarify the current position of the project.</p><p>I shall first set out the context within which decisions have been taken and in which the meeting of accommodation needs of schools must be considered over the coming years.  Overall enrolment figures are expected to grow by around 70,000 students between 2012 and 2018 - by over 25,000 at post-primary and 45,000 at primary level.  Post-primary level enrolment is expected to continue to rise until at least the year 2024.  In order to meet the needs of our growing population of school going children, the Department must establish new schools as well as extending or replacing a number of existing schools in areas where demographic growth has been identified.  The delivery of these new schools, together with extension projects to meet future demand, will be the main focus of the Department's capital budget for the coming years.</p><p>The five year programme was announced in March 2012.  It will provide over 100,000 permanent school places, of which over 80,000 will be new school places.  The remainder will involve the replacement of temporary or unsatisfactory accommodation.  The project for Dún Dealgan national school entails the construction of an extension to the existing school of approximately 495  sq. m plus associated refurbishment and site works.  The school is a four teacher school which has seen enrolments remain relatively consistent over recent years with 87 pupils enrolled in 2000-01 and 96 pupils in the current school year.  The school has also received sanctions amounting to €175,000 under various summer works grants over that period.</p><p>The project is at an early stage of architectural planning.  The project design team was appointed in early 2012 and the board of management was authorised to commence architectural planning.  The stage 1 report, which is the initial sketch design stage, was completed and reviewed late last year and the project was authorised to complete stage 2A which is the developed sketch design.  In the approval letter which issued on 1 October 2012 the board of management was informed that: &quot;[A]s this project is not on the 5 year construction programme, the Department would advise the Board of Management against entering into arrangements which are time bound until authorisation is given to proceed to tender following completion of the Stage 2B report&quot;.  My Department is awaiting submission of the stage 2A report from the board of management and its design team.  Due to competing demands on my Department's capital budget imposed by the need to prioritise the limited funding available for the provision of additional school accommodation to meet increasing demographic requirements it was not possible to include the project in the five year construction programme announced earlier this year.  Schools which have not been included in the five year programme but which had previously been announced for initial inclusion in the building programme will continue to be progressed to final planning stages in anticipation of further funds being available to my Department in future years.  The project for Dún Dealgan national school remains available to be considered for progression in that context. </p><p>I thank the Senator for allowing me the opportunity to outline the position and I will pass on her concerns to the Minister. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.320" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="18:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200039#NN00500"><p>I shall allow Senator Moran to ask a brief question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.321" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" speakername="Mary Moran" time="18:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200039#NN00600"><p>I appreciate the Minister of State's comments but he has not given me new information.  He gave me information that I already knew or discovered.  The argument stands because he said that enrolment has remained static.  The enrolment has remained static principally because the school cannot cater for any more students because the buildings are bursting at the seam.  From my experience of other schools, and other schools in Dundalk who deservedly got their projects, this school has been seriously curtailed.  It is a minority religion school.  It has been in Dundalk a long time and has a proud tradition.  I ask that the Minister visit the school and reassesses his decision not to include it in the five year plan.  There is a case for its inclusion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.322" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1042" speakername="Ciarán Cannon" time="18:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200039#NN00700"><p>I suggest that the Senator extend a written invitation to Minister to visit the school.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.323" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" speakername="Mary Moran" time="18:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200039#NN00800"><p>I have done so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.324" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1042" speakername="Ciarán Cannon" time="18:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200039#NN00900"><p>I do not want to give a sense that somehow the pause button has been pressed on development in Dún Dealgan and other schools.  There are a number of schools across the country who are in similar circumstances.  The process whereby they reach the point where they are ready to go to construction will continue.  The school has not been set aside because of the five year programme and the demands being placed on the resources on the Department in completing the five-year programme.</p> <p>These other schools which are outside the programme at present will be progressed to the point at which they are ready to go to construction on the basis that we may be able to look at another iteration of the programme in the years to come or that other funds may arise in circumstances of which we are not aware to allow us to begin that development.</p><p>Let me assure the Senator that the school will be progressed along that parallel process to bring it to the point at which it is ready to go for construction.  However, as I said in my reply, at this point the pressure on the building unit of the Department is to deliver on the five year programme to meet the major demographic challenge of 75,000 new school entrants in the next four to five years.  That is what the unit must respond to at this time and I hope it will get to schools such as Dun Dealgan and others that are in similar situation as soon as possible.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.326" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200040#OO00200">Water and Sewerage Schemes</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.327" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200040#OO00300"><p>I welcome the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government, Deputy Hogan.  Senator Moloney is very excited that the Minister is present to take this matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.328" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Maloney" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200040#OO00400"><p>I am absolutely delighted the Minister is present to deal personally with this issue and did not send anybody else to take his place.  I know I have him plagued about the saga of the Kilcummin sewerage scheme as I raise it with him on the corridors and everywhere I meet him.  This is a very important issue.</p><p>Kilcummin is located just outside Killarney and the saga of the provision of the sewerage scheme is a long and sorry story.  In 2007, the proposed sewerage scheme for Kilcummin was given the green light and funding was provided in conjunction with the Barraduff sewerage scheme.  Tenders were issued and the contractor was selected to carry out the works.  Work started on the Barraduff scheme first.  Along the way problems developed with the contractor which resulted in the Kilcummin part of the scheme being pulled.  This was the start of the problem for the people of Kilcummin.  Nobody knows what happened to the funding that was provided for the Kilcummin scheme.  We cannot get a straight answer to that question in County Kerry.  We do not know whether the funds were returned to the Department.  All we know is that six years later, Kilcummin has no sewerage scheme.</p><p>For the information of members, Kilcummin is the largest parish in Ireland and that is one reason for it having proper facilities to deal with sewerage.  I will outline other reasons for my belief that funding for the Kilcummin sewerage scheme is necessary.  Probably the most important one is that Kilcummin is in the catchment area of Lough Leane and this scheme was listed as a priority in a campaign to tackle pollution in Lough Leane.  Lough Leane is one of the major tourist attractions in Kerry and, as the Minister will appreciate, Killarney is renowned for the beauty of its lakes.  A number of businesses in Kilcummin pay significant rates to the local authority.  One business alone pays more than €10,000 in rates every year.  There is a well established nursing home in Kilcummin.  In 2006, when the current owners took over the nursing home as a going concern, they were advised by the planners in Kerry County Council that a sewerage scheme would be provided.  Since 2006, they have increased their workforce from 26 to 91 staff and they are ready to open a further 16 to 20 beds in the facility and take on another 40 members of staff.  Kerry County Council, however, will not entertain the company providing a further expansion of beds until such time as it upgrades its sewerage scheme.  This has been costed at €100,000 and it simply does not have that money.  The lack of a sewerage scheme is hindering job creation.  There is planning permission for a number of houses, subject to the provision of a sewerage scheme, and many people must look for an extension of their permission as the current permission is due to expire.  As Members will know, extension of planning permission is for a limited period.</p><p>I understand that everything is in order for the Kilcummin sewerage scheme to proceed at Kerry County Council but it must await the approval of funding by the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government.  I hope the Minister has come into the Seanad with good news for me to take back to the people of Kilcummin.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.329" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/967" speakername="Phil Hogan" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200040#OO00500"><p>I thank Senator Moloney for providing the opportunity to clarify the position on Kilcummin sewerage scheme.  As she rightly says, she has made many representations regarding this scheme.</p><p>The Water Services Investment Programme 2010-2013 provides for the development of a comprehensive range of new water services infrastructure in County Kerry.  The programme includes contracts under construction and to commence to the value of more than €92 million in Kerry during the period of the programme.  It also includes a number of schemes in the country to advance through planning.</p><p>Kerry County Council has completed eight schemes or contracts which include sewerage schemes for Firies, Milltown, Farranfore, Rathmore and Barraduff and water supply schemes or contracts in Listowel, Caherciveen and Ardfert.  The council expects that the Scart reservoir contract, which is part of the central regional water supply scheme and the Waterville water and sewerage scheme, will be completed by this summer.  Kerry County Council also expects to go to tender shortly for the sewerage schemes for Ardfert, Ballylongford and Tarbert.  The council is also pressing ahead with its water conservation programme throughout the county.  The Kilcummin sewerage scheme is included in the programme as a scheme to advance through planning during the life of the programme.</p><p>As the Senator mentioned, Kerry County Council awarded a contract for the combined Kilcummin-Barraduff sewerage scheme in 2007 and work commenced on this contract in April 2007.  The contractor at the time, however, was also engaged in construction work on another sewerage scheme, the Milltown sewerage scheme.  As a result, progress on the Kilcummin-Barraduff contract was slow.  In July 2007, the council suspended the contract in accordance with the terms that were set out in it.  The contractor agreed to withdraw from the Kilcummin portion of the contract and resumed work in Barraduff.  As a consequence of the problems, no work was carried out on the Kilcummin scheme.</p><p>Kerry County Council submitted a revised proposal for the Kilcummin sewerage scheme to my Department in December 2009 and in view of the high unit costs associated with providing this scheme, my Department requested the council in May 2010 to review the scope of the scheme.  The council submitted a further proposal to the Department in June 2012.  There are still concerns regarding the unit costs of the scheme and arrangements have been made between my Department and Kerry County Council to meet shortly to discuss this latest proposal.</p><p>I am conscious of the impacts that the discharges from Kilcummin are having on the local environment and on Lough Leane.  I am keen to have these issues resolved and I hope the discussions which will take place between the Department and Kerry County Council will resolve the issue to the benefit of Kilcummin community and I hope, as Senator Moloney has advocated, the scheme will proceed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.330" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Maloney" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200040#OO00600"><p>When will funding be made available for this scheme?  It seems to me from the Minister's response that the issue has gone back to Kerry County Council but according to Kerry County Council everything is in order at its end.  Why has the issue gone back again to Kerry County Council?  The funding was made available and it was accepted.  The Department asked for a revised figures and that was provided.  Now the Department is asking for more discussions on the issue.  Must we wait forever for this scheme as every time the council submits the information, it is asked for revised figures as the unit costs are too high?  Will the Minister give me some indication as to when this sewerage scheme will be provided, because, as I outlined, many business decisions are dependent on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.331" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/967" speakername="Phil Hogan" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013021200040#OO00700"><p>As the Senator will see from my reply under the Water Services Investment Programme 2010-2013 , the question of funding for the Kilcummin scheme was not included; it was to advance through planning only.  I have been conscious of Senator Moloney's representations on this matter and Kerry County Council and the Department's inspectors have not reached agreement on the unit costs of the scheme.  It is up to the technical people in Kerry County Council to convince the Department's inspectorate that this is a viable scheme.  If they reach agreement, we are in a position to look at the funding.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-02-12a.332" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00"><p>The Seanad adjourned at 6.30 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Wednesday, 13 February 2013.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>