<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.4" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Education and Skills to outline the justification for the non-phased closure of St. Thomas&rsquo;s school, Clonshaugh, County Dublin. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Jerry Buttimer of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Education and Skills to outline when work will commence on the new school for Ballintemple national school, County Cork.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Colm Burke of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Culture, Heritage and the Gaeltacht to outline the plans being put in place to mark the significant historical events which occurred in Ireland between 1918 and 1923.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Maria Byrne of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to allow rheumatoid arthritis as a qualifying medical condition under the long-term illness scheme.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Victor Boyhan of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to report on the closure, in January 2017,  of 12 hospital beds at the National Rehabilitation Hospital, D&uacute;n Laoghaire. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Tim Lombard of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Education and Skills to outline the budget and the timescale for the roll out of the schools summer works scheme 2018.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Frank Feighan of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister of State at the Department of Education and Skills with special responsibility for higher education to address the capital funding requirements for St Angela&rsquo;s college in County Sligo in light of increasing student numbers and the consequential demand for additional accommodation.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government to outline the cross-Border measures that are undertaken when implementing emergency co-ordination preparations for, and responses to, adverse weather conditions in Ireland.</blockquote> <p>Of the matters raised by the Senators suitable for discussion, I have selected Senators &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in, Buttimer, Colm Burke and Byrne and they will be taken now.  I regret I had to rule out of order the matter submitted by Senator Boyhan on the ground that it is a repeat of a Commencement Matter raised on 21 February 2018.  The other Senators may give notice on another day of the matters that they wish to raise.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.7" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#A00300">Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.8" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#A00400">School Closures</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#A00500"><p>I thank the Minister of State for taking this debate.  The issue is about St. Thomas's special school in Clonshaugh.  It is a small school, with a small enrolment, and a school that nobody really believes has a future, although that is not the issue at question here.  It is a school where, through circumstance, all the pupils enrolled are Traveller boys.  A decision was reached recently and communicated to the patron of the school that it is to close with immediate effect in June, not to be phased out over a number of years.</p> <p>I do not believe in segregated education and do not think many people do.  I do not believe boys should be separated from girls.  I do not believe children of different religions should be separated from each other in schools.  I do not believe children from families with financial advantage should be separated from children from families without that financial advantage and I certainly do not believe that Travellers should be educated separately from other children.  However, there is a way of changing that.</p> <p>If this school is to close, and the principal, the staff and the school community appreciate the need for that to happen, then it should be done in a compassionate manner.  There is a handful of young men in the senior cycle of the school, or approaching the senior cycle, who would be severely affected by this closure.  I do not know if the Minister of State can remember when he was 16 but I remember when I was 16.  If we had been told we had to leave the school we were in to go to another school, it would have been pretty difficult for us to do that, and we are not members of a much-discriminated against minority.  We are also not members of a minority that has a tradition of having difficulty in progressing in mainstream, formal education.</p> <p>The issue here is that there are a number of young men who do not really see themselves staying in education if this rug is pulled from under them.  The issue in St. Thomas's is not that the school should not close; I think everybody believes it should close.  The issue is that it should be done with compassion and understanding for the young men who it will affect most profoundly, namely, the young men in fifth year and in third year.  I could understand if the school was told not to take any more students in September.  I could also understand if the Department said it would do this over the course of a year or two years, particularly for those young men who will face the leaving certificate next year.  Despite the best will in the world, what will happen as a result of this situation is that young men who were going to do their leaving certificate in a year or two years will now not do it.  Understanding that the school has to close, what I need to know from the Minister of State is that it can be done over two years to allow these young men to continue in their education in St. Thomas's and to allow a calm and compassionate transition for other students to other educational facilities.</p> <p>We are not asking for the world.  We are not asking to reverse the decision.  We are just asking that the decision be phased, rather than immediate.  For a school to be told in April that it is to close in June is, I would contest, very unusual.  I do not think a school of a different character would get a message in April that it is closing in June for good.  That is the message from the school community.  These are vulnerable young people, they are in mainstream education and they are doing their best.  I would ask that the Department would give them that small bit of leeway, not to close the doors of the school overnight, but to do it over a more prolonged period.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1264" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#A00600"><p>I am taking this debate on behalf of my colleague, the Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy Bruton.  I wish to apologise on his behalf that he cannot be present due to a prior commitment to visit two schools with An Taoiseach.  I will make sure to convey to him the matters raised in this debate.  He is very familiar with this situation but I understand the importance of raising it today and he understands that too.  He just could not make it and I think Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in understands that.</p> <p>Education provision on an inclusive basis is a fundamental principle of our education and training system.  Ensuring every child is supported and given the opportunity to reach his or her full potential is a key priority for this Government and the Department of Education and Skills is committed to improving educational outcomes for members of the Traveller and Roma communities.  As Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in will be aware, St. Thomas&rsquo;s is a school with special school designation dating from a period when separate education provision for members of the Traveller community was the norm.  The phasing out of segregated education provision for Traveller children began in 2006 in accordance with Government policy which was developed in consultation with Traveller representative groups.   Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in acknowledged that was the right decision to make.</p> <p>St. Thomas&rsquo;s is currently the only remaining education centre in the country catering for Traveller boys.  Segregating Traveller children from mainstream children is not positive for Traveller children, the Traveller community or for society.  The agreed process for the phasing out of Traveller only provision was that new enrolments to such provision would cease in September 2008 and closure would be achieved when the current pupil cohort had left the school in question.  This did not happen in the case of St. Thomas&rsquo;s and I accept what the Senator said that this debate is about phasing it out.  That process started and was agreed back in 2008.</p> <p>Officials of the Department of Education and Skills have been engaging with the patron of the school for many years to progress the transfer of its student cohort to the mainstream school system in line with agreed national policy.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Damien English:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1781"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1781&amp;amp;pid=DamienEnglishFG&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=04&amp;amp;day=19"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is important to note that, as with all schools under private patronage, the decision relating to school closure, amalgamation etc. rests with the patron.  As a result of the most recent engagement during the current school year, the Department has come to the view that the arrangements for and delivery of education provision at the school are no longer appropriate to meet the educational needs of the current student cohort.  This view has been communicated to the patron of the school together with a proposal that relevant supports for the current enrolment would transfer to the mainstream school system.  </p><p>In order to ensure a smooth and effective transition of provision for students, officials of the Department are engaging with the school patron and the educational welfare services of Tusla with regard to future education provision for the current student cohort in St. Thomas's school.  Tusla's educational welfare services are available to work with parents to source school places for the current pupil cohort, including three students at leaving certificate level who would be due to sit exams in 2019.  The Department of Education and Skills will continue to engage with both the patron and the educational welfare services of Tulsa regarding arrangements for the future education provision for the pupil cohort.  </p><p>The Senator may wish to note that current overall policy on Traveller education is being progressed within the framework of National Traveller and Roma Inclusion Strategy 2017-2021.  The strategy has a particular emphasis on improving Traveller engagement with education and the Department of Education and Skills is currently working with relevant Departments and agencies and Traveller representative groups to implement relevant actions aimed at improving education outcomes for all Travellers, including the current student cohort of St Thomas's school.  I hope this brings some clarity to the matter.  Maybe the Senator might take it on board.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#B00200"><p>I listened to the Minister of State's reply.  I appreciate that the intention of the Department is to promote integration.  I believe in that and look forward to the day when we have more Travellers in the teaching profession and as role models in the educational sphere.  My fear is that in years to come, there will be three, four, five or six young men who will point to the closure of the school as the reason they do not have a leaving certificate.  Tusla and the Department will do their best to help these students transition to another mainstream setting but my fear is that for the want of a bit of leeway - a year or two - in allowing the students to stay in their current setting, the educational system could lose them completely.  I again ask the Minister of State to pass on my concerns to the Minister and the Department about these young men, the danger presented by the immediate closure of the school and the message that sends to them.  Nobody is arguing - I certainly do not - that Traveller-only schools or educational settings are the way to go.  They are not.  They are not healthy or progressive but I suggest that phasing in this closure is in the best interests of those young men, which must surely be our collective goal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1264" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#B00300"><p>Again, I understand the issue raised by the Senator, namely, phasing and dealing with it appropriately but I must point out that the phasing arrangement began in 2008, which is nearly ten years ago.  It was agreed national policy.  A lot of time has been given to this school.  Part of the difficulty was that in 2015, St. Thomas's school expanded its provision to cater for leaving certificate students without prior notification to, consultation with or approval of the Department.  As the school made a formal request to the Department in April 2017 for additional teaching resources to support this unapproved provision, there is a bit of history here.  All involved with the Department and the agencies have been trying to manage this to ensure the best educational outcome for the students in recognition of national policy, which has been phased in over nearly a ten-year period.  A decision was made 12 years ago so a lot of time has been given here.  A decision was made that it might not be the best outcome for the three students to continue in the leaving certificate year and do their examinations in 2019 in that school setting.  That has been communicated and there is ongoing discussion but there has been a genuine effort by the Department, together with Tusla and all the services, to make sure the best outcomes for those students are achieved and to make sure they are given appropriate provision.  The Senator needs to look at what has happened over the past year when he talks about phasing.  I think he is being a little unfair to suggest there has been no proper phasing or that it has not been approached sensitively.  I think it has been approached sensitively and it is now a matter of making the final decision that is best for the students.  The Department will do this in conjunction with all the local services.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.14" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#B00400">Schools Building Projects Status</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#B00500"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach for accepting this matter and the Minister of State is welcome.  I wish to raise the matter of Ballintemple national school, better known as Crab Lane, and a new school building project.  This is a co-educational school with a current enrolment of around 215 children, eight mainstream class teachers, four learning support resource teachers and a very active and positive principal.  The school is on a split site with the main school located on Crab Lane while the infant classes are located on Boreenmanna Road.  Thankfully, the project has been part of the Department's new school building programme since March 2017.  In September 2017, the board of management agreed a schedule of accommodation with the Department and the project has been progressed to the architectural planning section in the Department but therein lies the road block.  It has become a source of frustration, concern and annoyance, which have been expressed to me by many parents who I have met and who are looking forward to the project but want to see delivery.  The reason I am raising the issue this morning is because this is a very good school in an emerging area with a split campus that needs to see the project progress quickly so that we can go from planning stage to delivery in terms of construction.  I recognise that the Government has invested significantly in education in Cork in terms of capital expenditure but in this case, there is a need to give further hope to the pupils, teachers and parents.  I thank the Minister of State for being here this morning.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1264" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#B00600"><p>I am taking this debate on behalf of the Minister for Education and Skills who is unable to take the debate and sends his apologies.  He had a prior commitment to visit two schools with the Taoiseach.  He would like to be here to discuss the matter with the Senator because he knows it is very important for the Cork area and the area represented by the Senator.  Again, I thank the Senator for raising this matter as it provides an opportunity to clarify the Department's position regarding the provision of a major building project for Ballintemple national school, County Cork.</p> <p>The Senator will be aware that Ballintemple national school is a co-educational, Catholic ethos primary school catering for boys and girls from junior infants to sixth class.  Ballintemple national school has a current enrolment of 222 pupils with a 4% growth in pupil numbers in the period from 2013 to 2017.  The school has a current staffing complement of a principal, eight mainstream class teachers and four special education teaching posts.  This staffing level will remain unchanged for the next school year.  </p> <p>The Senator will be aware of the demographic challenge facing the education system in the coming years, including in the Cork area, because it is an issue he has raised quite often in both Houses.  In that regard, the construction programme aims to prioritise new building projects and major extensions, including special schools, in areas where demographic need has been established.  In light of the anticipated growth in the area concerned, it has been agreed with the school that it would develop from an eight-classroom to a 12-classroom school on a new patron-owned site at Boreenmanna Road in Cork.  </p> <p>In addition, the Department of Education and Skills has been in contact with the National Council for Special Education in respect of special education requirements in the Cork area.  In that regard, agreement was reached with the school that provision will be made in the project brief for an autism spectrum disorder, ASD, class.  Hopefully, that will be good news.  The project brief for Ballintemple national school is, therefore, being finalised to provide for a new 12-classroom primary school with a one-class ASD unit.  This process is nearing completion with a view to allowing the project to progress to architectural planning stages, including the appointment of a design team.  This is expected to be completed in the near future.  I am advised Department officials will be in further contact with the school to advise on the position once it enters the next phase.  On behalf of the Minister, Deputy Bruton, I thank the Senator for raising this matter and can confirm the Department's commitment to progressing the building project in the case of Ballintemple national school.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#B00700"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his response.  I also thank the Minister.  It is encouraging news.  I hope we can put timelines in place in terms of the development and delivery of the project but it is a good news story and again, is a further recognition that the Government is investing in young people in Cork, particularly those in Ballintemple national school in the Crab Lane and Boreenmanna Road area, which is an emerging population base.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#B00800"><p>It is a very heavily populated area.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1264" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#B00900"><p>The Minister is very anxious that this would progress through the phases as quickly as possible.  It is on the list and will be done.  All involved in the Department would like to see it progress and will work with the local school to do that.  Again, I thank Senator Buttimer for raising this issue on behalf of his constituents.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.20" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#B01000">Commemorative Events</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#B01100"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House and thank him for taking this matter.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Colm Burke:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2353"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2353&amp;amp;pid=ColmBurke&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=04&amp;amp;day=19"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> Last night, I attended an event in O'Connell House to celebrate the creation of the State as a republic on 18 April 1949.  The event in question highlights the need to mark momentous changes that have occurred in Ireland.  A significant number of centenaries are due to be celebrated in the coming years.  Those centenaries relate to the period 1918 to 1924, when major changes occurred in this country whereby we went from being ruled from London to Independence and the creation of the Free State.  However, there were also other significant historical events that occurred here during the period.  My request this morning is to know the plans being put in place to celebrate those events.</p><p>The period in question was difficult for people living in certain areas and it is important that we deal with any celebrations in a sensitive way.  It is in that context that I am seeking to discover the plans being put in place in order that these important historical events will be marked in such a way and that there will be recognition for those who brought about the changes that occurred in this country at the time.  As an independent country, Ireland enjoys significant international recognition and has made a major contribution on the global front.  It is in that light that I am seeking clarification regarding the plans that are being put in place.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1264" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#C00200"><p>I thank Senator Colm Burke for raising this important issue in such a sensitive manner.  His approach certainly reflects the type of sensitive approach that the Minister, Deputy Madigan, and her Department would take.  The Minister is sorry she could not be here.  This is an issue in respect of which she would like to engage with the Senator and this House.  However, she cannot be present due to prior commitments.</p><p>As the person with responsibility for leading the Government's decade of centenaries programme, the Minister's priority is to ensure that the complex historical events that took place, starting in 1918, on the road to the foundation of the State are remembered in an inclusive, appropriate, respectful and sensitive manner.  As the Senator stated, this has to be approached in a sensitive manner.  In the context of all the events held to date, that is what the Department has been trying to do under the guidance of and in co-operation with the Minister.</p><p>The Government will continue to be supported in its approach by the guidance of the expert advisory group on commemorations, chaired by the former Senator, Dr. Maurice Manning, and by the all-party consultation committee on commemorations, once established.  In October of last year, the advisory group published its second statement of principles.  This statement sets out a powerful structure of guiding principles which will support the State and other interested parties involved in delivering authentic, citizen focused and appropriate commemorations at national and local level during the second half of the decade of centenaries and which will respect all the sensitivities around that.</p><p>This year, the State centenary programme focuses on four broad thematic strands: the ending of the First World War; the enactment of the Representation of the People Act 1918, the Parliament (Qualification of Women) Act 1918 and the significant role of women in the events of that year; the rise of radical Irish nationalism and the consolidation of Ulster unionism; and the death of John Redmond and the decline and legacy of the Irish Parliamentary Party.</p><p>The First World War was a defining event of the early 20th century and a catalyst for immense change in the political, economic, social, cultural life of communities across Ireland 100 years ago.  The decade of centenaries has provided a new momentum in remembering and exploring the complicated narratives surrounding Ireland&rsquo;s participation in the First World War.  For years, the experiences of the many Irish-born men and women who served and died were largely hidden and ignored and yet they had a profound impact on the island of Ireland and would, almost certainly, have affected every community in the country.  This year, the Government will mark the signing of the Armistice that brought four years of fighting in the First World War to an end with a special ceremony to commemorate all of the Irish-born casualties of the First World War.  Last week, the Minister announced that a ceremony will take place in D&uacute;n Laoghaire on 10 October in remembrance of all of those who perished following the sinking of the <i>RMS Leinster</i>.  This will be an inclusive, respectful and fitting commemoration and she would like to thank D&uacute;n Laoghaire-Rathdown County Council, the family members of those affected by this tragedy and the many other stakeholders who are working with her Department.</p><p>On 6 February, the Minister launched the State centenary programme to mark the introduction of voting rights for women - a significant milestone on a long and difficult journey towards franchising men and women equally and a first step towards realising the full inclusion of Irish women in public life.  An exciting and innovative pop-up women's museum, curated by the historian, Ms Sin&eacute;ad McCoole, and commemorating women in politics and political life from 1918 to 2018, will be showcased in the Coach House in Dublin Castle from November of this year until January 2019.  It will then travel to venues around the country.</p><p>In March, the State commemorated the centenary of the death of John Redmond and paid tribute to his contribution, which spanned a parliamentary career of over 37 years, to the emerging Irish State.  This programme comprised a rich and diverse range of ceremonial, cultural, historical and educational activities in Dublin, Wexford, Waterford and Athlone.  One of the highlights was a special symposium which took place in the National Gallery on 6 March and which involved a partnership between the NUI, RIA, the school of history at UCD and the Department.  A ceremony also took place in Wexford on 15 April, attended by the President of Ireland, to commemorate the death of John Redmond.  This event, which was supported by the Department of Culture, Heritage and the Gaeltacht, was postponed from 4 March due to the adverse weather conditions at that time.</p><p>Politically, 1918 was a year of profound transformation.  The anti-conscription campaign of 1918 and the associated general strike were significant milestones in this movement, which culminated in Sinn F&eacute;in's landslide victory in the general election of 14 December 1918 in the South and the consolidation of the unionist vote in the North.  On 22 April, a special concert takes place in Liberty Hall, hosted by SIPTU and supported by the Department, to mark the centenary of the 1918 general strike.</p><p>Early next year, the State will mark the centenary of the convening of the First D&aacute;il in the Mansion House on 21 January 1919.  The Minister welcomes also the programme of events the Houses of the Oireachtas are developing to mark this momentous occasion.</p><p>The Department of Culture, Heritage and the Gaeltacht will continue to positively engage with, and to support, the local authorities, national cultural institutions, academic institutions, the artistic community and other stakeholders to deliver appropriate commemorative initiatives under each of these thematic strands.</p><p>The Minister would like to take this opportunity to acknowledge the critical importance of local authorities in supporting an inclusive approach to commemorations that is sensitive to the local historical context and experience.  She believes that a collaborative approach to the remembrance of this complex period in our history between the State, local authority network and local organisations and commemorative committees is very important.  The Minister was pleased to approve a funding allocation of &euro;5,000 in 2018 for each local authority.  This funding will support local authorities in developing initiatives to encourage people to explore the political, historical, social and cultural context of 1918 and the significant aspects of life in Ireland that were shaped by and also directed Ireland's participation in the First World War.</p><p>The Minister's predecessor, current Minister for Business, Enterprise and Innovation, Deputy Heather Humphreys, launched a public consultation process in October of last year, with the objective of stimulating a public conversation and a rich diversity of perspectives and ideas around how the significant historical events between 1918 and 1923 might be appropriately remembered.  The response his been extremely encouraging, with 72 submissions, 20 of which were made by local authorities, received.  These submissions have been helpful to the expert advisory group on commemorations as the group considers the advice that it will provide to Government.  The guidance of the advisory group will inform the State's approach to the remembrance of the seminal moments on our journey towards self-determination and independence from 2019 to 2023.</p><p>I hope that gives Senator Colm Burke an update on proceedings and thank him for raising this issue with us here today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#C00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State for the detailed reply.  I very much appreciate it.</p> <p>There were one or two issues that occurred to me.  First, I have noticed that there have been a short lead-in times in respect of certain events held in the past six months.  I wonder whether it would be possible to publish a calendar over the next 12 to 24 months so that people would have up to six months' notice of events as opposed to hearing about them three or four weeks in advance.  I am not blaming the Department or the Minister.  It is merely the way things happen.  The Department gives plenty of notice but it needs to be more proactive as regards highlighting what is coming up.  The second issue relates to providing some programme with schools, particularly in view of the significant change in Irish history in the period 1918 to 1924.  It is important that we involve schools as well.</p> <p>On a third point, I tabled this motion because I was approached by a community group.  A number of significant events happened in the group's area between 1918 and 1924 and it wanted to know what it can do to mark them.  The Minister of State outlined that there is &euro;5,000 allocated to each local authority.  This is about involving communities.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Colm Burke :</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2353"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2353&amp;amp;pid=ColmBurke&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=04&amp;amp;day=19"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The Minister might consider developing a community scheme for individual communities that have an interest in this area.</p><p>I referred to an area in which there was a tragic loss of life but the community celebrated the event in a very sensitive way about two years ago.  It was the best of all of the commemorations I attended and it was organised by a local community rather than a State agency or local authority.  That is not a criticism of State agencies but a significant effort was made by this community and it is important that their effort is given recognition as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1264" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#D00200"><p>I thank Senator Colm Burke for raising this matter and giving us the opportunity to discuss it.  The Senator has put forward some good ideas and the departmental officials will explore the possibilities and engage with the Minister on this, as well as with the advisory group.  I suggest that the various groups to which he referred should engage with the relevant local authority and feed in their ideas to the system.  The Minister wants to ensure the process is as inclusive as possible.  The Department has put in the effort in local communities, local authorities and other bodies to engage with the people and get them involved.  Naturally, we want to maximise the number of people who will be involved in the planning process and will participate in the events themselves.</p><p>The Minister and the Department are making a great effort to set out the events that will take place in the years ahead.  The best way to keep up to speed on all the information is to access the specific website that is dedicated to the decade of centenaries,<i>www.decadeofcentenaries.com.  </i>The Senator might pass it on to people as well because that is the best place to get the information and keep up to speed on the planned events in the years ahead.  The Minister is very keen to involve the communities, schools and others as much as possible.  The Department has been working very hard on events with some great success to date and will build on this success.  I would appreciate it were Members to let groups know that they should be able to link in with the local authorities and libraries as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#D00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State and Senator Colm Burke.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.28" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#D00400">Long-Term Illness Scheme</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#D00500"><p>I welcome the Minister of State at the Department of Health, Deputy Catherine Byrne, to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#D00600"><p>I appreciate that the issue I raised has been chosen as a Commencement matter.</p> <p>A number of people who are suffering from rheumatoid arthritis and are taking heavy medication to deal with the pain find that their condition is not included in the long-term illness book.  I wish to ascertain whether rheumatoid arthritis can be included in the long-term illness book.  I also am calling for an overall review of the long-term illness book, which resulted from section 59 of the Health Act 1970.  While the legislation has been slightly amended since, there has not been a great deal of change in terms of the different illnesses that have been included in it.  A number of people have had to pay out a great deal of money for the prescriptions to deal with their conditions, which in some cases are long-term illnesses.  It is not the case that the person will recover.  A prescription from one's general practitioner, GP, to deal with the condition is not covered by the long-term illness scheme but in certain circumstances, a case can be made for a hospital prescription to be filled for a short period.  It is time for a review of the long-term illness scheme.  A number of illnesses and conditions should be examined in a review.  I look forward to the Minister of State's response.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1307" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#D00700"><p>The Minister for Health, Deputy Harris is in the D&aacute;il taking questions on health.  The Minister apologises to the Senator for his absence but I will deal with the issue on his behalf.</p> <p>I thank Senator Byrne for raising this matter in the Seanad.  The long-term illness, LTI, scheme was established under section 59(3) of the Health Act 1970, as amended.  The conditions covered under the LTI scheme were prescribed in subsequent regulations and are listed as follows: acute leukaemia; mental handicap; cerebral palsy, mental illness, in a person aged under 16 years, cystic fibrosis; multiple sclerosis; diabetes insipidus, diabetes mellitus; muscular dystrophies, parkinsonism, epilepsy, phenylketonuria, haemophilia, spina bifida hydrocephalus and conditions arising from the use of Thalidomide drug. </p> <p>Under the LTI scheme, patients receive free of charge, drugs, medicines and medical and surgical appliances which are used directly for the treatment of their illness.  While the Minister appreciates that rheumatoid arthritis is a life-long condition, there are no plans to extend the list of conditions covered by this scheme.  For people who are ineligible for the long-term illness scheme, there are other arrangements that cover excessive medical costs.  I refer to the General Medical Services, GMS, scheme, the medical card, the GP visit card and the drugs payment scheme.  People who cannot, without undue hardship, arrange for the provision of medical services for themselves and their dependants may be entitled to a medical card.  In the assessment process, the HSE can then take into account medical costs incurred by an individual or families.  The scheme is independent of the LTI scheme.  People who are not eligible for the medical card may still be able to avail of a GP visit card, which covers the cost of the GP consultation.  The scheme is available to all those aged under six years or over 70 years.  However, access is based on income.  The income threshold is higher than for the medical card and various costs may be taken into account in determining the eligibility for this service.  Someone who has neither a medical card nor a GP visit card can use the drugs payment scheme, DPS, which limits the expenditure on prescription items.  Under the DPS, no individual or family pays more than &euro;134 a month towards the cost of approved prescription items.  This threshold was reduced from &euro;144 at the start of 2018.  The DPS significantly reduces the cost for families and individuals with ongoing medical needs.  The Government is committed in the programme for a partnership Government to reduce the cost of medicines for all citizens.  It has already been addressed through a range of measures, including significant price reductions and greater use of reference pricing and generic substitutions.  The further reduction in the DPS threshold and in the prescription charges for medical card holders will be considered in the context of the health commitments in the programme for Government and having regard to the funding available.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#D00800"><p>Senator Byrne might wish to ask a supplementary question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#D00900"><p>I thank the Minister of State, Deputy Catherine Byrne.  While I appreciate that the Government is committed to reducing the costs for people, especially those with long-term illness, I certainly would appreciate the Minister of State's bringing to the attention of the Minister, Deputy Harris, that there are a number of illnesses where people are on medication in the long term and perhaps a review be carried out of the LTI book.  It is quite a number of years since there was a review of the ailments that are covered under the LTI scheme.  It certainly is something that I meet ever more frequently.  Not every illness can be included and we cannot wrap our arms around everything but certainly there are a number of ailments that should be considered for inclusion in the long-term illness book.  It would be great if the Department could conduct a review of the LTI scheme.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1307" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#D01000"><p>I cannot give such a commitment.  The Minister will have to decide whether there will be a review or not.</p> <p>I come across this issue quite a lot as a public representative.  I am aware of it from members of my own family who have rheumatoid arthritis, which affects people as they get older and can lead to very disturbing inability to be able to move around.  I will convey the Senator's views to the Minister on the number of life-long illnesses that are not included in the LTI book.  A review may be overdue and perhaps as part of the budgetary process we may be able to bring it to the Minister and see whether we can seek some revision and review of the long-term illness card.</p> <p>I agree with the Senator that people are affected by a number of conditions that are life-long illnesses but do not come within the terms of the LTI scheme.  I will bring this to the attention of the Minister for Health.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#D01100"><p>I thank the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.36" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#E00100">Message from Dil</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#E00200"><p>D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann passed the Vehicle Registration Data (Automated Searching and Exchange) Bill 2018 on 18 April 2018, to which the agreement of Seanad &Eacute;ireann is desired.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.38" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 11.10 a.m. and resumed at 11.30 a.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.39" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#G00100">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#G00200"><p>Today's Order of Business is No. 1, statements on public service broadcasting and social media regulation, to be taken at 12.45 p.m. and to be adjourned at 2.05 p.m, with the contribution of group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes and those of all other Senators not to exceed five minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#G00300"><p>We will not be asking the Minister for Communications, Climate Action and Environment, Deputy Denis Naughten, to come into the House to discuss his other issues.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.42" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#G00500"><p>The Leader cannot hear Senator Mark Daly because of interruptions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#G00600"><p>He cannot hear, full stop.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#G00700"><p>I speak in a personal capacity and as a Senator.  For a Minister to say he is speaking in a personal capacity on an issue to do with his own Department defies belief and credibility.  He needs to explain what he is doing.</p> <p>Something else which needs to be explained is the fanciful figure-making represented by the recent pronouncements by the Government on house building.  Lorcan Sirr was on "Morning Ireland" this morning and filleted the numbers, as well as the spin put on them by the Taoiseach's spin unit, which obviously has not gone out of existence.  The Minister of State at the Department of Housing, Planning and Local Government, Deputy Damien English, was in Cork last week and said the Government had built 7,000 houses.  The cumulative figure for social housing from July 2016 to date was put at 2,592 which, less the total completed in 2016 of 652, gave a subtotal for 2017, including Part V houses, of 1,940.  Without the Part V houses it was 3,000 and the total local authority and social housing build completed in 2017 was 1,640.  One would have to have a PhD as Lorcan Sirr does to read the report.  The report states in one place that Part V houses are not included but elsewhere states that they are included.  The Government's report is lying to itself - quite an achievement by any Government.  The Government has to get a handle on the facts before it can get a handle on the housing issue.  At the moment, it is making up its own facts.</p> <p>I wish to propose an amendment to the Order of Business, which is that we take No. 61, motion 14, on the Order Paper.  The motion states, "That Seanad &Eacute;ireann recognises the outstanding achievement of the Storm Lake Times Newspaper, Storm Lake, Iowa, winning the Pulitzer Prize for editorial writing by its editor Mr. Art Cullen, whose ancestors came from Ireland."</p> <p>This Saturday there is a memorial mass for Fr. Joseph Cullen, who was the last surviving son of the 1916 leaders.  He was in Kilmainham Gaol the night before his father was executed.  He was two and a half years of age.  The last letter from his father told him, "My little man, be a priest if you can".  Fr. Joseph ended up as a missionary priest in Hong Kong, where he served for over 60 years.  I had the honour of sending him a birthday card on his 100th birthday and he wrote back to me.  He said he had got a letter from the then Taoiseach, Deputy Enda Kenny, congratulating him on reaching his 100th birthday and one from Sinn F&eacute;in but he had only written back to Sinn F&eacute;in.  On his 102nd birthday I organised two first class tickets for him to return to Ireland for the 100th anniversary of the Rising.  I rang him up to ask him if he had got them and he said he had, but "too old".  I told him to see how he felt the following year but he said it was not that he himself was too old.  It was that his doctor was too old, at 85 years of age.  He passed away at the honourable age of 104 and we should remember him and his family for their great sacrifice. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#G00800"><p>Well said.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#G00900"><p>Is the Senator formally moving an amendment to the Order of Business?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#G01000"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#G01100"><p>It will be at the discretion of the Leader.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#G01200"><p>I second the amendment to the Order of Business.  I thank the Leader for conveying to the Minister and the Department the need to publish the list of targets for social housing to be built by the 31 local authorities across this country for 2018.  I sit on the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Housing, Planning and Local Government and we received the information at 8.30 a.m. today.  It was a surprise to members of the committee and was certainly a surprise to me, as I was up earlier in the morning and had read the reports in all the national newspapers, which were briefed yesterday afternoon by the Department.  It was quite extraordinary.</p> <p>I took out a file to look at correspondence with the Department, which had indicated that it would convey the information but chose to go to the media before going to the political Chambers, something which the Department is asked to do.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Victor Boyhan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2463"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2463&amp;amp;pid=VictorBoyhan&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=04&amp;amp;day=19"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The issue is best illustrated by <i>The Examiner</i>, a newspaper with which the Leader is familiar.  I checked with the Department this morning and the figures from <i>The Examiner</i>are those that have been agreed.I will read them out.  The Government has committed to building 115 social houses in County Carlow, 41 in County Cavan, 29 in County Clare, 249 in Cork city-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#H00200"><p>That is not correct.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#H00300"><p>It is correct.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#H00400"><p>The Senator is wrong and should correct the record.  It is build, acquire and lease.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#H00500"><p>May I have the floor, please?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#H00600"><p>The Leader will have ample time to correct Senator Boyhan's figures if they are wrong.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#H00700"><p>I am citing local authorities' direct targets for the building of social housing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#H00800"><p>I presume the Senator is quoting from a newspaper.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#H00900"><p>Not only am I citing figures from a newspaper but I am also referring to documents I received today from the joint committee and Department.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#H01000"><p>The Senator cannot rely on those.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#H01100"><p>The figures are for the direct construction of social housing in the 31 local authorities and have nothing to do with bringing voids back into use.  The commitment given is to build 249 social houses in Cork city, 235 in County Cork, 104 in County Donegal and 1,045 in Dublin city.  The figures show that thousands of people are waiting for social housing in Dublin city.  The number of new social houses to be built by D&uacute;n Laoghaire-Rathdown County Council is 183, while the figure for Fingal County Council is 408.  In County Kerry, 140 social houses are to be built, while the figures for counties Kildare, Leitrim, Mayo, Meath, Monaghan, Offaly, Roscommon, Sligo and Wicklow are 217, 23, 69, 269, 46, 19, 41, 34 and 156, respectively.  I challenge the Leader to contradict me and if I am wrong, I will accept that.  However, if I am right, I expect the Leader to apologise on the record of the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#H01200"><p>The Senator is being selective.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#H01300"><p>I reiterate that these are the direct build targets sent to each and every chief executive this morning.  I have a copy with me and if someone wishes to challenge me on the figures, I will be pleased to debate the issue.  I challenge the Leader to contradict me.  If he chooses to do so, I will respond in greater detail.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#H01400"><p>The Senator may not challenge the Leader when he is speaking.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#H01500"><p>I fully accept that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1404" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#H01600"><p>Two years ago, when the Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy Richard Bruton, was appointed, he created a funding stream for new projects that would widen participation in education.  Yesterday, I had the pleasure of launching one such programme, Turn to Teaching, on which I congratulate the Department.  This is an access programme for children from diverse backgrounds, including migrants, Travellers and children from schools that would not be able to access the standard of Irish and other subjects required to enter the teaching profession.  It provides an access route and will create more diversity in the schools system in order that children from migrant or working class backgrounds can be taught by people who have had the same experiences as they have.  Not only will the programme help the school community, but it will also improve retention and encourage young children to aspire to entering the teaching profession as they will see peers who have done so.  Turn to Teaching is a positive programme and I am delighted to have been asked to give a weekly guest lecture in Maynooth University.  I am honoured to be part of the team.</p> <p>In this connection, I also raise the decision of the Department of Justice and Equality to withdraw funding from two intercultural centres in Tallaght and Clondalkin, which may result in their closure at the end of May.  These centres play a vital role in integrating migrants in the community and providing literacy and other programmes.  While the Department of Education and Skills is taking steps to widen participation in one area, the Department of Justice and Equality is taking steps to narrow participation in working class areas.  I ask the Leader to request that the Minister of State at the Department of Justice and Equality, Deputy David Stanton, come to the House to bring Senators up to speed on the reasons for the decision to withdraw funding from two vital programmes. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#H01700"><p>I will raise two issues if I may, the first of which is the ongoing crisis in University Hospital Limerick.  It is ironic that last Friday, on the same day the Taoiseach was making a glitzy presentation at the University of Limerick, the crisis at University Hospital Limerick continued with an 85 year old grandmother who presented subsequently spending four days on a trolley.  My colleague, Deputy Maurice Quinlivan, has written several times to the Minister for Health seeking a meeting and we are still waiting for an opportunity to discuss the crisis.  I would appreciate the Leader's assistance in this regard because Members are entitled to speak to the Minister and express the grave concerns shared by many people in Limerick regarding the ongoing and ever-worsening trolley crisis in University Hospital Limerick.</p> <p>An excellent and detailed TASC - Think-tank for Action on Social Change - report is being launched in Buswells Hotel this morning by Senator Alice-Mary Higgins who deserves great credit for doing so.  Entitled, Living with Uncertainty: The Social Implications of Precarious Work, it is a hell of a report.  It shows how precarious work affects many people's mental and physical health, many precarious workers are not covered by either the public medical card system or private health system and precarious work forces people to be dependent on others.  To put the issue in context, one in five people is employed on a part-time or temporary basis and precarious work has increased significantly.</p> <p>It is funny that my colleague, Senator Boyhan, spoke of correcting the record.  In that regard, I could speak about the childcare, transport and storage or education sectors but I will focus on the home care sector.  On Thursday, 22 March, Senator Colm Burke misled the House - unintentionally in my view - when he twice stated that workers employed by private providers of home care were receiving the same rates of pay as home helps employed by the Health Service Executive.  I accept the Senator made that statement in good faith and I expect he will be shocked to learn not only that the rates of pay differ but that they differ significantly.</p> <p>The home care sector has three types of providers, namely, public, voluntary and private.  Public and voluntary providers are fully funded through the HSE and the average rate of pay for home care workers in these sectors is &euro;15 per hour, which is a reasonable rate of pay for the challenging job done by the professionals in question.  The voluntary sector rate is between &euro;11.50 and &euro;12.50 per hour, whereas rates in the private sector are between &euro;10.10 and &euro;10.50 or &euro;5 per hour less than in the public sector.  However, the problem does not stop there because those who work for private home care providers are not paid for time spent travelling between clients, during which time they must work for free.  Only one type of contract operates in the private home care sector, namely, a precarious work contract under which workers do not know what hours they will work from one week to the next.  It is a scandal that the sector is built on poverty pay.  That is the truth and it is not good enough for the workers and certainly not good enough for the people they look after.  It also explains the high rate of turnover among staff in private home care providers.  It is incumbent on Senators to have a debate on the sector and recognise there is a major problem.  We must not be cheerleaders for a private sector that is built on poverty pay. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#H01800"><p>I sound a solemn warning to the Government this morning about the referendum on the removal of the eighth amendment to the Constitution.  If it does not wake up soon, it will lose the referendum.  It is not doing anything and there is no campaign whatever that I can see.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#H01900"><p>That might be a good thing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#H02000"><p>It is certainly not a good thing for democracy.  Senator Coghlan is entitled to his views and the rest of us are entitled to our views.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#H02100"><p>I ask Senator Coghlan not to engage in provocation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#H02200"><p>The Senator is an old pal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#H02300"><p>Senator Norris understands me.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#H02400"><p>I have received numerous communications addressed to me personally in the post from decent, well-meaning people.  These are printed documents that commence with the words "Dear David" and so on and include videos, pamphlets and leaflets.  I have received a number of these communications in my office.  Yesterday, as I was entering Leinster House, I was approached by a television crew who asked me my view on the eighth amendment.  When I stated I was in favour of removing it, the discussion became increasingly aggressive and harassing.  Luckily, I am not easily intimidated.</p> <p>I have not heard anything from those who wish to remove the eighth amendment.  This is a serious mistake as there is a great danger that the referendum will be lost unless the Government gets out and explains the position, particularly with regard to the 12 week gestation limit because that issue causes many decent people real concern.  Many people do not realise that the reason for the proposed limit is that the abortion pill is available on the Internet, which means young women can take it without medical supervision and do themselves great physical harm.  I call on the Government to start a campaign now, get off the fence and do something to ensure this obnoxious amendment is removed. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#H02500"><p>Well said.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#H02600"><p>My church, in a typically Protestant, stupid fashion, has dithered on the issue.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator David Norris:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1758"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1758&amp;amp;pid=DavidNorris&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=04&amp;amp;day=19"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->When it was being introduced in the beginning that church said very clearly that the Constitution of Ireland was not-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#J00200"><p>It has some very solid people.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#J00300"><p>-----the place for this kind of expression and it should be left to the legislators.  I say again, the people on the other side do not trust the legislators.  They do not trust the people.  They do not trust the judges.  Who do they trust?  Themselves.</p> <p>I would like to remark on the fact that there is an extremely fine portrait of President Michael D. Higgins in the lobby.  It is a very welcome addition.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#J00400"><p>Absolutely.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#J00500"><p>It is a very fine painting.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1380" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#J00600"><p>The portrait could have been of the Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#J00700"><p>On the other side, there is a painting of, I think, all the female Members from the year dot.  I am not an art critic but it looks to me like a pond full of tadpoles.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#J00800"><p>The painting dwarfs the President's portrait, which is a very fine portrait.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#J00900"><p>I thank the Senators for their critical analyses.  I call Senator Maria Byrne.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#J01050"><p>I welcome the fact that Aerospace Asset Trading has recently purchased a warehouse in Shannon Airport and plans to expand.  The company will join a cluster of 60 aviation companies, which is most welcome.  Aerospace Asset Trading is a Florida based company that operates in Shannon Airport.  When the company purchased the warehouse recently it stated that Shannon Airport gave it great access to Europe.  That is why the company has decided to locate its European headquarters in Shannon Airport.  One hears a lot negativity about Brexit but I believe it has encouraged companies to consider locations in Ireland.  I am also pleased that Aerospace Asset Trading plans to double the number of people it employs within the next two years.</p> <p>Recently, the Shannon Foynes Port Company purchased a state-of-the-art crane valued at &euro;2.8 million and, according to the company, the crane will be used to dredge the River Shannon.  There is potential for over 3,000 jobs to be created along the banks of the River Shannon, which run all the way from Limerick city to Foynes.  This is a most welcome development.  It is not often that we see such investment in companies.  It leads into part of the 2041 vision for the future development of Limerick port and Shannon Foynes Port Company.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#J01100"><p>I congratulate Mr. David McRedmond, CEO of An Post, for turning the company around to a profit through its stamps, parcels and the post office generally.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#J01200"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#J01300"><p>I also congratulate him on the development of community banking, which is ongoing.  We have had many discussions in here about the importance of a post office in locales, villages, towns and regions in Ireland.  I consider the post office to be a place of communication, resource, connection and engagement for people in cities as well as in country towns.  His success proves that he was a very good choice.  He has done a great job and will continue to do so.  He has also begun to control the impasse between An Post and the Postmasters General of Ireland.</p> <p>Senator Norris is a man of artistry and is a renaissance man.  Therefore, he should know that artistry and portrait painting is, of itself, unique.  The portrait of the women parliamentarians is a quite beautiful thing because it has brought all of them together.  Maybe some of the images are not what we might have liked.  What he has said is a bit of an insult to the women who, in the D&aacute;il and Seanad, work collectively and individually for the good and the betterment of Irish society.  He likened the portrait to looking at a pond of tadpoles.  He was not looking at tadpoles; he was looking at an artist's hand at work.  He was looking at great faces, endeavour and energy.  He was looking at people from all walks of life who represent something in here.  His comment was disingenuous, which surprised me because he is a man of artistic endeavour and one whom I consider to have a cultural heartbeat.     </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#J01400"><p>Tadpoles are beautiful.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#J01500"><p>Excuse me, Senator.  I did not hear his cultural heartbeat here this morning.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#J01600"><p>I rise to ask the Leader to arrange for the Minister for-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#J01700"><p>The Senator's colleague, Senator Norris, is in the same group and, therefore, the Senators must rotate their contributions.  I think Senator Mulherin has forgotten.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#J01800"><p>That depends on the Labour Party.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.95" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#J02000"><p>I will start the clock again for Senator Mulherin.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#J02100"><p>Go raibh maith agat.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#J02200"><p>Senator Norris should read his emails, a Chathaoirligh.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#J02300"><p>One should talk to any of them about rugby players.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.100" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#J02500"><p>The reality-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#J02600"><p>I do not want a row in public with the technical group.  The Senators can sort their differences afterwards.  I call Senator Mulherin.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#J02700"><p>I rise to ask that the Leader invite the Minister for Culture, Heritage and the Gaeltacht, Deputy Josepha Madigan, to this Chamber to debate issues arising from the habitats and birds directive, particularly in the context of Project Ireland 2040 and the various infrastructural projects that have been identified such as roads, rail, ports, etc.</p> <p>The directive designates lands as special areas of conservation.  It seems to me that such designation is very difficult to overcome when one seeks to develop the land.  In the normal course, one cannot interfere with a habitat that forms part of a special area of conservation, SAC.  Also, the opportunity to mitigate using engineering works in order to make a project acceptable, such as a road, are very slim.  This situation can be overcome by management plans but, unfortunately, such plans are few and far between in this country.  I want to cite Mayo as an example because 50% of the county has been designated an SAC.  Therefore, it is no surprise that in the past while every piece of infrastructure that we have tried to develop has stalled.  In 2010, development of the N26 was refused due to the potential impact on the habitat of Whooper swans.  Also, part of the road was over designed and two bridges were deemed necessary for an SAC, which was the River Moy valley.  We are now trying to upgrade a bridge located on a national primary road or N26, which dates from the last century.  There is an issue as it is an SAC with alluvial woodland and, potentially, freshwater pearl mussels.  We had an issue with flooding in Crossmolina.  We were told that we could not dredge the river due to the presence of freshwater pearl mussels.  More recently, An Bord Plean&aacute;la has refused an application for the building of a bridge on the R312 that runs between Castlebar and Belmullet due the existence of freshwater pearl mussels.</p> <p>There are problems in every area located along the western seaboard.  I will cite another example located outside of my county of Mayo, which is the road from Galway to Clifden.  The situation is only going to get worse.  We have plans and money to build.  Are we going to succeed with the way things stand?  There needs to be an intervention.  We need management plans that allow for human activity, human progress and economic growth.  We do not have all of those things right now and we are being tortured with the habitats directive.  We want to be responsible and we want development.  It is critical as we seek to develop and grow, under Project Ireland 2040, that the Minister is invited in here for a debate.  I ask that the Leader invites her here, as a matter of urgency.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#J02800"><p>Yesterday, I tabled a Commencement matter to which the Minister of State at the Department of Health, Deputy Jim Daly, responded.  My Commencement matter related to a motion passed in this House last February.  The motion was unopposed.  It stated clearly that a non-HSE parent representative should be on the HSE primary care national steering group for children with complex medical needs.  Unfortunately, that view seems to have been overturned, over-ruled, ignored and disrespected by, I presume, not just the HSE but by the Minister for Health.  The HSE has progressed with the focus group, which the parents do not want.  Instead, the parents want a direct professional voice to be part of the group.</p> <p>This morning I spoke to representatives of the Disability Federation of Ireland.  They strongly believe that we have a case.  I will find a way to ensure that the preferred representation occurs and that a parent is heard on the steering group.  The federation believes the current situation goes against the recently ratified UN Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities, in particular Article 4 that allows for equality of voice, inclusion and decision-making.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator M&aacute;ire Devine:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2468"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2468&amp;amp;pid=MaireDevine&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=04&amp;amp;day=19"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I also will pursue the issue regarding the Irish Human Rights and Equality Commission.  Members of this House need to be aware of and not allow something that was passed unopposed in this House to be ignored and disrespected.  Democracy itself has no meaning when it comes to the HSE, and I ask the Leader to request that the Minister for Health, Deputy Harris, come to the House to discuss this absolutely heartbreaking decision that has been made, underhandedly and not too obviously. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#K00200"><p>A couple of months ago I raised the issue of posters pertaining to this referendum.  I made the comment that perhaps it would be best for all sides if neither "Yes" nor "No" posters were erected because of the sensitive nature of the issue at hand.  I feel that even more strongly now.  Walking past Leinster House today, I was greeted by an incredibly offensive and insensitive banner.  Members of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na told me that there is a very long and complicated process involved in complaining about such an offensive banner.</p> <p>The posters around the city and the country feature statements that do not have to be verified or fact checked.  In fact, there is nobody whose job is to fact check or verify statements written on referendum posters.  As the Minister for Communications, Climate Action and Environment, Deputy Naughten, signed the order for the referendum quite early, we have a two-month campaign rather than the one-month one we were anticipating.  My suggestion to the Cathaoirleach is that the Minister should come in and discuss this matter.  There should be some mechanism for overseeing or verifying statements or slogans used in referendum campaigns.  One such slogan has no basis in fact whatsoever, namely, the claim that one in five pregnancies in Britain ends in a termination.  There is no basis for that declaration whatsoever but it is on every lamp-post in the land.  </p> <p>I spoke to a woman who rang the Labour Party offices and who last year was in the traumatic situation of having to deal with a fatal foetal abnormality.  Of course, she had to leave this country because of our archaic legislation and constitutional amendments on pregnancy.  She was highly traumatised by the entire situation and now has a poster outside her door that is extremely upsetting to her.  We arrived and stuck a poster on the same pole to countermand or balance the situation, because of how offensive that poster was to her.  Can we have the Minister for Communications, Climate Action and Environment before this House?  There is a loophole in legislation here.  It is nobody's fault but we need to rectify it.  If a referendum is taking place and posters are being erected, people should not be able to tell lies.  One should not be allowed to display deeply and gratuitously offensive messaging and posters outside the Houses of the Parliament of the Irish Republic in a huge and graphic style.  It is offensive to me, it should be offensive to every Member of this House and we should be in a position to do something about it.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#K00300"><p>Senator Mulherin has touched on this point in her remarks but there is a total imbalance when it comes to capital development projects being delayed.  In my native town, I was chair of the Lough Key Forest Park action group.  We secured a development worth about &euro;20 million.  However, about five different hotels have been refused planning permission in the past ten or 15 years and now there is no hotel in a region that has a huge tourism facility in Lough Key Forest Park.</p> <p>One development was refused because the lesser horseshoe bat was found in the cellar of the tower in Lough Key Forest Park.  The lesser horseshoe bat has never been seen north of Athlone.  If I was trying to stop a major development, all I would have to do is take - forgive me - droppings and place them 15 or 20 miles ahead.  That can stop a development worth &euro;100 million.  I would love to see the town if we had that development today.  We would have a vibrant town and tourism industry.  It is an issue and Senator Mulherin was right to bring it up.  It is something over which we, as politicians, have no say.  However, there is a huge imbalance and it needs to be addressed.  </p> <p>More importantly, last night's vote in the House of Lords was a major setback for Brexit in the UK.  The Government was defeated on an amendment to the European Union (Withdrawal) Bill 2017-19.  The amendment provides that the UK remains in a customs union with the EU.  The Government was defeated by 348 to 225.  It was probably one of the biggest votes in the House of Lords in recent memory.  I want to pay tribute, because sometimes people deride the Upper House of this Parliament.  These are people who are ahead of the curve.  We saw this with the report of the European Union Committee of the House of Lords on British-Irish and North-South relations.  I remember Lord Jay coming to Dublin for the launch.  For the first time, it had a statement on the impact on Ireland and it was welcomed.  That was more than a year and a half ago.  </p> <p>These things must be welcomed, and I hope that it is a wake-up call to ensure that Brexit does not happen, because Brexit will not just damage the UK.  It will damage the island of Ireland and this must be very much welcomed by our House today.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#K00400"><p>In recent days, the <i>Irish Examiner</i>carried a feature on some of the most enjoyable walks in Ireland.  Second on their list was Swan Park, Buncrana, County Donegal.  Eight months ago, that riverside park was destroyed by the floods in the Inishowen Peninsula.  I have raised this repeatedly in this room.  This is a major tourism amenity in the second largest town in Donegal.  I do not know anywhere in Ireland where this would be tolerated.  As a Member of this House, I have yet to get a meeting with a Minister.  I have yet to sit down face-to-face with a Minister, and the Leader knows that this was promised to me.  I have stayed silent for all of these weeks in good faith but nothing has happened.  There has not been a single face-to-face meeting with a Minister about the fact that a major tourism and community amenity, beloved by our community and our visitors, has been absolutely destroyed.</p><p>The cost of restoring this park has been estimated at &euro;2.3 million by Donegal County Council.  Some contribution from the Government would be welcomed at this stage.  I appeal to the Leader again today.  Parliamentary questions have been tabled and I have raised the matter face to face with Ministers in brief conversations in these halls.  However, I need a proper meeting with senior Department officials present.  Costings have been sent to them by Donegal County Council but Departments are batting questions on the issue back and forth to each other.  </p><p>Across all parties, all nine county councillors in the Inishowen Peninsula have asked for a meeting on this matter with the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government, Deputy Eoghan Murphy, and the Minister for Rural and Community Development, Deputy Ring.  A petition signed by over 4,000 local people was recently handed to the Minister, Deputy Eoghan Murphy.  I make the appeal again today for a cross-party delegation of local councillors from Inishowen and all the local Oireachtas Members to meet the two Ministers, thrash this out and find a solution.  It is absolutely intolerable that after eight months, I read in one of our major national newspapers that we have the second most enjoyable walk in the entire island and that walk lies in ruins.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#K00500"><p>In fairness to Senator Mac Lochlainn, he has raised this consistently and if my memory serves me correctly a commitment was given that some sort of meeting would be facilitated.  I will indulge that the Leader might attend to it, because it has been raised at least five times in this Chamber.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#K00600"><p>As Senator Feighan has said, it is interesting to note that yesterday in the House of Lords, the British Government suffered a major reverse on an amendment to the European Union (Withdrawal) Bill 2017-19.  The Lords quite rightly pointed out the benefits of a customs union after Britain leaves the European Union.  The Senator referred to the outcome of the vote, which was carried by 348 to 225.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paul Coghlan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1881"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1881&amp;amp;pid=PaulCoghlan&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=04&amp;amp;day=19"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The House of Lords very firmly wants a new arrangement which would enable the United Kingdom to continue participating in a customs union, which is the only sensible solution.  It wants a comprehensive deal with the EU which would totally remove any need for borders within this country or in the Irish Sea.  Obviously, it would not want to ignore the European Union market, a market of 500 million people, when the UK leaves, so it makes sense from the point of view of protecting jobs, supporting manufacturing and, as I say, removing the need for a border.  That new comprehensive UK-EU customs union after Brexit would continue the close relationship which exists within the EU.  I believe that what happened yesterday in the House of Lords will force the British Government to rethink its position.  Of course we do not know precisely what is being negotiated on the detail of the question of trade.  Those negotiations are going on every day in Brussels.  However, after the next European Council meeting it would be useful for this House to have a further debate on the matter.  </p><p>When I was in Britain a few weeks ago as part of my work on the Joint Committee on European Union Affairs, which is chaired by Deputy Michael Healy-Rae and on which Senator Neale Richmond also sits, we found that in meeting all of the groups across the parties there was tremendous good will in respect of the arrangement between Ireland and Britain.  It behoves us all to keep up our good contacts with all of our British friends and to support that, because it is having an effect.  We found that when we met different committees of both the House of Commons and the House of Lords.  That good will is there.  Coupled with that, yesterday we had the President of the European Council, Donald Tusk, warning that there will be no withdrawal agreement and no transition deal for Britain unless it forms and agrees to some sort of customs partnership.  It does not have to be the existing customs union.  That can be gotten around with a suitable formula of words.  It would be unthinkable for the UK Government to ignore this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#L00200"><p>I want to encourage Members from Fianna F&aacute;il to support the Provision of Objective Sex Education Bill 2018 which is being voted on in the D&aacute;il today.  I found the reasoning for its opposition to the issue last night to be somewhat pathetic, as was pointed out by Deputy Ruth Coppinger.  Fianna F&aacute;il claimed that the issue would be dealt with in the coming weeks by the Joint Committee on Education and Skills.  However, if any level of research had been done on the issue it would have found that the characteristic spirit clause, which is effectively a veto on curriculum for ethos-based schools, is by far the biggest obstacle to inclusive and robust relationships and sexuality education, RSE.</p> <p>Fianna F&aacute;il's representative went on to say that the Oireachtas should not dictate the curriculum in schools.  However, it was Fianna F&aacute;il, when in government, that implemented the characteristic spirit clause which has dictated the curriculum for the last few decades.  If we wish to see a curriculum that does not rely on dogma, that is fact-based and objective, and that equips our young people with positive values regarding their sexual health, we should absolutely support this Bill.  I hope Members of Fianna F&aacute;il in the Lower House would accept that.  I held a briefing with Senators Lynn Ruane and Grace O'Sullivan and not one Fianna F&aacute;il Member was present.</p> <p>I would also like to say to the people moving around this city with LGBT rainbow flags and graphic images relating to the referendum campaign that they may have the space to display those images outside Leinster House today but that they will be met with LGBT visibility when they protest our spaces.  I commend Radical Queers Resist and other LGBT people and our allies who have sent that message loud and clear.  The agenda of the LGBT community is about redefining a social code that is repressive to us all, and that includes the right to bodily autonomy and self-determination.  What does this come back to?  Those same people outside would have opposed contraception, marriage equality, the decriminalisation of homosexuality and, probably, sex work.  The people at the gates of Leinster House with graphic images are on the side of history that says that any sex that does not result in a family is abhorrent and wrong.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1380" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#L00300"><p>I support Senator Mulherin in her proposal to bring the Minister for Culture, Heritage and the Gaeltacht to the House in respect of the issues the Senator raised.  There have been many projects which have failed to get through.  It is unbelievable to think that a route cannot be found from Ballina to Swinford for a national primary road and that every avenue considered is closed off by the National Parks and Wildlife Service and the Department of Culture, Heritage and the Gaeltacht because of objections for various reasons, including the presence of snails, mussels and Whooper swans.</p> <p>I have also asked on a number of occasions for the Minister to come in.  I have spoken to some people in the National Parks and Wildlife Service with regard to projects which have gone ahead after objections were raised in respect of the displacement of species, whether grouse, Whooper swans, snails or mussels.  I wanted to see if there had been displacement and if the species did come back.  I have first-hand information myself of a case in which a wind farm went ahead despite objections lodged about the displacement of grouse.  I have seen where grouse are now nesting under the wind turbines.  They have come back.  I have asked that an investigation or assessment be carried out to see where there was displacement, if there was displacement, whether species have come back, and if there were any adverse effects on the environment.  Perhaps an independent assessment might be best.  Many of those projects took place more than 20 or 30 years ago so ample time has passed to see whether any displacement was permanent or whether the species have come back into those environments.  I support Senators Mulherin and Feighan with regard to bringing in the Minister for Culture, Heritage and the Gaeltacht because this is a very important matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#L00400"><p>I thank the 15 Members of the House who contributed to the Order of Business.  I am happy to take Senator Mark Daly's amendment to the Order of Business, which he articulated yesterday.  The Minister, Deputy Denis Naughten, will be in the House after the Order of Business.  To be fair, let us be clear, the Minister is a person of probity.  He is a man of great integrity.  The matter is before the courts, as the Senator knows quite well.  I think we would all prefer if the conversation had not taken place but it is important to recognise that the Minister made a purely personal comment on a matter that is in the public domain and, as he said in the Lower House yesterday, the outcome was well known.</p> <p>If the Senator wants to have the Minister come in, he is coming in.  He will make a statement as part of the debate later.  To be fair to him, he explained yesterday and he was supported by Eoghan &Oacute; Neachtain, who said that he would not change an ounce of what the Minister said.  This goes back to what we all said yesterday on the Order of Business.  Everybody wants to have an independent free press which is not, as Senator Coghlan said, controlled by a few.  It should be open to everybody to be involved in buying and ownership.  The Minister gave his answer to the D&aacute;il yesterday.  He will be here later on and will answer again.  I am quite happy to have him do that, but to be fair to him he acknowledged what happened.</p> <p>The other point that needs to be recognised is that there is an onus on those who lobby to register and to be held to account for their actions as well.  That also needs to be looked at.</p> <p>Senators Victor Boyhan and Mark Daly raised the issue of social housing.  Let us make it quite clear, the Government has committed &euro;6 billion to support the accelerated delivery of 50,000 additional social housing units by the end of 2021 through building, acquisition and leasing.  To clarify for Senator Boyhan, I was not disputing his figure in respect of building, I was saying that he was being selective in how we deliver.  Social housing is about building, acquiring and leasing.  If the Senator takes the page he has, the figure for Cork including all three aspects is 4,221.  That was the point I was making.  I was not disputing his figure for building.  I was saying that he was being selective in arriving at the point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#L00500"><p>No, I was not. I am sorry but-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#L00600"><p>He was.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#L00700"><p>----I was talking about social housing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#L00800"><p>Yes, and if he reads-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#L00900"><p>I was not selecting anything else, just social direct build.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M00100"><p>The Senator should read the page he has in front of him.  There are three-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M00200"><p>I gave it to the Leader.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M00300"><p>I have it here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M00400"><p>The correct Bill is the social housing-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M00500"><p>We cannot allow debate of this kind.  Senator Boyhan raised the issue and the Leader is entitled to respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M00600"><p>Let us be quite clear.  As a country and a Government, and in terms of local authorities, there are three ways of providing social housing, namely, direct build, acquisition and lease.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M00700"><p>We know that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M00800"><p>That is the point I was making.  I was not in any way being derogatory towards Senator Boyhan.  They are the three ways we deliver social housing.  If the Senator disputes that, we cannot agree to disagree on it because-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M00900"><p>I do not need a lecture on how to deliver social housing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M01000"><p>We also have approved bodies, so there are ways of delivering housing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M01100"><p>We all know that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M01200"><p>It is not just the old way of delivery by social build.  The other point I want to make is that targets announced today are a significant step in the provision of social housing.  What we must make happen, as I have said repeatedly, is that we deliver in terms of affordable and social housing.  That is why the unveiling of the commitments here is a significant approach by Government.  I am quite happy to support the Government's initiatives in terms of delivering affordable housing.  The Minister, Deputy Eoghan Murphy, has acquired extra infrastructure money to the tune of &euro;25 million for development on local authority sites.  What we must also do, as I said yesterday, is look at the issue of the affordability of land.  If we can do that, we will go a long way towards tackling our social housing crisis.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M01300"><p>The Leader will acknowledge that I was correct.  He should just do that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M01400"><p>If it makes Senator Boyhan happy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M01500"><p>If the Leader thinks it is right and proper to do so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M01600"><p>I am not in any way casting aspersions on the Senator's figures.  What I was implying-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M01700"><p>My figures were correct.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M01800"><p>If the Senator would do me the courtesy of letting me answer-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M01900"><p>Then answer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M02000"><p>What I was saying, if the Senator is prepared to listen to me-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M02100"><p>I am listening.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M02200"><p>I was not disputing his figure at all for the direct build but where he is incorrect-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M02300"><p>We will rest it there.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M02400"><p>-----is that county councils and city councils in the acquisition, building and leasing-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M02500"><p>I was not incorrect because I did not state that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M02600"><p>The Senator was being selective in what he said in his figures.  I am happy to clarify that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M02700"><p>I did not state that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M02800"><p>Both Senators have made their cases clear and we will move on.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M02900"><p>I commend Senator Ruane for her leadership on the issue of back to education and allowing for people to return to education.  She should be admired for what she stands for and for encouraging people to come back into education.  I commend her for launching the initiative today.  It is about offering people second chances, but also first chances for those who go to school, leave early and opt out of the education system for whatever reason.  As a teacher, who spent ten years directing education, I am aware of the number of people who in later life come back in and have that opportunity, including women and men and married, single, elderly and young people, who recognise that they have missed an opportunity but come back in.  For me, education is about empowerment and giving people that opportunity.  To be fair, the Minister, Deputy Bruton, has been very strong in the delivery of choice and opportunity.</p> <p>In regard to the migration and cultural integration centres, I have not got the information but if the Senator gives the details to me, I would be happy to talk to the Minister afterwards.  The Minister of State, Deputy Stanton, is very committed to the issue of integration and has done a power of work both as a former Chairman of the joint Oireachtas committee and as a Minister of State. </p> <p>Senator Gavan raised the issue of University Hospital Limerick and the trolley crisis.  As I said yesterday, we are talking about people who should not be on trolleys.  It is important to recognise that progress is being made in terms of the delivery of extra beds.  It is important to give the House a number of figures as doing so puts things in context.  Attendances are up by 7% and admissions are up by 7.3%.  Attendances of over 75s have gone up by over 20.1% and admissions of over 75s are up by 18.2%.  There are more people now using our hospitals, or arriving into hospitals.  The increased demand is about a combination of weather and other factors that we need to address as a country.</p> <p>Why is the acute hospital the first point of entry or first port of call?  It should not be.  There should be investment in primary care.  To be fair to the Minister, Deputy Harris, he has approved a further &euro;5 million in funding to support the safe discharge of patients and has also increased home support packages.  Some 300 additional transitional care beds have been allocated.  In University Hospital Limerick, which the Senator spoke about, there are 17 new beds being opened.  As the Senator knows quite well, it is about investment.  I would like to hear the Senator's plan for what we should do in the emergency departments because I do not hear any plan from him about what we should do.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M03000"><p>The Leader is absolutely wrong.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M03100"><p>Ah, now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M03200"><p>I have never heard him say anything about it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M03300"><p>We have the most detailed policy on health of any party.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M03400"><p>I asked Senator Gavan a specific question.  I have never heard him come in and say what he would do.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M03500"><p>Let us have the debate and we will tell the Leader what we will do.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M03600"><p>We have had the debates.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M03700"><p>The Minister will not meet with us.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M03800"><p>The largest amount of money in the history of the State has been allocated to the health budget.  <i>Per capita</i>, we are one of the top four in Europe for investment in health.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M03900"><p>It just shows how badly the Government is doing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M04000"><p>I will make the point again.  The Senator claims to be a trade unionist, and I will take him as he is.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M04100"><p>My groan was for the Leader.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M04200"><p>He is a trade union leader who deals with people every day.  There is something radically wrong with our health system when Government allocates the highest spend in the history of the State to a health budget.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M04300"><p>Lies, damn lies and statistics.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M04400"><p>It is not lies.  The problem with the Sinn F&eacute;in guys is that they want to engage in old politics the whole time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M04500"><p>The Leader is not comparing like with like in terms of investment in our public health system.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M04600"><p>The highest ever spend in the history of the State-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M04700"><p>The Leader is better than that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M04800"><p>It is the highest ever number of trolleys in Limerick.  Each month it gets worse.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M04900"><p>The highest ever spend-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M05000"><p>The Leader will facilitate a debate for the Senators.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M05100"><p>It is the highest ever spend in the history of the State on health and something is fundamentally wrong.  I ask the Senators to reflect on that.</p> <p>Senator Norris raised two issues.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M05200"><p>I raised another issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M05300"><p>In terms of home care packages, I have not got the figures to which Senator Gavan referred but it is a bit unfair to come in when Senator Colm Burke is not here to defend himself and raise the matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.173" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M05400"><p>That is not my fault.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.174" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M05500"><p>If the Senator wants to take it up again, I would be happy to have him debate it but to be fair, the Government has increased the number of home care packages and home help hours that are available.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M05600"><p>But they are based on poverty pay.  Those employers will not recognise their unions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M05700"><p>If the Senator had his way, the Government would do nothing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.177" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M05800"><p>There is a lot of disrespect for the Chair here today and if it continues, I will suspend the House for 15 minutes.  This is argy-bargy.  I am in the Chamber a long time.  Let the Leader respond.  If the Senator is not happy, he has the right to raise the matter again next week.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#M05900"><p>Senators Norris and &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in raised the issue of the eighth amendment.  I would say to Senator Norris that it is not the Government's to lose.  This is a democracy.  It is up to the people to make a decision.  It is up to the Members of the Oireachtas to show leadership and, if they are for repeal, to go out and campaign for it, not to come in here criticising those who are doing work on the ground to ensure the referendum is passed.  Equally, those who have a different viewpoint are entitled to it.</p> <p>The fundamental point that Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in addressed - I know as an independent Chair, the Cathaoirleach had to refer it to me - was that there is a fundamental problem that needs to be addressed about the inaccuracies in the postering by one side of the debate.  There is an obligation and duty on the Referendum Commission, in my opinion, but also on independent journalists to highlight, promulgate and verify that the facts are incorrect in postering on one side of the equation.  It is disingenuous of one side of the debate - the "No" side - to put up misleading information and to cast fear and use diversionary tactics.  I am all for debate that is informed and that is not based on scaring and fear.  There is a duty on the Referendum Commission to clarify.  We spoke about social media and the influence it may have.  Equally, the area of postering has had an influence on this debate so far.</p> <p>Senators Marie-Louise O'Donnell and Norris also raised the issue of the portrait.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=04&amp;amp;day=19"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I want to disassociate myself from the remarks of Senator Norris.  The portrait by Noel Murphy, an acclaimed artist, is a reflection of the 53 women who have served and serve in the Houses of the Oireachtas.  It is unfair to use headline grabbing sentences to denigrate the portrait.  I am not an artist or a critic-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#N00200"><p>The Leader is critical, however.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.181" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#N00300"><p>Please, do not provoke the Leader.  The Senators are only trying to divert you, Leader.  I know you are anxious to conclude.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.182" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#N00400"><p>Vot&aacute;il 100 is an important event in the history of our country.  It is right and proper we celebrate the women who have been and are elected to the Houses of the Oireachtas.</p> <p>Senator Marie-Louise O'Donnell raised the issue of An Post and commended its chief executive, David McRedmond.  It is good to see An Post going in the right direction.  It is about all of us using the service.  The Senator has been a champion of community banking.  We need to see further progress made in that regard.</p> <p>Senator Byrne raised the issue of the good news about Aerospace Asset Trading in Shannon.  I congratulate the company.  She also referred to the recent investment in Foynes Port.  It is a sign of the economy recovering and I commend all involved.</p> <p>Senators Mulherin, Feighan and Paddy Burke called for the Minister for Culture, Heritage and the Gaeltacht to attend the House on the birds and habitats directive.  All three Senators made pertinent points about getting the balance right between development and preserving and protecting endangered species or habitats.  We must get that right because we must have progress.  Yesterday, I forgot to mention that Senator Mulherin has been raising the fodder crisis for some time.  She also has been advocating balanced regional development for a long time, as have Senators Feighan and Paddy Burke.</p> <p>I told Senator Devine that we would not oppose the motion concerning a non-HSE parent representative being on the HSE primary care national steering group for children with complex medical needs.  The Minister was brought to the House on the matter.  At the time, he explained his and the HSE's reasoning why there should not be a parent representative on the board in question.  I am not going to rehash that debate.  I have had correspondence from parents on the matter myself.  The Minister is not bound by a motion of the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.183" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#N00500"><p>I am aware of that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.184" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#N00600"><p>It is important there is parent representation on the expert advisory group's sub-committee.  I would be happy to talk to the Minister again on the matter.</p> <p>Senators Feighan and Coghlan raised the issue of the House of Lords vote on Brexit yesterday and the statement it sends.  We should all reflect on what the House of Lords voted on yesterday.  The Seanad Brexit committee, which Senator Richmond chairs, will resume its work and be holding public meetings in a couple weeks.  It is my intention to have the Minister of State, Deputy McEntee, to the House to discuss Brexit.</p> <p>I have engaged with Senator Mac Lochlainn on the damage to the riverside park in Swan Park, Buncrana, County Donegal.  I am disappointed he has not got his meeting.  I will endeavour to take up the issue with the relevant Minister.  When the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government, Deputy Eoghan Murphy, was in Donegal, he was presented with the petition to which the Senator referred.  I will be talking to the Department afterwards regarding this matter.</p> <p>I share Senator Warfield's views on the two matters he raised.  There is no disagreement from me.  It is daft to put it mildly that the vote in the Lower House is being opposed and objective sex education cannot be pursued in a cross-party manner.  One of the ancillary recommendations of the committee on the eighth amendment concerned sex education.  It beggars belief that in a modern democracy-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.185" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#N00700"><p>It beggars belief the opposition to it is coming from a republican party.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.186" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#N00800"><p>I am not getting into that debate today.</p> <p>Senator Warfield is also right on the LGBT issue.  Some of those people would not give us any rights at all.  That must be highlighted and called out.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.187" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#N00900"><p>Senator Mark Daly has proposed an amendment to the Order of Business, "That No. 61, motion 14, be taken today without debate."  Is the amendment agreed to?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.188" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Order of Business, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.189" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#N01050">Pulitzer Prize: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.190" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#N01100"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That Seanad &Eacute;ireann recognises the outstanding achievement of the Storm Lake Times newspaper, Storm Lake, Iowa, winning the Pulitzer Prize for editorial writing by its editor Mr. Art Cullen, whose ancestors came from Ireland.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.191" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#N01200"><p>I second the motion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.192" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.193" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 12.35 p.m. and resumed at 12.45 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.194" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#P00100">Public Service Broadcasting and Social Media Regulation: Statements</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.195" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1234" speakername="Denis Naughten" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#P00200"><p>I thank the Seanad for the invitation to discuss a number of topics relating to public service broadcasting and social media regulation.  The issues raised include public service broadcasting in general, RT&Eacute;&rsquo;s strategy plan, RT&Eacute; advertising, licence fee income, the sale of RT&Eacute; State assets and the regulation of social media.  The opportunity to discuss our views on these issues is both timely and welcome.  Senators will be aware that the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Communications, Climate Action and Environment recently considered the future funding of our public service media and launched its report in November.  The recommendations made in this report are an important input into the deliberations by myself and my Department.</p> <p>Before I go into these issues, I wish to make reference to the issues raised in the other House in the past 24 hours.  I am in a difficult position, in that I have to comment on an alleged reference to me in an alleged affidavit that is supposed to be before the courts.  We have all been cautioned by Mr. Justice Peter Kelly on the issue so I am constrained in what I can say.  However, I want to let this House know that the view I gave to Mr. &Oacute; Neachtain was based solely on information that was in the public domain at that stage.  I did not have any information as Minister when I spoke with Mr. &Oacute; Neachtain in early November and the view I gave was as a result of reading media reports, like any other Member of this House or D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann.  I pointed out that he was the person who had informed me of the Competition and Consumer Protection Commission's decision and the discussion I had with him was in advance of the file coming to me as Minister.  When I spoke in the D&aacute;il, approximately a month later, an active file in my Department was under consideration and I was awaiting a report from my officials.  I stated in the D&aacute;il that I would make my decision based on that.</p> <p>I also stated clearly to Mr. &Oacute; Neachtain, in the very brief conversation I had with him, that I would decide solely on the advice given to me by my officials and I would not deviate from that.  That is exactly what I did.  I am not responsible for the way Mr. &Oacute; Neachtain interpreted that conversation or how he fed it back to his clients.  I sincerely regret expressing my view on this at that time.  I did not see anything wrong.  Anybody who knows me knows I am an accessible Minister to my constituents, to colleagues on all sides of both Houses in Leinster House, and to the media.  In fact, my mobile phone number is on my website.  I sincerely regret expressing a view on it but I am absolutely clear that I said I would abide by the recommendations of my officials and the files clearly show that that is exactly what I did.  The files are there for anyone who wishes to inspect them and I would facilitate that.</p> <p>I hosted a very interesting and successful open policy debate on online safety in March of this year and I am looking forward to hearing Members' views on these important issues today.  Public service broadcasting is provided for in Part 7 of the Broadcasting Act 2009.  The Act sets out the principal objects of the public service broadcasting corporations, RT&Eacute; and TG4, and provides the companies&rsquo; statutory obligations.  They include the specific objective of providing national, free-to-air public service broadcasting services.  They also include the provision of a broad range of other additional services that are seen as fundamental to the role of the public service broadcaster.  The Act subjects the public service broadcasting corporations to a range of additional requirements in their pursuit of these objects.</p> <p>Public service broadcasters play an important part in our democratic society.  Their role is more important than ever in a world of fake news where having credible, Irish sources of news and factual information is vital in protecting our democratic values and national perspective.  I believe that Irish audiences value our public service broadcasters in this regard.  Survey results in the Reuters digital news report of 2017 show that 66% of respondents used RT&Eacute; as their main source of news.  This is significantly higher than the international average of 49%.  For example, at the peak of Storm Emma, 950,000 people tuned in to watch RT&Eacute;&rsquo;s "Six One News".</p> <p>It is not only news and current affairs that are critical elements of public service broadcasting.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Denis Naughten:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=809"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=809&amp;amp;pid=DenisNaughten&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=04&amp;amp;day=19"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->With the increased availability of international channels and the advent of online content providers such as Netflix and Amazon, it is more important than ever that we invest in Irish content.  We need strong public service broadcasters that have the resources to produce and broadcast material which says something about who we are as a people and which helps to sustain a distinctive national identity.  Public service broadcasters are important, not just for raising the level of awareness on topical issues but also because they support a vibrant independent production sector in Ireland.  In any given year, the majority of Irish television programming is made or commissioned by RT&Eacute;.  This ensures that Irish audiences have access to high-quality Irish programming and is also vital to sustain and grow Irish talent on screen and in the independent production sector.  Both RT&Eacute; and TG4 support thousands of jobs across the Irish economy, not just those of people directly employed by the broadcasters.  Both public service broadcasters spend millions of euro each year on independently produced programming that has a significant impact within local economies.</p><p>All of this requires significant funding.  RT&Eacute; is dual funded through a proportion of television licence fee receipts and the commercial revenue it generates.  TG4 is funded by way of a combination of direct Exchequer grant, television licence fee receipts and commercial revenue.  As the House is aware, public service broadcasting is in serious financial trouble.  Substantial falls in commercial income and advertising revenue and increases in television licence fee evasion have all had a negative impact.  For example, RT&Eacute; earns &euro;100 million less now in commercial income than it did in 2008.  TG4 has suffered cuts in its public funding levels and is facing a major challenge to increase its audience numbers and commercial revenue.</p><p>There are a number of reasons for this reduction.  The impact of regionally targeted opt-out advertising has had a serious negative effect.  This is the practice whereby UK-based broadcasters create a mirror version of their channels for broadcast into Ireland.  While the content is the same, the mirror channel contains advertising content directed at Irish viewers.  These channels are created at a marginal cost and once this cost is met from advertising revenue, the channel makes a profit.  This allows the channel to sell advertising at a reduced rate.  In 2016, 39 of the 49 channels selling advertising in Ireland were opt-out channels and it is estimated that this form of advertising takes between &euro;40 and &euro;50 million in advertising revenue in the Irish market each year.</p><p>The growth of online advertising is also having an impact on commercial revenues available to the Irish broadcasting sector.  For example, the share of advertising spend in the digital sector has risen from 7% in 2007 to the current figure of 40%, representing an increase from &euro;100 million to &euro;445 million.  Of this, Google and Facebook obtain 75% of spend in the digital sector.  One step I have taken to counter these issues is my intention to seek Cabinet approval to further amend the Broadcasting Act 2009 to remove the hourly limit on advertising for commercial radio stations.  In conjunction with this, and to ensure fairness across the market, I will allow RT&Eacute; greater flexibility in respect of its hourly limits on radio advertising.</p><p>Both RT&Eacute; and TG4 have prepared five-year strategies for the period 2018-22.  These are currently being considered by the Broadcasting Authority of Ireland as part of its five-year review of public funding and I expect its view on these documents shortly.  RT&Eacute; has committed to focus more on digital platforms in the coming years.  It is no secret that online streaming services have become more popular than traditional broadcasting for younger people.  Making Irish-made, quality content available online is an important strategy for ensuring that younger audiences will continue to watch and listen to RT&Eacute;.  This work will be carried out by a new production unit called Digital Lab, which will create online content, bite-size video shorts, podcasts and digital series.  This is the way forward.  I believe RT&Eacute; has recognised that times are changing and it is moving with the times.  However, in order for RT&Eacute; and TG4 to carry out the objectives required of them and remain relevant in an increasingly digital world, significant additional resources will be required in the years ahead.  This is something my officials and I are examining at present.</p><p>RT&Eacute; concluded the sale of part of its Donnybrook site in July 2017, a sale known as Project Montrose  As the House will be aware, the gross proceeds from the sale of the Donnybrook lands were &euro;107.5 million.  However, considerable costs and related taxes are required to be deducted from the gross proceeds in order to arrive at the net land sale gain.  RT&Eacute; has informed the Department that the land sale will not solve ongoing operating challenges but the proceeds will likely be spent across three strands, namely, capital investment, organisational restructuring and reducing borrowings.  The sale of these under-utilised lands at Montrose is welcome and will provide RT&Eacute; with an injection of capital funding to reinvest, allowing for upgrades to technology and facilities, restructuring and reducing debt, ensuring it can compete with international broadcasters and continue to deliver on its public service broadcasting remit.</p><p>RT&Eacute; is funded through a mix of licence fee and commercial revenue.  In2008, its total income was &euro;440 million.  Today, it stands at &euro;340 million.  RT&Eacute; returned an operating deficit in 2015 and 2016, there were further operating losses in 2017 and deficits are inevitable for the coming years.  This is a scenario that cannot be allowed to continue.  The current television licence system faces a number of challenges, the current unacceptable levels of evasion being the most obvious.  While the rate has fallen from 15.3% at the end of 2013 to the current rate of 14.6%, it is very high.  Effectively, everyone who pays the television licence fee pays &euro;39 to cover the cost of those who will not pay.  This affects both the public service broadcasters and the independent sector.  Reducing the evasion rate would provide a mechanism to support a vibrant broadcasting sector without imposing additional charges on the public.  The high level of evasion represents an annual loss of approximately &euro;40 million to public service broadcasting.  Ultimately, members of the public are the losers here as the lack of funding means they are not getting the quality Irish content to which they are entitled, especially the majority who pay the television licence fee.</p><p>While the existing television licence fee model has provided a measure of stability to date, the rapid changes in technology, altering the traditional way in which television is watched, together with economic pressures generally, mean that a serious question mark exists over the ability of the current funding model to provide continued stable funding for public service media in the long term.  In addition to this review of future funding, I obtained Government approval to draft a number of legislative amendments to the Broadcasting Act 2009, including amendments for the tendering of the television licence fee collection system.  Once this legislative amendment has been enacted, it will be possible to hold a public procurement competition to tender for a new collection agent.  However, we are protecting the mechanism whereby people can buy their television licence through local post offices.</p><p>I have also made a number of proposals which, once implemented, will assist the broadcasting sector.  For example, the Broadcasting (Amendment) Bill provides for the introduction of a new funding scheme to offer bursaries to journalists working in local or community radio stations.  It also provides for a reduction in the broadcasting levy, which will alleviate the burden on broadcasters.  This proposal will reduce the overall levy to be paid by the sector and would be applied evenly across all broadcasters, with community broadcasters being completely exempt.  The committee issued its pre-legislative scrutiny report on these proposals on 8 March.  My officials are considering the report and it is also being considered by the Parliamentary Counsel in the drafting process.</p><p>The Leader asked me to refer to online safety, a complex matter in respect of which many Departments have responsibility.  A wide range of initiatives from the Government, the European Commission, non-governmental organisations, NGOs, industry and others, are in train.  However, as a Government, we recognise that we must demonstrate and deliver a more joined-up approach in respect of this matter for our citizens.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Denis Naughten:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=809"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=809&amp;amp;pid=DenisNaughten&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=04&amp;amp;day=19"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->When we speak about online safety, we are seeking to address a wide spectrum of content and behaviour.  At one end of this spectrum are the most heinous criminal acts committed by criminals.  At the other end, we find abusive or hurtful comments posted by individual users, some of whom are children. On8 March 2018, I hosted an open policy debate on the subject of online safety at the Royal Hospital Kilmainham in Dublin which was opened by An Taoiseach.  Over 120 representatives from a range of stakeholders participated, including NGOs, industry, parents' groups and young people.  The event was supported by five other Ministers and organised in conjunction with the Departments of Justice and Equality; Education and Skills; Health: Business, Enterprise and Innovation; and Children and Youth Affairs.  A recording of the event is available to view on my Department&rsquo;s website.</p><p>In opening the event, An Taoiseach announced that it was the Government&rsquo;s intention to prepare by June of this year an action plan on online safety with an integrated set of measures which we will use to ensure we support online safety at all levels.  My Department will actively contribute to the preparation of that plan and a report on the open policy debate will form one of the inputs to the plan.  The actions contained in this plan will be complementary to the initiatives being progressed by the European Commission, including the communication regarding illegal content on online platforms, the revision of the audiovisual media services directive and the EU Safer Internet programme.  Ireland believes we are in a much stronger position when we work with our European partners to agree a set of harmonised measures to address our common concerns.  </p><p>I must also recognise the excellent work which the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Children and Youth Affairs has carried out since September 2017 in considering the subject of online safety.  The committee held a series of meetings and heard from a number of academics, industry practitioners, young people themselves and departmental officials.  I must highlight one meeting in particular which was held on 21 February this year when four senior Cabinet Ministers gave evidence to the committee together.  I believe this is unprecedented and it is a clear sign of this Government&rsquo;s commitment to the subject of online safety.  The committee&rsquo;s report and recommendations will also be considered by the relevant Departments in the preparation of the action plan.</p><p>In the context of social media regulation, I should also mention the Online Advertising and Social Media (Transparency) Bill brought forward by Deputy James Lawless.  We are all aware that in various electoral processes around the world, social media has been misused to seek to manipulate public opinion through targeted advertising.  During the Second Stage debate on the Bill, I acknowledged that Deputy Lawless had identified a very important issue which goes to the heart of our democratic processes.  However, as currently drafted, the Bill has some significant flaws that could give rise to a number of unintended consequences.  For example, the legislation fails to recognise the role that should be played by the Standards in Public Office Commission in the regulation of such matters.  Its definitions are drawn too broadly and it could potentially lead to restrictions on the advertising of matters that are clearly not in scope, for example, constituency clinics.</p><p>With regard to all online regulation, we need to ensure that we strike an appropriate balance between free speech and clear and proportionate regulation, and that we draw on relevant national and international expertise in this matter.  With this in mind, the Government has established an interdepartmental group to consider the issues arising from recent experiences in other democratic countries with regard to the use of social media by external, anonymous or hidden third parties.  It will focus on the risks arising from disinformation spread by social media and other means, particularly in respect of safeguarding the integrity of electoral processes.  My Department is represented on that group which is chaired by the Department of the Taoiseach.  We are faced with the reality that the speed of innovation in media generally, and online media in particular, poses real challenges for legislators worldwide.  We need to ensure that public service broadcasters and traditional media continue to thrive and that there is an effective but proportionate regulatory regime of the online world that allows for innovation and freedom of expression while protecting citizens and young people.  I would be happy to hear Members' views and questions on these important matters.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.198" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#R00200"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House, particularly when he is in the middle of difficulties in his Department.  We will not add to those difficulties today because they are being dealt with in the D&aacute;il.  I respect the Minister for coming in today knowing that these issues might be discussed or considered.  He has also outlined to the House the current situation regarding the proposed acquisition by INM of Celtic Media.  The Minister will be aware that on 7 February 2017, the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Communications, Climate Action and Environment spent a considerable period of time taking submissions which we were then to submit to the Broadcasting Authority of Ireland under competition legislation from 2002.  We held public sessions that were attended by Robert Pitt, the then CEO of INM; Gerry Lennon, managing director of INM regionals; Frank Mulrennan, CEO of Celtic Media; and S&eacute;amus Dooley, secretary of the National Union of Journalists.  We spent a considerable period of time-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.199" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#R00300"><p>Forgive me for interrupting but I should point out that Members should exercise restraint in making their contributions and should not stray into the merits or details of any cases currently before the courts or into matters that could directly encroach upon the functions of the courts.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.200" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#R00400"><p>I appreciate that.  I am not making any reference whatsoever.  I am just pointing out that the media has not picked up the considerable debate we had on 7 February.  It might be of assistance in terms of current contributions.  At that stage, I was in favour of INM buying Celtic Media.  Nobody else was queuing up to buy it at the time and 98 jobs were involved, including at <i>The Anglo Celt</i>and newspapers in Westmeath.  I am just making a point.  It is all on record so if the media wishes to investigate what is there, it is on the Internet.  We made our case.  It was not unanimous.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.201" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#R00500"><p>I appreciate that the Senator is making his case but we are dealing with statements on public service broadcasting and social media regulation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.202" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#R00600"><p>I am just saying that we sent our deliberations to the Broadcasting Authority of Ireland.  That is all I am saying on that particular issue.  The reality is that the horse has bolted; the deal is off.  It is no longer relevant as far as I am concerned.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.203" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#R00700"><p>I do not wish to go into the deal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.204" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#R00800"><p>This is a very current issue and this Seanad must be current.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.205" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#R00900"><p>I know but the Chair must be careful.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.206" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#R01000"><p>I am just making a contribution to be helpful.  I am reminding people that this matter was debated for hours and we-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.207" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#R01100"><p>This is about public service broadcasting.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.208" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#R01200"><p>Will you leave me alone for God's sake.  The Minister outlined the situation and I am responding to be helpful in this regard.  I am not making any accusation about the Minister, who is a constituency colleague of mine in Roscommon.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.209" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#R01300"><p>I know you are not.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.210" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#R01400"><p>I respect the fact that it is a very difficult task and Ministry.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.211" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#R01500"><p>I think we should avoid it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.212" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#R01600"><p>I know what it is like being in government and the pressures I was under at particular times.  There were issues in my constituency.</p><p>The other point I want to make, and I do not think the Leas-Chathaoirleach will be able to comment, is that <i>The Irish Times</i>proposes to acquire Landmark Media Group.  That is being considered.  I certainly have an interest in this.  I am sure the Minister cannot express a interest anymore on an individual basis.  The <i>Roscommon Herald</i>is part of this proposed acquisition of Landmark Media Group by <i>The Irish Times</i>.  The agreement has been reached.  I hope this matter will be processed expeditiously because there are far too many delays.  <i>The Irish Times</i>and Landmark Media Investments signed a shared purchase agreement whereby <i>The Irish Times</i>will acquire all of the publishing and media interests of the Landmark Media Group.  The transaction is subject to a number of conditions, which include receipt of regulatory approvals from the Competition and Consumer Protection Commission, the Minister and the Broadcasting Authority of Ireland.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Terry Leyden:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=636"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=636&amp;amp;pid=TerryLeyden&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=04&amp;amp;day=19"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The process is too slow.  Business moves very fast.  Independent media outlets are vital but commitments were made by INM to Celtic Media that there would be freedom.  Like me, Senator O'Reilly is a member of the committee and he might recall the very detailed debate we had at that time.  We were very anxious to protect the integrity of the organisation.</p><p>I welcome the Minister's comprehensive contribution.  I wish to say "Well done" with regard to An Post and the record profits.  I was not very anxious to pay &euro;1 for a stamp and said at the time that it could be a case of the law of diminishing returns, but the chief executive said on "Morning Ireland" earlier that it was very successful and raised extra revenue.  Parcel delivery is a growth area, which is very exciting.  This is a good news story.  The Minister's efforts to protect the sub-post office system are also welcome.  I understand he is to make a statement on Friday or at the weekend.  That is very positive.  It is part of the Minister's portfolio and I welcome that.  There was a period during which there was some concern.  An Post was in dire straits when the Minister came to office but he took action.  It was not particularly popular but it is working out well.  The point has been made that we have a national postal service with deliveries every day to every part of Ireland, from Killybegs to Killaloe.  Every place gets its post.  That is a major achievement and it should be recognised.</p><p>I was formerly a Minister of State at the then Department of Posts and Telegraphs in the 1980s.  It was an exciting time in that area at that stage, but Departments did not really recognise the advent of the Internet.  They should have been more active in that regard and should have had Internet units at every post office to assist people.  Even now it would be a great service to offer to farmers and others who do not have access to the Internet.  Quite a number of people do not have the capacity to go through the system.  That is an area of development.</p><p>I compliment our public broadcasters, RT&Eacute; and TG4, TV3 and all the radio stations.  Any additional revenue the Minister can generate from the TV licence should be concentrated on local radio, particularly local radio's coverage of current affairs and sport.  The Minister's heart is in that area as well.  People in Roscommon, Monaghan and Cavan basically get all their information from Shannonside Northern Sound, MidWest Radio and Midlands 103.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.214" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#S00200"><p>Hear, hear.  I agree.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.215" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#S00300"><p>The stations are finding it difficult to survive in a competitive environment.  The news they generate is being taken by all the other platforms and broadcast around the world.  They have to generate the news but they do not get any payment for it, other than from the listeners.</p> <p>I thank the Minister.  He has done well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.216" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#S00400"><p>I warmly welcome the Minister.  I thank him for setting our some of the issues and difficulties, which I do not propose to discuss in detail.  I certainly do not wish to speak about INM, Celtic Media or any other media outfit.  I am conscious that there are proceedings and affidavits before the court so it is not appropriate to comment in detail on them.</p> <p>I thank the Minister for his comprehensive report.  Incidentally, my colleague, Senator Billy Lawless, asked me to apologise for his absence.  He had to go to a meeting.  He wishes to support the Minister and to thank him for coming to the House.  He asked me to put that on the record for him.  I thank the Minister for outlining his strategy for RT&Eacute;.  He dealt with RT&Eacute;'s advertising, the licence income - and he spoke in detail about the loss of the substantial sum of &euro;40 million in potential income - and the sale of RT&Eacute;'s assets, as well as the cost of regulating the social media.</p> <p>I do not have many questions.  The "Oireachtas Report" programme is now gone; RT&Eacute; has ceased broadcasting it.  A number of Senators met representatives from RT&Eacute; in recent weeks in a meeting organised by Senator Norris and the rationale was teased out again.  The RT&Eacute; representatives had already come here previously to speak to the political groups in the Oireachtas.  I am aware of how RT&Eacute; is changing in terms of online, digital and other new mechanisms for broadcasting but, as the previous speaker indicated, there are still some people who do not have access, or who choose or do not wish to have access, to other forms of media.  Those individuals liked "Oireachtas Report".  I accept that there is a substantial cost factor and that a number of staff are directly involved.  However, as is its right, RT&Eacute; has taken that commercial decision.</p> <p>I have a suggestion, although I do not know how it could be worked through.  Perhaps RT&Eacute;, through the Minister's good offices in contacts with the station, would look at the excellent Oireachtas service here.  There is already a brilliant Oireachtas service so could there be some synergies or an arrangement between Oireachtas TV, which is ongoing here in any event, and RT&Eacute; or, for that matter, with other broadcasters in that regard?  There are plans to have a new studio for political broadcasts on the Leinster House campus.  It is important that this does not become an exclusive facility for RT&Eacute; either.  There must be a level playing field.  That is another issue the Minister could examine because it is important.  We have to give access to independent broadcasting companies and independent radio stations to communicate.  It is all about communication and broadcasting.  At some stage, where it is appropriate, we should look at what already exists here and whether there can be some type of synergy between independent broadcasting and RT&Eacute;, if it so wishes and if it considers it appropriate, because I believe there is something good in that.</p> <p>Perhaps the Minister might clarify a matter regarding Project Montrose.  We know that is &euro;107 million was realised and that legal fees, taxes and other obligations must be paid from that.  However, they will not be very substantial in terms of the &euro;107 million obtained on foot of the sale of lands at Montrose.  Is the Minister saying that the money is being retained wholly and exclusively for RT&Eacute;?  I am not sure if that is right because there are other calls on some of the money.  The Minister will recall that there was a call for an audit of all State lands - I am not suggesting that it should all go to the delivery of social and affordable housing - and I would have considered the lands at Montrose to be owned by the State.  I am not sure that is necessarily a good way to spend the money.  Why is it all being retained by RT&Eacute;?  The Minister might explain the reason for that.</p> <p>I acknowledge the potential loss of &euro;40 million.  Ultimately, the public will be the loser if people do not pay the licence fee.  The Minister said he is going to look again at the issue.  Will he confirm or rule out the possibility of a digital tax for each home, which was something one of his predecessors proposed?  That proposal did not go down very well.  What are the Minister's views on the matter?</p> <p>The Minister said that the Government will establish an interdepartmental group to consider issues arising from the recent experiences in other democratic countries regarding the use of social media by external, anonymous and hidden third parties.  I welcome that initiative.  Perhaps the Minister would share the timelines for that work, indicate when it will deliver some strong recommendations and outline how all of that will be bedded down in some type of legislative format.  That is important.</p> <p>I wish the Minister well.  I have always found him to be a man of probity and high integrity in his work.  He said that he runs a very open system.  That is true.  I wish to give testament to that fact and to acknowledge that any dealings I have had with him or his Department have been open and transparent.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.217" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#S00500"><p>I welcome the Minister and thank him for doing the House the courtesy of making a statement on recent events.  Without engaging in wrong practice in respect of the event, all I can say, as Senators Leyden and Boyhan have said, is that as a member of the Joint Committee on Communications, Climate Action and Environment and having had the privilege of working with the Minister in both Houses of the Oireachtas over a number of years, I know him to be a man of absolute integrity who engages in absolute due process in all his dealings and who is above reproach.  If an error was ever made it would be in methodology, it would never be an error in due process.  The Minister is a great colleague and an excellent, proactive Minister.  I believe that is the view across the House and in many ways it is reflected in the response in this debate.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Joe O'Reilly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1610"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1610&amp;amp;pid=JoeOReilly&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=04&amp;amp;day=19"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is interesting that the Minister on this occasion was exhausting all investigative procedure and was allowing complete due process to take place.  He could have acted differently were he to have had a vested interest.  Were he to have had a vested interest, he could have operated in a different way at the outset.  He is a man of absolute probity and personal decency and somebody I know very well on a number of fronts and it is a privilege to work on the committee with him.<br/><br/>I turn to the events of today and the matters under discussion.  It is important we have a strongly resourced, independent national broadcasting service.  That is <i>sine qua non</i>.  It is something that should not even be considered a matter for debate.  It needs to be resourced and supported.  Local radio is also important, and Senator Leyden talked about this.  In my area Northern Sound is extraordinarily important to a lot of people and it is their source of news and information.  I am delighted that the Minister has decided to bring forward legislation to remove the hourly limit on advertising.  That will be helpful.  I welcome that there will be new funding for journalists working in local radio stations.  It is important and it would be negligent of me to represent the people I represent and not cite the interest they have in this question and in having a strong local radio service.<br/><br/>I am happy to know that by June the Taoiseach has committed to an action plan on online safety and that the reports will be looked at.  Deputy Lawless's Bill, which he talked about at the committee the other day, is a very helpful input, albeit needing the amendments cited by the Minister.<br/><br/>I refer to cyberbullying, abuse, misinformation, wrong information and, in some instances, pornography, etc., becoming available to young people.  Action is needed and the Minister is committed to this action, but as a parent, teacher and public representative, I can only stress the horror that is involved there, the real fear parents have around this and the need to deal with it.<br/><br/>I refer to recent events in relation to Facebook and social media.  It must be recognised that the basic premise on which social media operates is how they make their money.  The commercial premise on which they operate is to have names - two billion persons in the case of Facebook - who are the recipients of potential advertising.  That is fair enough and that is how it works.  It cannot be otherwise and we support that.  We recognise our domestic interest in the success of Facebook, what it means to Dublin and to Ireland.<br/><br/>Having said that, I refer to a situation where the private information of individuals can be harvested by sinister groupings and used to manipulate democracy, thwart the natural electoral processes and damage how elections function.  I know this is more prevalent in America and that, through the European Commission, there are rules which make it more difficult here.  However, at the same time, one has to state in this House that we have to be sure.  I appeal to the Minister to look at this in the context of the upcoming referendum.  We want to be sure that nothing untoward happens in the referendum on the eighth amendment and in the next general election and that that kind of information could not be manipulated, or voters exploited in this fashion.  That is extraordinarily important.<br/><br/>I mention something of which I and former and current Members of the Houses of the Oireachtas have been victims, namely, that is the use of fake accounts on social media to disseminate falsehoods, to play on a vulnerable audience and to present untruths.  Thankfully, in my case I had the mental resources and strength to cope with it.  That was not always the case for colleagues and it can be very difficult.  I know of many colleagues who have suffered a lot emotionally and personally because of this kind of online activity.  I refer to the elimination of fake accounts and rigorous processes being adopted by the social media outlets to eliminate fake accounts, recognise them and deal with them.  If there is one thing about I feel very strongly and which the Minister might take from my contribution to today's debate, it would be that.  That is extraordinarily serious, as is the harvesting of information, without people's willingness to provide it, to thwart democracy and to target advertising towards vulnerable people in a way they do not understand and to focus advertisements on their emotional conditions.  For people who are naturally fearful, there is a set of political advertising creating a fear in them and telling them untruths or manipulated truth based on that.  It is important we have control of our social media and that people know their private data cannot be used.  In some instances, it was even being used years after they had left the social media sites.  That should not happen.<br/><br/>I am heartened the Minister recognises, and once again commits himself to, the critical importance of an independent national news service and the augmenting and supporting of RT&Eacute; and TG4 to provide that and that he recognises the importance of local radio and the new services they provide to the people I represent and to people right across the country.<br/><br/>I also welcome the fact cyberbullying is recognised as a problem to be dealt with head on and that social media outlets would be controlled in a way that the data presented by people, and given in good faith, cannot be wrongly used.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.219" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#T00200"><p>I will not touch on the issues raised in regard to media mergers, except in so far as the Minister raised the question of his regret about the phone call that he made to Mr. &Oacute; Neachtain.  I accept the Minister has regret over the phone call, but I appeal for us to be careful about the language we use.  It is important if we are to restore the confidence of the public in politics that we do not suggest, for example, that it is personal when we talk to a key stakeholder who is affected by a decision and we are the decision maker.  That has to be really clear.  It is not personal in that context.  It cannot be considered to be personal when we are talking about a specific power of the Government in that regard.</p> <p>I refer to the phrase "we are not responsible for how information is used".  If we were to send out a signal to the public that we send information and we are not responsible for how it is used, that would be a really negative message to send.  We need to be clear and careful.  I have worked with the Minister on other issues and I respect that he is trying to move forward, but let us be very careful because we need to send a signal to the public that we recognise that is not an adequate excuse.</p> <p>We also need to ensure nothing is done to undermine the important role the independent institutions set up as checks and balances to how politics is done in this State, be it the Office of the Director of Corporate Enforcement, the Comptroller and Auditor General or the Data Protection Commissioner, play in politics and democracy in Ireland.  I will not speak further on this.  I simply wanted to respond because the Minister had raised that issue himself.</p> <p>I welcome the Minister's recognition of the deep importance of public service broadcasting, of what it says to us as a nation and of its importance in how it shapes our shared discussions and narratives.  There are wider issues I had hoped to address on public service broadcasting because we need to ensure public service broadcasting represents all the voices of the nation.  There have been issues of diversity within public service broadcasting.  I refer to diversity in all its forms in terms of ensuring a range of voices from people from different parts of the country, from different economic backgrounds, with different abilities and from different ethnic backgrounds.  One of the key areas is in gender.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Alice-Mary Higgins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2480"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2480&amp;amp;pid=AliceMaryHiggins&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=04&amp;amp;day=19"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I was working with the National Women's Council of Ireland when we produced the voices of women on air report and I recognise that RT&Eacute; has taken steps forward regarding its presenters and the participation of women in that media.  One aspect of that research that struck me, because the figures on direct participation were so stark it is a qualitative aspect that got buried, was that women were often on radio or television to describe what had happened to them and then men came on to explain what had actually happened to them and what the policies were.  We still need to dive a little bit deeper, not only around who is brought on but that we are bringing on those who have expertise and analysis and understand their experiences.</p><p>We also need to look to the voices of civil society.  Often civil society, NGOs or trade unions, are brought in to talk about the experiences of those they work with and yet the experts who tell us about how the economy works, often framed as neutral experts, are also interested parties.  Many of those experts are deeply imbedded and working closely with those who have high stakes in the business sector who, for example, are investing in property or the financial advisers to major corporations.  We need to look at that expertise and we need a little bit of transparency when persons, such as Mr. &Oacute; Neachtain, are popping up on radio programmes so that we know where they are coming from in that context and bring the strong economic analysis that many in civil society can bring into the mix.  That is a side point.  I will go straight to my other points now.</p><p>In its public service role, it is important that we recognise our investment in public service media and broadcasting.  It is not about making this a functional business.  In the investment we make in public service broadcasting, the dividend comes out in society, for example, through our orchestras and their role.</p><p>Local radio, which was mentioned, is important.  Community radio needs more of a focus.  In that regard, I am worried by the Minister's proposal that we would seek to increase the time given to advertising on both private and public channels.  What we are doing is making the public not the beneficiaries but the target.  The public is then the product that is being sold.  Besides, we know that when one increases space for that product, the price will go down and the competition will increase.  I oppose that proposal.</p><p>There are other fora in which I will discuss other aspects of online regulation but in the limited time I have, I want to address an issue which directly affects the Minister, Deputy Naughten, and is related to online advertising.  The proportion of advertising in the digital sector is 40%, up from 7%.  It is a huge market of almost &euro;500 million.  This needs urgent regulation.  While I recognise that there are other issues around fake news and abuse online, the key issue, that we have 40% of the advertising market unregulated, cannot stand.  That needs immediate action.</p><p>In our debate, we talked about the online advertising targeting of young people, for example, whether there are any regulations about what kind of online advertising can reach or be targeted towards young people.  Crucially, because it is immediate in relation to political advertising, I absolutely support Deputy James Lawless's Bill.  It does not affect constituency clinics.  It does not impact on their conduct.  We can debate that but I do not believe it does because what it says is that one needs to be transparent about who is placing an advertisement, and that is the key factor.  Once there is transparency in political advertising, so be it.  Right now, we have a situation where online advertising regarding the referendum is taking place.  The Transparent Referendum Initiative has produced information that tells us large amounts of money is being spent anonymously, large numbers of organisations outside Ireland are buying advertising, and money is being spent on misleading and untrue content.  A large number of those advertising are hidden, anonymous, not traceable or not registered anywhere.  This is directly related and I have a question for the Minister.  In the context where that is unregulated right now, should Facebook increase its early roll-out of transparency around who is purchasing advertisements or perhaps not sell advertisements?  On those platforms for which RT&Eacute;, the national broadcaster, is responsible, Google advertisements are appearing at present.</p><p>This is a final, simple point.  It is possible for any website that accepts Google advertisements to determine at present that they do not want to receive political advertisements.  Does the Minister believe that RT&Eacute;, RT&Eacute; Junior, TG4 and other public service broadcasters should not accept political advertisements in the period leading up to the referendum at a time when those advertisements are completely unregulated?  That is a specific request.  It is something that we could do in the interim.  I would like to hear the timeline and ask that there would be cross-party input into the committee.  I would suggest that differences should be put aside-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.221" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#U00200"><p>Senator Higgins is eating into other Senators' time and I ask her to conclude.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.222" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#U00300"><p>I would suggest the Minister amend Deputy James Lawless's Bill if he needs to, but we need legislation on this before the summer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.223" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#U00400"><p>I welcome the publication last month of the report on the future funding of public broadcasting.  My colleague, Deputy Brian Stanley, is a member of the committee that produced the report and I acknowledge the role of many stakeholders in the sector that made submissions.</p> <p>What Sinn F&eacute;in certainly does not agree with is any increase in the licence fee.  There is currently a two-year review under way.</p> <p>One part of the report that we are totally opposed to is using Revenue to collect licence fees.  While we accept that there is widespread evasion - that is clear for all to see - and that this means increased amounts for those who pay, we believe that having Revenue collect it will simply lead to those already paying and those on low incomes being hit the hardest.</p> <p>During the committee's deliberation, there were many alternatives to Revenue as the main collector put forward, such as a registration scheme.  There could also be a registration scheme once consumers sign up for various services, such as cable or satellite.  Therefore, we argue that An Post should continue to collect the fee and that there needs to be better methods of collecting data as well.</p> <p>Public service broadcasting, far from becoming outdated, is becoming more vital in light of recent developments.  The era of fake news both on TV and online means that news providers in which the public has a stake are more important than ever.  While we may not always agree with what the national broadcaster shows or with the opinions expressed, at least there is a complaints mechanism and some form of monitoring.  I take the opportunity to commend RT&Eacute; on its recent "National Treasures" show.  That was a valuable exercise, an all-island initiative that reached out to all of the communities on this island.</p> <p>In Ireland, there have been many attempts by individuals to gain control of a large portion of the media.  As a result, we need greater oversight of the handling of media mergers by the Government.  It is essential that Ireland has a diverse media that can accommodate broad political and civil debate and the free exchange of ideas.</p> <p>A free and open media requires the Irish language, gender representation and ethnic and religious minorities should be allowed adequate space in the media market.  The promotion of the Irish language in broadcasting is essential to the language as a whole.  TG4, broadcasting under the "S&uacute;iI Eile" slogan, has done sterling work, not only in promoting Irish language and culture, but in offering an alternative narrative.  TG4 is highly respected and the Government should be willing to offer its support.  We also need pressure on the British Government to ensure the permanency of the Irish language broadcast fund and the ongoing production of Irish language programming from the Six Counties.</p> <p>Another issue the report dealt with was the possibility of using licence fee revenue to support local radio stations.  Even though these are technically commercial entities, there is a valid argument that they provide a vital public service element through news, announcements and promotion of community projects.</p> <p>On the issue of social media and its usage, I wholeheartedly oppose the abuse, trolling and vilification of individuals on social media platforms.  In the world of politics, two women, Ms Carla Lockhart MLA of the DUP and my own colleague, Ms Michaela Boyle MLA, have been the subject of nasty and anonymous abuse on Twitter.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Fintan Warfield:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2458"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2458&amp;amp;pid=FintanWarfield&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=04&amp;amp;day=19"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This is wrong.  I also appeal to those who think that engaging with politicians in such an abusive and dehumanising way will ever achieve anything.  It merely diminishes us as a society if this is how we get our messages across.  Amnesty International recently published a report on the abuse faced by women, especially on social media such as Twitter.  An <i>Irish News</i>journalist in her story told of how criticism of her articles was mostly followed by sectarian and sexist abuse.  The role of journalists is vital and it is important that they feel safe in doing their job. Twitter also has a responsibility to make its platform a safer and less toxic space for women.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.225" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#V00200"><p>I realise that we are very tight on time, that another speaker wishes to come in and that the Minister needs to be gone by 2.05 p.m.  I will be as brief as I possibly can.</p> <p>I acknowledge the Minister's presence in the House and his first statement to this House on the issues he clarified in the D&aacute;il.  They are a very appropriate and honest reflection of what happened in those events.  I acknowledge the Minister's contribution on this issue.  I believe he has been a very honourable Minister and I fully support him in his endeavours.</p> <p>The Minister has two major problems with regard to the proposals on where we are going with public service broadcasting and social media.  I see two real issues, one of which is the sustainability of RT&Eacute; in the next decade and where RT&Eacute; will fit into the global media.  The other issue is the regulation of social media.  On Tuesday we had a very interesting debate with a vice-president from Facebook at the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Communications, Climate Action and Environment.  The space has moved so much in that way in the last few years.  One would have to question where we are going with RT&Eacute; as an entity going forward.</p> <p>Consider the amount of money going into social media platforms and the changes in people's behaviours.  How many people do not even have a television set now?  People have a tablet or a mobile phone.  People do not even want their television sets.  When they speak of TV it is about Netflix and not RT&Eacute;.  The Minister has said that there are exceptions such as when there is a storm and people want to see what is happening locally.  On average, however, people watch their Netflix and their box sets and that is how they get their information.  This is how fake media will have an awful input to society, especially if people are looking at Facebook and Twitter.  This will be a huge issue for us to regulate in the next few years.  The challenges are immense and this portfolio brings exceptionally important challenges to us as a society.</p> <p>With regard to RT&Eacute; and the failure to collect TV licences at an appropriate level, it is really the elephant in the room.  We have had a sale of land at Montrose in the last few years, which brought in &euro;107 million.  That will not happen again.  We need to look at the long-term vision of how RT&Eacute; is to be sustainable.  The broadcaster got that injection of cash but I cannot see any more lands being developed unless it takes the amazing step of moving away from the Donnybrook site.  RT&Eacute; can broadcast from any location in the State.  Why does it need to be in the exclusive environment of Donnybrook?  Should we look at moving the RT&Eacute; complex to a more suitable site and develop the entire complex itself?  Is that the injection that is required for RT&Eacute; to get a footing, or a leg underneath the table, so it can move on to become sustainable?  The word "sustainable" in the context of RT&Eacute; is the big issue in the room.</p> <p>Revenues are falling.  We have seen where the advertising is going.  We need to keep our national broadcaster.  This is going to be the strategy for the boss there; I was going to say the new boss but she is far from being the new boss as she has been in the position for more than 18 months.  That is going to be the long-term strategy if we are to ensure that RT&Eacute; stays in that space, with a real dimension of social media and where our news is to come from.  If five years ago I had said that most of our news was going to come through Twitter and Facebook people would have laughed.  We must be able to see where RT&Eacute; is going to be in ten years' time and where that space is.  This is a real dilemma.  The strategy for RT&Eacute; must be planned out and it must be an evolving and changing strategy.  The broadcaster has money coming in through the sale of land but it is only a stopgap.  A change to RT&Eacute; practices or perhaps a move to another site to start with a clean bill of health might be the appropriate way of moving RT&Eacute; forward.</p> <p>I shall now turn to Internet safety.  It is a huge issue.  There were more than 100 parents at a public meeting about the issue in Clonakilty last Monday.  It is a massive space affecting children's ability to access data.  Teenagers' ability to gain access to information will take a lot of education for parents - not for the children.  The kids know more about this space than their parents.  This will involve a whole generational change and will involve parents taking ownership of the issues.  I do not believe they have taken ownership of it.  It is a huge debate given that a child aged eight, nine or ten years could can have a phone with Internet capability and a parent who does not know what the child could look at or what the child is looking at.  First we must educate the parents on what needs to be done with regard to Internet safety.  Is it right that children have data or Wi-Fi around the house 24 hours a day?  To me that is nuts.  Would a house have the TV on 24 hours a day?  No.  It would, however, have data and Wi-Fi on.  There are so many issues such as this that need to be debated.  It will be a huge space for us to try to get a handle on.</p> <p>I am being beckoned at now so I would like to thank the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.226" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#V00300"><p>I thank the Minister for coming to the House and for his paper on public service broadcasting and social media regulation.  It cannot be easy for the Minister to sit and listen to Senators, especially today, as the Minister has other things on is mind.  It shows something about the Minister's courage and tenacity that he can sit with dignity and do this when he must face other issues later on.  I know he will come through them.</p><p>I congratulated the Minister earlier for the role of David McRedmond as chief executive officer of An Post.  I am absolutely thrilled that An Post is now turning over a profit.  All Senators agreed because it means so much.  A post office is such a communicative and engaging place for people all over the State, in cities, towns, locales and villages.  Mr. McRedmond's ideas for the future with regard to community banking will elevate the place of the post office.  They are so essential and very much a part of ourselves.  I congratulate the Minister on this because this is a huge part of his portfolio.</p><p>I absolutely agree with Senator Boyhan on the &quot;Oireachtas Report&quot; programme.  The Senator made a very good point about the synergies of our own Oireachtas TV and the Oireachtas communications.  One aspect on which the Seanad has been very weak is communicating who we are and what we do.  We expect other people to come in and communicate it, rightly or wrongly, badly or well.  Senators should be far more proactive in how we communicate.  I take that point.</p><p>The TV licence fee and non-payment is discussed in the pubs, clubs and bus stops of Ireland.  I am interested to hear the Minister's comments about legislation on collection of the fee.  How will the Minister pursue that in the future to make sure that people who have a television set and who have media in their homes are paying for it?  This is very important because it gives back trust to the community that something is actually happening in that everybody else is also paying the bill.</p><p>I am delighted to see provisions for the development of local community radio and the bursaries for journalism.  I come from a radio background.  Radio is the most engaging, the most available, the most economical and the cheapest medium for everybody.  Irish people are great radio listeners so I welcome that proposal.</p><p>Senator Warfield made a brilliant point about the pornography of social media in the way people are treated.  It is about how pornographic language and pornographic images invade the whole media area.  The late Neil Postman was a wonderful writer who wrote a book in the 1980s titled <i>Technopoly</i>.  He also wrote <i>The Disappearance of Childhood</i>and <i>Amusing Ourselves to Death</i>.  When one thinks of these they go together.  Neil Postman said that one of society's problems was going to be pornography and the second problem was how we were going to store all the information that we now have.  He wrote of society being in a chaos or a glut of information.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Marie-Louise O'Donnell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2390"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2390&amp;amp;pid=MarieLouiseODonnell&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=04&amp;amp;day=19"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This is a difficult area to navigate and previous speakers pointed out aspects of the problem.  I agree, however, that legislation is urgently required, although one cannot legislate for morality or what takes place behind closed doors.  Young minds can be educated and I would like the national broadcaster to have more young people on radio and television.  I got into terrible trouble when I stated recently that 16 year olds should not be allowed to vote.  What I meant was that the kind of politics in which we engage may not be for young people.  However, young minds are alive, creative and imaginative and young people should be seen on television and heard on radio.  Elderly people - I am fast becoming one - are another group who we do not see often enough on panel and discussion programmes.  We do not hear them much, yet they make up a large proportion of the population.  It is within the gift of public service broadcasting to ensure our elders are heard. </p><p>I also agree with Senator Higgins that public service broadcasting is extremely important because it reflects who and what we are and how we see, investigate and place ourselves on our island and outside of it.  It is also important for music, orchestras, language and politics.  It is sad that RT&Eacute; must sell land to survive.  It must be gifted and kept alive.  RT&Eacute; has a great deal of competition and it is important it remains the core broadcaster because much of our broadcasting has been commodified.  We now have the same programme repeated at the same time, with the same advertisements and providing a supermarket type view of what and who people are.  Broadcasting should be individual, unique, fresh and creative, just like the Minister.</p><p>I wish the Minister luck and thank him for coming to the House.  I appreciate everything he is doing across a wide divide. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.228" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#W00200"><p>Before calling on the Minister to reply to Senators, I welcome students from Dublin Institute of Technology who have come all the way from Guatemala with the prestigious Network of International Business Schools, NIBS, trophy.  I understand they participated in tackling real world international business challenges and came out on top, bringing the first ever world title to Ireland and only the second ever to Europe.  They are being hosted today by Senator O'Reilly.  They are very welcome and I wish them continued success.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.229" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1234" speakername="Denis Naughten" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#W00300"><p>Only a short time is available to me as I must be in the other House in seven minutes.  I thank Senators for their contributions.  One of the major issues facing us is that of online content.  Senator Higgins raised the issue of advertising, a complex area that can probably only be regulated at European Union level rather than domestically.  Having said that, I take the Senator's point regarding RT&Eacute;.  We will write directly to RT&Eacute; and other public service broadcasters on the specific matter she raised.</p> <p>I had some engagement with Facebook and I understand the company will soon implement new standards.  We are all conscious of developments in respect of the referendum next month, as are all of the online platforms.  There is no doubt but that our legislation needs to be modernised.  Some action can be taken domestically and we need to do as much as we can.  Last year, at a conference on online safety on Facebook, I noted that legislation is a 17th century tool being used to deal with a 21st century economy.  Regardless of how quickly legislators move, we will always be behind the curve.  The challenge facing us is difficult as enacting law requires us to go through ten Stages in both Houses, which means by the time legislation is enacted, it has been superseded by technology.  We need to try to get ahead of the curve.  I honestly do not know what tools are available to achieve this, whether they are global principles or core values that can be enshrined in some form of legislation.  However, I accept that this is an ongoing challenge and one we must seek to address. </p> <p>I will ask my officials to revert to Senators with replies to their detailed questions.</p> <p>The general data protection regulation, GDPR, will address much of these issues arising in the area of data harvesting.</p> <p>Senator Lombard raised an important point when he noted that we do not have our televisions switched on for 24 hours each day, whereas we have Wi-Fi switched on 24 hours a day in our homes.  As adults, we must learn some lessons from our children regarding the way in which technology has advanced.  In fairness to the Department of Education and Skills, it has a valuable resource.  The objective should be to try to bring this out into the wider community, rather than confining it to the Department.  </p> <p>I accept that we face a major challenge in respect of public service broadcasting, which faces a funding crunch.  When I was appointed, a number of issues were causing headaches throughout the Department, one of which was the deep crisis in An Post.  There is now light at the end of the tunnel regarding An Post.  The Department is working closely with the director general, Ms Dee Forbes, and her team in RT&Eacute; to see if we can plot out a clear future and create daylight for the organisation.  RT&Eacute; should not be about the footprint of its buildings but what it can provide to society as a whole.  RT&Eacute;, TG4 and other public service broadcasters are providing a vital public service and they will be very much part of what we are culturally in future.</p> <p>Senator Marie Louise O'Donnell stated that Irish people listen to more radio than people in any other country in the world.  My colleagues in the rest of Europe do not even know what community radio stations are.  I was glad to be the first Minister to take a proactive step in supporting community radio stations and I will continue to try to do so. </p> <p>I ask Senators to propose constructive suggestions and ideas for moving this issue forward as I do not have all the solutions.  Some thoughts and ideas have been proposed at the joint committee but I would welcome and will listen to further proposals and ideas.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.230" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#W00400"><p>When is it proposed to sit again?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.231" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018041900002#W00500"><p>At 2.30 p.m. on Tuesday, 24 April 2018.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-04-19a.232" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>The Seanad adjourned at 2.10 p.m. until 2.30 p.m. on Tuesday, 24 April 2018.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>