<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.4" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#A00150">Teachtaireacht ó Chomhchoiste - Message from Joint Committee</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#A00200"><p>The Joint Committee on Health has completed its consideration of the Health and Social Care Professionals Act 2005, section 95(3), variation of Title regulation 2022.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.7" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#A00300">Gnó an tSeanaid - Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.8" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#A00400"><p>Before I read the Commencement, I welcome to the Distinguished Visitors Gallery the ambassador from Italy.  He is most welcome.  Today marks Italy's Republic Day, the establishment of the Republic of Italy in 1946.  The Irish and the Italians have a great shared history of emigration.  We are known as builders of nations, in particular in the United States of America.  Migration between our two countries has been going on for thousands of years.  Irish monks, led by Columbanus, founded a monastery near Genoa in the 7th century.  There is a strong Italian-Irish community here, dating back to the 19th and early 20th centuries, and strong links to the homeland near Valle di Comino in Frosinone province near Rome, which is where all our fish and chips experts come from.  There are approximately 50,000 Italians living in Ireland at present.  Italian companies employ more than 1,600 people here and since 2020 we have an Italian-Irish Chamber of Commerce.</p><p>Last year marked the 700th anniversary of the death of the father of the Italian language, Dante, who was a giant of world literature and is famous for <i>The Divine Comedy</i>.  This year, Ireland and Italy share the celebrations of the centenary of the publication of James Joyce's seminal work, <i>Ulysses</i>.  Joyce was at heart a Dubliner but spent 15 years in Trieste and was a pioneer of modernism.  During his time, he was a giant of the Italian literary scene and was a close friend of the best known writer of the 20th century, Italo Svevo.  Italy's day is known as Festa della Repubblica.  I wish the ambassador and all the Italians living here in Ireland a happy republic day.  I thank the ambassador for being with us.  I also thank colleagues for being here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#A00600"><p>From that celebration to this celebration of democracy.  I have received notice of the following Commencement matters from Senators this morning.  I thank them for being here for Italy's national day.</p><p>I have received notice from Senator Fiona O'Loughlin that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, she proposes to raise the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister of State with responsibility for planning and local government to provide an update on the provision of a second bridge for Newbridge, County Kildare. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Eugene Murphy of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Transport to make a statement on the need for investment in remedial safety works on the N5 from Scramogue to Ballaghaderreen, County Roscommon. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Jerry Buttimer of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine to ensure Cork is a designated port for the importation of non-EU fresh produce. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Martin Conway of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Health to provide an update on the payment of the pandemic bonus to HSE and community-based workers. </blockquote> <p>The matters raised by the Senators are suitable for discussion and they will be taken now.  The Minister of State who is taking the first Commencement matter this morning is Deputy Malcolm Noonan, who informed me that his home town is twinned with a town in Italy.  It is fortuitous that he is the first Minister in the House this morning.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.10" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#A00650">Nithe i dtosach suíonna - Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.11" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#A00700">Road Network</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#A00800"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach for selecting this very important issue for the Commencement debate, and Senator Boyhan for chairing this session.  The Minister of State, Deputy Noonan, is very welcome.  I hope he has some good news for us in terms of the new bridge for Newbridge, which is my new mantra.  I will put it up on everything that I do.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Fiona O'Loughlin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2441"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2441&amp;amp;pid=FionaOLoughlin&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=02"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Everyone in the House, in the D&aacute;il and in the area around Newbridge will know I am practically blue in the face from raising this issue.  I have repeatedly called for a second bridge in Newbridge.  I am confident there has been some progress on it and Kildare County Council is working to put in place what is needed from its end to find a solution.  The bridge we need over the River Liffey is not just a bridge in its own right as it is part of an outer distributor ring road.  The bridge is one quarter of the solution.  With Kildare County Council working proactively with developers and the industry, we are three quarters of the way there.  At national level we need funding for the bridge itself.</p><p>The people of Newbridge and the surrounding areas can wait no longer.  This has been in every development plan for Newbridge for the past 20 years.  It is vital infrastructure and has to be delivered.  I know the Minister of State is familiar with the part of Newbridge I am speaking about.  There are five schools practically on the bridge itself.  There is a church and a number of cr&egrave;ches and doctors' surgeries.  There are more than 1,500 houses in the eight housing estates that access the town through the bridge.  It is ridiculous that in 2022 we still rely on one bridge that leads right into the centre of the town.  It causes pandemonium, particularly at rush hour and when schools are opening and closing.  I have to add at least 30 minutes to my journey every morning when I drive to Leinster House.  This is indicative of what people experience and that is on a good day.</p><p>I am very proud to see Newbridge continue to grow and develop as a commercial heart.  We have seen major investment by Primark and Lidl.  Pfizer continues to grow its operations and staff numbers increase year on year.  We are also home to a large number of independent family-run businesses.  This is very positive.  It concerns me when I speak to people, particularly from outside Newbridge, for example, in Milltown, Athgarvan, Rathangan and the Curragh, who say the problem with the traffic in Newbridge, which is directly linked to the bridge, puts them off going into their main regional town.  They prefer to go elsewhere to spend their money.  There is no doubt the lack of a second bridge is not only causing problems now but it is also hindering the potential for growth in Newbridge.  Traffic and congestion are a major issue for everybody.  The system we have in Newbridge is not fit for purpose.  We do not have a proper traffic management plan.  This is mainly down to the bridge.</p><p>We should use our development levies.  For example, there was &euro;7 million for the Primark distribution centre.  In Kildare we have an agreement that 71.8% of commercial development levies go to roads.  We need co-operation at a national level.  We want to see the Department working with Kildare County Council to provide this vital infrastructure.  I have further questions but I look forward to hearing the initial response of the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1512" speakername="Malcolm Noonan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#B00200"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this matter.  I am very familiar with the beautiful town of Newbridge.  As the Senator knows, my mother is from Morristown.</p> <p>The outgoing Italian ambassador, Mr. Paolo Serpi, is in the Gallery and I wish him well.  My city of Kilkenny is twinned with Formigine, a city in northern Italy.  The ambassador has had a fantastic tenure here and I wish him well in his future appointments.</p> <p>The urban regeneration and development fund, URDF, is one of four funds established under the National Development Plan 2018-2027, and was launched in 2018, primarily to support the national planning framework's growth enablers for the five cities and other large urban centres.  The URDF provides part-funding for applicant-led projects that will support more compact and sustainable development and enable a greater proportion of residential and mixed-use development to be delivered within the existing built-up footprints of our cities and large towns, while also ensuring that more parts of our urban areas can become attractive and vibrant places in which people choose to live and work, as well as to invest and visit.</p> <p>In keeping with the aims of the national planning framework and Project Ireland 2040, the URDF demonstrates a new and more tailored approach to the provision of Government support.  Over its planned duration up to 2030, URDF support in excess of &euro;2 billion will be targeted in an integrated, dynamic and responsive way to support the regeneration and rejuvenation of our towns and cities.  Through the URDF, successful applicants receive targeted integrated support for innovative holistic solutions to the issues that have hindered the regeneration and rejuvenation of our large towns and cities.</p> <p>To date, there have been two calls for proposals under the URDF, with a total of almost &euro;312 million allocated so far in respect of the 87 projects approved under the first call, while in March 2021 URDF funding support of &euro;1.3 billion was announced in respect of a countrywide programme of a further 45 proposals approved under the second call.  To assist local authorities with the application process for the second call, the Department hosted a number of workshops to provide information on the purpose of the URDF programme and the types of proposals that would be considered for support.</p> <p>In all, 75 proposals were considered, with every local authority submitting at least one application, and involving competing demands with a total combined value exceeding &euro;2 billion.  All applications were assessed in terms of their alignment with the intended purpose of the URDF programme and also their viability before being considered for approval.  The 45 proposals approved in the second call in March 2021 build on the existing pipeline of URDF-supported projects launched under the first call.  This URDF-supported programme of projects will ultimately contribute significantly to the transformative regeneration and development of our large towns and cities and to the achievement of the national planning framework and Project Ireland 2040 objectives.</p> <p>Kildare County Council submitted four applications under the second call, three of which were successful, attracting a combined total &euro;15,642,624 in URDF support.  This URDF funding in the second call is in addition to &euro;5.5 million already approved for four projects under the first call, bringing total URDF support for projects in Kildare County Council area to &euro;21.1 million over both URDF calls.  Kildare County Council's fourth proposal in respect of a second bridge over the River Liffey at Newbridge was one of 30 unsuccessful proposals.  A copy of the detailed assessment of this proposal has been provided to Kildare County Council, and a feedback meeting on the matter has taken place between officials of the council and the Department.  The ball is back in the court of Kildare County Council in terms of advancing the project further.  Certainly the Department will give all support it can.  I await the Senator's supplementary questions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#B00300"><p>With the greatest of respect to the Minister of State, I did not need a lecture on the URDF.  While he correctly stated that Kildare County Council submitted four applications, this particular application was highlighted as the second most important of those four.  It was bypassed for whatever reason.  We were very disappointed to receive word that the project was not included.  The Department cannot simply wash its hands of this.  It needs to work with the Department of Transport and Kildare County Council to find an innovative response.  Kildare County Council is working proactively to provide three quarters of the funding for the project.  The Minister of State has said it is back in the court of Kildare County Council.  When will we have the next round of the URDF?  The Minister of State spoke about one feedback meeting between the Department and Kildare County Council.  Is this the only engagement that has taken place?  Has there been other engagement?  What plans does the Department have to support the people of Kildare as well as Kildare County Council in securing sufficient funding to make progress on this vital infrastructure?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1512" speakername="Malcolm Noonan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#B00400"><p>I acknowledge the disappointment of the Senator and the people of Newbridge that the second bridge over the River Liffey was not included in the second call of the URDF.  Unfortunately, the project was deemed unsuccessful following a comprehensive assessment process that concluded it did not adequately meet the criteria for URDF support.  I suggest that the local authority continue to engage with the Department and look at other mechanisms.  There is significant funding available for active travel.  It should look at a myriad of solutions.  Road infrastructure is one part of the solution for a traffic problem but there is a wider set of solutions, particularly with regard to schools and active travel, such as cycling and walking, and trying to reduce car dependency in Newbridge town centre.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Malcolm Noonan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=MalcolmNoonan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=02"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->That type of added innovation will give an extra dimension to any new application the local authority submits to the URDF.  I cannot give the Senator a definitive answer on when the next round of calls will be, but I urge local authorities to continue to engage with my Department and, in regard to active travel, with the Department of the Environment, Climate and Communications.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.18" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#C00200">Roads Projects</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#C00300"><p>I thank the Acting Chairperson for his courtesy, as usual, in giving me the floor on this issue.  I am delighted it is being taken by my friend, the Minister of State, Senator Hackett.  Coming from Mayo originally, I am sure she is familiar with the N5 route.  We all know what has happened with that project.  Unfortunately, the contractors who were to construct the bypass from Scramogue to Ballaghaderreen have run into difficulties.  I have spoken about this on many occasions in the Seanad and previously in the D&aacute;il.  The contract is now off and that puts the focus back on the existing route.  It is a very dangerous one on which there have been a large number of accidents and fatalities over many years.  It is disappointing for the people living along the route that the new bypass is not going ahead.  They have lived with the terrible experience of having to deal with horrific accidents on the road morning, noon and night over the past 40 years.  It is not an exaggeration to say that when one looks back over those 40 years.  In excess of 30 people have been killed on the road and 60 to 70 have been injured.  It has been a nightmare for the people who live along the route.</p> <p>We now have a hold-up on the construction of the bypass.  I am very confident the Government is committed to the project and that the situation will sort itself out in time.  However, it is important that we focus again on the issue of safety.  In the time remaining to me, I will outline the problems along the route for the Minister of State.  Scramogue Cross is a massive crossroads that requires further upgrading.  In Strokestown, there is a Centra as one goes into the town, at the turn near the old football pitch.  There have been numerous crashes there over the years.  I acknowledge that Transport Infrastructure Ireland, TII, formerly the National Roads Authority, has carried out quite a lot of work there.  There are also problems in Lisryan, which is on the far side of Strokestown.  Tulsk village, which is a very elongated village with a school, community centre, church and some businesses, is also experiencing problems.  Traffic goes through it at an enormous speed.  The situation in Bellanagare may not be as dangerous but there are concerns about the volume of traffic going through it.  In Frenchpark, there is an appalling scenario in terms of accidents.  One occurred there recently involving a school bus.  There has been a litany of accidents in that village.</p> <p>We have seen some movement by TII in response to all the representations that have been made by a large number of politicians.  In fairness to all my colleagues, whatever party they are in, there have been requests to upgrade the crossroads in Frenchpark village and the route on to Ballaghaderreen.  We really need to focus now on advancing this project and money must be ring-fenced to ensure improvements are carried out.  As a result of the hold-up, even at the greatest speed at which it can now be done, it will be four or five years before the bypass is completed.  We must concentrate on safety issues.  It would not take a huge amount of money to make improvements in that regard and it must be done.  There are schools, churches and community centres along the route.  Farmers have to do their business along the road, taking cattle to different lands and so on.  They are really concerned about it because there is a threat every time they go out on the road.  I know this issue is not part of the Minister of State's portfolio and I appreciate her taking it.  I ask that she take the message back that TII needs to put extra effort into dealing with safety measures along this route.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1661" speakername="Pippa Hackett" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#C00400"><p>I thank the Senator for his question.  He is right that I am familiar with this stretch of road.  As he is aware, the Minister for Transport has responsibility for overall policy and Exchequer funding in regard to the national roads programme.  Once funding arrangements have been put in place with TII, under the Roads Acts 1993 to 2015 and in line with the national development plan, NDP, the planning, design, improvement and upgrading of individual national roads is a matter for TII, in conjunction with the local authorities concerned.  TII ultimately delivers the national roads programme in line with Project Ireland 2040, which is the national planning framework, and the NDP.</p> <p>Under the new NDP launched in October 2021, approximately &euro;5.1 billion is earmarked for new national roads projects to 2030.  This funding will enable improved regional accessibility across the country, as well as compact growth, both of which are key national strategic outcomes.  The funding will provide for the development of numerous national roads projects, including the completion of those already at construction stage and those close to it, as well as the development of a number of others.  Exchequer funding under the new NDP will also facilitate continued protection and renewal of our national roads infrastructure, including motorways, in line with Government policy. </p> <p>A priority in the NDP, in line with the Department's typical investment hierarchy, is to maintain the quality and safety of the existing national road network, which includes the N5.  This will serve to safeguard the significant investment that has taken place in our national roads over recent decades.  The NDP foresees an Exchequer allocation of approximately &euro;2.9 billion for the protection and renewal of existing national roads over the ten-year period to 2030, allocated fairly evenly across the decade. </p> <p>The N5 is a national primary road connecting Longford town with Westport.  The N5 Ballaghaderreen to Scramogue project consists of the construction of 33 km of new single-carriageway road between the Ballaghaderreen bypass and Scramogue, bypassing Frenchpark, Tulsk and Strokestown.  When completed, the project will reduce journey times, improve safety and deliver an improved urban environment in towns and villages along the route.  As the Senator outlined, construction on the project was due to start earlier this year.  However, works were suspended on 11 March due to the contractor, Roadbridge, entering receivership.  Roscommon County Council is currently engaged in the process of procuring the services of a new contractor to progress the construction of the project.  The tender process is under way and expressions of interest have been received.  Subject to the successful outcome of a tender process, it is intended that the award of the main contract will happen in the first quarter of 2023.  It is currently anticipated that the construction of the main scheme will take three years. </p> <p>In 2022, a pavement improvement scheme will be progressed on the existing N5 road between Moneylea and Carrowntoosan, with works expected to commence by early July.  In addition, a feasibility and options report has been received for a safety scheme at the junction of the N5 and R361 in Frenchpark.  This will proceed to the next phase and TIl will provide the necessary funding.  Active travel improvements for towns and villages along this route are also being investigated.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#C00500"><p>The Minister of State has given quite a positive response, which we do not always receive.  I am delighted to hear about the improvement scheme between Moneylea and Carrowntoosan.  Improvements to Frenchpark junction are also really important.  These are areas that have caused concern to the public for many years.</p> <p>There is also very good news in regard to the retendering for the N5 project.  I hope it will be up and running before too long.  It is really good to hear that expressions of interest have been received.  I am quite happy with the Minister of State's response and update.  It is only fair that I pay tribute to all my Oireachtas colleagues, irrespective of who they represent, for their representations on this issue, as well as the local councillors who have highlighted the problems time after time, for many years, particularly in regard to Frenchpark and Tulsk.</p> <p>On a related matter, I am calling for the installation of special traffic lights in Strokestown, where there is currently a major issue.  I will take that up directly with TII.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1661" speakername="Pippa Hackett" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#C00600"><p>It is good to be the bearer of some positive news, which is not always possible when there are particular difficulties.  I am glad the Senator is happy with the response and that he recognises the positive and proactive measures that have been undertaken.  Approximately &euro;51.6 million has been allocated to the N5 upgrade.  It is a significant project and it is important that it be completed as soon as possible.  I hope to see the tender process completed and construction starting, as projected, in the first quarter of 2023.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Pippa Hackett:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=0000"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=0000&amp;amp;pid=PippaHackett&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=02"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The Senator highlights the value of effective public representation at all levels.  We are supporting our communities through that.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.24" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#D00200">Ports Facilities</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#D00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State for being here.  Cork is the capital city of the south.  The Port of Cork is the second largest natural harbour and a key international gateway for trade.  I ask that Cork Port become a designated port for the importation of non-EU fresh produce and that it would receive clearance personnel from the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine for these products.  To illustrate the point I will describe the procedure for importation of non-EU fresh produce.  The containers arrive at Cork Port and must be transported by road to the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine inspection area in Dublin before receiving clearance to return by road all the way back to Cork for ultimate delivery.  That places a cost of about &euro;1,200 for each container.  It is bad for the environment at a time when we are conscious of climate change.  For example, three containers recently arrived in Cork and went all the way to Dublin and back down again.  As we speak, more containers are being rerouted to Dublin.  Deputy Colm Burke and I have been talking with the Port of Cork, as well as with members of the affected companies.  The Port of Cork has no Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine clearance personnel for fresh produce.  The only ports that currently have such personnel in place are Dublin and Rosslare.  I ask the Minister of State to change this to reflect the growth of Cork Port and the importance of what Deputy Colm Burke and I are speaking about both in this House and in the D&aacute;il.  The increased costs, the administrative burden, the slowing down of goods in reaching the businesses that require them, are all adding to delays and frustration.  It is particularly problematic for those importing fresh produce.  There are inconsistencies in the system.  I hope the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine and the Department of Transport can work together to ensure that we do not discommode people but make it easier for them to bring in goods and produce without having a situation in which goods are travelling to Dublin and back to Cork.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1661" speakername="Pippa Hackett" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#D00400"><p>I thank Senator Buttimer for his Commencement matter.  The Port of Cork is currently a designated border control post, BCP, approved for container shipments of wood and wood products.  Inspections take place at the Tivoli container terminal near Cork city where there is a leased Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine office and inspection room, where unloading bays have been shared with the Revenue Commissioners.  The Port of Cork is currently developing new facilities approximately 20 km from Tivoli at Ringaskiddy, which will accommodate both lo-lo and ro-ro trade.</p> <p>Between 2015 and 2018, a number of meetings took place between officials from the Department and representatives of the Port of Cork on the establishment of a border control post for goods of both plant and animal origin.  As part of these discussions the Department outlined the regulatory requirements for a border control post and considered the options put forward by the Port of Cork for the infrastructure required.  In December 2018, the port advised that it did not intend to pursue the building of a border control post at that time and it would leave such considerations until phase 2 of its development.  In recent years the focus in the Department has been on ensuring that sufficient border control post inspection infrastructure was available to deal with sanitary and phytosanitary, SPS, checks.  These are the import controls that apply on agrifood trade coming into the EU Single Market from third countries, including Britain following the Brexit referendum.  This work has involved considerable collaboration with the Revenue Commissioners, the Health Service Executive and the Office of Public Works and has resulted in a very substantial expansion of border control post infrastructure at Dublin Port, as well as the building of an interim facility in Kilrane close to Rosslare Europort.  Work on plans for the building of a permanent facility in Rosslare Europort was completed towards the end of last year and planning permission has been sought and approved.  The Irish Maritime Development Office's report indicates there is sufficient capacity on existing services in the roll-on roll-off network between Ireland and mainland Europe to satisfy demand.  The Port of Cork has since submitted a case for the building of a border control post capable of handling food products at the Ringaskiddy terminal.  It argues that Munster is the heart of the Irish agricultural sector and it believes the Port of Cork is the natural hub for imports and exports.  Many of the products that require inspection are routed through Dublin Port for inspection and it believes, as does the Senator, that a border control post in the Port of Cork could reduce costs to local business and reduce greenhouse gas emissions from transport contributing to Ireland's climate targets.  It also makes the point that the Port of Cork could be used as an alternative, contingency and overflow facility, should difficulties and congestion arise at the Dublin Port and Rosslare Europort border control posts.  The issue of whether a border control posts might be required in the Port of Cork remains under consideration.  </p> <p>While the Department already handles wood products in Cork, it should be noted that the physical infrastructure required for handling bulk wood products and that required for handling food products are very different.  Such a border control post would still have to comply with the official control regulation, be approved by the European Commission and be resourced by Department inspection staff.  In addition, the location of the physical inspection premises as a border control post may only be located in a customs-controlled area.  Officials from the Department are continuing to analyse the requirements for this facility. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#D00500"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  I support the call and the submission from the Port of Cork for the building of a border control post.  I appreciate the Minister of State's response and thank her.  A border control post must be established in Cork and in tandem with that is the need for border control personnel from the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine to be located in Cork.  I note the last paragraph of the Minister of State's reply refers to compliance with the European Commission and the issue of health and safety.  These issues can be addressed and overcome.  The important point is we need a border control post in Cork.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1661" speakername="Pippa Hackett" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#D00600"><p>I thank the Senator and can see the passion he has for this issue.  I am sure the Port of Cork welcomes his support for its submission.  The issue is still under consideration.  I cannot say whether it is ruled in or out.  It is still open and the submission from the Port of Cork seems justifiable.  The Senator's pleas for it to happen are justified.  We are continuing to analyse the requirements of the facility and there is a valid case for it.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.29" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#D00700">Covid-19 Pandemic</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#D00800"><p>The Minister of State is very welcome to the House.  As we all know, during the two years of the Covid-19 pandemic, the one group of people in the front line were nurses and healthcare staff in both the public and private healthcare sectors.  The tax-free &euro;1,000 that has been granted by the Government to these front-line workers is very welcome.  It is not the money but the appreciation, the respect and the acknowledgement from the people of Ireland to nurses, healthcare providers and those who supported and cared for us during the pandemic, in particular those who cared for the many thousands of people who ended up in hospital very sick with Covid-19.</p> <p>There were also those who helped to prevent many more people from getting sick and passing away.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Martin Conway:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2347"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2347&amp;amp;pid=MartinConway&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=02"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The &euro;1,000 was a very good gesture but I am most disappointed in the haphazard way its payment has happened.  I raised this matter today because I want a clear timeline as to when all the people who are being given the &euro;1,000 will get it.  What arrangements are in place to ensure they will get it?  I am hearing that staff in hospitals around the country have not gotten it yet.  I am hearing that nurses in nursing homes, carers and so on, people who are entitled to receive it, are still waiting for it and do not even know when they will get the payment.  I sincerely hope that as a result of me raising this Commencement matter, we will get a clear and definite timeline for the payment of the &euro;1,000.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1661" speakername="Pippa Hackett" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#E00200"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this issue today.  On 19 January, the Government announced a Covid-19 recognition payment for front-line public sector healthcare workers, to recognise the unique role they played during the pandemic.  The payment will not be subject to income tax, USC or PRSI.  The measure will be ring-fenced to staff who worked ordinarily on-site in Covid-19 exposed healthcare environments for at least four weeks within the period between 1 March 2020 and 30 June 2021.  Among those staff, the payment amount is &euro;1,000 for those whose work pattern is at least 60% whole-time equivalent, or &euro;600 for those below that threshold.  This payment is being made to those eligible public sector front-line healthcare staff, inclusive of agency staff working for the HSE, who worked in clinical settings.  While not an exhaustive list, and subject to eligibility criteria, public sector employees will include doctors, nurses, healthcare assistants, porters, cleaners and other eligible staff who work in clinical settings.</p> <p>The Department and the HSE have consulted extensively with health sector trade unions on this matter.  The eligibility guidelines for this payment that apply in HSE and section 38 organisations were published online by the HSE on 19 April.  Since then, local HSE sites and section 38 organisations have been assessing employees&rsquo; eligibility and arranging payments.  All services are in the process of actioning the payment to those staff who have been deemed eligible to receive it.  I have been assured that this is receiving priority attention across services.  Figures for payments to HSE staff are reported centrally every week.  Section 38 staff are excluded from these figures.  The latest available figures show that by 27 May last, 12,831 payments had been processed, to a value of over &euro;12 million.  Separately, I can confirm that payments have been made to staff in Beaumont Hospital and the Rotunda.</p> <p>The measure also extends to equivalent healthcare workers in certain other specific types of healthcare organisation.  Arrangements for the sectors encompassed by this measure are currently being progressed by officials in the Department of Health.  When it is available, officials will provide information for those other certain healthcare employees that are covered by the Government decision and the process available to their employers to implement this measure for their eligible staff.  This will cover eligible staff in private sector nursing homes and hospices; eligible staff working on-site in section 39 long-term residential care facilities for people with disabilities; agency roles working in the HSE; healthcare support assistants, also known as home help, home care or home support contracted to the HSE; members of the Department of Defence redeployed to work in HSE Covid-19 exposed environments; and paramedics employed by the Department of Housing, Local Government and Heritage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#E00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State for her comprehensive reply.  Everyone in the country acknowledges that the critical and vital role everyone in the hospitals, from nurses down to the porters, played on the front line during the healthcare emergency.  This measure was announced in January.  It is now 2 June.  It seems it is a case of big wheels moving way too slowly.  People are trying to plan holidays.  They have already decided what they are going to do with this money.  One healthcare worker asked me if they were ever going to get it.  It is great that 12,000 people have received the payment but there are many tens of thousands still waiting.  It should not take six months to pay 12,000 people and another six months to pay the rest.  While the Minister of State said this matter is receiving priority attention, it needs even more of it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1661" speakername="Pippa Hackett" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#E00400"><p>I share the Senator's frustrations.  I assure him that all those eligible will receive their payments, though I accept that it has not been very quickly delivered.  Department of Health officials are working hard to roll this payment out as soon as possible and the Minister looks forward to this progressing very shortly.</p> <p>Getting back to the original point about recognising that so many people put their lives at risk to support our nation and our citizens through the Covid pandemic, it is worth remembering that from February of next year a new permanent public holiday will be established to mark Imbolc, or St. Brigid's Day.  This new bank holiday will serve as recognition and a permanent reminder to us of all those people's efforts and sacrifices during the last few difficult years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.35" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar fionra&iacute; ar 11.17 a.m. agus cuireadh t&uacute;s leis ar&iacute;s ar 12.02 p.m.<br /><br />Sitting suspended at 11.17 a.m. and resumed at 12.02 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.36" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#K00100">Gnó an tSeanaid - Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#K00200"><p>Before I call on the Leader to outline the Order of Business, I welcome the ambassador of Denmark to the Distinguished Visitors Gallery.  Denmark's national day is Constitution Day.  As an EU member state, Denmark has been a valued friend of Ireland, especially during the Brexit process.  The Kingdom of Denmark celebrates Constitution Day, which marks its first constitution in 1849 and its current constitution in 1953.</p><p>The close bonds between Denmark and Ireland are well known and stretch all the way back to the Viking era, when the Danes were guests and tourists of sorts.  We cherish some of the lasting Viking influences on Irish culture.  The largest Viking warship, which is on display in the Danish national Viking Ship Museum, is called the <i>Sea Stallion</i>.  It was built in 1042 and made from oak from County Wicklow.  Of course, one of our iconic literary figures, James Joyce, began learning Danish at the age of 18 and he was convinced that he had Danish or Viking origins.  Seamus Heaney also had strong links to Denmark.  On the island of Bornholm there is a street named after him.</p><p>Ireland and Denmark joined the European Union together some 50 years ago.  We continue to work together in that context, especially concerning the crisis in the Ukraine.  We share values, including respect for the rule of law and democratic values.  There is a small but vibrant Danish community in Ireland, with approximately 2,500 Danish citizens resident here.  There is also a GAA club in Denmark.</p><p>We welcome the ambassador and we wish all the Danish community in Ireland and around the world a happy Constitution Day and continued long and fruitful relationships between our two countries.  <i>Glad forfatningsdag</i>. </p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.38" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#K00300">An tOrd Gnó - Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#K00400"><p>I welcome the ambassador and I hope he and all Danish citizens have a lovely day next week.  The Order of Business is No.1, Private Members' business, Protection of the Native Irish Honey Bee Bill 2021 - Second Stage, to be taken at 1.15 p.m., with the time allocated to this debate not to exceed two hours.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#K00500"><p>Before I call on the Deputy Leader of the Fianna F&aacute;il group, in the Gallery with us as well we have the pupils from sixth class in Grange National School.  Are they going to give us a wave?  They are.  I thank them.  This is Senator Ahearn's local primary school and I am sure he was a well-behaved student in his days there.  We have the deputy principal with us, Richard Carroll, as well as teachers, Marie and Lauren, and the chair of the board of management, Liam Ahearn.  Is he any relation to Senator Ahearn?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#K00600"><p>His dad.  He was a great councillor in his day and his good wife, Theresa, was a staunch Member of the Lower House.  We welcome Liam to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#K00700"><p>I thank Senator Buttimer for the point of information.  I also welcome Liam to the Gallery as well, and all the boys and girls from Grange National School.  I thank them for coming to Seanad &Eacute;ireann today.  I call Senator Fiona O'Loughlin.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#K00800"><p>I add my voice of welcome to the distinguished ambassador with us today.  I have enjoyed many pleasant times in his country.  I cannot claim to know any Danish, but the Gaelic version of my name, O'Loughlin, is &Oacute; Lochlainn, which means "The Viking", so I reckon I am descended from Viking blood.  I also welcome the boys and girls from Tipperary, because I also have blood from the county in me as well.  It is always a pleasure to welcome those from that lovely county.</p> <p>I support the Order of Business as outlined by the Leader.  I also acknowledge that June is Pride Month, when LGTB communities, and their allies, celebrate the freedom to be themselves.  During Pride Month, it is important that we all acknowledge, highlight and remember respect, understanding and compassion.  On that note, I ask the Leader to ask for an update in respect of the progress of the hate crime legislation, which the Minister of Justice has promised to commit to as a priority.  It is needed.  </p> <p>I also extend my thanks to all those involved in the inter-parliamentary unit here in the Oireachtas for all their work in supporting the Parliamentary Assembly of the Council of Europe, PACE, the members of which were here from Sunday right through to today, for some of them.  We had two excellent days of meetings and representatives from 46 countries gathered here in Dublin.  I thank the Cathaoirleach for his presence and his words.  It was a very successful set of meetings and we appreciate all the work that went into the undertaking.  </p> <p>I turn now to the matter of respect for special needs assistants, SNAs.  We have often spoken of this issue.  I was shocked to hear from several SNAs across County Kildare how they found out that they will have no jobs in September.  Basically, at 4.15 p.m. yesterday, on the website of the National Council for Special Education, NCSE, the allocation in this regard for schools was announced without any negotiation or correspondence with principals or boards of management.  This is simply not on.  The SNAs do a wonderful job in all our schools.  We need them and they are a valuable resource in the context of learning.  One school now has three SNAs who know they do not have jobs because they looked at a website.  These people love their jobs.  They want to be there in the school and they are a vital part of the school.  This is not the way we should do business.  </p> <p>We spoke last week about the decision to allow PDFORRA to affiliate temporarily with the Irish Congress of Trade Unions, ICTU.  It is important.  We all sought the same privilege for the Representative Association of Commissioned Officers, RACO.  I am pleased that has now happened and that this has been accepted.  </p> <p>I also address the issue of the serious delays being encountered by those trying to access disability services.  In my area of south county Kildare, I am working with several families who have been waiting for two and a half years to be able to access these services.  This is completely unacceptable.  In one case, a child needs to be seen in advance of starting school.  Due to delays, though, the parents are concerned that there will not be an opportunity to apply for an autism spectrum disorder, ASD, place in the time available.  Something must be done about this issue and we need to have a debate on it.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#K00900"><p>I thank the Senator for raising those important issues.  I thank her also for her leadership in PACE, representing Ireland across Europe.  It was important this week to have so many of our friends and allies from the European community and beyond in Dublin with us to enable us as a country to communicate our message.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">An Cathaoirleach:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2246"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2246&amp;amp;pid=MarkDaly&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=02"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is very important that, with her leadership and that of others, we continue our diplomatic efforts in relation to Brexit and all the challenges we face as a country.  I again thank the Senator for making sure that important conference took place in Dublin.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#L00200"><p>On 14 December 2022, during a Commencement matter debate, I raised the issue of the advanced paramedic motorbike unit for Cork.  The Cathaoirleach ruled out of order my raising of this as a Commencement matter on a second occasion because it had already been raised, which I understand, but there needs to be a forum for us as Members of the Seanad to hold the HSE to account for the lack of provision of an advanced paramedic motorbike unit in Cork.  We have no question time but we need to ensure, as Oireachtas Members, that there is accountability of the HSE.</p> <p>I again raise the matter during the Order of Business of the lack of two motorbike units in Cork.  They are idle, non-operational and they should be reinstated as a matter of extreme urgency.  We understand and we know that Covid changed parts of the delivery of the healthcare system, but we are now living in a post-Covid world.  Therefore, I call for the Minister for Health to come to the House to explain why the HSE has not reinstated the advanced paramedic motorcycle unit in Cork.  Advanced paramedics save lives.  They provide a care pathway and a rapid response service.  In cities like Cork, with narrow, winding streets, the motorbikes are pivotal in the response time to people who require urgent care and provide a pathway to hospital or care.  I ask that the Minister of Health, on behalf of the HSE, comes to the House to explain why the HSE has not reinstated the service and say when it will.  This is about saving lives.  It is about people and the provision of a care pathway.</p> <p>I welcome the inclusion of the Representative Association of Commissioned Officers, RACO, by the Minister for Defence in the pay talks to join the work of PDFORRA.  I commend the work of people like Mark Keane who have been so strong and steadfast in their advocacy on behalf of members of the Defence Forces.</p> <p>I welcome the boys and girls from Grange National School.  I formally pay tribute to Liam Ahearn who was an extraordinary county councillor and whose good wife, Theresa, was a wonderful parliamentarian and a friend to many of us.  We are very proud of the work that Senator Ahearn is doing here.  To the boys and girls from Tipperary, I am sorry your hurling season is over but enjoy the laethanta saoire.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#L00300"><p>Before I call Senator Keogan, I wish to associate myself personally with the words of welcome from Senator Buttimer and the Cathaoirleach to Liam Ahearn.  I am aware that Liam served on Tipperary County Council for ten years and was the chairperson of that body.  He was a very distinguished public representative in his own right.  All of us realise that the support of our families is critical to us being able to do this job.  Without that support we could not do it.  The great work Senator Ahearn does here is in no small way due to the support of and inspiration and mentioning from his wonderful father, Liam.  I join in Members' welcome to him.</p> <p>I also welcome to the gallery students of the fifth and sixth classes student council from Lusk Senior National School, Fingal.  In fact, I had an historic association with that school for many a day.  I might meet some of them later.  I also welcome their teacher, Erica, who is a friend of the Leader of the House.  Senator Doherty is anxious that I welcome our guests.  They may wish to wait until the end of the Order of Business, if they can, when the Leader will offer her own welcome to them.  We had better move on or it will be evening before we finish.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#L00400"><p>The law exists in a state of flux, as do the prevailing social opinions of the people it governs.  These two aspects of our shared existence act upon each other.  Sometimes, changes in the law affect people's opinion.  More often, legislators and the Government wait to see which way the wind is blowing before making a decision.  Where this balance fails is when the Government and legislators are beholden not to the prevailing widely held opinions of the public but to the carefully curated and concentrated views of a vocal minority who have been given powerful platforms as lobbyists.  This seems to have happened again in this country in perhaps the most cynical manner yet.</p> <p>To all the women and mothers in Ireland, did you know the Government is about to erase all mention of you from our legislation on maternity leave?  The proposition may sound ridiculous - indeed it is - but that is the plan under the deceptively named work life balance Bill.  After all, who would be against work-life balance?  Hidden among the miscellaneous provisions of the Bill are various amendments to the Maternity Protection Act 1994 regarding both breastfeeding and maternity leave that will remove all mention of the word "woman" and will assert that men can breastfeed too.  We are regularly told that words matter, yet when women tell us that the words "mother", "female" and "woman" matter to them, they are dismissed as unkind or exclusionary.  The reality is that maternity is undertaken by women and not by men.  To replace the word "mother" or "woman" with the word "person" is a retrograde step and strips women of the core part of their identity.</p> <p>Women have wombs where our children are conceived and nourished during pregnancy.  Women have breasts with which we feed our children.  These things need to be said without fear of causing offence.  Who is insisting we deny there are two sexes and why?  Sex is a protected characteristic in our Equal Status Acts, because women experienced discrimination based on their biology.  Can we not find a way to be inclusive without erasing women's biology and experience from our legislation?  This country spent years coming to terms with its treatment of women who became mothers outside of marriage.  It is a journey we are still making and I am sure there are more apologies to the women of Ireland to come.  Are we, at the same time as those apologies, going to launch yet another attack on women in the very legislation that was intended to protect them?  Perhaps it was thought these changes would not be noticed or that we would not care.  Both of these assumptions are wrong.  If the Government thinks it can quietly remove us from legislation, rest assured the women of Ireland will not go gentle into that good night.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1661" speakername="Pippa Hackett" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#L00500"><p>Today marks the start of Bord Bia Bloom 2022 in the Phoenix Park.  It provides a fantastic opportunity for people to engage with nature, gardening and biodiversity.  Bloom is open from today until bank holiday Monday, from 9 a.m. to 6 p.m. each day.  It is to be hoped there will be plenty of opportunity for people to attend and enjoy the show.</p> <p>This year's show incorporates 19 show gardens and nine postcard gardens, more than 80 Irish food and drink producers, 17 nurseries in the nursery village, more than 25 cookery demonstrations, and 130 retailers, all within a 70-acre site.  I am particularly pleased that my Department has sponsored an organic edible garden at Bloom this year.  The garden illustrates how to grow a range of organic vegetables and fruit crops within a linear urban space and demonstrates the steps we can take to protect the environment within our gardens.  It also highlights the need to restore hedgerows, meadows and trees within our wider landscapes and environments.</p> <p>I encourage everyone attending over the next five days to stop by and see what they can replicate in their own garden, however big or small, and how they can play their part for nature and biodiversity.  Bloom will attract more than 110,000 visitors and has evolved to become one of the most popular events over the June bank holiday weekend.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Pippa Hackett:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=0000"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=0000&amp;amp;pid=PippaHackett&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=02"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The festival is an opportunity for the public to experience and sample the very best of Irish horticulture, food and drink direct from Ireland's world-class designers, growers, producers and suppliers.  Bloom is not only a great family day out but also a platform to obtain a wide range of information and to engage with important topics like sustainability, biodiversity and mental health through beautiful floral design, expert talks and family-friendly exhibits.  </p><p>This year's festival celebrates the renewed public appreciation for outdoor spaces and their role in promoting positive mental and physical health.  For example, Coolmine Community School, Blanchardstown, has designed a garden space for students to calm the mind and focus.  Its postcard garden is inspired by a garden that currently resides in the school to offer students a relaxing open-air space.  In addition to being a space to promote positive mental health, the Zen garden promotes biodiversity by featuring plants that attract bees, butterflies and other pollinators as well as a range of sensory and edible plants.  </p><p>Bord Bia is encouraging as many people as possible to come by public transport if that option is available to them.  That is how I intend to travel with my hard-working constituency team from Laois-Offaly tomorrow.  There will be shuttle buses running in the Phoenix Park throughout the weekend.  I recommend this to anyone looking for something to do this weekend.  I believe the weather is - touch wood - to be nice.  I have heard different opinions but I hope it will be on the sunny side.  I encourage people to get to the Phoenix Park to see how they can help nature into their own gardens.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#M00200"><p>I know Senator Hackett will have a long and wonderful career here but, if she ever decides to leave this place, marketing would be a real option for her.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#M00300"><p>I apologise in advance that I will have to leave before the end because I want to go out to support the keepers of native Irish bees who are outside.  I hope everybody will support Senator Martin's Bill today.</p> <p>I welcome the relaunch of the Raise the Roof campaign.  We have been in lockdown for two years now but that does not mean that the housing crisis has gone away.  In fact, it has only got worse.  As Fr. Peter McVerry has said, the crisis is worse today than it has been at any time in the past 40 years.  We seem to have a Minister who is too arrogant to accept that circumstances have moved on and that his Housing for All plan has been overtaken.  We have also had to listen people saying that it takes time to build housing but people are now frustrated and fed up because we have been hearing that for the last ten years from Fine Gael in government.  What we need to address the housing crisis is a doubling of capital investment in public housing.  We need to increase the delivery of social and affordable homes.  We need to cut rents and ban increases.  We have to prevent homelessness by putting packages in place with local authorities to allow them to work with families when they get their notices to quit while also rolling out Housing First nationwide.  We also need to enshrine the right to housing in the Constitution.  The level of anger and despair in communities is palpable.  Workers cannot afford to live in the cities and towns and are emigrating in their droves.  I am sure many of the elected representatives here will have experienced parliamentary assistants and secretarial assistants leaving.  People are leaving because they are getting notices to quit and have no choice because they cannot live in our capital city.  </p> <p>I encourage everyone to attend the Raise the Roof public meetings that are happening around the country.  There was one last night.  There will be meetings in the Tower Hotel, Waterford, on 7 June, in the Limerick Strand Hotel on 13 June, in the Mansion House on 21 June, in SIPTU's offices in Galway on 28 June and in the Glenroyal Hotel, Maynooth, on 4 July.  All of those meetings are taking place at 7 p.m.  I encourage Senators to attend to hear from people at the coalface what we need to do to address the housing crisis.</p> <p>My final point is not relevant to the housing issue but it is always a good day to say that trans rights are human rights.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1672" speakername="Rebecca Moynihan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#M00400"><p>I call for a debate in the House on special education.  My party leader and colleague, Deputy Bacik, has also been calling for such a debate in the D&aacute;il.  We see from the published special needs assistant, SNA, allocations that they have been frozen for the third year in a row.  For an awful lot of SNAs, if issues have arisen, there will not be enough time for them to appeal and be in place in September.  It is very unfair on these essential workers in the Irish education system who need to have dignity and respect in their work and to be able to plan.  There are also 270 children with autism who do not have an appropriate place for September, according to AsIAm.  In light of these matters, coupled with things like the proposed special education centres and the delays in assessments of need, there is a need for this House to have a special focus and debate on SNAs, autism supports and autism within education.  I call for such a debate when we come back in June.</p><p>I welcome the unveiling yesterday of the six <i>Stolpersteine</i>in St. Catherine's National School, Donore Avenue, which is where I went to primary school.  Ettie Steinberg, one of six Irish victims of the Holocaust, also went to school there.  The area was known as Little Jerusalem.  It is very important that the school, the area and Ireland commemorate how Ireland let down an awful lot of victims of the Holocaust by not taking the number of European refugees we should have at that time.  There are approximately 2,000 <i>Stolpersteine</i>around Europe.  They are installed to commemorate and remember Jewish victims of the Holocaust.  They serve as a timely reminder that words matter and that they can be used to spread hate towards a certain group.  It is worth remembering that among the first victims of the Holocaust were LGBTI people.  That unveiling to commemorate Ettie Steinberg was very welcome.  She lived and went to school in Donore Avenue.  She was a seamstress and was one of the Irish victims of the Holocaust.  I congratulate the school and its principal, Karen Jordan, and the Irish Holocaust memorial group in Dublin City Council on yesterday's unveiling.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#M00500"><p>The school can be justifiably proud of the Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1652" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#M00600"><p>I call for a debate in the House on Ireland's corporate tax rate.  There is a need for a proper debate and discussion with the Minister for Finance on the future of the minimum global rate which, as we all know, has been quite a hot topic.  For context, I am watching developments in both the US and Poland.  In the US, the Republican Party in the House is holding up the agreement to accept the global minimum rate, which the Democratic Party therefore cannot implement despite being in power.  This is certainly going to be a problem.  The global rate is dead in the water if it is not implemented there.</p> <p>The Government of Poland has also not yet signed up to it.  This resulted in the matter being dropped from the agenda of last month's ECOFIN meeting.  I suppose that was to spare France's blushes more than anything else because it has been pushing so hard for this.  The OECD has accepted that it will be at least 2024 before the rate is implemented.  This is one year further along the timeline than had been proposed.  I would say it will be longer because, unless there is a change in America, which is very unlikely, and in Poland, which is probably also unlikely for a while, this is not going to change.  Ireland has very successfully used our corporate tax regime as an effective economic development tool for decades now.  It is estimated that the Exchequer will lose a sum in the region of &euro;2 billion annually, which is no small amount.  The background to this is the cost-of-living crisis, surging inflation, the war in Ukraine and the plethora of other complications on the horizon.  Just this week, the Irish Fiscal Advisory Council warned that the public finances are now too reliant on corporation tax, which is estimated to have brought in &euro;22 billion in total since 2005.  Surely we should now be carefully considering our fiscal policy and how best to support businesses, foreign investment and, ultimately, the people of this country when it comes to the redistribution of these funds at budget time.  </p> <p>On this basis, I ask the Leader to bring the Minister for Finance to the House for an open discussion on this matter.  It is a topic of discussion but it has not had any great airing here or in the D&aacute;il.  We could shed some light on this and we could certainly get the opinion of the Minister, Deputy Donohoe, on where things are going.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Aidan Davitt:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2475"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2475&amp;amp;pid=AidanDavitt&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=02"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> My thoughts are with the Burke family.  The Minister of State, Deputy Peter Burke, has been a great friend of this House and a super friend to councillors.  He has carried out work with councillors which had been going on for the previous ten years.  He is burying his father today.  It would be remiss of me, as someone who comes from Mullingar, not to mention it.</p><p>Maith th&uacute;, Senator Keogan.  Everybody is entitled to speak their mind here and express their opinion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#N00200"><p>Thank you.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#N00300"><p>We all express our sympathy to the Minister of State, Deputy Peter Burke.  I thank Senator Davitt for mentioning it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1665" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#N00400"><p>I take this opportunity to welcome two changes announced by the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Minister for Defence, Deputy Coveney, this morning.  We have had considerable debate on the issue of passports in this House and within parties.  We debated a Fine Gael motion on the matter in February.  A new agreement with the Garda on witnessing first-time child applications was signed yesterday.  At present about 50 applications a day are stalled and need new consent forms because of the inability to contact witnessing garda&iacute; after three attempts.  From now a daily list will be transmitted from the Passport Office to Garda management of the approximately 50 cases where contact has not been made.  Contact will then be initiated on the Garda side meaning the application will not be cancelled.  That is very welcome.</p> <p>I have often come across cases where applicants are rushing and complete consent forms at home.  They sign and date it and then bring it into the Garda station.  The garda is then signing and dating it with a different date meaning the garda has not witnessed the signature in front of the applicant, making the consent form null and void.  Applicants need to go back and get a new consent form.  People need to be aware of that.  It can take some time before they are notified that the consent form that was submitted was incorrect.  For example, today I have been dealing with an applicant who was notified in recent days about a consent form submitted in early May with two different dates.  I wanted to warn people about that.</p> <p>I welcome that the Minister for Defence, Deputy Coveney, has decided to offer the Representative Association of Commissioned Officers, RACO, temporary access to the Irish Congress of Trade Unions ahead of public sector pay talks.  The recent report of the Commission on the Defence Forces also made this recommendation.  The Minister consulted with the Attorney General on the matter.  I again ask for a wider debate on the issue of the Defence Forces because we have not had the Minister in the House for some time.  That report on the Defence Forces would be a worthy topic.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#N00500"><p>It is telling no secrets to say that many Catholics are concerned not to say terrified by the implications of the 2018 secret agreement between China and the Vatican about the recognition of bishops and the status of the Catholic Church in China.  The issue is whether the agreement is leading to more repression of Catholics and more restrictions on their priests and the practice of their faith in China, particularly as the Chinese authorities have required the formal registration of clergy.  This may have major consequences for the freedom and safety of clergy who previously operated as part of the underground church.  In recent years we have seen the crushing of democracy, human rights and the rule of law in Hong Kong.</p> <p>I link these because one man in the eye of both storms is the brave 90-year-old Hong Kong cardinal, Joseph Zen, who has been a prominent critic of the Vatican-China accord.  I met him personally in Lisbon in 2019 when he expressed his burning anxiety about the agreement but in terms which never compromised his faithfulness to the Holy Father.  Two weeks ago, Cardinal Zen was arrested by Hong Kong police from the national security department along with four others for alleged collusion with foreign forces.  Their only offence was to be trustees of the 612 Humanitarian Relief Fund which provided legal and financial assistance to more than 2,200 people prosecuted for their part in the 2019 pro-democracy protests.  The fund had ceased operations in 2021 after police announced it was under investigation and requested administrators to provide details on its donors.</p> <p>Cardinal Zen is on bail but he remains a strong supporter of democracy in Hong Kong because he recognises the link between democratic decision-making and respect for human dignity.  The fate of Chinese catholics and Hong Kong democrats, and the legal prosecution of this fine old man all demand our concern and attention.  The influence on this country of Christian traditions and the missionary links between Ireland and China should add texture and depth to our concern.  I hope the Government will speak out more on this issue particularly in the wake of the arrest of a 90-year-old cardinal for simply supporting democracy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1695" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#N00600"><p>I welcome the &euro;12 million funding announced to third level students with autism.  It will make colleges autism friendly through the use of apps.  I understand that it is &euro;3 million for this year.  The three third level colleges in my own part of the country, University of Limerick, UL, Technological University of the Shannon and Mary Immaculate College, will receive more than &euro;400,000.  While this is very welcome, no provision has been made for students who are studying part time.</p> <p>I know a student who has autism and mental health issues.  She is studying for a masters and hopes to complete a PhD.  However, it is not right that she was disqualified from a SUSI grant.  She is studying part time because the college recommended that it would be more beneficial for her in doing a masters.  The student is highly intelligent but it was deemed that it would be easier for her to do it on a part-time basis.  There is no provision for part-time students.  I have written to the Department about it.  I would like to have a debate on how students who are studying part time could be brought into the category.  They should certainly not be disenfranchised from being able to access the SUSI grant.</p> <p>I congratulate UL on receiving three awards at the national Digital Media Awards recently, including a gold medal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1656" speakername="Mary Fitzpatrick" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#N00700"><p>Taxis are an essential part of our public transport services.  The ten-year rule requires that vehicles more than ten years old be retired from service.  Next year, in 2023, more than 5,000 taxis will need to be removed from the road, which represents about one third of our national taxi fleet.  Taxis allow essential workers to go to work and attend medical appointments.  They allow people to reduce their carbon emissions by not having to own and operate their own car but avail of a car service.  They offer a secure and reliable service when and where some of our other public transport services are not available.</p> <p>Throughout the pandemic, with the support of Government, many of our taxi drivers continued to operate and provide a service.  Since the pandemic ended and the world has been reopened there has been considerable demand for their services.  There have been many complaints that we now have a shortage of taxis.  The ten-year rule which is looming in 2023 for approximately 5,000 taxis means that a fleet of essential public transport vehicles is likely to be reduced very significantly.</p> <p>The original intention of the ten-year rule was to decarbonise the fleet, which I wholly support, as do the taxi drivers themselves.  The reality is that the world has changed dramatically from when that ten-year rule was first conceived.  We now obviously have war in Ukraine and a shortage of vehicles as identified by the sector itself.  It is not easy to purchase an electric vehicle and they are very expensive.  Taxi drivers are committed to making the transition to electric vehicles.  Their earnings are still recovering, the vehicles are not available and the cost of operating and trying to purchase a vehicle is beyond them at the moment.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Mary Fitzpatrick:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=MaryFitzpatrick&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=02"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I would like the Leader to write to the Minister for Transport asking him to consider extending the deadline for another 12 months.  If he can do that, it will protect an essential part of the public transport service and give us a little breathing space to ensure that public transport services are not interrupted in our cities.  It will be greatly welcomed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" speakername="Mark Wall" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#O00200"><p>I wish to raise once again respect for special needs assistants, SNAs.  I had a wonderful trip on Tuesday with the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Autism to Ballyowen special school, where I saw at first hand the great work all our SNAs do in that school, but I am also aware daily and weekly, as all of us in this House are, of the great work our SNAs do for so many of the children across this State.  Yesterday, however, I received a number of phone calls from colleagues in Kildare who had found out at 4 p.m. yesterday that their jobs were gone.  That is no way to tell anybody he or she no longer has a job.</p> <p>It is disgraceful that those SNAs had to log into a website at 4 p.m. in the evening to find out they would have no jobs come September.  These people have mortgages and families, and to find out that way is totally and utterly unacceptable.  We all know, as I said, what our SNAs do for us, but they do much more for the families whose children attend these schools.  There is a great attachment between children and their SNAs, who go above and beyond.  They know the children inside out and they complement the teaching staff.  To find this out on a website at 4 p.m. in the evening beggars belief as to what is going on.  The SNAs tell me they will have to wait until May to hear whether they will have a job come September.  This really has to change.  Teacher allocations are announced, I think, in February and were probably into April this year.  The three people to whom I spoke in a school in Kildare, who no longer have jobs, told me they ran home after their teaching day, at 4 p.m., to turn on their computers to find they no longer had jobs.  It is wrong, it needs to change and I ask the Leader to raise this with the Minister of State with responsibility for special education.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#O00250"><p>Senator Horkan is patiently waiting.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#O00300"><p>I pay tribute to former Senator and councillor, Mary Jackman, who died during the week.  It is my first opportunity to do so on the Order of Business.  I was a councillor for 12 and a half years and I regularly met Mary at various conferences, often travelling with her sister.  She was always great company and an absolute lady.  I think she spent almost 30 years on Limerick City and County Council and a couple of terms in the Seanad.  I pay tribute to her.  I found her to be an engaging human being and a really nice lady to be in the company of.</p> <p>I do not know if any other Senator has done so already, but I welcome the funding for An Post, particularly those really small post offices that are not viable based on their transactions.  I think most of us understand that postmasters are, by and large, not employed by An Post.  I think almost 880 of the 930 post offices, or thereabouts, are run as individual businesses, whereby the only revenue they get is per transaction.</p> <p>The message needs to go out to all those people who use the post office and all those who want to make sure their post offices survive that this funding is there to support them but that if they want their post offices to continue in operation, they must use them or they will, unfortunately, probably, lose them.  The message is to use them more often and to get one's friends to do so.</p> <p>An Post is a highly trusted brand.  People can use An Post for bank transactions with AIB and Bank of Ireland and lots of other services.  It is important we support An Post because, particularly during the pandemic, post offices were rocks in every community right around the country.  Urban, suburban and rural areas really need their post offices.  It is important we recognise that they generate their revenue per transaction, so the more business they get the more viable they are and the more likely they are to survive.</p> <p>I wish everybody involved with Dublin Airport - the staff, the management and all the passengers - the very best this weekend.  The airport management is on trial, if you will.  We had its representatives before the Joint Committee on Transport and Communications yesterday.  We can never see those scenes again.  We can never see literally thousands of people missing flights to go perhaps to funerals or weddings or on holidays, business trips and so on.  It cannot happen again, and we must keep all our focus on the situation until it is resolved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#O00400"><p>Thank you, Senator Horkan, for your kind words about Senator Jackman, with whom I served.  I hope to speak about her personally the week after next.  I do not wish to hold up the Order of Business now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#O00500"><p>I support Senator Mullen in his comments on Cardinal Zen.  It is an appalling way to treat anybody, and it is only right we show our support for him.</p> <p>When we are in this Chamber we sometimes howl and growl on behalf of individuals and groups, which is our right, and we must do that for the public, but I always believe we should look also at positives that come out in life.  Senator Horkan mentioned the post offices.  There was commitment on the part of the Government - and Senator Horkan and I are members of Government parties - and that commitment has been honoured.  Of course, people may ask what will happen in three years' time.  In three years' time there will be a review, and I am sure that if more support is needed, whoever is in power will see fit to support the post office network.</p> <p>In that regard I thank An Post for letting the public know that the post office in one of my local towns, namely, Elphin, County Roscommon, where the people who have been carrying out the service for many years are doing a good job but are now retiring, will not be going out of that town.  It will stay in the town and everything should be up and running under the new management in about a month's time.  That is good news.  The money that is there might not be everything, but it is a help, as the Leas-Chathaoirleach and the Leader know, to many of those small post offices.</p> <p>It is also very important we note the funding from Government to our agriculture and rural community shows, which are part and parcel not alone of rural Ireland but of many parts of urban Ireland.  It should be noted that both the Minister for Social Protection, Deputy Humphreys, and the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine, Deputy McConalogue, have given significant funding to those shows right around the country.  Not alone that, but the Minister, Deputy McConalogue, has announced new breeding classes for livestock at a number of the shows, which his Department will fund.</p> <p>It is important we talk about the good things as well as the things that are not so good to let people know that not everything out there is negative.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#O00600"><p>In response to Senator Murphy, one would sometimes think there was nothing whatever but bad news from the discourses sometimes in both our Houses of Parliament.  I acknowledge we do not get everything right, but when we do get things right they need to be at least acknowledged.  The announcement of post office funding this week was very welcome, as was the announcement of rural and agriculture shows funding.</p> <p>Senator Horkan talked about the difficulties the Irish public experienced and witnessed in Dublin Airport last week.  To be fair, the testimony the witnesses gave yesterday was very earnest and very sincere.  Some might say they had no choice but to put their hands up, but the situation obviously needs to be resolved.  At least I think we feel now that all hands are on deck, and we wish anybody travelling this weekend a safe and relatively smooth journey through the airports.</p> <p>I thank Senator Horkan for his kind comments about Mary Jackman.  We were all incredibly sad to hear of her passing this week.  She was, as he said, a real character and a gem of a lady.  I missed the moment's silence the House had out of respect for her last night.  I had huge admiration for her.</p> <p>Senator Wall raised a really important topic, and his constituency colleague raised it at the outset this morning.  Nobody should hear in the manner the SNAs heard yesterday about any position or service they offer the State, and this is an incredibly important one.  The campaign Senator Wall has previously spoken about of respect for our SNAs certainly was not lived up to yesterday.  I will certainly bring back to the Minister of State the feelings he has raised this morning, and not just on behalf of the three people from Kildare because I am quite sure a number of other people felt the same way yesterday.  I thank the Senator for raising that matter.</p> <p>Senator Fitzpatrick asked me to write a letter to ask the Minister for Transport to extend the ten-year rule for our taxi services.  I will certainly make inquiries with the Minister, particularly given that a lot of our taxis were off the road for the best part of two years.  The ten-year rule should be at least managed or balanced with perhaps some sort of mileage quota.  I will certainly accede to the request to write to the Minister.</p> <p>Senator Maria Byrne spoke about the &euro;12 million announced by the Minister, Deputy Harris, in respect of students on the autistic spectrum attending university.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Regina Doherty:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2295"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2295&amp;amp;pid=ReginaDoherty&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=02"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->She also asked for a debate on why the SUSI grant is not available for students, particularly females, who want to access part-time courses.  That is certainly an anomaly.</p><p>Senator Mullen brought to our attention the despicable treatment of Cardinal Joseph Zen by the Hong Kong authorities.  I do not know as much as I should about it but do know it is not how you treat with dignity and respect a 90-year-old man who has given a lifetime to the service of his faith and parishioners.  There is already a request to talk about the rule of law in Hong Kong.  The matter raised by the Senator could form part of that debate, but I will chase it up again with the Minister to determine whether we can have a debate here in which he can raise his issues.</p><p>The Minister of State, Deputy Peter Burke, was mentioned this morning by Senator Davitt.  He has the very sad task this morning of bearing his Dad .  I extend my condolences to him publicly because those of us who are here obviously cannot be with him this morning.  However, we are certainly mindful of this very sad time for his family.</p><p>Senator Kyne welcomed this morning the passport changes that the Minister for Foreign Affairs, Deputy Coveney, has announced.  We are all aware that the Passport Office has been working incredibly hard over recent months, as is evident from the fact that the number of passports it has issued is far in excess of the number issued at any time heretofore.  People can apply online for a passport on a given day and it is put in the post the very next day.  While we know the office can do its work really well, we are all well aware that the difficulties faced by some families, particularly those waiting for a child's first passport, have caused tremendous stress.  The changes announced today recognise that the system was not working.  It is important that we work with people to make sure they can access public services in a very timely manner.  It is the very least we should do.</p><p>Senator Kyne and others welcomed the temporary inclusion of RACO in ICTU for the purpose of its public sector pay talks.</p><p>Senator Davitt asked for a debate on the Irish corporation tax rate.  I will put a request in to the Minister for Finance.</p><p>Senator Moynihan asked for a debate on special education.  I will talk to the responsible Minister to see whether we can arrange that.</p><p>Senator Boylan raised the relaunching of the Raise the Roof campaign this morning and would like a debate on housing.  </p><p>Senator Pippa Hackett regaled us, probably in the only way she can, using beautiful, descriptive language regarding the show that has become synonymous with the bank holiday weekend, Bloom.  Tens of thousands of people go to it and enjoy it.  To echo Senator Hackett, please God we will get the good weather that will encourage people to go.</p><p>Senator Keogan raised concerns not just on her own behalf but also on behalf of others regarding some of the amendments in the work&ndash;life balance Bill.  To be honest with the Senator, I was not aware of the matter raised until she brought it to our attention.  It is certainly something we will have to discuss further when the Bill comes to both Houses.  I thank the Senator for raising it.</p><p>Senator Buttimer asked for a forum to hold the HSE to account.  He has attempted to do so on Commencement Matters here but failed.  An obvious question needs to be asked: why are two advanced-paramedic motorbike units in Cork not being utilised?  I am not sure how I will satisfy the Senator regarding his request but I will put my thinking cap on and determine whether I can find a way to help him.</p><p>Senator O'Loughlin opened by saying Pride Month is synonymous with June.  It is a month that gives us an opportunity to highlight how we absolutely need to treat people with dignity, respect and, in some cases, tolerance.  I refer to treating people just with love.  From my perspective, human beings should be treated with dignity and respect regardless of their views.  We should have respect for each other.  Pride Month is an opportunity for those of us who are LGBT allies &ndash; I really believe we should all be &ndash; to offer support and solidarity to people in a minority group to ensure they receive the treatment, respect and dignity that we all take so much for granted.  </p><p>Senator O'Loughlin acknowledged the inter-parliamentary unit's interactions with the Parliamentary Assembly of the Council of Europe over recent days and stated how we have had 46 different countries here discussing international co-operation.  That is to be very much respected.  </p><p>Senator O'Loughlin also raised the issue of respect for special needs assistants and allocations for schools.  As I have informed Senator Wall, I will talk to the Minister responsible for special education.  Senator O'Loughlin also welcomed the inclusion of RACO in ICTU negotiations.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#P00200"><p>I thank the Leader for that comprehensive response.  Is the Order of Business agreed to?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.72" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.73" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar fionra&iacute; ar 12.55 p.m. agus cuireadh t&uacute;s leis ar&iacute;s ar 1.18 p.m.<br /><br />Sitting suspended at 12.55 p.m. and resumed at 1.18 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.74" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#R00100">Protection of the Native Irish Honey Bee Bill 2021: Second Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1667" speakername="Vincent P Martin" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#R00300"><p>I move: &quot;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&quot;</p><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Senator Hackett to the House.  It is always a pleasure.  It is a different type of welcome for the Minister of State because she is very familiar with the Seanad but it always a pleasure seeing her in the House.  It is good that Seanad &Eacute;ireann has a Member who sits at the Cabinet table.</p><p>Ireland is the envy of much of northern Europe where this bee used to be prevalent.  Due to hybridisation, the pure <i>Apis mellifera mellifera</i>is now only found in a few pockets.  Ireland is fortunate to have a pure population of its own native honeybee that is perfectly adapted to this island, this climate and this flora.  For years it was thought the native Irish honeybee was extinct but scientific research has well and truly proven otherwise.  However, it is threatened with extinction by hybridisation due to continued increasing and unnecessary imports of non-native honeybees.  Imported honeybees mate with natives and destroy the delicate balance honed by thousands of years of evolution.  The unique genetic traits of the native honeybee get lost.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Vincent P. Martin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=VincentPMartin&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=02"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Once genetic diversity is lost, it is lost forever.  This topic is slightly complicated so I ask Members to bear with me.<br/><br/>Under law, honeybees are generally treated in the same manner as fully domesticated livestock, with free movement of honeybees committed throughout the EU in much the same way as cattle or pigs.  However, while cattle and pigs are controlled in their mating habits through artificial insemination and fencing, bees mate in the open so it is not possible to control their mating.  As many Members will know, a hive comprises drones, which are the males, workers and a queen.  Drones from miles around will congregate in an area.  The jury is still out on why they select a specific area but it is normally 10 or 15 m above ground level.  That is called a drone congregation area, where they await virgin queens.  That is in stark contrast to cattle and pigs and therefore deserves much more consideration.  It is a complex matter, considering the drone has a mother but no father, two grandmothers and one grandfather.  It is very different and very precious and merits special attention.<br/><br/>The distinctive characteristics of the native Irish honeybee are the result of natural selection over thousands of years, which has produced a honeybee well-adapted to the current environmental conditions found in Ireland.  Furthermore, its genetic diversity means the population is best equipped to face future challenges the climate and environment may present.  In a nutshell, it is more frugal with its stores, less aggressive, less prone to swarming and is adaptable to the climate and the flora.  We do not want it to go the same way as the curlew.  The indigenous curlew, I fear, is almost beyond return.  I live in hope and BirdWatch Ireland is doing great work but we have lost our curlew.  We do not want to lose our native Irish honeybee.  Professor Tom Seeley, the internationally renowned honeybee expert, referred to this in his foreword to the book published by the Native Irish Honey Bee Society.  I welcome distinguished members of the executive of that organisation who have joined us today, including some of my former teachers, Colm O'Neill and Se&aacute;n Byrne.  They are candid people so no doubt they will tell me later if I got something wrong but I hope I am accurate in what I have said so far.  Well done to the Native Irish Honey Bee Society for fighting this campaign year after year for well over a decade.  The words of Professor Seeley, in the prelude to that excellent book, are very profound.  He says:</p><blockquote>	Ireland remains home to a widespread and remarkably pure population of Apis mellifera mellifera.  This is the subspecies of Apis mellifera that originally lived throughout northern Europe, from the British and Irish Isles to the Ural Mountains.  Over the last 100 years, however, this subspecies has been largely replaced over most of its range as beekeepers in northern Europe have imported countless queens of two subspecies native to southern Europe, A. m. ligustica and A. m. carnica. </blockquote><p>We have to say &quot;Stop&quot; when there is still time and take appropriate legislative action.  There are other bonuses to doing this.  Professor Seeley goes on to say:</p><blockquote>	Ceasing imports will support a drive to boost the abundance of wild colonies of the native Irish honey bee.  Having a sizable population of wild colonies fully exposed to the agents of natural selection - including climate change and novel parasites - will favour the long-term survival of Apis mellifera mellifera in Ireland. </blockquote><p>According to Dr. Helen Mooney, &quot;The genetic integrity of the black bee population in Ireland is the envy of black bee breeders across Europe and ideally, our entire country should become a special area of conservation&quot;.  We are the last stronghold in Europe.<br/><br/>Genetic studies carried out in NUI Galway and Limerick Institute of Technology, funded by the Government and the Native Irish Honey Bee Society, established beyond doubt that our native Irish honeybee has survived on this island and that the population is genetically diverse.  These findings were published in international, peer-reviewed scientific journals.  It is essential to stop imports of non-native bees to protect this valuable genetic resource.  Cross-breeding with subspecies of strains that were not selected by local conditions produces maladapted bees because the delicate and complex genetic systems that took millennia to evolve will be disrupted.  The extent of the risk is emphasised by the fact that in some parts of the island over 70% of swarms or wild colonies show clear evidence of being hybridised to some extent.<br/><br/>Last Friday, I had the honour of chairing a seminar at the Bar Council of Ireland, run by the Climate Bar Association.  One of the guest speakers at that seminar, Kyle Petrie of OpenHive Honey, said that 75% of the swarms he caught are non-native.  Once imports of non-native honeybees are banned, the degree of introgression will be reduced as non-natives are naturally and gradually replaced by native Irish honeybees.  Given the valuable genetic resource that is the native Irish honeybee and its suitability for apiculture, it is under further threat from parasites and pathogens that may be imported with honeybees of any strain, all originating from outside the island of Ireland.  The most destructive pests and pathogens afflicting the native Irish honeybee originated from imported bees.  The two most serious at the moment, the mite varroa destructor, together with its associated viruses, and nosema, are here because of imported honeybees.  Keeping the island clear of the wholesale introduction of pests and parasites reduces the need for chemical treatments to counteract these diseases.<br/><br/>It was reported last year that Ireland recorded a 327% increase in the importation of non-native queens.  This Bill will stop that happening.  It is not too late.  The demonstration outside Leinster House was very effective and done in a very dignified way.  It is not a protest.  The beekeepers are standing in solidarity asking and pleading for action.  They are encouraging the Government to take action.<br/><br/>It is clear that the proposed ban on the importation of honeybees raises a number of important legal issues, including EU law considerations.  Any ban on the importation of honeybees must be a restriction on trade and therefore would not be done lightly.  We are aware of that.  It would have to be justified and proportionate in light of the risk posed.  For fear I would fail the objective bias test as a beekeeper, I approached the Climate Bar Association to give me its independent expert report, conclusions and feedback.  I fully concurred with what it concluded, namely, that it is not repugnant to EU law.  That assessment was done under its chairperson Cl&iacute;ona Kimber SC, who is here today.  So are Donnchadh Woulfe, Sara-Jane O'Brien and Mema Byrne, barristers-at-law.  They have made wonderful contributions to this area and the Bill.  We would not be here today without the Climate Bar Association.<br/><br/>Article 36 of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union allows member states to take measures having an effect equivalent to quantitative restrictions or barriers to trade when these are justified by general non-economic considerations.  That expressly includes public policy or security and the protection of health or life of humans, animals or plants.  Measures adopted under this article are exceptions to the general principle of the EU and ought to be invoked.  Generally there are no barriers to trade between member states but there can be in this specific exception.  I accept this exemption should be interpreted strictly.  It cannot constitute arbitrary discrimination or be a disguised restriction on trade between member states.  It must have a direct effect on the public interest to be protected, not going beyond the necessary level in order to respect the principle of proportionality which is at play here.  The precautionary principle is set out in Article 191 of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union and allows for a higher level of environmental protection thorough preventative decision-making in the case of risk.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Vincent P. Martin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=VincentPMartin&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=02"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The habitats directive ensures the conservation of a wide range of rare, threatened or endemic animal and plant species and does not at present cover bees native to a particular region of Europe.  However, bees other than <i>apis mellifera mellifera</i>are imported into Ireland and they may threaten or adversely impact our biodiversity and related ecosystems.  A member state can add to a list of invasive species by suggesting the name to the Commission, together with a risk assessment, and filling in the form, which is set out in the regulation.  As there are a number of honeybees that threaten the Irish ecosystem, rather than classifying specific bees as invasive alien species, it is submitted that it is preferable to introduce legislation banning the importation of any bee not classified as <i>apis mellifera mellifera</i>.  This approach is in accordance with the precautionary principle and has the added advantage of ensuring that any ban on the importation of honeybees does not go further than necessary to achieve the stated aim.<br/><br/>For too long, we have been saying it cannot be done.  The beekeepers know it ought to be done and the expert independent lawyers have told us how to do it.  There is a way forward.  I will now hand over to my Green Party colleague, Senator Garvey.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1659" speakername="R&oacute;is&iacute;n Garvey" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#T00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State.  I appreciate her taking the time to be here.  I know she understands the importance of this issue.  As Minister of State with responsibility for biodiversity, I am sure she is more aware than most about this issue.</p><p>I thank Senator Martin for pushing this, as well as Senator McGreehan.  It is great to see all the parties united on this because that is a rare thing.  To me, the native Irish bee is like our language or like our hurleys - it is such an integral part of who we are as a nation.  We have struggled with our language, we have struggled with our native trees, and now we are struggling with our native bee.  It is important that we have had the backing of scientists, of beekeepers and of Comhshaol, which is a great organisation of senior counsel who care about climate so much.  We all know there is a biodiversity crisis.  It would be hypocritical in some ways if we did not get this Bill passed by the senior civil servants, even though we are saying there is a biodiversity crisis.</p><p>I was going to talk about other things but what really hit me today, when I went outside, was that I met a lovely 15-year-old, Cillian Fraher, who is a beekeeper.  He is making a living out of it and he is also wheeling and dealing in bits and pieces for the beekeeping industry.  If that is not enough of a reason to pass this Bill, I do not know what is.  I used to work with green schools which teach about biodiversity.  All the children are obsessed with the bee and with saving the bee.  We see this everywhere now and SuperValu is sponsoring a thing around it as well, jumping on the bandwagon.</p><p>Our native Irish bee is integral to who we are.  It is part of our culture and a big and important part of our nature.  We have to do all we can to make sure we get this across the line.  We have precedent in this regard.  The programme for Government does not specifically mention bees but the national pollinator plan states that Ireland has a duty to conserve this genetic resource.  The pollinator plan targets promotion and education of beekeepers to protect the native honeybee, so that is in our national plan.  There is peer-reviewed research from Dr. Grace McCormack of NUI Galway, so we have scientific backing to show that Ireland has a pure population of <i>apis mellifera mellifera</i>, the native Irish bee.</p><p>While I know this is unprecedented in Ireland, it is not unprecedented in other countries.  We have seen it on Scottish islands, Finnish islands and Danish islands, which have had similar challenges around native species.  The international treaties require Ireland to take action to protect native species where they are at risk from invasive species, which is what we are talking about here.  If they were not under threat, we would not be looking for this Bill and neither would the beekeepers.  There is an invasive species that is threatening to take over our native species.  We must learn from other mistakes we have made in not doing enough for biodiversity and protecting our native species.</p><p>This is very important.  Senator Martin is a beekeeper so he is not just making it up as he goes along.  This is coming from the heart of somebody who is a beekeeper and has worked with many beekeepers around Ireland to better inform himself of this issue.  It is very important that we recognise the work of the members of the Native Irish Honey Bee Society, which does its work on a voluntary basis.  We have all been volunteers and it can be exhausting.  However, they are still here and, hopefully, this Bill will get them what they want and truly deserve.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#T00300"><p>I welcome the Minister of State.  It is appropriate that she is here because I know she has a great understanding of this area, particularly when we talk about habitats, biodiversity, research, etc.  It is apt that she is here to preside over this Bill.</p> <p>I want to thank Senator Martin in particular for his enthusiasm.  From day one, he has been talking about the bee.  We have certainly had lovely gifts of honey from him.  He is a great ambassador for the native Irish bee and I want to acknowledge that.  He has engaged and tapped into many people and I have received many emails.  Politicians know that email is nearly like a barometer of public opinion, public support and public lobbying, and he has certainly done that well.  I acknowledge the campaign Senator Martin has run in this regard.</p> <p>It is also important that we acknowledge the co-sponsors of the Bill, Senators Martin, McGreehan, Garvey, Seery Kearney, Boylan, &Oacute; Donnghaile, Norris, Higgins, Craughwell, Gavan, Warfield and Wall.  That indicates the cross-party dynamic that exists and cross-party support for the Bill, which is, as the previous speaker indicated, very important.  It is important because it brings that sense of unity, purpose and function.</p> <p>I want to say a few things about the Bill without going into detail.  I fully support the Bill and I will be voting on every stage.  However, let us not use language that it somehow might be delayed by civil servants or anybody else.  We are the politicians.  This is the Legislature.  These are the Houses of the Oireachtas &ndash; the D&aacute;il and the Seanad.  This Bill is going to be happen.  It has to be driven by the legislators; it has to be driven by the Deputies and Senators.  I do not want to hear in six months time some sort of excuse that it is going to get a Second Reading or Third Reading, or it is going to be gathering dust, or "We have ticked a few boxes, kept a few people happy and they are off our back - get the monkey off our back."  I want to see real progress.  I put that challenge to Senator Martin, who is a member of a Government party, in particular.  He can drive this.  He will have support across the Houses.  I will be supporting him.  However, I want to see that being driven because it is important.  As I said, I acknowledge that cross-party support.</p> <p>It is important that we do not lose sight of the habitat of the bee.  It is important that we look at biodiversity and that we help to increase the rich flora which is very important for the bee.  The bee is a pollinator.  We know the role and significance of pollinators and the need to create habitats where bees can thrive.</p> <p>It is important that we have further education.  This is not that simple for people to understand so we need simple, clear language about it.  Of course, we also need to look at the issue of research.  Senator Martin talked about the varroa mite, which is a real issue in the context of bees.  There are very significant issues and we need a multifaceted approach.  It is about protecting the bee but also, as I said, it is about talking about habitats, biodiversity, education and research, because that is all part of it.  It is also about how we can help in terms of Irish honey and the Irish bee.  It is important that we put our hands in our pockets and support the produce.  There are many ways in which we can support this.</p> <p>I thank the guests in the Visitors Gallery.  It is great to see so many people.  The Gallery has not been full for a long time, certainly not with as many people as are here today.  I thank them all.  Their presence today is very significant and it endorses the importance of this legislation.  I thank the Senators from across the parties who have signed up to this Bill.  In particular, I thank Senator Martin for his continuous and positive engagement to drive this legislation.  I wish him every success.  He will have my absolute support at every stage of this Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1671" speakername="Erin McGreehan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#T00400"><p>I have so much to say about this and I am very excited that we are at this point.  I congratulate Senator Martin for his work on this Bill.  I am a proud member of the Native Irish Honey Bee Society.  I love to get its booklets and information every month because it is something I am passionate about.</p> <p>A very positive form of nationalism is ecological nationalism.  We can really work to look after our own ecology.  We can be very insular in this country in looking after what we have - all of our native crops and our native bees.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Erin McGreehan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=ErinMcGreehan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=02"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I have a project, M&iacute;le Crainn Na h&Eacute;ireann, that is all about native Irish trees.  I have planted approximately 1,500 native Irish trees so far as part of that initiative.  It is very important that we embrace it.  It is also really important, and is the reason we are here today, that the Department embraces it.   We want the Department to be bold, brave, and to say that it will look at EU law and the reality that we have to protect our native biodiversity and our native bees.</p><p>I will go local for a minute.  County Louth has a very strong tradition of protecting and enhancing bees.  The County Louth Beekeepers Association was founded in 1910.  Mr. Turlough O'Bryen, who is known as the father of beekeeping, was born in 1853 in Ardee and was reared and educated there.  The earliest written record of bees in Ireland dates back to the 12th-century Mellifont Abbey, which takes its name from the fountain of honey.  It is also very important to note that the Cooley area, where I hail from, is one of the few places in the world that produces bell honey, which is produced from bees that have gathered nectar from the bell heather.  All this beauty and history, and our heritage, is at risk of being lost if we do not act progressively and positively for the protection of bees.</p><p>The Minister of State is absolutely in favour of this Bill and there is cross-party acknowledgement and acceptance of it.  I know the Taoiseach is a committed biodiversity addict - he takes photographs of butterflies and bees when he is on his evening walks - and is passionate about this matter.  He wants this too.  We all want this and have accepted it.  I have a major ambition for beekeeping and bees.  We can work on many areas.  We know, and it is widely accepted, that bees are superpowers within their little bodies.  Not only do they produce honey, they are essential pollinators in this agricultural country we all belong to.  The Department needs to listen to that.  As I said, we have a long history of producing quality honey.  As we all know, bees have a complicated and innate ability to create and pollinate.  However, they need to survive.  What they need to survive is incredibly modest: pollen, nectar, honey, water and a safe environment.  It is up to us to provide that safe environment.</p><p>Pollen and nectar are foraged from nearby flowers.  That is why it is so important for bee colonies to be situated near a substantial number of native trees, native flowers and native flora.  It is also important we look towards the Department's significant increase in the budget for organic farming in this round of Common Agricultural Policy funding.  That is also one of the very important ways we will protect our native bees and all our native insects and pollinators.  I have put forward proposals, since our bees are classed as livestock, that we should work towards them being a unit of livestock.  Farmers should be encouraged to have beekeeping on their farms and beehives should be classed as a unit of livestock so farmers are able to claim for that and look to that.  If we positively encourage, we will get more beehives.</p><p>In the context of this Bill, I want to highlight that all honeybees are not born equal.  There is a real necessity to protect the native Irish bee.  We must protect it from all external species and uphold the integrity of our native stock.  Studies from the Limerick Institute of Technology prove this and that we have enough native bee stock to save it.  It is low enough to be considered endangered but we have enough to save it and to ensure its native survival across Europe.  We can be that island.  We can be a safe sanctuary.</p><p>I am very excited about this.  It could be said I am buzzing about this because it is very important.  I look forward to this matter being continued and to bringing it up continuously at parliamentary level because it is necessary, it can be done and I am sure it will be done.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1666" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#U00200"><p>I very much support this proposed legislation.  I join with others in thanking Senator Martin for proposing it and for all the work he has done regarding it.  I met the protestors outside Leinster House this morning.  There is a real sense of urgency regarding this legislation.  That is apparent when I meet people and talk to them on the ground, and even on the basis of the number of emails I have received in the past ten days, in particular, on this issue.  It is very welcome legislation.</p> <p>I look forward to going through the legislation section by section.  There are issues I will want clarification on through that process.  From reading the Bill, one of the clarifications I am looking for relates to the all-Ireland dynamic of this legislation and where and how that will fit in.  There are no borders when it comes to biodiversity.  How will we deal with that on the island of Ireland and how will we legislate for it?  It is a question we need to think about and have a solution for as we go forward.  Do we need to engage with our colleagues in the Northern Ireland Assembly?  Do we need to start talking about how we will have an approach to this that will affect the entire island?  I am fearful of how we will practically deal with it due to the Border.  I am unclear on that.  Maybe the proposer of the Bill and the Minister of State might bring clarity on how they will make sure that will be a functional part of the legislation.  There has to be functionality here.  I am a little concerned about how that will practically work through.  My only real concern is on the functionality of how it will work.  If I could get clarity in that regard, it would be very welcome. </p> <p>As for the Bill, the principle of it and where it is going, it is very important.  It is something we need to start talking more about.  There have been some very passionate contributions in the Chamber regarding this issue.  I add my voice of support to this Bill.  It is to be hoped we can work with all parties to make sure it gets through the Houses very swiftly. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#U00300"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it.  I commend members of the Native Irish Honey Bee Society who are here today, and the scientists, on their work on this Bill and for not accepting the excuses or lack of interest from departmental officials.  Through their persistence and dogged research, they have produced incontrovertible evidence that the native Irish honeybee is not only alive and kicking but is doing better than the non-native imports.  It is better in terms of bee health, hive health through the collection of propolis, and honey production, due to its frugal use of food collected and its ability to fly, gather pollen and mate at much lower temperatures proving it has evolved to the Irish climate.  The case for protecting our native Irish honeybee can no longer be dismissed by departmental officials on the grounds of a lack of science or a lack of evidence for the bee's existence.  That is where we see resistance to protecting the species within the Department falling back on that age-old excuse or golden nugget, which is that we cannot do it because the EU will not allow us.</p> <p>I commend the Climate Bar Association on its work and input to this Bill and for pointing out why that argument fails to stack up.  Not only is there a legal precedent in the European Court of Justice, with the Danish case, but all existing EU laws support greater protection for our native species.  The EU Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union clearly accepts that bans on trade are permissible, providing they are proportional and warranted for the protection of the health and lives of humans, animals and plants.  Furthermore, Article 191, which covers the precautionary principle, is much cherished by those of us who are involved in any environmental issues.  It is a principle I am proud to have fought hard to protect as an MEP, when it came under threat from trade agreements such as the Transatlantic Trade and Investment Partnership, TTIP.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Lynn Boylan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=LynnBoylan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=02"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The precautionary principle aims to ensure a higher level of environmental protection through preventative decision-making in the case of risk.  From the evidence that we heard today and the briefing we got in advance of this debate, there has been a 327% increase in the importation of non-native bee colonies.  Professor McCormack's research shows increased levels of hybridisation.  We would be remiss not to invoke Article 191 and ban the importation of non-native honeybees, especially given the way bees breed.  We have heard that they breed in the open which makes it much harder to control hybridisation.  We know that Ireland has a very poor track record historically on environmental protection and this Bill is a real opportunity to start to correct that.</p><p>We have an obligation to protect biodiversity.  We are not only in the midst of a climate crisis, but people forget that we are also in the midst of a biodiversity crisis.  The Bill is a very positive step in protecting a species of significant importance to our heritage.  I hope it will not only pass through the Seanad unopposed today but also that it will spark a conversation on how we can best protect bees and all pollinators.  Lots of people mistakenly believe that we should put hives everywhere or that getting a hive is the way forward, but unless someone is properly qualified and educated in how to keep bees, and also how to keep the right species of bees, then he or she could be doing more damage than good.  Sometimes, the best thing we can do for biodiversity is to let nature do the work by rewilding and stopping the use of non-essential pesticides and chemicals.  If we make space for nature, we will be rewarded.  However, we are legislators, and we have a responsibility to act when we are in the full knowledge of the information.  We know we have a native Irish bee.  We have the evidence and science to support that.  We know the native Irish bee species is under threat.  For this reason, we must pass this Bill and not just in the Seanad.  As Senator Boyhan has pointed out, we need the Bill to pass in the D&aacute;il and to be enacted.  We cannot have a situation whereby we pass this Bill and then it gets buried.  It should be progressed swiftly.  It is not controversial.  We have heard that 90% of beekeepers on the island of Ireland support this legislation.  The beekeepers are asking us to act.</p><p>My colleague, Senator &Oacute; Donnghaile, will speak to the Brexit-related issues and the all-Ireland dimension.  It is regrettable that the Assembly is not up and running.  We want it to be back up and running and we are happy to reach out to the Green Party in the North to see how we can help progress the work MLAs have done on the issue to date in the North.</p><p>I commend Senator Martin on his work on this Bill and his dedication to getting it to this point.  I hope he continues his work to get the Bill progressed all the way through the D&aacute;il.  He has ensured that all of the arguments against progressing this Bill have been effectively removed.  He has science, beekeepers and the law on his side, but perhaps more importantly, he has cross-party support win this Chamber, but that must continue at Cabinet level and in the D&aacute;il.  Otherwise, we are wasting the beekeepers' time and coming in here and giving them false hope.  I want to hear the Minister of State give a commitment to progress the Bill through this House and ensure it will not get buried then but will progress the full way and become enacted.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#V00500"><p>I was in my office dusting off my &quot;What is Plan B?&quot; posters that we had from debates in the previous Oireachtas on the Heritage Bill.  It was a debate on the related issue of habitat and the crucial requirement to protect hedgerows in the context of that legislation.  The focus in particular was on habitats that are crucial for pollinators.  At that point, we recognised the intrinsic role of pollinators, in particular our native bees, in every part of the ecosystem.  These are the enliveners, the continuers.  This is what makes for our ecologically rich biodiversity and also plays a crucial role in horticulture.</p><p>The fact is that we rely very heavily on pollinators, and we do not do enough to protect them.  If lost, they are not something that can be magically found again.  A loss can be devastating.  A bad decision, such as the ones we have seen regarding importation, can be devastating.  We have heard about the scientific examples such as the small hive beetle.  Ireland was free from varroa mite and we had managed to avoid the devastating impact on our bees but then we lost that status following the importation of that pathogen and disease.  Habitat is one crucial issue and the other one is hybridisation, as Senator Martin correctly identifies.</p><p>There are many advantages to the native Irish honeybee.  We will be praising it and outlining why it is particularly suited to Ireland, and why it is the favourite bee for beekeepers in Ireland.  Some 90% of beekeepers use it.  The reason is based on the temperatures it can live at and the placid nature of the bee, which is very important given that we are seeing more urban beekeeping, and more attempts to create the contiguous territories that are needed in terms of bees and pollinator pathways.  We are not simply talking about the role of pollinators in a rural context, but also in an urban context, which is crucial in terms of our national pollinator strategy.  It is why we are pressing towns and villages now to have pollinator plans.</p><p>We must bear in mind the nature of <i>Apis mellifera mellifera</i>, the native honeybee, the fact that it is the best bee suited to our environment but also, crucially, the dangers that are created by importation and hybridisation.  I looked at the research from NUI Galway, which confirms that 90% of Irish beekeepers choose to work with the native Irish honeybee.  The science is very clear on this matter.</p><p>I was going to make many of the same points Senator Boylan made, but I will not repeat everything.  The law is also very clear.  The precautionary principle is a core principle underpinning EU law and that is also evident in case law in the Danish case and other examples in the European Court of Justice.  It is within the remit of a country to seek to protect the life and health of species of animals.  We must consider the intrinsic dangers that are presented by the importation of diseases and pathogens for the horticultural industry as well.  The law is very clear on this.  It should not be an obstacle.  I say this as somebody who spent way too long deep in EU trade law.  The law is not an obstacle in this regard.  We are empowered to take the actions that have been outlined by Senator Martin in this regard.  I think it will be followed through.</p><p>I also wish to make a point that has not been mentioned concerning the sustainable development goals.  Again, they are something to which Ireland has signed up.  An implementation plan is being considered at the moment.  Target 15.8 of the sustainable development goals explicitly calls on governments like ours to &quot;introduce measures to prevent the introduction and significantly reduce the impact of invasive alien species on land and water ecosystems and control or eradicate the priority species.&quot;  Indicator 15.8.1, as a measure of the delivery on which that sustainable development goal is based, refers to the &quot;Proportion of countries adopting relevant national legislation and adequately resourcing the prevention or control of invasive alien species.&quot;  This is literally something we have signed up to in the sustainable development goals, as well as being allowable and indeed required if we are to be true to the precautionary principle under EU law.  In addition, the science tells us that it works and that it matters.  The support is there.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Alice-Mary Higgins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2480"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2480&amp;amp;pid=AliceMaryHiggins&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=02"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Let us celebrate and protect something precious we have.  I urge the Minister of State to ensure this does not get blocked in red tape because if we lose the native honeybee, it cannot be recovered in the same way.  If we expose ourselves needlessly to such a loss, we are endangering our national ecosystems, heritage, horticulture industry and future.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1672" speakername="Rebecca Moynihan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#W00200"><p>I pay tribute to the beekeepers outside and to Senator Martin for bringing forward this legislation.  As an inner-city Dub, biodiversity and bees do not come naturally to me and I found it a learning experience over recent days with the emails we have been getting and the threat the Irish honeybee is under.</p> <p>The Civil Service response is to the effect that it contravenes EU law.  Trade should not and does not trump climate, biodiversity or the need for protection of pathogens.  If we are to get to grips with our climate response, we have to understand that.  Sometimes that will require making balances against trade.  It is important, particularly given that the Bill comes from the Government side of the House, that Government parties work in co-operation with Opposition as a political system to try to change that and challenge the inertia we might see from the Civil Service when it comes to doing that.  The Green Party has the full support of its Government partners, as we can hear in this full House, and across the board in the Opposition.  We need to work as a political system to challenge that and ensure this Bill is passed.</p> <p>It is vital that native Irish honeybees are protected for themselves and for Ireland's ecosystem.  We have talked an awful lot in this Chamber about biodiversity and how important it is to protect it.  We have also talked about how sometimes biodiversity requires taking no action.  This is not one of those cases.  The beekeepers outside have told me that while you might not have one or two generations, when you have the super hybrid of cross-pollination against bees you might in a couple of generations end up with dangerous bees and you do not know what you are importing or bringing in.</p> <p>The Labour Party is supportive of the Bill and would like to see it progressed as quickly as possible.  I assure Government Members that this side of the House will back and support them using the weight of the political system to fight the inertia we might see from civil servants who do not necessarily want to progress this.  I urge Senator Martin to engage with people on pushing to get this beyond Second Stage so it is not one of those Bills that goes into the ether and that nobody else will address.  We do not have time on our side when it comes to something like this.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#W00300"><p>I am glad to be in the House to support Senator Martin's Bill.  I extend a c&eacute;ad m&iacute;le f&aacute;ilte to all the people in our Gallery and a major thank you to the people who gave us a wonderful presentation this morning.  I am sorry that I had to come into the Chamber when the bells rang but I was enjoying the presentation.</p> <p>I pay tribute to Senator Martin for bringing this Bill forward.  More than a year and a half ago through a Commencement matter I brought the same issue to the House but it was in the middle of Covid, down in the convention centre and did not get the coverage it should have got.  This is a far better way to do it by bringing the Bill forward and bringing everybody with Senator Martin.  At that time, a number of people involved in beekeeping contacted me.  The concern at that time was because of Brexit and bees coming in from Europe through Northern Ireland to go into England.</p> <p>I fully support the Bill but the most important issue is the message that needs to go out to the public on the importance of pollination for the production of food.  In our country, not enough people understand that but our younger generation is getting better.  The all-Ireland pollinator plan is important.  I see many communities and schools becoming involved in that.  It is so important that we protect our native honeybees.  This is workable.  Although the Minister of State has to have some concerns regarding Europe, those can be overcome.  The important thing is that all the people, whatever side of the House they are on, are fully supportive of what the Senator is trying to do.  It is important for existence and nature.  If any of us takes heed of nature every day, which I do as a former horticulturist, people will ask where our bees have gone and what is happening to nature.  Even people without a great interest in it will say nature has changed.  Surely that is enough for us as legislators to be supportive of this type of thing and to bring forward suggestions.  I will have some suggestions to add to the Bill when it goes through the House.  </p> <p>It is the road and path we must take.  We have to do it for future generations and for the world to be secure.  Our population in Ireland and over the world must understand how important pollination is for the production of food.  I thank Senator Martin, the Acting Chairman, the Minister of State and all Senators for showing a great interest and helping us along this road, because that is important as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" speakername="Mary Seery Kearney" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#W00400"><p>I welcome the Minister of State and all our beekeepers and scientists.  I apologise because I was in committee and could not come to the presentation this morning.</p> <p>It is my great honour to have been invited by Senator Martin to be a co-signatory of this Bill.  On the day I received his email, it brought me back to being a child.  I have beekeepers in my family.  I do not claim to know anything about beekeeping except having been a child standing and watching my family members as beekeepers.  I always visit the stand at Bloom with an ambition to do this at some point when I do the courses and learn what I should be doing.</p> <p>When I got the email, I reached out to family members to ask if this was something we needed.  I also wondered how many beehives there are in my constituency of Dublin South-Central.  I had the great honour of connecting with Austin Campbell of the Robert Emmet Community Development Project.  Here today we have Anthony Freeman O'Brien, who is the manager of Bee 8, which has two projects with 100 hives.  It has gone further and has a community development project that has partnered with the Digital Hub to put sensors on bees to monitor air pollution in the area.  Even in Dublin city, we have that ability.  I asked their advice regarding the Bill and they came back and said they absolutely supported it and asked if we could look at moving away from a reliance on honey-related revenue towards charging urban businesses to engage in a hive management model that would allow the likes of the Robert Emmet Community Development Project to provide local employment opportunities and enhance the urban environment.  There are opportunities with this.</p> <p>I asked the beekeepers in my family and those I know to put this in layman's terms for me.  The people who speak a lot in this Seanad are terribly impressive but also intimidating to engage with because I would never have the language to be able to engage with somebody who speaks with such great authority.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Mary Seery Kearney:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=MarySeeryKearney&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=02"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The feedback, for those of us who are lay people and know nothing, was that the native black bee was the only bee suited to our climate.  It has survived and thrived.  Currently, there is no ban on importing bees.  If someone wanted Buckfast or Italian bees, in order to have a tamer bee, the difficulty is that over time, bees inter-breed and this means that the hybrid bee is not able to adapt to the environment, humidity or rain and the colony starves and dies off.  It is rather challenging to keep a colony going through the summer to harvest time and even more so over winter.  By not acting to protect what we have, we are significantly contributing to the destruction of our native bee stock.  Absolutely anything and everything necessary to support native bees should be enshrined in legislation as soon as humanly possible.  That is provided that we plan on human beings being around a whole lot longer.  That sums it up in an incredible way.  </p><p>Those of us who are not beekeepers do not think about temperament.  From a temperament point of view, another beekeeper contacted me to say that the beekeeper's experience of having hybrid bees was that they were incredibly aggressive.  When replaced with a native bee queen, peace now reigns in the garden and it is safe for that beekeeper's grandchildren to come to visit.</p><p>It is my honour as a lay outsider to know that fundamentally we need to support our native bee.  I plant particular flowers in the garden to ensure that I am supporting the bees in the way in which I am familiar.  I thank Senator Martin and the Climate Bar Association for all the work it did with him.  I thank him for the opportunity to support this.  I will enjoy and relish the experience of learning as we go through this.  I am looking forward to going out to Bee 8 this summer to annoy Anthony Freeman O'Brien with a load of questions and enjoying that.  I embrace the fact that here in the city we can keep bees.  It is not the preserve of any one quarter.  We should be doing this everywhere.  Why not?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1651" speakername="Paul Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#X00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State and our guests in the Public Gallery.  I apologise for the fact that I did not make it out to them this morning due to prior engagements.  I compliment Senator Martin on his enthusiasm in promoting this Bill and bringing it to this Stage.  I am a firm believer that a stich in time saves nine and that prevention is better than cure.  While it is timely now, to an extent, it would have been preferable to have had this Bill ten, 15 or 20 years ago.  However, it is never too late.  We need to seize the opportunity when it shows and affords itself.  I am delighted to support the Bill and hope to see its speedy passage through this House and the Lower House.</p><p>Prevention is better than cure.  I am a farmer and my party's spokesperson on agriculture.  The Minister of State and I would have had various meetings with regard to forestry.  The case of ash dieback always comes up.  Ash is a prime example of one of our native trees which, through hurling alone, is one of our most famous.  It is threatened by virtue of a disease that was imported.  There are many different species of animal, including cattle.  Our red squirrel was taken out by the grey squirrel.  Our cattle breeds were allowed to diminish mainly, unfortunately, for commercial reasons.  More commercially viable breeds were brought in but we have Moiled cattle and Kerry cattle.</p><p>I will fight tooth and nail that there can be an EU law which can prevent us from stopping the importation of bees which can and will endange,r and have been proven to endanger, the existence of our native bees.  EU laws were very easily twisted and manoeuvred during Covid when we were the species under threat.  The old saying is no food, no people; no bees, no food.  I do not know how an argument can be an argument made that under EU law, we can stop the importation of what can be perceived to be a threat to our native species.</p><p>With regard to prevention, as opposed to cure, we seem to be able to get money readily from the EU, when we decide to close the door after the horse has bolted and want to rejuvenate a species that is extinct or almost extinct.  Unbelievable sums of money are spent through CAP on hen harrier schemes.  We look at &quot;Ear to the Ground&quot; and see projects which are costing the taxpayer considerable money to reinvigorate rare cattle breeds and protect the corncrake, another native species that is almost extinct.  How can the EU justify promoting schemes to reinvigorate and rejuvenate species once they reach that crucial stage of warranting the word &quot;extinct&quot;, rather than putting up barriers to help us to try to prevent getting to that day?  We need the Minister of State, the Department and its officials to argue that case at a European level.  At this juncture, it is not a valid argument and should not be used as such.</p><p>I have been beating this drum previously in terms of what was said earlier by my colleague from Louth, Senator McGreehan.  I am also a firm believer that within CAP and other schemes, a controlled keeping of bees on a farm in a <i>pro rata</i>ratio of numbers should equate, at some stage of the viable bee-keeping operation on a farm, to a livestock unit.  That would be very beneficial for our biodiversity and our ecosystems.  Without pollination, we do not have food.  Without food, we do not have people.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1688" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#X00300"><p>D&eacute; a beatha chuig an Aire St&aacute;it.  T&aacute; m&eacute; chomh s&aacute;sta go bhfuil an seal agam labhairt ar son na reachta&iacute;ochta t&aacute;bhachta&iacute; seo ar an mbeach meala d&uacute;chasa&iacute; &Eacute;ireanna&iacute;.  The Minister of State is very welcome to today's debate on this important legislation.  I am very proud and privileged along with my colleague, Senator Boylan, to be able to support the Bill.  I am very keen to see it progress through these houses speedily, efficiently and, most important, effectively in terms of outcomes.  It is amazing what this issue can galvanise among people.  Our guests are very welcome to the Public Gallery.</p> <p>I put a tweet up having met with some of our guests out the front.  We know that a load of pinging on Twitter is not always good but it was instantly very good, warm and supportive today.  People spoke about their own experiences supporting projects to protect our indigenous bees.  I was invited up to see a mural which included the native Irish honeybees at Ardoyne Kickhams GAC.  It is on the grounds of Bunscoil Mhic Reachtain.  I texted my colleague, Francie Molloy, who is the MP for mid-Ulster.  Mr. Molloy is a long-time beekeeper which many people may not know.  Much like other speakers, I am by no means an expert in this field and I had to explain this over and again to the people with whom I enjoyed speaking to out the front.  I asked Mr. Molloy for an idiot's guide to this because that is what is required.  He texted back to say that native Irish bees are much calmer and easier to work with and that protection is important, as bees being imported brings the risk of infection which can wipe out the colony and that local honey is good for one's health.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#X00400"><p>Does that conclude Senator &Oacute; Donnghaile's contribution?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1688" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#X00500"><p>It nearly does but I will move on to my notes.  As the Minister of State knows, the scientific argument for this Bill is impressive, but I am not a scientist or an ecologist.  I have left it to other colleagues to address the scientific merits.  All I will say is that, from my lay person's perspective, the threat of hybridisation to the native Irish honeybee warrants this legislative protection.  That is why the Bill is most welcome.</p> <p>I will instead look at some of the legal questions around the Bill.  It has incredible support from 90% of beekeepers throughout Ireland.  Some concerns were raised about how it impinges on freedom of trade within the EU.  However, at a briefing this morning, Cliona Kimber, senior counsel, argued that not only is it possible to ban the import of non-native honeybees, there is a requirement for us to act.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2477"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2477&amp;amp;pid=NiallODonnghaile&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=02"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We can point to many EU treaties that allow us have exemptions to free trade, but I mention just one, namely, Regulation (EU) No 1143/2014 on the prevention and management of the introduction and spread of invasive alien species.  It states: "Invasive alien species represent one of the main threats to biodiversity...especially in geographically and evolutionarily isolated ecosystems, such as...islands".  Ireland, as an island, is a single ecological unit.  The free trade in bees from abroad is a threat to the native population, so we can avail of exemptions to free trade for islands.  It underscores the point that if we are going to address the biodiversity crisis, it will very often need to be done on an all-Ireland basis.</p><p>One of the other legal questions raised is, if we ban the importation of bees down here, could they still be imported through the North.  Donnchadh Woulfe of Comhshaol address this point.  In Britain, there is a ban on the importation of broods.  The North is exempt from this British ban under the protocol because of the need to align with EU law and this jurisdiction, which has no ban.  However, if we were to bring in this ban down here, the reason for exemption would go away.  Thus there is no fear of broods coming in the back door.  However, non-native queens could still be imported under British law if it was applied in the North.  That is why, as I understand it, the assembly could work to introduce a similar ban up there as we are debating here.  I will be raising this with my colleagues in the North so that they can advance this solution when the Executive is up and running, which I hope will be sooner rather than later.  Colleagues in the Green Party will no doubt do likewise.</p><p>I conclude by paying tribute to Senator Vincent P. Martin for all his work in drafting the Bill in collaboration with Comhshaol, the climate bar association.  He found an issue that has not only widespread support among beekeepers across Ireland, but crucially, among Seanad&oacute;ir&iacute; from across the House.  I hope the Minister of State, as a proud and respected Member of this House, will keep that in mind as we progress this legislation.  In commending Senator Martin and wishing him well, I hope we get to see this back speedily.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#Y00200"><p>I thank the Senator.  Before I bring in Senator Kyne I welcome to the Public Gallery former Senator Se&aacute;n Barrett and his guest, L&aacute;szl&oacute; Moln&aacute;rfi from Hungary.  They are joining us and observing our proceedings.  They, along with our other guests, are very welcome.  It is good to see them all here for this debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1665" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#Y00300"><p>I support this Bill and commend Senator Martin for initiating this legislation that, as the Cathaoirleach said, has generated cross-party support.  I acknowledge also the presentation this morning and the briefing in the AV room, which was informative and well-attended.  There were many valuable contributions in the field, both legal and those involved in beekeeping.</p> <p>I will be brief in my comments.  I absolutely support this initiative.  It is not often you see 90% support among a group of individuals, in this case beekeepers, on a policy initiative.  There is some opposition and that is to be expected and respected and we should work with those individuals as well.  The Bill has not taken a heavy-handed approach to existing hives in the country.  Working with those individuals is a better way to go.  I mention some of the issues here.  If you are talking about a hive or a brood that is a larger structure, if you like.  It is not as easy to hide.  An individual queen or a small number of them could be more easily hidden.  That would be the concern with the implementation of this legislation and the sourcing of such queens, which, as I said, can be stored in small boxes.  I do not know how they would be transported but they are small.  It is not an elephant.  In fact it is the opposite.  It is about how this can realistically be instigated.  How non-native bees could be found is my concern.</p> <p>Overall, there is much work to be done continuously on education about the importance of bees.  I am aware many groups do important work on this but more is needed on the important role the bee plays across our country, countryside and ecosystems.  I commend all involved in this legislation and supporting it.  I hope to see it advance to Committee Stage and go to the other House as soon as possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#Y00400"><p>As no other Senators are indicating, I call on the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1661" speakername="Pippa Hackett" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#Y00500"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach Gn&iacute;omhach.  I thank the Senators who have contributed.  I welcome the visitors to the Gallery and acknowledge their genuine passion to protect <i>Apis mellifera mellifera</i>.  On behalf of the Government, I acknowledge also Senators' commitment to protecting the native Irish honeybee.  Clearly, the support across the House is stark; it is across all parties and none.  While I was in the Chamber earlier for the Order of Business, officials from my Department met the representatives of the Native Irish Honey Bee Society outside Leinster House to reassure them of the Department's commitment to the protection of the species.  I understand they have agreed to meet formally with the society in the coming weeks to discuss how we can best work together to deliver the protection for this special bee.</p><p>Bees and other pollinators have thrived for years, ensuring food security and nutrition and maintaining biodiversity and vibrant ecosystems for plants, humans and the bees themselves.  I was struck by Senator Martin saying in his introduction that bees breed in the open.  It is so true.  As farmers, we certainly strive to prevent our livestock breeding out in the open but it does not always work.  However, many Senators will be aware the Government has some concerns a statutory ban on bee imports into Ireland would constitute a restriction on trade under EU regulations.  I am aware that has been debated in the House today.  We are taking advice around the compatibility of the Bill with EU Single Market rules.  As Senator Martin highlighted in his opening statement, any such restriction on trade would have to be demonstrably necessary and proportionate to achieve an objective permitted by EU law.  Furthermore, it would also need to be demonstrated it would not be possible to achieve the policy objectives proposed, namely, protecting biodiversity and ecosystems, without such a restriction on trade and by any less stringent measures.  Additionally, it would be necessary to establish based on robust scientific evidence there is a threat to the native Irish honeybee arising from the importation of non-native species.  Senator Lombard raised a concern that would need to be examined and fully addressed around the all-island nature of this and how we might be able to operate this Bill on such a basis.  That is something that will also need to be ironed out.  Senator Martin may or may not address this in his closing statement but it is an issue.</p><p>There are other concerns that need to be addressed but, as Senator McGreehan said, let us look at this.  We are willing to look at this and let us see what we can do to fix this.  I understand during Covid there has been something of a proliferation of beekeepers.  I have spoken to some of those casually and asked people what type of bee they have and they do not know.  The education piece Senator Boylan mentioned is therefore important and something my Department has tried to support.  We must be careful here and people need to be educated not just on the management of the bees but also the species they are purchasing and where and how they are doing that.</p><p>The Government and my Department have put in many supports to date to protect the native Irish honeybee.  These were not only about raising awareness among beekeepers about the importance of that native species.  Funding has been provided by my Department through the scheme for the conservation of genetic resources and the scheme of investment aid for the development of the commercial horticulture sector.  There will also be supports for apiculture under the next round of the CAP.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Pippa Hackett:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=0000"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=0000&amp;amp;pid=PippaHackett&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=02"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We try to support beekeepers in sourcing native bees to assist breeding activities and ensure they are available to meet beekeeper demand.  Support is also being provided to beekeeping organisations, including financial support, for the conservation of the native Irish honeybee.  There is a focus on education and awareness-raising initiatives aimed at new beekeepers.</p><p>Senator Higgins spoke about the urban context of biodiversity and pollinators.  Senator Seery Kearney also addressed that matter.  I am pleased to announce that, last month, we saw the reintroduction of native Irish honeybee hives to the roof of Agriculture House, which is in the middle of the city.  Those bees are doing their bit for pollinators on St. Stephen's Green, Merrion Square or however far they fly.  It is nice to know that they are up there.</p><p>The All-Ireland Pollinator Plan 2021-2025 is a new five-year roadmap that aims to help bees, other pollinating insects and our wider biodiversity.  It includes the All-Ireland Honey Bee Strategy 2021-2025, which seeks to conserve not only the native Irish honeybee, but also our bumblebee and solitary bee populations.</p><p>I thank Senators once again for their interactions and comments.  Their contributions were valuable.  I look forward to engaging further with them on the progression of this Bill once the Government has received the detailed legal and technical advice around its concerns.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#Z00200"><p>It is always nice to chair a debate where everyone is on the same side and there is not too much controversy in the room.</p> <p>Senator Ahearn wishes to contribute.  Unfortunately, he will not be able to get a response from the Minister of State, given that she can only speak once, but he can certainly put his thoughts on the record.</p> <p>Before he does, though, I welcome to the Gallery a person I knew a long time ago when he was in university.  He is back now and helping with this legislation, namely, Mr. Donnchadh Woulfe.  He is here with his son.  He has put a great deal of work into the Bill.  They are both welcome to the Chamber.  It is good to see Mr. Woulfe.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1629" speakername="Garret Ahearn" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#Z00300"><p>I am sharing time with Senator O'Reilly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#Z00400"><p>The Senators can each have six minutes.  If Senator Ahearn does not need his, we can just move on to Senator O'Reilly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1629" speakername="Garret Ahearn" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#Z00500"><p>I am grateful for the opportunity to contribute.  I had a busy morning and have only just come back on time, as I wanted to make a contribution on this important matter, which affects many people in Tipperary.  We have many beekeepers in the county and Clonmel is the home of honey.  It is an important sector for us.  I acknowledge the work that the Minister of State has done on this matter over the past two years in her role in biodiversity, which will play an important part over the coming years.</p> <p>It is great that we are all on the same side.  This is a technical Bill and we need to work together on it.  We will do so.  I support the Bill.  I thank my colleague, Senator Martin, for having the commitment and energy to introduce it.  In my eyes and those of the people to whom I have spoken in Tipperary, this is important legislation.  We might need to make changes, and that is fine.  We can all work together to make that happen.  It is important that the Bill be supported from all sides.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#Z00600"><p>I thank my colleague, Senator Ahearn, for offering to share time.  As the Acting Chairperson said, it was not necessary.</p> <p>I welcome our colleague from the Seanad, the Minister of State, to the House.  It is apt that she should take the debate on this legislation.</p> <p>I congratulate my great friend, colleague and neighbour from home, Senator Martin, on introducing the Bill and, in his inimitable way, achieving unanimity on it among the parties and Independents.  That is a testament not only to his sincerity and competence, but also his skills in mediation and organisation.  I salute him for that and for this legislation.</p> <p>The Bill is worthy.  I was busy today, but I watched on my monitor as our colleague, Senator Boylan, whom I understand has a level of expertise in this area, made the apt point that the Department was now being presented with incontrovertible evidence on the science behind the need to preserve our native bee - the black bee - and the legal frameworks within European law.  The science is established and the legal situation has been well established by the best of legal experts.  Well-known and published people on European, international law and commercial law have stated that this Bill will pass muster legally, although that is a secondary consideration.</p> <p>From the point of view of biodiversity, the preservation of this important and indigenous species of bee and our honey production industry, there is a case for this legislation.  I might not be able to stay and listen to him - he will not mind, as I will be able to read it in the Official Report - but I would like Senator Martin to answer a question for me.  I understand that they are few in number, but how will we deal with those who are importing non-indigenous bees and stand to make a certain level of commercial loss under this Bill?  If I understand the matter correctly, they would be phased into the new situation, but there might have to be some compensation for them, especially if they have employees.  It is important that the Senator comment on this matter and that the Minister of State respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#Z00700"><p>The Minister of State will not be able to respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#Z00800"><p>I am sorry.  I did not realise.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#Z00900"><p>I am sure she will be able to on Committee Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#Z01000"><p>Given Senator Martin's eclectic and great intelligence, I presume that he addressed in his mind before producing the Bill the question of how to deal with those who could be impacted commercially, including how to phase them into the new reality.</p> <p>This is excellent legislation.  I had the privilege of attending the briefing organised by Senator Martin, where good questions were asked.  There is an incontrovertible case for this Bill.  It is timely legislation that is supported by us all.  I am enthusiastically backing it, as is my party.  I wish it well and I hope it goes through all Stages quickly and successfully.  I will read the Official Report, or speak to the Senator privately, to see how he proposes to address the question I raised.  I can think of no other issue.</p> <p>I thank the Acting Chairperson for the opportunity to contribute.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#Z01100"><p>Next is Senator Maria Byrne.  I cannot say yet whether she will be a supporter of the Bill, but I imagine she is.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1695" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#Z01200"><p>I was listening to the debate upstairs because I had some work to do.  It has been a fruitful debate and I compliment Senators Martin and Garvey on tabling this worthy legislation.  I lend my support to it.  Much of what I would like to say has been said and I am not in the habit of repeating comments, but the Bill has my full support and I am delighted that it has support from across the House.  I wish Senator Martin and the legislation all the best.  We see bees every summer and we are all aware of them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1667" speakername="Vincent P Martin" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#Z01300"><p>I thank my colleagues for their kind words and for their support, bar none, for this legislative initiative.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Vincent P. Martin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=VincentPMartin&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=02"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I deliberately set out to have, if one looks at the list at the back of the Bill document, a representative from each of the groupings in this House and there are others who are not on the list who ought to be on the list.  I know that Senator Keogan is a supporter as is horticulturalist, Senator Murphy, who made a contribution earlier and I regret that he did not make the deadline for this short opening and window of opportunity.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#AA00200"><p>I think Senator Martin might have had mine and all names on this list if the Senator had pursued all Members in this regard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1667" speakername="Vincent P Martin" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#AA00300"><p>The Public Gallery attendees may get the wrong impression that the Chamber is like this all of the time and it is not.  That is why it is so incredibly amazing today.</p> <p>Last week we had the first member of the U.S. Congress here to address the House in the 100 year history of the Seanad and I was struck by the bipartisan congressional delegation.  In America, politics is so fragmented but they spoke with one unified voice on the protocol and the way forward for Northern Ireland and on protecting the Good Friday Agreement.  That is just one positive moment to reflect upon and I find it uplifting.</p> <p>I also find it very uplifting to get this cross-party support which we are forever grateful for.  I also thank the Minister of State for her contribution.  If it is ever going to happen it will happen now.  The beekeepers are around long enough to know that this is progress today.  We are not getting carried away.  If it gets through today, it will be put to a vote.  I am not a betting person but it looks like this measure could easily get passed today from the contributions I have heard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#AA00400"><p>It is probably the safest bet the Senator would ever make.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1667" speakername="Vincent P Martin" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#AA00500"><p>I would also like to single out Senator McGreehan as part of that collaborative approach.  We brought a Commencement matter together on this issue.  I also acknowledge the support of Senators Boylan and Seery Kearney.  Senator Seery Kearney's modesty pervades her when it comes to beekeeping but she is a respected member of the Law Library and would know this area of law and the legalities of it sit easily with her.  It is also good to have her support.</p> <p>The members of the Native Irish Honey Bee Society, NIBS, are the volunteers on the front line.  They are not paid officials and do this for love and dedication.  They know the price of this and what is at stake.  As was said, this was tested in the courts when biodiversity was less in vogue and it stood the test in the Court of Justice of the European Union, ECJ, in the Denmark case.  There is what is called a precedent there.</p> <p>I thank Sinn F&eacute;in.  I lost my two Green Party colleagues and representatives in the recent election in Northern Ireland, Rachel Woods and Clare Bailey, who gave us a voice there but this is beyond politics.  For Sinn F&eacute;in, Stormont should be up and running as soon as possible.  This biodiversity crisis knows no borders and does not recognise party political coloured jerseys.</p> <p>To draw a far-fetched sporting analogy, there was a team in the English soccer Premier League years ago that just wanted to stay up and not get relegated and it occasionally tried to score on the break.  They were defensive and not offensive and the full team was accused of parking a bus in front of the goals.  It is not time to park the bus now but is time for what the Netherlands did in the 1970s, which was to play total football and to be proactive.  We do not have time to hang around.</p> <p>This is a crisis. The planet is burning and time is not on our side.  We have declared a biodiversity and climate emergency.  What does that mean in practical terms?  This is a golden opportunity.  We have to go beyond decade-old concerns which have been in the Department for years that there will be a trade war.  Will all butter be banned?  Really, this is not going to happen.  There are exceptions laid down and people cannot afford to be conservative.</p> <p>There is a potential to develop jurisprudence here and this approach may be judge-led and created, where there is positive discrimination in favour of ambition and of giving the bounce of the ball to being proactive to protect our climate and our biodiversity, if it is the case that this protection does not come through legislation.  I foresee that because the EU is a changed place.  It is no longer a cold home.  It is a very welcoming and radical home for the protection of our environment.</p> <p>It is crucial that we preserve a vital piece of Europe&rsquo;s biological treasury.  To take up the issue raised by Senator Joe O&rsquo;Reilly, there are some who will not like this and for whom this will not be music to their ears, namely, commercial importers of non-native species.  We have many commercial beekeepers, however, of native bees and this measure is not just for people who have a hobby.</p> <p>I will conclude by saying that all of the representative bodies support this.  In respect of the few people who may not, I received four emails when I introduced this Bill last October, all from people who worked in the commercial sector who imported the non-native species.  They must be respected and listened to as it could affect their livelihood.  We must support them in this step change and in adapting a new way for them, show them that it is not the end of the road and that they can bring this forward.</p> <p>At the end of the day, with the indulgence of the Cathaoirleach Gn&iacute;omhach, I omitted to mention the economic value of this legislation.  Trinity College Dublin prepared a report for the Environmental Protection Agency on the market and non-market value of pollination services in Ireland.  It found from these data that the global value of animal pollination to crop production was estimated to be $158 billion to $412 billion.  Using the same approach, the annual value of animal pollination to home-produced crops in Ireland was estimated to be &euro;20 million to &euro;59 million per year.  We do not need the economics but it is also on our side.</p> <p>This is more important than pounds, shillings and pence.  This is a biodiversity crisis.  We cannot undo it if it happens.  The Germans are very upset that they let their bee go.  We have to stand up for our bee and to be ready for action.  We have to go big or go home and we cannot fall aside for lack of ambition.  It is time to be very proactive and not to be afraid of litigation.  We are doing the right thing.  If truth, justice, resilience and prioritisation of biodiversity are on our side, we cannot go too far wrong.  Gabhaim bu&iacute;ochas.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1661" speakername="Pippa Hackett" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#AA00600"><p>Well done.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#AA00700"><p>I thank Senator Martin.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.120" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#AA00900"><p>When is it proposed that we take Committee Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1667" speakername="Vincent P Martin" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#AA01000"><p>Next Tuesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#AA01050"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.124" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Committee Stage ordered for Tuesday, 7 June 2022.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#AA01200"><p>When is it proposed to sit again?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1695" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022060200002#AA01300"><p>At noon on Tuesday, 14 June 2022.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-06-02a.127" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar athl&oacute; ar 2.47 p.m. go dt&iacute; me&aacute;n lae, D&eacute; M&aacute;irt, an 14 Meitheamh 2022.</p><p>The Seanad adjourned at 2.47 p.m. until 12 noon on Tuesday, 14 June 2022.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>