<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Leas-Chathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.4" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#A00200"><p>I have notice from Senator Billy Lawless that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Education and Skills to outline whether children of returning emigrants are eligible for free third level fees.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Gerald Nash of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport to review the mechanism whereby taxi licences can be transferred to family members in the event of the death of the licenceholder.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator P&aacute;draig Mac Lochlainn of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Business, Enterprise and Innovation to make a statement on whether the growth in IDA Ireland supported jobs in County Donegal since 2000 is less than half the national average.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Maura Hopkins of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister of State with responsibility for mental health and older people to provide an update on the measures being taken by the Health Service Executive following the recent Mental Health Commission report regarding the Roscommon inpatient mental health unit.</blockquote> <p>The matters raised by the Senators are suitable for discussion and they will be taken now.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.7" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#A00300">Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.8" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#A00400">Diaspora Issues</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#A00500"><p>I welcome the Minister of State at the Department of Education and Skills, Deputy Mary Mitchell O'Connor.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1429" speakername="Billy Lawless" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#A00600"><p>I thank the Minister of State for attending to discuss this important topic.  In February last, the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade published a report by Indecon Economic Consultants on addressing challenges faced by returning emigrants.  I am pleased the Minister of State with responsibility for the diaspora is committed to implementing the report in full.  This independent research found that payment of fees is a significant issue for the diaspora community abroad.  More than 40% of respondents in the study indicated the issue of third level fees was a factor in their decision not to return to Ireland.  On foot of these findings and representations received, the report recommended that consideration be given to a means-tested grants system for first-time third level education for children of Irish or European Union citizens.  Some of the criteria suggested in the report include that the recommendation only apply to cases where the parents are Irish citizens of the European Union, have lived in Ireland for 15 years or more and would have financial difficulties funding their children's university education in Ireland.  These are common-sense proposals.</p> <p>The report also found merit in considering a wider eligibility for EU fees for children of Irish emigrants.  It further suggests there may be potential to expand the existing Government of Ireland international educational scholarships to assist those who are not eligible for European Union fees.  I would be grateful if the Minister of State would answer three questions on this matter.  First, will the Minister be able to implement the recommendations of the Indecon Economic Consultants report?  Second, is primary or secondary legislation required to implement any of the recommendations?  Third, what timeline does the Minister envisage for the implementation of the recommendations?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1247" speakername="Mary Mitchell O'Connor" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#A00700"><p>I thank Senator Lawless for raising this important matter.  I will try to answer the three questions he asked.  The current position is that to qualify for funding towards tuition fees, students must be first-time undergraduates, hold <i>inter alia </i>European Union, European Economic Area or Swiss nationality in their own right and have been ordinarily resident in an EU-EEA state or Switzerland for at least three of the five years preceding their entry to approved third level courses.  Where undergraduate students do not qualify for free fees, they are required to pay fees to their higher education institute at either an EU rate or a higher non-EU rate.</p><p>The Department responded previously to concerns about the impact of the free fees eligibility criteria on individuals who have had to move abroad for occupational or economic reasons and which required them to take their children out of the Irish education system in the process.  To this end, in March 2014 the Department of Education and Skills requested that the Higher Education Authority advise the higher education sector that full-time undergraduate students who hold EU, EEA or Swiss nationality but do not meet the residency clause of the free fees initiatives and have completed five academic years of study at either primary or post-primary in an EU or EEA state or Switzerland and commenced their undergraduate course of study in an approved institution here should, from the following academic year onwards, be charged an EU rate of fee rather than the higher non-EU rate by their higher education institution.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Mary Mitchell O'Connor:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2284"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2284&amp;amp;pid=MaryMitchellOConnor&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This approach was implemented for new students from the commencement of the 2014-15 academic year.  It is a matter for the institutions to apply this policy to such students and I am not aware of any particular issue arising from the implementation of this policy direction.</p><p>It is important to recognise that higher education institutions are autonomous bodies and the Department has a limited role in the day-to-day running of their operational affairs.  It is an issue for higher education institutions in the first instance to determine the level of fee applicable to particular programmes or elements of academic programmes.  The student contribution, which currently stands at &euro;3,000, applies to all students who benefit under the Department's free fees initiative.  This student contribution is paid by the Exchequer in respect of students who qualify under the Department's third level grant scheme.  Tax relief is also available for second and subsequent siblings to alleviate the costs for families of approved courses at approved colleges of higher education.</p><p>In early 2018, the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade commissioned a report, entitled "Economic Report on Addressing Challenges Faced by Returning Irish Emigrants".  This report, which was undertaken by Indecon, identified education along with other issues - driving licences, health insurance etc. - as one of a number of factors influencing the return of emigrants.  The report made a number of recommendations on addressing education-related barriers in respect of third level education, those being, to consider a means-tested third level grant for children of emigrants and to introduce increased flexibility for EU postgraduate fees.  I have already spoken to the Ministers, Deputies Coveney and Donohoe, and the Minister of State, Deputy Cannon, but we will shortly have a formal meeting to discuss these proposals in detail.  The Minister of State will report to the Cabinet in the coming months.</p><p>The Department will consider the report's recommendations in the context of a broader programme of higher education funding reform.  However, it is important to recognise that in implementing the free fees and student grant schemes, my Department needs to be conscious of the need for consistency in how individuals are treated and the potential financial and other policy implications arising from any specific proposal to make changes to either scheme.</p><p>I thank the Senator for affording me the opportunity to respond to the House.  As to his question on whether we would be able to implement the report, I will meet the Ministers and Minister of State.  We are taking this matter seriously and the Department is scoping it out.  I will have to check as to whether primary or secondary legislation is required.  As to the timeline, the meeting with the Ministers and Minister of State will take place after Easter and the Minister of State will report to the Cabinet in a few months' time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1429" speakername="Billy Lawless" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#B00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  As an educationalist herself, she understands the implications of this situation.  The number of people involved is small, so we should be able to handle them.  In many instances, a lot of the parents who emigrated through intra-company transfers and so on are high achievers with kids who are also high achievers and who would qualify for scholarships in the US, but they cannot avail of those because they are not American citizens.  They return to Ireland as Irish citizens only to be penalised here as well.  It is not fair.</p> <p>The Minister of State is aware of another suggestion.  The universities are autonomous bodies but we are still subsidising many of them and we should be examining the possibility of a scholarship scheme for those individuals coming home.  There are cases in which parents cannot afford to send their children to university.  That is not right.</p> <p>I thank the Minister of State for her concern.  She has a personal interest in this matter.  I thank her for her response, which I appreciated.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#B00300"><p>Does the Minister of State wish to add anything?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1247" speakername="Mary Mitchell O'Connor" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#B00400"><p>No.  I will leave what I have said.  The Minister of State, Deputy Cannon, will report to the Cabinet.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1429" speakername="Billy Lawless" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#B00500"><p>I thank the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.17" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#B00600">Taxi Licences</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#B00700"><p>I raise an important matter concerning the Taxi Regulator and the treatment of the next of kin of deceased taxi licence and plate holders.  As the Minister will understand, taxi owners form an integral part of the public transport system.  They are largely self-employed and work hard to earn what can only be described as very modest incomes.  They comply with the law and pay their taxes and have been subject to an increased degree of regulation in recent years, which has helped to professionalise the industry and root out many of the dubious elements who had been involved in recent decades.  The Minister will concede that they and their families are entitled to have a fair crack of the whip.</p> <p>I wish to share with the House and the Minister the shocking experience of a Drogheda woman, Ms Marie Keegan, at the hands of this bureaucracy.  Marie's husband-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#B00800"><p>We are not supposed to name particular people.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#B00900"><p>It is important in order to illustrate the point.  This woman has spoken publicly and has no difficulty being referred to in the House.  Her husband was a taxi driver for almost 30 years.  When the business was deregulated in 2000, he bought his own plate like thousands of others.  He worked hard for 17 or 18 years as the owner of that plate and met all of the industry regulations with which he had to comply.  Tragically, Tommy died in Lanzarote while on holidays in January.  His sudden passing was an unspeakable tragedy for Marie and Tommy's wider circle of friends in the Drogheda area.</p> <p>In recent weeks and in an effort to tie up the loose ends that occur when someone passes away, Marie, with the help of Tommy's colleagues in Drogheda, contacted the Taxi Regulator to make arrangements for the transfer of the taxi licence to her.  What happened next came as a shock.  The regulator stated that the licence that Tommy owned in effect died with him.  Marie was told that a little known form called the S15N had not been filled in by him in order to nominate her in the event of his passing.  In the absence of that form being signed, the licence simply reverted to the regulator.</p> <p>Not only has Marie had to deal with the unspeakable grief of suddenly losing her husband in very difficult circumstances, but she now has to deal with the reality of losing his business and a critical source of income for her as well.  This has been described by many in the media and Marie herself as something akin to stealing from her husband.  I would have to agree with that analogy.</p> <p>There is another case of a woman who has spoken publicly on "Liveline" in recent weeks, that of Carol Lee, who lost her husband Mick, a taxi driver of long standing.  Her circumstances directly mirror the experience of Marie Keegan in Drogheda.  She has lost her husband's taxi licence.  She made contact with the Taxi Regulator only to be told that, because this form had not been filled in, the licence essentially died with him.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Gerald Nash:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2281"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2281&amp;amp;pid=GeraldNash&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> It seems to me that the taxi sector is not broadly familiar with this system.  There does not seem to be any appeal or discretion and there is no human understanding whatsoever of the situation in which people like Marie Keegan find themselves.  Surely, a taxi licence is an asset and, like any other asset, it can be transferred through a person's estate to next of kin in the normal way.  I believe this has been dealt with in a cold, callous and inhumane fashion.  I call on the Minister to respond on the associated policy matters and to commit to working with the National Transport Authority, NTA, which is the regulator of taxis, to try to divine a way in which this matter can be resolved in the interests of the next of kin of deceased taxi drivers who have not filled in this nomination form.  They find not only that they have to deal with the grief of losing a family member but they have the difficulty of losing their business too.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#C00200"><p>I thank Senator Nash for raising this issue, which is one that has obviously caused great distress.  I wish to express my sympathy for the widow on the death of her husband in this case.  I understand the distress she is suffering and the expectation that she might have received something that she has not.  My guess is that the human elements of this are extremely worrying for the family and that we probably have uncovered a somewhat complicated issue that has the capacity to cause unexpected distress to bereaved people, something they could do without at a time of grieving.</p> <p>As the Senator is probably aware, under the Taxi Regulation Act 2013, the NTA is the independent regulator of the taxi, hackney and limousine sectors.  Technically, these are known in the legislation as small public service vehicles or SPSVs.  Section 15 of the Act deals with the transfer of SPSV licences in the event of death.  The 2013 Act sets out new rules and arrangements relating to licences for small public service vehicles.  It took account of a review of the taxi industry conducted in 2011.  Recommendations arising from the review were widely publicised at the time through the media, the NTA website and industry updates.  Action 14 of the published report recommended the introduction of a general prohibition of the transferability of taxi licences.  The measure was provided for in section 41 of the Taxi Regulation Act 2013, which was commenced with effect from 6 April 2014.</p> <p>Provision was made in section 15 to enable the reassignment of an SPSV licence in the event of the death of the licenceholder.  Under the law, a licenceholder can formally nominate someone to take over the licence when the holder dies.  The Act sets out rules governing the process.  The provision applies to all categories of SPSV, including taxi, hackneys, limousines, wheelchair-accessible taxis and wheelchair-accessible hackneys.  This process relates to the licence for the vehicle to be used as a public vehicle.  Obviously, in the interests of public safety and consumer protection, the vehicle is still required to meet the normal safety standards set for SPSVs and the new driver must meet the requirements for an SPSV driver licence.</p> <p>The NTA is the independent regulator and administers the process for these formal nominations and reassignments of vehicle licences.  The NTA website has details about the process and the relevant forms.  The nomination form and an information guide can be collected in hard copy at all NTA inspection centres or when requested through the industry information line.</p> <p>The industry is regularly requested to complete this free nomination process through the SPSV industry updates newsletter.  I am told that these forms are also handed to licenceholders or their representatives after every annual vehicle inspection.  The NTA has informed me that it urges all SPSV licenceholders to submit a completed nomination form.</p> <p>I am aware that there have been cases where licenceholders have passed away without completing this form.  I am asking the NTA to consider raising the level of awareness of the nomination process.  I strongly support the NTA in encouraging SPSV licenceholders to complete the nomination form and I advise all SPSV licenceholders to take the time to complete this form as soon as possible.</p> <p>We have a really difficult situation here, which obviously is not unique.  However, we also have a situation whereby it would be extraordinarily difficult to retrospectively anticipate the wishes of anyone in this predicament.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#C00300"><p>I thank the Minister for his response and I thank you, a Leas-Chathaoirligh, for indulging me in permitting me to mention the two particular cases, with one of which I am especially familiar.  I did so merely to illustrate the point and the human cost of this overly bureaucratic system and its impact on people on a regular basis.  I tend not to mention individual cases in this House and I understand the restrictions that ought to apply, but I took the view it was important to illustrate the point that I was trying to make, that is to say, that there was a human cost to this.</p> <p>I have looked at the form on the website.  It appears tenth on a list of obscure forms on the website.  It seems to me that the existence of this form is not widely understood in the taxi sector.  I have spoken to many smart people who work in the taxi sector in recent days to assess their level of knowledge.  The level of knowledge is extremely poor.  In cases like this families are put in difficult situations.  There appears to be no flexibility whatsoever and no humane and compassionate understanding of the circumstances in which people find themselves when someone dies suddenly.</p> <p>Every year, taxi drivers are required to renew the licence.  It would be worthwhile if the regulator would consider informing individuals on an annual basis of their obligation to sign these forms if they wish to reassign their licences for consideration to family members in the event of their passing.</p> <p>I appeal to the Minister to take a personal interest in this matter and to work with the regulator of taxis to try to have this resolved.  I am committed to doing that.  I believe we need a far more humane and compassionate system to try to work with women like Marie Keegan and Mrs. Lee, who lost her husband recently, to address these real and human problems.  I appeal to the Minister to commit to doing that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#C00400"><p>The fact the Senator has pointed out that this is not a unique case indicates there is certainly a problem.  This may be a problem with communication.  I have pointed out the ways the NTA is communicating the need or obligation on anyone in this situation to fill out the form and nominate someone.  If they do not, then the licence dies with them.</p> <p>It seems to be something I cannot retrospectively change but we can certainly make stringent efforts and ensure that State agencies and others insist that communication is better.  Perhaps the suggestion that taxi drivers or drivers of SPSVs should be informed and reminded of this every year is a good one.</p> <p>I do not know the details in the particular instance and we cannot anticipate such cases but it certainly seems that there is a recurring problem, if the Senator is right.  I urge the NTA to address it by communicating more frequently with those who hold these licences.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.25" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#D00100">Job Creation</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#D00200"><p>In recent years, I have had submitted to the Minister and her predecessor a number of parliamentary questions to try to understand foreign direct investment, FDI, and IDA-supported jobs in Donegal.  In July 1999, County Donegal had lost more than 1,000 jobs in the textile industry.  Companies such as Fruit of the Loom, which was a significant employer, was on the verge of leaving the county and it eventually left.  Magee was a textile manufacturer in south Donegal and Unifi was based in Letterkenny.  They all left in subsequent years but already in July 1999 we had lost 1,000 jobs.  The Government of the day set up a Donegal employment initiative task force and it presented its recommendations in July 1999.  It said that Donegal was way behind the rest of the State in job creation, especially foreign direct investment, and it targeted almost 5,000 additional jobs in foreign direct investment for the next seven years.</p> <p>I decided to track how we progressed in the past 17 years.  What I have discovered from the responses of the Minister and her officials is that today in Donegal the IDA supports fewer companies that it did in the year 2000.  It supported 14 companies then and it is 12 today.  When one looks at the growth in jobs in IDA-supported companies across the State, it was 140,000 in 2000 and today it is more than 210,000, which is 50% growth.  I commend the IDA on the excellent job it has done in bringing companies from around the world to the State.  I say good luck to all the locations that got such companies.  In County Donegal, even though we set a target of 5,000 additional jobs in the following seven years, the growth has been less than half of the State-wide level of 50% at 24% growth.  We would be in serious trouble were it not for companies such as Pramerica and Optum, which employ more than two thirds of all the IDA-supported jobs in Donegal.  It is a fantastic story of Donegal leadership.  There has been a failure to deliver foreign direct investment to Donegal but there is good news in that we have Pramerica and Optum, as well as other companies.  In particular, I refer to Pramerica, which employs more than 1,500 companies and which demonstrates we can get jobs in Donegal, keep them there and grow them.</p> <p>The Letterkenny Institute of Technology provides fantastic leadership.  The adjoining CoLab develops and incubates small businesses.  There is also a science and technology park.  In addition, there is the leadership of Donegal County Council, as well as Derry City and Strabane District Council.  They are breaking down the Border and talking about the north-west city region.  While I need to focus today on the historic failure and the negatives, I want to bring to the Minister's attention the significant positives.  The Minister must work with her Government colleagues to fast-track the commitments in Project 2040 in terms of roads investment, broadband, airports, bridges and harbours.  I ask that the Minister would work with her Government colleagues to fast-track the commitments made concerning Donegal.  Donegal was playing catch-up in 1999.  We put in place recommendations but fell further behind.  I urge the Minister to work with me and other public representatives in Donegal to bring more foreign direct investment to the county and to make sure that the commitments in Project 2040 are delivered.</p> <p>As a Minister from a Border county, Deputy Humphreys knows how hard it has been.  She knows the struggle that we have had and the threat of Brexit.  We need a strong statement from the Minister today about how we are going to bring new businesses to the area.  I ask her not to quote the jobs growth in Pramerica.  We know all about that.  She should please tell me about her plan to bring new companies to Donegal, on the back of Pramerica and Optum, to turn around the historic failure we have seen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1249" speakername="Heather Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#D00300"><p>I thank Senator Mac Lochlainn for raising this matter.  As a representative from the constituency of Cavan-Monaghan, job creation in the Border region is particularly close to my heart.  In that regard, I will begin by stressing that the Government is determined to support the growth of high-quality and sustainable employment across Ireland, including in County Donegal.  Regional development is - and will remain - a national priority and sustained efforts are being made to foster job creation and investment all over the country.</p> <p>As Senator Mac Lochlainn said, the Donegal employment initiative task force was set up in 1999 as a long-term plan to target sustainable job growth for the region.  The task force set out extremely ambitious targets for job creation for Donegal in terms of foreign direct investment and internationally traded services.  While not all of the task force's targets have been met, the overall employment trends in the county are positive.  When looking at employment growth in Donegal over the past ten years - or elsewhere across Ireland for that matter - it is also important to take account of the impact of the financial and fiscal crisis that began in 2008.  We must be mindful of that.  It had the effect of effectively reversing job creation and investment for a number of years, stalling the country's wider economic progress.  Significant steps forward have been taken, however, since the country emerged from recession.  If one compares, for example, foreign direct investment-related employment in Donegal at the beginning of our economic recovery in 2012 with our most recent FDI employment data at the end of 2017, one will find the county has experienced a 52% increase in FDI employment in that five-year period.  Job numbers in IDA Ireland client companies there have grown from 2,223 in 2012 to 3,389 at the end of last year.  That growth rate compares very favourably with the national average increase of 31% in FDI employment within this same period.</p> <p>Last year alone, the number of IDA-supported jobs in Donegal increased by 11%, with the region now home to 12 IDA companies, which currently include SITA, Optibelt and Pramerica.  The agency continues to work hard to create further employment opportunities in the county and to increase the number of multinational companies located there.  Last October, my predecessor attended the opening of Pramerica's new state-of-the-art campus in Letterkenny, where more than 220 local tradesmen were employed during its construction.  Pramerica's presence in the county began in 2000 with just eight employees and the firm has grown to become a highly successful company with more than 1,500 employed in County Donegal.  I believe that exemplifies the potential that exists in the county and the efforts the Government and the IDA have made, and still are making, to bring more investment there.  We want that to continue, which is why the IDA is working closely with both existing and new clients to encourage further projects and more job creation for the county.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#D00400"><p>As I anticipated, we now need to get to the core of the issue.  That is the reason I had those questions tabled and why I am probing the issue.  Pramerica is a fantastic story in Donegal.  It employs more than 1,500 jobs and has local Donegal leadership.  I was at the launch of the fantastic new building, known as the Rock.  It is a great story but it is not enough.  Why are we not building on the story of Pramerica?  The Minister talked about a 52% increase over a number of years but it was from a low base.  The unemployment levels in Donegal in the 2016 census and historically have been around twice the national average.  A significant factor in the reduction in unemployment levels between 2011 and 2016 is emigration.  People in Donegal know that.  We have lost young people to the United States, Australia and Canada and many of them are not coming home.</p> <p>I want to hold up the positive examples of Pramerica, Letterkenny Institute of Technology, Donegal County Council, Derry and Strabane council, and their visionary leadership, but the Government is not meeting them half way.  It is not bringing new jobs.  The low number of IDA site visits in the past ten to 15 years is despicable.  The Government is basically riding on the back of Pramerica's success and it is not delivering new investment to the county.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator P&aacute;draig Mac Lochlainn:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2321"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2321&amp;amp;pid=PadraigMacLochlainn&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The Government is not acknowledging the scale of the disadvantages we have faced historically and is not delivering the new investment and jobs that are required.  It is clearly not telling the story of Donegal or of Letterkenny Institute of Technology, LYIT, and the visionary leadership in the region.  If Pramerica Systems Ireland Limited and Optum were taken from the figures for new and additional jobs, Donegal would be a disaster zone.  The Minister cannot continue to point to Pramerica to make the Government look good.  She must start to build on Pramerica's delivery.  Local Donegal leadership and good friends in America delivered in Pramerica.  What the IDA must do now is bring in new companies and new investment and accept that, historically, there has been huge Government failure.</p><p>The Minister started by talking about the Donegal employment initiative task force back in 1999.  She must accept there has been utter failure in achieving those targets.  The target was almost 5,000 for the next seven years for Donegal, but it has had less than half the growth of the rest of the State.  Not only did it not catch up, it fell further behind.  That is an indisputable fact.  I ask the Minister to accept that and to promise to stop quoting Pramerica to the people in Donegal.  We know about that.  She should tell us when she will bring new jobs and new investment on foot of the brilliant leadership in Pramerica, LYIT and Donegal County Council.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1249" speakername="Heather Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#E00200"><p>I do not accept what the Senator says regarding the lack of effort on creating jobs in Donegal.  That is untrue.  The figures the Senator quotes go back to 1999.  He forgets to mention that in the middle of all that time we had a huge economic recession.  He knows that as well as I do.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#E00300"><p>Jobs grew every year during it.  The recession has nothing to do with it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1249" speakername="Heather Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#E00400"><p>The Senator fails to acknowledge that.  Most new IDA supported jobs are created from existing companies.  There are three very good FDI companies in Donegal and the IDA continues to work closely with them.  I have just returned from the United States and I have to make the point that the work the IDA does abroad is second to none.  American politicians said to me, "How did you do it?  You have one of the best agencies in the world in terms of attracting foreign direct investment".  I assure the Senator that the IDA is doing everything it can to encourage foreign companies to locate in Donegal, Cavan, Monaghan, Louth, Sligo and Leitrim.  I accept that those Border counties need increased attention and investment, and that is a priority for me.</p> <p>The IDA's clients based in the county have performed well.  The IDA retains a healthy presence in the north-west region despite the challenging economical operating environment over the last number of years.  The latest CSO figures show a significant drop of over 8% in the unemployment rate in Donegal since 2011.  This recovery is not driven by FDI companies alone.  Enterprise Ireland, EI, has also grown its jobs numbers in the county with 3,552 people now employed in EI client companies in Donegal, an increase from 3,420 last year.  Both Enterprise Ireland and the IDA maintain constant engagement with their clients in Donegal to encourage them to grow both jobs and investment in the county even further.  The agencies also work closely together, where possible, to help spur employment creation.  The local enterprise offices, as well as InterTradeIreland, are also working hard to ensure sustainable job growth for County Donegal and the wider north-west region.</p> <p>I acknowledge that more work remains to be done both in Donegal and across the north, west and Border region in terms of creating opportunities for the people of those areas.  As the Senator knows, I am from the Border area and following my appointment as Minister with responsibility for business I said from the outset that I wanted to shine a light on the region for job creation because traditionally it has been one of the areas that has lagged behind.  I recently met the chief executive officers, CEOs, of the local authorities in Cavan, Monaghan, Louth and Meath and I will also meet the CEOs from Donegal, Sligo and Leitrim.  Those meetings involve senior officials from my Department, as well as the IDA and Enterprise Ireland.  I am committed to ensuring that we do more for the Border region and I hope to see more investment in the region in the years ahead.  In fairness, Donegal County Council and Letterkenny Institute of Technology have done great work.  The Government has supported them and will continue to support them.</p> <p>Another issue is the N2-A5.  The Minister of State, Deputy McHugh, and I are absolutely committed to that road going all the way from Dublin to Letterkenny.  That would be a wonderful addition in terms of opening the north west and reducing the time it takes to get from the airport in Dublin to Donegal.  Both of us are committed to that and it is included in the national development plan and the national planning framework for 2040.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.33" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#E00500">Mental Health Services Provision</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1415" speakername="Maura Hopkins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#E00600"><p>I thank the Minister of State at the Department of Health, Deputy Catherine Byrne, for coming to the Seanad this morning.  The important issue I wish to raise is the inpatient mental health unit in Roscommon town.  As the Minister of State will be aware, a recent inspection by the Mental Health Commission has found that the unit is non-compliant with 14 regulations, one rule and four codes of practice.  She will also be aware that an external report on mental health services was published last September.  It is difficult for me, as a public representative, for people in our community and for people who need to use our mental health services and their families to have confidence in the acute inpatient mental health unit as well as the other services in the county when there is non-compliance in a number of key areas.</p> <p>These inspections take place every year.  I should emphasise that our results have been getting worse, not better, through 2015, 2016 and 2017.  We are not making improvements.  In 2015, there were 18 non-compliant areas, in 2016 there were 13 and in 2017 there were 19.  That is very serious.  I will highlight the difficulties that were found in the report.  They are basic issues - I worked as an occupational therapist in mental health services - such as poor hand hygiene, no soap in dispensers, dairy products not stored at an appropriate temperature, inadequate staffing, no up-to-date training and broken handles on windows and lockers.  One section of the report indicates huge issues with recreational space.  It was described as a cage-like area.  I acknowledge that work commenced last November on developing a garden at the inpatient mental health unit, which is something of an improvement.</p> <p>However, I am not happy.  We had a meeting last night with the Minister of State at the Department of Health, Deputy Jim Daly, about another unit, the Rosalie unit in Castlerea.  There was no HSE management at that meeting.  Who exactly is running our mental health services at present?  I am not satisfied with the level of care being given to people who are going through very difficult times.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Maura Hopkins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2478"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2478&amp;amp;pid=MauraHopkins&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I want to know exactly what measures are being put in place to ensure we do not see results like this again.  I ask the Minister of State for a response that deals with the practical solutions that will be put in place immediately.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1307" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#F00200"><p>I thank Senator Hopkins.  I will read the response I have been given.  I may not be able to address some of the details.  On behalf of the Minister of State, Deputy Jim Daly, who could not be here, I thank the Senator for raising this Commencement matter.</p> <p>Mental health remains a priority of the programme for Government.  Since 2012, around &euro;200 million, or 28%, has been added to the HSE mental health budget which now totals over &euro;910 million.  This is a significant investment by any standard and the Programme for a Partnership Government gives a clear commitment to increase our mental health budget annually as resources allow to expand and modernise all aspects of our services, including those in Roscommon.  One of the strategic priorities for mental health in the HSE national service plan 2018 is to deliver timely, clinically effective and standardised safe mental health services in adherence to statutory requirements.  Specific provision is made to improve compliance through monitoring services in collaboration with the Mental Health Commission.  The HSE&rsquo;s national service plan 2018 also highlights the implementation of the HSE best practice guidance for mental health services, including developing and delivery of training and reporting for quality surveillance.</p> <p>The Mental Health Commission is charged with visiting and inspecting every approved mental health centre at least once a year.  On 15 March 2017, the commission published its report on the department of psychiatry in Roscommon University Hospital.  This followed an inspection of the approved centre which took place from 5 September to 8 September 2017.  While the facility received satisfactory rankings for elements of its performance, there were concerns raised by the commission on the detailed aspects of service delivery.  The inspection team found, for example, that the unit failed in some respects on appropriate recreational activities, visitor areas, therapeutic services and programmes, privacy and premises, risk management procedures and admission and transfer and discharge records.  Details of the full report are available on the Mental Health Commission website.</p> <p>The HSE community health care organisation 2 has welcomed the commission&rsquo;s report on the Roscommon acute psychiatric unit.  A corrective and preventative action plan was drafted by the HSE following the receipt of the inspection report to ensure all issues identified in the report are addressed.  The Minister of State, Deputy Jim Daly, is satisfied that the HSE is committed to improving this particular service overall and is in the process of addressing the specific issues highlighted.  One of the main concerns related to a lack of proper garden facilities for the residents and the HSE has already commenced construction of a new garden at the hospital.  The Senator may rest assured that the Department of Health and the HSE will continue to closely monitor the issues raised in the Mental Health Commission report to ensure the necessary corrective actions are progressed as quickly as possible.  The Senator will also be aware that the report of the Roscommon mental health services was published last September.  Good progress is being made by the HSE in implementing the 27 recommendations of this report to help modernise mental health services overall in Roscommon.  This will by its nature help raise standards and practice for mental health overall in Roscommon, including inpatient and community-based services.</p> <p>I will respond to any supplementary questions the Senator raises.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1415" speakername="Maura Hopkins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#F00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State for her response.  She will understand how frustrated I am.  I do not rest assured.  We had a meeting last night with the Minister of State, Deputy Daly.  There was no HSE management at the meeting on the Rosalie unit in Castlerea.  I have absolutely no faith in HSE management of mental health services in County Roscommon.</p> <p>The Minister of State mentioned action plans.  We know the 27 recommendations of the report.  I was at a meeting last Friday with the chief health officer, Tony Canavan, about the report.  We were told an action plan has been developed.  I would like to see a little bit of action from that action plan.  I acknowledge there has been work on the garden.  What about basic hand hygiene?  What about broken handles on lockers and windows?  What about food safety?  What about mandatory training?  What about staffing?  They are all very serious issues.  The response I got last Friday on mental health services in County Roscommon overall is not at all positive.  We have absolutely no clear pathway to improve services in the county.  The only words that were used at that meeting last Friday were about closures of day centres and hostels and the serious concerns that have been raised here.  A strong focus from the Minister and Ministers of State in the Department of Health would ensure we improve things because we need to.  Our people in Roscommon deserve better than this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1307" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#F00400"><p>I can see clearly the Senator is very upset and frustrated by what has happened.  The simple issues the Senator raised around hand hygiene, food hygiene and locks on windows are very common-sense things.  Those of us who have an association with health services believe there should be management and leadership at grassroots level.  Some of the small issues the Senator raised have not been corrected.  That is down to the leadership and management at HSE level and at the level of the management of the service.  We owe the best of care to people who go into a service like this.  If the management in place is not sufficient to deal with the mundane, every-day clinical and hygiene issues in a centre like this we are in really deep trouble.  I agree with the Senator on that.</p> <p>I do not have details of a further clear pathway to give to the Senator but I will outline her frustration, which she has spoken about clearly, to the Minister of State, Deputy Jim Daly.  I will ask him to meet or respond to the Senator in detail on the pathways to address the issue.  I am very sorry I do not have specific answers and I understand the Senator's frustration.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#F00500"><p>I am sure the Senator appreciates what the Minister of State will do for her.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.40" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 11.27 a.m. and resumed at  11.37 a.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.41" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#G00100">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#G00200"><p>Today's Order of Business is No. 59, motion 14, cross-party motion re Syria, to be taken on conclusion of the Order of Business, without debate; No. 1, motion re Planning and Development Acts 2000 to 2017 (Increase in Number of Ordinary Members of An Bord Plean&aacute;la) Order 2018, back from committee, to be taken on the conclusion of No. 59, motion 14, without debate; No. 2, statements on councillors' conditions, to be taken at 12.45 p.m. and to adjourn no later than 2.15 p.m. if not previously concluded, with the contributions of each group spokesperson not to exceed eight minutes and of all other Senators not to exceed six minutes; and No. 3, motion re appointment of seven commissioners to the Irish Human Rights and Equality Commission, to be taken at 2.15 p.m. and to conclude no later than 3 p.m., with the contributions of each Senator not to exceed five minutes and the Minister to be given no less than five minutes to reply to the debate.</p> <p>I welcome the former Deputy, Mr. Anthony Lawlor, who is in the Gallery.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#G00500"><p>The former Deputy is welcome.  I understand that there are also some people from the good country of Ballinhassig present, including Senator Lombard's aunt.  They are welcome to today's proceedings.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1380" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#G00600"><p>She is a young-looking aunt.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.45" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#G00800"><p>It is not very often we see Senator Lombard blushing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#G00900"><p>He told me on the way in that she was his favourite aunt, but she did not tell me that he was her favourite nephew.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#G01000"><p>There is a slight air of end-of-term giddiness about the place, which is probably not a bad thing in some ways after the week we have had.  I welcome the former Deputy, Mr. Lawlor, who may be a future Senator.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Gerry Horkan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2476"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2476&amp;amp;pid=GerryHorkan&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I am sure we all wish him well in his endeavours in the next few weeks along with some of our candidates running for various positions.</p><p>An hour and a half is probably not sufficient to discuss councillors' terms and conditions today.  I would expect that 43 of us are in here primarily as a result of votes from councillors and indeed Members of the Oireachtas and I am sure most of us will want to say something on it.  As a former trustee of the Association of Irish Local Government and a councillor for 12 and a half years, I certainly want to contribute to the debate on councillors' terms and conditions either today or at some other stage but we have an hour and a half today so I am not going to delay that further.</p><p>This day next year will be Brexit day.  It is coming faster than anyone would have expected.  We are far closer to the day the UK is leaving than the day on which it voted to leave.  An awful lot is still uncertain and up in the air, if Members excuse the pun, affecting areas, such as aviation, which are hugely important.</p><p>It is a huge issue for anybody living anywhere near the Border in terms of movement.  It is a major issue for people in the freight industry, those importing or exporting and agriculture.  Our lives will be hugely affected by Brexit and how it pans out.  It is very important that we reflect on the fact it will happen this day next year.  I acknowledge that there may be a transition agreement.  Hopefully, this will be the case and whatever deal we get will be the softest Brexit we can get but it is still a very important point and we need to keep our focus on it and maybe have another debate in here with the relevant Ministers.  I accept that nearly every Minister is affected by it but particularly the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade.</p><p>We will not be back by 10 April in time to commemorate the day the Good Friday Agreement, which is 20 years old, was reached.  I remember campaigning and voting in the referendum.  It was a great piece of work on the part of my former leader and former Taoiseach, Bertie Ahern, along with Tony Blair and many others in the unionist and nationalist communities.  It has served this island and these islands well and we should reflect on it and the fact we have had 20 years of relatively peaceful times.  It is important we acknowledge it and I am sure others will make contributions.  Perhaps when we come back after the break, we should have statements on it and how it has served us well and certainly put to bed the notion from some people that it should be scrapped, which has been mentioned - certainly in the British Parliament.  </p><p>Fianna F&aacute;il published a document yesterday on teacher shortages and how to alleviate them in the short term and medium term, including reflecting on pay inequality in the system.  Equally, it is very difficult to get people to provide cover if somebody is sick, on maternity leave or on a career break.  It particularly affects Irish, the sciences, continental languages, home economics, technical drawing and technical graphics.  It is very difficult to get people to provide cover.  The Department and the Minister really need to reflect on how we are going to deal with it and the fact that the salary is a national salary with which we are very familiar but that it goes a lot of further in some parts of the country than it does in others.  If people getting jobs in south Dublin spot a job somewhere else, they are gone because their disposable income will be far greater.</p><p>The homelessness figure is higher than ever.  I think an additional 222 families last month were reported as homeless and, overall, nearly 10,000 people in the State were homeless in February.  I am sure the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government can bring us lots of statistics about what is actually happening but the figure is getting worse all the time despite what is being done and there needs to be a greater emphasis on it.</p><p>On Good Friday, for the first time in 91 years, someone will be able to go into a pub, restaurant or, indeed, a supermarket or off-licence and legally buy a drink.  It was this House that launched that and we should reflect on it.  Hopefully, people will drink sensibly and enjoy themselves despite what Senator Norris might think.  To be honest, the off-licences will be disappointed that they have less time off.  I wish everybody a happy Easter.  I hope they enjoy the break.  I will see all of them after the break.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#H00200"><p>I wish to comment on what Senator Horkan said about an hour and a half not being long enough to consider councillors' conditions.  If it is any consolation to him, I will not be contributing to that debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#H00300"><p>The Senator had 26 minutes on Committee Stage yesterday so I think he did okay.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#H00400"><p>If the Senator was nominated by councillors, he would be contributing.  You can bet your boots on that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#H00500"><p>The second issue I was going to mention was touched on by Senator Horkan, namely, the rising tide of people who have no home.  Coming into Leinster House, it was interesting to hear the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government dealing with this issue as best he could in an interview on RT&Eacute; radio.  However, the fundamental problem as I see it is that we are not engaged in joined-up thinking on housing, homelessness and the kind of infrastructure we need in Ireland.  There are a lot of people in different silos pursuing different projects.  It was mentioned by the interviewer on RT&Eacute;, Sean O'Rourke, that student accommodation is now being built at breakneck speed across Dublin.  I am acquainted with one project on Church Street opposite where I have an office.  It went from nothing to something in the space of a year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#H00600"><p>The same with Gardiner Street.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#H00700"><p>It is extraordinary to see the speed with which these kinds of buildings can be built because there are tax incentives and there is a green light for them.  One then asks oneself why it takes so long to build accommodation for other classes of the community.  I fully accept the point that if a student is accommodated, some other property is not required elsewhere and, therefore, it has a horizontal effect.  We must have a joined-up approach to the kind of cities in which we are planning to live in ten or 20 years' time.  Are there to be apartments, is everybody to be a renter from now on or have we abandoned the idea of home ownership?  Are we, as a society, creating a new situation in which vulture funds and REITs will be the economic masters of where people live and where and if accommodation is built for them?</p> <p>Many years ago when I was in the Progressive Democrats, we had an ambitious project to move Dublin Port to Bremore and use the land there for a major high-rise city.  Some people described it as a Manhattan in Dublin Port but we must have more imaginative thinking about what kind of city we are building.  We are now spending or are planning to spend &euro;4 billion on a metro system to connect Dublin Airport with Sandyford.  We are pretending we are consulting the public about it but a vast amount of money has already been spent on this project.  The alternatives to that expenditure have not been publicly considered.  Should Rathfarnham, Tallaght, Stillorgan, UCD and St. Vincent's hospital be considered?  There are all sorts of places on the south side of the city that could be connected but we have this one project to cannibalise the green Luas line, which we recently extended at a cost of &euro;368 million to connect it with Cabra.  If someone wants to travel from Bride's Glen to Cabra, he or she must get on a tram at Bride's Glen, get off at Sandyford, get on a tram at Sandyford to bring him or her to Ranelagh and get off the tram there and get on another tram, which will bring him or her through the city.  The person will get some exercise going from A to B - there is no doubt about that - but I am really doubtful that anybody is actually planning the city of Dublin.  That is the point I am making.  Nobody is planning what Dublin should look like.  A group of railway engineers is making decisions for billions of euro when we are not planning the housing layout or anything to do with our city.  Nobody is taking responsibility for it.</p> <p>The time has come, and I hope I am not being parochial in talking about Dublin because I am sure the same applies to other cities in the country, where we must have an urban plan.  Somebody has to work out whether we really need this metro system, whether it should take certain routes and whether we need housing down on the docks or in Kildare.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Michael McDowell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=719"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=719&amp;amp;pid=MichaelMcDowellPD&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->What kind of city are we building?  I am sorry to say that we have got to the point where vast amounts of money are being earmarked for expenditure but nobody is taking any democratic responsibility and nobody is democratically accountable for the decisions that are being made.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#J00200"><p>I call Senator Mac Lochlainn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#J00300"><p>It is Senator Conway-Walsh.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#J00400"><p>Will I do?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#J00500"><p>Is there a coup?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#J00600"><p>No, she is my leader.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#J00700"><p>We only have women leaders in Sinn F&eacute;in.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#J00800"><p>They are all anointed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#J00900"><p>Are we?  I wonder what that feels like.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#J01000"><p>Senator Mac Lochlainn was in pole position so I was confused temporarily.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#J01100"><p>I will refer briefly to three things this morning.  The first is to welcome the announcement by the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Flanagan, that the Government has agreed to advise our President, Michael D. Higgins, to exercise his constitutional right to grant a pardon to Maolra Seoighe from the M&aacute;m Trasna murders.  That is a very positive, significant move.  I look forward to the programme that is going out on TG4 on Wednesday, 4 April.  It will unveil some of the things that happened around that time.  It speaks to several different things and the importance of our language, the Irish language, and what happened there.  I welcome that move by the Minister for Justice and Equality.</p> <p>It is with a heavy heart that I go on the Easter break.  I listened to Sister Stanislaus Kennedy talking this morning about the increase in the homelessness figure.  Sometimes we have a lot of banter in here and the other House about political perceptions and all that but what really brought it home to me was her saying that there is an abject Government failure in dealing with the housing crisis.  I know that she would not say that lightly.  She is a woman of great integrity and experience and she said it happened either through inability or failure, in that the Government did not care in terms of the provision of housing and preventing the things that continue to make people, families and children homeless.  I hope, now that the Government spin unit is being got rid of, that these things, such as homelessness, can be really faced up to and the reality of homelessness can be dealt with.  Listening to the announcement of the recent figure and to what Sister Stanislaus Kennedy had to say, it would be easy to feel a sense of hopelessness about this.  We all need to work together.  I know my party has put forward proposition after proposition on tackling homelessness and the Government needs to take heed of them and do something urgently about it.</p> <p>In light of the recent Belfast rape trial, while I am not specifically talking about that case, we need to learn from two aspects of it.  There is an absolute need for an all-island approach to dealing with sexual violence and gender-based violence and over the coming months, I would like to work on that so that we can take the best bits from both areas to have solid legislation that will make this a safer place for women.  I also urge those within the media and responsible reporters to come together with the National Union of Journalists, NUJ, to have a protocol for the reporting of gender-based violence and to work with the front-line services on that protocol so that we never again have to witness some of the headlines that have appeared in recent weeks.  I ask them to think if it was their daughters or sisters, they would report the same headlines as they have reported over the last period.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#J01200"><p>I have to laugh at the idea that an hour and a half is not long enough to discuss councillors' well-being and such.  I know this is all about Members of the Seanad who are elected by councils lickspittling their electorate-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#J01300"><p>What about Trinity?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#J01400"><p>What about Senator Norris?  It is just like he talks about his electorate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#J01500"><p>I would like to say that they do not have much courage when it comes to looking at our own terms and conditions.  Very few voices are raised in here.  When I raised this the other day, I was mocked for my pains by Miriam Lord.  I am going to continue to do it.  There are 111 civil servants in Leinster House who get more than we get.  The long-service increment was abolished.  I do not know of another job that does not have a long service increment.  I get the same after 32 years and about ten elections fought and won as somebody who was nominated the other day.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#J01600"><p>It is the same as councillors.  Councillors do not get any long-service increment either.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#J01700"><p>Senator Horkan is dealing with that but why does he not speak out about our issues?  Why do Senators not have some guts and talk about it?  One will not get many energetic, brilliant young minds into politics if one continues to pay them dirt.</p> <p>The 10,000 homeless figure is appalling.  I listened to Sister Stanislaus Kennedy who said there was a failure.  There was an amendment introduced in the D&aacute;il at the behest of her organisation which would protect people in a situation, for example, where somebody was a tenant in an apartment and the apartment was sold over that person's heads, following which that person could be immediately evicted.  That is appalling.  We heard all this stuff about 1916, the great leaders and so on but how is it tolerable in an Irish Republic in the 21st century for people to be evicted?  When it was 5,000 not so long ago, I warned that it would soon be 10,000, then 15,000, then 20,000.  The Government was incapable of dealing with 5,000 homeless.  How on earth will it deal with 10,000?  There is a Bill in my name on the Order Paper of this House which would deal with this situation and get rid of the vulture funds.  I hope in the first weeks of the new term, when we get back after Easter, that we can address this issue.</p> <p>Finally, I understand that the Committee on Procedure and Privileges will discuss some time in the future my suggestion that we remove Standing Order 41, which prohibits Members from putting down amendments which create a charge on the Exchequer.  This was Mr. de Valera really trying to keep the Seanad as weak as possible.  We should stand up to it and fight for ourselves.  This only allows discussion.  Surely Seanad &Eacute;ireann is about discussion.  We are always talking about reform of the Seanad and not a damn thing has happened.  This is one way in which we ourselves are responsible and can take action to ensure that the proper debate on economic subjects is allowed.  The Government can reverse it in this House or the other House, but we should allow for discussion.  If this is not changed, every time a Member stands up in this House and complains - Members from all sides and from all parties and none complain about this measure - having done nothing about it, I will publicly shame him or her.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#J01800"><p>On this day, one year from Brexit, it is worth recalling in this House that one of the great successes of the EU has been the Common Agricultural Policy, CAP.  The Common Agricultural Policy has ensured an adequate supply of food at all times at a reasonable, affordable price for consumers, and a high standard of food.  That is a misunderstood aspect of the Common Agricultural Policy at times.  It makes sure that people can get food, that there is enough food and that it can be reasonably priced.  It has to be subsidised to achieve that.  It is of extraordinary importance to farmers in this country.  The Teagasc report said that it ranges from 38% of income on dairy farms to an extraordinary 115% on cattle rearing farms.  It is of huge importance to the farmers.  It is of particular importance this year because of the very difficult winter, fodder price, margins being reduced and psychological and financial stress that that is creating for farmers.  That brings the importance of the CAP into focus.  To give a practical example, in County Cavan, current figures show that the CAP brings in &euro;54 million while it brings in &euro;41 million into County Monaghan.  It is obviously crucial to the local economy.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Joe O'Reilly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1610"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1610&amp;amp;pid=JoeOReilly&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It could be said that rural Ireland effectively depends on the Common Agricultural Policy and that were it to suffer, one could close down rural Ireland, including small towns, villages and the entire human infrastructure.  My point is that in the context of Brexit, which is going to happen in some form, it is crucial that we preserve the Common Agricultural Policy and its budget here.  There must be no diminution of that budget.  If anything, it needs to increase to take account of the very low margins in the current environment.  I will not go through the list of schemes that can arise from this.  That is another day's debate.  However, I am asking the Leader to make sure that Commissioner Hogan appears before the House, as he is planning to do, to discuss the maintenance of the Common Agricultural Policy.  I also ask that the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine, Deputy Creed, comes into the House to discuss how he proposes to pursue this fight within a European context.  This is a question of national interest that is surpassed by none other. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#K00200"><p>I request the Leader of the House to keep No. 2, "Statements on Councillors&rsquo; Conditions", open-ended, in order that we can come back to it at a further time.  There are several Members here who would like to contribute to that.  Senator Norris ably represents Trinity College, and his graduates and electorate, and Michael McDowell, who is a senior counsel, represents the graduates of the National University of Ireland ably and well.  As such, I offer no apology.  Our electorate are councillors, Deputies and Senators and we are entitled to represent their views.  To give an example, in County Roscommon, the number of councillors was reduced from 26 to 18 but there was no increase in the remuneration of councillors.  The amount of work has increased and they are more in demand than any Member of this House - or most Members of this House - except those running for election to D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann.  They have a very good case.  Their salary is pegged at approximately 25% of a Senator's salary.  Were it increased to 33% without having this regular debate, at least one would have a reasonable amount of money to survive.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#K00300"><p>How about rectifying some of our own reductions?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#K00400"><p>Senator Norris has a good point but there is very little sympathy in the general electorate in respect of our position.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#K00500"><p>Ignore them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#K00600"><p>I am one of Senator Leyden's electors.  I will be voting in the next election.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#K00700"><p>So am I.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#K00800"><p>After my attack on the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Ross, over rugby, he instructed me not to darken his door again for a vote.  I am very sorry to say that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#K00900"><p>One cannot trust that man if he promises a vote.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#K01000"><p>The Minister, Deputy Ross, reprimanded me for making a statement here about the unfortunate disaster of the Rugby World Cup.  It would be in Ireland if the Government was more active.  He is very sensitive about it.  He told me not to darken his door and that his vote was gone.  I am very sorry, because I really needed that vote and he was very good to me in the past.  I have to admit that.  He was very generous.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#K01100"><p>We will be having a debate on that later.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#K01200"><p>Councillors are the front-line troops.  Senators are the generals.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#K01300"><p>They are the front line of Senator Leyden's election campaign.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#K01400"><p>They are going over the top.  They are working hard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#K01500"><p>Guns blazing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#K01600"><p>They are in front of the people.  The Senators are the generals behind the scenes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#K01700"><p>I would much prefer to be a general.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#K01800"><p>Most council meetings are now broadcast live on the Internet.  As such, there is a very high standard among councillors, and it is very competitive.  Just like Senators, councillors always communicating via emails or mobile telephone.  Life has changed.  In order to be fair and not to have this as a permanent issue, let us do something sensible.  Let us not be afraid of the electoral situation.  All the political parties are afraid to say too much about councillors' pay because there could be a backlash.  As far as I am concerned, let there be a backlash, and let there be fairness.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#K01900"><p>I was sitting in my office, minding my own business, preparing for the debate on councillors when Senator Norris got to his feet.  He is one of my electorate.  I am not afraid to talk about our terms and conditions of employment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#K02000"><p>Good man.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#K02100"><p>I published a rapporteur's report in February 2016 on the class K arrangements for pay related social insurance, PRSI.  Along with five councillors, I also took a court case against the State for introducing class K PRSI, which is a tax on public service.  I pay 4% of my salary to the PRSI fund and I get nothing for it.  If I fall sick when I leave here, I get no entitlements.  When I came into this House, I was forced to pack in my teaching job and take a career break.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#K02200"><p>Senator Craughwell was not forced.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#K02300"><p>I was forced.  I took a pay cut of &euro;8,000 a year to take my seat in the Seanad.  I took it.  We need to look at our own terms and conditions of employment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#K02400"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#K02500"><p>We need to be brave.  I make no apology whatsoever to the public for the job I do.  Nobody in the public, apart from the extremely rich, pays class K PRSI contributions.  My court case was settled a couple of weeks ago and the councillors that took that case with me were looked after.  Ultimately, however, we did not succeed in having class K PRSI banned.  It is all very well for us sitting here.  Think of this.  A young Deputy who gets elected into the House, spends one term here and then leaves, having lost his or her seat, has no PRSI entitlements whatsoever.  Such Deputies have broken their PRSI record while giving this State service.  That is wrong.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#K02600"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#K02700"><p>I am not afraid to speak on our terms and conditions of employment and if the Leader is brave enough to call a debate on it, I will take it on head on.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#K02800"><p>We call for a debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#K02900"><p>I wish to note the kind response to my family members coming to the House.  I especially thank the Chair for acknowledging my aunt.</p> <p>I wish to raise the issue of the Wild Atlantic Way and its success.  That infrastructure, starting in Kinsale and continuing all along the west coast, has been a fantastic success.  As a consequence, the west coast and the southern region are alive with tourists.  An issue, however, has emerged over the last few weeks or months.  A review of the Wild Atlantic Way to consider the inclusion of other areas was proposed.  I refer to Union Hall in particular.  The Minister visited Union Hall last July and announced that a review would be carried out early in 2018.  He said there would be a comprehensive review with a new link in Union Hall proposed for this summer season.  That has not happened yet.  We need to examine the Wild Atlantic Way, pursue this review and ensure that these small beautiful villages all along the west and south coasts of Ireland can be included in this unbelievable story.  The Wild Atlantic Way has changed the outlook for tourism in the towns and villages along that driving route.  We need to work with that key infrastructure and expand it.  I welcome the review; I just need it to happen.  We must make sure that those towns and villages that are slightly off the Wild Atlantic Way are included.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#K03000"><p>The Leader has very kindly agreed to have a debate on councillors' pay and conditions as soon as the Order of Business has concluded at 12.45 p.m.  I think it is inappropriate to raise this again, if Senators would not mind.  It is pointless to bring the Minister here for an hour and a half.  We should discuss other issues.  The Leader has his job done and the Minister can answer any queries Senators may have.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#K03100"><p>I ask the Leader to raise my first issue with the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade.  Ms Danielle McLaughlin was a young women from my home town of Buncrana in County Donegal.  I know her family very well.  Just over a year ago, she was murdered in the most appalling circumstances in Goa, India.  Liaising with her mother, Andrea, and her family was a real education for me.  I learned something about just what happens to Irish citizens when they are in this situation overseas.  This case involved the most awful thing that can happen to a family.  Danielle, like many Irish people, was born outside of the island, but moved home at a very early age.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator P&aacute;draig Mac Lochlainn:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2321"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2321&amp;amp;pid=PadraigMacLochlainn&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->She was raised in Buncrana from where her family come and was an Irish citizen, holding both an Irish and a British passport.  She travelled on her British passport while in India.  While I do not propose to discuss the case in great detail, I was extremely disappointed with the initial response of our consular services to Danielle's death.  I have dealt with our consular services overseas many times and they are usually brilliant.  In this case, I believe they were leaning on the fact that Danielle held a British passport.  I made clear to them that many Irish people who are born overseas have several passports and pointed out that I knew Danielle's family.  Eventually, the position improved a little.  The family had to rely on the Kevin Bell Repatriation Trust, a fantastic organisation established by the Bell family after they endured a similar experience with a loved one.  The trust assured the McLaughlin family and did more in India to bring Danielle home than our consulate did.  While the consulate eventually assisted with bits and bobs, the Kevin Bell Repatriation Trust did fantastic work, as it has done in many other cases.  I apologise for running a little over time but I ask the Cathaoirleach to give me one more minute to discuss this sensitive issue.</p><p>Our consular services failed initially to help with repatriation costs.  Unfortunately, many people have died in controversial circumstances in Goa.  There are problems with the legal system in the region, meaning cases tend to drag on and can fall down the list.  For this reason, families of victims must have legal representatives in India to ensure justice is served.  The McLaughlin family have not received any financial assistance from the Government.  I ask the Leader to raise this matter with the Minister and request that some level of financial assistance be provided in cases such as the Danielle McLaughlin case.  Families should not have to rely on fund-raising to secure justice, as the McLaughlin family must do for their daughter. </p><p>Unfortunately, Sinn F&eacute;in cannot support the taking of the motion on Syria without debate.  We raised the issue of human rights abuses on all sides, including widespread human rights abuses associated with the Turkish invasion and siege of the city of Afrin.  We also asked that the motion be amended to secure all-party co-operation.  I ask for a debate on the motion because, sadly, Sinn F&eacute;in will oppose it if the House does not agree to a debate.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#L00200"><p>I had intended to thank the Leader for proposing to take the motion on Syria without debate.  I had not realised it would give rise to conflict but I will be pleased to withdraw it to try to reach an agreed version of the text.  I corresponded with all the group leaders on the motion and I was aware that Sinn F&eacute;in was not willing to sign up to it.  However, we secured support from the Fine Gael and Fianna F&aacute;il parties, Senator Higgins and, obviously, the Technical Group and Labour Party, which initiated the motion.  I am disappointed there is contention regarding the motion, which focuses specifically on the terrible atrocities in eastern Ghouta and civilian deaths in that region.  Our desire was to focus on that issue.  Colleagues can table motions on human rights abuses and violations in other areas and I would be pleased to support them.  I communicated with Senator Conway-Walsh that I could not accept the amendments she suggested to the original version of the motion.  However, I accepted amendments from other colleagues and I believed we had produced a fairly uncontentious motion calling for repeated, continuous and unhindered access to eastern Ghouta and other besieged areas in Syria for United Nations-led humanitarian relief operations.  As I stated, I am willing, with the assent of the Leader, to withdraw it from the Order Paper if there is some dispute over it.  I am disappointed nonetheless.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#L00300"><p>Senators would like a debate on the motion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#L00400"><p>We will have a debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#L00500"><p>Perhaps we could debate when the House returns after the break.  As I said, I understood there was strong support for the people of Syria in this House.  I am, therefore, disappointed by this.</p> <p>On the verdict announced yesterday in the trial in Belfast, I ask the Leader to arrange a debate when we return on the trial of sex offences in this jurisdiction.  We have had some significant changes to the law here and reforms in the Criminal Law (Sexual Offences) Act.  The Domestic Violence Bill, which is before the D&aacute;il this week, will also make some changes.  We could reflect further on how we can reform our processes to ensure the experience of reporting a rape or sexual assault and giving evidence in court is not like a secondary victimisation for any complainant.  I am conscious, as I have outlined elsewhere, that the procedures here are more humane for both the accused and complainants in terms of publicity and privacy in the courtroom and so on. </p> <p>I wish Senators a happy Easter.  On our return on 17 April, we will have a transition year debate with D&iacute;osp&oacute;ireacht na n&Oacute;g in the Seanad Chamber, as agreed by the Committee on Procedure and Privileges, as part of our V&oacute;t&aacute;il 100 programme to commemorate the centenary of women's suffrage.  I hope colleagues from all sides will be able to come along and watch 16 wonderful young people taking part in the debate in the Seanad Chamber. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#L00600"><p>As the motion on Syria is on the Order Paper, it is a matter for the Leader to amend the Order of Business if Senator Bacik is minded to withdraw the motion.  The Leader can deal with that matter in due course.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#L00700"><p>I raise the issue of Parkinson's disease.  A recently published report indicates that unfortunately, the incidence of the disease in this country is increasing.  It also highlights that Ireland lags behind international standards on the treatments and back-up supports available to people who suffer from this horrible disease.  I understand families of loved ones affected by the condition will protest outside the gates of the House this afternoon and I have no doubt Members of both Houses will take the opportunity to attend.  I understand only a small number of specialist nurses are available to families of people with Parkinson's disease, with none available in counties Monaghan, Cavan and Roscommon.  I ask the Leader to bring this matter to the attention of the Minister for Health to ensure it is addressed as a matter of urgency.</p> <p>P&aacute;raic Duffy will complete his term as ard-sti&uacute;rth&oacute;ir of the GAA in the next week or thereabouts.  Mr. Duffy has been in the role for the past ten years and has performed in a competent and efficient manner.  The people of County Monaghan are well aware of his ability from his former role as principal of St. Macartan's College for many years.  I am glad people nationally are now aware of the ability he brought to the position of ard-sti&uacute;rth&oacute;ir.  Mr. Duffy steered the GAA through a difficult decade caused by the recession and emigration and transformed the all-Ireland club football championship to give players more time to play club football, which is vital.  I acknowledge his contribution to the GAA and wish him and his family well in the next phase of his life.  I understood he has taken up a role as selector for his beloved Scotstown GAA club and I wish him well in that regard. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#L00800"><p>We all join Senator Gallagher in wishing Mr. Duffy well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#L00900"><p>Yesterday, our colleague, Senator Feighan, referred to a visit to London earlier this week of a delegation from the Joint Committee on European Union Affairs and the Seanad Special Select Committee on the Withdrawal of the United Kingdom from the European Union.  The group was comprised of Deputy Michael Healy-Rae, Senators Richmond, O'Reilly, Black, Mark Daly and myself.  I was honoured to be part of the delegation which met some very interesting people, notably the Minister for the Cabinet Office, Mr. David Lidington, who is an interesting man.  Ireland has some great friends in the Labour Party, including the Members of Parliament, Hilary Benn, Conor McGinn and Keir Starmer.  We also had informative meetings with the chairpersons of various committees.  We were scheduled to meet Mr. David Davis, the Secretary of State for Exiting the European Union but he was indisposed.  However, we met his under-secretary of state, a most interesting lady.  We invited all those we met to visit Ireland, specifically the Border region, and I believe they will all take up our invitation.  Some of those who have visited the Border already intend visiting again.</p> <p>It is helpful that the Labour Party in Britain has formally adopted a policy of maintaining a customs union.  This approach could assist the minority Government of Prime Minister Theresa May who is experiencing difficulties because she presides over a divided Cabinet and party.  We met people on all sides of the Conservative Party.  I do not believe the British wish to ignore the European market of 500 million people.  Negotiations towards alignment will proceed slowly but we must be patient.  I believe some form of customs partnership will ultimately be agreed, perhaps as late as October.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paul Coghlan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1881"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1881&amp;amp;pid=PaulCoghlan&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We do not know what it will be called but it will be as close as it can to alignment between the UK and the EU.  Mr. Jean-Claude Juncker intends to visit Ireland and I reiterate the call to the Leader to have him invited to address the House.  Commissioner Phil Hogan is coming and will address us in due course.  They are very informative people.  The visits we undertook are very important to maintain and improve relations and we did achieve that.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.115" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#M00200">Visit of Georgian Delegation</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#M00300"><p>Before I call on the next speaker, I am sure Members of the House will wish to join me in welcoming a parliamentary delegation from Georgia, led by Ms Sofio Katsarava, chair of the Foreign Relations Committee and members of the Georgia-Ireland parliamentary friendship group.  I also welcome the charg&eacute; d'affaires of the Georgian Embassy to Ireland, Mr. George Zurabashvili, who is almost an honorary Member of this House.  On my behalf, and on behalf of all of my colleagues in Seanad &Eacute;ireann, I extend a very warm welcome to them and good wishes for a very successful visit to Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#M00400"><p>I join in the Cathaoirleach's welcome to the delegation from Georgia to the House.  They have built up a very good relationship with the House, especially since - I apologise but I cannot pronounce his surname - George's appointment.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.118" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#M00450">Order of Business (Resumed)</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#M00475"><p>The Parkinson's Association of Ireland has been discussed in the House previously.  I ask the Leader to have a debate shortly after the Easter break on services for people suffering from Parkinson's disease.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#M00500"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#M00600"><p>The Parkinson's Association of Ireland has 12,000 members who receive no State support.  We heard heart-moving stories yesterday, especially from Gary, a young man suffering from Parkinson's disease, who said support from the HSE has been excellent and that support has helped him to live a fuller life.  Certainly, there is a need for practice nurses and for support workers with regard to the Parkinson's Association and I would like to see Members having that debate soon after Easter.</p> <p>I wish to raise another matter that was raised earlier by Senator McDowell on a very important point.  It is with regard to the planning of cities and towns.  We have failed miserably in this regard.  We have development plans and a planning department but more and more, it is engineers who are tearing up and ripping up our city.  MetroLink is very welcome and it is needed.  An underground system is needed in our city.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#M00700"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#M00800"><p>However, we need proper planning and a cost-benefit analysis.  Putting massive rail lines through communities such as Rathmines and Ranelagh, where they may not be needed, is probably the wrong way to go.  I am very concerned that engineers are planning our cities.  We wish to see a city of villages and living, breathing communities, for which we need proper planning, whereby people of all wealth status can live side by side, and the person working in a hotel or restaurant, as well as the millionaire, has an opportunity to live in the city centre.  At present, in Dublin city 9% of the country's GDP is generated and develops within four square miles with very little planning.  While we have engineers, we have very few planners.  We really need a strong debate with regard to planning in our villages and towns, because we have seen our villages, towns and cities hollowed out from being living, breathing communities.  This echoes from Cork to Dublin to Limerick to Mallow.  We need proper planning and it is long due time we had that debate.  We need to debate this before we pour billions of euro into the MetroLink.  We need a debate with the Minister, Deputy Ross, in the House to let him explain his proposals.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#M00900"><p>I was also on the delegation to Westminster with my esteemed colleague from Kerry, Senator Coghlan.  It was informative in many ways because we were given a copy of a report by the House of Commons committee on the issue of the Irish Border and its assertion there is no viable technical solution that will allow the Border to remain frictionless and seamless and that no such system exists anywhere in the world.  With regard to Brexit itself and the backstop, all sides from all parties on the delegation were emphatic that we will insist on the backstop being in any final agreement but we are concerned about the backsliding by Britain on this.  Its interpretation of the backstop seems to be entirely different to the Government's interpretation and Europe's interpretation.  At the next Council meeting, we need to ensure this is clarified and that unless it is clarified and Britain signs up to it, there can be no further discussion on trade because it is of such vital interest to Ireland.</p> <p>This is organ donor week.  The inaction of the Minister, Deputy Ross, on allowing information to be shared between medical practitioners and the driver licence authority is nothing short of ridiculous and reckless.  At this moment in time, he has already signed-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#M01000"><p>Could Senator Daly repeat that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#M01100"><p>This is with regard to the sharing of information between the organ donor transplant organisation, the HSE and medical professionals and the driver licence authority, which holds information on whether people have indicated on their driver licence that they would like to be an organ donor.  If the number 115 is on the card it indicates the holder would like to be an organ donor.  This information cannot be shared with anybody but the Minister has signed a ministerial order allowing information from a driver licence to be shared with the M50 toll company and with regard to the collection of fines from the courts, as is appropriate.  I cannot understand why he will not allow the information that is held to be shared.  A total of 2.6 million driver licences are renewed over a ten-year period.  Already, 40% of those who have renewed driver licences, and over ten years that would be almost 1 million people, have indicated they would like to be organ donors.  When someone is being asked whether they would consider donating their loved one's organs the information on their loved one's wishes, as indicated on the driver licence, could make all the difference-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#M01200"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#M01300"><p>-----between that decision being made and not being made, and I cannot understand why the Minister, Deputy Ross, is allowing the information to be shared between the driver licence authority and private companies to collect fines but is not allowing it to be shared with those who can save and transform lives.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#M01400"><p>He is a capitalist.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#M01500"><p>Perhaps the Leader could find out why the Minister, Deputy Ross, is focusing on everybody else's portfolio except his own.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#M01600"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#M01700"><p>In the next few months, Ministers will meet to plan the budget for 2019.  It is appropriate that we have a debate here on taxation.  Some of the complaints I now receive from employers, particularly with regard to doctors and nurses, are about going into the higher tax bracket once they go over &euro;34,500 in earnings and comparing this with taxation levels in Northern Ireland and the UK.  We are competing for workers with those areas now.  This morning, I spoke to a builder who brought people back from England to work here on building sites.  He advised me they are now returning to the UK because they find the tax rates here extremely high and they would be better off staying in the UK.  It is now a problem and we need to look at our taxation system.  While we need to ensure we have adequate money to improve services, we also need to ensure we can compete on the world market for people in many areas, from the building industry to the hotel industry to the medical area.  We should have a debate in the House in April or early May on this issue with regard to taxation and future planning.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1380" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#M01800"><p>At some stage after the Easter break, the Leader might invite the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade to the Seanad to discuss the undocumented in the US.  Recently, I read the special envoy from Ireland to Washington, Deputy Deasy, has said that the number of undocumented is 10,000, rather than the 40,000 or 50,000 that has been alluded to on numerous occasions previously.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paddy Burke:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1866"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1866&amp;amp;pid=PaddyBurke&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->His assertion has not been disputed by the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade.  I ask the Leader to invite in the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade to give us the up-to-date position on the number of undocumented Irish the Department believes to be in the United States and what progress has been made with the President of the United States following the visit by the Taoiseach to the United States over St. Patrick's weekend.  It would be a very worthwhile debate to have in this House.  I hope the Leader will arrange for such a debate on our return following the Easter recess.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#N00200"><p>I thank the 16 Members of the House for their contributions on the Order of Business.  I am happy to withdraw the motion, resubmit it and have a debate on another occasion rather than to divide the House on an issue we assumed had cross-party support.  I will not divide the House on an important issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#N00300"><p>If the Leader wishes, he can move an amendment to remove the business from the Order Paper.  A revised motion can be resubmitted.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#N00400"><p>I will do that.  Senators Horkan, McDowell, Conway-Walsh and Norris raised the issue of homelessness following today's announcement.  It is disappointing to see the current figure.  The issue is a priority of Government.  Rebuilding Ireland provides for an investment of &euro;6 billion in multi-annual funding.  We accept that there is a crisis in the homelessness area.  It is distressing and disappointing.  However, it is also important to acknowledge that work is being done.  To listen to people from some quarters one would swear nothing was happening.  A lot of work is being done.  We understand it is unacceptable to have people who are homeless or in hotel rooms but the Minister, Deputy Eoghan Murphy, has put together a package of measures that will take time to produce results.  I listened to Sister Stan this morning on the radio.</p> <p>Part of the difficulty we have is that we did not plan in the past for student accommodation in university towns such as Cork, Galway and parts of Dublin.  While it might not be achieved, the hope is that by building dedicated student accommodation that will free up houses.  In Washington Street, in the area surrounding University College Cork, this week Cork City Council gave planning permission for new student accommodation.  We hope that when it comes on stream houses will be freed up which could be bought by the council for social housing and areas would become gentrified and people would buy there.</p> <p>I agree with Senator McDowell that there is a need for joined-up thinking between the Department and local authorities.  The all-party committee on housing that was chaired by Deputy Bailey produced a report.  Let us look at the issue and be a bit more adventurous.  Some say we should not have private landlords while others say we should not have the construction sector involved.  Where would we be without them?  Perhaps we need to take a different viewpoint in terms of how we look at the crisis.  Another point which is important, and which Senator McDowell touched on, is that all of us aspire to buy and own our own home.  We should never take that dream away from people.  The Minister and the Government are committed to Rebuilding Ireland, which is delivering solutions.  People are exiting hotels and emergency homeless accommodation, but to listen to some people one would swear nothing was happening.  We accept progress is slow but it will take time.</p> <p>Senator Horkan referred to councillors' pay and conditions.  The debate will resume on 24 April.  It is the third occasion in this calendar year to have such a debate and it will resume again.  The points made by Senators Craughwell, Leyden and Horkan are valid ones on the body politic and how we value politics and the work of politicians.  Members were criticised for making comments in the past but I hope we will never allow our democracy to become like others, where big business can fund politicians and where it is only the chosen few who can run for office or be elected.  I hope we will not allow that to happen in our country.  As a consequence, we need to look at how we pay people.  That is not a very popular thing to say but if we need to do that then let us look at how we can provide remuneration.  I assure Senator Craughwell that I am happy to have such a debate in the coming months.</p> <p>Senator Horkan also raised the Good Friday Agreement.  I welcome the commemoration that will take place on 10 April.  The Senator is correct that we have had significant stabilisation in terms of peace in our country.  That is because of the ability of all people on the island to reconcile and to move forward.  Unfortunately, it looks like we will not have devolved government in Stormont for the anniversary but I hope we can see that happen soon.  The T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade, Deputy Coveney, and the Secretary of State for Northern Ireland, Ms Karen Bradley, have been working with the other parties to achieve that end.  I hope it happens in the short term.</p> <p>The shortage of teachers was discussed yesterday on the Order of Business.  The Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy Bruton, has convened a specialist group to examine the matter, which is under his remit.  It is also worth saying that we have seen investment in education increase by &euro;1 billion in the past two years.  The Minister has provided 5,000 additional teaching posts in the past two years.  Notwithstanding that, the Senators are correct to highlight the fact that there are deficiencies, for example, in home economics, science, Irish and in other subjects, as Senators Lombard and Gallagher mentioned yesterday.  Since 2013 there are now 8,900 more teachers working in schools.  I accept there are issues that need to be addressed.  We have seen educational establishments offer more places, for example, St. Angela's in Sligo, in terms of home economics.  The teaching conferences are coming up next week and it is a very important time for teachers in terms of debating their conditions.  I am sure we will have such a debate following the conferences.  I hope we will have positive engagement on the various interventions the Minister is making to address the supply of teachers.</p> <p>In terms of the opening hours on Good Friday, Senator Lawless's Bill was the catalyst for the pubs opening tomorrow.  I sincerely hope that people will drink sensibly and will not go overboard.  It is a new day in terms of pub openings on Good Friday and it is one that I am sure will be met with opposition in some quarters and with joy in others.  I hope it does not turn into a drink-fest and that people are sensible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#N00500"><p>A town in the Leader's good county has decided to remain dry.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#N00600"><p>I think that is Newmarket.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#N00700"><p>It may not be alone.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#N00800"><p>If a publican decides to close his or her premises tomorrow that is his or her prerogative and I will not castigate anyone for doing that.  It is the choice of publicans.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#N00900"><p>None of us would.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#N01000"><p>Like any day of the year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#N01100"><p>Yes.  Senators McDowell and Humphreys raised the metro and the need for planning in Dublin.  I refer my two esteemed colleagues to the Ireland 2040 plan.  That is what this Government is about, namely, ensuring that we plan for the development and growth of the entire country.  The points made are valid and I am happy to have such a debate with the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Ross, in the post-Easter period.</p> <p>I join with Senator Conway-Walsh in welcoming the decision by the Minister for Justice and Equality on the pardon to Maolra Seoighe.  The issue she and Senator Bacik raised about the coverage of sexual offences, rape trials and cases concerning physical domestic violence is one that requires significant sensitivity and protocols.  I do not wish to refer to any specific case but I hope that any woman or man who feels she or he is a victim of abuse can come forward and have her or his story heard.  We must always support people in those vulnerable situations.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I really hope the Domestic Violence Bill will be passed quickly in the Lower House.  Again, I thank our colleagues in this House for the way in which this legislation has been dealt with.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#O00200"><p>In fairness, the reporting of the trial that has just ended will deter many young women from coming forward, and that is really sad.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#O00300"><p>We cannot re-open the Order of Business.  The Leader should conclude.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#O00400"><p>Senators Conway-Walsh and Bacik noted that we have made progress in our jurisdiction.  There is a duty and an obligation on those who cover trials to do so in a sensitive manner.  We are dealing with cases of vulnerable people and we need to support and encourage them.  All of us, in our roles, have a duty to work with people.  It is important that we handle these matters with sensitivity.</p> <p>Senator Norris raised the issue of the Committee on Procedure and Privileges, CPP.  That is a matter for that committee and I would be happy to have that debate there.  </p> <p>Senator O'Reilly, with Senators Coghlan and Mark Daly, raised the issue of Brexit.  He also raised the matter of the Common Agricultural Policy, CAP.  The former Minister, Commissioner Hogan, will be in this House in April, and I assure Members that we will have the opportunity on that occasion to discuss the issue of CAP and the future of agriculture in Europe.</p> <p>Senator Lombard raised the issue of the Wild Atlantic Way and the town of Union Hall.  I would be happy to have the Minister of State at the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Griffin, come to the House in this regard</p> <p>Senator Mac Lochlainn raised a very sensitive issue, which he has raised before, regarding the repatriation of the body of Danielle McLaughlin.  That situation is distressing for a family in itself, but to have the added complication that the Senator has outlined is most traumatic.  It is disappointing that the response from the consul was what it was.  As the Senator said, it was not a typical response.  The issue has to be highlighted, and we should not depend upon the Kevin Bell Repatriation Trust to assist families.  We have to be hugely sympathetic and work with families in these situations.  My own experience has been different to what the Senator has outlined, because I find the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade and the consular staff to be most co-operative and helpful.  It is a matter of which the Minister should be made aware and I would be happy to oblige.  It is hard to argue with what the Senator has said this morning.  I will revert to his contribution on the issue of Syria.</p> <p>Senators Gallagher, McFadden and Humphreys yesterday held a briefing in the audiovisual room.  Senator Humphreys raised the issue of Gary Boyle's testimony and he praised the HSE.  We all agree that the Parkinson's Association requires more funding to develop further services, and as Senators McFadden and Hopkins said yesterday, the issue of the nationwide nurse specialist is one that should be pursued.  I would be happy to have the Minister come to the House.</p> <p>On behalf of the House and on my own behalf, I congratulate and thank P&aacute;raic Duffy for his stewardship of Cumann L&uacute;thchleas Gael.  I had the pleasure of working with him and of getting to know him over the past decade.  He brought huge competency to his role as ard-sti&uacute;rth&oacute;ir and I thank him and his family for their service.  He is a proud Monaghan man and I am glad he is going back to his club.  I thank and congratulate him and wish him well in his new career, I also wish Tom Ryan, the new ard-sti&uacute;rth&oacute;ir, every success.  P&aacute;raic Duffy brought huge calibre and vision to Cumann L&uacute;thchleas Gael.  </p> <p>Senator Mark Daly raised the issue of organ donation.  We are in the middle of organ donation week, which is a very important week.  We all know that the level of organ donation and transplant operations has increased this year.  The Minister of Health, Deputy Harris, is working on a Bill.  The information arising from the issues raised by Senator Mark Daly should be shared.  People can give the gift of life by carrying an organ donation card.  I appeal to all Members of this House to promote organ donation.  It gives life and joy to people.</p> <p>Senator Colm Burke raised the issue of taxation and budget 2019.  I am sure we will have the debate before the budget, and I will be happy to have that discussion.  </p> <p>Senator Paddy Burke raised the issue of the undocumented, and I would be happy to have the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade, Deputy Coveney, come to the House to discuss the matter.  </p> <p>I am happy to withdraw the motion on Syria to allow for a consensus debate on it.  The intent of the motion was to highlight the atrocities that are taking place.  It certainly was not intended to divide the House.  If we can agree on a compromise motion I am happy to do that.  Senator Bacik put a huge amount of work into it but rather than divide the House, I will amend the Order of Business to remove that motion in order that we can come back after Easter and have that debate on Syria.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#O00500"><p>Did the Leader mention Brexit?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#O00600"><p>On Brexit, I want to commend the visit of the Committee on European Affairs and to commend Senator Richmond on his work on the Seanad Special Committee on the Withdrawal of the United Kingdom from the European Union.  We have heard the views of the T&aacute;naiste, the Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade, Deputy McEntee, and An Taoiseach, and they have not demurred from that view.  There has been a realisation in the United Kingdom that the Border question will not go away and must be resolved.</p> <p>The invitation to British parliamentarians to visit the Border is something I would encourage.  As Senator Wilson and others living close to the Border will recognise, Brexit will have a huge impact in the future, especially if a hard border is allowed.  Progress is being made.  The Government has always stated the backstop will apply unless another solution is found.  It is important that this august Chamber should invite our fellow parliamentarians to visit the Border and to see for themselves the daily economic and social activity that goes on there and the impact that a hard border would have.  Senator O'Reilly mentioned the fact that milk lorries cross the Border regularly, and cattle travel back and forth between the jurisdictions on a regular basis.  This is not going to go away.  I have asked the Minister to come to the House after Easter in respect of Brexit and he has agreed to that.  We will be happy to have that debate as well.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#O00700"><p>I acknowledge Councillor Pat Daly from Ennis, County Clare, and Mr. Tommy Moylan from the Association of Irish Local Government, AILG.  I am sure they are here for the very important debate that will follow.  I am somewhat curtailed in what I can say but I hope the debate goes well and that they leave with some positive news.</p> <p>The Leader has proposed an amendment to the Order of Business to the effect that the proposal regarding No. 59, motion 14 on Syria, be deleted from the Order of Business.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.152" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Order of Business, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.153" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#O00900">Planning and Development Acts 2000 to 2017 (Increase in Number of Ordinary Members of An Bord Pleanla) Order 2018: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#O01000"><p>I move:</p><p>That Seanad &Eacute;ireann approves the following Order in draft: </p><blockquote>Planning and Development Acts 2000 to 2017 (Increase in Number of Ordinary Members of An Bord Plean&aacute;la) Order 2018, copies of which have been laid in draft form before Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 21st February, 2018.&rdquo; </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.155" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.156" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#P00100">Councillors' Conditions: Statements</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#P00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State at the Department of Housing, Planning and Local Government, Deputy Phelan, to the Chamber.  The Minister of State will speak first.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1265" speakername="John Paul Phelan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#P00300"><p>I will start as soon as I get my statement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#P00400"><p>That is okay.  I will be replaced by the Leas-Chathaoirleach in a moment.  You can start when it is appropriate.  I am told you have very good news for councillors today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1265" speakername="John Paul Phelan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#P00500"><p>We will soon see.  I appreciate the opportunity to attend the Seanad today to provide Members with an update on the position concerning supports for elected members of local authorities and the associated terms and conditions.</p> <p>We were due to have this discussion when Storm Emma came but the snow got in the way, as it did with many things that week.  This issue is one to which I have devoted much of my time and attention during the past eight months.</p> <p>I note that the issue is held in similarly high regard by Senators.  This is the third occasion that I have been invited to attend the Seanad in recent months to speak on the matter and listen to the views of Senators.  Since the last time, some improvements have been made to supports provided to councillors.  On 10 November 2017 I co-signed amending regulations under section 142 of the Local Government Act 2001 with my colleague, the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, Deputy Donohoe.  The amending regulations gave effect to and improved on the measures first announced by the former Minister with responsibility for local government, Deputy  Coveney.  In implementing these measures we have ensured that a new allowance, worth &euro;1,000 per annum, in recognition of the additional workload following the 2014 reforms is provided to all councillors to avoid any suggestion of a two-tier system of local government.  While the new allowance is backdated to 1 July 2017 I am aware that some local authorities are only now making payments to councillors.  While this is regrettable, I imagine Members fully appreciate that payments made to councillors must be fully compliant with tax law.</p> <p>The Revenue Commissioners commenced a review of the terms and conditions of the supports provided to councillors following commencement of the amending regulations.  The review was not completed until January, when all associated matters relating to implementation of the regulations were finalised.  The Revenue Commissioners ruled that the new allowance is taxable income - this was thought to be the case beforehand - and this was promptly communicated to local authorities by the Department.  This clarification should allow for outstanding payments to councillors backdated to 1 July 2017 to be issued.</p> <p>The amending regulations also gave effect to a new option of a vouched expenses allowance for councillors' work up to a maximum of &euro;5,000 per annum, which is also backdated to 1 July 2017.  The terms of the allowance are based on the public representation allowance payable to Members of the Oireachtas.  All Members will be familiar with this.</p> <p>When I last addressed the House I informed Members that the categories of eligible expenditure for the new allowance would be further extended.  The need to further extend these categories was expressed by Senators during that discussion.  I have since issued directions to local authorities along the following lines.  Councillors may now claim expenses incurred in respect of rent, rates and utilities for offices, including home offices.  Councillors may also pay any person to provide secretarial support so long as the person is eligible to work.  These measures have been backdated to 1 July 2017.  The measure also includes provision for carers and child care.  This means in effect that councillors can now claim for the same range of vouched expenses as Deputies and Senators given that they have a constituency base that they serve.  I am aware that the take-up by councillors of this new vouched allowance option has not been high thus far.  Such a new allowance will take time for fuller acceptance and I believe it should be given that time.</p> <p>A range of other financial supports are in place to assist councillors in performing their functions.  The main support is a representational payment, which recognises the work that councillors volunteer to undertake when they stand for election and subsequently serve their community.  I recall that when I began my political career as a member of Kilkenny County Council in 1999 supports for councillors were limited to expense payments for attending council meetings.  This puts in context how far we have come in the past two decades in recognising the importance of local government and improving the range of supports available.  The representational payment was introduced in January 2002.  Since that time it has been linked to the basic salary of a Senator.  In line with adjustments made to a Senator's salary, the representational payment was increased on 1 January 2018 by &euro;246 to &euro;16,891 per annum.  The payments will further benefit councillors over the term of the Public Service Stability Agreement 2018-2020 in proportion to further increases in a Senator's salary.</p> <p>I have previously addressed the House on the establishment of a review of this basic payment to councillors.  The process has been somewhat delayed by the fact that the lead official from the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform has transferred to a different Department.  It is still firmly the position of Government that a review will be completed before the end of this year.  The review is to be chaired by an independent outsider who will consult with officials in the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform, the local government section in the Department Housing, Planning and Local Government and councillor representative organisations, including Local Authority Members Association and the Association of Irish Local Government.  The review will devise a system of linking councillors' pay directly to a Civil Service grade and bring all the ancillary benefits that such a change would entail.</p> <p>Councillors also receive a composite annual expense allowance designed to defray in a structured way reasonable expenses incurred by them in attending council meetings.  It is calculated using a formula based on the distance from a councillor's residence to the council offices, current Civil Service travel and subsistence rates and a notional number of meetings that a local authority would be expected to hold in a year.  The alignment of the current Civil Service travel and subsistence rates ensures that payments may be made on a tax free basis.</p> <p>As Members are no doubt aware, the Civil Service travel rates and bands that had been in place since January 1999 were revised last year by the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, Deputy Donohoe.  My understanding is that the new revised rates reflect changes in technology, road conditions, commuter behaviour and car ownership patterns.  The key changes include an increase in the number of distance bands from two to four with a lower recoupment rates for the first 1,500 km of travel followed by an increased recoupment rate for distances between 1,501 km and 5,500 km.  A lower rate applies for distances in excess of 5,500 km.  These rates now apply throughout the public sector and have also been applied to councillors' travel expenses.  I am aware that this has had a mixed impact on councillors, depending on individual circumstances, as it has had across the public service.  Some councillors have benefitted while other have seen a reduction &ndash; significant in some cases &ndash; in annual travel remuneration.  Those councillors who have seen their travel allowance reduced include those who live close to council headquarters, such as members of city councils, as well as those based in larger geographic counties who commute long distances.  I am most familiar with some of the concerns of those based in west Cork.</p> <p>It is important to bear in mind that the annual expenses allowance is just that.  As with any expense allowance it is payable on the basis that it offsets costs incurred by the individual claiming it.  The allowance is not and should not be considered as income.  Having said that, councillors should not be forced by circumstances to rely excessively on remuneration from travel expenses as a means of financial support.  I appreciate that travel is an integral part of a councillor's duties.  Councillors are perhaps unique in the public sector in the range of public bodies to which they may be appointed or nominated to represent their local authorities.  Given the extensive revision of Civil Service travel rates, the Department is examining the methodology for calculating councillor's travel and subsistence expenses to ensure that it remains fit for purpose.  It is also the case that the complex means for calculating the annual expenses allowance imposes an administrative burden on local authorities and individual councillors alike and there could be benefits in a simplified approach.  It is of great importance to support councillors appropriately with due regard for transparency and accountability to ensure they can effectively carry out their role as elected representatives and can continue to give expression to local identity, concerns and the setting of local priorities.  Ensuring that supports for councillors are sustainable and appropriate in future will require further consideration between the Department and relevant stakeholders.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1383" speakername="Paul Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#P00600"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House.  I welcome the councillors, who are representing their colleagues and members of the AILG, to the Public Gallery.  I wish them continued success in their great endeavours to ensure that their representatives achieve fair play, fair pay and fair terms and conditions for the great work they are doing.</p> <p>I note that the Minister of State alluded to the fact that the debate was to be held during the week when Storm Emma landed.  Unfortunately, for obvious reasons, it had to be postponed.  Storm Emma was another example of the great, valiant and un-rewarded work that councillors and public representatives do in their local communities throughout the country.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paul Daly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2464"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2464&amp;amp;pid=PaulDaly&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It was a time of crisis for many communities.  The first people at the coalface were councillors and public representatives.  Without reward or pay, they led the lines of action, which helped many people to overcome the severe storm.</p><p>Fianna F&aacute;il supports fair and appropriate pay and conditions for local representatives.  Moreover, we believe it is time to overhaul and reform the local government system and to put additional powers and responsibilities into the hands of our local representatives.  A major change in councillors' conditions was the expansion of local electoral areas to cover a much broader geographic area.  Some councils were abolished and others were amalgamated, and the number of local representatives in Ireland was reduced from a previous high of 1,627 to the current number of 949.  This means that, on average, each councillor represents approximately 4,500 constituents, which is a dramatically increased workload for each individual councillor.</p><p>The Government proposes to reduce the size of all local electoral areas to between five and seven seats, with provision for some even smaller three seaters and four seaters in sparsely populated places.  However, the overall number of councillors across Ireland will remain the same at 949, so this will have no effect on the number of constituents that each councillor serves.  In fact, the workload will increase even further, as the population continues to grow in virtually all areas of the country.</p><p>As the Minister of State is aware, councillors were surveyed in July and August 2016 and asked about their conditions.  The overwhelming conclusion from that survey was that their workloads had greatly increased as a consequence of recent changes.  The results of the survey show that 74% of councillors are spending ten hours or more attending meetings every week and 68% of them are spending an additional ten hours or more attending community events.  As former councillors and current public representatives, the Minister of State and I both know that councillors work 24-7.  One cannot quantify it by attendance at meetings or community events.  A councillor is on call 24-7 and cannot go outside the door even at a social event without people making representations to him or her.  The survey's figure of 20 hours is staggering, but the fact of the matter is that people at the coalface of the democratic system are working and are on call 24-7 and we still cannot agree proper pay, terms and conditions for them.</p><p>Against the background of much larger workloads, the Government introduced changes to councillors' expenses in January.  It was clear at the time - I even said it to the Minister of State in this Chamber - that the proposed changes would lead to at least some councillors being worse off.  That is exactly what happened, as the Minister of State has acknowledged.  I am given to understand that more than half of all councillors are in a financially worse position than they were before the changes were introduced.  I am at a loss to see what possible justification there could be for introducing what in reality amounted to a punitive measure against councillors, especially when it was well known within the Government the level of effort and commitment that councillors showed everyday serving their constituents.</p><p>It should be remembered that all of this occurred against a background of the economy growing by 7.8% in 2017 according to recent GDP figures released by the Central Statistics Office.  Even if there are problems with GDP as a measure of economic performance, it is clear that the economy is growing and it is time for the Government to give proper recognition to the unique and vital role of councillors across Ireland.</p><p>The system as it currently stands is not fit for purpose.  The Minister for Finance and Public Expenditure and Reform announced in February that he would establish a review of councillors' pay and conditions.  This review should take place as a matter of urgency under the direction of a strong and independent chairperson.  The issue of councillors' pay and conditions must be properly addressed and resolved once and for all.</p><p>I will repeat a caveat.  The major issue with the lack of urgency shown in addressing this situation is the fact that the people in government - the people in power - do not want to be seen giving something that might be viewed as beneficial to fellow politicians.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1265" speakername="John Paul Phelan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#Q00200"><p>Is it not that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1383" speakername="Paul Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#Q00300"><p>That day has to go.  If we, as public representatives, cannot look after the hard working members of our own establishment, we cannot look after anyone else.  The notion that this issue should not be touched because the media might play ball with it is a figment.  We must stand up to the plate, be strong and reward people as they deserve for the rewardable jobs they are performing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#Q00400"><p>I welcome the Minister of State.  Before I get into what I have to say-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1265" speakername="John Paul Phelan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#Q00500"><p>Attack me.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#Q00600"><p>-----I have to say the Minister of State's commitment to this issue is honourable.  I am not sure where the logjam is, but I believe that the Minister of State wants to solve it.</p> <p>It is important to put this debate on councillors' pay, terms, conditions and employment, or the lack thereof, in context.  There is no master-servant relationship.  They are not employees.  It is the same with the Minister of State and me, in that we are not employees.  We must get that point straight first.</p> <p>On 21 April 2015, the then Minister of State at the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government advised the House during a Commencement debate that the representational payment to councillors was a recognition of the work they chose to undertake when they stood for election.  According to her, that payment was never meant to be a salary and councillors knew this when they took on the commitment.  Clearly, that response was prepared for her by the Department, so it must have reflected the Department's thinking.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1265" speakername="John Paul Phelan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#Q00700"><p>Three years ago.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#Q00800"><p>In the same debate, the then Minister of State acknowledged that the annual representational payment was not fully commensurate with the workload of councillors.  Having been a local authority member, I am sure that the current Minister of State would agree with that.  Indeed, we could not pay them.  As my colleague just pointed out, it is a 24-7 job.  One councillor told me that he could not go to the toilet without someone standing beside him and telling him about a problem that person wanted solved.  That, I am afraid, is part and parcel of local representation.</p> <p>We were told in the same debate in 2015 that the then Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government had indicated his intention to start a review of local authorities following the passing of the 2014 Act.  The review was to be broadly representative and the advisory group would include within its working group members of the Association of Irish Local Government, .  That debate was almost three years ago to the day, but we have still not seen the establishment of that group.</p> <p>Let us deal with the real issue, that being, the money people are paid.  Something like 30% of councillors are dependent on the representational payment.  It is all they have.  That is their employment.  We have had to bring this country kicking and screaming to change councillors' conditions.  I have with me the rapporteur's report that I presented on class K PRSI.  Until it was presented, councillors were paying class K PRSI and getting sweet damn all for 4% of their incomes.  I made the point this morning that the same rate applied to Senators, but we have not had the guts to stand up and do anything about it yet.  Following the report, the then Minister - the current Taoiseach - changed councillors to class S PRSI.  At least now there is a pension for those who are young enough to benefit from it, but what about the ones who have been serving their communities for years, are well past 66 years of age and have no pensions despite having paid PRSI for years?  It is wrong in every sense of the word.</p> <p>There has been a blurring of the lines.  We have pay, allowances and expenses.  The problem is that expenses have been used to augment the income of councillors.  Doing so has been to the detriment of the vehicles they drive.  As the Minister of State pointed out a few moments ago, expenses are only meant to recoup out-of-pocket losses.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Gerard P. Craughwell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2402"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2402&amp;amp;pid=GerardPCraughwell&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->They are calculated to cover tax, insurance, servicing and replacing vehicles, replacing tyres and all these things.  If that money is used to pay the ESB bill, it is being misused because it is not being set aside to replace the vehicle, for example.  We have to get back to identifying where everything lies.  We have to pay councillors a proper salary for the job they do.  We should separate them from Members of this House and align them to a member of the public service, perhaps a clerical officer, an assistant clerical officer or someone like that.  We should put them in at that level.  Their remuneration will move up and down in accordance with public service pay.</p><p>County councillors have been promised that something will be done for them for the almost four years I have been in this House.  They have been told we are going to look after them and we are going to do this, that and the other.  The truth of the matter is that if we were willing to do something here and if the political will was there, it would have been done by now.  I believe the Minister of State has the political will, is willing to put his neck on the line and take whatever public criticism will come with looking after those who serve their communities.</p><p>Why should we be embarrassed about it?  These people work around the clock.  My colleague asked who people went to during the recent storms.  One county councillor told me that on Christmas morning a family arrived at his house to tell him they had no electricity and could not cook their dinner.  He said what could he do but bring them in and give them a dinner.  That is what public service at local representation level is about.  We need to represent and recognise what is being done.</p><p>I want no more promises and no more statements saying we are going to look after councillors.  By the way, I want a detailed explanation sent to councillors about what is meant by "travelling expenses".  It was never meant to be a form of income.  We need councillors to know that and to stop playing games with them.  It is grossly unfair.  They represent their communities not just on the councils but in the HSE and on university and institutes of technology boards, although, importantly, we have reduced the power of county councillors.  Even in the recent Technological Universities Bill, we reduced the number of county councillors on the boards of technological universities.  We are stripping away more and more power from these people.</p><p>If a group is being put together to look at the terms and conditions of employment of county councillors, we must first determine if county councillors are employed.  We must give them a salary but, more importantly, the review group must have representatives of local authorities on it.  We must also look at the allowances and the way they are paid and distributed across a council.  We must make sure that there is fairness and nobody suffers in the long term.  Everybody must get a chance at being the chair of a board or of a strategic policy committee, SPC.  We need to be far more equal and egalitarian in the way we look after these people.  What we do not need are promises of great things to come which have not happened so far.  The ball is at the feet of the Minister of State.  We will be looking to him-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1265" speakername="John Paul Phelan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#R00200"><p>We do not have the ball at our feet in Kilkenny, we have the ball in our hand.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#R00300"><p>I realise that the Minister of State, as a Kilkennyman, might have a difficulty kicking a ball.  However, what he can do is learn how to kick a ball.  If he is not able to kick a ball, then we will give him a hurley and he can play the ball but, for God's sake, he must play the game and start to look after the people who get him elected.  In a couple of months' time, when the Minister of State is looking to be elected, they will be knocking on doors on his behalf, saying that he is a great guy.  I would hate them to say that he is full of promises and delivers nothing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.173" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.174" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#R00500"><p>I would hate that to happen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.175" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1374" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#R00700"><p>He was playing junior B hurling there.  It was very low.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.177" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#R00800"><p>With studs up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#R00900"><p>I have placed the Minister of State on the spot.  He knows where he stands and what is expected from him.  I wish him well as he goes forward.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.179" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#R01000"><p>With the Leas-Chathaoirleach's permission, I wish to give two minutes to my colleague, Senator Kieran O'Donnell.</p> <p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House and acknowledge that since he came into office, he has taken this subject by the scruff of the neck and has been proactive.  I know from private conversations with him, and from his returning the &euro;1,000 lost to councillors, that he is sincere and genuine in trying to resolve this.  I appreciate that.  The important news in the Minister of State's speech today is that he has given a commitment to immediately set up the local authority remuneration review group.  That is an important development.  He has also agreed to give it an independent chair and he has not made it a long fingering exercise because he has agreed that it will report this year.  Those three things, namely, the independent chair, the quick report and the broad terms of reference, will make that review group very effective.</p> <p>The review group will quickly discover that councillors work 24-7 and that they are the front-line workers in our democratic system.  They are the lightning conductors for public anger, rage and angst among communities and individuals.  They are available to attend public meetings on behalf of councils on a round the clock basis.  They now have huge areas to cover, which I know the Minister of State proposes to reduce, and that should be the case.</p> <p>Some 30% of councillors are totally dependent on whatever income they get from being a councillor.  Apart from that 30%, the other 70% are greatly disadvantaged in terms of their careers and personal income if they are in business or in farming and must be replaced, etc.  They suffer huge financial disadvantage and they and their families give a commitment 24-7.  They are at the front-line of democracy.  That is why the review body must address the four key issues of concern to councillors.</p> <p>The requirement to aggregate travel from a multiplicity of outside bodies is not a runner because of the sheer number of bodies on which councillors represent their councils.  I will not read the full list which is enormous.  It is virtually impossible to implement that, and the Minister of State said as much in his speech.  This must be a key issue for the review body to study.</p> <p>The other key issue the review body must study is that the changes to the travel rate are causing a drop in income for a number of councillors.  Some 541 councillors are disadvantaged financially under the new system and they are getting less money.  It is not a question of earning but a question of getting money back for the enormous losses they suffered on their election in 2014.  They are in a very difficult situation.  The losses range from as high as &euro;280 to &euro;291 in some instances.  It is a very difficult situation.</p> <p>Another issue this review body will need to look at under the independent chair is that we will have a huge deficit on the front-line of democracy if we cannot attract good quality people into local government in the future as well as maintain the existing people.  Does the Minister of State have figures on the attrition rate in the current councils?  I would submit that it is very high and will get higher if we do not deal with this critical question.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Joe O'Reilly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1610"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1610&amp;amp;pid=JoeOReilly&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The issue of vouching needs to be looked at by the new review group and it needs to be dealt with immediately.  Vouching is not working.  The pick-up of 3% to 5% is a clear indication it is not a success and is not something councillors can embrace.  I admire the Minister of State's effort to be proactive and reactive to our demands.  He tried to widen the terms of reference and the basis on which people could claim the vouched allowances.  That is typical of the Minister of State's effort to resolve the issue.  It is still not working and it needs to be studied.  I am happy with the new authority being set up to do the examination.  I am happy there will be a timeframe and it will not be an indefinite thing that will go on <i>ad nauseam</i>until some of the councillors have resigned.  I am also happy it will have an independent chair.  I would like an assurance from the Minister of State but I think it is implicit in what he has already said, that it will take a holistic look at every aspect of a councillor's income.  The Minister of State is nodding assent that there will be a holistic approach.  It should look at every facet of a councillor's existence and what he or she is losing.  I appreciate the opportunity to speak.  It is a very important issue if we want to preserve our Irish democratic system.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.181" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1374" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#S00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Phelan, to the House.  The role of councillors has changed significantly over the years.  We now have metropolitan areas, much larger electoral areas and SPCs.  The role of the councillor is virtually a full-time role.  I welcome that the Minister of State is setting up the local authority remuneration review group.  It is important it is established as quickly as possible.  There will be an independent chair.  It needs to be someone who has an industrial relations background, who councillors have confidence in and who the Government can work with.  The timetable the Minister of State is talking about is that it will report back by the end of the year.  I always feel that timetables should not be too long or too short.  If they are too long, they drag on and if they are too short, they are not comprehensive enough.  It is something that is extremely important.  I also welcome that the two key elements for a councillor are salary and expenses.  I welcome the revision of the Civil Service travel scheme.  It has had a wide range of revisions.  The Minister of State will look at the methodology for how it is calculated for councillors and maybe at simplifying the system.  That should form part of the terms of reference for the local authority remuneration review group.  Councillors do phenomenal work on the ground.  They are a basic element of democracy.  The key focus in setting up a local authority remuneration review group with an independent chair, for the public, councillors and Government, is to be seen to be taking a holistic view.  It is long overdue.  It should be transparent so the public can see what is involved in being a councillor, including how much time it takes, the hours people put in, the expenses involved and that it has key elements of what democracy is about.  People should be remunerated in a fair way in terms of salary and expenses.  The key things are the local authority review group is being established with an independent chair and that the issue of travel expenses is addressed.  I thank the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.182" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1385" speakername="Grace O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#S00300"><p>The Minister of State is very welcome.  I am sharing time with my colleague, Senator Black.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.183" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#S00400"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.184" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1385" speakername="Grace O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#S00500"><p>In preparation for speaking on this matter I contacted councillors across the country to hear from them about their lived experiences of councillors.  I got considerable feedback from a diverse range of elected representatives, including men and women, young and old, party and non-party and rural and urban.  All of them were absolutely united in being dissatisfied with the current system of remuneration and the pressures they face as councillors.  Many indicated difficulty in making ends meet with family to support, debts to pay and large outlays on the business of being a local representative.  Some indicated they did not intend to run again in the 2019 local elections due to the pressures.  Some talked about working up to 70 hours a week to represent constituents often with little support, only to feel let down by central Government which they work so hard to make more accessible to fellow citizens.  I agree with Senator O'Reilly they are front-line people.</p> <p>Some of the urban based councillors asked about the huge disparity between the representation levels and those of other councillors.  A councillor in Dublin City Council north inner city ward, for example, represents an average of 8,375 people, while a councillor in Leitrim represents on average 1,765 people.  Some disparity is to be expected but the north inner city ward has 3.2 times the number of people as Leitrim but less than half the number of local representatives.  Unsurprisingly, those representatives are severely overworked trying to represent their constituents.  This is something that needs to be addressed in any review that takes place.  I have heard of the deprivation many councillors are facing, often caused by the way in which they are paid for their work.  The current mishmash of expenses, direct payments, mileage, etc., has led to many unintended consequences and real crises.  One councillor with five children to support had applications for family income support rejected as he is considered self-employed.  Another could barely pay her bills and recent funeral expenses before her pay cheque was gone.  These problems are real and serious and more immediate and drastic action needs to be taken.  </p> <p>Some specific demographics among councillors face particular challenges.  Young councillors were in touch about their first time on the council.  They find themselves with a lot of middle aged and well-established peers, all of whom are able to finance themselves and their local work through private means, which puts such new entrants at significant disadvantage.  Women face various challenges getting a foot in the door on an equal footing in local authorities.  There is no existing provision for maternity leave or cover which is an active barrier to women's full participation.  I have heard this again and again from female councillors.  It is little wonder that women make up 21% of councillors and less wonder again that we have a problem getting enough women to come to the Oireachtas though the local Government system.  In Waterford, there are 32 elected representatives, of which just four are women.  This needs to be addressed if we are to challenge the problem of female representation.  Councillors also face rising costs in the performance of duties.</p> <p>Other Senators have outlined concerns.  What I have seen from the letters I have received, which we can send to the Minister of State's office, is that there are concerns among councillors.  They need more representation and more respect.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.185" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#S00600"><p>Senator Black has four minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.186" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1408" speakername="Frances Black" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#S00700"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the Chamber.  I will try to be as quick as possible because I am aware we have limited time.  I thank every councillor who called, emailed and texted me over the past weeks after I sought input on this issue.  It is hugely important to hear directly from those affected.  I wish I could put every email and testimony into this speech today.  I will try to touch on as many of the issues raised as possible.</p> <p>The first and broadest point is that there is a lack of awareness of the work that local and city councillors do and the role they play.  In running for the Seanad and attending AILG meetings, I have met many people who do the job and it has been an eye-opener for me into the daily realities of the role and the long hours they work.  It is almost a vocation for some of the councillors.  They leave their families and everything behind.  </p> <p>For the majority of people, local councillors are the first port of call when one has a problem.  This is aside from attending council meetings and voting and all the more formal aspects of the job.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Frances Black:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2474"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2474&amp;amp;pid=FrancesBlack&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is about making sure they are always available if somebody locally needs help.  If a key service is not working or somebody needs State support to get by, it is the local councillor who is there to answer that call.  This is especially true for vulnerable people, in whom I have a particular interest, who may not know what support is available for them or how to access it.  For example, in my work with the RISE Foundation and on the Public Health (Alcohol) Bill, I have met many county and city councillors who are also working with drug and alcohol task forces in local communities to try to tackle this problem.  All local representatives I have spoken to have told me that if they want to take their role seriously and if they want to be able to respond to each constituent with care, compassion and time, they end up working extremely long hours on top of doing their regular jobs.  This is a real problem because councillors are then trying to do a full-time role, but through out-of-hours work after their job or by taking unpaid leave.  They spend less time with their families and are under huge pressure at work.</p><p>The big impact of this is that it squeezes out people on lower incomes or people who do not have the flexibility and support that comes with certain professions.  The low pay means it is just not viable for most people.  That is making it unsustainable in the long run.  A councillor who contacted me had agreed to go on a 3.5 days working week to allow for meetings and constituency work.  That is difficult enough, but many people just do not have that option.  Another young woman councillor is trying to do the job while raising her three young children.  She felt it was essentially a choice between being there for her family or continuing in the role.  There has been some movement in recent years where various expenses and allowances have been introduced, but the feedback on this process is that it is really complicated and difficult to get through.  We have a patchwork process where one thing has been added to another and that has made it increasingly difficult to navigate.  I spoke with the Association of Irish Local Government, AILG, which said that as a result it expects 3% to 5% of councillors to sign up for this.  I am encouraged by the Minister of State's comments today on trying to introduce a simplified approach and the potential for linking remuneration to a Civil Service grade.</p><p>Ultimately, we must have a genuine debate about what role we want councillors and local government to play and how inclusive we want the positions to be.  At present, we are caught between two poles - it is not a voluntary position with a low level of commitment and it is not a full-time position with the resources available to do the job that people expect.  If we want people on lower incomes or people from less advantaged backgrounds to step forward into this role, we cannot leave it so that only those with a high salary and a flexible job can afford it.  As an Independent Senator, I am proud of the achievements I and my fellow Independent Senators have had in this House.  Irish politics needs strong, independent voices, particularly those who will represent the most vulnerable in society.  This is as true for local government as it is for Leinster House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#T00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for attending this debate.  I hope he takes on board what we say today.  I was a councillor in the west Mayo area for seven years and, as has been said, the role of the councillor is changing all the time.  I disagree with the urban versus rural issue.  We have to be careful about that in terms of making chalk of one and cheese of the other.  The role of a councillor is challenging regardless of where one is.  For me, the challenge was that the area stretched to 123 km or a four hour round trip and being acutely conscious that one had to serve all of the area equally across the constituency.  This is a challenge for rural councillors.</p> <p>What challenges people across the board is the role of the councillor in trying to deal with very serious issues and in trying to fill in the gaps that exist because services are not provided.  One might be dealing with a young person with mental health problems, the lack of infrastructure, education and, increasingly, with health problems.  A councillor tries to serve all these roles.  I commend all the councillors across the country who are doing Trojan work trying to support the people in their communities.  They spend a huge amount of time doing this work.  They are also dealing with people in extreme poverty and as a result they are often reluctant to come forward and say they cannot afford to do their job any longer.  Other good people would like to be public representatives but the fact is that they cannot afford to do it.  How could somebody who is trying to bring up children alone, for example, or in other situations become a councillor?  Financially, people cannot do it, and it is a huge loss to society and to politics that they are barred from doing it.  Are we going to end up with people who are elderly, and there is nothing wrong with that, and people who are already financially secure?  That would be wrong.  We need new and diverse voices.  We need people at different stages of their life cycles to be public representatives at local and other levels.</p> <p>I wish to focus in particular on councillors who are rearing a young family and trying to pay a mortgage and all the bills.  Many of these councillors cannot access family income supplement, FIS, payment because their local authority cannot confirm that they work over 19 hours per week in order to qualify.  If they have no other employment, they are relying on their representational payment of &euro;302 per week.  I thank all the councillors across the board who have contacted me about this and the other matters that affect them.  One councillor I spoke to has three children.  His spouse is not working and he is a full-time councillor.  As the hours he works cannot be confirmed he is losing &euro;98.40 per week.  That is not right.  Social Justice Ireland produced a report last week on 100,000 people living in consistent poverty in this country.  Many of our councillors are in the working poor bracket, the people who are working day and night but cannot afford to pay the bills.</p> <p>It was mentioned somewhere that a councillor works about 20 hours per week.  I guarantee that I would never have stopped being a county councillor if all that was required was to work 20 hours per week.  We all know that a councillor works well over 60 hours per week - I can speak for the hours I put into it - when one takes account of the meetings, the municipal district, the workshops and the myriad other occasions one has to attend.  In addition, sometimes people are under the impression that when one attends an event as a councillor one is paid to do that.  A great deal of material is put out in the media with regard to headline figures for what councillors earn and so forth, without looking into how much actually goes into their pockets.  I worked it out on one occasion and I probably should not have done it, because I ended up calculating that I was being paid approximately &euro;1 per hour as a councillor.  I did the job because I loved doing it.  It is a little like the curse of the cause because one gets into doing it and one wants to do more and more and to do one's best.  Financially, however, that is what the rate was, and it is the rate for many councillors across the country.  There has been an increase of &euro;1,000 in salary and &euro;2,000 in vouched expenses since then, but that has to be just a start.</p> <p>I wish to clarify something relating to the vouched expenses.  Some local authorities are requiring that home offices must be rateable offices before vouched allowance for home office and associated utilities will be paid.  Can the Minister of State clarify that?  I am perplexed as to why all the councils are not being compelled to implement the positive changes that have been made before now.  Many young people who were elected in 2014 lack the support they require.  That is the reason many councillors are leaving as well.  Sometimes it can be put down to other issues but the enormity of the task they have to do without the resources they require to do the job is posing a problem.  The aggregation of mileage returns becomes impossible when the entire spectrum of bodies has to be included.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Rose Conway-Walsh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2462"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2462&amp;amp;pid=RoseConwayWalsh&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Very often councillors must represent their local authority at the last minute in front of bodies such as the Health Service Executive, education and training boards and regional assemblies etc., and this must be taken into account.  New regulations on the annual fixed travel allowance are having an impact on councillors who were elected in 2014 and now must operate under this regime.  That should be addressed.  Many of these councillors also made financial predictions based on the system that was in place at the time of their election.</p><p>I could speak for much longer about this.  It is not about "poor me" and we know so many people are in poverty in this country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.190" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#U00200"><p>We accept that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.191" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#U00300"><p>We speak in here so many times about workers' rights, precarious working hours, zero-hour contracts and all that.  We need to do the same for our councillors.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.192" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#U00400"><p>Absolutely.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.193" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" speakername="Gabrielle McFadden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#U00500"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House again.  Before I start giving out, I acknowledge the work he has done for councillors' pay and conditions.  It is great to see him here but I cannot help but feel that we should not be having this debate again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.194" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1380" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#U00600"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.195" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" speakername="Gabrielle McFadden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#U00700"><p>One councillor said to me recently that never has so much been said about so little money.  In the 21 months since this Seanad convened, this is the third time we have discussed this matter, not to mention the times I and other Senators in the House have raised it on the Order of Business or at our own parliamentary party meetings.  Most of us have been councillors, including the Minister of State, and all of us are aware of the great service that councillors provide to this country with their long hours.  There is no need to rehearse over and over the reasons they deserve due recognition for their contribution because we already know them.</p> <p>The time for talking is over and we need to just get the job done.  In this regard I welcomed the undertaking the Minister gave us last November for a review of the supports provided to councillors, as well as the associated terms and conditions.  I also welcomed the commitment from the Minister for Finance, Deputy Donohoe, in our parliamentary party meeting in February to the same review, with a board and an independent chair.  If anybody is in doubt about that pledge by the Minister, Deputy Donohoe, they can check it out because it was leaked to RT&Eacute; after the meeting of 21 February.  It is now time to stop looking and start doing.  The review should not take a further eight months and this is not new, as we know all about it.  Whatever the decision, it should be agreed and done before the summer break.</p> <p>I know the Minister of State will take on board everything that has been said today and that he wants to bring closure to this.  I acknowledge his hands are tied because the Minister, Deputy Donohoe, has a say in it too.  I nevertheless urge the Minister of State to stop the talking and let us do the job.  Let us hope we will not have to come back here for another debate on this topic.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.196" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1380" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#U00800"><p>I thank Senator McFadden for sharing her time with me.  I have spoken on quite a number of occasions on this matter so I will stick to a number of points.  I welcome the Minister of State back to the House to debate the issue.  As Senator McFadden has said, much has been spoken about what is a relatively easy matter with which to get to grips.  I have no doubt but that with what has been done so far, there will be big improvements between now and when the review is finalised.</p> <p>Having an independent chair, the setting up of the review and the timeframe for the review - it has been said it will be later this year - are very important.  This must be done fairly quickly.  I ask the Minister of State for a commitment today that when the review is finished, whatever the recommendations may be, they will be backdated to when all this started.  The review has been ongoing, and we can allow it continue like that, but the Minister of State should give a firm commitment here on it.  The review is most important, as this will set the standard and the framework for the future for local authority members.  If it needs extra time, that is fair enough, but the Minister of State should at least give a commitment that the review, whatever its findings, will have its recommendations backdated either to now or a number of months ago.</p> <p>I was first elected to a local authority nearly 40 years ago in 1979.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#U00900"><p>The elder statesman.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.198" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1380" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#U01000"><p>Huge changes have taken place in the role of the councillor.  In my time it was part-time but now I do not know if a councillor's job is full-time, part-time or something else.  In any event, it takes considerable time.  To put this in context, somebody who is self-employed must more than likely employ somebody to do work every week, whether on a part-time basis like a day or half a day a week, and that would have consequences for business people.  If these people are members of the local authority for five or ten years, they might have to pay redundancy at the end.  Before the recession, a stipulation of two weeks of pay for every year of redundancy was used, with the Government paying 80% of the cost of the redundancy.  Now the employer must pay the full cost of the redundancy.  Somebody could be in the local authority for ten or 20 years employing a person part-time over that period and he or she could have to pay huge redundancy while getting a very small salary.  This is important and should be taken into account in the review.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.199" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#U01100"><p>Before calling the next speaker I welcome our friends in the Gallery.  They are Councillors Pat Daly, P.J. O'Hanlon and Tommy Moylan of the AILG.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.200" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#U01200"><p>Councillor Joe Carroll is there too.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.201" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#U01300"><p>Forgive me.  My macular oedema is at fault.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.202" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#U01400"><p>I appreciate the opportunity to speak.  The Minister of State may look at Senators speaking passionately on the matter of councillors' rights with a small bit of cynicism.  I would not necessarily blame him as the vast majority of Senators are here because we got elected by councillors, in the main.  We did the circuit and we went around to all the different meetings.  To be frank, the vast majority of councillors to whom I spoke were more concerned with national issues, although there were always concerns about the terms and conditions of the job at hand.  Many people have spoken on this and I do not really want to repeat what has been said.</p> <p>Before I came into politics, there was a general perception of councillors that was quite negative.  Being from Dublin and having gone through the 1980s and the tribunals, the assumption was that a councillor's reputation was not great.  I was elected to a local authority in 2004 and I was in the north inner city.  I am very taken by Senator Black's comments on the responsibilities that councillors had in the north inner city, where I was elected.  My mind was blown first because party whip and affiliation are well down the list of priorities when it comes to being a councillor.  It is not like being in here or in the D&aacute;il and there is not the same adversarial nature of party politics on the council.  Councillors genuinely work across parties and there is not a strict whip system.  If one goes to a public meeting, councillors generally work hand in glove in trying to get matters resolved.  Councillors deal with matters that are very sensitive, such as parks, playgrounds and the public space, which is very important.  I first ran for election because the library closest to where I taught in Sheriff Street did not open on a Saturday for some bizarre reason.  I learned that was because the local authority decided it should not open on Saturdays.  When I was elected we engaged with other parties, councillors and the city management and after a period the library was opened on Saturdays.  It is that public space that they defend and advocate for and it is extremely important, as are the committees on which councillors sit.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2301"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2301&amp;amp;pid=AodhanORiordan&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I was unable to sit on a remarkable number of committees because I was teaching at the same time as I was a councillor.  They included the local drugs task force.  I appreciate the comments made by Senator Conway-Walsh on the rural-urban divide and I accept that the comparison between rural and urban councillors is not necessarily fair considering the distances the former must travel.  However, in various parts of the country, including cities, local authority members must attend crucial meetings dealing with life and death issues, for example, meetings of local drugs task forces.</p><p>Councillors have to become experts on everything overnight, from planning and drugs to traffic and ramps.  Members of the education and training boards, previously known as vocational educational committees, must become experts in education.  Councillors clearly take their responsibilities extremely seriously and the concern is that the only people who will be attracted to run for local election are those who have time on their hands or enough money to allow them to do the job.  It would be a dangerous development if the only people attracted to local politics were those with time and money.</p><p>A large number of members of Dublin City Council resigned during my time as a councillor from 2004 until 2011.  Most resignations were not related to political concerns or the reasons that Senators or Deputies resign but genuinely because some of those who ran for election in 2004 and 2009 did not realise the workload they would have and what was expected of them.  A great deal is expected of local councillors.  Following the resignations, those who were co-opted to take the vacant seats also found the job very difficult.</p><p>In fairness to the Minister of State, he gave a commitment on this issue at a meeting of the Fine Gael Parliamentary Party.  Perhaps Senators will be invited to the next such meeting.  He also established a review with an independent chair, which will report by the end of the year.  I am willing to accept that commitment and I will support the Minister of State in his endeavours in this regard.  I look forward to the findings of the group.  I will give him a fair wind by assuming the review will come up with the goods by the end of year.</p><p>I do not need to rehearse the arguments made by previous speakers.  The jibes and jokes made about councillors are hurtful, for example, when they are asked how many brown envelopes they received in the previous week.  Before I entered public life and ran for election, I made similar types of jokes.  I subsequently observed that, regardless of political background or party, local representatives worked thanklessly, day in, day out on nitty-gritty issues and were always willing to engage with other political representatives.  During my time on Dublin City Council, I joined the four other councillors in the north inner city, Christy Burke, Thomas Stafford, Emer Costello and Mick Rafferty, at many meetings across the north inner city which were attended by more councillors than residents.  Sometimes people do not realise the commitment, time, dedication, knowledge and expertise councillors give to their work.  They are supposedly part-time and if they are at a financial disadvantage and find they cannot keep going, they will resign which is a very difficult decision to make when one has secured a mandate and then finds one cannot continue to represent one's electorate.</p><p>If Members of the Oireachtas were honest, we would admit that between 80% and 90% of the work we do is council related.  Who are at the front line of the housing crisis?  It is councillors who must deal with local authority waiting lists and so forth.  For this reason, having love bombed the Minister of State just now and another Fine Gael Party Minister yesterday, I was disappointed by the communication circulated by the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government, Deputy Eoghan Murphy, to local authority members concerning their ability to make representations on planning applications.  That was a bad, unfortunate and regrettable move because councillors know their areas well and are entitled to make representations on planning applications.  Having said that, I agree with all the sentiments expressed by Senators on the work done by councillors.  I am concerned, however, by the number of councillors who are resigning and the type of person who will be in a position to run for local office in future.  We will support the review mechanism proposed by the Minister of State in the hope that it will produce the goods.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.204" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#V00200"><p>Senator Mark Daly has six minutes' speaking time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.205" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#V00300"><p>I am sharing time with Senators Wilson, Gallagher, Davitt and Murnane O'Connor.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.206" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#V00400"><p>The Senators will have less than one and a half minutes each.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.207" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#V00500"><p>We will take whatever time we are given but perhaps the Acting Chairman will show a little latitude.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.208" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#V00600"><p>On a point of order, the debate will resume on 24 April.  Rather than having five or six Senators speak for one minute each, perhaps some of them will take the opportunity to speak when the debate resumes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.209" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#V00700"><p>I understand that Senators who contribute today may not speak again when the debate resumes.  It may be preferable, therefore, to have two speakers share the slot.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.210" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#V00800"><p>In that case, I will share time with Senator Robbie Gallagher.</p> <p>Many of us understood that the review to which the Minister referred related to the holistic issue of terms and conditions for councillors.  One of the proposals was to consider the type of system that operates in the Oireachtas.  In his contribution, however, the Minister of State indicated the Revenue Commissioners had commenced a review of councillors' terms and conditions.  While stakeholders will be consulted, I expect the review will deal only with the tax treatment of councillors' terms and conditions, for example, the matter raised by Senator Craughwell in respect of class K contributions.  As such, it will not examine ways of improving terms and conditions.  The Revenue Commissioners never improve anyone's conditions because rather than giving people money, they take money from people.  I ask the Minister of State to clarify whether the review has changed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.211" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1265" speakername="John Paul Phelan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#V00900"><p>The Senator is referring to two different things.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.212" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#V01000"><p>There was no mention of the overall review.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.213" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1265" speakername="John Paul Phelan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#V01100"><p>I referred to the other review in my speech, although it does not feature in the speaking note that was circulated.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.214" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#V01200"><p>That is fine.  I will look at the blacks because this is an important issue.  The timeline is also critical.  It will be important to consider a system for payments to public representatives similar to that in operation for Deputies and Senators.  Local councillors are treated as but not paid as civil servants.  They are not treated in the same way as national public representatives.  The organisations representing local councillors made representations to Senators and Deputies and some are represented in the Gallery.  They are also examining a scheme that would be appropriate and workable.</p> <p>The abolition of town councils saved &euro;5 million in direct payments to town councillors and &euro;45 million overall.  These savings should be used to improve the terms and conditions of the smaller number of local authority members and providing them with facilities such as secretarial supports.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.215" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#V01300"><p>I welcome the Minister of State.  I acknowledge the work done by the representative associations, the Association of Irish Local Government, AILG, and the Local Authority Members Association, LAMA.  The one word that springs to mind in this discussion is "frustration".  Everyone is extremely frustrated by the time it is taking to make progress on this urgent issue.  I speak with some authority on this matter having been a member of a local authority for more than 14 years.  The Minister of State was also a local authority member and it is past time that we grasped the nettle and gave councillors what they deserve.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Robbie Gallagher:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2471"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2471&amp;amp;pid=RobbieGallagher&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The Minister of State mentioned he will put together a review group to look at this particular issue and I have a number of questions in this regard.  I welcome the review group and it is important that local authority members are represented on it and that it would be chaired by a local authority member.  I also understand that aside from the Department of Housing, Planning and Local Government, the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform through the Minister, Deputy Donohoe, will be involved in it.  Will the Minister of State advise us as to the current position in this regard?  It is important a timeframe be set as to when the review group is meant to report back.  As the Minister of State is aware, the local elections are scheduled for June next year and this does not give us much time.  If we are to try to hold onto the elected members we have, we will have to get clarity on this issue because, as other Members have said, local authority members are walking away and we cannot afford to have this situation.  Local authority members are the first direct contact above all other ranks of representation because they are on the ground 24-7.  I would be delighted were the Minister of State to answer these few questions for us and give us some clarity on this issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.217" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#W00200"><p>We welcome the Minister of State and accept his good intentions.  Across the House, we are all prepared to act in unison.  We agreed this with the AILG and LAMA at the meeting in Buswell's not too long ago.  I agree with everything that has been said and the Minister of State accepts it also.  The system is a mishmash and needs resolution.  It needs to be brought to a head quickly and we want that job done now. The councillors are fed up with the system and we are equally fed up with it.  We depend on the Minister of State, in conjunction with the Minister, Deputy Donohoe, to proceed with the establishment of the proposed local reform remuneration group with an independent chair who has the required industrial relations experience.  I agree very much with the AILG and LAMA that we need a short timescale for the report to be finalised and produced.  Equally, it is important to note there has been a very low uptake among councillors of the &euro;5,000 vouched expenses.  Perhaps this is a clear indicator that councillors simply do not see the benefit to them because there is a limited scope to what they can spend the expenses on.  As I have said, we have spoken sufficiently on this and I understand the frustration all round.  We are all united and we are prepared to go forward from the House united.  We are very dependent on the Minister of State.  We know his good intentions and it is over to him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.218" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#W00300"><p>I echo what Senator Coghlan has said.  It is very much the principle of all parties working together on this.  I speak to councillors quite a lot, and they are fed up of receiving a succession of correspondence and email from practically every Member of the House about councillors' pay and conditions, stating they have made representations to the Minister and so on.  We all make representations to the Minister.  I have great time for this particular Minister of State and believe he is probably one of the most genuine people in Irish politics but ultimately, the Minister is the man with the power.  None of us here have the power.  What power do we have?  We have the power to vote against legislation and we can be disruptive but we do not want to do this because the citizens of the country are the people affected when that happens.  Moreover, it impedes legislation going through the House.  This is the power that is open to us.  We are in a situation where the people with the power are those in the Government.</p> <p>The case has been very well articulated.  We all have many examples of the length and breadth of the responsibilities and workload dealt with by councillors.  My old electoral area of north Clare is now known as the west Clare municipal district.  It starts down at the ferry in Killimer and goes right up to the Galway border.  One could not service that.  It is ridiculous and the Minister knows it too, which is why we are having a local government review.  This will come out in June and will have more manageable constituencies.</p> <p>Ultimately, the basic principle to which we all sign up is a fair day's work for a fair day's pay.  It is reasonable to suggest the vast majority of councillors are putting in a fair day's work but they are not getting a fair day's pay.  I know the Minister of State will respond, not today but on 24 April, and I hope that by then we will have some white smoke on this issue.  Whatever the outcome will be, will it be backdated to cover the period of this review?  If a payment is made, it should be a salary of &euro;25,000 or &euro;30,000.  The AILG has suggested something along the same lines.  Those for whom local authority membership is the primary principal occupation and a full-time job would pay the minimum rate of tax but if it is a second occupation, they would pay the higher rate of tax.  This would create an equilibrium in its own right.</p> <p>Ultimately, we should not be standing here talking about councillors' pay.  It is an issue we should not have to debate in the Seanad.  I encourage our colleagues in D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann to have a debate on councillors' pay because they have a role in this as well.  I do not hear very many of them standing up and fighting for councillors but when a general election is called, they will all be looking for them to go out canvassing.  I would like to see a similar debate in D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann and get the commitments of Deputies in this area.  Members of the Seanad obviously have a vested interest because councillors vote for Senators and that is logical.  The councillors have an absolute expectation that we will do the business for them as best we can and the vast majority of us do.  I believe D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann also has a vested interest in this because a properly functioning local government with active councillors is good for democracy.  It is also good for D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann.  I encourage the Minister of State to have a similar debate in the D&aacute;il where these issues can be articulated also.  I am looking forward to good news from the Minister of State because ultimately it will come, but I hope the good has not gone out of it by the time it does.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.219" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1382" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#W00400"><p>I echo what has been said.  I acknowledge the Minister of State's acknowledgement that there is an issue that needs to be addressed and that the impact of the revised payments to councillors had unintended consequences that need to be resolved.  Whatever the resolution, it is vital it is backdated to when the problem first emerged.  That would only be fair and correct.  It would happen in any other scenario and it is important that it would happen here also.</p> <p>We are speaking about an employment rights issue and individuals who give of their time for their local community but also for their local public service, which is the local council.  The role of councillors should not be denigrated in any way to be less important than the role played by any other official at management level in the county council or city council structure.  It is important this occurs.  We have been speaking in here but as Senators, we do not have the capacity to introduce a Bill that would place a financial burden on the State by increasing the pay of councillors.  We do not have that power.  If we did we would do it, but we do not have that power and let us be clear about it.  It is the Government that has the power to do this.  The best way to do it is, as has been proposed by the AILG and LAMA, the establishment at arm's length of an organisation that would look into the remuneration of local authority members.  Linked to this should be a re-evaluation of payment levels for all employees across the local government structure, including the chief executive officers.  We do not have to go too far to learn of the experience of other jurisdictions in establishing such commissions.  For example, there is an independent remuneration panel in Wales, and I have to hand a copy of its annual report.  It looks at the payment of councillors, which is higher than here.  It is independent.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2261"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2261&amp;amp;pid=BrianODomhnaill&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The chairman is independent, as are board members, and payment levels are provided to local authority members based on the public sector pay levels of officials.  That is what we should follow.  The same is evident in London regarding the remuneration of councillors.  In London, it is divided into five bands with the lower band starting at a level of payment in the region of &pound;15,000 to &pound;17,000.  It increases to a level of &pound;65,000 to &pound;90,000.  They obviously treat democracy with the respect it deserves.  We need to start doing the same and we need to stop listening to the media on this issue because if we do not, the people who will be disenfranchised will not be the councillors but the ordinary citizens because when the system is broken, people must ring up a public representative to get it fixed.  That is the most important aspect of our functioning democracy at the level closest to the citizen, which is the councillor.  One can look across the Atlantic to Canada, a jurisdiction with a local government structure similar to that in Ireland because our system is based on the British model, where they really value democracy.  Canada has independent commissions in each of their councils.  If one considers the independent council commission committee in Edmonton, I note average councillor pay is $93,000, which is around &euro;60,000.  An independent commission also operates in Deer Lake with the same level of remuneration.  In Vancouver, the minimum is $80,000.  There is lots of other information out there.  The template has been established.  Let us remove this from the politicians, get an independent chair and report back within a reasonable timeframe but let us make sure the findings are backdated to when the problem was first identified.  That is vitally important.  </p><p>The issue of councillors being obliged to attend conferences and meetings and sit on boards just to make up a living wage - it is not even a living wage when one breaks it down with all the hours - is not right or fair.  Councillors deserve a proper level of remuneration - a wage.  It is called a representational payment but it should be a salary and should provide for proper remuneration at a level that is comparable with other jurisdictions, our public sector and the chief executives in each local authority because they are protected by the trade union movement, while the councillors are not.  The average wage of a chief executive officer is well in excess of &euro;100,000.  Some are in receipt of &euro;150,000 to &euro;200,000.  Is their job more important?  Some might argue that it is but do they deal with the public on a daily basis 24-7, seven days a week?  No, they do not because they work nine to five and are protected by that.  I am not in any way denigrating the role of chief executives because it is very important but so too is the role of the councillor.  We need to get real and set the terms and conditions, establish the committee as soon as possible and make sure the chairperson of that committee has an independent ethos and a public understanding of the role of a councillor.  There should be an opportunity for the representative bodies - the AILG and LAMA - to feed into that system as well and provide evidence if the opportunity emerges.  I hope the Minister of State will deal with this as quickly as possible.  What level of engagement and sincerity is being extended from the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform on this issue?  Has it given the green light to the establishment of this commission?  If not, why not?  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.221" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#X00200"><p>It is 2.14 p.m.  Senator Dolan would have 16 seconds if he wanted to start.  Rather than having a 16-second contribution today, it is probably more sensible for him to start the next day.  We will resume on 24 April - I am not sure of the actual time - and Senator Dolan will be the first speaker on that day.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.  It must be adjourned at 2.15 p.m. and it is now 2.15 p.m.  That is the Order of Business that was agreed this morning by the House.  I raised it myself but it must be adjourned at 2.15 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.222" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#X00300">Appointment of Members of the Irish Human Rights and Equality Commission: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.223" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#X00400"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That Seanad &Eacute;ireann, noting that the Government on the 27 February, 2018, nominated Francis Conaty, Heydi Foster-Breslin, Salome Mbugua Henry, Caroline Fennell, Patrick Connolly, Tony Geoghegan and Colm O'Dwyer for appointment by the President to be members of the Irish Human Rights and Equality Commission, recommends, pursuant to section 12(3) and section 13(1)(<i>b</i>) of the Irish Human Rights and Equality Commission Act 2014, that Francis Conaty, Heydi Foster-Breslin, Salome Mbugua Henry, Caroline Fennell, Patrick Connolly, Tony Geoghegan and Colm O'Dwyer be appointed by the President to be members of the Commission, with effect from a date to be determined by the President, for a term of office of 5 years.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.224" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1277" speakername="David Stanton" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#X00500"><p>I thank the Seanad for the opportunity to make my remarks on this important motion today to recommend the appointment of seven commissioners to the Irish Human Rights and Equality Commission, IHREC.  The commission is Ireland's national human rights institution and also our national equality body.  The functions it serves in the protection and promotion of human rights and equality are core elements in the proper functioning of a democratic society.</p> <p>These appointments are significant for all of us.  The commissioners work in pursuit of an inclusive Ireland where human rights and equality are respected, protected and fulfilled for everybody everywhere.  The IHREC's mission is to build a fair and inclusive society that protects and promotes human rights and equality in Ireland.  I cannot overstate the importance of its work.  </p> <p>The IHREC was established as an independent statutory body by the Irish Human Rights and Equality Commission Act 2014.  Now in 2018, we see the commission really hitting its stride with a recent public human rights and equality awareness campaign underpinned by a public information service.  Significant progress has been made on the public sector duty raising awareness in public bodies of their legal obligation to eliminate discrimination, promote equality of opportunity and protect human rights.  Furthermore, the IHREC has a significant programme of research under way that has already seen publications in a range of key areas to support equality and human rights policy development.  This represents only a sample and snapshot of the important work undertaken by the commission.  </p> <p>We are fortunate in Ireland to have a human rights and equality commission with an "A" status accreditation from the International Coordinating Committee of National Human Rights Institutions.  This recognition underlines the commission's domestic and international standing and institutional independence.  It is because of the structural independence of the commission that we have this motion before us today.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy David Stanton:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1053"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1053&amp;amp;pid=DavidStanton&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Members of the commission are appointed by the President following the passage of a resolution in each House of the Oireachtas.  This safeguards the independence - the word appears again - of the commission and precludes any Government influence in the appointments process.</p><p>The 2014 Act sets out the appointments process.  It requires the Department of Justice and Equality to engage the Public Appointments Service to carry out the selection of the best available candidates.  The Department consulted with the Public Appointments Service in agreeing the selection criteria and process to be implemented.  The process took account of the skills needs identified by the commission and sought to ensure that the provisions of the 2014 Act were complied with.  The State boards process is followed in these circumstances with one notable exception, as provided for in the legislation.  Instead of providing the Minister with a list of suitable candidates to select from for appointment, the final selection was made by the Public Appointments Service.  The Public Appointments Service appointed a selection panel with no representative of the Department on either the shortlisting panel or the interview board.  The entire selection process, from the placing of the advertisement on the Public Appointments Service website to the final selection, was managed independently by the Public Appointments Service.  There was a high level of interest with a total of 149 applications.  Seven candidates were recommended for appointment.  I note that two of the seven selected served a previous term on the commission.</p><p>I doubt there can be any disagreement that the seven candidates recommended by the Public Appointments Service are eminently qualified for the role of commissioner.  They possess a broad range of skills required by the commission, an in-depth knowledge of matters connected with human rights and equality and bring a wealth of experience across multiple sectors.  It is important that membership of the commission is suitably diverse to broadly reflect the nature of Irish society.  This is a requirement under the 2014 Act, which also includes a provision to ensure an appropriate gender balance.  These are the types of issues that the Government considered when it accepted the recommendation of the Public Appointments Service to appoint the seven members.</p><p>It would be entirely remiss of me not to take this opportunity to pay tribute and express my sincere thanks to the outgoing commissioners for their hard work, dedication and in particular for the expertise and knowledge they contributed to the essential work of the commission in its implementation phase.  It is my privilege today to recommend the candidates to the House for appointment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.226" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#Y00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House.  I thank him for his outline of the appointments to the commission, which is important for the protection of Irish human rights and equality.  Much remains to be done to achieve the aims and objectives of the commission.  As the Minister of State pointed out, the inclusion of Patrick Connolly and others who have served in other areas, such as Caroline Fennell who served on the Irish Research Council, and Tony Geoghegan, who is chief executive of Merchants Quay Ireland, is welcome.  It is important to have such diversity of views and backgrounds.  We welcome the appointments and the ongoing role of the commission.  We will, of course, be looking at the broader debate on the work and recommendations of the commission at a later date.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.227" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#Y00300"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House.  I wish those who are set to be appointed to the Irish Human Rights and Equality Commission the best of luck.  I wish to use this opportunity to remind those involved that it is okay to rock the State boat and to criticise where fair criticism is required.  It is okay to hold the Government to account and call it out on its failures in the area of rights and equality.</p> <p>Rights and equality are fundamental pillars in any functioning forward thinking society that holds egalitarian values at its core.  Incidentally, rights and equality are at the centre of the debate around the current impasse at Stormont.  It is, therefore, integral that those who hold those positions acknowledge their influence and power and keep them to the forefront of their minds when partaking in the Irish Human Rights and Equality Commission or any other rights advocacy bodies.  I am confident that those entering the Irish Human Rights and Equality Commission in the coming weeks will do precisely that and that they are more than capable of doing so.</p> <p>I know the Minister of State has been sent certain documents.  I am unsure whether he or his officials are aware of the questions being raised and the perceived conflict of interest between the Public Appointments Service and the Irish Human Rights and Equality Commission.  I do not intend to go into the matter in depth or make individual accusations but I know the matter was raised in the D&aacute;il recently.  I am happy to give way for the Minister of State to respond if he so wishes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.228" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#Y00400"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Stanton, to the House.  He was Chairman of the Joint Committee on Justice, Defence and Equality when the issue of the Irish Human Rights and Equality Commission was discussed on many occasions.  I believe the commission is doing a good job.</p> <p>The country has an unrivalled reputation in championing human rights.  We are considered a neutral country.  Ambassadors and volunteers from Ireland have gone abroad to assist in conflict resolution over many decades.  The work carried out by the Defence Forces, including the Army, in peacekeeping illustrates this as does the work of the thousands of people who went to the Third World over many decades to try to promote human rights and to help people who were in challenging situations.</p> <p>It is appropriate that we have a human rights and equality authority completely above reproach.  The fact that neither the Government nor the Department of Justice and Equality has any hand, act or part in anything in terms of the selecting of the commissioners is relevant.  The Minister of State has quite rightly pointed this out in outlining the process from the placing of the advertisement right up to the appointment.  The list of candidates is not required to come before the Minister in shortlist form as with other State boards.</p> <p>Those involved have an important job to do.  I hope sometime we will be able to look at our country as a society that is completely equal and that respects human rights of all minority groups and all citizens.  The work that must be carried out by the Irish Human Rights and Equality Commission is immense and important.  I agree with Senator Warfield that the commission should not be afraid to challenge Government.  Challenging Government and those of us in the Oireachtas makes us do our job better.  Ultimately, the net beneficiaries will be the citizens and, in particular, those whose human rights may not have been protected and respected the way they should have been.</p> <p>I welcome this motion.  Perhaps at some stage, the Minister of State could come to the House for a more in-depth discussion on equality and human rights issues.  From a Fine Gael perspective, we are very happy with the work being done by the commission and we wish it well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.229" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1277" speakername="David Stanton" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#Y00500"><p>I thank Senators for their contributions and support for the motion.  I wish to emphasise one or two points.  The commission has A status accreditation from the Global Alliance for National Human Rights Institutions.  That is important and it includes the method of selection of commissioners.  Government has to be completely distant from the process; it must have nothing to do with it.  That is why the Public Appointments Service is involved.  As Senator Conway said, I was Chairman of the Joint Committee on Justice, Defence and Equality when the commission was established originally and that point was understood by everyone involved.</p> <p>The structure and independence of the commission is important.  There is no Government influence in the appointments process and those who the PAS nominates.  The service nominates seven people.  Today, both Houses are tabling a motion to enable the President to appoint them.  The Irish Human Rights and Equality Commission is completely and totally independent.  The commission has an important job to do under the Act.  The commission must also bear in mind the required skills needs.  There must be balance in this regard and it is up to the commission to identify the required skills.</p> <p>There was a high level of interest in the advertisement.  It was completely up to the Public Appointments Service to select the seven from the 149 applications submitted.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy David Stanton:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1053"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1053&amp;amp;pid=DavidStanton&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The Government had no hand, act or part in that.  The service nominated seven people.  I appreciate that it was probably a difficult job; I do not know that but that is my guess.  What we are doing today is accepting the seven who were nominated by the independent Public Appointments Service to go forward.</p><p>The commission has an important job to do.  As I mentioned earlier, there is also a public sector duty of raising awareness in public bodies of their legal obligation to eliminate discrimination, promote equality of opportunity and protect human rights.  The Irish Human Rights and Equality Commission is responsible for working not just with the Government but all State agencies and bodies.  It has important domestic and international standing, as well as institutional independence.  It has an "A" status accreditation from the International Coordinating Committee of National Institutions for the Promotion and Protection of Human Rights and would not have that accreditation unless it was completely independent and was seen to be independent.  The Government and these Houses acknowledge, respect and champion its independence.</p><p>I again thank the Senators for their comments on this important institution.  I wish the new appointees and the commission the best.  Incidentally, the commission has its own Vote, which also ensures its independence.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.231" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.232" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#Z00300"><p>When is it proposed to sit again?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.233" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018032900002#Z00400"><p>At 2.30 p.m. on Tuesday, 17 April 2018.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-29a.234" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>The Seanad adjourned at 2.30 p.m. until 2.30 p.m. on Tuesday, 17 April 2018.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>