<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Leas-Chathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.4" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#A00100">Gnó an tSeanaid - Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#A00200"><p>Maidin mhaith a chomhghleacaithe agus f&aacute;ilte romhaibh.  I have received notice from Senator Maria Byrne that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, she proposes to raise the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Justice to make a statement on the barriers facing non-fluent English speakers in reporting sexual and gender-based violence. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senators Se&aacute;n Kyne and Barry Ward of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Social Protection to make a statement on the measures being put in place to support Ukrainian refugees as they arrive in Ireland. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Garret Ahearn of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister of State for Heritage and Electoral Reform to amend the Wildlife Act 1976 to extend the period to burn vegetation from 1 March to April. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Martin Conway of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Health to carry out a review of the Shannondoc out-of-hours GP service. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Fiona O&rsquo;Loughlin of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Justice to make a statement on the document requirements for Ukrainian nationals entering Ireland. </blockquote> <p>Of the matters raised by the Senators suitable for discussion, I have selected Senators Maria Byrne, Kyne and Ward, Ahearn and Conway and they will be taken now.  Senator O'Loughlin has withdrawn her Commencement matter, which I had originally selected.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.7" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#A00300">Nithe i dtosach suíonna - Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.8" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#A00400">Victim Support Services</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1695" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#A00500"><p>I thank the Minister of State for taking this important matter.  I thank the Minister for Justice, Deputy McEntee, and the Minister of State for their work and commitment in this area.  So much has been done on gender-based violence, especially towards women.  I am grateful for all the work they have done and I am grateful that it is a priority.  It has been spoken about a great deal in both Houses in recent times.</p> <p>Senators will be aware that many victims of gender-based crime find it difficult to report it when something happens.  I have found this is especially true if there is a language barrier.  I have been working with a company in Limerick that worked with the Department of Justice when it was part of the EU inHERE project, on the basis of which it developed its continuous professional development, CPD, accredited training for interpreters.  So many interpreters are coming to Ireland.  With refugees coming here as well, we are going to have to depend so much on people being able to break down the language barrier.  While some of the refugees who will come here will have English, not all of them will.  As a result, the matter I raise is important.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Maria Byrne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2465"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2465&amp;amp;pid=MariaByrne&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=09"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> Women's Aid reported that calls from non-English speakers through its multi-language helpline increased by 90% in 2020 in comparison with 2019.  That is a big increase.  Of all of the minority groups who sought help from Women's Aid, 93% were migrant women, which is a very high number.  Apart from Women's Aid, many other Irish organisations deal with non-native English speakers in the context of sexual violence.</p><p>I look forward to hearing what the Minister of State has to say.  This is an issue which needs to be highlighted more.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1618" speakername="James Browne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#B00200"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this important matter regarding the commitment relating to the barriers facing non-fluent English speakers reporting sexual or gender-based violence.  The Senator has been very much to the forefront on this matter, not only in this Chamber but also behind the scenes in working with the Department of Justice, the Minister, Deputy McEntee, and other Departments.  The Minister is determined to do everything she can to combat all forms of domestic, sexual and gender-based violence.  This has been a priority area for the Minister since taking up this post and she has the full support of the Government.</p> <p>Becoming the victim of any kind of crime can be a deeply traumatic experience.  This is especially true in the context of offences linked to domestic, sexual and gender-based violence.  It can be incredibly daunting to enter a Garda station or criminal court for the first time.  This can be intensified for the members of marginalised communities, particularly when barriers such as language and-or feelings of disenfranchisement may exist.  The Department of Justice is working on a number of initiatives to support victims in order that when they engage with the system, they will know what to expect, what their legally enforceable rights are and what supports are available at every step in the process.  Language or any other barrier should not get in the way of this.</p> <p>The Department is in the process of developing actions to reach all communities in Ireland, including translating the posters and leaflets used to raise awareness of rights under the Criminal Justice (Victims of Crime) Act 2017 into other languages commonly spoken among Ireland's immigrant communities.  This year, the Department will launch two campaigns, in partnership with the Dormant Accounts Fund, expanding awareness-raising activities of victims' rights and on the topic of consent to reach marginalised communities.  The Department will do this by working with community organisations to adapt various assets and resources in culturally appropriate ways.  I know An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na is very aware of the difficulty language barriers can present when someone is seeking justice.  If someone who is not fluent in English or Irish presents to garda&iacute;, a free interpreter service will be provided in order that the person will receive the same quality of service, as far as possible, as any other victim of crime.  An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na's victim information booklet is currently available in 39 different languages, as well as in braille and audio versions.  The Legal Aid Board provides a free legal advice service to victims of human trafficking and complainants in rape and certain sexual assault cases, which can include interpretative services where required.  Interpretation is provided in criminal cases if directed by the court.  The Department of Justice has also put in place victims of domestic violence immigration guidelines.  The guidelines rightly state that no one should have to suffer domestic violence and recognise that migrants may have additional vulnerability in this area, as the perpetrator may threaten a victim with the loss of their status if they report the abuse.</p> <p>Support services also do incredible work in trying to support people whose first language is not English.  Women's Aid, which runs the national domestic violence helpline, offers a telephone interpretation service facility that covers 200 languages for callers needing support in their own language.  The Dublin Rape Crisis Centre provides similar on its national sexual violence helpline.</p> <p>I thank the Senator for raising this important topic and I reassure her that it is a focus for the Government.  While there are services in place to support non-fluent English speakers in reporting domestic, sexual and gender-based violence, the Minister is committed to increasing the supports available to better support this particularly vulnerable group.  At the end of last year, on foot of a mapping exercise carried out by the Department, the Minister made additional funding available to 18 organisations that support victims of domestic and sexual violence.  This was provided to address gaps identified both in terms of the geographical availability of services and in services provided for specific categories of victims.  The Department will be keeping this under review and will fill any future gaps identified in order that all victims in every part of the country will receive the supports they need to access the justice they deserve.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1695" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#B00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State for that detailed response.  Translit in Limerick provides a training course for many interpreters in the context of the sensitive nature of this issue, and it is my understanding that it is the only company that does training in this regard.  The Minister of State indicated that the Department is keeping this matter under review and is looking at different ideas.  There are organisations like Women's Aid, the Mid-West Rape Crisis Centre and many others to which women can turn for help.  However, if people are to be interpreters, they need training, which is something the Minister of State might take back to the Minister.  It is such a sensitive area that interpreters have to be taught how to handle it in a very sensitive way in order to make people feel comfortable about reporting.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1618" speakername="James Browne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#B00400"><p>I again thank the Senator for raising this very important matter.  I hear her point in regard to how sensitive these issues are.  Those dealing with very vulnerable people need to understand how to deal with those situations in a very sensitive manner.</p> <p>As the Senator will be aware, the Minister is leading on the development of a new whole-of-government strategy to combat domestic, sexual and gender-based violence.  The goal of the strategy is zero tolerance for violence against women, and it recognises that added vulnerability of certain groups of women, including women in marginalised communities and migrant women.  Separately, the Minister continues to work to implement all 52 recommendations of the O'Malley review, which looked at the journey a victim faces from the moment a crime is committed against them, to the initial reporting of the offence and right through to the end of any court proceedings and beyond.  Their implementation will make our criminal justice system one that protects and supports vulnerable victims.</p> <p>These initiatives include a campaign to raise awareness of the rights afforded to people under the victims of crime Act of 2017.  This will include information being translated into a number of languages outside Irish and English that are commonly spoken in Ireland.  The Department of Justice will soon be inviting partners to a newly established victims forum for State, social and community groups, including groups working for and representative of marginalised communities.  The University of Limerick has been tasked with developing the framework for the operation and training of intermediaries who will partially facilitate communication with vulnerable people in the justice system in order to provide the best evidence possible.  A nationwide roll-out of the divisional protective service units has been completed to ensure victims of sexual violence are met with respect, professionalism and compassion.</p> <p>I again thank the Senator for raising this important topic.  I reassure her that this is a priority focus for the Government.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.14" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#B00450">Foreign Conflicts</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1671" speakername="Erin McGreehan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#B00500"><p>Senators Se&aacute;n Kyne and Barry Ward are sharing time.  I call Senator Kyne.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1665" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#B00600"><p>I thank the office of the Cathaoirleach for choosing this very important matter for debate.  I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Malcolm Noonan.</p> <p>We see before our eyes the tragedy unfolding across Ukraine, where, a fortnight ago, people were living their lives, perhaps in trepidation and fear, but as normally as possible in their own country.  Now, we see people leaving in their thousands and becoming refugees across Europe, including here in Ireland.  Some 2,200 Ukrainians have arrived since the visa requirement was lifted on 25 February, many of them to come to live with family who are already in Ireland.  It is important that the Irish State welcomes them, supports them and keeps them safe for as long as they need to be here.  It is fair to say that many of them would wish to go home to their own country eventually and, hopefully, that can be soon, if it is safe to do so and if the war ends in a timely fashion.</p> <p>T&aacute; spiorad agus flaithi&uacute;lacht mhuintir na h&Eacute;ireann le feice&aacute;il agus iad ag cur c&uacute;naimh agus maoinithe ar f&aacute;il chun cabhr&uacute; leis an gCros Dhearg agus le gn&iacute;omhaireachta&iacute; eile san &Uacute;cr&aacute;in.  Is iontach an rud &eacute; tairiscint&iacute; agus sp&eacute;is na ndaoine ar fud na t&iacute;re l&oacute;ist&iacute;n a chur ar f&aacute;il ina dtithe f&eacute;in ach n&iacute; haon ionadh &eacute;.  Tr&eacute;asla&iacute;m leis an gceannaireacht &oacute;n Rialtas agus &oacute;n Aontas Eorpach ar an trag&oacute;id seo san &Uacute;cr&aacute;in.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Se&aacute;n Kyne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2343"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2343&amp;amp;pid=SeanKyne&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=09"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->T&aacute; daoine a bh&iacute; ina gc&oacute;na&iacute; ina dt&iacute;r f&eacute;in coic&iacute;s &oacute; shin anois ina dteifigh trasna na hEorpa.  Is &eacute; an rud is m&oacute; a theasta&iacute;tear anois n&aacute; s&aacute;bh&aacute;ilteacht do na daoine seo, go h&aacute;irithe mn&aacute; agus p&aacute;ist&iacute; agus na fir f&aacute;gtha ag troid ar son na h&Uacute;cr&aacute;ine.</p><p>The Government is working hard to ensure that people get personal public service, PPS, numbers, rights to work and so on.  It is important that we see the generosity of spirit of Irish people in pledging their support for families.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" speakername="Barry Ward" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#C00200"><p>Gabhaim bu&iacute;ochas leis an gCathaoirleach Gn&iacute;omhach agus cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it.  T&aacute; an br&oacute;d orm as an m&eacute;id at&aacute; &aacute; dh&eacute;anamh ag Rialtas na h&Eacute;ireann faoi l&aacute;thair.  Is uaf&aacute;sach na heachtra&iacute; at&aacute; ar si&uacute;l san &Uacute;cr&aacute;in.  T&aacute;imid br&oacute;d&uacute;il as an m&eacute;id at&aacute; &aacute; dh&eacute;anamh ag an bpobal, ag muintir na h&Eacute;ireann, ar son muintir na h&Uacute;cr&aacute;ine.  Sular th&aacute;inig m&eacute; anseo, bh&iacute; m&eacute; ag caint le hambasad&oacute;ir na h&Uacute;cr&aacute;ine, a bh&iacute; anseo i dTeach Laighean.  Bh&iacute;omar ag iarraidh rud a dh&eacute;anamh le Cros Dhearg na h&Eacute;ireann chun cabhr&uacute;.  Bh&iacute; s&iacute; ag labhairt linn faoi na heachtra&iacute; at&aacute; ar si&uacute;l faoi l&aacute;thair.  Mar a d&uacute;irt m&eacute;, t&aacute;im br&oacute;d&uacute;il as an m&eacute;id at&aacute; a dh&eacute;anamh againn.</p> <p>As much as we can do, it is very important.  All of us support what the Government is doing.  These strong measures will hopefully yield strong results.  It will not solve the problem but it will help the people who come to Ireland.  The aid that is coming through here will also help the people in Ukraine.  Earlier, the Irish Red Cross told us that it anticipates raising &euro;20 million for Ukraine.  It is an extraordinary amount.  It is an extraordinary crisis.</p> <p>I hope the Minister of State can allay our fears that we can cope with the people who are coming here and that, as Senator Kyne said, we will put in place all the things needed to support those people to ensure that they can come here and for the time that they are here, continue their lives in as normal a way as possible however awful and difficult it might be for them.  I hope we will put at their disposal the facilities of the State the same as they would be available to any European Union citizen.</p> <p>I welcome the announcements already made in relation to PPS numbers, health provision and education provision.  Can the Minister of State give us any greater detail on what will be available to them?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1512" speakername="Malcolm Noonan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#C00300"><p>Gabhaim bu&iacute;ochas leis an gCathaoirleach Gn&iacute;omhach agus leis na Seanad&oacute;ir&iacute;.</p> <p>Like Senator Ward, I share that pride that we have in the response of the Irish people and the Government.  It has been really touching.  We attended an event this morning with the Ukrainian ambassador and ambassadors of other countries and it was chilling to hear the testimonies coming out of Ukraine at present.  It is an unjustifiable war; an attack on a sovereign state.  Our thoughts and prayers are with those fleeing the war and those who are caught up in it because, as the former Minister, Mr. Pat Carey, said this morning, it looks like it could be a protracted war.  We will have to continue these supports.</p> <p>In Ireland, we are responding.  I spoke to the Minister of State at the Department of Justice, Deputy James Browne, about driving licences and this morning, Deputy &Oacute; Cathasaigh raised the issue of education in terms of integrating into the education system.  There is a whole-of-government response happening.  We are having to think on our feet.  We are having to act quickly and adapt.  We can take great collective pride in the fact that we are responding rapidly to what is a fast-moving and truly tragic situation.</p> <p>On 4 March 2022, the European Council adopted unanimously the implementing decision regarding the temporary protection directive due to the mass influx of persons fleeing Ukraine as a consequence of this war.  This will allow Ukrainian citizens and others fleeing Ukraine to avail of supports throughout the EU.  I want to emphasise to the House that people arriving from Ukraine have been granted the status to avail of income supports from the Department of Social Protection under the EU temporary protection directive.</p> <p>The Minister for Social Protection, Deputy Humphreys, and her officials have an excellent record in reacting quickly and appropriately to emergency situations and this was clear from the way they responded to provide emergency income throughout the pandemic.</p> <p>The immediate priority for the Department of Social Protection will be the allocation of personal public service numbers, PPSNs, and the provision of immediate financial supports.  A fast-track approach in processing these supports will include a simplified decision-making process and quick processing of PPSNs to allow access to public services that will be provided to people arriving here.</p> <p>People will be eligible for financial support initially under the supplementary welfare allowance scheme.  Under the temporary protection directive, Ukrainian citizens and others fleeing the war will satisfy the habitual residence condition, HRC, and the relevant associated means test.</p> <p>The aim of the Minister, Deputy Humphreys, and that of her Department is to ensure that applications for supplementary welfare are processed as quickly and efficiently as possible to provide immediate financial assistance to these people.  The Department of Social Protection will also arrange for payments such as child benefit to be made within a very short period.</p> <p>The Department of Social Protection is working closely with the Department of Justice, which is responsible for providing such people with letters or certificates confirming that they are covered by the EU directive.  From today, officials from both Departments will be based in Dublin Airport to meet people arriving from Ukraine and they will ensure that temporary protection permission letters and PPSNs are allocated, and the appropriate financial supports are provided.  The Department of Children, Equality, Disability, Integration and Youth will lead on the provision of accommodation for those arriving in Ireland.  All Departments will keep this position under regular review, in particular, to provide for people entering through other airports or ports.  As the Senators will be aware, the Department of Social Protection has a network of Intreo offices around the country and they will be used to help people from Ukraine during their stay in this country.  It could be a short period.  It could be a much longer period.  We do not know this yet.</p> <p>For those people who have already arrived in Ireland, they will be invited into Intreo offices so that they can be provided with a PPSN number and the appropriate financial supports.  The Department is putting arrangements in place to provide information in the English, Ukrainian and Russian languages.</p> <p>I know that the people of Ireland will support these people as they settle into our country, the generosity has already been quite overwhelming, and that they can help to rebuild their lives in our country.  It is something that we are good at.  It is something we do well constantly in time of crisis.  We proved this during the Covid pandemic.  Certainly, the Irish people will not be found wanting on this occasion as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1665" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#C00400"><p>I thank the Minister of State for the comprehensive response.  It is quite clear that the Government is doing all it can.  It is acting proactively and quickly.</p> <p>Of course, we are dealing with vulnerable people who have been through a trauma, who are leaving family and loved ones behind and who have seen their lives destroyed.  They are particularly vulnerable to individuals who may not have their best interests at heart.  That was evident in previous situations in this country in the past when people arrived here during the 2000s.  It is important that there is a port of call - a first stop-off for people at the airports - in order that they can get that assistance and be told what is available for them and the supports that are put in place, and they have somewhere to go such as the Intreo offices.</p> <p>The generosity of spirit of the Irish people is coming to the fore in terms of providing assistance.  I am confident that will continue over the coming months and, if needs be, depending on how long this tragedy and this awful war lasts, years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" speakername="Barry Ward" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#C00500"><p>Ba mhaith liom a r&aacute; go bhfuil an-mhuin&iacute;n agam de bharr an mh&eacute;id at&aacute; r&aacute;ite ag an Aire St&aacute;it.</p> <p>The description of a whole-of-government response is tremendously important.  I welcome commitments the Minister of State made to having people in the airports available to meet people as they come off planes because, as has been said already, they will be in a distraught condition in no uncertain terms.</p> <p>I hope that we can extend that famous c&eacute;ad m&iacute;le f&aacute;ilte to them in every respect and accommodate them in every way that we can as they come here.  It is the least that we can do.  It is the least that we would expect to be done for us if the shoe were on the other foot.  I welcome the moves and I look forward to delivery of those commitments from the Government.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1512" speakername="Malcolm Noonan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#C00600"><p>I, again, thank both Senators for raising this.  It is important we continue to respond, as I said, as this evolves.</p> <p>We are in a wartime scenario.  As a State, we are putting in place measures to ensure that people of Ukraine who are seeking refuge here will receive all the support they require.  They will need psychological and other supports as well and this is something we have to respond to.</p> <p>I acknowledge the important role that is being played by the NGO sector in responding to this humanitarian crisis.  They will play a significant role in the coming months to provide supports across a range of areas for those needing assistance.  The Irish Red Cross has stepped in to play a key role.  I am deeply grateful to it, as we saw this morning with Mr. Pat Carey, as well as the fantastic response of the Irish League of Credit Unions.</p> <p>The Department of Social Protection will work with the NGOs in assisting Ukrainians who are arriving here to ensure that those who require assistance from the Department will get it.  The Department is already working with some of the NGOs, such as Crosscare, and will continue to do so in the weeks and months ahead.</p> <p>I thank both Senators for raising this.  I am overwhelmed by what has happened within a very short period of time.  Within two weeks, due to the financial support, we see convoys leaving Ireland at present.  Twenty million euro was the figure Mr. Carey mentioned this morning from the Irish Red Cross.  That is phenomenal generosity.  The Government will not be found wanting either.  As this crisis will unfortunately deepen, we will continue to respond in a compassionate and humanitarian way.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1671" speakername="Erin McGreehan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#D00100"><p>Our third matter is from Senator Ahearn.  I am very interested to hear the reply to this one.  I thank the Senator for raising it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1629" speakername="Garret Ahearn" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#D00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for coming to the House to take this important matter.  This is slightly off topic, if the Chair will allow me, but I wish to I thank him for the announcement this week on the built heritage investment scheme.  He has given &euro;10,000 to Knocklofty House in my parish.  He met the group Save Knocklofty House.  He committed to supporting it and he has now done that.  On behalf of the people involved, who are very grateful, they wanted me to thank the Minister of State for supporting them.  This will go a long way to protecting that building.  The Minister of State might be able to expand on it if there are measures he can take in the future to support it.  I thank him for that.</p> <p>I visited the Ardfinnan-Ballybacon-Grange-Newcastle, ABGN, Gun Club recently on top of the beautiful Knockmealdown Mountains.  I met with a number of its members in regard to heather mulching activities on the mountain.  The club's red grouse conservation project is considered vital work by the club's members, of whom there are nearly 100.  Since its inception in 2004, red grouse numbers have increased by more than 30%.  The club's honorary treasurer, Mr. Pat O'Sullivan, and its members believe that ensuring young heather is available to the grouse is probably the most impactful work they can do in order to ensure the grouse's successful breeding and continued presence on our lands.</p> <p>The preferred method of clearing old heather for new is that of controlled burning, an activity in which ABGN Gun Club has invested, for more than 18 years, a huge amount of its time and resources with great success.  Club members' success has generated much interest over the years, and they have hosted representatives of the National Parks and Wildlife Service, Teagasc and the Irish Red Grouse Association on the mountain to witness the work they have done.</p> <p>While they have had success in increasing the grouse population, the work is not without its challenges.  Strip burning of heather to provide suitable habitat in terms of food and shelter for grouse to flourish is highly weather dependent.  Since 2014, the club has not been able to undertake a burn due to the weather at weekends, the time at which members are mostly available to do this work because it is voluntary.  It is for this reason that the club members have experimented with other heather management techniques.  These techniques are less susceptible to disruption due to the weather but are, unfortunately, much less effective in providing a suitable habitat for grouse when compared with controlled burning.  It is also very expensive.  The machine they got, which I saw last week, cost &euro;3,000.  There is a great guy, Richie Long, who does it and is doing great work, but it is expensive and they have to cover the bill for that.</p> <p>The current window for burning, 1 September to 28 February, is unduly restrictive, particularly when compared with our EU neighbours, whose windows extend to 15 April.  A similar window here, or the ability to apply and be granted a derogation for conservation purposes, would greatly aid the voluntary work they do on the mountain.  As per the Wildlife Act 1976, and the amendment made to the Act in 2000, it is not permissible to burn vegetation between 1 March and 31 August.  The window to burn is between September and February but, in reality, it is only after Christmas that burning is recommended.  There are a number of reasons for this.  If the summer is good, the peat under the heather burns too easily, which is something one never wants.  The heat of the burn helps dormant seeds to germinate.  If this is done before Christmas, the seeds are open for too long and succumb to harsh weather as winter progresses.  A heavy snow over winter will cover all but the tallest heather, reducing the food available to the grouse.  As a result, it is better to wait until the snows have passed, which is normally in January or February.  Consequently, there are only a number of weeks during which this work can be done.  If there is weather like we have had in recent weeks with storms coming through, those involved really do not get any time to do this.  They can only volunteer to do the work at weekends and can only do it in January and February.  They are constrained in the context of time.  I am interested in the Minister of State's response to see if there is something the Government can do to help them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1512" speakername="Malcolm Noonan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#D00300"><p>I will come back to the Senator on Knocklofty House in my summary.</p> <p>In the context of the matter before us, I met with a number of gun clubs, the National Association of Regional Game Councils, NARGC, and other organisations involved that are representing the gun clubs.  I recognise the important role they play in conservation, particularly of the red grouse, a very important species.</p> <p>It has long been a common agricultural practice in Ireland to occasionally burn vegetation growing on uncultivated land, especially on upland farms.  Much of the vegetation burned comprises gorse and mature heather.  Light burning can remove old growth and, as the Senator said, stimulate new growth.  The aim of such burning is to improve grazing and access for livestock.  Fire was also often used in the past to dispose of waste arising from hedge and tree cutting.  The burning of such dead vegetation as waste is regulated by laws concerned with air quality rather than with wildlife protection, and such law is not the responsibility of the Department of Housing, Local Government and Heritage.</p> <p>The first Wildlife Act was enacted in 1976.  Section 40 of the Act prohibits the burning of "vegetation growing on any land not then cultivated or in course of cultivation for agriculture or forestry" during the period beginning 15 April and ending 31 August.  Subsequently, it was noted that birds began to nest earlier than before.  Accordingly, the Wildlife (Amendment) Act 2000 restricted period to begin on 1 March.  It also removed the wording "or in course of cultivation for agriculture or forestry".</p> <p>The dates of the restricted period for the burning of living vegetation were reconsidered in 2018 and this led to the enactment of the Heritage Act 2018.  Section 7(1) of the Act empowered the Minister with responsibility for natural heritage to make regulations that could allow the burning of vegetation during the month of March "in such part or parts of the State as specified in the regulations", notwithstanding section 40 of the Wildlife Act 1976.  No regulations were made on foot of that power.  Section 7(4)(a) of the 2018 Act provides that section 7 would expire two years after the enactment date unless continued by a resolution by each House of the Oireachtas.  As no such resolution was passed, section 7 of the 2018 Act expired on 17 July 2020.  The position now is that there is no provision allowing for the alteration of the dates of the restricted period as set out in the Wildlife Act 1976, as amended.  Any such changes would require an amendment to the Wildlife Act 1976.  However, it is my intention to review and strengthen our wildlife laws, including the Wildlife Act 1976.</p> <p>On the issue of burning living vegetation, while I am aware of the arguments for and against a change of dates, I have no plans at present to propose any change to the statutory dates.  I recommend that all stakeholders involved should establish a forum, which I mentioned previously.  It might be for the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine to lead on.  It is important that stakeholders, such as those involved in hunting, landowners, upland-hill farmers, fire services, etc. come together in a forum where these matters could be teased out further.  It is critically important that we have a broader conversation.  I do see a conservation role here, but I encourage the setting up of an initiative that would bring stakeholders together under some kind of a task force that could look at upland burning and its role in the management of our hills and uplands.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1629" speakername="Garret Ahearn" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#D00400"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his response . I agree with him.  The Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine should play a greater role in this.  The Irish Farmers Association, IFA, has taken this onboard in Tipperary.  We have very good members in the gun club, including Pat O'Sullivan, who I mentioned earlier, Robert Phelan and Brendan McGill.  There are almost 100 members and they do incredible and fantastic work.  If a body is set up, perhaps the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine would take a role.  The amendment of 2000 was on the back of research done which showed that birds were nesting earlier than before, and that was why the date was put back.  There is certainly a strong argument being made by the group and the IFA that birds nesting in 2022 are nesting later than they did in 2000.  That should be looked at as part of the review to see if that is the case.  If it is the case, perhaps something could be done on the back of it.</p> <p>I thank the Minister of State for his response.  I agree with and would be supportive of the setting up of such a forum.  I know the ABGN Gun Club would support that as well, because its members are best placed compared with anyone else to look after that land.  They know it well and they love it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1671" speakername="Erin McGreehan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#D00500"><p>I will add my tuppence worth in respect of the Cooley Mountains and the Cooley uplands farmers association, about which I have spoken to the Minister of State.  We need an upland management programme that deals with invasive species, the protection of the heathers and the beauty of the biodiversity that exists.  We have a great resource and we are not managing it correctly.  I welcome this Commencement matter.  The answer to it was great.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1512" speakername="Malcolm Noonan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#E00100"><p>I welcome both comments.  I was in the Cooley Mountains last week with an upland farmer.  I met the Brandon Hill farmers and people involved in the Blackstairs EIP, European Innovation Partnership, project; they are fantastic people doing really important work.  They need to be supported to do that.  An initiative like this would be able to tease out all those issues and have a really good conversation on the best way to manage our uplands in a sustainable way.  I would suggest that perhaps the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine would be a more appropriate lead.  Certainly, we would play our part in such an initiative but it is critically important.  These people are volunteers and they do important conservation work.  We would like to support them in that way.</p> <p>To return to Knocklofty, I am delighted that the built heritage investment scheme was able to support that.  I would encourage the stakeholders involved in Knocklofty to look at our grant schemes and to look at a longer-term conservation plan for the project.  The Department has really good grant schemes and if initiative is shown around a long-term strategy for Knocklofty I do not think any of us will be found wanting in support for having such an important built conservation project on the books. </p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.29" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#E00200">General Practitioner Services</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#E00300"><p>I welcome the Minister of State back to the House and thank her for taking this Commencement matter.  Shannondoc is a community healthcare service, a co-operative of doctors as it were, in the mid-west region to provide out-of-hours service.  We can recall how years ago, doctors were on call all the time.  It could be 6 p.m. or 8 p.m. it did not matter; doctors were still on call.  In order to give doctors a quality of life and to improve the quality of service, and to ensure that there was a service, the doctors came together and created Shannondoc.  That has been emulated around the country.  To be fair, the Governments stood up to the plate and did provide resources to support the community out-of-hours doctors initiatives around the country.  However, while in some areas they have worked extremely well, in others they have been average or extremely poor.</p> <p>The experience of Shannondoc in my area has been mixed.  The doctors who work in it when they are available are very committed and do a very good job.  They can take the pressure off our emergency departments.  The problem is that the Shannondoc service has been consolidated and it has been curtailed and cut back to such a degree that there are real challenges to the provision of services.  There was a time when there was a Shannondoc facility just outside the towns of Ennistymon and of Kilrush and in other areas.  However that has been consolidated and I believe that Miltown Malbay is the only facility that Shannondoc is providing in west Clare.  That is a challenge.</p> <p>There has been Covid and other things but the Minister of State will be very aware of the enormous challenges to the emergency department in University Hospital Limerick, UHL.  It is the most overcrowded emergency department in the country.  It regularly has 90 to 100 people on trolleys.  Many, or at least some of them could be diverted from hospital if they were to present to a Shannondoc-type facility.  We have minor incident clinics in places such as Ennis and Nenagh and so on but they close at 8 p.m.  If somebody is injured after 8 p.m., it may not be life threatening but if it is something the person is concerned about, in the absence of a Shannondoc facility his or her natural reaction is to go to the emergency department in UHL.  That is adding to the numbers.  I know that a review of the Shannondoc out-of-hours service has been committed to.  I also understand that there may be a national review on the out-of-hours service.  The point is about whether we believe in primary care and in trying to care for people within their community as a first response.  It may be that people need to attend an emergency department or hospital but the people at primary care level can make the decision that their care must be escalated but in many cases, they can deal with the injury at local level.  The out-of-hours doctor service is a critical component of such a service.  When someone is injured late at night, they can panic and worry.  They may be over-panicked or worried.  The out-of-hours doctor service is one which can give them reassurance and provide necessary medical interventions and maybe calm the situation, ensuring that people do not present at the emergency department's front door in Limerick.  We want to avoid that where possible.  </p> <p>Is the review happening or has it happened?  If not, when will it happen and what is the timeline for a report and recommendations for how we can improve the out-of-hours GP service?  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1614" speakername="Mary Butler" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#E00400"><p>I thank Senator Conway for raising this issue as GP out-of-hour co-operatives are essential to the delivery of primary care health services.  I thank the Senator for continuing to raise health issues in his own area in a constructive way.</p> <p>As he will be aware, GPs are required under the General Medical Services scheme to make suitable arrangements to enable contact to be made with them, or a locum or deputy, for emergencies outside of normal practice hours.  Most GPs meet this obligation through GP out-of-hours co-operatives that facilitate the provision of GP services outside of normal surgery hours.</p> <p>Shannondoc out-of-hours co-operative provides urgent GP services to patients in the mid-west region, including Limerick, north Tipperary and Clare.  While GP out-of-hours co-operatives are private entities, the HSE provides substantial funding to support co-operatives through service level agreements covering a wide range of costs.  Last year, the  HSE provided over &euro;5 million in funding for Shannondoc GP out-of-hours co-operative.</p> <p>The HSE maintains regular contact with the co-operatives to help optimise out-of-hour service levels.  Even greater engagement was undertaken to ensure that the services continued to provide the supports needed by local communities during the Covid pandemic.  Since the emergence of the Covid-19 virus, the HSE provided out-of-hours co-operatives with a support grant to ensure continuity of care.  Funding for Shannondoc was increased to over &euro;6.8 million in 2020, including increased funding due to the pandemic.</p> <p>Where there is increased demand in certain areas, Shannondoc can provide support from other treatment centres, to ensure services are provided where needed most.  The service is demand led, and the HSE has advised that Shannondoc has continued to meet the targets for urgent and routine calls set out under its service level agreement.  More generally, the Government is committed to increasing the number of GPs working nationwide and therefore improving access to GP and GP out-of-hours services across the country.</p> <p>Under the 2019 agreement, investment in general practice is to increase by 40% between 2019 and 2023.  Expenditure has already been increased to date by &euro;206.6 million annually, increasing to &euro;211.6 million per annum next year when the agreement is fully rolled out.  This provides for significant increases in capitation fees for participating GPs, as well as new fees and subsidies for additional services.</p> <p>The agreement also provides for improvements to maternity and paternity leave arrangements, introduces a &euro;2 million support fund for GPs in areas of urban deprivation and increases the existing support funding for rural GP practices.  The increased investment provided will increase the number of GPs working in the State and will help sustain general practice nationwide, both GP practices and out-of-hour services.   The positive impact of the measures undertaken by the Government is evident from the increasing numbers of entrants to GP training, from 120 in 2009 to 233 trainees enrolled last year and 258 places will be made available this year.  That is something I know everyone will welcome.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Mary Butler:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2445"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2445&amp;amp;pid=MaryButler&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=09"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> The 2019 GP agreement includes a commitment to undertake a strategic review of GP services to examine how best to ensure the sustainable provision of those services into the future.  The sustainability of services is what we all want.  The review will encompass a broad range of issues, including examining how best to provide for GP out-of-hours care, and will include consultations with relevant key stakeholders. The Department of Health is engaged in the preparatory work for the review which, once completed, will inform future contractual changes.  I am sure the Senator will agree that over the past two years, between Covid and the cyberattack, a lot of time was lost.  This review is very important and is a commitment under the 2019 agreement with GPs.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#F00200"><p>I again thank the Minister of State for coming to the Chamber with a logical answer to an important question.  Of course, Covid has been a problem and much healthcare ended up being stalled because of it.  Progress, and the incremental progress we like to see, has been challenged.   The problem with Shannondoc is that on many occasions there has been no cover.  That was simply down to the fact that GPs could not be got and were not available, as was the case for locums and so on.  That is always a problem because the public need to have confidence that once GPs sign off on their practices, surgeries and so on, the Shannondoc out-of-hours co-operative service will kick in.</p> <p>A review is good, and it should happen because it will consider the lessons where things have been done right and identify the gaps where improvements can be made.  I see a review as positive and a way of incrementally improving the service as opposed to anything negative, or something the HSE or those in the services should be concerned about.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1614" speakername="Mary Butler" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#F00300"><p>I agree with the Senator that a review is a good thing.  The provision of out-of-hours GP services will be examined as part of a wider strategic review of general practice for which preparatory work has commenced this year.  That is welcome.  I note the Senator's point that there have been situations where cover has not always been available.  The agreement provides an initial &euro;2 million support fund for GPs in areas of urban deprivation and increases the existing support funding for rural GP practices.  The improvements to maternity and paternity leave arrangements are also very important for practices where there might only be one doctor.  It can be very challenging if they are on maternity leave or, for example, they are out sick and it is difficult to get a locum.  We await the results of the review with interest.  I again thank the Senator for raising the matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.35" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar fionra&iacute; ar 11.23 a.m. agus cuireadh t&uacute;s leis ar&iacute;s ar 11.30 a.m.

Sitting suspended at 11.23 a.m. and resumed at 11.30 a.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.36" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#G00100">An tOrd Gnó - Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#G00300"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, statements to mark International Women's Day 2022, to be taken at 12.45 p.m. and to conclude at 2.15 p.m., with the opening contribution of the Minister not to exceed ten minutes and those of all Senators not to exceed six minutes, with the Minister to be given no less than ten minutes to reply to the debate; No. 2, statements on brain health and dementia, to be taken at 2.15 p.m. and to conclude at 3.45 p.m., with the opening contribution of the Minister not to exceed eight minutes, those of group spokespersons not to exceed six minutes and those of all other Senators not to exceed five minutes, with the Minister to be given no less than eight minutes to reply to the debate; No. 3, r&aacute;it&eacute;is maidir le Seachtain na Gaeilge, to be taken at 6.15 p.m. and to conclude at 7 p.m., with the opening statement of the Minister not to exceed five minutes, the contributions of all Senators not to exceed five minutes, with the Minister to be given no less than five minutes to reply to the debate; and No. 4, Merchant Shipping (Investigation of Marine Casualties) (Amendment) Bill 2021 - Second Stage, to be taken at 7 p.m., with the opening contribution of the Minister not to exceed ten minutes, those of group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes and those of all other Senators not to exceed five minutes, with the Minister to be given no less than ten minutes to reply to the debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1638" speakername="Malcolm Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#G00400"><p>I thank Senator Keogan and a number of other colleagues who organised a very successful coffee morning in aid of Ukraine earlier.  The event reflected the enormous cross-party support for the humanitarian efforts of the Red Cross and many others.</p><p>This year marks 50 years of Ireland's membership of the European Union.  In that context, I call for a debate on the future of Europe which also celebrates that milestone.  Ireland's EU membership has allowed us to step out from the shadow of our nearest neighbour, to prosper economically and socially and to take our place among the nations of the world.  In celebrating that, we also need to look at how we can support Ukraine and the other countries of central and eastern Europe that want to become members of the EU.  We must do whatever we can to assist Ukraine, Georgia and Moldova, all of which have now applied for membership, as well as those countries in the Balkans that want to accede.  Given our experience of membership of the EU, we should assist them in every way that we can.  As part of that debate, we must also include the question of our Common Security and Defence Policy.  We must co-operate closely with our friends in the other non-aligned countries of Finland, Sweden and Austria.  We can learn from their experiences and share their views.  In fact, a closer partnership with those other non-aligned countries in the EU will be important.</p><p>I also want to acknowledge that my local radio station, South East Radio, and the <i>Wexford People</i>newspaper group have organised a day to recognise the contribution of the people of Ukraine to Ireland and to highlight the impact of the abominable Russian invasion on the people of Ukraine.</p><p>On a separate issue, I welcome the Minister for Education's plan to appoint a representative of the Irish Second-Level Students Union, ISSU, to the National Council for Curriculum and Assessment.  The ISSU has grown in strength in recent years and was particularly active on some of the challenges around the leaving certificate in the last year or two.  The union has shown itself to be a very professional and capable body.  I have always advocated for strong student representation at decision-making tables and this move on the part of the Minister for Education, Deputy Foley, is very welcome.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#G00500"><p>I thank my colleagues, the Members of this House and the international community, including the ambassadors representing Turkey, Korea, Cyprus, Singapore, the Vatican City, the Philippines, Jamaica, Colombia, Spain, the Czech Republic, Belgium, Chile, Croatia, Iceland, Portugal, Georgia, Norway, Indonesia, Denmark, Poland, the Netherlands, Australia, Estonia, Latvia, Israel, Greece, Lesotho, Brazil, Finland, New Zealand, Lithuania, Guatemala, Slovakia and Kenya who showed up to show solidarity with our Ukrainian friends and with the Ukrainian ambassador.  I thank them all for turning up to support our coffee morning.</p> <p>I contacted the Irish League of Credit Unions to see if it would be interested in partnering with the Irish Red Cross so that its community banking facilities could be used by people who may not necessarily want to donate online, for whatever reason, to the Irish Red Cross.  Credit unions are the grassroots banks in our communities.  I wanted to see if they would team up with the Irish Red Cross and they willingly got involved.  That donation facility is being launched in more than 500 credit unions over the next week and that should bring in lots of money for the Red Cross.  It is heartbreaking to hear the stories of what is happening on the ground in Ukraine and it is incumbent on all of us to do whatever we can.  This is just the start of what I would like to do.  I thank my colleagues for their support.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#G00600"><p>I thank Senator Keogan.  On behalf of colleagues and everyone in the House, I warmly congratulate her on the wonderful initiative this morning, which was hugely successful.  Ambassadors from all over the world attended, which has never been known to happen previously.  It was a wonderful, very well organised event for a hugely important cause.  Out of evil and bad, good can sometimes come and this event was an example of that.  There is great unity among peoples now, forged for the wrong reasons.  The people who met here today have a new-found unity and solidarity.  Again, I congratulate Senator Keogan on her initiative.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1693" speakername="Pauline O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#G00700"><p>I thank the Leas-Cathaoirleach for allowing me to contribute at this point, even though my name was not on the list.  Yesterday, I mentioned my disappointment that the Fur Farming (Prohibition) Bill was removed from the schedule.  Today, I am still unsure as to what is happening with the Bill.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Pauline O'Reilly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=PaulineOreilly&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=09"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is a programme for Government commitment that commenced Committee Stage on 16 February.  Since then, we have had less than two hours of debate and it is now 9 March.</p><p>Next week, mink-breeding season starts again.  I can only come to the conclusion that this is being drawn out.  This was initiated in the D&aacute;il back in October.  If anybody wanted to have any discussions in the background, there was ample time to do so.  There was also ample time in the programme for Government to discuss it.  Mink farming is a cruel practice and we all acknowledge that.  It must end.  There has already been a commitment on compensation for the three farms that do it.  Those farms had 120,000 mink in very confined circumstances.</p><p>We all know that it has to be ended.  Given that, the very fact that it is removed from the schedule with no notice, begs some questions.  I have spoken to the Minister, Deputy McConalogue, who is anxious to put forward with this.  He gave a commitment last week on redundancy payments.  However, everybody knows that redundancy payments cannot happen until the Bill is signed into law and it is a matter for statutory instrument.  That is the same practice all of the time.</p><p>I would like for it to be put back on the schedule.  I would like an explanation from Fine Gael, in particular, to its electorate as to why it is drawing this out month after month and going into another year of fur farming and this hideous practice.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#H00200"><p>I call on Senator McGahon.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1670" speakername="John McGahon" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#H00300"><p>I thank the Leas-Chathaoirleach-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#H00400"><p>Senator O'Reilly asked a question and will not even stay for the answer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1693" speakername="Pauline O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#H00500"><p>I will be back.  The Leader could have called me.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#H00600"><p>Senator McGahon, without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1670" speakername="John McGahon" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#H00700"><p>I pay tribute to Mr. Stanislav Lapko, who many of us have seen on our national broadcaster over the past couple of days.  Mr. Lapko is from Dundalk.  He is a Ukrainian national who came to our town and set up a life there.  Just two and half weeks ago, he was working in PayPal in Dundalk.  He is now on the front lines fighting a Russian oppressor in Ukraine.  He is there with a number of other Ukrainians who have left Ireland to go back in defence of their native country.</p> <p>The greatest act of bravery and heroism is to run into a war zone to defend one's country.  It would be so easy for people to sit in the safety of Ireland or western democracies where they have been for the past ten, 15 or 20 years.  To go back to one's country in its greatest hour of need is an incredible feat of heroism and bravery.  A number of Irish people have also gone to help in Ukraine, whether that is with first aid or medical supplies or to act as ambulance drivers, stretcher carriers and a whole range of stuff.</p> <p>I pray this awful episode in our world and continental history will be over, as soon as possible.  When those individuals come back to Ireland and the lives they have built in our country for the past ten or 15 years, they should be honoured by the President in some form of a State civic reception at the highest level in &Aacute;ras an &Uacute;achtar&aacute;in, to say that we greatly appreciate them  in our country and what they have done here and wish to recognise the bravery they have shown in the defence of their own country.  We also want to recognise the bravery of Irish people who have gone over there to provide any sort of help.  We should seriously consider doing that.  When this whole godawful episode is over, we should put clear plans in process for that.</p> <p>I will also acknowledge the work of the Minister, Deputy Humphreys, in respect of what she has done to provide absolute clarity.  When Ukrainian refugees come to this island, they will have a PPS number; will be able to avail of social welfare supports; will be able to get housing assistance payment, HAP, and to rent, if that is the case, and will have access to all of the social welfare protections of which we are able to avail in this country.</p> <p>The greatest testament of any country is to be able to welcome refugees from a war-torn country with love, compassion and open arms and make sure they are valued, safe and appreciated members of Irish society for however long they want to stay here.  It may only be for a couple of months or years or they may want to stay here for even longer.  They are very welcome here and it is very important.  It is a testament to the Irish personality of hospitality and warmth.  That has to be remembered during these dark days.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#H00800"><p>I had the pleasure of attending the original London Irish soccer club, Tottenham Hotspur, on Monday evening.  It was very moving to see the ceremony beforehand in support of Ukraine.  There was a fantastic song from local schoolchildren and huge solidarity from supporters of both clubs.  However, the topic of conversation before and during the match was the appalling stance of the British Government in terms of visas for Ukrainian refugees.  Conservative ministers made appalling comments the previous week that they could come if they wanted to pick fruit.  It really speaks in shameful terms of the values of that government.</p> <p>I commend our Government on the positive moves it has made to welcome Ukrainian refugees.  It is very important we have joined-up thinking throughout this.  The challenges will be great but it was wonderful to be able to say to people at that match that the Irish Government was taking a proactive attitude to welcoming people to our country in response to the horrors we were seeing throughout Europe.</p> <p>One of the other aspects of this crisis is the issue of rising costs for Irish families.  I am pleased to see the Irish Government finally take a stance on reducing excise duties.  My fear is that whatever is announced today will be swallowed up by tomorrow.  What is very important is that the Government take Sinn F&eacute;in's advice to fix a price for petrol and assure the public it will not go beyond that price during this crisis period.  I was speaking to a woman from Limerick earlier today who explained to me that her pay-as-you-go electricity costs have effectively doubled.  Pay as you go goes half as far as it used to go which is an appalling prospect.  We need to see very clear commitments.  I do not understand why home heating oil will not be included.  I hope there is a late change in stance on that.  Home heating oil costs have doubled.  It is now &euro;400 for half of a fill of heating oil.  Working families cannot afford those sorts of costs.  We need to see joined-up thinking.</p> <p>A number of people have raised the issue of education in the past couple of weeks.  It is high time we had a debate on the future of education.  I see we have had correspondence from the Catholic education group in terms of its stance on integrated education.  We need to talk about integrated education.  As an old-fashioned republican, I believe in the complete separation of church and State.  We have not gone half as far as we need to in terms of our schooling.</p> <p>The other issue in education on which I want to have a debate is the subsidy to private fee-paying schools.  It was &euro;111 million last year.  I have no problem with anyone choosing to send their children to fee-paying schools.  I have a massive problem with those people expecting Irish taxpayers to subsidise those fee-paying schools.  When one thinks of the back-to-school costs that we talk about every year, &euro;111 million would go a long way towards solving those costs for ordinary families in our public school system.  It is high time we had a debate on education, our priorities and the need to move to a separation of church and state in our school system.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1638" speakername="Malcolm Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#H00900"><p>Mine is the only party whose leader who did not go to a private fee-paying school.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#H01000"><p>No interruptions, thank you.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1657" speakername="Eileen Flynn" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#H01100"><p>I show my solidarity with the Ukrainian people, those who are fleeing war and Russian aggression and those who are still in their country.  I am very proud of our country.  I am very proud of Ireland for standing in solidarity and supporting Ukrainian people at this time to seek refuge in the unfolding crisis.  I would like to see an important step in our rethinking of how we deal with humanitarian and refugee crises around the world.  I wish our country would offer the same solidarity and support to all refugees that they rightly show Ukrainian people.</p> <p>Seeing these events unfold over the past two weeks has been extremely disheartening and difficult to process.  Every day, we see innocent victims of war.  We also see these victims in Afghanistan, Palestine, Syria and Yemen.  I call on the Government to show the same solidarity that is rightly shown to Ukrainian people to people in these countries.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Eileen Flynn:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=EileenFlynn&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=09"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Violence is violence; war is war.  We should give all people the same dignity to be able to cross our borders.  We should look after all people in that respectful way.<br/><br/>A well known broadcaster recently referred to an image of a blonde Ukrainian schoolgirl as &quot;looking like us&quot;.  To get protection in the world one should not have to look like an Irish person.  I do not know in what way a person would have to look like an Irish person to seek refuge in this country.  Many other people, including Muslims, have travelled here in the past from other war countries.  Two years ago, we had a refugee crisis.  Last year, we had a refugee crisis.  This time last month, we had a refugee crisis.  Unfortunately, we could not deal with those refugees.  I hope to God that going forward we are going to treat people equally. <br/><br/>I am worried about the Roma people in Ukraine at this time, in particular whether they are being treated fairly and are getting equal access to safety.  Yesterday, a book was launched entitled, <i>End Direct Provision AND Tackle the International Protection System</i>.  There are people in direct provision in this country who are living in horrible situations.  <br/><br/>Today I again call on the Minister for Children, Equality, Disability, Integration and Youth, Deputy O'Gorman, to come into this House to outline what is going to happen to other people here, such as the Muslim people, who are fleeing wars.  Are these people to be provided with protection and to be given PPS numbers?  Are we going to end direct provision for all or for just some countries?  As a Traveller woman, I am concerned that we are leaving too many communities behind.  <br/><br/>I want it to be very clear that I stand with the Ukrainian people and with all people who seek protection, including people from Palestine, Syria and Afghanistan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#J00200"><p>Well said.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#J00300"><p>Well said.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#J00400"><p>I was intrigued by the exchange between my colleagues, Senators Gavan and Malcolm Byrne, on the subject of education.  It should not be a matter of either pride or shame to have not gone or sent one's children to a fee-paying school.  It seems that the difference between fee-paying schools and non-fee-paying schools is that fee paying schools get less of a subvention from the State because those who pay fees are presumed to be able to pay more.  There is nothing intrinsically wrong with the idea that parents should subvent their children's education if they wish and still expect to get a measure of State support by virtue of the fact that they are also taxpayers.  The idea that faith communities cannot establish schools or that fee paying schools should be somehow looked down on is not republicanism; that is statism and that one-size-fits-all approach.  Let different kinds of education flourish and let those who can afford it pay more.  Every taxpayer in this country is entitled to expect a certain level of State support for the education of their children.  That is an important principle.</p> <p>I want to raise the credit that is due to Senator Keogan for bringing us together in solidarity with the people of Ukraine, rescuing us temporarily from the impotence that many of us feel in the face of this crisis.  Enormous credit is due to those who are taking practical steps to be of assistance.  Last Monday, outside Portiuncula Hospital in Ballinasloe, there were people loading up a van with blankets and anything else that people were in a position to contribute, people taking active steps in solidarity with others in their need.  That is where the good stuff is to be found.  I would rather lead by example than criticise other countries for what they are not doing.  It is our deeds that will speak much louder than our words of criticism of others.  Let us seek to encourage that spirit of solidarity.  We may all individually and collectively be asked to make sacrifices in terms of the space we enjoy in our homes, the property that is available to us and so on in solidarity with people.  Let us do it.  Let us go for it.  Let us encourage each other in the effort.</p> <p>I ask that we would keep Ukraine on the agenda so that we can continue to reflect on the geopolitical issue.  Small as we may be, we have things to say.  There are things we need to be thinking about, such as how we get to a solution where there is a prosperous, neutral and free Ukraine again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#J00500"><p>I must interrupt at this point to welcome to the Visitors Gallery Ms Mary McDonagh and her fellow senior executives from Ifac, which is a friend of the farming community and an integral part of rural Ireland.  It provides an enormously professional service to our farmers and a support to our rural communities and, by extension, our small urban societies around the country.  They are an appropriate delegation in the present context.  They are accompanied by our distinguished and esteemed colleague, Senator Ahearn.  I welcome Ms McDonagh and her colleagues.</p> <p>I call Senator Hackett. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1661" speakername="Pippa Hackett" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#J00600"><p>Am I coming in ahead of someone else?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#J00700"><p>No.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#J00800"><p>Senator Boyhan will follow Senator Hackett.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1661" speakername="Pippa Hackett" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#J00900"><p>I think I may have skipped about two people.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#J01000"><p>No.  It is Senator Hackett's turn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#J01100"><p>Senator Boyhan was only indicating to me in case I missed him.  Senator Hackett may proceed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1661" speakername="Pippa Hackett" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#J01200"><p>I need to speak doubly quick now or I will run out of time.  Our economic system is having detrimental impacts on our planet.  While the current crisis in Ukraine is first and foremost a humanitarian crisis and we cannot and must not lose sight of that reality, it highlights nonetheless just how quickly difficulties can arise when our needs are dependent on imports.  The past few months, indeed days, have highlighted our reliance on imported energy, food, fertiliser and animal feed.  This has brought into sharp focus how quickly a major supply chain breakdown, such as is happening now, can expose so many of our families and farmers to spiralling costs.</p> <p>The Government is working with all sectors to try to address these serious issues.  As we do so, it is important that we also think about the future.  One solution is to implement system change by working with nature, within its ecological boundaries, to produce high-quality food in a profitable way.  I agree that is easier said than done, but we must not use this catastrophic situation in Ukraine to discontinue action on climate and biodiversity.  That would put even greater strain on our long-term future and that of our already stressed environment.</p> <p>Planning for short supply chains and circularity must be part of our solution as this will help to prevent future crises in sectors such as agriculture being compounded by events outside of our control.  Our very presence on this planet impacts the natural world as we draw on its resources to survive.  Every home we build, every field we plough and every tree will plant will have an impact.  While we may not be able to mitigate all the impacts, we need to ensure minimal impact and to balance inequalities across our planet, not just societal and economic, but environmental too.  As we assist those affected by the devastation in Ukraine, we should do so with an eye to the future.  An eye on how change is brought about as a result of this horrific crisis can help make food production here more resilient.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#J01300"><p>I join with others in thanking my colleague and friend, Senator Keogan, for organising the coffee morning.  It was fantastic.  It was great to see such diversity, different backgrounds and different traditions, all together.  It is important to acknowledge that.</p> <p>I ask the Leader for a debate at some point on the Children's Rights Alliance Report Card 2022.  I want to dwell on the positives of that report, which was circulated to all Members.  It was confirmed by the Children's Rights Alliance that the Government has made very positive progress over the past 12 months in the following areas: children living in direct provision, which is interesting; pathways for undocumented children; reform of early childhood education and care; and harassment and harmful communication and related offences.  They are the four areas singled out by the Children's Rights Alliance as areas where the Government has made substantial and real progress.</p> <p>I want to acknowledge that and to ask that we would have a debate on the report.  If ever we needed to be mindful of undocumented children coming into our State, now is that time.  While it is great to have people welcoming children and supporting them, we have to be careful about the areas they are arriving into, where they are to be housed, cared for and supported, and their welfare.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Victor Boyhan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2463"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2463&amp;amp;pid=VictorBoyhan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=09"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We have always got to be vigilant where there are children.  That is important.  I ask the Leader if we could have a debate on that.</p><p>There was some discourse about mink earlier, which I watched on the monitor.  The way we order business in this House is a matter for the Leader and I have every confidence in the way that is being done.  I accept there are controversies about mink, but the one thing I can say from the debate in this House is that no one is in favour of continuing mink farming.  Let us clear up that misconception.  I am totally against mink farming.  There is nobody in favour of mink farming right across this House.  What everyone wants is a fair deal for mink farmers.  That is all: a fair deal for them and their workers.</p><p>It is spring and the mink are raring to go.  If ever there was a headline for a press release it is that: "The Mink are Raring to Go, and it is Spring".  Legally, they can mate from 1 March.  All mink farmers today are currently in possession of a full breeding licence.  My last word on the matter is that there are only three mink farmers in this country and they are acting fully within the law.  It is legal for them to do what they want.  Let us just take time and get a fair deal for mink farmers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#K00200"><p>I thank Senator Boyhan for the inspirational-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#K00300"><p>For giving us a mental image none of us wanted to have.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#K00400"><p>It is my pleasure now to call on the Leader to respond to the comments on the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#K00500"><p>I did not expect to be called so soon to respond.  The last speaker, Senator Boyhan, raised mink farming, but Senator Pauline O'Reilly - in some strange tones - expressed her concerns publicly this morning on the drawn out delay, month after month, with the animal health and welfare Bill.  I was here last Thursday debating it, as I am sure all of my colleagues were.  As Senator Boyhan says, there are some concerns, but it has nothing to do with mink.  There is some element of trying to pit this as anti-Fine Gael, anti-Fianna F&aacute;il and anti-Independent and to say that some are pro-mink farming.  I do not think anybody I have ever spoken to is pro-mink farming.</p> <p>As Senator Boyhan says, the mink farmers do have a licence to continue farming, but there is no breeding going on in this country and there is no intention of allowing the breeding of mink here.  The intentions of the Members of this House are to make sure that the 30-plus workers who are losing their jobs and the three farmers who are losing their income, get a fair deal.  Until that is ironed out, concerns will continue to be raised by Members of this House, as one would expect in a democratic society.  I just want to put that to rest.</p> <p>Senator Boyhan and a number of colleagues spoke about Senator Keogan.  I want to put on record our compliments to what is the powerhouse of a woman called Sharon Keogan.  I know she is new to most Members in this Seanad, but I have known her for many years.  While she can talk the talk, she also walks the walk.  She is nothing short of a powerhouse.  Whatever she puts her mind to has an impact.  I acknowledge and congratulate her and everyone else, including the ambassadors who came this morning, to support the Ukrainian coffee morning.</p> <p>The Minister of State, Senator Hackett, spoke this morning.  She was dead right in her tone.  While we are all consumed by the atrocities of war and the impact of it on the cost-of-living crisis and potential shortages of food and energy in the coming weeks and months, climate change will wait for no man and no woman.  That should not deflect us from any of the changes we must make within this country to ensure we meet our climate change targets.</p> <p>Senator Mullen spoke about fee-paying schools.  He makes a good point but there are two sides to the argument.  I do not come from an area where there are incredibly wealthy people, but there are a number of people in my town who do choose to send their children to fee-paying schools.  The sacrifice they have to make is that they do not have fancy cars or holidays every year, so there is a balance.  I take on board what Senator Gavan said as well.</p> <p>Senator Flynn spoke about her solidarity with Ukraine.  She has requested a debate on the future of the Government's plans for the ending of direct provision.  I have arranged to have such a debate, but I do not have a date for it yet.  I made the suggestion to the Minister a number of weeks ago.  Such a debate is timely given that a stalwart of the direct provision community passed away this week.  It has caused major sadness in the community that she has spent all of her time in Ireland in direct provision.  We need to put a roadmap on the table so that people can see what our aspirations are for those people who find themselves, through no fault of their own, asking for refugee status in Ireland.  I will organise the debate as soon as I can.</p> <p>Senator Gavan said something that I only said to my husband this morning.  While the 20 cent and 15 cent decrease, respectively, on excise duty on diesel and petrol are very welcome today, I fear that by this time next week the prices will have gone back up again.  The Government must continue to keep an eye on the situation and make sure that the decisions it makes are reflective of that and that they are made in a timely manner.  We will have to pass that order both in the D&aacute;il and the Seanad in the coming days and we will try to arrange that as quickly as possible.</p> <p>Senator McGahon paid tribute to a gentleman called Mr. Stanislav Lapko, a resident of Dundalk and an employee of PayPal.  In a way, he spoke with pride at the fact that the young man has gone back to fight for his nation's freedom.  I am not sure I would have the same pride if I was related to him.  There is something awful about sending men - anybody's man, whether it is a husband, child or brother - into a situation where we have no knowledge of whether they will be safe.  We must double down, first, on sanctions and, second, on diplomatic efforts, to make sure that this war is ended in a way that perhaps does allow Putin to save some face, because ultimately it will allow the saving of thousands of lives.</p> <p>I cannot even begin to understand or appreciate what 2 million people fleeing a country looks like.  As someone said yesterday, it is the equivalent of the entire population of Northern Ireland just getting up and leaving.  It is hard to get one's head around how that would impact on us.  I pay tribute to the bravery of the Ukrainian people and recognise the response from the Government to the Ukrainian people coming here, which is done with an enormous heart.  We have opened the social welfare system and the housing system, albeit that they are under pressure.  We must make sure that we look after these people with a heart and a half.</p> <p>I spoke already about Senator Keogan.  Senator Malcolm Byrne spoke about the Common Security and Defence Policy.  He acknowledged the move by the Minister for Education to appoint somebody from the Irish Second-Level Students Union to the National Council for Curriculum and Assessment.  That will make a massive difference.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.71" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.72" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar fionra&iacute; ar 12.27 p.m. agus cuireadh t&uacute;s leis ar&iacute;s ar 12.53 p.m.

Sitting suspended at 12.27 p.m. and resumed at 12.53 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.73" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#P00100">International Women's Day 2022: Statements</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#P00200"><p>I welcome the Minister for Children, Equality, Disability, Integration and Youth, Deputy O'Gorman.  He is a very good participant in debates in this House.  I also welcome his colleagues.</p> <p>These statements are important.  International Women's Day has happily and thankfully become a major part of our annual calendar.  It gives important and overdue recognition of women and, in some respects, compensates for years of the position being otherwise.  It is a recognition of the importance of gender equality in all facets of life, including the political sphere.  It is a reminder of the need for equality and mutual respect.  It is very timely and, sadly, overdue but it is good that at least we are attempting to compensate for the wrongs of the past.  There is no point in not describing them as wrongs because that is what they were.  I call on the Minister to make his introductory remarks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1477" speakername="Roderic O'Gorman" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#P00300"><p>The Leas-Chathaoirleach has stolen my opening line because International Women's Day is an important part of my calendar, given that I am the Minister with responsibility for gender equality.  In reality, it is a day of significance for all of us, both men and women.  Gender equality remains a profound challenge, as the Leas-Chathaoirleach alluded to, despite significant changes and improvements, and the progress that has been made in recent years.  As a Government, we are committed to taking real and practical measures to highlight and tackle existing gender inequality across all aspects of our society.</p> <p>The gender pay gap is one of the major challenges to full gender equality both internationally and here in Ireland.  The impact of the gender pay gap is a lifelong one, with lower incomes contributing to lower pension entitlements in later life for women.  The Gender Pay Gap Information Act we debated in this House and which was passed last year introduced a legislative basis for gender pay gap reporting in Ireland and reporting by organisations with over 250 employees will begin this year.  According to the Central Statistics Office's Business Demography 2019 report, there are 732 private sector employers and 80 public service employers with more than 250 employees.  Regulations to give effect to this legislation are in preparation and will be published in the coming weeks, along with guidance for employers, who will have to choose a snapshot date in June of this year and report on the employees they have on that date.  The date for reporting will be the equivalent date six months later in December this year.  Those reporting this year will be required to publish that information on their own websites or other public forums.  An online reporting portal is planned for use in 2023, which will be publicly searchable.</p> <p>Reporting requirements will also be rolled out over the next few years, initially to organisations with over 150 employees and then to organisations with over 50 employees.  This will eventually encompass more than two thirds of employees in the State.  Gender pay gap reporting will help employers to identify the drivers behind the individual pay gaps within their firms and they will be required to include in their annual reporting the reasons they believe there is a gender pay gap in their companies.  That is important.  Crucially, they must also outline the steps they are taking to address and solve the gender pay gap that the reporting mechanism has revealed.</p> <p>The reporting requirements will also provide for transparency for employees as to what companies are doing and which companies are doing the most to address their gender pay gaps.  That information in its totality will help to inform public policy initiatives the Government will undertake to address the issue, perhaps on a sectoral basis.  By getting this information, we can then shape policy tools to intervene in areas where that intervention is needed most.</p> <p>I am also committed to supporting women to remain in the workforce, as well as allowing parents to have a work-life balance.  Significant advances in the provision of family leave have been made in recent years, including the introduction of paid parent's leave, which provides an entitlement to each parent to encourage a sharing of the care of a child in its earliest years.  There has also been an extension of unpaid parental leave.  Parent's leave is due another extension in July of this year, which will bring the entitlement to seven weeks for each eligible parent to be taken within the first two years of a child's life or adoptive placement.  This has gone up from two weeks when the Government came to power.  That leave entitlement will have increased to seven weeks over the past two years.</p> <p>I will also shortly bring to Government legislative proposals to transpose the remaining elements of the EU's work-life balance directive, including a right to request flexible working within the terms of the directive and an entitlement to leave for medical care purposes.  This legislation will also fulfil a long-standing Government commitment to extend the entitlement to breastfeeding breaks under the Maternity Protection Act to a full two years.  The importance of extending breastfeeding for the child is well-established and breastfeeding breaks facilitate this and will make it easier for a mother to return to the workplace after maternity leave and continue breastfeeding.  Such breaks are only provided for 26 weeks now and any mother who takes up her full paid maternity leave benefit will have passed the period within which she can use breastfeeding breaks.  We will be extending it from 26 weeks to 104 weeks, which is a significant extension, to recognise the long-standing policy to support women returning to work and to support a greater uptake of breastfeeding in those first two years.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Roderic O'Gorman:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=RodericOGorman&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=09"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> I am very conscious of the role childcare plays in supporting everyone&rsquo;s participation in the workforce but in particular supporting women&rsquo;s participation and return to the workforce.  I know the issue of childcare is one we have discussed many times in this House.  We have reflected on the fact that Ireland has a long history of underinvestment and neglect in the area of childcare.  However, we have made progress in recent years with the introduction of the national childcare scheme and, about ten years ago, the introduction of the ECCE two-year free preschool services.  The Government has now embarked on a wide-ranging reform of this sector.  This includes support for childcare professionals in a sector where the workforce is overwhelmingly female and this reform seeks to improve career structures and rates of pay.  Earlier this week, I announced details of a new &euro;221 million funding stream for services to help meet these goals while also improving affordability for parents through the introduction of a freeze on fee increases.</p><p>As I noted, Ireland is not alone in facing gender inequalities and it is important we use our voice to speak up and emphasise the need for gender equality internationally.  I will be travelling later this week to the United States, where I will lead Ireland's delegation to the 66th session of the United Nations Commission on the Status of Women, which opens on 14 March.  The priority theme for the commission this year is to achieve gender equality and the empowerment of all women and girls in the context of climate change, and environmental and disaster risk reduction policies and programmes.  Gender inequalities mean women are often more directly and severely impacted by climate change and the potential contribution of women to addressing the climate crisis is often overlooked and undervalued.  We need to unlock the unique capabilities and strengths that women have to address this challenge of a generation.  Women's voices need to be heard at all levels.</p><p>Violence against women crosses borders and boundaries.  It is an issue of serious concern to the Government.  We all recognise that the shocking and tragic death of Ashling Murphy has strengthened our resolve to bring in meaningful supports for women experiencing violence of any form.  The response to domestic, sexual and gender-based violence is a cross-departmental and multi-agency issue.  Tusla, the Child and Family Agency, which is under my responsibility, has statutory responsibility for the care and protection of victims of domestic, sexual and gender-based violence.  With input from the Taoiseach, the Minister, Deputy McEntee, and I worked intensively on the audit of the segmentation of the Government's responses to domestic, sexual and gender-based violence, which is something that has been called for by NGOs in this sector for many years, and on how the results of that audit fit with the new third national strategy on domestic, sexual and gender-based violence.  The result of that audit has been an agreement that the Department of Justice will become the lead Department with responsibility for responding to domestic, sexual and gender-based violence and responsibility for policy, accommodation and services will now transfer to the Department of Justice.</p><p>Domestic violence can result not only in women having to leave their homes but also in losing their employment and becoming at higher risk of experiencing poverty.  In order to mitigate that risk, officials in my Department have been examining the issue of domestic violence leave.  A report on this work has been compiled and I will bring it to Government shortly.  It reflects consultations that I carried out with stakeholders and an analysis of international examples.  It includes recommendations on what form the leave should take and also other supports for employers to develop domestic violence workplace policies.  This report will contribute to legislative proposals which I intend to advance this year as part of the work-life balance and miscellaneous provisions Bill.</p><p>I thank the Senators for this opportunity to speak to them on this very important issue as we mark the hugely important day of International Women's Day.  As I have outlined, the Government is working to address gender inequality across a range of areas.  In the coming months, we will see parent&rsquo;s leave expanded, the extension of breastfeeding breaks, the introduction of domestic violence leave and significant additional resources placed into childcare.  I thank the Senators for the invitation to be here.  I look forward to their contributions and to being able to respond to them later.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#Q00200"><p>I thank the Minister for his contribution and for initiating this important Bill.  I want to briefly interrupt the debate to welcome to our Visitors Gallery Deputy James Lawless and, very appropriately, two women friends for International Women's Day.  They are very welcome, as is Deputy Lawless.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1659" speakername="R&oacute;is&iacute;n Garvey" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#Q00300"><p>I do not know if it is comical but it says something that we are celebrating International Women's Day on 9 March, a day after International Women's Day.  I cannot for the life of me understand why we did not have space for this yesterday, which was actually International Women's Day.  I cannot wait to hear why that happened, why it was not a priority and why we got bumped up by a day.  It says a lot about the situation for women in Ireland.  I am laughing but it is quite serious in some ways.  It goes beyond a joke, given there are so many issues facing women in Ireland.</p> <p>It was a momentous day for me when I was elected to the council in 2019 as the first woman ever elected in my local area.  Even though I was proud, I was also deeply embarrassed.  When I go to secondary schools, I meet young women and I am always embarrassed to say that we never had a woman represent us in north Clare until 2019.  If it was 1919, maybe I would be proud, but in 2019 it was amazing to see.  It was a hard battle, it was quite a shock and it was not easy.  It is shocking that we had never had a woman elected before.</p> <p>That is partly because women do not always put themselves forward because, in the mainly male-dominated profession of politics, it can be quite intimidating.  As I said to a group of young girls yesterday at the Irish Second-Level Students Union, they should never doubt that they are as capable as any of the men in politics because it is not as intimidating as people expect it to be.  I was telling the young girls that all of them would be just as capable as anybody else who has ever been in the Seanad or the D&aacute;il, and to please think about putting themselves forward and engaging.  We cannot expect things to change for women unless women are willing to put themselves forward and we need to do a lot more about encouraging women to do so.</p> <p>If the decisions on women's issues are made mainly by men, we are never going to solve the problem.  I remember going through the public maternity services when I was pregnant.  There were 80 women in a room with 40 chairs.  We had all been told to be there at 2 p.m. to meet our consultant, who we never saw, and to have our uterine and blood samples checked in a pre-maternity check-up.  I remember looking around and asking how this was happening.  We are the givers of life and there would be no children without us, but there were 80 women with 40 chairs and we were all waiting for about three hours.  It was insane.  I swore to my unborn child that day that when he was sorted, I would run for election because I realised that until more women step up, why would men prioritise maternity services?  That is no offence to men but they are not pregnant so they do not know what it is like.</p> <p>What was also sad in some ways was that a lot of the women in the room were quite accepting that this was good enough, and it is not good enough.  It is not good enough for women to be treated in that way.  When one is demoralised during pregnancy, of course one is demoralised during the birth.  Our breastfeeding rates are the lowest in Europe and that is partly why.  We need to empower women to feel that they own their pregnancy, that they own their births, that they own their right to breastfeed and that the supports have to come into place.  With the best will in the world of all the men in Ireland, until we have more women representing us at the decision tables, none of those issues are going to change.  That is why we have had childcare issues and many other issues.  Historically, it is mainly women who have been the primary carers.  There are some great men doing great work around childcare but the majority are women, so until the women are at the decision-making table, none of that is going to change.  That is a very important point.</p> <p>Do not be intimidated.  Every woman is just as capable as every man at being at a decision-making table, whether it is in politics, on health boards, as principals of schools or anywhere else.  We have to really believe that we are every bit as good as men and put ourselves forward, even if it is intimidating.  It is okay to feel the fear and do it anyway because one will not regret it.  We are just as capable and that is a clear message that we have to remind ourselves of.  I still have to remind myself that I can do this, that we have got this.  When one is reared in a patriarchy, one is not always told that, so one has to constantly remind oneself that we are equal, we are as capable and we need to put our hands up and say &ldquo;Yes&rdquo;.</p> <p>There is a mad statistic that, in general, men will apply for jobs they do not feel qualified for, but they will apply anyway, and women will only apply for jobs they are definitely at least qualified for, if not overqualified for.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator R&oacute;is&iacute;n Garvey:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=RoisinGarvey&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=09"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->That says much about how we see ourselves and how we are seen in society.  I completely digressed on what I was going to say.  I will focus briefly on rural women.  A figure of 36.6% of the Irish female population live in rural areas.  The National Women´s Council of Ireland 2021 study entitled, Paper on Women in Rural Communities: We Want to Live and Work Where We Are, was a real eye-opener.  It identified an undervaluing of the contribution of women to rural communities.  As far as I can see, the women do nearly everything where I come from.  They organise everything and yet they are not the ones in charge and are not recognised.  They do much of the work but they are so busy working, they do not put their hands up and take photographs to get recognised for the work.<br/><br/>Rural women are more likely to be poor, to parent alone, to be the main provider of unpaid care work, to work in precarious employment, to earn low wages and to be at risk of domestic or sexual abuse.  That is just a fact.  Rural women&rsquo;s experiences and their role and contribution to families, communities and businesses, including on farms, often goes unacknowledged and unrecognised in the social protection system and rural development strategies.  The most marginalised are disabled women, Traveller and Roma women, lone parents and migrant women.<br/><br/>According to the 2016 census, 18% of rural Ireland does not have a broadband connection although the Minister of State, Deputy Ossian Smyth, has definitely moved things along to improve that slightly.  Some 139 Garda stations and 500 post offices have closed and rural banking is all but gone.  These are all services in which mainly women are running the show.  It looks like a man is in charge but I discovered that women are actually the main organisers.  That kind of sounds quite sexist but that is based on facts on statistics.<br/><br/>Coming from somebody who is herself a lone parent, I want to highlight a couple of things around lone parents.  Those in receipt of the one-parent family payment have the highest rate of consistent poverty among all social welfare recipients.  The Poverty and Social Inclusion: The Case for Rural Ireland report states:</p><blockquote>	The reasons behind poverty are complex but one of the main reasons behind lone parent poverty is that welfare to work supports were designed for unemployed people and simply extended to lone parents without any adaptation to take account of the specific needs of one parent families. </blockquote><p>Almost 60% of lone parents could not afford to access childcare services, which is three times the rate of two-parent families.<br/><br/>I also acknowledge that since we have come into government, many great things have happened in the last year and a half.  I said at the beginning that if anybody can challenge these issues, it will be the Ministers, Deputies McEntee and O'Gorman.  They have done great work in developing the third national strategy to combat domestic, sexual and gender-based violence.  The Minister, Deputy O'Gorman, outlined some great work that has been done on childcare improvements.<br/><br/>My colleagues in the Seanad, Senators Fitzpatrick, McGreehan and Chambers, have done great work on new legislation on the Non-Fatal Offences Against the Person (Amendment) (Stalking) Bill 2021.  Basically, it will be illegal to stalk people.  I have personally been stalked and there was nowhere I could go.  This is, therefore, a hugely important issue.<br/><br/>The first day I walked into the Seanad, we had 40% women, which is great.  It just feels different.  I did not realise how different it would feel because I came from a county council where it was nearly all men.  It is really important that we believe in ourselves on International Women's Day.  We need to engage with men on these issues.  There is no point in going into silos and having women preaching to the converted.  We need to spread the word and engage with all the good men of Ireland.  With their help, we can progress to a society in which we will be proud to tell our young women to go forth and they will be treated as equals.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1671" speakername="Erin McGreehan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#R00200"><p>The Minister is very welcome to the House.  It is now international women's week.  We are celebrating it for an entire week these days.  It is another week of repetition and asking for the same things again - demanding and hoping for equal rights, better healthcare, safer streets and homes, improved childcare and asking to be listened to in this male-dominated world.  It often feels overbearing.  There are so many issues to work on and there have been many setbacks.  I can say with confidence, however, that we are moving in the right direction.</p> <p>The Minister outlined an awful lot in his speech.  We saw yesterday a huge investment in women's health.  The Minister announced the regulation for gender pay gap reporting.  The Minister of State, Deputy Rabbitte, announced funding into gender-based violence against people with disabilities.  The Minister had the biggest childcare budget in budget 2022.  I know he is working on the next phase of his plan for next year towards public childcare because that is where we need to go.</p> <p>As Senator Garvey said, the third national strategy to combat domestic, sexual and gender-based violence is movement in the right direction.  Many things have happened in the 12 months since the previous International Women's Day.  As I said, many were positive but some desperately negative things and horrific crimes have occurred.  I think of all those people who have been murdered, raped, assaulted and beaten to a pulp at the hands of someone else over the past 12 months.</p> <p>Then, we look to our eastern European friends and the dark cloud that hangs over all of us due to Russian aggression and the greed and lies from Russia towards its neighbour.  I cannot stop thinking about those families inside and outside Ukraine and the mothers who are holding them together.  They are holding their babies, children, husbands and partners together.</p> <p>Everyone suffers and feels the pain of war and violence.  It is mostly women who make homes out of the most desperate of situations, however.  When peace reigns again, it is usually women who put families back together, build people up again and are the backbone of those communities who bring things back to some sort of normal.</p> <p>As we stand here, absolutely everything to me these days seems so small.   We see an entire country being destroyed by a man who has simply no regard for any life or any rule of law but his own.   He has no regard for decency or for the utter destruction and pain he is inflicting on people.</p> <p>Look at the beautiful wee faces on all the little children, and the mothers and fathers struggling to bear the weight of the horror of war and the pain of trying to simply stay alive.  I cannot even comprehend how they are not breaking under this but still they stand with courage and conviction.  They are protecting their children for the love of their family and country.  I cannot even imagine what it is like to send a child off to war or to go to war oneself; to leave one's husband or wife and either fight for one's country or life or find sanctuary.  All our privilege in this beautiful room seems almost obnoxious.  We seem so detached and I feel so useless.  In so many countries, we could not prevent this happening to one.  We could not protect one.  It is all-consuming, all-devastating and heartbreaking.  I am only watching it.  I am trying to explain it to my children and to myself.  Peace will be won by men and women.  We must make sure that no woman will be left behind.</p> <p>This year, the theme is breaking the bias, which I will speak about very briefly.  We must break the bias within us first.  We must be confident in our uniqueness, difference and individuality of who we are as women.  Women all around the world are held back by the bias that is ingrained in us by centuries of patriarchy.  I meet that bias every single day.  I also have to break it within me.</p> <p>I leave my children at 7 a.m., for example, and I do not see them until the next morning for a little while before I leave again.  It can be so hard and soul-shattering.  Ironically, when a man is working those long hours and days away from home and not getting to see his children, he is often seen as a good provider, worker, father and decent man who works all those hours to provide.  When women do it, however, they are sometimes perceived as a bad parent who is not providing what a mother should provide.  I can tell the Minister it is hard enough to leave my four boys at home without that unconscious bias within me and which comes from society as well.</p> <p>Perhaps we will stand here next year and it will be a great day on which we actually look towards real gender equality.  It is necessary to bring both men and women with us.  I do not want my male colleagues to give us platitudes that they recognise the difficulties and barriers we face.  I want them to come into both Houses, speak on the radio and tell us what they are planning to do to change the norms and make it better for all of us.  We are humans on this land and we need to support each other.</p> <p>What can men do to challenge the norm and break the bias that men need to be strong and brave and not weak, or to be the breadwinners and not stay at home with their children?  Things are changing but we need to support one another and challenge those gender-based norms.  We all need to be permitted to show our strengths, weakness and vulnerabilities because every single one of us has them.  We need men to take the lead on gender-based and domestic violence.  We have been speaking about it for years.  We need men to start.  Instead of standing behind twitching curtains and saying that a man has a reputation for beating the wife, when we all know it and no-one says anything, we need to call out gender-based violence.  We need to make this the safest and best country for women so we do not need all those refuges.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Erin McGreehan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=ErinMcGreehan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=09"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> Let us provide a safe space for us all to call out our vulnerabilities, to be proud of them and to allow both men and women to live in safety.  Ours is often as difficult a world for a man to navigate as it is for a woman.  I fear for my young boys, who are growing up with the norms of nowadays.  I want that to change for them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" speakername="Mary Seery Kearney" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#S00200"><p>I welcome the Minister and thank him for his tremendous work, not least that which is ongoing in committee.  I greatly appreciate it.</p><p>I want to reflect a little on how the bias can be broken from the perspective of both policy and practice.  We need to make a shift in respect of how we plan policy and practice and to ensure we see that through the lens of women's experience.  In the first chapter of her book <i>Invisible Women</i>, Caroline Criado Perez writes about the snow-clearing practice and policy in a town called Karlskoga in Sweden.  She describes how the clearing of snow involved the main roads and arteries first, then the pedestrian routes and the cycle routes.  According to the data on injuries during one snow period, women had been more greatly affected, constituting more than 70% of injuries in hospitals, and they had been, in the main, pedestrians.  The author points out how the original snow-clearing schedule had not been designed to benefit men.  Nobody had sat down and deliberately excluded women or not prioritised them.  Rather, the men around the table had made the policy based on their own experiences.  They were the ones who drove to work, so they cleared the roads first because they saw the problem through their own lens.  There were more than 200 km of cycling and pedestrian routes.  The very next year after they introduced the changes to the prioritisation, the number of injuries fell by 50%.  That is extraordinary and it goes to show that if we just look at things through a different lens, policy and practice will change.  I do not think any of our colleagues sit down with any <i>mala fides</i>to be fair.  I think they just do not think about it.  Having women around the table, therefore, is fantastic to ensure their experiences will be included.  It is a bit like the disabilities motto &quot;Nothing About Us Without Us&quot;.  We need to apply that also to women.</p><p>I welcome the changes in regard to the gender pay gap, which are important.  I ask that we tack that in more widely such that, if a Department is tendering for a public contract, a weighting will be applied with regard to gender equality in that workplace.</p><p>I will spend the rest of my time paying tribute to ordinary women.  Sometimes we come to the Chamber and talk about high-profile heroes, but in our everyday lives, there are ordinary women who are incredible heroes too.  I refer to women such as family carers, that is, the mothers, sisters and daughters who live sacrificial lives, including as the carers of children with disabilities.  I spend much of my days listening to them and advocating on their behalf.  They are extraordinary advocates, but they are unable to advocate for their children as much as they might like.  They feel the inadequacy of that when they should not.  It is not their fault and they are not to blame.  For both family carers and families who live with someone with disabilities, whatever we are doing, and I accept we are doing a lot, we need to do more.  I am thinking of people, one of whom contacted me in the past 24 hours, who live with the effects of thalidomide.  They have lived their 60-odd years with extraordinary disabilities that were not of anybody's choosing.  I think of their mothers and how that experience, of taking medication they should never have been given, was for them.</p><p>I am thinking also of mothers who live in homes where there is domestic violence, who may not yet have made the phone call, perhaps because they are calculating the cost and suffering the abuse until they have everything lined up.  They think about their children and the needs of their children, and about the social prejudice they may suffer when they tell their story and go to a refuge, if such a place is available to them.  They think about how, if they make all those decisions, people around them who will say, &quot;I told you so.  I knew.  Why did you not do something earlier?&quot;  They think about the people who will condemn and shame them rather than envelope them with gratitude for their courage.</p><p>I am also thinking about the mothers in Ukraine, some of whom have been making journeys.  Over recent weeks, I have heard about the extraordinary things they have had to do, the decisions they have to make and the sadness of trying to maintain normality in their children's lives amid the horrific butchery and murder that is going on in Ukraine.  In that regard, I pay tribute to H.E. Ms Larysa Gerasko.  I am sure that when she was appointed as ambassador and presented her credentials, she did not envisage this.  We all think of ambassadors&rsquo; jobs as like something from a Ferrero Rocher advertisement, and we imagine how exciting the job must be and how grand and lovely it must be, yet here is a woman who has been an extraordinary leader in this moment.  I have had a number of meetings with her.  She is kind and compassionate but steely strong, and she represents her people with extraordinary nobility.  I am proud to have met and encountered her.  Nevertheless, she is a sister, a daughter and an aunt.  She is greatly affected by what is going on in her country and feels the heartbreak of knowing and hearing from her friends and of receiving videos showing what is going on.  She has been extraordinary.  The ordinariness of her pain as a daughter, sister and aunt contrasts with her extraordinariness as a leader at this time leading our responses as people.  She is marvellous and is to be commended.  Today I think of all the ordinary women who are heroes, extraordinary in their everyday lives.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#S00300"><p>I express my solidarity with the women of Ukraine who have been forced to vacate their homes, communities and country.  Ireland stands with them as a voice for peace, demilitarisation, freedom and democracy.</p><p>I am proud to serve on the Joint Committee on Gender Equality, which is united in purpose and clear on the message that there can be no delay in the implementation of the recommendations of the Citizens' Assembly on gender equality.  It is clear also about the work on constitutional change that we will deal with, and about the work of Departments and the Attorney General.  The work of preparing the referendums must happen in parallel with the work of the gender equality committee.  I reiterate the three recommendations on constitutional change, for the record of the House:</p> <blockquote> 	Article 40.1 of the Constitution should be amended to refer explicitly to gender equality and non-discrimination.<br /><br />Article 41 of the Constitution should be amended so that it would protect private and family life, with the protection afforded to the family not limited to the marital family.<br /><br />Article 41.2 of the Constitution should be deleted and replaced with language that is not gender specific and obliges the State to take reasonable measures to support care within the home and wider community. </blockquote> <p>Members of the citizens' assembly were definitive in their recommendations and their urgency needs to be matched by urgency within the Government.  Too often the State fails to tackle areas of public policy that disproportionately affect women.  Childcare and social protection are just two examples, as is the provision of refuge places.  Women pay the price for the unaffordable cost of childcare and they do so at the expense of their aspirations.  Those working in early years education and childcare need to be given decent wages and conditions.  When social protection measures are weakened, it is women and lone parents who shoulder the greatest burden.</p><p>When the next strategy on domestic, sexual and gender-based violence is published, it must be fully resourced and urgently implemented.  The crisis in refuge places has to be brought to an end.  The State does not provide that service and that is incredible.  Entire counties do not have a refuge for women fleeing domestic violence.  Such women do not need just a bed; they also need wraparound services such as counselling and childcare.</p><p>In these dark times, I want our country to be a beacon of hope for people throughout the world, including the women of Ukraine, Palestine, Yemen, Syria and Afghanistan.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Fintan Warfield:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2458"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2458&amp;amp;pid=FintanWarfield&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=09"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I want Ireland to be a beacon of hope to transgender folks as well, as we once were.  We need to double our efforts.  We need transgender healthcare in this country, as it is a system that is failing transgender people.  This was most recently articulated by the former CEO of the Transgender Equality Network of Ireland, &Eacute;ir&eacute;nne Carroll, who having come to the Ireland from the United States to take up the role as head of an NGO here in Ireland, faced harassment, physical assault on the streets of this city and  verbal assault and was infantilised by our health system that denies basic care and surgery to transgender folks in this country.  I hope she is healing back home.  I hope that we can double our efforts in terms of transgender healthcare in this country because it is a scandal, considering we once were a beacon in terms of a self-determination model for transgender folks to recognise their true gender in law.  </p><p>Those are some of the things I am thinking about during this International Women&rsquo;s Week.  I thank the Acting Chairperson for the time afforded me to contribute to the debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1663" speakername="Annie Hoey" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#T00200"><p>International Women's Day, L&aacute; Idirn&aacute;isi&uacute;nta na mBan, is when we always hear the phrase, "Lots done, lots more to do."  I hate that phrase.  I see it in my old social media posts where I would say things like, &ldquo;Yay! Look how far we have come!  We have done so much work and we have got lots more to do.&rdquo;  I was very optimistic about things.  I do no know if I am just having a bad year, a bad day, a bad International Women&rsquo;s Day week or because it is the day after International Women&rsquo;s Day, but when I think about the &ldquo;lots more to do&rdquo; things, I think of safe access zones.  We have been around this House a number of times talking about safe access zones and there are promises of this, that and the other.  The gender pay gap is another example.  I note the Minister&rsquo;s opening statement listed very important things that he and his Department are doing.  I want to thank him and his Department for that.  I am very glad that he is the Minister in there because I do not doubt his sincerity and commitment to equality.  Bear with me on my bad humour during international women&rsquo;s week.</p> <p>Today affordable childcare was mentioned.  My colleague, Senator Warfield, talked about transgender healthcare and how we used to be a beacon for transgender rights.  Part of the problem with having been a beacon is that we are getting much transphobia nonsense coming in from the UK.  It seems somewhat ridiculous when we have our transgender siblings fighting so hard for basic healthcare needs.  </p> <p>On diverse representation in politics, we look around our Houses and it is nowhere near where it needs to be.  These are issues that we are raising again and again.  The Minister has heard them, I have said them and women are sick of raising them.  I am sick of raising them.  I would not like to be the Minister for Children, Equality, Diversity, Integration and Youth because it must be an enormous pressure, with all of these things that just keep going around and around.  </p> <p>It feels a little bit hollow standing up and talking about International Women&rsquo;s Day when I think of Ms Vicky Phelan, who announced that she is not well enough to travel to do the fundraising she was planning to do with Mr. Charlie Bird.  She is not well at the hands of the State.  Some 80% of Traveller women are rearing children without running water or toilet facilities.  There was a women dead for four days, potentially, in a direct provision centre in Cork.  The new national maternity hospital will built on Catholic-owned land.  Women in Ukraine are fleeing from war imposed by a cracked dictator.  Mothers in Yemen are looking at their starving children.  There is violence in Palestine and there was a picture yesterday of a young boy beside the body of his mother after his whole family had been killed.  It feels very hollow to be standing up and talking about seeing some of the #GirlBoss stuff that some of the corporations have been doing.  It just feels so sanitised and hollow when there are these very real issues affecting women.  </p> <p>It also feels a little bit hollow to stand up here today on International Women&rsquo;s Day 2022 when we could have had transformative change.  We have had two years of an incomprehensible global pandemic.  Out of that, we could have had real opportunities for working from home, flexible work, the right to switch off, a four-day week and affordable childcare.  Some of these things were not about reimagining how we could have been as a society.  Many of those things that people connected with and felt during the lockdowns were actually a reconnecting with their community and tribe and a reconnecting with themselves and ourselves.  It seems to be a little be like we are going back to the same old thing.  I was driving by Pearse Station this morning and there was a line of people trudging getting off the train and everyone trudging back to their workplaces.  I wondered how we are back at this again.  We could have a transformative society about balancing work, family, life, joy and happiness.  It just felt very glum watching everyone trudge up Pearse Street coming off the train this morning.  </p> <p>We have also had a stark reminder this year, as the Minister referenced, that simply taking up space is dangerous for women.  Ms Ashling Murphy just existed and she was murdered for that.  There are thousands of women everyday who just exist and they are murdered just for existing.  We are constantly telling young women to be unobtrusive and to take up less space.  </p> <p>International Women&rsquo;s Day was part of a campaign of women&rsquo;s trade union and garment workers to tackle poor working conditions, low wages and sexual harassment.  It seems we are still talking about those very things.  </p> <p>As I said, I feel like International Women&rsquo;s Day 2022 does not resonate with me.  I feel a little bit afloat or adrift from it.  I have had enough of this kind of asinine corporate #GirlBoss, lean in, "you can do it" feminism kind of stuff, which is everywhere.  It is very draining.  </p> <p>I am in here because I talk about wanting a seat at the table.  I put myself forward for election because I wanted a seat at the table and I want to be able to effect change.  However, the more I am in this, the more that I come to realise that the table was built by the patriarchy to uphold the patriarchy, and I am not entirely sure the benefit of getting me at that table.  I want to just smash up the table, toss it out the window and repurpose the wood for a community building project.  I find myself really conflicted and frustrated at the moment about how we can effect change as women.  It seems like we all come in here and we talk about issues and share issues every single year and it just feels like we are just not moving, even though we are obviously moving, because it would be silly of me to say that we are not.  </p> <p>The feminist fight is not over.  I will get over my frustration and I will put on my &ldquo;Smash the Patriarchy&rdquo; t-shirt tomorrow and I will brush myself off and get back to it.  Those of us who see the fight for equality every single day will keep it going.  I have no doubt that the Minister is one of those people.  I will submit a report to the repeal review.  I will keep fighting for student nurses and midwives and on and on.  The grind will keep going.  However, I feel like next year we will be back and ruefully saying, once again, &ldquo;So much done, so much left to do&rdquo; as if the powers that be were impotent and could do nothing to effect real feminist change in the intervening year.  I wish the Minister the very best with the work his Department is doing.  I hope that other Departments can take inspiration from that.  Happy International Women&rsquo;s Day yesterday #GirlBoss.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#T00300"><p>Just to follow a brilliant speech from Senator Hoey, I always say it is not about getting to the table, it is about shaping the agenda and changing what is being discussed at the table.  However, I think Senator Hoey&rsquo;s smash-up-the-table-altogether-and-repurpose-it is taking it perhaps the necessary step forward.  I think the Minister is hearing that it is about power when we talk about it.  It was from women who did not have power but who formed a union and insisted on taking power that International Women&rsquo;s Day came.  It is about challenging it.  There was a great moment at one of the big UN events where different countries were speaking about the things they were doing for women with the various organisations.   I think it was the Costa Rican representative who stood up and instead of beginning with the three or four things Costa Rica did for women, they said what they did to address the patriarchy problem and the problem of a huge systemic imbalance in power.  That is what it is.  It is not about dealing solely with the symptoms; it is about dealing with the core problem of power inequality.  That is where we are at.  It is a transformation.</p> <p>We are seeing that the world can totally change in response to Covid.  We are seeing the world change in terms of Covid.  Women are tired of seeing small, incremental slight improvements while keeping business as usual, effectively trucking along.  That is why I am also on Committee on Gender Equality that Senator Warfield spoke about.  That has a very strong mandate from citizens.  I say this directly to the Minister in his Department to be clear, as it is very important.  There need to be referendums next year.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Alice-Mary Higgins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2480"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2480&amp;amp;pid=AliceMaryHiggins&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=09"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Our committee is not just minding the issue and keeping it off the table for the next nine months.  We expect the Government to produce a referendum next year to deliver crucial changes.  I will speak to two of them, the first of which is the gender-neutral recognition of care, not only by removing the clause about women being in the home, which is important, but also through a recognition of the State's responsibility to support care.  Care cannot just be the invisible structure that keeps everything going.  During Covid, we have seen how much everything relies on it.  The Minister is starting from a low base and knows that more needs to be done in the context of working conditions for childcare providers.  We probably need a public childcare system.  That is what the Citizens' Assembly looked for.<br/><br/>Other care work is systematically undervalued and carers are not cared for.  In this respect, there is a significant issue with student nurses.  According to today's edition of <i>The Irish Times</i>, applications to the Central Applications Office, CAO, for nursing courses are down 27%.  This is because nursing is undervalued and under-respected.  The Minister will be aware that, globally, 2.6 million nurses wrote to the UN to point out the human rights violation against them as front-line health workers because the EU blocked the sharing of Covid-19 vaccine information.  Those 2.6 million nurses have sent us a message, which is one to remember as I look at the painting in this Chamber of Elizabeth O'Farrell, who was a nurse who contributed.  Irish student nurses are voting with their feet.  The message is that we need to focus on care.<br/><br/>All families must be recognised.  It is not a coincidence that 53% of homeless families in Ireland are headed by a lone parent, usually a woman.  The highest levels of deprivation in the State are seen among lone-parent families, which are usually headed by women.  Let us make it a goal for the Government and all of us this year to ensure that, by next year, we will have addressed the fact that women who have children are still effectively being penalised by the State.  As the Minister will be aware, they were systematically penalised in the past in terms of mother and baby homes, and they still are.<br/><br/>The Government also needs to listen to women on issues like the National Maternity Hospital.  It is not enough to say we will try to treat you a bit better or ask those in a voluntary trust linked to a religious group to treat you a little better.  The people are saying that we want to own our maternity hospital.  We want public healthcare.  The women who are citizens of the State - they represent the majority of citizens - want a national maternity hospital that is theirs, not simply because they have been treated badly and want to be treated better, but because they want the power relocated to them, that is, to women.  That is where it needs to be.  This emerged in the opinion of the Citizens' Assembly's because those involved understood it was not just a wish list.  It said that the right to collective bargaining was a gender equality issue in order that women could use their collective strength in unions.  It pointed to gender budgeting.  We need to remember that women's voices need to be heard when we decide how money is allocated.<br/><br/>Lastly, I come to the question of conflict.  We have spoken about Ukraine, but we also need to remember the women starving in Yemen and Afghanistan and the women who fought for a civil government in Sudan and did not get the support they needed.  At a time like this, women's voices and power are crucial.  Under UN Resolution 1325, women must be at the table in any negotiation on the end of conflicts and the building of peace.  Their voices must also be heard when rebuilding peace.  It is not okay that their voices are pushed to the margins, including voices of peace.  Those voices are crucial.  Female human rights defenders, including environmental human rights defenders like Berta C&aacute;ceres who lost their lives on that other front line, namely, the battle against climate change, must not be pushed to one side and told that, yet again, we need to wait because we are focusing our energies on business as usual and following the same playbooks we have used before in terms of militarism.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#U00200"><p>I welcome the Minister on this important day.  He takes a particular interest in the matter.</p> <p>The theme of this year's International Women's Day is breaking the bias.  During the past two years under Covid, breaking the bias would have referred to our unfinished business of advancing gender equality, combating gender-based violence and addressing the gender pay gap.  All of these are important issues that we need to consider and keep fighting for.  This year, however, it is the Ukrainian women who are uppermost in our minds and who preoccupy our thoughts during international women's week.  We have all seen photographs and coverage on television and streaming on our phones of women sheltering their children from harm, giving birth in bomb shelters, taking up arms to defend their country and fleeing with their children to our shores and other countries.  The Ukrainian women who are already living in Ireland are doing their best to ensure that their families reach here and to organise the sending of provisions to their country.  We stand in solidarity with the women of Ukraine.</p> <p>While it nearly seems strange to speak about other challenges and issues, it is important that we do exactly that while reminding ourselves that we have the privilege of being able to do so and of gathering here in this safe space of the Seanad to listen and debate, a privilege that is now denied the women of Ukraine and many of the women of Russia.</p> <p>I have been reading Michelle Obama's memoir recently.  In her epilogue, she reflected on the journey that she took from the tough south side of Chicago to the elite Harvard Law School and then to the White House.  She concluded that what she learned about most was inviting women in to work together.  If we do that, we can begin to fear less, to make fewer wrong assumptions and to let go of the biases and stereotypes that sometimes divide us unnecessarily, which might allow us to embrace our similarities better.  It is not about being perfect or where we get to by the end.  There is power in allowing ourselves to be known and heard, owning our unique stories and using our unique voices.  There is grace in being willing to know and hear others.  That is how we become - as in the title of Michelle Obama's biography - and how we break bias.</p> <p>The situation of the women of Ukraine has particular poignancy for us because it comes during the commemoration of the centenary of our own War of Independence and the establishment of one of the longest continuous democracies in the world.  We can never forget the central role that women played in our successful revolution.  It is almost impossible to imagine how it could have succeeded without that role.  It should be a source of immense pride for us as Irish people that the Proclamation of 1916 may well have been the first revolutionary declaration of independence to demand full rights for women.  The extension of the still unequal franchise to women in 1918 was an essential part of the radicalism of that election and the sweeping victory won by separatist republicanism, and so it continued through the War of Independence.  However, there is certainly much more that remains to be done 100 years on in terms of equality for women.</p> <p>We must pay tribute to the women in our communities and in local government.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Fiona O'Loughlin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2441"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2441&amp;amp;pid=FionaOLoughlin&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=09"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Local government is an important part of the administrative structure of the Republic.  I am pleased to know so many strong and impressive Fianna F&aacute;il councillors and, indeed, councillors from other parties.  With the advance of social media and all the other challenges, it is a difficult road for women to take.  We need to do what we can to ensure that maternity leave is in place for local authority members and Oireachtas Members.  I know the Minister is working on that and I appreciate the meetings we have had about it.<br/><br/>I commend the Minister for Health and the Ministers of State, Deputies Butler and Rabbitte, for the very comprehensive women's health strategy they launched yesterday.  It is the first such strategy we have ever had.  It addresses many different matters, including fertility, menopause, period poverty, contraception and perinatal health.  It is extremely important.<br/><br/>In 2019, Safe Ireland published a report called Gender Matters.  It surveyed every type of community and society in Ireland and some of the findings and conclusions were interesting to say the least.  For example, 17% of people felt that household chores should be a female responsibility rather than male.  Interestingly, there was a stronger bias among people living in rural areas, where that figure went up to 28%.  The report states:</p><blockquote>	Traditional views of gender equality, roles and responsibilities haven&rsquo;t gone away.  In fact they may be more traditionalist than expected, particularly in younger ages.<br /><br />[...]<br /><br />Lad culture is alive and well.<br /><br />[...]<br /><br />There are conflicting views on what constitutes progression. </blockquote><p>It is a study that would merit another debate in the House.  I thank the Acting Chair for giving me the opportunity to speak on this matter and I thank the Minister for listening.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1695" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#V00200"><p>I am delighted that the Minister is here for this all-important conversation.  I am also delighted that I can contribute to the debate on and recognise International Women's Day, which took place yesterday.  It is a day for acknowledging not only our struggles but also our successes.  While there is a lot that divides us, there is more that unites us.  While we have differences, we should not allow them to divide us when striving for greater equality.  The Minister is committed to this area.  We should utilise our differences in a positive way.</p><p>International Women's Day is a day to remind us about the wider conversation on gender and how we can pursue equality.  We must open a wider conversation about marginalised groups in society.  This morning, I raised a Commencement matter with the Minister of State, Deputy James Browne.  I acknowledge both him and the Minister for Justice and their commitment to dealing with sexual violence against women.  I raised the barriers facing non-fluent English speakers when reporting gender-based and sexual violence.  This is an area of huge concern.  Women are a marginalised group in their own right but we have to pay special attention to the groups of women who face further discrimination, such as trans women or Traveller women.  We are very lucky to have our colleague Senator Flynn here.  She represents that area and portrays a very positive image and is very good at bringing forward points and ideas.  I also refer to women of colour and women with disabilities.  Women in these groups feel disenfranchised at times but we should utilise these differences to unite ourselves.</p><p>Ironically, International Women's Day started with women in Russia on 23 February 1913.  Their slogan was &quot;Bread and Butter&quot;.  In 1914, the day was recognised globally and the date for it was set as 8 March.  It it important to recognise the women in Ukraine at the moment.  The Acting Chair is very involved in the issues around surrogacy.  Many mothers have been birthing in train stations and women who have given birth to surrogate babies in the last few days are now fleeing their country.  It is frightening.  We can all agree that the strength and courage of all Ukraine at the moment is admirable.  Women there are experiencing very difficult circumstances and their strength is unimaginable.</p><p>I recognise the work the Minister is doing around breastfeeding.  Limerick City and County Council was the first local authority to announce a breastfeeding-friendly city.  I compliment it on its foresight in that regard.  Limerick has had 826 mayors.  Of those, five have been female.  I am honoured to have been the fourth female mayor to serve in 826 years.  Colleagues spoke about the strength of women on local authorities and what women have to offer there.  We need to encourage more female participation.  I am glad that the Minister mentioned childcare and the investment of &euro;221 million in that regard.  We have to support a greater work-life balance and we have to encourage women to come forward for election.  This is something I feel very passionate about.</p><p>Ireland has a very long history of strong women going back to before the establishment of the Republic, including the work of the Daly sisters and Countess Markievicz.  In recent years, we have had two female Presidents.  Ireland has many issues around women's equality but there is no question that we have a history of women who have continuously and actively strived for a better and more equal world.  G.D Anderson has said:</p> <blockquote> 	Feminism isn't about making women stronger.  Women are already strong.  It's about changing the way the world perceives that strength. </blockquote> <p>We have women with strength and passion in our history books.  In this Chamber alone there are so many female Senators who are actively breaking the bias on a daily basis.  The theme of this year's event, #BreaktheBias, is to be commended.  I pay tribute to a former Fine Gael Deputy, Ms Brigid Hogan-O'Higgins, who celebrates her 90th birthday this week.  I wish her all the best.  She retired from politics following the 1977 general election having served for 20 years as a Deputy.  On breaking the bias, she fondly remembered being called to the Ceann Comhairle's office on more than one occasion for going into the D&aacute;il bar, for not wearing a hat in the Chamber and for using the men's toilets as there were no female toilets in this building at that stage.  The ladies had to go across the road to Buswell's Hotel.  We have come a long way since then.</p><p>I came across another quote yesterday that stated &quot;Well-behaved women seldom make history&quot;.  &quot;Behaved&quot; may not be the best word to use in this sense but women and men who stick to the norms and do not break the bias will rarely be remembered.  We owe it to society to continue to break the bias every day.  By doing so, we can make a change for everyone in the Ireland of the future and hopefully across the world.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" speakername="Mary Seery Kearney" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#V00300"><p>I thank the Senator for bringing that to our attention.  It is scandalous that there was not a ladies' toilet in this wonderful complex.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" speakername="Barry Ward" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#V00400"><p>N&iacute;l m&eacute; ach chun c&uacute;pla focal gairid a r&aacute;.  Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire chuig an d&iacute;osp&oacute;ireacht ar an &aacute;bhar t&aacute;bhachtach seo.  I do not want to speak today because I can match, particularly experientially, any of the comments of my colleagues on this issue, with the possible exception of Senator Warfield.  Throughout the horrible issues we have faced in recent months in this House, one of the things I have always said is that men must not step back from these issues.  Men must centrally involve themselves.  The danger is that only the female Members of the House will come down to speak in a discussion on International Women's Day.  I wanted to contribute to the debate at that level.  While many of these issues have come to the fore in the last number of months, we now know, if we did not before, that they have been there all the time.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Barry Ward:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=BarryWard&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=09"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->There has been this level of stress and intimidation of more than half of our society.  It has largely been ignored.  An acknowledgement of that is important with regard to breaking the bias.</p><p>Yesterday I had the pleasure of attending the Women in Business Alliance lunch, which was organised by the D&uacute;n Laoghaire-Rathdown Chamber, in the Talbot Hotel, Stillorgan.  Again, there are very few men at that.  I could understand this because it was primarily female business leaders who attended, with more than 100 attendees.  The strength of spirit and solidarity there was quite extraordinary.  We had a number of talks from local business women who had so much experience and so much to say about various issues that are, in reality, not discussed enough.  I thank Gabby Mallon for the invitation to be there.  Even the people sitting either side of me at the table had so much experience and insight into how much further we have to go in  fostering female business leadership in particular.  I say this in the context of my own mother who is an entrepreneur.  We did not realise when growing up that our mother was very much in a minority.  She set up her own business in Dalkey in the 1980s and she continues to run her own business, albeit a different one now.  There is a much used expression: "You cannot be it if you cannot see it..  My two younger sisters could definitely see it with my mother and there was never any question that she had any less of a right to go out to work and earn a crust crossed than my father did.  I suspect that my mother contributed as much to the household as my father did.</p><p>As members of society perhaps we sometimes have that inherent bias because we see men in these roles and other roles, and there is a presumption therefore that this is the way it should be.  Of course, that is not correct.  In looking around the Chamber there are certainly colleagues who disprove that.  My mother has disproven that.  I had wanted to contribute to this debate in that respect.</p><p>The theme of International Women's Day this year was BreakTheBias. One of the things that we can contribute in this House is to constantly acknowledge the need for that equality.  I had this conversation many years ago with Monica Barnes who was a Fine Gael Deputy for D&uacute;n Laoghaire.  Monica Barnes was a very ardent supporter of women in politics, and I also counted her as a friend and a supporter.  She was such a strong voice and was one of the co-founders of the Council for the Status of Women.  She really articulated that voice back in the 1980s and the 1990s, when it was not a popular or an easy thing to say.  Monica was a real pioneer and unfortunately is no longer with us.  We remember her on days like this.  In my contribution to the debate I just wanted to say how important it is for those of us who are not women to also contribute to the debate, to stand up, to agree, and - while paying homage is perhaps too dramatic a term - to put down the marker of respect for people who have been pioneers in this area.  I congratulate them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1648" speakername="Emer Currie" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#W00200"><p>I have just lost 50% of the time I had, but that is okay.  The Minister, Deputy O'Gorman, is welcome.  We are in the same constituency but the Minister knows how much I value his work and the work he is doing.  I know we are not supposed to say this because we are constituency rivals, but it is true.</p> <p>I still believe that we are at a turning point of all of the reasons I got into politics, and we have an opportunity to address them here right now.  I was working in an advertising and marketing agency.  I was a business director and I was there for 15 years.  I was pregnant with my second child and I wanted flexible work but I could not get it.  I made the hard decision to leave a job into which I had invested so much.  I became a stay-at-home mum for a few years, and I realised how difficult that is too.  Even the tax system is against us.  Days like International Women's Day are so important, and it is important that we highlight those.  The Minister is aware how I feel about flexible working and the EU work directive.  It should be universal.  We should have a system such as the one in New Zealand, or be more like Finland.  With the legislation that will soon be going through the Houses on the right to request remote work, I believe that the reasons to refuse should be reasonable.  As it states in the heads of the Bill, the reasons for refusal should be reasonable and demonstrable.  We need to see a culture change that has to be supported with employers.  They need assistance through this.  If we can invest in the digital transformation with SMEs because we recognise their productivity, then we need to be investing in digital transformation for remote work in the Digital First strategy, so that nobody gets left behind.  I welcome that we are beginning to move on the the gender pay gap also.</p> <p>Yesterday I and others attended an event with the Muslim Sisters of &Eacute;ire.  This is an incredible organisation.  Obviously, there is a lot of attention on Ukraine at the moment, but at the same time we must support all refugees.  We must ensure that the supports are there for all women and children who are affected by conflict.  These are the most incredible women, many of whom have suffered themselves.  They also suffer from the bias.  There is a need the work that they do with soup kitchens and period poverty packs.  It was fantastic to be with them on the day, not that it is not fantastic to be here too.  We have so much work to do and I really hope we can pull together and do it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1477" speakername="Roderic O'Gorman" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#W00300"><p>I thank all Senators for their very detailed, knowledge-based and passionate contributions to our debate today.  I have a pre-prepared speech listing out all of the great things the Government has done over the past year, and the plans for the next year.  I believe a couple of reflections might be a little bit more useful.</p> <p>I was struck by Senator McGreehan saying that here we are asking for the same thing again.  I was also struck by Senator Hoey's contribution about it feeling a bit hollow to stand up and talk about International Women's Day again.  I reflect also that this is my second opportunity to address this House on International Women's Day.  Hopefully, I will have that opportunity again in future years.  We must ask, however, if there has been change.  If there was one thing that has not changed in this area in the way I would like, and Senator O'Loughlin touched on this, it is around maternity leave and ensuring that we have maternity leave for Members of the Oireachtas also.  There was a focus on this matter last year in the context of the Minister for Justice, Deputy McEntee, and administrative arrangements were put in place.  Another Member of the Oireachtas has since been pregnant and given birth.  Similarly, and perhaps with even more impact, we must look to maternity leave for local authority members.  This falls within the Department of Housing, Local Government and Heritage.  Maternity leave for Oireachtas Members falls within my Department, and we are working on that.  I am sorry that we have not advanced it further but it is important that we look at what has actually been done.</p> <p>This brings us to the wider debate, on which Senator Higgins spoke, about incrementalism versus absolute systems change and the idea of smashing the table.  I will not give any conclusion on that but I do believe that we can work towards both.  In my life, and coming from a very small political party, for 25 years I have been used to the tap, tap, tapping away and making little changes.  Sometimes one gets the opportunity to make the bigger change.  I am thinking, for example in the area of climate and in our understanding of climate.  That is where we are now and we have the chance to make a systems change in that regard.  Similarly, there were other political campaigns such as those on LGBT+ rights and the marriage equality campaign.  I remember as a member of the Green Party when we were in a previous Government introducing civil partnership legislation, which is something I felt very passionately about.  It was not marriage equality, and I recognised that.  My predecessor in this role, former Deputy Katherine Zappone, and her late wife Dr. Ann Louise Gilligan, were very critical of civil partnership yet I felt that it was an important incremental step that helped to deliver marriage equality.  Then we took that sudden dramatic leap, which was a vote by the Irish public, in marriage equality.  We can see this type of change also with the repeal of the eighth amendment campaign where many people worked on the issue of repeal for a very long time.  We had some small incremental changes and then, suddenly, the big leap happened.  There is a place for incrementalism and for systems change.  I do not believe it has to be one or the other.  I am not saying that anybody was suggesting that but this is about keeping our hopes up and realising that we are making things better.  </p> <p>Senator Currie spoke about the need for a turning point.  I hope we are reaching a turning point in how we treat women and how we engage with women in our society.  Even in the very short time that I have been in the Oireachtas this conversation has changed.  Covid drove a change.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Roderic O'Gorman:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=RodericOGorman&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=09"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Some incredibly tragic murders have driven a change in that but I suppose time will tell if we have reached that particular turning point.</p><p>The issue that many have touched on is the issue of women at the table.  That is why I would come back to the whole local authority area, election to which is such an essential step to take in providing a platform for any future Member of the Oireachtas, but particularly any future female Member of the Oireachtas.  Looking around, maybe one Member of this House here today is not a former councillor.  Everyone else has come in through that local authority route.  It is so important we support that, whether in the context of maternity leave or whatever.</p><p>Caucus groups are setting up in many local authorities.  I met members of the Fingal women's caucus on Monday outside the House.  They passed on a petition about increasing the amount of refuge space in the Fingal area which is something that many Senators have touched on.</p><p>We must do whatever we can to support female councillors, once they are elected but also in getting elected.  As Senator Garvey said, every woman is as capable as every man.  The Senator said she has to remind herself of that sometimes.  Making provision for that and supporting the membership and participation of women in local authorities is so important and will make the change here.</p><p>Certainly, the gender quotas that we have introduced for general elections are something I would strongly favour bringing in for local elections as well.  It causes a complication within parties, particularly bigger parties, but it is worth it in terms of getting that greater degree of representation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#X00200"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1477" speakername="Roderic O'Gorman" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#X00300"><p>Nearly all the Senators touched on the issue of Ukraine.  It is something that the Government and, more importantly, the entirely country are united on in terms of our open and generous response.  Almost 10,000 pledges of support have come in through the Red Cross portal in the past number of days.  Irish women and Irish men are saying what they will do, for instance, giving a spare room or providing meals.  That is an enormous support.  I hope that the Ukrainian ambassador can draw some comfort from that degree of solidarity.</p> <p>I have had the opportunity to meet one or two families who came to my Department seeking to register here and heard at first-hand some of those stories.  There was one child just lying on the couch in our reception he was so exhausted.  In fleeing the crisis, the family had driven from Ukraine to Ireland.  The child was not playing.  He was literally lying there.  I could sense the exhaustion.  I could sense the exhaustion in his parents.  They were slumped on the seats.  It is so important that we as a country meet all our EU requirements - they are generous requirements - but also our humanitarian requirements in terms of providing for Ukrainian refugees.</p> <p>Assuming this conflict goes on as we must, that will cause pressures in all our communities.  It will be up to the Government to work to alleviate those pressures but it will be up to all of us to provide leadership.  Sometimes the outpouring of support can be strong at the start but when things get more difficult we will have to be there to provide leadership and say that this is the right thing to do, this is a necessary thing to do as part of our own humanity and this is something that we must do.</p> <p>Senator Curry referred to the event that was hosted by the Muslim Sisters of &Eacute;ire yesterday.  Our focus day, yesterday and this week is on women but we also have to recognise the issues of intersectionality.  There are women, as in every part of society, who because of other factors are more at risk or who have faced greater degrees of discrimination, for instance, women who have, either themselves or have a child with a disability, women who are the sole carers of their children, women who are members of the Traveller community, women who are black, women who are immigrants and transpeople.  The intersectionality of this day is important.  Many of those issues fall within my Department.  My colleagues in the National Traveller Women's Forum, in particular, Maria, would murder me if I did not talk about the intersectionality on a day such as International Women's Day.</p> <p>Reflecting on when we come together this time next year to speak on these issues, if there are a few things in that idea of us making progress it is the work led by the Minister for Justice, Deputy McEntee, but with me and other Departments feeding in as well in terms of the creation of a new domestic, sexual and gender-based violence, DSGBV, agency to focus all our response to DSGBV, to begin the process - it will only be beginning - of providing additional refuge space around the country, and the work I will be doing on delivering DSGBV leave.</p> <p>There will be significant further steps in terms of the affordability of childcare.  This is a long-term project.  We put a huge amount of extra money into it in this year's budget.  That is not enough and the Government does not believe that is enough.  There is real agreement across budget that more needs to be done in that context, that it is essential that breastfeeding breaks would be available for long periods of time and that we will be undertaking the work of giving a meaningful response to the recommendations of the Citizens' Assembly.  Being a multiplicity of recommendations, everyone accepts they will take time.  If we can be measured on those, that is worthwhile.</p> <p>Senator Ward spoke about the importance of men not stepping back from these issues.  I hope this time next year it will be judged that I and my Department have not stepped back and we have continued to advance these issues, that we can continue to see steady change in terms of Government policy and Ireland's approach to these issues, but always realising that the change that we need to make in terms of society's treatment of women is a systems change and that can be delivered.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" speakername="Mary Seery Kearney" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#X00400"><p>I acknowledge that on International Women's Day last year I asked the Minister for progress on surrogacy and provisions for women who are not acknowledged as the mothers of their children in Irish law.  I note that yesterday the members of the Oireachtas Joint Committee on International Surrogacy were announced.  I hope that next year I will be thanking the Minister when all of us are trotting off to the courts, getting our parental orders and being recognised in law.  I thank the Minister and Senators for a good debate.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.100" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#X00500">Brain Health and Dementia: Statements</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1641" speakername="Shane Cassells" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#X00600"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Butler, to the Chamber.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Shane Cassells:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2448"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2448&amp;amp;pid=ShaneCassells&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=09"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I note we had a very engaging debate yesterday in the audiovisual room with Ms Siobh&aacute;n O'Connor, CEO of the Alzheimer Society of Ireland, and many eminent speakers.  I thank the chair of the all-party committee, Senator O'Loughlin, for organising that and for the engagement that happened.  I ask the Minister of State to open the debate; she has eight minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1614" speakername="Mary Butler" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#Y00200"><p>Dia is Muire daoibh go l&eacute;ir.  T&aacute; an-&aacute;thas orm a bheith anseo.  I welcome the opportunity to update the House on the measures the Department of Health is taking to ensure older people in Ireland benefit from advances in modifying therapies and research around brain health and dementia.  I specifically welcome our visitors in the Gallery.  They are currently taking part in an Erasmus project on dementia rights.  We have representatives from Portugal, Spain, Greece and Turkey, in addition to St. Joseph's in Shankill, who are leading the way in the provision of dementia supports in Ireland.  They are all very welcome.  I also welcome my colleague, Deputy Cormac Devlin, who is present.</p> <p>I acknowledge at the outset the hard work that my other colleague, Senator O'Loughlin, is doing as chair of the all-party committee on dementia.  I previously co-chaired that committee with former Senator Colette Kelleher.  A lot of good work has been done.  I thank Senator O'Loughlin and all the people who engage on that committee.  Politics are left at the door and the only provision is to try to enhance the supports we have for people living with dementia in this country.  I thank the committee very much for that.</p> <p>I have long been an advocate for the development of dementia services and supports.  Since being appointed Minister of State with responsibility for this area, unprecedented levels of investment have been ring-fenced specifically for dementia services and supports in this country.  Sl&aacute;intecare reform is transforming how we deliver healthcare in Ireland.  It places people and their families at the centre of the health system.  Through the development of new models of care it will support older people, including those with dementia, to stay healthy in their homes and communities for as long as possible.  To support this reform, the National Dementia Office has been developing a model of care, which works towards the vision of the national dementia strategy 2014, of timely diagnosis for dementia and integrated post-diagnostic support, including for family carers.  With the prevalence of dementia expected to rise by 134% by 2045, it is essential we have these services in place.  The model of care will look at the needs of the person with dementia, with a strong focus on brain health interventions that can benefit the whole population.</p> <p>Disease-modifying therapy is a major goal for research around dementia.  Of the 126 agents currently under trial for Alzheimer's disease worldwide, about 83% are disease-modifying therapies.  The potential future impact of modifying therapies is very hopeful.  These treatments may allow us to treat, slow or prevent a disease that can be devastating for the people diagnosed and their families.  There is great optimism that these therapies will become available in the coming years.  Our health services will need to be ready for the potential future of these modifying therapies for dementia along with the projected increase in people living with dementia.  It is anticipated that the introduction of these therapies would result in increased referrals of people with cognitive difficulties to our services.  This will require future development of our diagnostic services, which will include neuroimaging and specialist testing.</p> <p>I was delighted to secure additional funding in 2021 and 2022 to develop a number of specialist diagnostic services throughout the country.  Of note, funding allocated across 2021 and 2022 will allow for the development of two specialist regional memory clinics in Cork and Galway and nine new memory assessment and support services.  Establishing these essential services will ensure that there is timely access to care and a reduction in waiting times.  Early diagnosis will be key in the treatment of dementia, with advances in modifying therapies and brain health interventions key tools to slow progression of the illness and maintain a person's quality of life.</p> <p>In June 2021, the National Dementia Office established an expert national working group consisting of two sub-groups: a diagnostic imaging sub-group and a disease-modifying treatments sub-group.  This group will consider the most likely near future disease-modifying therapies, additional neuroimaging requirements, such as MRIs, and other additional resources for implementing disease-modifying treatments.  When the moment comes that disease-modifying therapies are available to limit the impact of dementia, our healthcare services will be prepared.</p> <p>Recent areas of additional investment have also focused on brain health and reducing the risk of dementia.  It is estimated that up to 40% of dementia worldwide is preventable.  Recent funding has supported the dementia Understand Together campaign to improve public awareness and understanding of dementia, including how to reduce risk factors.  In 2022, additional funding will allow for the recruitment of a brain health project manager to support a dementia risk-reduction working group and collaborate with clinical programmes to promote brain health.  We should be encouraging the whole population to actively prioritise their own brain health.  A campaign on dementia and brain health will be run as part of brain awareness week from 14 to 20  March by the national risk-reduction working group to include key messages around brain health for the public through social media, press releases and newspapers.  National campaigns, such as Quit Smoking, Ask About Alcohol and healthy eating and active living campaigns, all help to address risk factors associated with dementia. </p> <p>Once people have received a diagnosis of dementia, additional supports are in place to support people with dementia to live well for as long as possible.  A key focal point of the post-diagnostic pathway is the dementia advisor service.  I was delighted to launch the expansion of the service in November 2021.  An additional 11 dementia advisors allowed this vital service to be expanded nationally.  I was delighted to build on the work of my predecessor, former Minister of State at the Department of Health, Jim Daly.  We had many conversations about increasing the number of dementia advisors and we now have 28 throughout the country, which is fantastic.</p> <p>Funding in 2021 also allowed for an enhancement of memory technology resource rooms.  These services provide practical ways of managing the challenges of dementia and improving independence, safety and quality of life through various assistive technologies and occupational therapy guidance.  I was delighted to travel to Tralee before Christmas to open the 30th memory technology resource room in Tralee, which was purpose-built.  We have come such a long way in the past four or five years.  To now have 30 memory technology rooms throughout the country is amazing.  I thank everyone who worked on that because it was a collaborative effort, which is fantastic to see.  In addition, the proportion of new home support hours that will be ring-fenced for people with dementia will more than double in 2022 to 11%.  This will provide support for family carers of loved ones living with dementia and enable people living with dementia to remain living in their own homes.</p> <p>To improve the outcomes for people living with dementia in acute care settings, I was pleased to secure additional funding through budget 2022 for the provision of a dementia assistant director of nursing post in each hospital group and four additional dementia clinical nurse specialist posts.  Funding in 2021 also allowed for the implementation of the national clinical guidelines on appropriate prescribing of psychotropic medication for non-cognitive symptoms in people with dementia.</p> <p>I will address more of the points when I reply to the debate later.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1641" speakername="Shane Cassells" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#Y00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State for all her work and her acknowledgement of the former Minister of State, Jim Daly, who was very well regarded.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#Y00400"><p>I thank the Acting Chairperson and the Leader of the House for giving us time to discuss this very important subject.  I thank the Minister of State for taking the time to attend this incredibly important debate.  I add my voice of welcome to Deputy Devlin, who plays a key part in the all-party committee, and to Ms Emma Balmaine and Ms Siobh&aacute;n Grant, together with Elaine and Norma, from St. Joseph's, Shankill.  I also welcome those who are representing Alzheimer Portugal, Alzheimer Hellas in Greece, the University of Oviedo in Spain, the institute of St. John of God, Portugal, and the Association of Social Inclusion and Education, BUHAYAD, in Turkey.</p> <p>As we know, and as the Minister of State has pointed out, St. Joseph's, Shankill, has vast experience in the field of dementia and is collaborating in the development of a charter of rights for people with dementia and their caregivers.  We all look forward to hearing and seeing the results of the Erasmus project and possibly having the opportunity to debate it, either within our all-party committee or back in the Chambers of Leinster House.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Fiona O'Loughlin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2441"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2441&amp;amp;pid=FionaOLoughlin&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=09"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It has been a privilege to initiate this debate as chair of the all-party group on dementia.  Today, we speak in the House on behalf of more than 64,000 people in Ireland who are living with dementia and, of course, their families who are bearing the brunt of caring.<br/><br/>At the outset, I pay tribute to the Alzheimer Society of Ireland, ASI, for organising such a moving and empowering briefing for us in the audiovisual room yesterday and for the incredible work and support it offers to people with dementia and their families.  It was clear from that briefing that significant strides have been made in the area of brain health and dementia in this country.  I thank Professor Sean Kennelly, Professor Mary McCarron, Professor Iracema Leroy and Samantha Taylor from the ASI, as well as the strong and powerful dementia advocates, Kevin Quaid and Helen Rochford-Brennan.<br/><br/>It may be a surprise to many that, according to the WHO, up to 40% of dementia cases are potentially preventable if we work to support and maintain our brain health.  We can all take action to protect our brain health.  Dementia has become much less taboo thankfully in recent years, which is very important in terms of early intervention.  In years gone by, dementia was a hush-hush disease.  People did not talk about it and many were afraid of what others might think, how they might be viewed, how their lives would change, and that people would see the dementia and not the person.  However, as was eloquently presented in yesterday's briefing by Professor Leroy, advancing the historical journey of dementia is key in achieving a dementia-free society.  We have now become a dementia friendly society, and that is clear from the work the Minister of State has done and from the commitments she achieved in budget 2022.  I pay tribute to her for the clear focus in last September's budget for this year on enhancing community-based services to enable older people to continue living in their homes with dignity and independence for as long as possible.<br/><br/>The &euro;150 million funding secured in 2021 for 5 million additional hours of home support has been maintained for this year.  In addition, the proportion of these new home support hours that will be ring-fenced for people with dementia, will more than double from 5% in 2021 to 11% in 2022, which is just incredible, and we want to see that maintained in years to come.  I got a strong message from Siobhan O'Connor from the Alzheimer Society of Ireland to press that point today.  For many people and their families, the option to remain in their homes is key to their quality of life.  I thank the Minister of State for engaging with us and other stakeholders, for listening and delivering for those living with dementia.<br/><br/>I know there has been talk about and work done in extending the fair deal scheme to homecare in the home.  I would appreciate if the Minister of State could give an update on that, because it is a very important piece of the jigsaw.  Points were very well made at her briefing yesterday, notwithstanding the excellent work that nursing homes do in terms of caring for their patients, that stimulating patients, particularly those with dementia, is hugely important, as is looking at different models, such as the butterfly model used in St. Joseph's in Shankill.  In addition, the extra education for those in the health business and nursing for dealing with patients with dementia is very important.<br/><br/>In many cases, dementia is preventable and while being a dementia-friendly society is important, we need to move to a healthy brain society.  We need to focus on preventive measures and working on our brain health to ensure that we achieve a healthy brain society and, therefore, delay the onset of dementia.  According to The Value of Delaying Alzheimer&rsquo;s Disease Onset report of 2014, any intervention that delays the onset of dementia caused by Alzheimer's disease for five years, will result in 41% lower prevalence of dementia and the associated cost will reduce by 40% by 2050.<br/><br/>We all know the importance of a healthy heart, maintaining healthy cholesterol levels and exercise to support cardiovascular health, but do any of us really know how to maintain brain health?  Do we even know what it is?  We need to support a mass communication campaign on the importance of brain health and how to promote healthy brain function.  Brain health is the preservation of optimal brain integrity, mental and cognitive function, and the absence of overt neurological disorders.  The landmark report of <i>The Lancet </i>concluded that 40% of dementia is due to just 12 risk factors, such as a lack of physical activity, smoking, social isolation and many others.  This shows that we can and we must do everything we can as a legislative executive body and as a society to tackle those factors head-on.<br/><br/>There is no doubt that we can reduce the prevalence of dementia in our society, but we must act now.  I am confident that the Minister of State will be the Minister who makes the difference.  I am proud of what we, the Fianna F&aacute;il Party, have already achieved through her and the Minister, Deputy Stephen Donnelly, in Government in terms of delivering the enhanced memory technology resource rooms on nine sites, dementia diagnostic services delivered through a specialist regional memory clinic in Cork, four new memory assessment and support services in Mayo, Wexford, Waterford and Sligo, and the enhancement of acute care pathways for people with dementia through the recruitment of more clinical nurse specialists.<br/><br/>What was clear from yesterday's briefing, particularly from the contribution of Kevin Quaid, was the fight, grit and determination of those living with dementia to advance the cause and to push for treatment, innovation and preventive actions.  Again, I have no doubt - no pressure - in the Minister of State's ability to drive this forward.  I appreciate the Acting Chair's indulgence.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1641" speakername="Shane Cassells" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#Z00200"><p>As acknowledged already, Senator O'Loughlin is chair of the all-party committee, and I thank her for her work in that regard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#Z00300"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it.  The Minister of State is very welcome.  I apologise in advance for the fact that I will not be able to stay to hear her response, but I will certainly read it later, because this is an important debate.  I compliment all who have been responsible for bringing it to the floor today, including Senator O'Loughlin and her committee, which I commend for its important work, and the organisations and people who advocate on the issue of brain health for people with dementia, in particular, the Alzheimer Society of Ireland and champions, such as Helen Rochford-Brennan, who have been mentioned and rightly so.  I pay tribute to their important work in growing awareness.</p> <p>I can remember when I started thinking about this issue properly a number of years ago.  The figure at the time was 50,000 people and I remember it being said that the figure would grow to 150,000 within a couple of decades.  We all know why that is the case, or at least we know some of the reasons, such as the fact that people are living longer, and the population and demographic trends make that inevitable to a degree.  However, it is interesting that the figure is no longer 50,000.  Now we are in the 60,000s and we are talking about an increase of 11,000 a year in the number of people getting a diagnosis or living with dementia of one kind or another.  That highlights the importance of this issue, not just for those who might be affected, by that I include those who are living with and caring for persons living with dementia, but for wider society.  This includes everything from health budgets to the care demands being made on society as a whole, and the loss of opportunity in terms of the talent and the ability a person loses to contribute to the working world when he or she is affected by a diagnosis.  It is very important that we as a society recognise what remains.  What remains is a person with real dignity and, in the words of Professor Des O&rsquo;Neill, who has done wonderful work in the area of gerontological care, the inner life of the person.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2250"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2250&amp;amp;pid=RonanMullen&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=09"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I sometimes think that we talk too much about our personal experiences as politicians when it comes to these kinds of debates.  On the one hand, we are conscious of how these issues connect us with others when we have that experience ourselves but we are all tempted as politicians to engage in personal discussion to an extent that sometimes could border on narcissism.  That is a temptation we all have to resist.</p><p>Nonetheless, in my own experience of being part of a family caring for my father through his near decade of dementia, I learned an awful lot.  I learned a lot about my own capacity to make mistakes, to fail to recognise my father's inner life, perhaps my own fears and unwillingness to accept the limitations that had come into his life and, by definition, into our relationship with him.  I am also glad to say that I learned, as I think we did as a family, how to love my father more in a way that I had not learned throughout our life up to that point and we had a good family relationship.</p><p>In reflecting on what people like Professor Des O'Neill have to say about respecting the inner life of the person or in other words, respecting the person's capacity to express their will, desire and needs even at a point where we think they are no longer capable of making those kinds of decisions is a real challenge.  We see that in our advanced-care related legislation that we are moving from a rigid ward-based model of dealing with a person to a situation where you assess the person in his or her individuality and needs and the kind of assistance he or she needs with decision-making and at what point and what decisions.  You are dealing with a much more kaleidoscopic picture.  I think that applies when we think of dementia and how we care for persons with dementia.  I still have moments when I find myself worrying whether I was too interventionist.  Was I too much of a dictator in the way that I cared for my dad?  I even worry about the way I was feeding him on the day he died.  Because there were times when you just had to make decisions because it was what good care required.  Yet even in those moments you found yourself wondering "am I dealing with my own impatience today?  Am I dealing with my own frustration today?" rather than what my father would have needed in that situation.  There is a real need to always be ready to learn; to learn to shut up, to not just contradict or bring the facts when something mistaken or erroneous is said.  At the same time you have to forgive yourself for the moments when you are just human and you fail to be as patient or selfless as you ought to be.  And you must also recognise that there are moments where you have to make the best decision you can in the circumstances.  We have learned a great deal about moving away from coercive care to that more reflective approach.  That is really important.</p><p>It is also really important for society that we think about how we think about dementia, as well as frailty and dependency of other kinds.  It intersects with that very difficult debate around euthanasia and assisted suicide, which comes up from time to time.  Very often those debates start out from a place of fear where we, in the whole of our health, say "I would hate to be in this situation".  I think what we learn when it comes to palliative care, and I was involved in doing a report for the Council of Europe on that, and dealing with dementia, we need to learn to not presume about how things might be in the future.  Through accompanying those affected, we can perhaps learn something about our own future frailty and how we would like to be able to cope with it ourselves.  I saw with my father, that he would not have liked to think in advance about the level of dependency he was going to have on his family and loved ones in the future in their giving of intimate care and so on.  Yet, as I can say looking back, as I would have said on the day of his funeral, that many people looking in from the outside would say that it is a terrible affliction and even that can be stigmatising.  It can be very difficult where there is change in personality and where there is anger and all sorts of things where you just have to say "this is not the person I love.  It is not them".  We have to try and understand that.  Nevertheless, there are also moments of laughter and joy.  There was tremendous consolation for us in the fact that we worked to keep our dad as happy on the outside as he appeared to be on the inside.  In that way, we had it very good.  We also received great support from the State and from the Alzheimer Society of Ireland.  It may be uneven across the country, and there may be patchiness that needs to be addressed, but there are other areas where people are dependent with sickness or other kinds of disability where the services might not be as good or available.  We have to be open to that.</p><p>We must never presume too much about what it is like.  We must work to grow in our understanding but to always recognise that there continues to be that dignity in the person in ageing and where dementia is.  There is dependency but there is also dignity.  There is also an inner life and a need to respect that inner life that continues, that is not over. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1641" speakername="Shane Cassells" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#AA00200"><p>I thank Senator Mullen for detailing his own experience.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#AA00300"><p>It is humbling listening to Senator Mullen sharing his experience of the on-the-ground reality of his father having dementia.  I regularly spoke to him in the latter years of his father's life.  R&oacute;n&aacute;n always bore the challenge, which it is and was, with dignity and compassion.  I really admired the way he and his family did that over the years.  It is a lesson to everyone.  It is not the end of the world.  There are ways and means.  It is a matter of being creative and different and thinking outside the box.  It is heartening to hear the Alzheimer Society of Ireland and the State agencies were able to give assistance.  Services probably are patchy around the country.  We all receive calls from people who are very frustrated particularly in the early stages when they are trying to put a care plan together.  That is very difficult.  First, people have to accept the new reality and that it will become progressively worse.  I am very happy that two new memory clinics are to open.  That is good news.  That is in addition to the diagnostic services it has improved enormously in recent years and State funding has improved enormously too.  It is an ageing population and we will have many more people who will suffer from dementia.  I was not at the briefing yesterday because of other commitments.  However, I am fully aware of the work that is being done by the phenomenal volunteers and the dedicated people, as well as the people who are suffering from dementia who want things to change for them.</p> <p>There is also a lesson about lifestyle.  It is about people working towards preventing dementia and acute dementia.  It is about trying not to drink too much, not smoke and try to live a healthy lifestyle.  That applies to many things but particularly dementia.  Research has shown that the onset of dementia could be reduced by 40% or 60% and it takes longer if people have lived a healthy lifestyle.  When people are diagnosed that is the critical time.  That is when they need the care plan and the support.  I often say when someone has been diagnosed with something that is life-changing, the initial step-down engagement is extremely important.  I have campaigned successfully in this House to have five clinical liaison contacts appointed around the country.  I think one will be appointed in Waterford very soon.  The same kind of model is needed, regardless of whether people are diagnosed with cardiac problems, dementia, blindness or deafness.  There needs to be a caring human being who knows how to navigate the system and how to advise a family who might not necessarily have dealt with that before and would not necessarily have had any knowledge or experience or a family member with knowledge or experience.  That needs to be there.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Martin Conway:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2347"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2347&amp;amp;pid=MartinConway&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=09"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The State needs to fund those advisers to hold out the hand of love, tell people what the range of services are and advise them on whether A, B or C suits them better than D, E or F.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" speakername="Mary Seery Kearney" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#BB00200"><p>I congratulate the Minister of State on the significant amount of work that she and her predecessor and my party colleague, former Deputy Jim Daly, have done.  The concept of brain health is important.  During Covid in particular, we have had many conversations about mental health.  If I sprain my leg, it will swell, I will not be able to walk on it and I will be in pain.  How do we know when we are affecting our brain health and mental health and what the differences and correlations between the two are?  Work needs to be done through an information campaign and by resourcing people to look after themselves.  We know about eating better, getting more exercise, not over-drinking - or not drinking at all - and not smoking.  These are things that we know to do but we do not know, and are not resourced or equipped, when it comes to mental health and brain health.</p> <p>Turning to dementia, I thank Senator Mullen.  Apart from the sharing of the experience, his sense of self-reflection and reflective practice within the care of his father is a good model and template for others.  I am sure it reflects the experience of other families as they second-guess themselves in their love, compassion and service of the people whom they love.</p> <p>The prospect of dementia is a frightening one.  While accepting all that has already been done, I urge us to consider from a policy perspective whether we are co-producing mental health and research programmes, capturing in our research the lived experience of those who have dementia and their families and carers, and using it to inform our policy.  How are we gathering data?  Are we gathering data?  We must look through the correct lens when considering our policy and practices.  Organisations like the Alzheimer Society of Ireland are at the table, but we must ensure the idea of nothing about us without us is practised and that our policies are based on their perspectives.  I hear that in the programmes that the Government is rolling out.</p> <p>Are there social care programmes that we could be running in other areas, for example, youth work and community groups, that would give information, talk about the experience, take away the fear and point to how we have significant interventions and how there have been considerable developments in medical treatments?  In this way, we could ensure that we were equipping all actors dealing with dementia with information on all of these experiences and that our policy on resourcing those actors reflected what they needed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#BB00300"><p>It is good to see the Minister of State.  She is always welcome.  I will begin by acknowledging the good work she has done in this area.</p> <p>According to the Alzheimer Society of Ireland, there are more than 64,000 people living with dementia in Ireland.  The estimate is that 141,000 people will be living with dementia by 2050.  These are stark figures.  Research tells us that not all dementia can be prevented, and while not all the research and evidence is exactly clear on what dementia prevention works, many evidence reviews provide useful guidance and have identified important factors that, if addressed, could modify dementia risk by up to 40%.  These include health behaviour factors, cardiovascular factors, psychosocial factors and developmental factors.  Some of these are common health problems that we are familiar with, for example, hypertension, hearing impairment, obesity, depression and diabetes.  There are also lifestyle and socio-economic factors such as lower levels of education in early life, social contact in later life, smoking and excessive alcohol consumption.  In particular, lack of physical activity can, if addressed, improve brain health as well as helping with cardiovascular health, mental health and mobility in later years.  We know that if we are to modify dementia risk, addressing these factors needs to start in middle-aged people, not among older people.  Most of these risk factors are preventable and treatable with a healthy lifestyle and proper access to healthcare.  The first point that springs to my mind is the relationship between some of these risk factors and poverty and access to health care.</p> <p>I wish to speak about intellectual disability as a particular risk factor.  Professor Mary McCarron, who spoke at the all-party Oireachtas group briefing yesterday, highlighted that, for people with intellectual disabilities, the risk of developing dementia was five times greater than for their peers in the general population.  Many people with Down's syndrome have the hallmarks of Alzheimer's disease by 40 years of age and have an 88% risk of developing the clinical symptoms of dementia by age 65.  As such, the promotion of brain health and the diagnosis of disease must begin at early ages.</p> <p>Toxic proteins that cause Alzheimer's disease build and accumulate up to 15 to 25 years before clinical symptoms present, but cognitive reserve education, exercise, cognitive stimulation and social engagement at any age will help to slow or counteract these changes.  It is possible to reduce the risk of dementia.</p> <p>Actions to promote brain health in people with intellectual disabilities is needed now and at all ages.  I acknowledge the Minister of State's work, particularly her support for the development of the national intellectual disability memory service for people with intellectual disabilities.  Further memory support services are needed throughout Ireland and I hope she will provide more services and funding to address the particular risk of dementia for people with intellectual disabilities, who have an increased risk of developing dementia.</p> <p>Awareness is important in dementia prevention.  I acknowledge the work of the Understand Together campaign, the Alzheimer Society of Ireland and the all-party Oireachtas group on dementia.  However, it is important that Government policy does not just talk about brain health and dementia prevention, but also actively seeks to improve our health system to support those prevention measures.</p> <p>Severe brain injury is a risk factor for dementia.  Recently, my Sinn F&eacute;in colleague, an Teachta D&aacute;la Cullinane, highlighted the lack of neurology nurses.  By the HSE's own reckoning, we only have approximately 30% of the specialist neurology nurses that we need, which is making their job difficult.  We need 100 more.  University Hospital Limerick is the mid-west regional centre for neurology but it is short on neurology nurse specialists.  Patients are unnecessarily waiting longer for diagnoses and treatment.  Based on the catchment area, national and international guidelines recommend that there should be 11 neurology nurse specialists, but there are only three.  Patients deserve better and I hope that we will hear a positive response in terms of how this issue is being addressed locally in Limerick and nationally.</p> <p>There are many problems in our health service that will hinder the prevention of dementia.  There is a large gap in the provision of mental health services across the country, shockingly long waiting lists for outpatient hospital appointments and GP shortages.  None of this is helpful when we are talking about addressing risk factors for dementia or minding our brain health.</p> <p>During the pandemic, day care centres for people with dementia were closed.  This put considerable pressure on carers, with many telling us that they were at breaking point.  Most of the centres have reopened, but I hope that more will be done to increase the number of day care centres and services in the community.  They are important not only to people with dementia, but to their families and carers, who need this support.  The work of carers was highlighted over the past couple of tough years and we need to do better for them.</p> <p>Preventing dementia means promoting brain health and preventing common risk factors.  It also means tackling the wider issues of poverty and the healthcare crisis.  Awareness of the risk factors can be helpful in the first instance and I do not want to take away from the good work that has been done, but there is clearly much more to do.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1663" speakername="Annie Hoey" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#BB00400"><p>I welcome the Minister of State.</p> <p>This is an important topic and it is great that people have spoken about us moving towards being a dementia-friendly society.  Like some others, I attended yesterday's briefing, which was organised by Senator O'Loughlin, on the topic of dementia and brain health.  It was an eye-opening experience for me.  Many young people tend to think of dementia as being far away and as having nothing to do with them because they are invincible and will skip through life without having to worry about it.  Hearing about some of the measures we could take at every age to help our brain health was interesting, so I thank Senator O'Loughlin for organising the briefing.</p> <p>Senator Mullen has left the Chamber, but I thank him for speaking so eloquently about caring for and loving his father during his illness due to Alzheimer's disease.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Annie Hoey:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=AnnieHoey&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=09"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I know the bond and closeness created when one shifts from being a child to being the carer of a parent.  It is an experience like no other.</p><p>Given that we have just completed the statements on International Women's Day 2022, it would be apt to think about how dementia disproportionately affects women.  I know at the presentation yesterday it was said that 65% of people living with dementia are women.  As we know, women are in the majority among those who provide all aspects of caring, formally and informally.  As I said, we tend to think of dementia as being other or happening to someone else, far away from us, and not as something that will affect us.  People with dementia are individuals in their own right.  They have rights.  In the past, the issue was pushed away and dealt with elsewhere.  There were two people with different forms of dementia at yesterday's briefing.  They talked about living their own lives fully, their empowerment and experiences.  That made me shift my thinking in terms of who has dementia and what a dementia sufferer looks like.</p><p>Another thing I took away from yesterday's briefing was the message that brain health affects us all.  We have a responsibility as public representatives, as has the Minister of State's Department, to spread awareness around brain health, both our future selves and for society at large.  Some people have talked about the possibility of cutting costs by delaying the onset of dementia by five years and so on.  We have also talked about the fact that evidence suggests up to 40% of dementia is potentially preventable.  Representatives of the Alzheimer's Society of Ireland told me yesterday that they are delighted with the funding for the brain health project manager in the dementia office within the HSE.  As I have said already, the important element in that regard is that brain health is an issue for young people.  There are steps or actions that those of us in our 20s, 30s and 40s can take in order to reduce the risk and hopefully delay symptoms of dementia.</p><p>I was trying to think of the appropriate phrase and having discounted "changeable factors" and "moveable factors", I got to grips with "modifiable risk factors".  Such factors include smoking, obesity, alcohol, exercise and hearing loss.  I was struck by the importance of making sure to stay on top of one's blood pressure.  It occurred to me I do not even know how to get a blood pressure test.  As a young person, I have never had my blood pressure tested.  I do not know how I would go about doing that.  I will ask my GP the next time I am in.  As a young person, that is not something I have had to do.  I do not get check-ups on a regular basis.  That has gone into my mind.</p><p>I was also struck yesterday by the fact that social isolation and a lack of social connection are risk factors.  That is important as we emerge from the pandemic.  Social isolation is very bad for our brain health.  As we emerge from the pandemic, we need to think about that.  We need to consider it individually and reflect on who is socially isolated in our networks and communities.  Social isolation is also an issue for Government.  We need a national conversation around tackling loneliness and social isolation.  We must create connections.</p><p>I keep mentioning things that struck me yesterday but it was a very striking session.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1671" speakername="Erin McGreehan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#CC00200"><p>It was.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1663" speakername="Annie Hoey" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#CC00300"><p>Another of the things that struck me was the link between hearing loss and the development of dementia.  I was surprised to hear that.  I looked it up afterwards because I wanted to know what the story with it is.  A 2020 report in <i>The Lancet</i>highlighted that people who live with hearing loss have a greater risk of developing dementia.  That is something I would not have had a clue about.  I did not know anything about it.  A message for us all today is that we need to get our hearing tested in the same manner in which we get our eyes tested, particularly as we age.  That was a good example of modifiable risk factors about which we do not know.  We tend to think that dementia is an old person's disease, that it is far away and there is nothing anyone can do in their 20s, 30 or 40s to take proactive steps to try to reduce the risk.  We should all get our hearing tested.</p><p>As we move into being a dementia-friendly society, the idea of opening up a conversation about brain health is a useful one.  It was not something with which I was overly familiar.  Yesterday, when I went home, I was googling how to look after my brain health.  I wanted to know if we should be doing Sudoku or what might help to stretch our brains.  I was struck that it is all about the daily things we are told to do and look after, including exercise, social connection, reducing our alcohol consumption and not smoking.  We always think about some of those things as part of our physical health.  I never understood the link between them and brain health.  I again thank Senator O'Loughlin for organising that briefing yesterday.  It was incredibly helpful for me in how I think about my own health and that of our communities, and health in general.  I also thank the Minister for Health for all the work she is doing in this area.  It is an important topic.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1632" speakername="Frances Black" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#CC00400"><p>I warmly welcome the Minister of State to the Chamber.  This is a very important debate on which I am glad to make a contribution.  I thank Senator O'Loughlin for all her work in this area.  I also commend and acknowledge the ongoing work of the all-party Oireachtas group on dementia, which I believe was established by the Minister of State and former Senator Colette Kelleher.  I know this is an area about which the Minister of State is very passionate.  She has done phenomenal work in the area.</p> <p>There are many people across this island living with dementia and they deserve our support every day of the year, not just during brain health week.  I want to highlight the figures that others have highlighted.  Some 64,000 people in Ireland currently live with dementia.  Those numbers are predicted to rise to 150,000 by 2050, which is shocking.  It is essential that we adequately plan to support these people who are our loved ones, parents, siblings and partners.</p> <p>I will also use the opportunity presented by brain health week to once again raise the urgent issue of adult safeguarding.  I have spoken many times in this Chamber about the urgent need for the Government to progress adult safeguarding legislation to support and safeguard adults across the State who are at risk of abuse.  Adults at risk of abuse include those living with dementia.  Indeed, those living with dementia are likely to be impacted more by particular forms of abuse.  It is important that we develop legislation which safeguards and supports the rights of all adults living with dementia.</p> <p>I will read out some facts and statistics from the most recent annual report of the national safeguarding office of the HSE.  In 2020, there were 3,412 notifications of safeguarding concerns for persons aged over 65.  For those people aged over 65, the most significant categories of alleged abuse are psychological abuse, physical abuse and financial abuse.  Alleged financial abuse and neglect increase with age, with the highest level of reporting in those over 80 years of age.  Among those aged over 65, it was immediate family members who were most commonly the subject of safeguarding concerns, which is very sad, to be honest.  The rate of alleged abuse of adults aged 65 or over is more than double that for younger adults.</p> <p>As the prevalence of dementia increases dramatically for those over 65 years of age, we must, therefore, consider how adult safeguarding can support the rights of those living with dementia.  The HSE safeguarding report also notes that persons with dementia were significantly impacted by the pandemic, as I am sure we are all aware, and all the disruptions to care that resulted from it.  The importance of adult safeguarding legislation was highlighted by the situation in nursing homes during the pandemic and we heard recently that a wrongful death claim had been lodged against a nursing home in Cork in respect of a 64-year-old mother of three living with dementia who died of Covid-19 while in that nursing home.  Those living with dementia have a higher rate of Covid-19 and so failures in care have very serious consequence in this context.</p> <p>Introducing rights-based and person-centred adult safeguarding legislation is going to be key, going forward.  The Law Reform Commission review of adult safeguarding legislation is due to be completed soon.  I urge the Government to progress that legislation as soon as possible.</p> <p>Aside from legislative steps we can take to safeguard and support the rights of those living with dementia, we can also implement a number of practical measures to improve the experiences of people living with dementia in our healthcare system.  I welcome the Government's announcement last week of a new programme to upskill healthcare workers in dementia care.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Frances Black:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2474"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2474&amp;amp;pid=FrancesBlack&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=09"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is essential that healthcare workers are trained and supported to develop competency in dementia care.  This is in line with the national dementia strategy and I am very happy to see that being rolled out.  I hope it will not only be continued but expanded as time goes on.  However, more can still be done at a practical level within the health system and our hospitals.  For example, in an article which appeared in <i>The Irish Times</i>this week, Professor Rose Anne Kenny, a geriatrician, called for dedicated spaces and systems in emergency departments for older people, which is a wonderful idea.  She notes that some older patients have intimidating or frightening experiences in emergency departments where they may not be able to clearly hear or understand questions and communications.  Some may be confused as a result of their illnesses, while others may be living with chronic cognitive issues such as dementia.  I remember bringing my mother into hospital and seeing elderly people wandering around the hospital, not knowing whether they were coming or going and not knowing where to go.  It is very frightening.  <br/><br/>I cannot speak on dementia and brain health today without bringing up the issue of carers and our duty to support them.  It has been acknowledged that the bulk of care for people with dementia in Ireland is being provided free of charge by family caregivers, many of whom are adult children and spouses.  The value of informal care for those with dementia is estimated at &euro;807 million per annum.  The widening of the eligibility net for carer's allowance last year was very welcome but as was highlighted by Family Carers Ireland, the additional &euro;5 per week simply did not go far enough.  I ask the Government to review the allowance to see how it can be increased and to outline what other innovative measures could be considered to support those who give care free of charge to their loved ones living with dementia.<br/><br/>Positive steps are being taken to support those living with dementia and I know how passionately the Minister of State feels about the issue.  While the national dementia strategy is progressing, the Government needs to prioritise adult safeguarding legislation.  The Government must consider what particular provisions should be included in future adult safeguarding legislation to support the rights of those living with dementia.  I also ask it to consider the other practical steps that can be taken within our health services for those living with dementia, how supports can be expanded for our carers and how we can tackle early risk factors for dementia by improving child safety online, an issue I would love to discuss further with the Minister of State at some point in the future.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1671" speakername="Erin McGreehan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#DD00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House today for this very positive and timely debate on how best to move forward in this country in looking after people with dementia and on the wider topic of brain health.  Senator Hoey referred to the briefing we attended yesterday which was so positive and enlightening.  I learned so much from it and got a different view of how to care for my own health and that of my parents and my partner.  It was really enlightening and I thank those who organised it.</p> <p>I want to acknowledge the work that the Minister of State has done since assuming office and the work of my party colleague, Senator O'Loughlin, as chair of the all-party Oireachtas group on dementia  and Alzheimer's disease.  As a member of that group, it has been a pleasure to work with all of the members alongside the Alzheimer Society of Ireland.  The Minister of State served as chair of that group previously and what better ministerial post to have, having worked so hard on this issue?  She has brought forward many of the proposals made at meetings of the group.  </p> <p>Senator Mullen spoke passionately, kindly and delicately about his experience of caring for his father when he developed Alzheimer's disease.  A diagnosis of Alzheimer's disease or dementia can be so frightening for the individual and his or her family.  People wonder how they are going to give the individual the life they deserve and how they will meet all of life's struggles and challenges in the context of the diagnosis.  </p> <p>One of the main messages from yesterday's meeting was that there is so much hope.  It was so positive and empowering.  The briefing outlined what we can do to prevent dementia, what we can do to help and what is happening in the area of research to make outcomes better in the future.  Alzheimer's disease and dementia affect so many families and communities.  There are over 64,000 people in Ireland currently living with dementia, with the numbers predicted to rise to 150,000 by 2050.</p> <p>It is very important to acknowledge the family carers, who are often women.  Having just had statements on International Women's Day, it is important to acknowledge that most family carers and home carers in this country are women.  We must all support advancing the rights of carers.  Another strong message from yesterday's briefing was that up 40% of dementia could be preventable.  It is important to address early risk factors such as hearing loss, high blood pressure, diabetes, smoking and depression.  There are interventions that can reverse cognitive decline through education, exercise, stimulation, and social engagement.  Further to this, there is a suite of significant new medical treatments becoming available which slow down early onset.</p> <p>Addressing Oireachtas Members yesterday, the consultant physician in geriatric and stroke medicine at Tallaght Hospital Professor Sean Kennelly said that dementia is the most significant health condition globally for which we have no definitive treatments but that we are on the cusp of a new era of better interventions to prevent, diagnose and treat Alzheimer&rsquo;s disease and other dementias.  He added that it is imperative that we educate people in order that they understand what a brain-healthy lifestyle is and they take action to reduce the risks.  Despite all of the struggles and the very real difficulties and challenges faced by those with dementia and Alzheimer's disease, there was such optimism at that briefing yesterday about working on brain health.  </p> <p>I really welcome the Minister of State's work on brain health awareness.  A new working group has been convened by the national dementia office.  The HSE's health and well-being unit will run a brain health awareness week in March and will collate important information on brain health from a public attitude survey on dementia.  In addition, the brain health project manager will commence work in 2022 to support the delivery of those actions recommended by the working group and will support national campaigns and programmes to incorporate dementia risk reduction.  There is so much work being done, with much more to do.  I congratulate the Minister of State on securing additional funding for 11 new dementia advisers.  I acknowledge the work done by the Minister of State, the Alzheimer Society of Ireland and all of the people across the nation who are working really hard, not least the family carers.  I also acknowledge the patients with dementia who are upping their own marks and making their own brain health better every single day.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-09a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1695" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030900002#DD00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State, Deputy Butler, for coming to the House to discuss this all-important topic.  Having served on the all-party group previously with her, I am fully aware of her dedication to the area.  I also thank Senator O'Loughlin for organising the briefing yesterday on behalf of the all-party group.  It really was a very enlightening briefing, particularly with regard to brain health and preventative measures in the context of dementia.  The importance of feeding the brain and making sure that it and the heart are healthy were two clear takeaway messages from the briefing.</p> <p>I pay tribute to the many carers who look after their loved ones at home.  The longer we can keep people at home, the better.  I welcome the increased funding and additional home care hours for people with dementia that the Minister of State announced recently.  The longer we can keep people at home, in familiar surroundings, the better.  </p></speech>
</publicwhip>