<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.2" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 14:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.4" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.5" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900003#B00100"><p>I have received notice from Senator John Whelan that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:<blockquote><br />The plans the Minister for Justice and Equality has to relocate the Portlaoise courthouse to a new and more appropriate premises and location as its present position on Main Street is no longer appropriate or fit for purpose and is completely disruptive on the main thoroughfare of the county town.</blockquote></p> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Jillian van Turnhout of the following matter:<blockquote><br />The need for the Minister for Justice and Equality to ensure that the revised EU Data Protection Directive-Regulation does not impair the right of the citizen to engage in bona fide genealogical, biographical or historical research and that the principle of public ownership and right of access to our genealogical heritage will be enshrined as a guiding principle.</blockquote>I have also received notice from Senator Paschal Mooney of the following matter: <blockquote>The strategy, if any, the Government has to prevent the spread of Japanese Knot Weed along Irish roadways and if he will provide a policy which will oblige local authorities to address this matter.</blockquote>I have also received notice from Senator Denis Landy of the following matter:<blockquote>The need for the Minister for Finance to carry out a full review across all rates of value-added tax in order to examine the scope of implementing a fairer system than that currently in place, particularly in view of the fact that the reduced rate on tourism is proving successful but is due to be reviewed in the medium term.</blockquote>I have also received notice from Senator Averil Power of the following matter:<blockquote>The need for the Minister for Education and Skills to amend the current regulations for third level fees in order that someone who acquires Irish citizenship during his or her period of study can have his or her fee status changed from that point forward. </blockquote>I have also received notice from Senator Denis O'Donovan of the following matter: <blockquote>The need for the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport to make a statement on the withdrawal of the bus service serving Ballinspittle, Garretstown and the Old Head of Kinsale in County Cork.</blockquote>I have also received notice from Senator Mary Moran of the following matter:<blockquote>The need for the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government to address the concerns of the residents in an estate in Dundalk (details supplied), the ongoing issues of anti-social behaviour and why requests to have a wall heightened to deter such behaviour were denied by Louth County Council despite a recent plebiscite.</blockquote>I regard the matters raised by Senators Whelan, van Turnhout, Mooney and Landy  as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment and they will be taken at the conclusion of business. </p><p> I regret I have had to rule out of order the matter raised by Senator O'Donovan as the Minister has no official responsibility in the matter.  I also regret I have had to rule out of order the matter raised by Senator Moran as the Minister has no official responsibility in the matter.  Senator Power may give notice on another day of the matter she wishes to raise.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.8" nospeaker="true" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900004#C00200">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900004#C00300"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, motion re the Electricity Regulation Act 1999 (Restricted Electrical Works) Regulations 2013, to be taken at the conclusion of the Order of Business, without debate, and No. 2, Land and Conveyancing Law Reform Bill 2013 - Second Stage, to be taken at the conclusion of No. 1 and conclude not later than 5.45 p.m., with the contributions of group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes and those of all other Senators not to exceed five minutes and the Minister to be called on to reply not later than 5.35 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900004#C00400"><p>I propose an amendment to the Order of Business, to delete No. 2, because so far the Leader and the Government have refused permission to allow the Seanad to discuss the revised code of conduct on mortgage arrears.  In the absence of that discussion and in the absence of taking that document seriously, the repossession Bill which the Government is putting forward is an outrage.  It is about time some people in Fine Gael and the Labour Party started to examine their consciences on that Bill, because it will directly allow approximately 71,000 family homes to be repossessed.  We estimate the number of arrears cases to be 142,118, about half of which will be open to repossession under the code of conduct on mortgage arrears and under the Bill, which will revise the Dunne judgment.</p><p>It is interesting to note that the Dunne judgment is still before the Supreme Court and instead of legislating for that case the Government is legislating against it.  We need a full debate on the code of conduct long before we come to the repossessions Bill.  It is two years since the Family Home Bill, proposed by Senator Marc MacSharry and I, was introduced.  At the time the Minister of State at the Department of Finance, Deputy Brian Hayes, promised that action would be taken within months but instead what we have been told is that time and again the banks have been asked what they want and have been told they will be accommodated.</p> <p>That is the Government's attitude to the repossession of family homes.  It is a wrong attitude, however, and will have serious consequences for families in Ireland once the House passes the measure, as presumably it will.  The Government parties have not examined their conscience on the issue, so it will become law and the repossessions will start.  The banks will then have what they want.  That is my proposal on the Order of Business.</p><p>There is a second issue on which we need to have a debate here.  Time and again, the Taoiseach has alleged in the D&aacute;il that the file on the bank guarantee in the Department of the Taoiseach has been, and I quote him, &quot;shredded&quot;, &quot;disposed of&quot; or &quot;dispatched with&quot;.  It would be important for this House to examine the Taoiseach's words and other similar allegations he has made, particularly concerning the file that does exist in his Department, and the list of documents that Fianna F&aacute;il received from that file.</p><p>The Taoiseach says one thing, while on the other hand a freedom of information request proves that there is quite a large file in his Department.  That discrepancy requires a full debate here.  We need to know what the position is with the file, why the Taoiseach makes these allegations or seems to be unaware of what the position is in his Department, when the freedom of information section is able to find a complete file there on the matter.  The public deserves a full debate and the House should have such a debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900005#D00200"><p>This is a particularly busy week with six pieces of legislation before the House.  The Leader will respond to Senator Byrne's comments about the proposed amendment to the Order of Business.  This afternoon, however, we will be dealing with the Land and Conveyancing Law Reform Bill, which will offer an obvious opportunity for colleagues to debate the revised code of conduct on mortgage arrears.  Indeed, I am sure many people will be referring to that at length in the course of their speeches.  It is not helpful to hear Fianna F&aacute;il scare-mongering about the number of repossessions, however.  It is a typical tactic to distract people from the fact that Fianna F&aacute;il sleep-walked us into a situation where so many people are in the desperate situation of mortgage arrears.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900005#D00300"><p>We stopped repossessions under our original code of conduct.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900005#D00400"><p>Senator Bacik without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900005#D00500"><p>A particular court judgment stopped that.  It was nothing to do with Fianna F&aacute;il.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900005#D00600"><p>Our code of conduct held them up before that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900005#D00700"><p>Senator Bacik without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900005#D00800"><p>It is deeply hypocritical of Fianna F&aacute;il to claim some sort of ownership for stopping repossessions when, in fact, it created the situation we are currently in.</p><p>I commend the Minister for Social Protection, Deputy Joan Burton, for yesterday's initiative in introducing the JobsPlus plan to take 2,500 people off the live register through a system of incentives for employers.  There are many models for this plan elsewhere.  We have debated this issue here before and colleagues have spoken about the German policy whereby the car industry is subsidised through the payment of part-time wages to workers during periods of downturn in the sector.  We can see that working in other countries, so it is important to introduce a similar model here.  The Minister's new plan is commendable and welcome, and will offer a real boost for the long-term unemployed.  I ask the Leader to arrange a debate on that plan when we come back in the autumn to see how it is working and what outcomes are being achieved.</p><p>Following further revelations from the Anglo tapes at the weekend, I am glad we will be debating Second Stage of the Houses of the Oireachtas (Inquiries, Privileges and Procedures) Bill tomorrow.  That Bill, which is being introduced by the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, Deputy Howlin, will provide the opportunity that Mr. David Drumm appears to seek, namely, to answer questions in public and give an account of his actions.  It would be welcome to see that being done before an Oireachtas committee of inquiry.  It is all very well granting interviews to chosen interviewers, but it would be good to see an Oireachtas inquiry up and running with individuals giving evidence before it.</p><p>I also wish to ask the Leader for a debate on medical expenses.  Earlier today, I attended a briefing by the Irish Society of Chartered Physiotherapists, as did many colleagues.  The society put forward a strong case for a change in the law on reimbursement of medical expenses.  The Department of Health is supportive of that initiative that physiotherapy should be included as a reimbursable medical expense.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900005#D00900"><p>I salute Pope Francis I, who is emerging as one of the great figures of the 21st century.</p> <p>I say that because on his first journey outside Rome he recognised the plight of the people in desperation from north Africa trying to make it to &quot;Fortress Europe&quot;.  It was a dangerous position for a Pope to take.  He will be opposed by all the right-wing governments in northern Europe, but I found it very moving that he celebrated mass on one of those pathetic little boats and spoke up for those marginalised people.  However, I am a little worried about the representative here because he is in a difficult position and I hope this Pope will be able to sort it out.  I refer to the Papal Nuncio, Monsignor Brown, who despite the sound of the name is of German, not Irish extraction, which might explain some of the rigidity.  I do not think he distinguished himself in Dundalk.  He sailed very close to the wind when he intervened on the abortion issue.  I would like to ask the Leader whether he could request information for me from the Department of Foreign Affairs.  Does the Papal Nuncio have a unique position among ambassadors to this country so that he alone is permitted to intervene in the domestic affairs of the country to whom he is accredited?  No other ambassador would presume to do so.  He does not even provide the historical context of his own church, because we know now, thanks to an excellent piece of historical research by Patsy McGarry in <i>The Irish Times</i>, that the position of the Roman Catholic Church up until 1869 - in other words for nearly 2,000 years - was that abortion was completely permissible under canon law up to the 166th day which is when the church had calculated that ensoulment took place and the child was &#8220;quickened&#8221; to use the terminology.  The recent authoritarian restrictions on every form of abortion, even in life saving circumstances, in cases of fatal foetal abnormality or as the result of incest or rape are very new and must be challenged.</p><p> I wish to salute one of our judges in the High Court who peremptorily dismissed the impertinent request from the United States of America, with no evidence whatever, that it should extradite Mr. Snowden.  People should really appreciate what the United States is doing and the alarming fact that there is no difference between Mr. Bush and Mr. Obama except for the fact that he is black, he speaks well and he looks nice.  Apart from that, he is exactly the same.  He has increased tenfold the number of drone attacks, suspended <i>habeas corpus</i>and ridden roughshod over international law, and I would say again-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900006#E00200"><p>Does Senator Norris have a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900006#E00300"><p>Yes.  Would the Leader please write on our behalf to the Swedish Academy to ask it to withdraw the Nobel Prize it gave without evidence &ndash; to use the current phrase &ndash; to Mr. Obama before he had been tried, while he was on probation?  He has now shown himself to be in the same class as Mr. Bush and I think it should be-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900006#E00400"><p>Is that relevant to the Order of Business?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900006#E00500"><p>It is absolutely.  It is relevant to the world.  The academy should take back the Nobel Prize and give it to Mr. Snowden for letting us know what is happening in these murky areas.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900006#E00600"><p>I will start by making a brief comment on the proposed amendment to the Order of Business.  The debate will be held this afternoon.  It is all very fine to pretend we are King Canute but the reality is that to have a legal system where the lender cannot have recourse to the charged asset is nonsense.  The Opposition should take into account that we have introduced personal insolvency legislation in this country, which the previous Government did not, to allow people who are in-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900006#E00700"><p>And it privileges the banks too.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900006#E00800"><p>-----a situation where their family home will be repossessed to have real options to be able to retain it.  I agree with my colleague, Senator Bacik, that it is wrong to put out the charge that there will be hundreds of thousands of repossessions if we introduce the legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900006#E00900"><p>I said there will be 71,000.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900006#E01000"><p>However, we will have the debate later this afternoon.</p><p>I wish to praise the Ombudsman, Emily O&rsquo;Reilly, for raising the plight of asylum seekers in direct provision.  I and colleagues on the Opposition benches have raised the matter as well.  Unfortunately, to date, we have seen no positive action in this area.  Others have also commented on this appalling situation, for example, Geoffrey Shannon, the special rapporteur for children.  The reality of the matter is that one in every three asylum seekers spends longer than three years in direct provision and one in ten spends longer than seven years.</p> <p>There are families living in direct provision who have never had the opportunity to cook a family meal.  It is outrageous.  The point was made previously in our discussions on the Magdalen laundries that we should be conscious in this country of not looking behind the high walls.  I ask that the Leader provide time for a debate at the earliest opportunity on the issue of direct provision.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900007#F00200"><p>I rise to ask the Leader for an urgent debate on the rural transport restructuring programme announced this morning by the Minister of State, Deputy Kelly.  I have known the Minister of State for a long time and have always found him to be very affable and a decent man.  However, something has gotten to him.  I am not sure whether it was Brussels or his new portfolio but he is not thinking clearly in terms of what he is proposing to do.</p><p>There are currently 35 programmes operating countrywide, from Donegal along the west coast to Cork, Kerry and so on, under the rural transport scheme.  By and large, the scheme has been a huge success.  It should be realised that approximately 2.5% of the national budget for transport is allocated to rural transport initiatives.  By way of example, the west Cork transport scheme has been in operation for 11 years.  It has its own bus fleet provided in the main by way of funding from the scheme's own lottery system, charity events and so on.  The lottery system has successfully subvented the programme for many years.  A commitment was given that any of the rural transport companies that had their own fleet would not be interfered with under this new system.</p><p>The rural transport scheme in west Cork - I am sure this is replicated across the country - also operates a cancer connect system.  Under this system, people in areas such as the Beara Peninsula, Skull, Bantry and so on who have cancer and require hospital treatment such as radiotherapy, chemotherapy and so on are transported free of charge on a daily and weekly basis to Cork University Hospital and other hospitals.  In addition, approximately 30 to 40 retired bus drivers, garda&iacute; and so on have volunteered their services to support this system.</p><p>The Minister of State is now proposing that the number of schemes be reduced to 18 or 17 and that they be administered by the local authorities, which is crazy.  As I have said previously, the local authorities have difficulty even filling potholes never mind taking on responsibility for local transport schemes that are run and working well.  I will go a step further and propose an amendment to the Order of Business that the Minister of State, Deputy Kelly, come to the House today to explain in detail the reason he is dismantling a very efficient scheme that has proven itself beyond reasonable doubt.  There may be schemes in Ireland that are not operating as well as those in Donegal, west Cork and the west of Ireland but the Minister of State should not be throwing out the grain with the chaff.  I urge him to come to the House today to explain this proposal and to rethink it so as not to do damage to a wonderful scheme that is operating successfully in rural Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900007#F00300"><p>Senator Coghlan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900007#F00400"><p>I was not sure which Senator Coghlan was being called.  The Cathaoirleach may recall that last week a Senator - I think it was Senator Thomas Byrne - quoted Senator Coghlan but did not clarify whether it was Senator Paul Coghlan or Senator Eamonn Coghlan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900007#F00500"><p>I was quoting Senator Eamonn Coghlan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900007#F00600"><p>People were looking at me as though I had accused the Taoiseach of deciding an issue over a pint in a pub.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900007#F00700"><p>T&aacute; br&oacute;n orm.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900007#F00800"><p>With respect to the Acting Leader of the Opposition, we are wasting time.  What is proposed deals with mortgages, title, registration thereof and so on.  The code of conduct is an integral part of this.  As stated by Senator Bacik, all of this discussion could take place this evening.  In my view, thousands of people will not be affected.  Hundreds of people may be but we do not yet know that.  With respect, let us wait and see.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900008#G00100"><p>It is too late for them already.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900008#G00200"><p>It is not, with respect.  There is due process in this country.  This is a constitutional little republic.  We will not do anything rash like that.  There will not be thousands of people put out of their homes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1142" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900008#G00300"><p>The Government is making fair inroads into the Constitution already.  It is trying to get rid of one part of the Oireachtas.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900008#G00400"><p>The Senator, without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900008#G00500"><p>I will have to discuss that with Senator O'Sullivan elsewhere.  I am sure we will manage to do that.  The Leader is right.  He cannot accept this amendment because we would be putting off until later what can usefully be debated this afternoon.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900008#G00600"><p>I welcome the success of the incorporation of the Orange Order march in Donegal last Saturday into The Gathering and the success of the event.  The Grand Master of the Orange Lodge of Ireland, Edward Stevenson, told the crowd it was "extremely pleasing" the authorities in the Republic had incorporated the Rossnowlagh event into The Gathering.  I gather it is the first time it has happened and the occasion was extremely successful.  Mr. Stevenson went on to say: "We trust those in the corridors of power in Dublin will continue to recognise and value the contribution of the minority Protestant community to the wider society in the Republic of Ireland."  This is an opportunity to commend the Leader who brought those leaders to this House and created the atmosphere that has been so improved upon by the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Leo Varadkar, and the Minister for Arts, Heritage and the Gaeltacht, Deputy Jimmy Deenihan.  This is something we should continue.</p><p>I have just received a copy of Dr. Pauline Holland's history of east Donegal.  She says it is the only part of Ireland where three national languages are spoken, Irish, Ulster-Scots and English.  The purpose of the book and its associated art project is to advance the peace process by bringing these languages and their associated cultures in contact with each other.  The EU is involved through the PEACE programme and so is Donegal County Council.  Members of the Assembly in Belfast, on both the Unionist side last week and the Nationalist side today, have again asked that we not persist with the abolition of this House, because it is a way in which people in Northern Ireland participate in the Oireachtas.  Even at this late stage I ask the Leader to communicate that to the Taoiseach.  Is it an unwitting or unintended consequence that at a time the Leader of the House and the people in Donegal are so successfully promoting better relations, we are cutting asunder people whose help and support we need to make this a better island?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Maloney" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900008#G00700"><p>I welcome the introduction of the JobsPlus scheme which was announced yesterday by the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, Deputy Richard Bruton, and the Minister for Social Protection, Deputy Joan Burton.  This will be a great boost for employers in small and medium-sized enterprises who are financially stretched but are anxious to take on extra employees.  It will also be a great help to those who are long-term unemployed to get back into insurable employment.</p><p>Today, I speak on behalf of the survivors of the barbaric medical procedure called symphysiotomy.  These women have waited a long time for the publication of the Walsh report.  There were great expectations that the report was to be published today, but there appears to be no move on it by the Minister's office.  These women are not getting any younger.  They need help now.  I ask the Leader to advise the Minister for Health that this House demands the publication of the Walsh report without further ado and that the Minister come to the House to debate the findings of that report with the Members.</p><p>Will the Leader invite the Minister of State at the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Alan Kelly, to the House?  I heard him say on the radio news that he is of the opinion that his proposals will enhance rural transport and provide it in places that have never had a rural transport scheme.  Perhaps he would come to the House, when he gets a chance, to outline his proposals and how he believes they will benefit the people of rural Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1155" speakername="Kathryn Reilly" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900008#G00800"><p>First, I wish to comment on Greece and the troika programme, given that the troika is back in Ireland this week to examine our priorities for budget 2014.  The troika has set the Greek Government some new homework, including concrete steps to crack down on its health care spending.  Under the terms of the bailout, for example, the Greek Government is required to lay off 4,000 public sector workers by the end of the year.</p><p>The issue I wish to raise is the budget 2014 priorities for this country.</p> <p>It is remarkable that the Government will be discussing with the troika the details of the forthcoming budget before they are debated in the Oireachtas.  Fine Gael and the Labour Party promised to reform the budget process and in this context it is stated in the programme for Government that, "We will open up the budget process to the full glare of public scrutiny in a way that restores confidence and stability".  However, we are heading towards the introduction of the Government's third budget with the same absence of public scrutiny that was the hallmark of the previous Administration.</p><p>In view of the fact that representatives from the troika are here again to scrutinise our public finances and examine the details relating to the budget to be introduced in October, will the Leader arrange a debate on the Government's commitment to reform the budget process?  Will he also ensure that, if possible, the House will commence its debates on the budget now in order that we might inform the budgetary process?  The budget is being introduced earlier this year - in October as opposed to December - and it is important that we should be in a position to comment on the type of budget which this House and the Oireachtas in general wants put in place in order to stimulate the economy, get people back to work and give hope to households and local communities.  The Unite trade union is holding a pre-budget conference later in the week.  If these are the dying days of the Seanad, it is important that the House should inform the budgetary process and be seen to be relevant and functional.  I would welcome it if the Leader could bring a relevant Minister before the House in order to discuss the budget and the negotiations taking place with the troika in respect of our priorities.  Will he prioritise my request and ensure that such a debate is held prior to the summer recess?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900009#H00200"><p>I welcome the JobsPlus initiative announced yesterday by the Minister for Social Protection, Deputy Burton, and the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, Deputy Bruton.  This is a very progressive scheme which will hopefully encourage many employers to take on additional staff.  It will also give hope, courage and confidence to those who have been unemployed for a long time.  I accept that it is a pilot scheme restricted to 2,500 places but I hope that if it proves successful, it will be expanded and that many additional people will be taken on in the months ahead.  I ask the Leader to arrange a debate with the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation on the jobs initiative in order that he might provide an update on his plans and proposals and the number of commitments in the programme for Government which have been met.</p><p>I strongly support Senator Hayden's call for a debate early in the next session on direct provision.  I have met many people who have lived in direct provision for quite a number of years.  Such provision was a temporary arrangement designed to deal with a crisis situation but in many instances people are living in inhuman conditions.  This is one of the awful legacy issues we inherited from the previous Administration.  We have resolved many difficult issues in the past two and a half years.  That to which I refer is one which cannot be allowed to fester for much longer.  This has the potential to become the human rights issue of our time and the Government has a responsibility to resolve the matter as quickly as possible.</p><p>I welcome the fishing industry safety package announced yesterday by the Minister for Transport, Sport and Tourism, Deputy Varadkar, and the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine, Deputy Coveney.  This is a multifaceted, cross-agency initiative which will hopefully lead to lives being saved.  Sadly, it has come too late for those who lost their lives in recent years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900009#H00300"><p>I wish to propose an amendment to the Order of Business to the effect that the Minister for Health should come before the House to discuss SI 325 - European Union (Quality and Safety of Human Organs Intended for Transplantation) Regulations 2012.  I attended the Irish Kidney Association's annual general meeting earlier this year and I am aware that the association is dissatisfied at the manner in which this statutory instrument was introduced and the lack of consultation in respect of it.  I ask the Leader to arrange for the Minister for Health to come to the House today to discuss the matter.</p><p>I second Senator Byrne's amendment to the Order of Business.  On the matter to which he referred and the comments made by colleagues opposite, the Anglo tapes appear to indicate certain things with regard to who was calling the shots many years ago.  The Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Shatter, came before the House to debate what has become the Personal Insolvency Act and he would not - despite numerous questions put to him by myself and others - outline the discussions that were held with the banks or indicate the amendments sought by the latter in respect of that legislation.</p> <p>Effectively, the banks wrote the legislation.  It is entirely in favour of the banks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900010#J00200"><p>That is nonsense.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900010#J00300"><p>We are seeing the code of conduct being amended to suit the banks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900010#J00400"><p>Senator, have you a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900010#J00500"><p>There is no protection in it for the mortgage holders and those in distress.  I call on the Leader to facilitate the request of my colleague, Senator Byrne, for an amendment to the Order of Business to discuss the issue.  The game goes on and the people writing the legislation are not the legislators.  The Minister would not outline what changes he has allowed to be made to the legislation following the lobbying by the banks.  That is an appalling abuse of the parliamentary process by the banks.  If we wanted openness and transparency, then the Minister would be able to tell us what the legislation looked like before the banks got hold of it and what it looked like afterwards.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" speakername="Mary Moran" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900010#J00600"><p>I echo the calls made earlier for the media publication of the Walsh report.  I have raised this matter on a weekly basis for the past two years.  I hope that the Minister will publish the report and urge him to do so before we break for summer recess.</p><p>I congratulate an initiative spearheaded in County Louth by two Dundalk Institute of Technology research centres.  It was named recently as one of the top projects in Europe at a European Union award ceremony for active and healthy ageing practices.  As many Senators know, County Louth is the age-friendly county.  The Dundalk Institute of Technology and two associated centres, the Netwell Centre and CASALA, have been doing major innovative work in the area of age-friendly initiatives.</p><p>The DKIT based Netwell Centre and CASALA along with University College Cork got together for a collaboration on ageing.  Theirs was among 32 initiatives to be named as the reference site by the Commission, but only one of 13 to receive three star status.  These awards have been referred to as the Oscars for innovation.  COLLAGE and other recipients are paving the way for age-friendly initiatives.  I congratulate the directors of the Netwell Centre and CASALA on their success and on their aims to continue to work to reduce the average healthy life-span of a European by two years by the year 2020.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" speakername="Feargal Quinn" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900010#J00700"><p>I call on the Leader to assure us that there will be no guillotine on the Thirty-second Amendment of the Constitution (Abolition of Seanad &Eacute;ireann) Bill. Committee Stage is scheduled to commence tomorrow.  I gather the Leader has already said that he will allow for a full debate but I wish to be assured that this is the case.</p><p>Recently, we held a debate in the House on defibrillators.  I was impressed to receive a letter yesterday from St. Conleth's School.  Gavin Maguire is the man who organised it.  He organised a walk to Glendalough for his students.  Unfortunately, one of his students, a young man called Neil Quinlan, died and they were unable to revive him.  Then, the students got together to see whether they could raise money for defibrillators.  They raised money for four defibrillators by going on a walk, called the Neil Quinlan walk, to Glendalough.  They organised money for four defibrillators, one of which is in Glendalough, one is in Killarney, one is in Knockree and the last is in Errigal, County Donegal.</p><p>What jolted them was that they had to pay VAT of &euro;919, which would almost have bought another defibrillator.  It seems such a scandal.  Earlier this year, there was a fuss about the high cost of some drugs but the Minister was able to organise to get VAT negotiated.  We have introduced legislation and it has taken a first step.  If ever there was a case for defibrillators, it would be a shame if we do not do something about the associated VAT.  Someone will tell us that it is an EU issue and that we cannot address it here but I am sure it is possible to do something.  I urge the Leader to see what he can do to urge the Minister for Finance to make an exclusion for defibrillators.  If we are to have them in future, then to spend money like that when it is saving lives is something to which we should have a different attitude.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900011#K00100"><p>In recent days more than 600 young people who qualified with a medical degree started working in Irish hospitals.  I am sure everyone joins me in wishing them well in their future careers.  I hope most of their careers will be in Ireland and not in other countries.  I welcome that the Minister for Health has announced that by November he hopes to have in place more structured contracts for junior doctors.  Having more than 2,000 junior doctors on six-month contracts is not helpful to the system.  I urge the HSE to work with all the training bodies to deal with this complex issue which has been left to run for the past ten to 15 years.</p><p>I also welcome the Minister's decision on new structures for the hospital system with boards of management managing a number of hospitals in different regions.  We should have a debate on the matter in the next term to ensure we are familiar with the structure and that the structure operates.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900011#K00200"><p>I second Senator O'Donovan's amendment to the Order of Business.</p><p>I join colleagues in welcoming yesterday's announcement of the JobsPlus pilot scheme.  I hope it is a success even though it starts with relatively low numbers of just 2,500.  I commend everybody involved in the JobBridge scheme, which has been very successful to date even though there are some anomalies.  People have been provided with work experience from educational establishments such as the new educational and training boards.  Even though some people have only worked for a number of months on the scheme, they find themselves laid off during the summer months because the schools are closed for the summer holidays or the offices are not operating to full capacity during the summer.  This is regrettable.  Schools still need to be maintained even though the students are not present.  Painting and other summer work schemes need to take place.  I ask the Minister to look at that anomaly regarding educational establishments because several hundred people have been laid off over the summer months even though they have not completed their placements.</p><p>I agree with what Senator Quinn said about defibrillators.  Some mechanism should be introduced to avoid having to pay VAT on these essential pieces of equipment that can save lives.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" speakername="John Kelly" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900011#K00300"><p>Like others, I welcome the JobsPlus initiative announced in recent days by the Ministers, Deputies Bruton and Burton.  I championed this cause in this House and at the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation on numerous occasions.  That was acknowledged by the Minister, Deputy Bruton, and by the Chairman of the committee today.  Whereas self-praise is no praise, I point out to those who see no value in this House that this is another example of where we have been proved to be effective.  When I raised the issue in this House I got cross-party support and it is now being rolled out on a pilot basis.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900011#K00400"><p>Well done.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" speakername="John Kelly" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900011#K00500"><p>That is an achievement for the Seanad.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900011#K00600"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" speakername="John Kelly" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900011#K00700"><p>I also asked the Minister whether the JobsPlus plan has any negative impact on other incentives to employ people, such as the tax incentives and enterprise board employment grants.  I am glad to say that it does not.  It is a major boost particularly for employers in rural areas to have these packages to take these people off the live register.</p> <p>Again, I am delighted that that idea originated in this House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900012#L00200"><p>I disagree with Senator Kelly.  I had always heard that self-praise was the best praise because it comes from the heart.</p><p>I am one of those people who does not like to see the undeserved attention being lavished in recent days on an organisation called Exit International, which seeks to promote euthanasia-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900012#L00300"><p>Splendid.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900012#L00400"><p>-----run workshops and so on to help people end their lives in circumstances where they are in pain, suffering or very often in fear.  I would contrast the approach of such organisations with the wonderful work being done by the hospice movement.  We frequently see that it is the people in the hospice movement who are involved in the giving in hospice care who are most opposed to the despairing approach being promoted by organisations such as Exit International.  Euthanasia rather perversely comes from the words "good death".  For many years in Ireland people were encouraged to pray for a happy death.  A happy death and a good death is a death where pain is well managed and loved ones are present.</p><p>It is one of the tragedies of this country that appropriate hospice care is still not available to thousands of people.  Approximately 2,500 people are deprived of the hospice care they need each year.  For our population we should have approximately 450 hospice beds; we have about one third of that in operation.  It is not just about inpatient beds.  It is about all the services the hospice can provide including home care, outpatient day care and respite.  Where there is good and effective hospice care many people would have-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900012#L00500"><p>Is the Senator looking for a debate on this issue?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900012#L00600"><p>Yes.  I am asking for a debate on hospice care and specifically on the funding for hospice care.  The latest report, Access to Specialist Palliative Care Services and Place of Death in Ireland, documents the issues very well.  I do not have the figure to hand but it mentions that of the &euro;78 million designated for specialist palliative care, about &euro;4.5 million of that is unaccounted for as against regional service plans.  It would be a good idea to have the Minister in the House to discuss the Government's plans for hospice care.  I know the Taoiseach gave certain commitments to Galway hospital some years ago-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900012#L00700"><p>The Senator is over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900012#L00800"><p>-----which I hope have been honoured by now but we need to see much more consistent care for people in hospices throughout Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900012#L00900"><p>On a point of information and order-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900012#L01000"><p>One can be sure it will be a point of disorder.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900012#L01100"><p>If Senator Walsh shuts up I would get it made.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900012#L01200"><p>Senator Norris, what is the point of order?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900012#L01300"><p>On a point of order, disorder and information, would Senator Mullen be kind enough, through the Leader, to circulate the details of Exit International because I will certainly be joining it?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900012#L01400"><p>Senator, that is not a point of order.  I call Senator Brennan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900012#L01500"><p>I congratulate him because having spent a lifetime of political activity trying to control people's lives-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900012#L01600"><p>Senator Norris, please resume your seat.  I call Senator Brennan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900012#L01700"><p>-----he is now trying to control their deaths as well.  He can hump off as far as I am concerned.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" speakername="Terry Brennan" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900012#L01800"><p>I refer to the short stay visa waiver programme.  I welcome the significant growth in the number of trips to Ireland from countries covered by the short stay visa waiver programme, which was launched on 1 July two years ago.  Provisional figures indicate that the number of visits in 2012 by persons from the 17 countries covered by the programme was 38% higher than in 2010.  I remind Members that the programme allows visitors in possession of a UK visa to travel on to Ireland without the need to apply for a separate visa.  I welcome the decision of the Government in March last year to extend the programme until the end of October 2016.  This initiative has a positive impact on the Irish economy and augurs well for tourism and jobs in this industry for many years to come.  I note also that the Minister is looking to expand this programme to cover additional countries.  This initiative is a wonderful success and I look forward to its continued success for many years to come, with many more visitors coming to our island.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900013#M00100"><p>I welcome the statement made today by the Chief Justice with regard to the need for ethics in corporate governance.  It is welcome and I ask the Leader to consider having a debate on the matter.  We can all see the difficulties, and ongoing revelations in the newspapers show the dearth of ethics particularly in the banking sector, although this also applies in other sectors of business.  I do not necessarily agree it is either-or when it comes to ethics and profit.  The directors and employees of companies have an obligation to shareholders and their returns, because this is what drives the engine of the economy and a business.</p><p>Companies also have a responsibility to their employees, the customers without whom they would not be able to operate successfully, and the wider community.  Often this is relegated to almost insignificance.  Morality and ethics are fundamental to any operation, including politics and the administration of our public services to ensure we do not waste taxpayers' money.  In the Houses in the coming days we will face a challenge as to where we stand on ethics and morality with regard to the abortion legislation which is fundamental to human life.  Businesses and politicians face challenges and if we reflect and think about this it will do us good.  I very much welcome the statements by Catholic Church leaders in recent weeks regarding the legislation.  They did this knowing they would be criticised by anti-Catholic bigots, and of course this will happen, but the courage they have shown sets an example for us-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900013#M00200"><p>The Senator is over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900013#M00300"><p>-----when it comes to voting on this terrible legislation, which unfortunately has been introduced by the Government.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1147" speakername="John Crown" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900013#M00400"><p>I associate myself with some of the comments of Senator Mullen, those which called for an increase in investment in hospice beds.  Some of us have the sad duty sometimes of giving people very bad news.  The hospice provides a wonderful source of comfort and solace for people, which some, but not all, patients will choose in the final phase of life's journey.  What is fairly horrific is if a person makes this choice but a bed is not available.  I do not want to make any jokes about the length of the waiting list for the hospice, but people can get some idea of where I would go if I were to do so.  Will the Leader bring to the Minister's attention the rather stark figures which I mentioned a few weeks ago and which Senator Mullen correctly pointed out today?</p><p>A frustration of being a backbench Independent Senator is the limited number of legislative initiatives one can make by virtue of scheduling.  I was very concerned to read today a report by Ms Nessa Childers, MEP, who has done a very good job in outlining the pressure which MEPs come under from the tobacco industry.  What is very obvious with regard to the forthcoming attempts to change tobacco regulations at European level, and should be considered if we ever intend doing it here, is the massive imbalance in the muscle and financial power available to the tobacco lobby and that available to health advocacy groups.  It is estimated the number of health advocacy groups with direct access to MEPs is two, whereas at least 100 people who are registered act on behalf of the tobacco industry at European Parliament level.  There is a huge variation in the degree of compliance of European parliamentarians with the United Nations recommendations, which we discussed previously in the context of the unfortunate meeting the Taoiseach and two senior Ministers had with the tobacco industry.  We need to blaze another trail internationally on tobacco control by introducing in the House legislation which would make it illegal for any tobacco company to have any contract with any advertising or public relations agency.  Will the Leader ask the Minister to schedule a debate or launch an initiative in this regard?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900013#M00500"><p>It is fitting to ask that when we speak about life and death matters, be it abortion or euthanasia, we be very tempered in the language we use, knowing our words affect others.</p> <p>All I ask for is tolerance and respect.  Clearly, Senators are coming from different starting points.  That is fine, but let us be careful about the language we use.</p><p>Will the Leader ask the Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy Quinn, to make a statement on the urgent issue of resources for children with Down's syndrome?  They are in our schools and have been classified as having mild learning difficulties, which is the intellectual classification, but they have additional needs in terms of speech, movement, etc.  Parents are concerned.  This is happening in every county, including Galway.  Before we go into recess, parents need to know where they will stand in September.</p><p>After the general allocation model came into being approximately five years ago, children with Down's syndrome were stripped of their specialist teaching resource hours.  As a result, they have been disadvantaged.  Education is a right and there must be a level playing field.  This is what equality of opportunity means in terms of education provision.  The Minister must man up before the summer recess.  We might only need one hour for the debate, but it would be worthwhile.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900014#N00200"><p>Ghabh muid go l&eacute;ir comhghairdeas le Emily O'Reilly an tseachtain seo caite tar &eacute;is a ceapach&aacute;in mar Ombudsman Eorpach.</p><p>  Last week, we celebrated the election of Ms Emily O'Reilly as the European Ombudsman.  It is interesting that, this morning, she launched <i>Studies: An Irish Quarterly Review</i>, in which she wrote the lead article, entitled &quot;Asylum Seekers in our Republic: Why Have We Gone Wrong?&quot;  Today, she intimated her frustration - these are my words - with the way direct provision has been handled and the situation for those asylum seekers in direct provision.  She outlined a number of legal issues with the system and the lack of oversight.</p><p>  As Ms Justice McGuinness put it, some future Government should not find itself in the same position as this Government, which needed to apologise and recompense people in respect of the Magdalen laundries.  A future Government should not need to recompense people in direct provision.  We need an urgent debate on direct provision, possibly as soon as we resume.  We must examine all of the aspects, including the legal situation, and determine how to redress the situation so that people who validly or invalidly seek asylum are treated properly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900014#N00300"><p>Senator Byrne proposed an amendment to the Order of Business regarding the code of conduct on mortgage arrears.  As the Deputy Leader mentioned, we will have ample time to discuss the code in the context of the Land and Conveyancing Law Reform Bill, which will be before the House this afternoon.  I am sure that it will also be discussed when the Oireachtas inquiries Bill will be before the House.</p><p>Senator Bacik referred to the JobsPlus plan, which was announced in Waterford yesterday.  It is an excellent plan to tackle long-term unemployment, as it cuts out the red tape and gives &euro;10,000 to each employer who takes on for one or two years people who are on the live register.  The Government is responding.  Senator Wilson outlined the success of JobBridge, but also pointed out anomalies.  There will be anomalies in every scheme, but JobsPlus is a result of listening to people like Senator Kelly, heeding debates such as the Seanad's on the jobs action plan and responding to the needs of employers and everyone else.</p> <p>I am sure it will succeed.  It has been welcomed by employers and people who are unemployed.  It is certainly a new step on the road to tackling the scourge of long-term unemployment which we face.</p><p>Senator David Norris complimented Pope Francis on highlighting human rights issues and the plight of immigrants.  He raised the question of the duties of ambassadors and whether they can interfere with internal politicals.  He also raised the question of the Nobel Peace Prize for President Obama.  I do not think a majority of Members of the House would support the Senator on that matter.</p><p>Senator Aideen Hayden praised the Ombudsman, Ms Emily O'Reilly, on her report on the plight of asylum seekers in direct provision.  Senator Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh made exactly the same point.  I will try to arrange for the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Alan Shatter, to come to the House to debate that matter when we come back in September.</p><p>Senator Denis O'Donovan raised the question of rural transport.  We certainly recognise the excellent work being done in west Cork, as outlined by him.  However, it is not working well in other parts of the country.  The matter was also raised by Senator Marie Moloney.  I will invite the Minister of State at the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Alan Kelly, to the House to address the matter and give us an outline of his proposals but I do not think we can arrange it today.</p><p>Senator Sean Barrett spoke about the incorporation of the Orange Order march in Rossnowlagh into the Gathering and said that it could only advance the peace process, with which I am sure we would all agree.  He said members of the Northern Ireland Assembly favoured the retention of the Seanad as it is a forum for Northern Ireland representatives.  We will take those points on board, which I am sure will be made during the Committee Stage debate on the Bill.</p><p>Senator Marie Moloney raised the question of JobsPlus and rural transport, which I addressed.  Along with Senator Mary Moran, she raised the question of symphysiotomy, which Senator Moran has raised on numerous occasions in the House.  They called for the publication of the Walsh report.  I will find out when that report will be published.  I was told it was imminent but that was a number of weeks ago, so I will find out the exact position for the Senators.</p><p>Senator Kathryn Reilly spoke about pre-budget discussions in this House.  The Minster for Social Protection, Deputy Joan Burton, will give an outline on the budgetary process, a briefing on the budgetary proposals and will accept suggestions at the Oireachtas joint committee on Wednesday next.  There will be a significant debate on that issue at the joint committee.  The troika is still with us unfortunately but the Government is working full steam ahead to get back our economic sovereignty.  Hopefully, in the next year or so, we will have our economic sovereignty back and we will not have to have meetings with the troika.</p><p>Senator Michael Mullins called for a debate on the jobs action plan with the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, Deputy Richard Bruton, for which I will ask.  He also raised the question of the safety measures outlined for the fishing industry.</p> <p>I announced a number of weeks ago that the Minister, Deputy Varadkar, and the Minister, Deputy Coveney, would make a statement in that regard.  The safety measures as outlined by the Ministers will be welcomed by all involved in the fishing industry.  It is to be hoped it will lead to greater safety throughout the industry.</p><p>Senator Daly referred to organ transplants.  I am seeking an update on that, for which Senator Quinn asked last week.  I understand the contracts Bill will complete all Stages in the other House.  I propose that we debate it before the summer recess.  It will probably come before the House for discussion during the last week of the sitting, on 22 or 23 July.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" speakername="Feargal Quinn" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900016#P00200"><p>What about Committee Stage of the Bill to abolish the Seanad?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900016#P00300"><p>I will come to the Senator.  He was mentioned in dispatches all along. </p><p>Senator Moran outlined research done by Dundalk Institute of Technology on active and ageing practices.  All involved are to be congratulated. </p><p>Senator Quinn referred to VAT on defibrillators, a point I will make to the Minister for Finance.  Some six or seven hours have been allocated to Committee Stage of the Seanad Bill.  We should be able to complete Committee Stage within that time, which is much more than the 40 minutes allocated in the other House.  We will see how we get on with the debate.  We will have another bite of the cherry on Report Stage.  </p><p>I acknowledge that JobsPlus was part of a suggestion which Senator Kelly made in the House.  It is one of the many good ideas which have come from the House and have been introduced by the Government. </p><p>Senator Mullen contrasted the work of Exit International and the hospice movement.  The question of hospice care was raised by Senator Crown who referred to a lack of beds.  The Government is addressing the needs of the hospice movement.  I suggest he reads the reply given by the Minister to Senator Burke's Adjournment matter last week.  He asked about hospice beds and care in the country and received a comprehensive reply. </p><p>Senator Brennan referred to the success of the short stay visa waiver programme.  The initiative has proved to be quite successful and I am sure it will continue. </p><p>Senator Walsh referred to ethics in corporate governance and the statement by the Chief Justice.  The corrupt practices by directors of any company should be condemned.  We will have a further debate on the question of ethics in corporate governance over the coming weeks. </p><p>Senator Crown referred to hospice beds, which I have addressed, and the pressures from the tobacco industry.  We all know how powerful it is.  The pressure it exerts on Members of the European Parliament was outlined by MEPs.  I do not know whether we can legally introduce the measures mentioned by Senator Crown.</p> <p>It should certainly be investigated.</p><p>Senator Healy Eames spoke of tolerance, respect and dignity, which is what we expect from all debates in the House, and I hope that will continue up to the summer recess and way beyond it when we speak on legislation or any other matter.  She also mentioned resources for children with Down's syndrome and I will certainly bring that matter to the attention of the Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy Quinn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900017#Q00200"><p>Senator Thomas Byrne has moved an amendment to the Order of Business, "That No. 2, Land and Conveyancing Law Reform Bill 2013, be deleted from the Order of Business".  Is the amendment being pressed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900017#Q00300"><p>Yes, absolutely.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.96/1" nospeaker="true" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900017#Q00400"><p>Amendment put:</p><p>The Seanad divided: T, 16; Nl, 30.</p><p>Tellers: T, Senators Ned O'Sullivan and Diarmuid Wilson; Nl, Senators Paul Coghlan and Aideen Hayden.</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.96/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2013-07-09" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900017#Q00400">
            <divisioncount ayes="16" noes="30" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" vote="aye">Sean Barrett</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" vote="aye">Thomas Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1147" vote="aye">John Crown</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" vote="aye">David Cullinane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" vote="aye">Mark Daly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" vote="aye">David Norris</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" vote="aye">Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1169" vote="aye">Mary Ann O'Brien</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" vote="aye">Denis O'Donovan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1142" vote="aye">Ned O'Sullivan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1154" vote="aye">Averil Power</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" vote="aye">Feargal Quinn</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1155" vote="aye">Kathryn Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" vote="aye">Jim Walsh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" vote="aye">Mary White</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" vote="aye">Diarmuid Wilson</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" vote="no">Ivana Bacik</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1121" vote="no">Paul Bradford</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" vote="no">Terry Brennan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" vote="no">Colm Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1114" vote="no">Deirdre Clune</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" vote="no">Eamonn Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" vote="no">Paul Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1124" vote="no">Michael Comiskey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" vote="no">Maurice Cummins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" vote="no">Jim D'Arcy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1160" vote="no">Michael D'Arcy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" vote="no">John Gilroy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1144" vote="no">Jimmy Harte</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" vote="no">Aideen Hayden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" vote="no">Fidelma Healy Eames</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1152" vote="no">Imelda Henry</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" vote="no">Ca&iacute;t Keane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" vote="no">John Kelly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1162" vote="no">Denis Landy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" vote="no">Marie Maloney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" vote="no">Mary Moran</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1134" vote="no">Tony Mulcahy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" vote="no">R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" vote="no">Michael Mullins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" vote="no">Catherine Noone</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" vote="no">Marie Louise O'Donnell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" vote="no">Susan O'Keeffe</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" vote="no">Pat O'Neill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" vote="no">Jillian van Turnhout</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1143" vote="no">John Whelan</mpname>
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.96/3" nospeaker="true" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900017#Q00400"><p>Amendment declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="16:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900018#S00100"><p>Senator Denis O'Donovan has proposed an amendment to the Order of Business, "That a debate on the proposal by the Minister of State at the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Alan Kelly, re rural transport scheme, be taken today."  Is the amendment being pressed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="16:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900018#S00200"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.99/1" nospeaker="true" time="16:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900018#S00300"><p>Amendment put:</p><p>The Seanad divided: T, 15; Nl, 32.</p><p>Tellers: T, Senators Ned O'Sullivan and Diarmuid Wilson; Nl, Senators Paul Coghlan and Aideen Hayden.</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.99/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2013-07-09" time="16:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900018#S00300">
            <divisioncount ayes="15" noes="32" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" vote="aye">Sean Barrett</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" vote="aye">Thomas Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1147" vote="aye">John Crown</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" vote="aye">David Cullinane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" vote="aye">Mark Daly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" vote="aye">R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" vote="aye">David Norris</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" vote="aye">Denis O'Donovan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1142" vote="aye">Ned O'Sullivan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" vote="aye">Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1154" vote="aye">Averil Power</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1155" vote="aye">Kathryn Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" vote="aye">Jim Walsh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" vote="aye">Mary White</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" vote="aye">Diarmuid Wilson</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" vote="no">Ivana Bacik</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1121" vote="no">Paul Bradford</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" vote="no">Terry Brennan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" vote="no">Colm Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1114" vote="no">Deirdre Clune</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" vote="no">Eamonn Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" vote="no">Paul Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1124" vote="no">Michael Comiskey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" vote="no">Maurice Cummins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" vote="no">Jim D'Arcy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1160" vote="no">Michael D'Arcy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" vote="no">John Gilroy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1144" vote="no">Jimmy Harte</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" vote="no">Aideen Hayden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" vote="no">Fidelma Healy Eames</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1152" vote="no">Imelda Henry</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" vote="no">Ca&iacute;t Keane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" vote="no">John Kelly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1162" vote="no">Denis Landy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" vote="no">Marie Maloney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" vote="no">Mary Moran</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1134" vote="no">Tony Mulcahy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" vote="no">Michael Mullins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" vote="no">Catherine Noone</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1169" vote="no">Mary Ann O'Brien</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" vote="no">Marie Louise O'Donnell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" vote="no">Susan O'Keeffe</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" vote="no">Pat O'Neill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" vote="no">Feargal Quinn</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1163" vote="no">Tom Shehan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" vote="no">Jillian van Turnhout</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1143" vote="no">John Whelan</mpname>
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.99/3" nospeaker="true" time="16:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900018#S00300"><p>Amendment declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="16:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900019#T00100"><p>Senator Mark Daly has moved an amendment to the Order of Business, "That a debate on SI 325 be taken today."  However, the amendment was not seconded in the debate, and consequently falls.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.101" nospeaker="true" time="16:20:00" ><p>Amendment lapsed.</p><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.102" nospeaker="true" time="16:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900019#T00300">Electricity Regulation Act 1999: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="16:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900019#T00400"><p>I move:<blockquote><br />That Seanad &Eacute;ireann approves the following Regulations in draft:Electricity Regulation Act 1999 (Restricted Electrical Works) Regulations 2013,copies of which have been laid in draft form before Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 13th June, 2013.</blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.104" nospeaker="true" time="16:20:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.105" nospeaker="true" time="16:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900020#U00100">Land and Conveyancing Law Reform Bill 2013: Second Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.106" nospeaker="true" time="16:25:00" ><p>Question proposed: &quot;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&quot;</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1025" speakername="Alan Shatter" time="16:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900020#U00300"><p>I am pleased to introduce the Land and Conveyancing Law Reform Bill 2013 to the Seanad and I look forward to hearing the contributions of Senators.</p><p>  This is a short Bill which is designed to deal with the legal uncertainty which has arisen as a result of several High Court judgments concerning lending institutions' remedies in cases of mortgage default.  I want to emphasise at the outset that the Bill does not grant any additional powers to financial institutions.  It merely restores the position which was thought to apply when the previous Government enacted the Land and Conveyancing Law Reform Act 2009, that is, that the relevant provisions of the law in force prior to the commencement of that Act on 1 December 2009 would continue to apply to mortgages created prior to that date.</p><p>  I am, however, availing of this opportunity to introduce two provisions which I believe will be of benefit to borrowers in mortgage distress.  These are particularly important provisions that did not exist or apply in the law up to now in the context of applications taken to the courts for repossession.  First, I have introduced an additional safeguard for borrowers in section 2.  It provides that in any future repossession proceedings in respect of a borrower's principal private residence, the court may adjourn proceedings so that a proposal for a personal Insolvency arrangement, PIA, under the Personal Insolvency Act 2012, may be fully explored as an alternative to repossession.  This will mean in effect that lending institutions cannot in future proceed to the repossession stage without engaging in good faith in the alternative measures provided for in the Personal Insolvency Act 2012.</p><p>  Second, I have introduced, in section 3, a requirement that repossession actions in regard to a principal private residence where the mortgage was created prior to 1 December, 2009 must be commenced in the Circuit Court.  This provision will lead to a reduction in legal costs for parties and will also mean that the matter can be dealt with at Circuit Court level thereby obviating the need to attend High Court hearings in Dublin.  This puts such mortgages on the same footing as similar mortgages created after 1 December 2009; under the 2009 Act actions for repossession must be commenced in the Circuit Court.</p><p>  The current uncertainty in relation to the remedies available to lending institutions in the case of mortgages created prior to 1 December 2009 originated in the 2011 case, Start Mortgages <i>v. </i>Gunn<i>. </i> In that case, the High Court found that the repeal of section 62(7) of the Registration of Title Act 1964 in the Land and Conveyancing Law Reform Act 2009 had the unintended consequence in certain cases of restricting lending institutions from exercising their repossession rights.  The judgment in this case has been appealed to the Supreme Court but the appeal has not yet been heard.</p> <p>While later High Court judgments in similar cases appear to have limited the potential impact of that judgment, the resulting uncertainty is undesirable.  This legislation confirms the simple point that the law in force prior to commencement of the 2009 Act on 1 December 2009 should continue to apply to mortgages created prior to that date.  That was the intention of our predecessors in Government when the 2009 legislation was enacted.  Mortgages provide lending institutions with security for their loans.  This is a centuries old principle and is the basis of all mortgage law.</p><p> The Land and Conveyancing Law Reform Act 2009 was the result of a joint law reform project undertaken by my Department and the Law Reform Commission.  It repealed approximately 150 pre-1922 statutes, the earliest of which dated from the late 13th century, and replaced them with updated provisions.  The statutory provisions in relation to mortgages, which had been contained for the most part in the Conveyancing Acts 1881 to 1911, were repealed and replaced by the provisions set out in Part 10 of the 2009 Act.  Chapter 3 of Part 10 of the 2009 Act contains provisions relating to the obligations, powers and rights of lenders.  Section 96 of the Act confirms that these apply in the case of mortgages created after the commencement date, namely, 1 December 2009.</p><p> As regards mortgages created prior to that date, the joint project proceeded on the basis that the law applicable on the date of their creation would continue to apply by virtue of section 27 of the Interpretation Act 2005.  Section 27 provides, <i>inter alia</i>, that where an enactment is repealed, the repeal does not &quot;affect any right, privilege, obligation or liability acquired, accrued or incurred under the enactment&quot;.  However, in the Start Mortgages case which I mentioned earlier, the High Court interpreted this provision of the Interpretation Act in a manner which restricts the application of the law in force prior to 1 December 2009 to certain cases where default had occurred prior to that date and demand for repayment had also been made before that date.  As I said, a Supreme Court appeal is pending in this case.</p><p> Put simply, section 1 of this Bill does nothing other than restore the position intended by the Oireachtas when enacting the 2009 Act.  I would, at this juncture, like to comment on certain ridiculous claims which I understand have been made in the media about the effect of this Bill.  It has been brought to my attention that a statement was made on a well-known radio show to the effect that the passing of this Bill would result in the eviction of some 300,000 people from their homes.  I am at a loss to understand from where this figure of 300,000 comes.  It appears to have been plucked out of the air and has no basis in reality.  I do not believe, as has been suggested, that this Bill will open the floodgates for repossessions.  The Bill merely reinstates the legal right of lenders in pre-2009 mortgages to go to a court as a last resort to repossess mortgaged properties where there has been a major default by a borrower.  As I have repeatedly said, it was never the intention under the 2009 Act that this right would have been compromised by the legislation, but arising from the manner in which provisions in the Interpretation Act 2005 have been interpreted in certain court cases, this is in fact what happened.  It is, therefore, necessary for the Oireachtas to take the measures provided for in section 1 of this Bill to rectify the situation.</p><p> This Government views repossession of a family home or a principal private residence as a last resort after all other avenues to resolve the mortgage difficulties have been tried and failed.  It is clear from the Central Bank code of conduct on mortgage arrears that there are serious procedures and timelines to be worked through between lender and borrower before any question of an action for repossession arises.  The personal insolvency legislation provides for a personal insolvency arrangement in which it should be generally possible for debtors to remain in their family homes.  I should add that, even where the point of a court action for repossession of a person's home is reached, this Bill makes very specific provision for a late intervention safeguard for borrowers by allowing for an adjournment for the parties to investigate the alternative of a personal insolvency arrangement.  This particular option was not contained in the 2009 Act.  Those who may criticise this Bill from a party political perspective should be aware of the fact that when the 2009 Act was enacted, the intention was that the blunt instrument of repossession would be available and the alternative process of a personal insolvency arrangement which would facilitate an individual in debt difficulties retaining his or her home was not part and parcel of the 2009 Act.</p> <p>As public representatives we know that people in mortgage arrears are already under tremendous stress.  It is unfortunate, to say the least, that scaremongering of the type we recently witnessed on the radio show referred to can be aired unchallenged.  It is all too easy for people to make political or emotive capital out of the terrible circumstances in which many people with serious indebtedness problems find themselves.  This Government has provided the appropriate vehicle to assist people extricating themselves from debt, where possible, in the insolvency legislation.</p><p> The Bill also provides, in section 2, for the adjournment of actions for repossession in cases involving a borrower's principal private residence where the court considers that the matter could be resolved through recourse to the mechanisms set out in the Personal Insolvency Act 2012.  This provision is in line with the commitment I gave in the course of discussions on the Personal Insolvency Bill in each of the Houses last year.</p><p> One of the main priorities of this Government is to deal with the problem of unsustainable personal debt.  When I took office as Minister for Justice and Equality in March 2011, it became clear that little work had been undertaken to reform or modernise the law relating to bankruptcy and insolvency despite the enormous financial difficulties being experienced by so many people.  The introduction of a modern, practical and humane insolvency and bankruptcy process through the Personal Insolvency Act and the establishment of the Insolvency Service of Ireland was a necessary priority in our path to recovery and growth.  The three new insolvency arrangements offered through the Insolvency Service will be of substantial assistance to thousands of individuals and families in financial difficulty.  The new arrangements have the capacity to provide a path back to sustainability for those crippled by unsustainable debt.  In particular, they provide fair and equitable solutions for those who have no prospect of repaying their debt.</p><p> This Government believes it is important that all households can contribute to our economic recovery and that all those currently affected by unsustainable debt have real hope for the future.  Under the new arrangements, people will be given the opportunity to start again, relieved of the financial pressure of unsustainable debt.  Nobody in this House can be unaware of the issues that arise where repossession proceedings relate to family homes.  It is an emotive and sensitive topic and one to which I and the Government have given extensive consideration in formulating this short Bill.  That is why, in the course of preparing the Bill, I sought and obtained Government approval for the inclusion of provisions which are set out in section 2 and which will allow a court to adjourn repossession proceedings in such cases in order to explore whether a PIA under the Personal Insolvency Act 2012 would be a more appropriate and acceptable alternative to repossession.</p><p> In line with the aim of the Bill which I set out earlier, section 1<b><i></i></b>seeks to ensure continued application of certain repealed provisions of the Conveyancing Acts 1881 to 1911 and the Registration of Title Act 1964 to mortgages created prior to 1 December 2009, the date on which the repeals took effect on commencement of the Land and Conveyancing Law Reform Act 2009.  The intention is to remove the uncertainty which has arisen regarding lending institutions' remedies in certain cases of default.  Subsection (1) provides that the section shall apply to mortgages created prior to 1 December 2009, the date on which the 2009 Act came into operation.  Mortgages created after that date are subject to the 2009 Act's provisions.  Subsection (2) provides that the statutory provisions referred to in subsection (6),<i></i>which were repealed by the 2009 Act, may be invoked or exercised by a person as if those provisions had not been repealed in the 2009 Act.</p><p> While the High Court judgment in the Start Mortgages case dealt specifically with the unintended effects of the repeal of section 62(7) of the Registration of Title Act 1964, the opportunity is being taken, on the advice of the Office of the Attorney General, to make it clear that relevant mortgage-related provisions in the Conveyancing Acts 1881 to 1911 will continue to apply to pre-1 December 2009 mortgages.  Subsection (3)<i></i>provides that provisions which were amended by the 2009 Act may be invoked or exercised by a person as if those provisions had not been amended in the 2009 Act.  These statutory provisions shall apply to mortgages created prior to the commencement of the 2009 Act notwithstanding their amendment by that Act.</p> <p> Section 1(4) is a without prejudice provision which provides that subsections (1) to (3) do not affect the ability of any person who is in a position to rely on other rights or entitlements to exercise those rights or entitlements.  In short, a lender that is already in a position to seek and obtain repossession within the limits of the Start Mortgages judgment will not be affected by the provisions contained in subsections (1) to (3).</p><p>Section 1(5) provides that the section will not apply to any proceedings already before the courts.  This is in compliance with the &quot;separation of powers&quot; principle in our Constitution.  Section 1(6) is an interpretation provision which contains relevant definitions.</p><p>Section 2 provides that in repossession proceedings involving a principal private residence, a court may, where it considers it appropriate or on application by a borrower, adjourn the proceedings to enable the parties to consider whether a personal insolvency arrangement, PIA, under the Personal Insolvency Act 2012 would be a more appropriate alternative to repossession.  The intention behind the provision is to ensure that lending institutions do not resort to repossession proceedings without considering the PIA option under the 2012 Act.</p><p>Section 2(1) makes it clear that the provision relates only to principal private residences.  These include family homes under the Family Home Protection Act 1976 and shared homes under the Civil Partnership and Certain Rights and Obligations of Cohabitants Act 2010.  Section 2(2) allows the court, either of its own motion or on the application of a person, to consider an adjournment for a period of two months to enable the parties to explore the possibility of a PIA as an alternative to repossession.  I ask Senators to note that this provision is designed to enable the parties to explore the possibility of a PIA as opposed to making any final submission to facilitate possible agreement thereon.</p><p>Section 2(3) outlines certain matters the court may take into account in its consideration of an application for adjournment.  These are particularly important and include whether the borrower has engaged in a process relating to mortgage arrears, whether payments have been made by the borrower in the preceding 12 months, whether the matter has been adjourned previously and the conduct of the parties to the mortgage in seeking to resolve issues concerning arrears on the mortgage.  Bad faith on the part of either party may be taken into account by the court.  If, for example, either the lender or borrower has not engaged meaningfully in attempts to resolve the arrears, that matter can be taken into account by the court in determining whether to adjourn repossession proceedings.</p><p>Section 2(4) provides that at the end of the adjournment period the court may grant a further adjournment if it considers that progress has been made in preparing a PIA.  Section 2(5) provides that the court may adjourn a case to a different venue within the relevant circuit in order to meet with the period of two months provided for in subsection (2).  Section 2(6) provides that the section will apply to mortgages created both before and after the coming into operation of Part 10 of the 2009 Act  on 1 December 2009 and section 2(7) contains relevant definitions.  As a result of confusion on the part of some contributors to the debate on the Bill in the Lower House, I wish Senators to note that if a second adjournment is to be granted in order to facilitate an individual entering into a PIA, the length of such an adjournment will be at the discretion of the court.  It will not be confined to a maximum of two months.  It is, therefore, designed to enable individuals to work through the process that is envisaged, which can result in parties entering into PIAs.</p><p>Section 3 provides that in the case of mortgages in respect of principal private residences which were created prior to 1 December 2009, repossession proceedings must, as indicated earlier, be commenced in the Circuit Court.  Up to now, the venue would have been the High Court.  This means that such cases must be commenced in the Circuit Court, irrespective of the date of creation of the mortgage.  However, in order to avoid legal challenges in respect of proceedings already in being, section 3(4) provides that where other such proceedings relating to the enforcement of a mortgagee's rights have been commenced in the High Court but have not yet been determined then, notwithstanding section 3(2), proceedings for repossession of a principal private residence may be taken in that court.  This will effectively avoid the risk of enforcement proceedings being taken in two separate courts simultaneously.  The latter would lead to increased costs being incurred by the parties concerned, which would be undesirable.</p> <p> Section 4 is a standard provision containing the Short Title and a commencement provision in respect of section 2.</p><p>The Bill is a short but important Bill.  It restates the law that has existed over the centuries which enables a lending institution to rely on its security in respect of a mortgage.  Section 1 does nothing more than restore the position intended by the Oireachtas when enacting the 2009 Act.  Section 2 seeks to ensure that where repossession proceedings concern a principal private residence, full account is taken of the alternative options available under the Personal Insolvency Act 2012.  This is a major reform of the law compared with the position as it would have been had this difficulty not arisen under the 2009 Act.  In addition, section 3 provides that repossession actions in respect of principal private residences must, following the coming into force of the section, be commenced in the Circuit Court.  The Bill will restore legal certainty, promote utilisation of the options available under the personal insolvency legislation and enhance protection levels for borrowers' homes.  On this basis, I commend the Bill to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900024#Y00200"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House.  While I realise that the Bill is amending previous legislation, I note that the Minister referred in his speech to good faith.  We should reflect on the actions of the banks to date.  We saw in the newspapers today reference to the banks being hauled over the coals by the Central Bank because they have not met the targets in terms of coming to arrangements with mortgage holders.  However, when there is no sanction for banks, then those working in the bank are unlikely to worry too much about what the Central Bank says to them.  We saw what the banks did in respect of what Patrick Honohan said to them last March.  He asked them to consider split mortgages, set out as a possibility under the personal insolvency legislation and under the new code of conduct as well.  Rather like the personal insolvency legislation, the new code of conduct was really a charter for the banks for what they can do.  While we can talk about good faith, the banks do not act in good faith.  The banks act to make a profit.  They act in their own best interests and in no one else's interests.</p><p>Let us consider what they did for Patrick Honohan, the Governor of the Central Bank, when he asked them to start addressing the 142,000 mortgages in arrears.  He asked them to consider split mortgages, and they did so.  To date, a total of 142 split mortgage arrangements have been made.  However, if we split that among the five banks, it does not amount to much activity by the banks when it comes to making an arrangement in good faith with people in mortgage arrears.  The banks have no more regard for the Central Bank now than they did five years ago.</p><p>The last time he was here I asked the Minister what discussions were held with the banks and whether he could make available to us details of the discussions and the position papers that the Government had for the Personal Insolvency Bill prior to the banks discussing it with them and what the legislation looked like after the banks came in.  Perhaps the Minister would enlighten us about whether he could make those papers available to us?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900024#Y00300"><p>The Minister will not reply until the end.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900024#Y00400"><p>He had no problem replying last time.  We were not even on Committee Stage last time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900024#Y00500"><p>In fairness, Senator Daly, the Minister is not obliged to comment until the end of Second Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900024#Y00600"><p>Since the Minister had no problem replying the last time, I am affording him the opportunity to give a response this time.  Is he considering making available to us the position papers that the banks had when they approached him with regard to the personal insolvency legislation?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1121" speakername="Paul Bradford" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900024#Y00700"><p>Is it my turn now?  The previous speaker appears to have concluded.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900024#Y00800"><p>Senator Daly, you had eight minutes to make your contribution.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900024#Y00900"><p>I am making my contribution.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900024#Y01000"><p>You have five minutes remaining.  The Minister is not obliged to comment until the end of Second Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900024#Y01100"><p>He does not have to respond if he does not want to respond.  I am giving him an opportunity to respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900024#Y01200"><p>It is quite obvious.  The Minister is quite capable of answering if he wishes to do so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900024#Y01300"><p>He responded the last time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900024#Y01400"><p>Obviously, he does not want to respond until the end of Second Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900024#Y01500"><p>This is contemptuous.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900024#Y01600"><p>As the Minister knows, silence is not acquiescence in the eyes of the law.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900025#Z00100"><p>Senator Daly, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900025#Z00200"><p>Would I take that as-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1025" speakername="Alan Shatter" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900025#Z00300"><p>The Senator knows he is only play-acting given that it was his party that destroyed the economy and put tens of thousands of people in difficulties in their homes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900025#Z00400"><p>Sorry, Minister, please.  Senator Daly, without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1025" speakername="Alan Shatter" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900025#Z00500"><p>A little humility from the Senator might do a lot.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900025#Z00600"><p>Is that a "No"?  Is the Minister not willing to give the transparency he promised when entering government?  When the banks discussed the Personal Insolvency Bill with the Government all we asked for was transparency.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900025#Z00700"><p>We got a lot of that from the Senator's party.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900025#Z00800"><p>Senator Daly, without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900025#Z00900"><p>The people want to know what the banks asked for when it came to the Personal Insolvency Bill.  The last time the Minister was in the House I asked him to make those papers available to us and we still do not have them.  Would the Minister consider making available to the people what the Personal Insolvency Bill-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900025#Z01000"><p>On a point of information------</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900025#Z01100"><p>A point of order, Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900025#Z01200"><p>Yes, it is a point of order.  I understand we are on Second Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900025#Z01300"><p>I also point out that-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900025#Z01400"><p>Senator Daly, please.  I have called Senator Healy Eames on a point of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900025#Z01500"><p>I understand we are discussing Second Stage of the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900025#Z01600"><p>That is not a point of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900025#Z01700"><p>The Minister is obliged to answer at the end and not at this point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900025#Z01800"><p>The Chair is doing its best.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900025#Z01900"><p>I find this behaviour contemptuous.  We are dealing with a very important subject for which I have complete regard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900025#Z02000"><p>I ask Senator Healy Eames to resume her seat.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900025#Z02100"><p>That sort of behaviour is contemptuous.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900025#Z02200"><p>For the Senator's information, the Minister was here when we discussed the personal insolvency legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900025#Z02300"><p>Senator Daly, on Second Stage of the Bill, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900025#Z02400"><p>If the Senator had been here for it, she would have noticed that the Minister did reply.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900025#Z02500"><p>Senator Daly, please do not-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900025#Z02600"><p>I just afforded the Minister the same opportunity as he took the last time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900025#Z02700"><p>Senator Daly, on Second Stage of the Bill, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900025#Z02800"><p>If the Minister does not wish to take that opportunity, he is more than entitled not to respond to the question of what the banks sought when it came to the changes in the Personal Insolvency Bill, which has a bearing on this Bill.  We have seen what the banks did when it came to the Central Bank.  Never mind that a bank manager might tell a poor mortgage holder that the bank wants to repossess the family home, the Central Bank has informed them to give split mortgages but for the 142,000 people in arrears they have only handed out 142 split mortgages because they do not want to do it and there is no compulsion on them to do so.  Can one imagine what they will be doing to people who are sitting before them in good faith?</p><p>If we had all the safeguards and proper personal insolvency legislation that had not been written by the banks or if we had a powerful Central Bank that could compel the banks to give split mortgages when people seek to resolve their arrears issues, then we might regard the Land and Conveyancing Law Reform Bill as part of a banking system in a normal working economy.  However, we have seen that the banks do not act in good faith and only operate in their own interest.  Blaming a bank for making a profit does not make sense because that is what they are established to do.  They are not too concerned about the mortgage holders, which beggars belief when one considers that if they repossess these houses they will not grant loans to buy the same houses.  It leaves the economic situation in paralysis.</p><p>I have said it numerous times and President Bill Clinton, when he was here in November two years ago, said that Ireland needs to solve its mortgage problem.  A mere 142 split mortgages indicates that the banks are not solving our mortgage problem, despite the Government's best efforts.  The Government is trying as did the previous Government, but unfortunately the banks seem to be ignoring the Government and the Central Bank.  Now the troika is going to haul the Government over the coals because the banks are not dealing with the mortgage arrears crisis despite numerous attempts by the Government to make them do so.</p><p>When the Government is engaging with the banks and asking them for their opinion, it will only have one result.  Those who have worked on behalf of those people in arrears and those who have borrowed money from the bank have pointed out in briefings to many in political parties that the personal insolvency legislation and the Land and Conveyancing Law Reform Bill explain why we had a stay on the amount of repossessions.  The previous Government had introduced an initial moratorium and the Land and Conveyancing Law Reform Bill, by accident more than anything else, has put a further stay on it.</p> <p>Once the banks get their teeth into this they will go through the process of making many offers that are unsustainable.  We know they make unsustainable offers because in almost one third of all mortgage arrears solutions offered, the people involved have again gone into arrears.  That indicates the level of engagement by banks with people in difficulty.</p><p>This is an amazing week in that three major legislative measures are coming before the House on democracy, people retaining their homes, and abortion.  It is probably the most important week for any legislator.  We are passing this Bill, which is a charter to allow banks repossess homes once they engage in good faith with the owners, having seen the way they engaged in good faith with the Government.  The Government is seeking to reduce the number of legislators by one third but we need more legislation when it comes to banks.  </p><p>On the abortion issue, and some of my colleagues opposite hold similar views to mine, there is a great deal of evidence before us yet we are now legislating for a solution that all the experts tell us is not the solution.  It will be an amazing week.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1121" speakername="Paul Bradford" time="17:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900026#AA00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Lynch, and her colleague, the Minister, Deputy Shatter, who made the opening remarks.  Whatever about this being an amazing week, the contribution from Senator Daly was not particularly amazing.  I heard much of it when he spoke on the personal insolvency legislation, which was very important, but the Senator's contribution was by way of a single transferable speech, which we heard again today.  The Senator knows that we are obliged to pass this legislation because of a court case and that we are simply restating what the previous Government, which was very much led and directed by the Senator's party, believed to be the position at that time.  Fortunately for distressed mortgage holders across the country, of whom there are tens of thousands, the Minister is at least using this legislation to put some additional measures in place which might be of some help.  We all wish we would not have to be in this place politically but our country and our economy is broken and, sadly, these property crises arise from that.</p><p>We got the lecture from Senator Daly about the admonishment by former President Bill Clinton when he told us to get our house in order, if Members will excuse the pun, but the way they get their house in order in the United States in terms of people who cannot pay their mortgages is that they repossess and sell.  The huge foreclosure market in America is as much a product of President Bill Clinton's Democratic Party as it is a product of the Republican Party and therefore I am not interested in listening to lectures from President Bill Clinton on housing or on many other policy issues facing us, particularly this week.</p><p>Every Member recognises that there is a profound problem with mortgages.  Sadly, too many families cannot repay their mortgages and face a genuine financial crisis.  We must try to work with them to assist in that regard.</p><p>It is ironic that we are debating the legislation here when the troika is in town.  Apparently, part of the troika's discussions this week with the Government, the Department of Finance and other Departments concerns this issue in its broadest format.  It will probably cause further reflection on Government thinking but it is fair to say that as a result of the personal insolvency legislation a suite of measures were put in place by the Minister, Deputy Shatter, and the Government some months ago.  We are at least setting out some sort of roadmap and, it is hoped, a path to safety for a reasonable number of families.  That must be welcomed.</p><p>In terms of one of the measures being taken by the Minister, the legal obligation on him would be to simply put in place what we believed was the position before the court case but he is now bringing about the possibility of substantial negotiation with the personal insolvency provisions.  This is not a personal attack on him but Senator Daly said that the banks will continue to ignore us as they have always done in the past.</p> <p>If the banks are not co-operating to a reasonable degree the courts can decide not to let the repossession go ahead and direct the banks and the borrowers down the route of the personal insolvency process.  This degree of slowing down the process is helpful.  No new powers will be provided as a result of the legislation; I know we will hear this statement later in the week, but it is true with regard to this Bill.  It is a tidying up measure arising from the Start Mortgages court case, but it is appropriate the Government puts in place any further additional assistance it can by way of this legislation.</p><p>The Minister has been very clear in his statement as to where he wants the legislation to lead and how he wants it to help.  I am sure the Minister of State, Deputy Lynch, would agree with the Minister's view that the repossession of a family home or principal private residence must be a last resort after all other avenues have been tried.  This is the starting point of the Government's policy and is at the core of this and other legislation.  We must recognise that tragically there will still be cases where repossession will take place, but at least let us have it structured and be aware of the full legal underpinning of the rules so people can be helped as far as possible even though the outcome would not be desirable.  The availability of the Circuit Court option is welcome so people will be in a position to avoid having to travel to the High Court in Dublin.</p><p>The Acting Chairman often speaks in the House on the question of personal debt, housing debt, mortgages and the need for us to do whatever is possible.  The backdrop is our economic crisis, our broken economy and the fact that hundreds of thousands of people borrowed to a level where repayment in full is not sustainable.  The personal insolvency arrangement measures are a part response and this is a necessary tidying up of another part of the problem.  We all recognise that further efforts are required.</p><p>I thank the Minister for his contribution and his personal commitment, which we saw very much in the House, as we also saw from the Minister of State, Deputy Lynch, when dealing with the personal insolvency legislation.  It was considered in a thorough and inclusive fashion whereby amendments from the Opposition were listened to with great respect.  Many were taken on board and are now part of the legislation.  Rather than Opposition Senators, such as the previous speakers, trying to rewrite history and making smart comments and silly interventions on a subject as serious as a person's house, home and family home we should all try to work together.  If people have genuine problems with the legislation let us try to improve it, but let us not pretend we live in a Walter Mitty land where we can ignore these problems and wish them away.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="17:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900027#BB00200"><p>I congratulate the Minister, Deputy Shatter.  He made the point that one of the priorities of the Government was to deal with the problem of unsustainable mortgage debt.  As somebody who has been working in this field for a long time I am well aware of the previous attempts made to try to deal with the situation very unsatisfactorily.  Measures to reform and modernise the law relating to bankruptcy and insolvency are critical in removing us from the current impasse we are at in regard to resolving the mortgage debt situation.</p><p>I have worked in this area and as a personal solicitor for many years and I am more than aware, as many of us are, of the dreadful position in Ireland today of those facing mortgage arrears.</p> <p>Let us be real about it, they are facing mortgage arrears because of the collapse in the housing market and the economy.  This is the bottom line.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="17:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900028#CC00200"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="17:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900028#CC00300"><p>This Bill is viewed with concern by many for whom I have the deepest of respect as part of a wider strategy to permit easier repossessions, coming as it does on foot of the revised mortgage arrears resolution process, which appears to place lenders in an even stronger position than heretofore.  Well-respected organisations such as the Free Legal Advice Centres, FLAC, have stated that the revised code reconfirms the lender as the sole arbiter of whether a mortgage is sustainable.  A bank will decide whether a borrower is co-operative and what solution will be sustainable.  No proper appeals process is in place and there is no provision for the borrower to take credible independent advice when dealing with a lender.</p><p>I regret the Bill's timing.  It would have been more appropriate to introduce it when the personal insolvency service was up and running and the manner in which the service was going to do business was clear in the public mind.  We have not reached that point.</p><p>While attempts by the Government and the Central Bank to force the six main mortgage credit institutions to offer solutions to distressed borrowers by way of the 2013 mortgage arrears resolution targets are well meaning, they have yet to show tangible results.  Among the wider public, there is considerable fear that, as the housing market recovers in parts of the country, particularly Dublin, banks are proposing so-called solutions that they determine in their sole wisdom to be reasonable, but that will achieve nothing in the long run other than repossessions.  It would have been wiser to propose this legislation after the efficacy of the solutions being offered to borrowers could be seen to be just.</p><p>The Minister views this legislation as part of a jigsaw, in that it removes a loophole enabling those in mortgage arrears who will not pay - I distinguish between those who will not pay or are reluctant to reach agreements with their lenders and those who cannot pay - to avoid coming to the table in a meaningful way.  Not for one moment do I believe the words of Ulster Bank's CEO when he asserted last week that one in three of those in long-term arrears were effectively in the category of those who would not pay.  It was a serious overstatement of the situation.  However, some people are in that category.  They could make payments but choose not to do so.  They do an incredible disservice to those who must deny themselves and their children basic necessities to make mortgage repayments.  Among this latter group, there is genuine fear that this legislation, intended for others, will be used to dispossess them of their homes.  We must address this concern by demonstrating that we are willing to listen to them.</p><p>In this context, will the Minister review the revised code of conduct on mortgage arrears as a matter of urgency?  Too much power has been placed with the lending institutions.  In particular, that a lender has been allowed the discretion to decide what constitutes a sustainable and affordable solution for a borrower goes against the principles of natural justice.  A more level playing field must be introduced to balance the rights of borrowers and lenders.  The absence of expert legal and accounting advice for many borrowers at the negotiating stage of an agreement is a powerful impediment to the creation of confidence in the system.  While the Money Advice and Budgeting Service, MABS, is a wonderful organisation, it is woefully under-resourced in this crisis.</p><p>Moreover, there is a lack of transparency in the system.  No one knows which lender is offering what to which borrower.  This is unacceptable and leads to a lack of confidence in the system.  Why a lender cannot be open about what solutions it is offering to borrowers is beyond credibility.  The refrain that every borrower and every situation is different rings hollow to someone who is trying to determine whether to accept an offer from a lender.  This culture of secrecy leads to the suspicion that those who owe more are being treated better by lending institutions than those who owe less.</p> <p>I am well aware - I was a practising solicitor - that it is nonsense to behave like King Canute in the face of what is a legal lacuna and to propose that a lender should not have recourse to charged assets.  Countries which have an inadequate legal system have, by extrapolation, an inadequate mortgage system.  If we want to see the recovery of our housing market, we need to see a robust legal system where lenders have access to the charged assets.  However, it is not appropriate to introduce this legislation at this time.  I will ask the Minister to take into account the serious concerns in the public domain and to consider delaying the implementation of this legislation until such time as the Personal Insolvency Service of Ireland is up and running and we see what results come forward from the six banks required to reach agreement with borrowers.</p><p>I have a major concern I would like to bring to the Minister's attention which relates to recent statements by the Governor of the Central Bank of Ireland, Professor Patrick Honohan.  He stated that he foresees that repossessions will be focused on the buy-to-let property sector and not on family homes.  That is perfectly understandable but we must understand that currently 20% of the entire housing market comprises people renting their homes.  Currently, we have no procedures in place as to how those repossessions are to be treated and how the families in those homes are to be treated.  That is a very significant lacuna in the law as it stands.</p><p>I understand the necessity for this legislation to remedy the lacuna which has come to pass but the Minister should exercise his discretion and take into account the serious concerns in society.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="17:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900029#DD00200"><p>I welcome the Minister.  I always listen with particular interest and respect to Senator Hayden's contributions, especially on this issue in which she has considerable expertise and about which she has concern and passion.  Having read the legislation, I take the view that it is not about letting banks have any kind of free rein to repossess homes and I think Senator Hayden would acknowledge that.  As has been acknowledged, it is about remedying a loophole caused by the repeal of other legislation, which restricts lending institutions from exercising their right to repossess properties in the event of default in certain particular instances.</p><p>We have an extremely low number of repossessions in this country, which is positive, and this legislation could help, to some degree, the normalisation of relations between banks and customers.  It could also help lessen the problem of so-called strategic defaults, where people who can afford to repay their debts opt not to do so in the hope of a debt write-off some time in the future.  If such people could be cut off, we could have a better overall picture of people who really cannot pay and who need help in some way.</p><p>Like most other people in this country, I have little sympathy for the banks but it is worth noting in passing some commentary from Reuters which said that totally avoiding repossessions could delay Ireland's exit from its EU-IMF bailout programme and make the eventual write-downs more costly for banks, as has happened in Spain.  I would like, in principle, to support measures to ensure the country regains its economic independence as soon as possible in this area.  Mr. Karl Deeter of Irish Mortgage Brokers argues that the reduced repossession time, as contained in the code of conduct on mortgage arrears, is probably a good thing because, as he put it, it might provide a faster solution for people going into deep arrears and help them to crystalise losses earlier.  I certainly hope that is the case.</p><p>The fact this legislation provides for a debt arrangement or an examination of the possibilities under the personal insolvency legislation during the adjournment of the case for repossession for two months is very welcome.  This situation of negotiation is very much the norm in business where one business negotiates with another where one cannot pay.  However, a bank can vote against a personal insolvency proposal if it believes it is an inappropriate solution.  I echo what has been said in that I would like to see a more equitable balance in this situation and seek more power for the customer to negotiate.  We have to bear in mind that, as in any business, it must be based on trust but banks have lost that trust.</p> <p>This situation has been exacerbated by the most recent revelations from the Anglo Irish Bank tapes. </p><p> Can we really trust banks to do a fair deal with the customer?  On top of this, it is very concerning to hear reports that distressed homeowners with equity in their homes who talked to their banks are more likely to be targeted for repossessions.  However, those in negative equity are more likely to be given a debt deal, according to New Beginning.  It says responsible mortgage holders are being targeted and homes which have a market value greater than the loan amount owed are usually considered to be the low hanging fruit for banks on a repossession campaign. </p><p> People who have equity in their homes, often as a result of sustained payments over years, might find themselves facing repossession by banks eager to reclaim their value.  New Beginning says, &quot;We are in danger of creating a system in which those who are behaving themselves get the worst treatment and those are behaving badly are apparently rewarded&quot;.  This claim was substantiated by Bank Check, a firm which checks mortgage records on behalf of Irish borrowers who have found themselves in difficulty.  If this situation is true it is very worrying, especially for people who have made such an effort and have been very responsible in their repayment of debt.  We must bear in mind the views of other organisations assisting people in trouble with their mortgages.  The Free Legal Advice Centre's director general, Ms Noeline Blackwell, says of the new code of conduct on mortgage arrears, &quot;Lenders will control how they deal with arrears more than they ever did before.  It is likely to result in borrowers in arrears coming under considerable pressure to accept whatever alternative offer is made to them by the lender, if one is made to them at all&quot;.  </p><p> The revised code reconfirms that the lender is the sole arbiter of whether a mortgage is sustainable.  The bank will decide whether a borrower is co-operative or what solution might be sustainable.  There is no proper appeal process and there is no provision for advice and support for a borrower going through the negotiation with the lender.  I would like the Minister to reassure mortgage holders that they will not be under more pressure as a result of the code and that there will be a chance of fair deals with lenders.  I acknowledge much of what Senator Hayden has said. </p><p> I would also like Minister to comment on the idea that mortgage holders could be given a legal right to change their mortgage temporarily to a rent agreement for a certain number of years.  Instead of repossession homeowners would be given the option to stay in a house for seven or ten years while paying a fair market rent determined by an independent appraiser.  Mr. Dean Baker of the Centre for Economic Policy in the US who came up with the policy said, &quot;The own to rent plan is a simple and low cost way to help moderate income homebuyers.  It does not require money.  It does not set up a new government bureaucracy to manage the housing market&quot;.  Mr. Andrew Samwick, a former economic adviser to the US Presidency, put it as follows, &quot;If the Government is going to intervene in the aftermath of this meltdown I haven't seen a better proposal than this one&quot;.  It is an idea that has been endorsed by <i>The New York Times</i>, although I would not endorse everything coming from it, and supported by Mr. Simon Johnson, a former chief economist in the IMF and a professor at Massachusetts Institute of Technology.  Has consideration been given to the possibility of a variation of this policy?  Is it something which should be taken into our discussions with the IMF?</p><p> A major factor in the mortgage crisis is that we have to put in place everything we can, especially in light of recent moves in the area, to prevent people from losing their homes and to guarantee them that right.  The right to rent solution would be an innovative part of the solution and merits attention.  Legislation to this effect has been sponsored in the US and perhaps we should consider such a move, which would allow people to stay in their homes.  It also has the ability to release cash into the economy as people would not be as constrained as they otherwise would be because they would have smaller repayments. </p><p> If banks are getting more power in the area of mortgages, as some argue is the case, could we at least give the consumer an opportunity to transfer mortgages to fair rents for a number of years, determined independently?  If a mortgage holder was guaranteed this right through law we would have a better knowledge of those who are in trouble with their mortgages.  It would be a fair deal for the customer to give them the right, through law and not influenced by banks, to restructure his or her mortgage if he or she wants to do so.  It is a proposal that should be considered and I would like to hear the comments of the Minister.  I ask him to let us know whether the Government has considered this option as one of the tools to help us solve the mortgage crisis.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="17:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900030#EE00200"><p>I welcome the Minister.  It is timely that we are discussing the Bill in the House because it has given us an opportunity to debate in issue of major concern.</p> <p>It is that there is a prevailing view that the banks and lenders are ruling the roost at the expense of the mortgage holder.  It is very important that we flag the issue with the Government because the matter needs to be addressed.</p><p>The Land and Conveyancing Law Reform Bill 2013 is clearly rectifying an issue arising from a court case and we are remedying a loophole in a previous Act.  We must act to remove the unintended constraint on banks to realise the value of a loan collateral under certain circumstances.  We must also ensure at the same time that the rights of the home owner are protected.  I particularly welcome section 2 of the Bill, which provides that in repossession proceedings involving a principal private residence, a court may, where it considers it appropriate on application by a borrower, adjourn the proceedings to enable the parties to consider whether a personal insolvency arrangement under the new Act would be a more appropriate alternative to repossession.  That is helpful.</p><p>We really need to be careful in Ireland because we do not have a history of repossessions.  Should that begin to happen here, we will change the landscape completely, and we will alter a trust that has existed for decades.  We can give out about banks all we want but there has not been a history of repossessions.  I lived in the United States for three and a half years and there is a very big history of repossession there, with auctions of repossessed properties and foreclosures.  Should we go down such a road, much trust will be lost at very delicate moment in our history.</p><p>Will the Minister of State collaborate with the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Shatter, as we urgently need a thorough review and analysis of the prevailing concern that banks are getting too much power in the impending repossession scenario?  I accept that we have a low rate of repossessions but we do not want that to unnecessarily increase if people can be enabled to stay in their homes.  I request for the autumn a progress report on the personal insolvency legislation and the split mortgage issue in particular.  If there are so few split mortgage being arranged, we need to know the reason, as a split mortgage is one of the best ways to enable people to repay what they can afford while parking another piece of a mortgage until they are in a better position to pay.  Like others have indicated, such as Senators Hayden and Mullen, I would like a review of the code of conduct on mortgage arrears.</p><p>I want to be able to see people enabled to stay in their own homes so we should call a spade a spade.  The collapse in the economy was largely - and perhaps wholly - caused by banks and a lack of regulation by the previous Government.  The Minister of State might address the following question in summing up.  Would people be facing repossession today if the banking collapse had not happened, through no fault of those people?  If the answer to the question is &quot;No&quot;, the people in question should be enabled to stay in their own homes.  However, if people were reckless enough to be facing repossession regardless of the banking collapse, we are talking about a different kind of customer.  On the whole, we condemn the behaviour of people who can pay but will not pay but we must carefully work out which is which.</p><p>I am particularly concerned about the prevailing reports that banks are moving on homes that have equity because they are good value.  That would be despicable behaviour.  The majority of proposed changes should not favour the lender over the borrower in the mortgage arrears process and it must be on a level playing field, with engagement between customers and advisers.</p><p>There are many concerns and much to say about the Bill.  I do not know if my time is close to an end.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="17:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900031#FF00200"><p>The Senator's time is up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="17:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900031#FF00300"><p>The most important information we can get from the Minister of State concerns when we will have a discussion on the new mortgage arrears code.  We should have that before the summer.  There must be a review of the personal insolvency legislation in the autumn.  Let this Government not be judged on failing home owners who did not cause the banking collapse in this country.  It is pushing them down the road of arrears on the family home, which is a person's most important possession.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="17:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900031#FF00400"><p>I stand to absolutely and wholly oppose this legislation, which is the wrong legislation at the wrong time.  In a normal, functioning economy, when people are in work, one would not mind having a system of repossession.  However, when people do not have a job and cannot pay their mortgages, it is not right.  There is no evidence of the strategic defaulters referred to by Senator Mullen.  When a person cannot pay a mortgage, why should the banks be given the power to oust him or her from a home?</p><p>This legislation is giving banks the power to put people out of their homes, as under it the banks will be entitled once again to go to court to seek repossession orders.  The court has no discretion but to grant the order, except with regard to a two-month adjournment and an adjournment relating to personal insolvency legislation.  If the Minister for Justice and Equality or the officials had read the texts on this law as it applied before the 2009 Act, they would have seen that there was always a major gap in the law and a judge has no discretion but to give a repossession order.  The judge has no guidance whatever on what factors should be taken into account when he or she must give the repossession order.  This means that in effect there is no point in having a court process as nothing will happen aside from a granting of the order or pushing the process towards the personal insolvency area if it is not there already.  I am surprised this issue has not been addressed.</p><p>On this side of the House we put forward a family home Bill at around the same time as the Dunne judgment, which was designed to address the loophole created by the judgment as there is nothing to guide the courts in this area.  That position is not changing with the Bill and there is still a major gap.  If the Department officials had looked at the texts in this area they would know about this, as they would have if they had looked at our Bill.  The Bill before us is simply putting the banks back in charge.</p><p>I pay tribute to the Oireachtas Library and Research Service because once again it has produced a totally unbiased and potentially controversial statement in the Bill's digest.  The service has done that before with the septic tanks legislation, as it contradicted Government statements.  The digest indicates &quot;Repossessions will allegedly focus mostly on investment properties rather than family homes&quot;.  There is no difference except that with a family home case, personal insolvency arrangements may apply.  Why can that not happen with other properties or why does it only apply to family homes?  The family home ought to be protected and there should be guidance but there is nothing to tell the court that if people have nowhere to go, the repossession order cannot be made, or that alternatives like a mortgage to rent scheme can be suggested.  Our family home Bill tried to facilitate a position where if proceedings went to repossession, many other options would have to be considered.  There is nothing in this Bill in that respect.  That is wrong and unfair.</p><p>I pay tribute to the Members of D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann who stood up at the Allsop auction last week and I will do the same if any family homes in County Meath - or anywhere else - are in a similar position.  It would be wrong and unjust for that to happen.  Senator Healy Eames analysed the position very well.  If a person is in a bad position because of the economic collapse or the loss of a job that is beyond the person's control, he or she should not have the family home repossessed.  If somebody has gone overboard, on the other hand, it is hard to justify keeping him or her in the house, as long as there is some place for that person to go.  We cannot kick out people to the streets, no matter who they are.  Why should this not be addressed in the Bill, as that is what we tried to do with our family home legislation?</p><p>The Government has been lobbied by the banks, as has happened before and is happening once again.  The code of conduct is another bankers' charter.  There was some nonsense during the by-election a few months ago about targets that would be reached but the issue has proven to be a bankers' charter.  It is the same with this Bill.  It is about time we had some fairness.</p> <p>The Irish public has given so much to the banks that it is time for those institutions to give back something.  There should be some balance on that see-saw; it is currently stacked in favour of the non-paying borrower who cannot be put out of a house, in effect, but the see-saw is going right in the other direction.  We are only seeking balance because if somebody is not paying a mortgage on a property, the matter must be addressed.  Nevertheless, the State cannot put these people out on the street because the consequences for society would be horrendous.</p><p>One can consider some of the cities in America where repossessions are rife and some parts have turned into ghost towns.  I do not know if that is likely here but there are tremendous social consequences to repossessions which have not been addressed at all in this debate or legislation.  We really need to give people a break until they get back to work because once people are working, there is no excuse.  If people are working in a sustainable job but their mortgage remains unsustainable, something else must be done.  There should be a proper mortgage to rent or mortgage to shared equity scheme in place, with some fairness shown to people in difficulty.</p><p>This Bill ought to be opposed or at least amended significantly to consider the family home Bill that we produced.  We consulted with the Free Legal Advice Centres and New Beginning but I do not know their position on this Bill; they can speak for themselves.  At the time we produced our Bill, they felt the lacuna in the law was significant, although the Dunne judgment addressed it to some extent by essentially postponing repossessions.  The matter has not been dealt with in the Bill and I ask the Government to look at what the standard Irish textbooks on conveyancing state about repossession orders.  The gap is not being dealt with in this legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="17:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900032#GG00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House.  The Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Shatter, has already given a full and detailed explanation of the reasons for this Land and Conveyancing Law Reform Bill 2013, which is meant to deal with a loophole that has arisen with the 2009 Act.  That law was introduced to reform the Registration of Title Act 1964 and the Conveyancing Acts 1881 to 1911.</p><p>It is interesting to hear Senator Byrne argue that this legislation should not proceed.  It is important to consider the Minister's speech for a clear example of what he is talking about.  He states &quot;However, in the Start Mortgages case which I mentioned earlier, the High Court interpreted this provision of the Interpretation Act in a manner which restricts the application of the law in force prior to 1 December 2009 to certain cases where default had occurred prior to that date and demand for repayment had also been made before that date.&quot;  Taking Senator Byrne's comments into account, this means that if a person owns a &euro;5 million house in default prior to 1 December 2009, with demand for repayment made prior to that date, the Senator wants the person to continue living in that house.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="17:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900032#GG00300"><p>People with &euro;5 million houses do not come to my clinics.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.173" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="17:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900032#GG00400"><p>I am giving an example from the Senator's comments.  The Senator argued there should be no change in the law and it should be left as it is, even if the house in question is worth &euro;5 million.  There is a loophole in the legislation and the Minister has brought forward this Bill, making provision under sections 2 and 3 specifically with regard to a principal private residence, as the courts would have certain obligations with regard to new personal insolvency arrangements.  That is to ensure proper procedures are followed so that every opportunity can be given to the home owner in dealing with the matter.  There would also be an attempt to reduce costs by ensuring the matters are dealt with in the Circuit Court.</p><p>In supporting the Minister and this legislation, it is important that we analyse how the banks behaved when they gave out money prior to 2008.  For example, I know of one case where &euro;4.5 million was given to a borrower, with &euro;1.5 million of the sum given to the borrower in order to buy shares in the bank lending the money.  There were 11 properties remortgaged in that case and the bank did not hesitate in repossessing those properties.  The banks behaved disgracefully in that case.  In another example, &euro;180,000 was borrowed by a couple who went their separate ways.  A parent tried to help one of the parties who wanted to stay in the house, and an additional &euro;40,000 was borrowed, with the parent signing a mortgage for the full &euro;220,000.  That property is now worth 50% of the value.  It is another example of unreasonable behaviour from the banks prior to 2008.</p><p>At the time the banks were acting on behalf of builders and in order to keep cash flowing, they wanted bank officials to contact colleagues and get customers to buy properties that the banks' clients had for sale.  That ensured constant cash flow for builders.  One branch would loan the money and another would collect the money in a builder's account.  All this went on when the banks had no real control or supervision, which was a major contributory factor to many of the problems we ended up with.  I have had discussions with bank officials about their concerns that decisions are not being made at the coal face or by the people meeting borrowers; instead they are made at a central level in Dublin.  There is a big concern about the process and banks should ensure that all the facts are being considered before decisions are made.</p><p>This legislation must be put in place to remove the loophole that exists but it is also important that the banking sector should deal with the buy-to-let area.  In a small number of cases there are people with extensive borrowings collecting rent but making no contribution to the bank.  As a result, the taxpayer will unfortunately end up carrying the can when insufficient money is collected for the repayment of those loans.  Such issues must be dealt with.</p><p>I agree with other contributors with regard to principal private residences, and every opportunity and assistance must be available to families and house owners so that it will be a very last resort for legal proceedings or repossessions to take place.  Priority should be given to the house owner and the Minister in the legislation is ensuring that changes have been brought in to incorporate the personal insolvency process and ensuring courts must follow certain procedures.  I support the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.174" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1147" speakername="John Crown" time="17:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900032#GG00500"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Kathleen Lynch, to the House.  I have always found it a great pleasure to deal with her as she is helpful, co-operative and respectful to us here.  I will say a few words about the Bill and ask the Minister of State to go on the record with her opinions in this House as to whether in her various visits here, she has felt that legislation, motions and statements have been strengthened by the input of Senators and if she believes there will be any loss to our legislative process if the Seanad is abolished.</p><p>This is, indirectly, yet another piece of legislation and regulation dealing with the fall-out of the economic collapse.  My research team has put together some figures, although I know many numbers have been plucked from rather strange places in the national debate over the past couple of weeks.  The figures I have come from verifiable sources.  Some 80,000 households, or approximately one in 12 families, have mortgages in our Republic that are more than six months behind in repayments.  These mortgage holders now owe approximately &euro;1.7 billion in mortgage arrears on top of their existing mortgages.  The underpayment is likely to expand to &euro;3 billion by the end of the 2014 calendar year.  Nearly a third of these houses, or almost 26,000 households, are now more than two years behind in repayments.</p><p>I would argue that the market will remain bad.  In 2012, only 17,000 homes were sold and should banks attempt to repossess the homes they have with the aim of reselling them, they will precipitate a further massive decline in house prices, which are already down 50% nationally from a peak value in September 2007.</p> <p>Is the Government simply enacting this legislation knowing that the banks cannot afford to use these powers in order to fulfil some requirement placed on it by the troika?  </p><p>Let us say the 25,000 homes sitting on more than &euro;5 billion worth of defaulting mortgages are seized by the banks.  Who will the banks sell them to?  Who will provide the mortgages to the people who are going to buy these homes?  How will the banks, which must mark their mortgage book to market and will, therefore, require a fresh inflow of capital to meet their Basel II requirements, never mind their Basel III capital requirements, fund these mortgages?  Does the Minister have a plan that will paper over the &euro;100 billion hole in the banks' balance sheets, which will open if they are stupid enough to move in on these homes?  What about next year when about 28,000 new people will be more than two years in arrears?  What will happen to them and their &euro;5.3 billion worth of mortgages?  What about the 20,000 who hold almost &euro;6 billion of buy-to-let mortgages?  There are certain aspects to the financial underpinning of the implications of this Bill which, to say the least, are phantasmagorical.  </p><p>In support of what my colleague Senator Byrne said, it is really important to look at what is going on here.  There is a certain amount of the rub of reproach on the Irish people for the allegation that we partied, an allegation we heard made by Angela Merkel and the Taoiseach and recently by the former deputy head of the IMF.  Most people did not party.  They did exactly the same thing their parents, grandparents and, in most cases, great-grandparents did.  They bought a house.  The difference was that the house, which was often the same kind of house their ancestors would have bought, was sold at a grossly inflated price due to the bizarre market forces of which we are aware and which were wrapped in cheap credit.  Sober people, not necessarily party animals, working people and young parents went out and made what they were told was the responsible decision to get on the property ladder.  These were not, by and large, wild cowboy and cowgirl speculators.  They were people who, rather than spending their money on short-term expenses, made what they thought would be a long-term investment that would underpin their future and that of their families.  I can recall how people who made the decision to live in rented accommodation because they wanted to have more disposable income were looked at as being somehow irresponsible as if they were the partiers.  </p><p>What changed?  What changed was the banks.  In a previous generation, banks would not have given people on a limited income a mortgage to buy a house they could not afford.  Trusted banks which were a near priestly caste in this society gave people prudent advice as to what would be in their interest knowing it was also in the banks' interest.  Instead, what happened was a culture in which the banks as entities, their senior executives and people all the way down to branch level who were on huge bonuses to advise people in a colossal conflict of interest to take out mortgages they could not afford suddenly found themselves peddling mortgages that would never have been admissible before.  </p><p>I put it to the Minister that in attempting to redress the situation, and it has been mentioned by the Minister for Justice and Equality in this House before in another context, he cannot give a chancer's charter with Bills.  There was another lot who were definitely chancers in this and I do not believe that everybody in the banks knew or believed they were in error.  I believe many of them made these decisions because they knew there was a short-term bonus gain in it for them.  If we are making redress, the least we can do is look at things like non-recourse mortgages.  This is a situation which applies in many parts of the world where if somebody has bought a house, is in colossal negative equity and wants to make a fresh start in life, he or she can go to the bank and say &quot;Here, take it, it's yours.&quot;  That is the way it should be.  It would not deal with people who would become homeless but it would deal with many people who would be in that situation.  I speak as somebody who found himself in substantial negative equity and has worked hard to pay it down to equity at this point in time so it probably would not help me too much.  It would help the average person who wants to make a fresh start, even people who want to change jobs such as those who, God forbid, may get a good job abroad but who cannot go because they cannot walk away from the mortgage they have.  Could we not look at some means of redressing that imbalance and acknowledging in the system we have that much, if not most, of the responsibility for these business decisions was not that of ordinary working people who had no financial background but that of skilled professionals who deliberately manipulated them?  When we are seeking some kind of redress, we should at least look at splitting the difference in this sort of situation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="18:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900033#HH00200"><p>Cuirim c&eacute;ad f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it.  T&aacute;im ag &eacute;isteacht go c&uacute;ramach le gach a bhfuil le r&aacute; ar seo.  Almost 190,000 households are in mortgage distress and almost one in four residential mortgage holders are unable to meet their repayments.  Some are in arrears for extended periods of time while others are in reduced payment schemes but one in four are unable to repay their mortgage debt and the numbers are rising.  While this problem was created by Fianna F&aacute;il, it has got significantly worse since Fine Gael and the Labour Party took office.  The number of struggling mortgage holders has doubled.  Many of us cringe when we hear Fianna F&aacute;il Senators and Deputies offer solutions to a crisis they created and then refused to tackle when last in government.  </p><p>However, Fianna F&aacute;il's role in this crisis does not absolve the current Government of its responsibilities.  Fine Gael and the Labour Party have continually talked about giving priority to addressing the mortgage crisis and we heard it here again today but it took it almost two years to publish the Personal Insolvency Act, which is the centrepiece of its response to this crisis.  After all its talk of protecting the family home and standing up to the banks, what did the Government do?  It did what Fianna F&aacute;il did when it was in office and allowed the banks to dictate the agenda.  In fact, it did something worse.  It gave lenders a cast-iron veto over any solutions to individual distressed mortgages.  These same banks have done virtually nothing to assist struggling family home owners since this crisis erupted and many have made things worse by hiking up interest rates on variable rate mortgages.  </p><p>To add insult to injury, the establishment of the personal insolvency service has been much delayed.  We still have no idea when personal insolvency practitioners will be on the ground working with distressed families.  Not a week goes by without more bad news for mortgage holders such as rate increases, regressive changes to the mortgage arrears code of conduct and delays to the personal insolvency service.  This is hurting families and the local economy and is, without doubt, a major contributor to the ongoing recession.  </p><p>In response to this growing crisis, what does the Government do?  Does it force the banks to step up to the plate and help struggling families?  Does it take away the banks' veto over insolvency arrangements?  Does it give the Central Bank and the Financial Regulator the powers to insist that ECB interest rate reductions are passed on to mortgage customers?  No, it does not.  Instead, it brings forward a Bill that makes it easier to evict struggling families from their homes.  This is what the Bill before us is about.  It is not just removing an unintended loophole from earlier legislation.  It is not about ensuring that legitimate repossessions can take place from so-called strategic defaulters.  Plain and simple, it is an eviction charter with one simple purpose - to empower the banks to take people's family homes.  </p><p>The Minister and the Government should be ashamed of themselves.  They should be ashamed of the additional burden of stress and uncertainty they are heaping on struggling mortgage holders.  If they had held this legislation back until the personal insolvency service was up and running and the number of families in mortgage distress was falling, Sinn F&eacute;in may have taken a different approach.  I note that this was a proposal put forward by Senator Hayden.  We accept that there are occasions and exceptional circumstances when repossession is necessary but to give the banks these powers now while the mortgage crisis continues to rage all around us is not only bad policy but bad ethics.  </p><p>The Government is rewarding the banks for their intransigence and their failure to do the right thing by their mortgage customers but then, since taking office, the Government has really changed its tune on the banks.  It talked tough on remuneration when in opposition but rolled over once in office.  It is almost halfway through its term of office and we still have no banking inquiry.  What the Bill before us today makes clear is that when it comes to the banks, Fine Gael and the Labour Party are no different to Fianna F&aacute;il.  Senator Bradford noted the single transferable speech.  I think the previous Government might have left behind some of its single transferable speeches and they were picked up by this Government.  When the banks say &quot;Jump&quot;, this Government, like its predecessors, says &quot;How high?&quot;  Sinn F&eacute;in will oppose this Bill and I urge all other Senators to do likewise.  I note Senator Hayden's comments and I agree with a lot of what she had to say.  If we are to oppose this route of dealing with this scenario, the best way to delay this is to vote against it and I call on Senator Hayden and other Senators in her party to do so.  </p> <p>T&aacute; an Bille seo n&aacute;ireach.  Ba cheart go mbeadh n&aacute;ire ar an Rialtas leis an rud at&aacute; &aacute; dh&eacute;anamh aige.  N&iacute;l s&eacute; ag dul i ngleic leis an bhfadhb.  T&aacute; fadhb na morg&aacute;ist&iacute; ag dul in olcas.  T&aacute; s&eacute; ag m&eacute;ad&uacute; in aghaidh an lae agus n&iacute;l an Rialtas ach ag leanacht an bh&oacute;thair c&eacute;anna, ag leanacht na n-amad&aacute;n a chuaigh rompu.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="18:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900034#JJ00200"><p>I welcome the opportunity to contribute to the debate.  The loophole that is being filled today, while the anomaly needs to be addressed, puts the final tool into the shade of the banks in terms of making them all powerful in pursuit of their debts.  In 2009 we were in Government when I first started to lobby on this issue in the north west and set up the Prevention of Family Home Repossessions Group.  People laughed at what we predicted would be a huge crisis and so it is.  Some of the media covered this point at the weekend. Senator Sean D. Barrett often used the phrase "a metaphorical backstairs" that was available exclusively for the use of the banks into the Department of Finance.</p><p>The recommendations of the Prevention of Family Home Repossessions Group eventually grew into the Family Home Bill.  The then Minister, the late Brian Lenihan, believed in those points of view, that before an order for repossession could be granted the bank would have to convince the court of the quality of the original underwriting in the application, that a full range of alternatives was considered by the bank, including, split mortgages, extending the mortgage up to 20 years, intergenerational mortgages and a number of other measures of which the House is well aware, having listened to me in recent years.  The then Minister's concern was that his officials advised that one had to be conscious of the market and what the market might think of this and, as a result, the best the Minister could do at the time was to get me to make a presentation to the then Hugh Cooney expert group on mortgage arrears and personal debt.</p><p>We also had the Keane group on mortgage arrears, others reviews, a Cabinet subcommittee and a code of conduct, which was useless.  Indeed, the Minister of State, Deputy Brian Hayes, representing the Minister, said when the Family Home Bill was before the House on 11 July 2011 that the code of conduct on mortgage arrears was working exceptionally well.  There was no problem.  He also questioned the constitutionality of the Bill, which is the default position for Ministers when they do not want to accept a Private Members' Bill.  We now have a renewed code of conduct, on which Senator Aideen Hayden and I are on the same page, which gives complete power to the banks.  As Deputy Joe Higgins put it in the other House, the fox is now firmly in control of the hen house, which makes no sense whatsoever.</p><p>In normal trading conditions and if we were considering normal economics and its effects on society, whether one is neoclassical or Keynesian, or whatever aspect one wants to take, I would say that perhaps we have to let repossessions take place.  I have heard others refer to advice that repossessions have to take place and we need to get on with it, in order that we can find the floor and move on.  If this was in a normal scenario, I would say perhaps but we are not in a normal scenario.  There is no school of economics in any trading conditions that would advise guaranteeing the entire banking system to save the euro, to pay back the bondholders in Germany and France.  There is no economics book that will advise one to do that.  For good or for bad, we did it.  Many of us would feel there was no other option at the time.  If Fine Gael was in power it would have had no choice but to do the same; even the mighty Sinn F&eacute;in may have had to do the same, and probably would have done it.  We will never know.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.179" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="18:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900034#JJ00300"><p>Thank you very much.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/982" speakername="Kathleen Lynch" time="18:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900034#JJ00400"><p>They did.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.181" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="18:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900034#JJ00500"><p>The point I am making is that the Irish people stepped up to the mark in a major way and it saved the euro at that time.  I believe they are entitled to something in return.  We are not in normal trading conditions and equally the banks, in their relentless pursuit of profitability - as a State we are shareholders in them - should have to take cognisance of the people who saved them.  They are not doing so.  I ask the Minister of State to take it from someone who knows, who is dealing as an intermediary for many people in mortgage distress, that the banks, despite what her officials say and despite what the Bankers Federation produce in terms of statistical analysis, are only engaged at a superficial level.  I challenge anyone in the Chamber to give me one example of one person they know who has had 15 years added to their mortgage.  The answer is none, because it has happened to nobody.  Ask anybody who has been given a new mortgage rate or a doubling of their mortgage and the answer is none.  Some 144 lucky people have had their mortgages split but the reality is that the level of superficial engagement with people does not reflect the needs of the people on the ground.</p><p>I agree with Senator Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh who said there is little to differentiate between a banking policy of the previous Government and this Government in the context of mortgage arrears, because there is none.  The same advice that was given to the late Brian Lenihan, in terms of how to deal with the mortgage arrears crisis, is being given to the Minister for Finance, Deputy Michael Noonan.  That is as clear as day.  There are two axis of collusion, one is that Department officials and their counterparts in Europe only tell the Minister what it suits them to tell him.  That is a fact, and the few Ministers I have known over the years will bear that out.  The second axis of collusion is clearly the hold that the Central Bank and the banks have over the key officials in the Department of Finance.  Those two axis of collusion need to be broken down, otherwise the people will always come last.  I believe it is time the people began to come first.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.182" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="18:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900034#JJ00600"><p>I welcome the Minister of State and thank Senators for their contributions.  I am learning a great deal, as always, on housing from people such as Senators Aideen Hayden, Senator John Crown and Senator Marc MacSharry.  The problem was that in a period when incomes doubled, the price of houses increased by 500%.  Nobody partied, so far as I can see, except banks.  As Senator John Crown said, people had to have some place in which to live and we steadily put that beyond their reach.  Mortgages of two-and-a-half times the first income and one-and-a-half times the second income would not have bought any house that people wanted.  That is what we are trying to clear up.</p><p>I am concerned that when the consumer wins in a court case it is called a loophole.  That is the relationship between the law, banks and the citizen in Ireland.  The briefing document states that the repossession rate, which the IMF said is too low, at 0.03%, could rise to between 3% and 5%.  Therefore, that raises the spectre of ten to 15 times more repossessions than at present.  Given that  95% of owner-occupied mortgages are in serious deficit and 30,000 buy-to-let mortgages are in the same position, that is a sizeable number of people facing some kind of evictions.</p><p>As Senator Aideen Hayden said, there should be protection for those who rent from buy-to-let mortgage holders.  The landlord changes but there are stories to the effect that the new buyers of those mortgages will impose stricter conditions or, maybe, even require the tenants to be evicted.  They have got to be protected.  I would like the Bill, in its later versions, to put a Chinese wall between the family home and those who invested in buy-to-let mortgages.  I hope the Bill will make that distinction clear.  </p><p>The briefing note states that the purpose of the Bill is explicit.  It has been noted by the IMF in its most recent view of Ireland prompting calls for a need to strengthen the efficiency of the repossession regime.  It an oblique way of saying we need to put more out if we want to get to the 3% or 5% repossession rate rather than 0.03% as at present.</p> <p>The risk of flooding the market is mentioned on page 17 of the briefing document, which was helpfully prepared by Oireachtas staff.  That risk has been recognised by banks and alternative options are being considered.  Therefore, we are trying to keep up the price of houses artificially so that they look better in banks' balance sheets because the Government does not want to put more capital into the banks.  I see it as pretty well inevitable that the banks will have to be recapitalised again.  Why are we organising this strange kind of fake market at the banks' behest?  Immediate measures should be taken to sell off ghost estates rather than letting them fall apart.  Somebody could buy them and they would make housing more affordable.  That is one of the routes by which this economy will eventually recover from the dreaded recession for which the banks and property sector bear the prime responsibility.</p><p>In this period of madness, we have seen the destruction of building societies which were a quasi part of the co-operative movement.  In the Educational Building Society, older teachers gave younger ones funds to buy houses and other building societies were also based on various sectors.  We should look askance at such developments, including the destruction of the banking system and building societies, ever being allowed to happen again.</p><p>This side of the House proposed stricter penalties on banks when dealing with recent legislation on regulating banks.  The Minister for Finance, Deputy Noonan, praised us for doing what he called the heavy lifting.  The following day, however, the Minister of State, Deputy Brian Hayes, threw out everything we had said.  Much stricter regulation of banks is needed to prevent a recurrence of this situation.</p><p>I am as unhappy as Senator Crown is about any measure that makes life easier for banks.  We have an alternative Bill on the Order Paper to change to the Danish system of mortgage finance here.  This is an unhappy occasion.  I gather that the banks have appealed against the High Court verdict in the Dunne decision.  They brought in some of the heavy guns in the legal profession and I gather that verdict is due on 12 September, although I do not know whether that will affect what we are saying here.  It appears to be distinct from the appeal to the Supreme Court, which the Minister mentioned.  We have a lot to do in order to remedy this situation and get a new system of housing finance, rather than just facilitating banks that wish to repossess houses, which were sold to mortgage holders at vastly inflated prices during the boom.  We are all trying to correct that situation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.184" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/982" speakername="Kathleen Lynch" time="18:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900035#KK00200"><p>I appreciate Senator Crown's remarks.  I genuinely believe that when Senators stand up to speak, they do so on behalf of the people, regardless of how they managed to get here.  We all get to the D&aacute;il or Seanad by different routes but, nevertheless, Members of the Oireachtas speak on behalf of the people.  The voice of the people is the voice of God and that has always been my opinion.  I believe fundamentally in democracy and that is why I take particular note of what is said in here.  I appreciate very much some of the thoughtful considerations that are expressed here.</p><p>For the last two years, due to the awful problems that have befallen the country, I keep hearing from certain people that we need a new type of politics.  They say the old politics did not work, so new politics are required.  The very people who shout that at me are the same ones who, when I give open responses, revert to type with the old politics.  They start telling us about typical U-turns and say the Government is no different to any other, yet they are the very people who refer to the need for new politics, which always amazes and amuses me.  </p><p>I always take criticism on the basis that people have a genuine concern about certain issues.  We should take the pressure that is put on Government Ministers in all sorts of areas as a call to arms, a call to do something about a particular issue.  There are some matters we can do nothing about, while we can deal with others.  That type of pressure, however, ensures that these issues get the attention they deserve.  </p><p>While some Senators were not as genuine as others, virtually everyone who contributed today had a genuine concern about people who are in danger of losing their homes.  One can talk about lenders and borrowers, including mortgage holders, but we are discussing people's homes.  I cannot imagine a worse scenario than having to return to one's spouse and children and tell them that they have to leave the family home.  None of us can imagine that and I hope none of us will ever have to do it.  Many people have to leave their homes, however, and it is something the Government has to do more about.  </p><p>Senator Byrne said that judges do not have any alternative to granting repossessions, but they do.  Judges make these decisions every day of the week.  In a recent court case, a judge decided not to grant an order for repossession because the bank did not act honourably or in the manner it should have.  Judges, therefore, have incredible powers of discretion which are used daily.</p><p>Senator Mullen was anxious that every assistance should be given to those in debt to ensure that they are not put out of their homes willy-nilly.  The Bill deals with that matter clearly via a two-month adjournment period.  In the event that that is not enough to allow the insolvency programme to kick in, there is an opportunity for a further adjournment.  That is very important because, as Senator MacSharry said, this will be an issue for negotiation.  When the rules become clearer, such negotiations will be happening more and more. </p><p>I agree with Senators Crown and Barrett.  I do not believe that all bankers are bad and, by the same token, I do not believe that all politicians are bad either.  Having said that, however, we need to be extraordinarily careful that, given the circumstances we find ourselves in, we do not give exceptional powers to enable lenders to render people homeless.  </p><p>I concur with Senator Hayden whose contributions on housing are not just thoughtful and considered but also very knowledgeable.  The legislation is about what happens when the action for possession occurs.  We believe that the insolvency service will be up and running in a few weeks.  The Senator's points, which were well made, have already been thought out and discussed in terms of what action comes first.  </p><p>Senator Mullen referred to people being able to stay in their homes and rent them.  I am a great believer in cross-government co-operation, but the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government is proactively working on this issue.  The mortgage-to-rent scheme, to facilitate families to stay in their homes, is currently being worked on.  However, I will bring the Senator's views to the Minister's attention.</p><p>How could we disagree with what Senator Hayden said about people who are living in such circumstances?  Sometimes we imagine that buy-to-let properties comprise a separate little nest egg waiting for the market to rise again so that they can be sold, but these are people's homes.</p> <p>That is where they live and it is something on which we must take careful views.  Again, it will be about ensuring that people who live there will not simply be turfed out as a result of the banks repossessing those homes.  All of those points were well made.</p><p>In response to Senator Crown, we cannot sustain a legal system in which lenders&rsquo; rights to repossess are in doubt.  The Bill is clear.  Members have made grandiose speeches, some of ten pages long &ndash; I do not refer to Senator Crown &ndash; about the fact that we are so concerned about the possibility of people&rsquo;s homes being put on the line.  We must ensure that the legal system is robust and that when loopholes are identified they are addressed.  I like Senator Barrett&rsquo;s point that when the common man wins it is a loophole.  I will take that on board.  I assure Members that all of their points will be brought to the attention of the Minister and he will respond himself in a more fulsome manner.  I thank Members for their contributions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.186/1" nospeaker="true" time="18:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900036#LL00150"><p>Question put:</p><p>The Seanad divided: T, 30; Nl, 16.</p><p>Tellers: T, Senators Paul Coghlan and Aideen Hayden; Nl, Senators Ned O'Sullivan and Diarmuid Wilson..</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.186/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2013-07-09" time="18:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900036#LL00150">
            <divisioncount ayes="30" noes="16" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" vote="aye">Ivana Bacik</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1121" vote="aye">Paul Bradford</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" vote="aye">Terry Brennan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" vote="aye">Colm Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1114" vote="aye">Deirdre Clune</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" vote="aye">Eamonn Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" vote="aye">Paul Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1124" vote="aye">Michael Comiskey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" vote="aye">Maurice Cummins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" vote="aye">Jim D'Arcy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1160" vote="aye">Michael D'Arcy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" vote="aye">John Gilroy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1144" vote="aye">Jimmy Harte</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" vote="aye">Aideen Hayden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" vote="aye">Fidelma Healy Eames</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1152" vote="aye">Imelda Henry</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" vote="aye">Ca&iacute;t Keane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" vote="aye">John Kelly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1162" vote="aye">Denis Landy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" vote="aye">Marie Maloney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" vote="aye">Mary Moran</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1134" vote="aye">Tony Mulcahy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" vote="aye">R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" vote="aye">Michael Mullins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" vote="aye">Catherine Noone</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" vote="aye">Susan O'Keeffe</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" vote="aye">Pat O'Neill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1163" vote="aye">Tom Shehan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" vote="aye">Jillian van Turnhout</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1143" vote="aye">John Whelan</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" vote="no">Sean Barrett</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" vote="no">Thomas Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1147" vote="no">John Crown</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" vote="no">David Cullinane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" vote="no">Mark Daly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" vote="no">Terry Leyden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" vote="no">Marc MacSharry</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" vote="no">Paschal Mooney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" vote="no">Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" vote="no">Denis O'Donovan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1142" vote="no">Ned O'Sullivan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1154" vote="no">Averil Power</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1155" vote="no">Kathryn Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" vote="no">Jim Walsh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" vote="no">Mary White</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" vote="no">Diarmuid Wilson</mpname>
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.186/3" nospeaker="true" time="18:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900036#LL00150"><p>Question declared carried.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.187" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="18:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900037#MM00100"><p>When is it proposed to take Committee Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="18:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900037#MM00200"><p>Next Tuesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.189" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="18:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900037#MM00300"><p>Is that agreed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.190" nospeaker="true" time="18:35:00" ><p>Question, &quot;That Committee Stage be taken on Tuesday next&quot;, put and declared carried.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.191" nospeaker="true" time="18:35:00" ><p>Committee Stage ordered for Tuesday, 16 July 2013.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.192" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="18:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900037#MM00500"><p>When is it proposed to sit again?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.193" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="18:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900037#MM00600"><p>At 10.30 a.m. tomorrow.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.194" nospeaker="true" time="18:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900037#MM00800">Adjournment Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.195" nospeaker="true" time="18:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900037#MM00900">Court Accommodation Refurbishment</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.196" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1124" speakername="Michael Comiskey" time="18:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900037#MM01000"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Perry, to the Chamber.  The first matter is in the name of Senator Whelan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1143" speakername="John Whelan" time="18:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900037#MM01100"><p>I thank the Minister of State for taking this matter which pertains to the location and suitability of Portlaoise Courthouse.  It was built in 1782.  While I am all for historic buildings to be put to good use and good purpose, in terms of having a viable, modern courthouse, this building is well past its sell-by date.  Its location in the context of modern Ireland is absurd.  It is on the main street of Portlaoise, which would be tantamount to having a courthouse in the middle of Grafton Street in Dublin.  It is not fair on business or on the Courts Service and the people who work there.  The Prison Service has a serious problem with it in terms of security, parking and safety, as do the Garda authorities.  All the stakeholders would like to see the courthouse relocated and reappointed to a purpose-built building that would be more appropriate to its use.</p><p>Another factor is that the courthouse used to be the companion building to the former Marlborough jail which was closed in 1830.  The courthouse was in that kind of use dating back to that time.  In 1982, a colleague of the Minister of State, Councillor Tom Keenan of Fine Gael, had the foresight to relocate the civic offices, the Laois County Council offices, from the courthouse building to a new modern purpose built complex in county hall.  The relocation of Portlaoise courthouse is long overdue, bearing in mind that it no longer only runs the business of court in Portlaoise due to rationalisation of the Courts Service.</p> <p>I am opposed not to the rationalisation of the Courts Service but to the closure of small rural courthouses such as those in Birr and Edenderry.  As a journalist, I covered proceedings in the courthouses in Abbeyleix, Mountmellick, Portarlington and Rathdowney.  All of these courthouses have since been amalgamated and centralised in Portlaoise which also houses the Circuit Court.  Because of its close location to two high security prisons, there are often high profile cases in Portlaoise courthouse.  When this happens, the entire main street is blocked with Garda and prison vehicles and people attending the courts by whom senior citizens and other people going about their business often feel intimidated.  The situation is no longer tenable.  I urge the Minister of State, Deputy Perry, to impression upon the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Shatter, the need for investment by the Courts Service in a modern courthouse in Portlaoise, in a building which is fit for purpose and not located on the Main Street of the town.  The current situation is absurd. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.199" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1081" speakername="John Perry" time="18:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900038#NN00200"><p>On behalf of the Minister for Justice and Equality, I thank the Senator for raising the matter.   I appreciate his interest in Portlaoise courthouse and the issues relating to its existing location on the Main Street in Portlaoise.</p><p>As the Senator will appreciate, under the provisions of the Courts Service Act 1998, management of the courts is the responsibility of the Courts Service and the Minister has no role in the matter.  Section 4(3) of the 1998 Act provides that the Courts Service is independent in the performance of its functions which, of course, include the provision, maintenance and management of court buildings.  However, the Minister has had inquiries made and the Courts Service has advised that Portlaoise courthouse is a neoclassical building constructed around 1805 on a corner site.  The courthouse is owned by Laois County Council and was last refurbished by the Courts Service in 2001 at a cost of &euro;2.75 million. </p><p>More recently, in 2010, some minor works were also carried out.  In relation to proposed works, the service has stated that some work is also planned for the provision of cell facilities within the courthouse.  The service has stated that it is aware that the facilities in Portlaoise courthouse fall short of what is required to meet the demands placed on the courthouse but that there is limited scope for development within the existing courthouse building and site.  In 2007, the service in co-operation with the OPW, began a search for an appropriate alternative site in the town for a new courthouse development.  A number of potential sites were considered during 2007 and 2008.  However, no site was acquired at that time.</p><p>Since 2008, the service, in common with all other public service organisations, has been operating in a very difficult and challenging economic environment.  While continuing its search for a new site for a courthouse, the service has indicated that it currently has limited funding available for site acquisition and development.  In the absence of a suitable site, the service has informed the Minister that it is not possible to bring forward specific proposals for the replacement of Portlaoise courthouse at this time and that a new courthouse cannot be delivered in the short to medium term.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.200" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1143" speakername="John Whelan" time="18:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900038#NN00300"><p>I appreciate the frankness and directness of the response.  It is, however, bad news as far as I am concerned.  I believe refurbishment of Portlaoise courthouse, which is hundreds of years old, was a waste of money and a case of throwing good money after bad.  It suggests to me that the problem is being long-fingered and will not be addressed in the short term.  I am further concerned to hear that cell facilities are to be provided at the courthouse.  While this may resolve some of the security issues it will not resolve the core issue of the relocation of the courthouse.  If the Courts Service needs assistance in securing and sourcing a suitable site I am sure many of the local businesses would be willing to assist it in that regard.  While I realise that resources are limited, this issue will have to be revisited as a matter of priority.  The holding of a court sitting almost every day of the week at the courthouse on Main Street cannot be allowed to continue.</p><p>It mesmerizes me in the extreme that the previous Government spent &euro;30 million on a site for the proposed Thornton Hall prison, which will never be built.  A number of sites in respect of the relocation of Portlaoise courthouse could have been purchased with that money, which was taxpayers' money that has been squandered.  I ask that the Minister of State, Deputy Perry, impress upon the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Shatter, my ongoing concern in this relation to this matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.201" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1081" speakername="John Perry" time="18:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900038#NN00400"><p>The Government is conscious of the value of providing for an excellent court system and has continued to provide substantial resources to the service, with a supplementary estimate of &euro;5 million provided last year on top of the original net budget of &euro;54.1 million.  However, the Senator will appreciate that no area is exempt from the financial constraints of the past few years.</p><p>In relation to some court locations, the board has had to take the unpalatable decision of closing a number of small, non-viable venues and has had to introduce more efficient work processes to allow the service to continue to provide front-line services within the reduced staffing levels that are essential nowadays.  The service has stated that it will keep the issue of Portlaoise courthouse under review.  Given the Senator has had meaningful dialogue on the issue with the Courts Service I am sure it is conscious of the needs in this regard.  </p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.202" nospeaker="true" time="18:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900038#NN00500">Data Protection</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.203" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" speakername="Jillian van Turnhout" time="18:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900038#NN00600"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House.</p><p>  I am aware that an informal meeting of Ministers for Justice and Home Affairs will be taking place at the end of next week in Vilnius and understand that the general data protection regulation is the agenda of that meeting.</p><p>  I have been contacted by a number of people in the genealogical community who are concerned that the European Commission plans to unify data protection within the European Union with a single law, the general data protection regulation, which may have unintended consequences.  I have specifically been contacted by Michael Merrigan, general secretary of the Genealogical Society of Ireland who, in turn, has been contacted by the Genealogical Society of Finland.  I thank them for the information with which they have provided me.</p><p>  I have a keen interest in researching my family history and have first-hand experience of accessing resources through my research.  I realise the sensitivity of some data and so understand that we need to protect privacy.  We have all welcomed the renewed focus on genealogy due to events surrounding The Gathering.  In addition, the Government has proactively engaged in the provision of online access to genealogical resources through the national repositories and its genealogy web portal <i> .  </i>I am also aware of the sheer dedication and work by genealogists such as Stuart Rosenblatt who has provided the State with an invaluable 16 volume archive spanning more than four centuries.  He is a guiding example to us all.</p><p>  The recent report published by the Joint Committee on Finance, Public Expenditure and Reform with regard to its hearings in relation to the draft general scheme of the Freedom of Information Bill highlighted the need to seek the inclusion in the proposed legislation of the following as a guiding principle by which record holders, the State and State agencies, would give public access to records with a genealogical potential by the inclusion of a section that states that the legislation endorses and fully supports the principle of public ownership and right of access to our genealogical heritage.  Doing it in this way will allow statutory instruments and departmental guidelines to take cognisance of the principle when assessing public accessibility to records with a genealogical potential. </p><p>  I am cognisant that an EU regulation must be observed by all member states.  The impact of the inclusion of civil registration records in the scope of the data protection directive, if that is what is proposed, would have a very detrimental impact on genealogical, biographical and historical research.  While such a measure would have no impact on existing public access to genealogical resources held by the National Library and the National Archives, it could create an atmosphere of fear of litigation on the part of custodians of records of genealogical potential.  </p><p>  Can the Minister ensure that the revised EU data protection directive-regulation does not impair the right of the citizen to engage in bona fide genealogical, biographical or historical research and that the principle of public ownership and right of access to our genealogical heritage will be enshrined as a guiding principle?  I believe genealogy should be expressly mentioned in the regulation and hope that the Minister of State can give us assurances today.</p><p>  On a specific point, Article 6, paragraph 2, of the regulation should be rewritten so that it makes an exception from the general principle for processing of personal data, namely, the data subject has given consent to the processing.  As a result, it would not be necessary to request consent to processing of personal data when the purpose is historical research or genealogy.</p> <p>I hope we can obtain assurances from the Minister of State that the access to genealogical, biographical or historical records will not be impaired and that we will be able to ensure public access for generations to come.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.205" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1081" speakername="John Perry" time="18:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900039#OO00200"><p>I am here on behalf of my colleague, the Minister for Justice and Equality, who is unable to be present.  I thank Senator van Turnhout for raising this important subject.</p><p>In the first instance, I will briefly set out the background to the European Commission's proposals for reform of data protection law.  The centrepiece of existing EU legislation on personal data protection is Directive 95/46/EC which seeks to reconcile the protection of personal data with the free flow of such data within the Internal Market and to countries outside the EU.  It is widely recognised that the 1995 directive needs to be updated to take account of more recent developments such as increased use of the Internet, blogs and social networking sites and increasing globalisation of data transfers.  In 2010, the Lisbon treaty introduced a new legal basis for strengthened data protection standards in the European Union, and Article 8 of the Charter of Fundamental Rights of the EU enshrines protection of personal data as a fundamental right.</p><p>In January 2012, following completion of an extensive consultation process, the European Commission tabled proposals for a radical shake-up of the current regulatory framework.  These proposals are being discussed separately by the Council of the European Union and the European Parliament at present.  Adoption of the reform package is subject to co-decision between both institutions.  Article 5 of the Commission proposal for a general data protection regulation, which sets out the principles relating to personal data processing, recognises that it may be necessary to retain personal data for historical, statistical or scientific purposes.  Article 83 sets out specific provisions for the processing of personal data for historic, statistical and scientific research purposes.  While the Minister has until now not been made aware of the specific concerns of the genealogical sector, he is aware that concerns have been raised that the provisions in the Commission proposal are not sufficient to accommodate the processing of personal data for historical, statistical, scientific or archival purposes.  The Minister shares these concerns.</p><p>As the Senator may be aware, achieving progress on the European Commission's proposals to update the Union's data protection standards was a priority of the Irish Presidency and I am pleased to say that substantial progress was achieved on key aspects of the reform package.  In June, the Minister submitted a progress report to the Justice and Home Affairs Council, which identified key aspects of Chapters I to IV of the draft regulation.  In addition, a draft revised text of Chapters I to IV, which reflects the view of the Minister, as the then President of the Justice and Home Affairs Council, of the state of play of negotiations at that stage, has been prepared. The Minister has arranged to have these documents laid before the Houses for the information of Deputies and Senators.  The draft revised text includes a number of proposals, which have yet to be discussed in detail at expert level, to address concerns in respect of the implications of the draft regulation for the processing of personal data for historical, statistical or scientific purposes.  I understand it is intended to discuss this issue at expert level shortly.  The detailed discussions relating to these proposals will provide an opportunity to consider whether proposals to deal with the processing of personal data for historical, statistical or scientific research purposes are sufficient to cover archival purposes as well as bona fide genealogical and biographical research or whether specific provisions in this regard will be necessary.</p><p>The Minister believes that the concerns relating to the implications of the draft regulation for historical, statistical, scientific or archival purposes, including for bona fide genealogical and biographical purposes, must be examined further at expert level by the Council working party on data protection and exchange of information, DAPIX, and addressed, where necessary, by means of appropriate amendments to the regulation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.206" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" speakername="Jillian van Turnhout" time="18:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900039#OO00300"><p>I would appreciate it if copies of the Minister of State's script could be made available.  Traditionally, such scripts are provided to Members.  It would be useful if we were able to examine its contents.</p><p>I thank the Minister of State for the assurances he provided.  I reiterate the importance of including a specific reference to genealogy to ensure there will be public access to these records when such access is for bona fide purposes.  I will correspond with the Minister for Justice and Equality on this issue because it is important that it be viewed in conjunction with the general data protection regulation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.207" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1081" speakername="John Perry" time="18:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900039#OO00400"><p>I will be happy to supply the Senator with a copy of my script.  The European Commission tabled proposals for a radical shake-up of the existing data protection framework.  Those proposals undoubtedly comprise one of the most important reform packages being discussed at EU level at present.  Data protection affects all of us, whether in a private capacity as individuals, in a business or professional capacity or as users of personal data.  It is for this reason that the Minister for Justice and Equality launched a public consultation process in March 2012 to seek the view and inputs of interested bodies and individuals in order to inform the negotiations on the proposal.  The Minister continues to welcome such views and inputs on the implications of the draft regulation, particularly as discussions on this detailed and complex proposal are ongoing at European level.  He would welcome the views and inputs of the Senator and others on the specific concerns which may exist in respect of the implications of the draft regulation for bona fide genealogical, biographical or historical research.</p><p>As stated, the protection of personal data is a fundamental right.  However, the right to this protection coexists with other rights and this is recognised in the draft regulation.  For example, Article 83 of the draft regulation sets out specific provisions for the processing of personal data for historic, statistical and scientific research purposes.  The Minister is of the view that the draft regulation must be examined further to assess the implications of the proposals relating to the processing of personal data for historical, statistical, scientific or archival purposes.  He would, therefore, welcome any specific amendments to the draft regulation which are considered necessary to accommodate bona fide genealogical, biographical or historical research or which take account of the need to provide high levels of data protection to individuals.</p><p>On behalf of the Minister, I again thank Senator van Turnhout for raising this important issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.208" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" speakername="Jillian van Turnhout" time="18:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900039#OO00500"><p>I thank the Minister of State and I will communicate the information he has provided to the Genealogical Society of Ireland and the wider genealogical community.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.209" nospeaker="true" time="18:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900039#OO00550">VAT Rates Application</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.210" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1162" speakername="Denis Landy" time="18:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900039#OO00600"><p>I welcome the Minister of State.  I also welcome Councillor Brian Collins from Kells who is in the Visitors Gallery and who is one of the driving forces behind the campaign for VAT reform.</p><p>As a businessman, the Minister of State is very familiar with the various VAT rates which obtain here in respect of goods and services.  There is a need for a comprehensive review of the VAT regime.  Such a review has not been carried out and what has happened is that the various rates of VAT have evolved over time.  Some of these rates have been in existence since prior to our entry to the EU and some have arisen as a result of the emergence of new goods and services.  This matter was not discussed by previous Governments, nor has it been discussed to any great extent by the current Administration.  The only change introduced in recent times was the reduction in the rate of VAT which relates to tourism.  It has been proven that this reduction has been of major assistance to the tourism industry.  Those in the tourism sector lobbied strongly for the reduction and they have proved that what they requested has borne fruit.  In the first six months of the year, the number of tourists coming here was up almost 20%.  Some of this increase was due to The Gathering but a great deal of it reflects the value for money available in Ireland at present.</p><p>I wish to provide a number of examples of the ludicrous situation which obtains in respect of VAT at present.  The rate of VAT on fruit juice is 23%, while that relating to frozen pizzas is 0%.  The rate on walking sticks is 23%, while that relating to limousine hire is 0%.  The Minister of State can clearly see that there is no connection between the services people need and the system of VAT currently in place.  If we carry out a review of and reform our VAT regime, this would give rise to great job creation opportunities.  I alluded to tourism and it is important to note that the number of jobs and the packages on offer from hotels, restaurants and others in the sector have both increased.</p><p>The rate of VAT on wool is 23%, whereas the rate which applies in respect of purchases of gold for investment purposes is 0%.</p> <p>If one wishes to buy gold for investment, it is VAT-rated at 0% while something we all have to use, toilet roll, is rated at 23%.  A tax manual is rated at 0%.  I could go on with other examples, but given the weather we have at the moment, I will focus on that.  Sun cream, sun hats, bottled water and ice are rated at 23%.  One could imagine that we would almost prefer if the sun did not shine in this country since we have to pay 23% to protect us from the sun's rays.</p><p>The VAT rate in the tourism section which is in place at the moment is only temporary and must be reviewed.  In that light I call for all rates of VAT to be reviewed before the next budget and for a reduction on the VAT rate on aids for the elderly, for example, which is currently at 23%, to the minimum rate of 4.8%.</p><p>On a lighter note - I cannot give it as the reason Tipperary were beaten last Saturday night by Kilkenny - surely VAT-rating a hurley at 23% does not help the hard-pressed tax hurlers in Tipperary.  With that, I hope the Minister of State will have some good news about a review.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.212" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1081" speakername="John Perry" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900040#PP00200"><p>I am taking the debate on behalf of the Minister for Finance, Deputy Michael Noonan, who conveys his apologies to the Senator for not being here to reply.  I am pleased to have the opportunity to contribute to today's debate and to respond to Senator Landy's motion concerning the equity of Ireland's VAT rates.</p><p>The VAT rating of goods and services is subject to the requirements of European Union VAT law, with which Irish VAT law must comply.  The EU VAT directive provides that each EU member state must apply a standard VAT rate to the majority of goods and services.  The standard VAT rate must be set at a rate not lower than 15% and there is political agreement that it does not exceed 25%, although it is possible to set the rate higher.  Hungary has introduced a standard rate of 27% in recent years.  In addition, member states may apply up to two reduced VAT rates of between 5% and 15% for a range of goods or services which are set out in annex III of the VAT directive.  Member states also have the option of maintaining, at a reduced rate of not less than 12%, any items not listed in annex III, provided they applied a reduced rate to those items on 1 January 1991.  This is known as the parked rate.  Member states may also continue to apply the zero rate, or a rate lower than 5%, known as a super-reduced rate, to goods and services provided they applied at a zero rate or a super-reduced rate to those items on 1 January 1991.  However, it is not possible to introduce a zero rate or a super-reduced rate on any new items.  That point must be made.</p><p>In the context of the rules at EU level regarding VAT, the structure and scope of Ireland's VAT rates are as follows.  The standard VAT rate in Ireland is 23% and applies to such goods as cars, petrol, diesel, alcohol, tobacco, electrical equipment, CDs and DVDs.  Ireland applies two reduced VAT rates of 9% and 13.5%.  The 13.5% rate applies mainly to residential housing, labour-intensive services and general repairs and maintenance.  In addition, the 13.5% parked rate applies to fuel used for heat or light and commercial construction.  The 9% reduced rate applies mainly to tourism services including hotel and holiday accommodation, restaurant services and various entertainment services.  The rate was introduced as part of the jobs initiative and applies from 1 July 2011 until end December 2013.  Those services at the 13.5% rate that had been parked were prohibited under the EU VAT directive from availing of the 9% rate.  The zero rate applies to most food, children's clothes and shoes and oral medicines.  Ireland also applies a super-reduced VAT rate of 4.8% but this is limited to livestock sold by VAT registered persons.  In addition, services provided by non-profit organisations, transport operators, medical professionals, undertakers and certain financial services are exempt from VAT, as are schools and hospitals, etc.  Exempt suppliers do not generally charge VAT on the services they provide and cannot reclaim VAT incurred on the goods and services they purchase.</p><p>As of 1 July 2013, a total of 23 of the 28 EU member states have a standard VAT rate of 20% or higher.  The average standard rate in the EU is 21.5%.  Six member states have a higher standard VAT rate than Ireland, namely, Hungary at 27%, Denmark, Sweden and Croatia at 25% and Finland and Romania at 24%.  This means Ireland has the joint seventh highest standard VAT rate, along with Portugal, Greece and Poland, at 23%.  A further 13 member states have a rate of between 20% to 22%.</p><p>The trend among EU member states has been to increase VAT rates as a means of covering the budgetary shortfall generated by the economic downturn.  A total of 23 of the 27 member states, not including the recently acceded Croatia, have increased their VAT rates since 2008, with 18 member states making an increase in their standard rate alone.  Of the member states that have not increased their VAT rates during this period, two already have in place the maximum standard rate of 25%.</p><p>VAT increases continue to be considered.  In October 2013, Italy is due to increase its standard VAT rate to 22%.  In January 2014, France will increase its standard VAT rate to 20% and its reduced rate from 7% to 10% and Cyprus will increase its standard rate to 19%.  In addition, Luxembourg, which has the lowest standard VAT rate in the EU, also plans to increase its standard rate in 2015.  At 13.5%, Ireland has the fourth highest reduced VAT rate in Europe after Hungary, at 18%, the Czech Republic, at 15%, and Finland, at 14%.  However, we apply reduced rates to an extensive range of goods and services relative to other member states.  In addition, Ireland, along with the United Kingdom, is unique among member states in applying a zero rate of VAT to a sizeable proportion of economic activity.  In contrast, for example, Denmark applies a rate of 25% to all taxable activity, as it does not have any other VAT rates in operation.</p><p>There is equity in the application of Ireland's VAT rates.  While the system of VAT rating in Ireland is often historic, the application of Ireland's VAT rates is none the less very equitable.  In applying the zero VAT rate to basic foods, medicines and children's clothes and the 13.5% reduced rate to domestic fuels, the burden of VAT is reduced on basic commodities and utility services, which results in a lower tax burden on the less well off.  The application of the 13.5% reduced rate to construction and labour intensive services and general repairs as well as the maintenance and the application of the 9% reduced rate to tourism services encourages employment through the reduced VAT burden on service related businesses.  The VAT system encourages good health by applying the 23% standard VAT rate to alcohol, tobacco and sugary foods.  The environmental benefits of applying the standard rate to cars, petrol and diesel are also evident.  I point to the equity of Ireland's VAT rates.  It is also made apparent in the context of the scope of VAT rates in other EU member states.  Ireland applies reduced and zero rates of VAT to a much higher proportion of goods and services than any other member state.  Ireland is one of a small number of member states which apply the zero rate to basic foods and medicine.  Ireland is also among a small number of member states which apply a reduced rate of VAT on domestic fuels.</p><p>I wish to draw the attention of the House to the fact that Ireland's VAT rates, their scope and their structure, are revised on an annual basis in the context of the annual budget.  Such reviews takes into consideration the equity of VAT rates, along with the EU legislative constraints and the Exchequer and economic impact of any potential changes.  Accordingly, the scope of the VAT rates will be reviewed in advance of the upcoming budget in this context.  That is a comprehensive reply in a complex area.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.213" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1162" speakername="Denis Landy" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900040#PP00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State for what was, as he said himself, a comprehensive review of the VAT situation in Ireland.  I accept that we have made great strides in this area and we are ahead of many other EU countries.  I have highlighted some particular items.  A fisherman needs lobster pots to go fishing for lobster and he must pay 23% VAT on the lobster pot.  However, when a customer buys lobster over the counter he pays 0% VAT.  There are some areas we can improve.  I welcome the fact that there will be a full review.  It is timely that I brought forward this Adjournment topic because we have made great strides in tourism by reducing the rate.  We could demonstrate more equity and fairness, especially to vulnerable people in society.  For example, I have outlined that the rate for aids for the elderly, currently at 23%, should be reduced to the minimum rate.</p> <p>I hope we can look at all those areas in the review before the budget 2014.  I thank the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.215" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1081" speakername="John Perry" time="19:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013070900041#QQ00200"><p>As regards the 9% VAT rate, it is important to note that every reduction costs a considerable amount of money.  As to the numbers employed in the tourism sector, research was carried out by the Department and published in the medium term fiscal statement in November 2012.  This report entitled Measuring the Impact of the Jobs Initiative examined where the VAT reduction had been passed on and where jobs were created.  It contains detailed information on the impact of the 9% VAT rate on prices and employment numbers.  The report is available on the website.</p><p>Using the statistics from the CSO, the report indicates that an additional 6,200 jobs have been created in the accommodation and food sectors for Q2 2011, and there was an increase of 6% in Q2 2012.  While other factors impact on employment rates in these sectors, I have no doubt the 9% VAT rate has contributed in no small way to those employment gains.  Furthermore, these figures underline the positive impact of the 9% VAT rate as comparable sectors experienced a decline in employment numbers over the period concerned.  This indicates that employment in the accommodation and food sectors may also have declined without the introduction of the 9% rate.</p><p>With regard to prices in the tourism sector, the response to the 9% VAT rate has been positive.  The report indicates that the VAT reduction was for the most part passed on to consumers. While tourism numbers fluctuated over the period since the introduction of the 9% rate in July, expenditure by overseas travellers in Ireland in 2012 increased by &euro;37 million over 2011.  This excludes transport and air travel costs which are exempt from the VAT rate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-07-09a.216" nospeaker="true" time="19:10:00" ><p>The Seanad adjourned at 6.45 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Wednesday, 10 July 2013.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>