<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.1" nospeaker="true" time="12:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.2" nospeaker="true" time="12:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 12:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.3" nospeaker="true" time="12:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.4" nospeaker="true" time="12:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.5" nospeaker="true" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Maria Byrne that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, she proposes to raise the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Justice and Equality to provide additional Garda resources in east Limerick.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Justice and Equality to provide an update on Garda resources for Beaumont in north Dublin and the measures being taken to address the escalation in anti-social behaviour in the area.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Jennifer Murnane O'Connor of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government to outline when the threshold cap for the housing list in County Carlow will be increased.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government to outline the timeline to facilitate the planned referendum on presidential voting rights in May 2019.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator P&aacute;draig Mac Lochlainn of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government to provide an update on the mica redress scheme for affected homeowners in County Donegal.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Colm Burke of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Education and Skills to arrange for an inspection of St. Patrick's girls' national school, Gardiner's Hill, Cork, to enable the immediate carrying out of remedial works.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Rose Conway-Walsh of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Culture, Heritage and the Gaeltacht to consider the need for the provision of a helicopter pad on Inishturk Island, County Mayo. </blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Michelle Mulherin of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government to outline the reason for delays by An Bord Plean&aacute;la in making planning decisions, particularly regarding environmentally designated lands.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice form Senator Victor Boyhan of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government to make a statement on the local government County and City Management Association, CCMA, shared service programme; the number of shared service projects currently in operation; and plans to expand shared services and synergies across the local government sector.</blockquote><p>Of the matters raised by the Senators that are suitable for discussion, I have selected Senators &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in, Byrne, Murnane O'Connor and &Oacute; Donnghaile and they will be taken now.  I regret I have to rule out of order the matter submitted by Senator Boyhan on the ground that the Minister has no official responsibility in the matter.  The other Senators may give notice on another day of the matters that they wish to raise.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.8" nospeaker="true" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800003#B00200">Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.9" nospeaker="true" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800003#B00300">Garda Deployment</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800003#B00400"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Stanton.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800003#B00500"><p>I thank the Minister of State for taking this debate on anti-social behaviour in the Beaumont area.  I am always reluctant to discuss matters of anti-social behaviour in a public forum because it does not necessarily lead to a good outcome and can stigmatise an area if not done sensitively, but the issues at hand have got to such a degree that I feel my hand has been forced.</p>  <p>There is an estate called Collinswood, and in that estate is a laneway that leads to the main Beaumont Road.  In that laneway, a number of incidents have happened, including multiple muggings, and there is a general sense of danger and intimidation.  A number of individuals have been intimidated in the wider estate and a gang seems to be going around the place causing havoc.</p>  <p>After a public meeting that I organised, a number of other people from around the area have contacted me.  One told me that her son had been the subject of a 45-minute mugging in August.  There was the well-publicised case of a 13 year old boy who was assaulted and had his bike taken from him just outside Beaumont Hospital.  Another individual contacted me to say that his wife, when intervening alongside their daughter in a mugging in the same area, had her shoulder broken.</p>  <p>There seems to have been an escalation in anti-social behaviour in and around the Beaumont area in recent months.  I have met senior Garda management, which is familiar with the issues and is trying in whatever way it can to respond to them.  I have no issue with the response or determination of the Garda to sort out the problem, but the question inevitably comes back to the resources the Garda in that area has, be it at Raheny Garda station, Clontarf Garda station or Santry Garda station.  A point raised by a resident is that Santry Garda station closes at 7.30 p.m.  A large amount of Government time, energy and resources have been put into the reopening of Stepaside Garda station.  I do not know what kind of criminality or anti-social behaviour is happening in Stepaside to warrant that amount of resources and political attention, but the area I am discussing, which I live near and which I am trying to represent to the best of my ability, is in need of special attention to root out this problem and ensure that people can live quiet lives without a sense of intimidation hanging over them and the area in which they live.  It is a proud and good area with decent people who are just trying to live their lives.</p>  <p>If it were not for the seriousness of the issues and the fact that they are being raised time and again, I would not necessarily be standing here and talking about them, as I am often reluctant to go public with an issue and name a particular district.  I want the Minister of State to respond positively to what I am outlining and commit to providing more resources so that garda&iacute; can patrol the area better and give a sense of security to people living locally, allowing them to go about their daily business without the threat of intimidation or assault hanging over them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1277" speakername="David Stanton" time="12:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800004#C00100"><p>On behalf of the Minister, Deputy Flanagan, who sends his apologies for not being here, I thank the Senator for raising this matter.  As he will appreciate, the allocation of Garda resources, including personnel, is a matter for the Garda Commissioner and his management team.  The Minister has no direct role in this matter.</p>  <p>The Minister is informed by the Garda Commissioner that in regard to the deployment of Garda personnel a distribution model is used which takes into account all relevant factors, including population, crime trends and the policing needs of individual Garda divisions, including the DMR north division, with a view to providing an effective and responsive police service.  This may include directing resources at areas designated as hot spots for anti-social behaviour.  The area referenced by the Senator forms part of the DMR north division and the Minister is informed by the Garda Commissioner that the Garda strength in this division as of 31 October 2018, the latest date for which figures are readily available, was 698.  There are also 40 Garda reserves and 48 civilians attached to the division.  In addition, where appropriate, the work of local garda&iacute; is supported by a number of national Garda units, such as the National Bureau of Criminal Investigation, the armed support units, the Garda National Economic Crime Bureau and the Garda National Drugs and Organised Crime Bureau.  Working with communities to tackle public disorder and reduce anti-social behaviour remains the key priority for An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  This approach includes a strong focus on quality of life issues and collaboration with local authorities to help address the causes of anti-social behaviour.</p>  <p>The Minister emphasises that joint policing committees have an important role in facilitating consultation, co-operation and synergy on policing and crime issues between An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, local authorities and elected public representatives.  The active and constructive engagement by elected representatives on the committees is very important.  Garda visibility is also important in tackling anti-social behaviour in our communities and this Government remains committed to ensuring a strong and visible police presence throughout the country to maintain and strengthen community engagement, to provide reassurance to citizens and to deter crime.  Since the reopening of the Garda college in September 2014, just under 2,400 recruits have attested and been assigned to mainstream duties nationwide, including 78 to the DMR north division.  Taking account of projected retirements, Garda numbers will reach approximately 14,000 by the end of this year.  This focus and investment in personnel is critical.  The moratorium on recruitment introduced in 2010 resulted in a significant reduction in the strength of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and the organisation is now being rebuilt.  The Minister is providing the Garda Commissioner with the resources to deploy increasing numbers of Garda to every Garda division, including the DMR north division, to increase Garda visibility and to protect our communities from the type of anti-social behaviour referred to by the Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="12:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800004#C00200"><p>Unfortunately, I am not overly impressed with the Minister of State's response.  An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na says it needs more resources and that this requires political decision but when one raises the issue with political masters they say it is an issue for the Garda Commissioner.  The assistant Garda commissioner said that Stepaside Garda station was not a priority yet the Government is proceeding to reopen it.</p>  <p>I ask the Minister of State, Deputy Stanton, to impress on the Minister, Deputy Flanagan, the seriousness of what is happening in this area in terms of the number of muggings and assaults on young people, leaving them traumatised.  I recently sat in the kitchen of the home of one young man traumatised by the ordeal he had to endure, which was a 45 minute assault.  It is appalling that the Minister of State's response is that it is a matter for the Garda Commissioner to decide where policing resources are allocated.  I suggest that greater emphasis needs to be put on policing in the north Dublin area, with less obsession on the reopening of Stepaside Garda station.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1277" speakername="David Stanton" time="12:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800004#C00300"><p>Regarding the division, it is a matter for the chief superintendent of the division to determine the optimum distribution of duties among the personnel available to him or her having regard to the profile of the area and specific needs.  Community policing is at the heart of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and it has a proud record of engagement with communities to address their concerns and successfully tackle the type of anti-social behaviour referred to by the Senator.  There are a range of strong legislative provisions available to An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na to combat anti-social behaviour, including provisions under the current Criminal Justice (Public Order) Acts, the Criminal Damage Act and the Intoxicating Liquor Acts.  There are also the incremental provisions contained in the Criminal Justice Act 2006 which provide for warnings and civil proceedings in regard to anti-social behaviour by adults.  Part 13 of the Act provides for warnings, good behaviour contracts and civil proceedings in relation to anti-social behaviour by children.</p>  <p>Over the last few years, unprecedented resources have been made available to the Garda Commissioner, which provide him with the resources to increase Garda visibility in our communities and to support all Garda activity, including tackling anti-social behaviour.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="12:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800004#C00400"><p>I understand Senator Byrne is caught in traffic so we will move on to the third Commencement matter.  It will be up to the Minister of State, Deputy Stanton, if he wants to address Senator Byrne's matter should she arrive before we conclude this business.</p> <p>We will move on.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.17" nospeaker="true" time="12:50:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800005#D00200">Social and Affordable Housing Eligibility</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="12:50:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800005#D00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State for being here, although I am disappointed that neither the Minister nor the Minister of State at the Department of Housing, Planning and Local Government could be here to address this issue.  While I understand and respect the fact that all Government Ministers and Ministers of State are busy, the situation with regard to housing is at crisis point and deserves a response from the responsible Minister or Minister of State.  That said, I thank the Minister of State at the Department of Justice and Equality for taking this Commencement matter today.</p>  <p>I wish to discuss whether there will be a change to the income threshold for qualification for a place on the housing list in Carlow.  This is a very serious issue locally because genuine people who should qualify for social housing are being excluded at present.  A family came to me recently seeking my help.  They were earning between &euro;350 and &euro;400 per week and were in receipt of family income supplement, FIS.  When people qualify for FIS, it means that they are not earning enough and need assistance in meeting their household needs.  Despite this, the family was told that they did not qualify for registration on the housing list in Carlow.  It is unacceptable that people who are working, trying to make ends meet and who qualify for FIS do not qualify for inclusion on the housing list.  </p>  <p>I have consistently raised this issue and have been told that it is being examined.  There are people in Carlow and in other counties in the low cap zone who are in limbo because they do not qualify for social housing under the current social housing income thresholds but they do not earn enough to be able to afford a mortgage.  They need answers.  They are not being included in the social housing waiting lists or on the emergency lists.  Those lists are incomplete because these people are crying out for help but are not receiving it.</p>  <p>The most recent summary assessment of social housing needs published in September shows that the number of households in Carlow qualifying for social housing support from the local authority was just 499 which is not a true reflection of the situation on the ground, as evidenced by the number of people coming to my clinics.  Seven years have passed since the last review.  The social housing assessment regulation in 2011 set the maximum net income limits for each local authority in different bands, according to the area, with incomes being defined and assessed according to a standard household means policy.  I understand that a new assessment was due to be done in the summer.  There is now an urgent need to finalise this and to increase the income limits for social housing in Carlow and several other counties.  There are no millionaires out there looking for help.  These are real families who are working hard but are not getting a break.  We need to give them a break.  </p>  <p>Carlow currently has one of the lowest income thresholds in the entire country.  The maximum net income threshold for a single person is &euro;25,000, for a childless couple it is &euro;26,250 and for one adult and one child it is &euro;25,625.  The threshold for two adults with one child it is &euro;26,875, while for two adults with more than one child it is &euro;27,500.  This compares to a limit of &euro;38,000 in Kildare for two adults with one child and &euro;39,000 for two adults with more than one child.  Not only is it unrealistic to have such a marked difference between two counties, the limits themselves are far too low for working adults.  These limits provide an incentive to decline opportunities to increase household income.  The aim of social welfare is to help people to get on their feet, not to force them onto their knees in order qualify for assistance.  There is a difference of almost &euro;11,000 in the income threshold between Kildare and Carlow, while the difference between Carlow and Kilkenny is &euro;6,500.  This is inexcusable and is putting enormous pressure on families in Carlow.  The Government is well aware that unless a person is on the local authority housing list, he or she will not qualify for rent allowance or for the housing assistance payment, HAP.  It is extraordinary that in the midst of a housing crisis, the Government is denying families who are under intense financial pressure access to the rent allowance and the HAP schemes.  This Government must ensure that the income threshold in Carlow is increased and is brought in line with the thresholds in neighbouring counties.  It must also allow families to earn a second income or to avail of promotion or overtime opportunities in order to better their living standards.  We are condemning people by not allowing them to go onto our social housing waiting lists.  We are not giving them a chance.  What action is being taken by the Department and when will the review of social housing income thresholds be completed?  We really need to help these people.</p> <p>These are the working poor.  They qualify for nothing but pay out for everything.  We want to help everybody.  This is about everybody who needs to be on the housing list but is not able to get onto it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1277" speakername="David Stanton" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800006#E00200"><p>I thank the Senator for tabling this Commencement matter.  The Minister, Deputy Eoghan Murphy, is unfortunately not available and has asked me to send his apologies personally.  I will make him aware of the debate and of what the Senator has said.</p>  <p>On 1 April 2011 the social housing assessment regulations introduced a new standard procedure for assessing applicants for social housing in every housing authority.  This included the introduction of maximum net income limits for each housing authority in different bands according to the area, with income being defined and assessed according to the standard household means policy.  Before the new system was introduced there was considerable inconsistency in the approaches taken across local authorities.  Some authorities had income limits for social housing and some had none.  How income was assessed against limits also varied widely, with different arrangements in place in various housing authorities.  The income bands and the authority area assigned to each band, which were introduced in 2011, were based on an assessment of income needed to provide for a household&rsquo;s basic need, plus a comparative analysis of the local rental cost of housing accommodation across the country.</p>  <p>The limits also reflect a blanket increase of &euro;5,000 introduced prior to the new system coming into operation in order to broaden the base from which social housing tenants are drawn and thereby promote sustainable communities.  This increase has largely had the welcome side effect of future-proofing the income bands so that they still very much cater for those who find that they must spend a very high proportion of their income on rent in order to afford to pay for their housing needs from their own resources.  The maximum bands apply to single adult households and can be adjusted by housing authorities to take account of additional household members.  These allowances are 5% for each additional adult household member, up to a maximum of 10%, that is, two additional adults, and 2.5% for each additional child, again up to a maximum of 10%, that is, four children.</p>  <p>There are currently three income bands applicable across the country and Carlow County Council is in band 3, along with 15 of the other 30 local authorities.  This reflects the fact that the cost of rental and housing accommodation in the county is, relatively speaking, lower than in higher band counties such as, for example, those in the greater Dublin area.  The income threshold for a household of two adults and two children in County Carlow is &euro;27,500 net income per annum with higher limits applying to larger households up to a maximum of three adults and four children.</p>  <p>It is important to note that under the household means policy, which applies in all housing authorities, the thresholds for social housing assessment are based on net income.  This is defined as gross household income less income tax, PRSI and the universal social charge.  Therefore, the &euro;27,500 figure I referred to as the income threshold for a household of two adults and two children in Carlow is the net income figure after tax, PRSI and USC.  The household means policy also provides for a range of income disregards and, in addition, housing authorities have discretion to decide to disregard income that is temporary, short-term or once-off in nature.</p>  <p>I can confirm to the Senator that as part of the broader social housing reform agenda, a review of the income eligibility limits for social housing supports is under way.  It is unfortunately not possible to give a definitive timeline at this stage for the completion of the review as it will also have to take into account the impact of other parallel initiatives being brought forward on affordability and cost rental.  In that context it should be noted that, in terms of the cohort of people that are just over the income eligibility thresholds for social housing support, the Government is responding to the needs of such households through a number of initiatives including a new affordable housing scheme and a cost rental scheme.  In addition, earlier this year a new local authority mortgage scheme for first time buyers, the Rebuilding Ireland home loan, was introduced.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800006#E00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  In fairness, it is a concern that it has been seven years since we have had a review.  At our last housing meeting we got an assessment of the price to rent a house in Carlow, which was &euro;700 a month.  That is totally wrong.  It is &euro;1,000 per month if not &euro;1,100.  The figures are totally wrong.  The biggest issue here is that when people apply to go on the local authority housing list their overtime, maintenance payments and family income supplement are taken into consideration.  That limits the number of people who can qualify.  There is no real appeal mechanism.  Perhaps we need to look at that.</p>  <p>Mortgages with local authorities are only based on earned income.  One has to be earning an income to qualify for a mortgage.  That is another bracket.  People on family income supplement do not qualify to go on the housing list and people cannot get a mortgage.  This is urgent.  The figures the local authorities and the Government are giving are totally wrong.  We need to help these people.  These are the people who cannot save, cannot afford a mortgage and cannot go on the housing list.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1277" speakername="David Stanton" time="13:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800007#F00100"><p>I thank the Senator again and recognise her deep interest in the research that has been carried out into this matter.  I will ask the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government to respond in writing to her quite soon on the points she has raised.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="13:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800007#F00200"><p>She has shown her passion for this issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1277" speakername="David Stanton" time="13:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800007#F00300"><p>Absolutely.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="13:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800007#F00400"><p>If the Minister of State is prepared to wait for Senator Byrne, who is on her way, we will take Senator &Oacute; Donnghaile's matter next.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1277" speakername="David Stanton" time="13:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800007#F00500"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.27" nospeaker="true" time="13:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800007#F00600">Presidential Elections</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="13:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800007#F00700"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it, an Teachta Cannon.  He has four minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="13:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800007#F00800"><p>Gabhaim bu&iacute;ochas leis an Aire St&aacute;it.  I will not need four minutes.  The question I have submitted is very straightforward.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="13:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800007#F00900"><p>That is good.  It is nice to see that kind of approach as we come up to Christmas.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1241" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Cannon" time="13:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800007#F01000"><p>The Cathaoirleach will be encouraging that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="13:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800007#F01100"><p>Yes.  I was in Senator &Oacute; Donnghaile's position a few times in the past.  I often took a similar approach to see what the Minister or Minister of State would say.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1241" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Cannon" time="13:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800007#F01200"><p>I thank Senator &Oacute; Donnghaile for giving me an opportunity to address the Seanad on the important matter of voting rights.  I believe it is of interest to all Members of the House.  Earlier this month, the Government reviewed the progress of Bills to amend the Constitution and decided that subject to the passage of the necessary constitutional amendment Bills, two referendums will be held on the same day as the local and European elections, which are due to take place between 23 and 26 May 2019.  The Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade, in consultation with the Department of Housing, Planning and Local Government, is continuing to make progress with the work needed to inform the development of an appropriate constitutional amendment Bill for the holding of a referendum on extending the franchise at presidential elections to Irish citizens resident outside the State.</p>  <p>As the Senator will recall, the Government decided on 7 March 2017 to accept in principle the main recommendation in the fifth report of the Constitutional Convention that citizens resident outside the State, including citizens resident in Northern Ireland, should have the right to vote at presidential elections and that a referendum would be held to amend the Constitution to give effect to this.  Following this announcement, an options paper which was jointly prepared by the Departments of Foreign Affairs and Trade and Housing, Planning and Local Government was published on 22 March 2017 to inform public debate on this significant policy change.  The options paper set out a broad range of options that are available to give effect to the possible extension of voting rights at presidential elections.  It examined the key operational issues involved, including voter registration, the methods of voting, the implications for the administration of presidential elections and the estimated costs associated with an extended franchise.  The options paper considered seven possible options for the extension of the franchise.  It considered whether it should be extended to all citizens resident outside the State, to citizens who have a period of time living in the State, to citizens who have left the State within a defined period of time, to citizens who were previously on the register of electors, to citizens who hold valid Irish passports, to citizens born on the island of Ireland or to citizens who have lived in Ireland for at least one year.</p>  <p>The options paper provided a focus for discussions at a dedicated session on voting rights that was held at the second Global Irish Civic Forum on 5 May 2017.  When the participants at the forum considered the seven options, their almost unanimous view was that the franchise should be extended to all citizens resident outside the State.  In addition, there was a strong view that an extension of the franchise should not be restricted by time, prior residence in the State or previous registration in the State.  Against this background, the next step will involve bringing proposals to the Government early in the new year on the question of to whom, in particular, the vote should be extended.  Ultimately, this will inform the drafting of the constitutional amendment Bill.  When the Bill has been published in the D&aacute;il, the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government will need to establish a referendum commission, which will need to have enough time to carry out its functions.  Previous commissions have recommended that a period of approximately 16 weeks is appropriate to enable the statutory functions involved to be undertaken satisfactorily.  In this regard, it should be noted that a referendum commission cannot be established until a constitutional amendment Bill has been initiated.  In broad terms, this means the Bill should be drafted and published approximately four months prior to the holding of the referendum, with a good proportion of that period being between the passage of the Bill and polling day.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="13:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800007#F01300"><p>Gabhaim bu&iacute;ochas ar&iacute;s leis an Aire St&aacute;it.  I thank the Minister of State for the timely and useful update.  I want to take this opportunity to acknowledge his role.  I travelled to London recently to meet a number of groups and organisations that are representatives of the Irish diaspora in Britain.</p> <p>They all acknowledged the Minister of State's leadership role on issues pertaining to them, but not least on this important referendum.  The timeline is clear in respect of the outline of what the next steps should be.  If the Minister of State does not mind I will home in on his last paragraph, which means that in broad terms the Bill should be drafted and published some four months prior to the holding of the referendum.  That would be very early in the new year, possibly January or early February.  How confident is the Minister of State that this would happen or is still on course to happen? I often come into the House to criticise the Government but I cannot criticise the Government in its diligent approach to this.  The Government has been steadfast on it.  As we get tantalisingly close to this referendum, we need to ensure we see it over the line with regard to the processes that are required.  I will finish with that question.  Go raibh maith agat.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1241" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Cannon" time="13:20:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800008#G00200"><p>I thank the Senator for taking the time to engage with our diaspora groups in the UK.  I have been making the point as best I can to all of our diaspora groups around the world that they need to become very actively involved in this campaign in the run up to the referendum next May.  I am very confident that the necessary legislation will be in place during the timelines I referred to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="13:20:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800008#G00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State, Deputy Cannon.  I welcome back to the House the Minister of State at the Department of Justice and Equality, Deputy Stanton.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.38" nospeaker="true" time="13:20:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800008#G00400">Garda Deployment</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="13:20:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800008#G00500"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Stanton.  I rise today to discuss areas of justice.  I am looking for a greater Garda presence in the east Limerick area.  Recently I made a submission to the Castletroy development plan in which I looked for a full-time Garda station in that region.  The area is expanding.  At the time the chief superintendent said that due to lack of resources it would not be warranted to put in a full-time Garda station.  However, the area is growing and expanding and there are many part-time stations in different parts of the region.</p>  <p>My main concern is Castleconnell and the greater Castleconnell area.  There has been a spate of burglaries in the last month and one house was targeted two to three times.  On one road alone there were some 20 burglaries, but there is no full-time Garda in the area.  The region is looked after by the Garda station in Henry Street, which is right in the city centre, but there is a population of more than 20,000 outside that part of the city.  The area covers Castleconnell, Castletroy, Monaleen, Annacotty, Lisnagry and down into Montpelier.  It is a growing population.  There is also a large student population closer to the university but the area I refer to is very residential.  A lot of the residents have had to put up electronic gates, lights and other elements to deter people from breaking into their houses.  I am concerned because there is no full-time Garda presence in the area and the garda&iacute; tell me that they are working on limited resources and personnel.  This is why I call for a greater Garda presence to be put into this area.  It is frightening to think that these issues are ongoing and appear to be on a constant basis.  I look forward to the Minister of State's response.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1277" speakername="David Stanton" time="13:20:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800008#G00600"><p>The Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Flanagan, sends his apologies.  The Cabinet is still in session and he is in attendance.  I  thank the Senator for raising this matter.</p>  <p>As the Senator will appreciate, the allocation of all Garda resources, including personnel, is strictly a matter for the Garda Commissioner and his management team.  The Minister has no direct role in this regard.  The Minister is informed by the Garda Commissioner that in regard to the deployment of Garda personnel, a distribution model is used that takes into account all relevant factors including population, crime trends and the policing needs of each individual Garda division, including the Limerick division, with a view to providing an effective and responsive police service.</p>  <p>The Minister is of course very much aware of the impact of crime such as burglary and theft on local communities in rural areas like east Limerick.  The Minister assures the Senator that An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na is committed to a vigorous and comprehensive response to this type of criminal activity, which ingrains fear in our local communities.</p> <p>The scale of Garda activity against burglary and property-related crime under Operation Thor has led to concentrated Garda activity resulting, as of 30 November 2018, in more than 168,600 targeted checkpoints and 243,200 crime prevention patrols nationwide.  This concentrated policing activity has produced in the region of 8,830 arrests and 10,143 charges covering a range of offences which, in addition to burglary, include handling stolen property, possession of firearms and drugs offences.</p> <p>The area referred to by the Senator forms part of the Limerick division and the Minister is informed by the Commissioner that the Garda strength of the Limerick division on 30 October 2018, the latest date for which figures are readily available, was 580.  There are also 26 Garda reserves and 54 Garda civilian staff attached to the division.  In addition, when appropriate, the work of local garda&iacute; is supported by a number of Garda national units such as the national bureau of criminal investigation, the armed support units, the Garda national economic crime bureau and the Garda national drugs and organised crime bureau.  The Minister is further informed by the Commissioner that since the reopening of the Garda College in September 2014, 2,400 recruits have attested as members of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, of whom 35 have been assigned to the Limerick division.  Garda numbers, taking account of projected retirements, are expected to increase to around the 14,000 mark by year end.  This focus on investment in personnel is critical.  The moratorium on recruitment introduced in 2010 resulted in a significant reduction in the strength of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  The Minister is now rebuilding the organisation and providing the Commissioner with the resources to increase Garda numbers and activity in order to tackle and prevent crime in all our communities, including east Limerick.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="13:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800009#H00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  I neglected to say that the community garda&iacute; are meeting the residents tonight and have been very responsive.  It is a big factor that people do not see the Garda on the ground.  It is pretty much a rural area.  There has been a spate of burglaries.  I commend the Government on the reopening of the Garda College.  It is good that there are so many extra garda&iacute; coming on stream.  However, there is such a large population out there without a full-time garda deployed.  The Minister of State might suggest to the Minister, Deputy Flanagan, that he speak to the Commissioner again about it.  There was an article in a newspaper during the week stating that an extra 6,500 people are expected to be employed in that area shortly.  It is expanding at a very fast rate.  I would appreciate if the Minister of State could give me some commitment on that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1277" speakername="David Stanton" time="13:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800009#H00300"><p>The Minister assures the Senator that Garda management and the Commissioner keep the distribution of resources under continual review in the context of crime trends and policing priorities and that the needs of all divisions, including the Limerick division, are taken into consideration in the allocation of Garda resources.  He is pleased to say that budget 2018 will support the continuation of the high level of investment in the Garda workforce of recent years and ensure that the vision of an overall workforce of 21,000 by 2021 remains on track.  In addition, the Government&rsquo;s plan for an overall Garda workforce of 21,000 is complemented by substantial increases in resources across the board for An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  Some &euro;330 million, including &euro;205 million under the capital plan, is being invested in Garda ICT infrastructure over the period 2016 to 2021.  This major investment will allow An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na to deploy the latest cutting-edge technologies in the fight against crime and will facilitate progress on important reforms arising from the Garda Inspectorate&rsquo;s report on crime investigation.  The capital plan 2016 to 2021 provides for an investment of &euro;46 million in the Garda fleet to ensure that An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na has a modern, effective and fit for purpose fleet.  This is in addition to the investment of almost &euro;30 million in the period 2033 to 2015.  In the period 2013 to end of 2017 almost &euro;44 million will have been invested in the fleet with some 2,000 vehicles coming on-stream.  This investment will facilitate the provision of more effective policing services and the Minister expects that the Limerick division, like all other Garda divisions, will benefit from these new resources becoming available.  I will certainly bring the Senator's concerns back to the Minister.  I note what the Senator said and that she has a passion and deep concern for this area.  I will certainly make the Minister aware of the matter.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.44" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800009#H00400">Messages from Dil</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="13:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800009#H00500"><p>D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann has passed the Wildlife (Amendment) Bill 2016, to which the agreement of Seanad &Eacute;ireann is desired.  D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann has passed the Local Government Bill 2018, to which the agreement of Seanad &Eacute;ireann is desired.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.46" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 1.05 p.m. and resumed at 1.35 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.47" nospeaker="true" time="13:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800010#O00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="13:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800010#O00200"><p>Before I call the Leader to outline the business of the day, I would like, as Cathaoirleach, as I should have done last week, to express my gratitude and thanks to the Clerk Assistant of the Seanad, Ms Bridget Doody, and the staff.  We had long and late hours.  I omitted and neglected to do it last week.  They were very professional, patient and helpful to me.  It is important to acknowledge the work done by Ms Doody and the other staff in the absence of the Clerk of the Seanad.  At the last sitting, there was such intense debate that I omitted to do that and apologise that I neglected to convey my thanks and, I am sure, those of the House, to the staff.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="13:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800010#O00500"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.50" nospeaker="true" time="13:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800010#O00600">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="13:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800010#O00700"><p>The Order of Business today is No. 1, Consumer Protection (Regulation of Credit Servicing Firms) Bill 2018 - Committee and Remaining Stages, beginning at 2.45 p.m.; No. 2, Finance (African Development (Bank and Fund) and Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill 2018 - Second Stage, to be taken on conclusion of No. 1, with time allocated to group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes and all other Senators not to exceed five minutes; No. 3, Social Welfare, Pensions and Civil Registration Bill 2018 - Report and Final Stages, to be taken on conclusion of No. 2; No. 4, Irish Film Board (Amendment) Bill 2018 - All Stages, to be taken on conclusion of No. 3, with the time allocated to group spokespersons on Second Stage not to exceed eight minutes, with all other Senators not to exceed five minutes, and the Minister to be given no less than five minutes to reply, with Committee and Remaining Stages to be taken immediately thereafter; No. 5, Criminal Law (Extraterritorial Jurisdiction) Bill 2018 - Order for Second Stage and Second Stage, to be taken on conclusion of No. 4 and to adjourn after one and a half hour if not previously concluded, with the contributions of group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes and all other Senators not to exceed five minutes; and No. 6, Local Government Bill 2018 - Second Stage, to be taken on the conclusion of No. 5 with the time allocated to group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes and all other Senators not to exceed five minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="13:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800011#P00100"><p>I thank the Leader for outlining a particularly busy day and week for all of us.  I will speak on Nos. 1, 2, 3 and 4 and also on the Order of Business.  I thank the Leader for outlining the Order of Business.</p><p>I will raise a number of points this afternoon.  The first is a very sensitive issue but it cannot go unmentioned.  I refer to what happened in Strokestown.  Strokestown is an area I know a bit better than people might think because my grandmother was from and grew up in Strokestown although she has long since passed away.  Strokestown was formerly known for having one of the widest streets in Europe despite the fact it is in a relatively small country town.</p><p>I appreciate that much of what happened in the past week to ten days is not familiar to all of us and I am sure there are details that are being kept confidential.  The evictions that happened last Tuesday and the scuffles and so on that happened are very distressing.  I do not think anyone can condone violence towards people.  We need to be very vigilant.  There are many people facing similar circumstances.  If they are evicted we end up having to rehouse them.  The State needs to look at a mechanism whereby if people are in difficulty the State takes over the property and leaves people there and manages the business in some way or other.  We could end up having all these properties being taken over with similar levels of unrest.  It is not good that people are losing their family homes.  Much of the story was in the paper this morning.  There were very significant debts and an issue going on a long time.  Perhaps people were not engaging the way we hope they would.  The State and the Government needs to take the issue into account.</p><p>It is just over 18 months since the Minister told us the expected cost of the children's hospital was &euro;1 billion and that, perhaps more importantly, it would be delivered on time.  We now know that neither is the case.  It was reported last week in <i>The Irish Times</i>and in further reporting today that the projected cost of the national children's hospital is now &euro;1.4 billion.  That is more than twice the &euro;650 million estimate that was used when planning permission was given only two years ago, which looks to be a projected cost increase of almost &euro;1 million a day.  The suggestion is the hospital will now be the most expensive hospital ever constructed in the world.  What are we getting for this &euro;1.4 million?  Will the sum climb higher again?  None of us can have faith that a figure that was &euro;650 million, then &euro;1 billion and now &euro;1.4 billion will not rise further.  We need to know that taxpayers and citizens will ultimately get a good service and value for money.  The Minister needs to come into the House sooner rather than later and let us know what is happening.</p><p>On another health-related matter, it is reported the Minister, Deputy Harris, is expected to seek Cabinet approval for the first phase of construction of the National Maternity Hospital to proceed on the site of St. Vincent's Hospital in Dublin, but the legal agreement between the Department of Health, the National Maternity Hospital and St. Vincent's Hospital on the final contract is not expected until the new year.  Since the announcement of that hospital there has been nothing but controversy and little progress on the site.  We need to be very guarded and mind taxpayers' investment in hospital facilities.  I know the Minister was very busy in the House last week on a particularly important issue for many people on both sides but these are very significant infrastructural projects with very significant cost overruns and if I was a member of the Government or a governing arrangement, Opposition people would certainly be challenging me on the figures.  It is important.</p><p>On Brexit, will the Leader outline the Government's plans in the event of a likely no-deal scenario?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="13:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800011#P00200"><p>It will not happen.  There will be no Brexit.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="13:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800011#P00300"><p>We might hope that is the case.  I certainly hope it will be the case.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="13:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800011#P00400"><p>Senator Horkan is anxious to conclude.  Please do not interrupt him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="13:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800011#P00500"><p>I am anxious to conclude.  I do not need to be goaded by Senator Norris.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="13:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800011#P00600"><p>I am just assisting him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="13:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800011#P00700"><p>We are only delaying proceedings.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="13:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800011#P00800"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach and the Leader.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="13:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800011#P00900"><p>I will share some good news.  Since 2007, I have been campaigning for the National Rehabilitation Hospital in D&uacute;n Laoghaire.</p> <p>Despite significant correspondence to the Minister we were making no progress.  I am delighted to say that with like-minded Independents and party Members - I particularly acknowledge the work of some Fine Gael Senators and Deputies - we have been successful.  Needless to say we have not heard this news from the Minister, but I contacted the hospital last week to confirm that a new consultant's hours have been extended.  They are not very good at telling the good news, but the consultant who had ceased to be there has been re-engaged with additional hours and the seven beds have been reopened, which is marvellous news.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="13:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800012#Q00200"><p>It is.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="13:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800012#Q00300"><p>It is even nicer to have found that out myself without notification from any Minister telling me about it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="13:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800012#Q00400"><p>The Minister is a good egg.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="13:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800012#Q00500"><p>I thank people who have been indulgent with me for many months.  All that is at stake is the six remaining beds in that hospital.  I appeal to Senators who have worked quietly behind the scenes to continue with their parties' health spokespersons to try to lobby to get the additional six beds open, as they should be.</p>  <p>I do not know if anybody listened to "Morning Ireland".  Our vegetable production has dropped by 50%-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="13:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800012#Q00600"><p>Absolutely.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="13:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800012#Q00700"><p>-----in the past three years and we have below-cost selling of fresh produce.  I appeal to people inside this House and beyond to demand high-quality Irish homegrown vegetables because when the suppliers are put under pressure it will happen.  I ask the Leader for a debate in the new year with the Minister of State with responsibility for horticulture to discuss Irish vegetable production.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="13:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800012#Q00800"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="13:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800012#Q00900"><p>I know the Leader comes in here and reads out the daily Order of Business and time slots.  I know that is rough and is a moveable feast.  I respect that and know it is not an easy job.  Would it be possible to get ten or 20 hard copies of what he reads out left in the Chamber as it would help us?  I do not want to ask the Leader to stand up and call the list out again.  It is a busy station here.  It would be helpful for the smooth running of the House and for the smooth running of our diaries.  I am aware that such a document exists and is given to the Cathaoirleach and to the Seanad Office.  Ministers are aware of it and it is only right that we too should be aware of it.  I want to be flexible and reasonable.  I hope the Leader will agree to that very reasonable and simple request.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="13:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800012#Q01000"><p>I ask for the Minister for Health to come to the House to explain the &euro;100 million overrun on the national children's hospital.  Day after day and week after week I stand here being told that Sinn F&eacute;in is not on top of economic issues and asking what would happen if Sinn F&eacute;in were running the economy.  However, a project like this overrunning by &euro;100 million is absolutely unacceptable and we need transparency on it.  That &euro;100 million will be taken from other vital services within the health service and it cannot be allowed to happen.  I ask that the Minister come to the House at the very first opportunity.  This time last year we were told that the national children's hospital would be brought in on time and on budget.  Something has gone disastrously wrong here and somebody must be held accountable for it.</p>  <p>The appalling scenes of eviction in Roscommon in recent days have highlighted the need for urgent regulation of private security firms.  I welcome the Bill tabled by my colleague, Deputy &Oacute; Laoghaire, to regulate private security firms.  We witnessed scenes of people coming in to evict an elderly couple from their home, regardless of the individual circumstances.  We do not know who these people were or where they came from.  They had no identification whatsoever.  This cannot be allowed to continue.  It is a disgrace and was unjustified.  It brought to mind scenes from our past of people being thrown on to the side of the road.  Those scenes have touched a raw nerve, certainly with people living in rural areas.  I commend the community on coming together and standing against this type of behaviour.  I want the Minister for Justice and Equality to come to the House.</p> <p>I want to ask him to explain to us how An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na could stand by and let a situation like this develop.  We need to know what is impeding it from intervening in such situations.  I welcome the Bill, which will go some way to addressing this and providing accountability with regard to private security firms, which seem to be running riot around this country and seem to be running riot at the behest of the banks, which have treated the citizens of this country, and continue to treat them, appallingly.</p> <p>I welcome the British Competition and Markets Authority, CMA, recommendations around the auditing of the big firms in order to separate audit from consulting services.  This is something I have asked to be done through our finance committee.  I raised it before because of the auditing firm that had given a clean bill of health to Carillion and to others.  The cost of what has happened to smaller businesses within the State due to Carillion has to be addressed and one of the ways of addressing it is to hold the auditing firms to account.  These are the same auditing firms which told us the banks had a clean bill of health before the last crash.  Something needs to be done.  I ask the Minister for Finance to come to the House in the new year specifically to discuss that issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800013#R00200"><p>I genuinely want to ask the Leader for a debate with anybody in government who can justify the new confidence and supply agreement.  It reminds me of when a mother used to come home having left her child to tidy up the house.  Nothing would have been cleaned up and she would ask, "What have you been doing for the last number of hours?"  We have had high level negotiations between two crack teams from Fine Gael and Fianna F&aacute;il for six weeks-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1438" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="14:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800013#R00300"><p>Two what teams?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800013#R00400"><p>Two crack teams.  Two teams of the highest calibre.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1438" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="14:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800013#R00500"><p>With that Dublin accent of the Senator, I get lost now and again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800013#R00600"><p>The best negotiators they could find, three from each side, in secret negotiations over a period of months-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800013#R00700"><p>What's another year?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800013#R00800"><p>They came out with not even a sheet of paper between them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1438" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="14:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800013#R00900"><p>The Senator will have to take down his posters.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800013#R01000"><p>The frustrating thing, as the Leader will agree, is that this country faces a huge number of challenges - Brexit, homelessness, housing and the health crisis, which have all been mentioned today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1438" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="14:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800013#R01100"><p>Is the Senator saying the Labour Party will do better than the Labour Party in England?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800013#R01200"><p>Order, Senator Lawlor.  You are the next speaker.  If you want to use this opportunity instead of speaking then, I will take you off the list.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800013#R01300"><p>Is it not unbelievable that the two main parties in the Oireachtas could have six weeks of negotiations and not come up with a single sheet of paper with a single word written on it?  If they had a single sheet of paper with the word "homelessness" written on it, at least we could have an argument over and back as to the importance of that word or what they are going to do about it.  However, they literally came up with nothing.  We are being governed on the basis of nothing.  We had an agreement that went up to the budget last year.  Water was the most important issue two and a half years ago and it took up the vast bulk of that agreement.  Now, we have a crisis of homelessness and, after six weeks of negotiations, not even a sheet of paper emerges.  It is unbelievable.  Somebody from the Government should come in here to account for it.</p>  <p>On a more positive note, I would like to debate in this House the nature of female participation in sport by girls and women.  Anybody who observed the RT&Eacute; sports awards at the weekend will see that massive advances are being made in female participation in sport, which is to be remarked upon and encouraged.  There is a campaign, 20x20, which is seeking a 20% increase in funding, a 20% increase in participation and a 20% increase in coverage of women's sport by the year 2020.  It would be a good idea to have the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport in the House to discuss the issue and the 20x20 campaign, and to see what politics can do to help that agenda for female participation in sport by girls and women.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.84" nospeaker="true" time="14:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800013#R01400">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800013#R01500"><p>Before I move to the next speaker, I welcome to the House Mr. Bruce Knotts and his husband, Issac Humphrey, who are seated in the Visitors Gallery.</p> <p>Mr. Knotts is director of the Unitarian Universalist United Nations Office.  He was born in California.  Among other things, he has ably represented many people who are concerned about climate change.  He has just come back from the long Poland conference.  He is a tireless campaigner against homophobia throughout the world, and it is our pleasure to acknowledge the work he has done and to recognise him and his husband.  He is most welcome and I hope he will have an enjoyable stay in our little nation.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.87" nospeaker="true" time="14:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800014#S00200">Order of Business (Resumed)</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1438" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="14:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800014#S00300"><p>Just in case I do not get an opportunity to speak again, I wish all my colleagues here a very happy Christmas and a prosperous new year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800014#S00400"><p>Is that what the Senator was shouting at me?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800014#S00500"><p>There are two more days.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800014#S00600"><p>Please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800014#S00700"><p>Was he shouting that at me earlier?  I could not really make out what he was saying.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1438" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="14:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800014#S00800"><p>As the Cathaoirleach mentioned earlier, the hours put in last week on the abortion legislation and the judicial appointments Bill were phenomenal, and I wish the staff a happy Christmas and a prosperous new year too.</p><p>I wish to raise an issue I have been raising constantly, namely, the payouts associated with soft tissue injuries and the legacy this has left on every one of us here.  Only at the weekend there was an article in <i>The Sunday Times</i>according to which, typically, the legal profession blocked a potential Bill from coming before the D&aacute;il and Seanad which would regulate the amount of moneys being paid out in this regard.  The Bar of Ireland and the Law Society of Ireland both blocked the chair of the Personal Injuries Commission, Nicholas Kearns, from potentially bringing forward legislation that might be useful in saving each and every one of us money.  The Insurance Ireland representative quoted was very much in favour of this type of legislation being brought forward.  Perhaps the onus is on us to bring forward Private Members' legislation that would allow for regulation of the payouts being made, which are four and a half times more than in the UK, and the bulk of that goes to the legal profession.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800014#S00900"><p>I now call on Senator Norris.  I am slightly jumping the gun but I have a reason for doing so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800014#S01000"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach.  I do appreciate the-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800014#S01100"><p>It is Christmas.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800014#S01200"><p>It is, and I have just spent three and a half hours at the dentist so I am a little all over the place.</p>  <p>I wish to express my absolute outrage at the evictions in Roscommon.  It is disgusting that an elderly trio of siblings were kicked out of their home in the run-up to Christmas.  The vulture funds should be run out of this country without any excuse.  We should get rid of them.  What is the Government doing to protect Irish people in their homes?  I have to laugh at Sinn F&eacute;in bleating about this.  If Sinn F&eacute;in had supported my Bill, this kind of thing would have been obviated, but however.  That is politics, I suppose.</p>  <p>I wish to ask about the involvement of the police.  The unfortunate members of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na were stuck in the middle of this thing.  It is appalling when people are brought in from a foreign country to throw Irish people out of their homes.  I wonder if the Taoiseach is aware that "eviction" is a dirty word in Ireland.  I have no time whatever for the leaders of 1916, but they would be turning in their graves at the idea that eviction is commonplace in this alleged Republic.  I feel very strongly about this.</p>  <p>I agree with Senator Boyhan's comments about vegetable farmers.  It is appalling to think they are asked to accept 20 cent per kilo for carrots and potatoes.  How on earth can they possibly make a living?  They cannot.  The number of vegetable farmers in Dublin - and throughout the country, I think - has halved in the past five years.  It is a real crisis, and once again it is the multinational supermarkets that are doing this.  They ought to be called to account.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="14:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800014#S01300"><p>No doubt everyone in this House will at this point have heard about the theft of an ATM from outside the Bank of Ireland premises in Ballybay, County Monaghan.  It is the only on-street ATM available to the public in Ballybay.</p> <p>In the run-up to Christmas, the main street was closed off for a considerable period and it was not possible for local people to access the many shops, restaurants and bars that the town has to offer.</p> <p>In many ways, this could have been a complete disaster for a small rural town like Ballybay, but I am glad to report a positive news story today, in that Ballybay is fighting back.  Last night, the local chamber of commerce held an emergency meeting at which it decided that this Christmas was not going to be disastrous for it and that it would do something about the situation.  The chamber met staff from the local Bank of Ireland branch, which I am glad to report has, to accommodate local traders and shoppers, decided to open its branch doors on Saturday and Sunday of this week.  I compliment the local bank staff on doing that.</p> <p>The chamber also decided to hold a number of events to kick-start the town's Christmas.  It has arranged everything from a carol service to music on the streets to promote the local town and encourage people to shop locally over Christmas.  We can refer to CCTV and more garda&iacute; for the town, and we will do so in the new year, but what could have been a disaster for a small rural town has ended up being a good news story.  I compliment the people of Ballybay on their good community spirit.</p> <p>I will take this opportunity to encourage people throughout the country to shop local where possible.  It is the local business that sponsors the local football or athletic club and puts its hand in its pocket all year around.  This is the time of year where the customers have an opportunity to thank the local shop, bar or restaurant by putting their hands in their pockets and shopping locally.  I encourage as many people as possible to keep that in mind over the Christmas period.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:20:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800015#T00200"><p>My colleague, Senator Norris, just referred to the Roscommon incident.  There is no escaping the fact that land and its ownership run through the heart of what it is to be Irish.  However, I sometimes think that we get the emotional side of the argument without getting the full facts.  Clearly, there is high emotion across Roscommon and the west over what has happened.  Many Senators will have sailed close to the wind with family debt at some stage as their lives changed.  In my case, it was when my business failed.  There is a requirement on all of us to engage with those who loaned us money.  I have no idea why that family was being evicted other than there was an unpaid debt, which was put through the courts and on which the courts made a ruling.  The method by which the family was evicted was outrageous.  That people can come down from wherever dressed in black uniforms without identification marks, in some cases in vehicles that have no visible registration or tax discs, is not acceptable.</p>  <p>It is equally not acceptable for a shower of thugs to enter a property afterwards and beat up security officers who are working for the minimum wage.  I have stood as a security officer in some of the most precarious places, places where I was scared stiff, for an entire night on my own.  It is grossly unfair of any shower of thugs to beat up eight men.</p>  <p>First, we need regulation of such operators.  Second, we need the full details.  Third, I will call on the Leader to ask the Minister for Justice and Equality to look at Facebook because the name and address of the county sheriff in Roscommon has been published on it today.  The county sheriff is doing a job, the same as anyone else.  None of this is going to put that family back in its home.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:20:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800015#T00300"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:20:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800015#T00400"><p>At the end of the day, those who work for the State are entitled to the protection of the State.  In future, before we all get tied up in emotion, let us have the full story published, not just the bits that suit our particular cause.  I feel desperately sorry for that family - I really do - but, by God, I feel equally as sorry for the security officers who were in hospital over the weekend.  The thugs on both sides - the ones who evicted the family and the ones who beat up the security officers - should be behind bars.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="14:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800016#U00200"><p>I support Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in's call for a debate on women and sport, an issue about which I am very passionate and have a keen interest in.  I congratulate the ladies' hockey team who won the best team award in the RT&Eacute; sports awards on Saturday night.  It was a great tribute to their contribution representing Ireland, for which they won silver medals.  They have set a high standard for many other teams.  I am involved in a local school from which one of the students has been selected to play basketball for Ireland.  The team has a lot of competitions coming up.  It is time we had a debate on women's participation in and contribution to sport.</p>  <p>Shannon Foynes Port Company has been awarded EU transport corridor status today.  It is one of nine ports across Europe awarded this status.  It was awarded this status because it is a very deep port.  This is a Brexit present in that if Brexit proceeds it will pose many issues for UK ports.  This award is very positive for the Shannon Estuary and the Shannon Foynes Port Company.  The company's development plan out to 2041 provides for the additional physical infrastructure and innovative digital technology.  This designation today will lead to delivery of that plan and job creation.  It is a good news story, which I welcome.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800016#U00300"><p>I agree with previous speakers' comments regarding the outrageous increase in costs for the national children's hospital.  Another outrage is the damaging effects of this construction on the communities of Dublin 8, where I come from, in terms of air pollution, infrastructural damage to homes and traffic noise and the fact that this work which was supposed to be completed in a decade is being pushed out to 15 years.</p>  <p>The nurses unions have voted overwhelmingly for industrial action and strike.  Today, the INMO is considering an all-out strike following a 95% ballot in favour of it.  Yesterday, the PNA announced 95% support for a strike.  Nurses are not known for their militancy but it seems it takes strike action to get things done.  Nurses are at the coalface.  This is about staff retention and recruitment, and the nurses' response to the public pay commission report of last September, which utterly failed to address the serious staff shortages.</p>  <p>On Friday my colleague, Deputy O'Reilly, received a response to a parliamentary question from the HSE which stated that there have been 11,000 acknowledged assaults on HSE staff over the last decade, 70% of which were on nurses.  This is a perform storm.  The winter plan, it appears, is year long.  The most concentrated period of need is January to March and every day in our accident and emergency departments is a winter day.  I ask the Leader to find out from the Minister for Health, Deputy Harris, what action he proposes to take and if he will engage and provide meaningful solutions to this winter of discontent.  Nurses are speaking with one voice and calling for the proper staffing of hospitals in order that they can do their job.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800016#U00400"><p>Today is International Migrants Day.  It is important that we record the day.  I ask that the Leader provide for a debate in the new year on the issue of migrants.  The Committee on Migration, Refugees and Displaced Persons has issued a statement recognising how much more there is to be done on the issue of migrants, which references the 3.5 million refugees from Syria and the over 2,000 deaths in the Mediterranean this year.</p> <p>The committee referred to the fact that behind these figures are individual human fates, men women and children compelled to leave their homes who depend on humanitarian support, whose human rights must be respected and who must be allowed to contribute to our common future.  To my shock and horror, at that committee meeting members of the Fidesz fascist party stood up and objected to this wording.  They objected to use of the terms "human rights" and "common future".  Thankfully, there were enough votes to defeat them and prevent what they wanted to do in terms of changing the statement.  </p> <p>I do not raise this matter in order to score points.  These people are absolutely scary.  Yesterday they passed a law compelling workers to work 400 hours overtime for which they will have to wait three years to be paid.  They have issued statements on LGBT rights that are offensive.  Fidesz is a fascist party and, unfortunately, Fine Gael is sitting with its members in the European Parliament.  In the 1930s fascism flourished because people did not stand up and say what needed to be said and call out the horrific policies for what they were.  I am calling on Fine Gael to act here.  In fairness, I have spoken to Senator Joe O'Reilly, who has been very helpful with regard to this issue.  However, I cannot accept that Fine Gael members would sit with these fascists, who are busy inflicting horrific policies on their own people and on migrants, and not call them out and call for their expulsion from the European People's Party.  That is what we need to hear and see today.  I ask the Leader to engage on this issue seriously because we cannot stay silent in the face of the Fidesz fascist party. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800017#V00200"><p>I call on the Leader, who may be expecting a very good Christmas, given that Senator Devine referred to him as a Minister on two occasions, to respond.  Maybe there will be something special in his Christmas stocking this year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800017#V00300"><p>That is possibly the last of the good news from Senator Devine for a while-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800017#V00400"><p>It is not be beyond the bounds of possibility that someone from the Senate could be appointed to Cabinet.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800017#V00500"><p>I do not think I will be following in the footsteps of the late Senator James Dooge, but perhaps we should all aspire to that.</p>  <p>I join the Cathaoirleach in thanking Ms Bridget Doody and all the Seanad staff for their sincere professionalism in what was a very trying and long week last week.  I also welcome back our esteemed Clerk and friend, Mr. Martin Groves, and offer him the sincere sympathy of all in the House on the very sad passing of his brother, Tony.  I know that Martin appreciates that we stood last week for a minute's silence in his brother's honour.  I thank Martin for his continued service and for coming back to the House today.  Ar dheis D&eacute; go raibh a anam d&iacute;lis.  </p>  <p>I also join the Cathaoirleach in welcoming our esteemed guests to the House, Mr. Bruce Knotts and his husband Isaac Humphrey who are here today as guests of Senator Wilson.  It is important, in the context of the contribution of Senator Gavan, that the work Mr. Knotts has done around the world in promoting diversity, equality and in fighting homophobia is commended.  He is also involved in the biggest global challenge of our generation, that of climate change, which speaks volume about him.  As a member of this House and of the LGBT community, I welcome them both and thank them for being here.  I hope they are not led astray by Senator Wilson.  I offer them a sincere c&eacute;ad m&iacute;le f&aacute;ilte.  </p>  <p>Senators Horkan, Conway-Walsh, Norris and Craughwell raised the incident in Strokestown, County Roscommon, at the weekend.  The horrific nature of the incident has captured the public imagination.  Local garda&iacute; have described it as criminal damage and assault.  While I am not familiar with all the circumstances, nobody wants to see anyone evicted from his or her family home or property.  It is important to recognise that there is a process involved in an eviction that must be followed.  The eviction took place on foot of a court order.  Engagement is critical in all such circumstances.  Every effort must be made to ensure that people do not lose their family home.</p> <p>As Members will be aware, prior to last weekend the Government had convened an interdepartmental group which will report to the Minister for Justice and Equality early next year.  The purpose of that group is to examine the administrative and legislative resources and other matters required to provide for the regulating and licensing of private security personnel assisting in enforcing court orders.  It is important that we do that.  Our language and behaviour is also important and critical.  We are very fortunate that we have a very strong and very fair Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na in our country.  We must support it at all times.  There are wrongs on all sides of the incident that happened at the weekend.  I condemn utterly the barbaric nature of the events.  Equally it is important that we understand the full facts of the situation before us.  Engagement by both sides, particularly the lending institutions, is critical.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:35:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800018#W00200"><p>With respect, we need some sort of legislation or ministerial order requiring evidence that engagement had taken place.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:35:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800018#W00300"><p>I will be happy to have the Minister come to the House to have a debate on the whole wider issue in due course.  As I said, none of us wants to see people evicted.  All parties involved have obligations and responsibilities.  It is important that reasonable voices are heard rather than just the loudest or the voices of the baying mob.  It is about everybody being heard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:35:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800018#W00400"><p>Which Minister will be invited to the House?  Will it be the Minister of Justice and Equality?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:35:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800018#W00500"><p>I assume the Minister for Justice and Equality would be the relevant Minister.  That is what I would envisage.  I will revert back to Senator Horkan in due course.  The Senator, along with Senators Conway-Walsh and Devine, also made reference to the issue of the national children's hospital.  Any of us who is fair and who has been involved in this issue must be concerned about the rising costs.  I was involved as Chair of the Joint Committee on Health and Children for five years.  An explanation is needed.  I am talking off the top of my head now but, even allowing for some type of construction inflation, the level of increase is way beyond what would be envisaged, notwithstanding the contribution of Senator Devine regarding the local issue.  Before the last general election I was on the Joint Committee on Health and Children and we went on a site visit.  There are local concerns, as Senator Devine has said.  I know that she, and other Members from her constituency area, such as the Minister of State, Deputy Catherine Byrne, have articulated and voiced those concerns and have met with local residents.  I have been part of groups that have met with local residents in the past.</p>  <p>We all want to see a national children's hospital constructed.  We need it.  Our country requires it.  In saying that, however, it is also important to say that this could potentially have an impact on other capital projects and that is very unfair.  I believe Senator Conway-Walsh was indirectly accusing me through her implication regarding Sinn F&eacute;in economics.  The important point is that the Government signed off on a project of &euro;1 billion in April 2017.  We are very much committed to it.  It is important that we understand and hear what the Minister had to say in Cabinet today.  I was not in Cabinet, so I am not familiar with the up-to-date situation.  We will have that debate in due course.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:35:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800018#W00600"><p>The Leader will be back in Cabinet soon.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:35:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800018#W00700"><p>I thank Senator Devine.  The issue Senator Craughwell raised around St. Vincent's Hospital was discussed on the Order of Business last week.  I referenced the contribution of Dr. Rhona Mahony on the Marian Finucane programme.  That is the best reference point.  Again we can debate that issue as part of the overarching debate on health in the new year.</p>  <p>Senator Craughwell also mentioned the issue of Brexit, which is ongoing.  It has certainly been heightened by the decision of the Tory Party last week to hold a vote of no confidence in the Prime Minister and the decision by the leader of the Labour Party, Jeremy Corbyn, to place a motion of no confidence in the Prime Minister before the House of Commons.  The important point is that the Taoiseach, the Minister of State with responsibility for European affairs, Deputy McEntee, and the T&aacute;naiste are very much aware of the need to up our preparations for a hard Brexit.  We are still not giving up on a deal being achieved.  Our deal took two years to negotiate.  By "our deal" I mean the deal between the European Union and the British Government.  The Taoiseach met with Prime Minister May in Brussels last week, as the Senator knows.  They had a very good conversation.</p> <p>Ireland's perspective has not changed.  The deal that has been put forward is the only deal on the table.  While many people will disagree on its composition, we all agree the best deal is on the table.  As Senators will be aware, the T&aacute;naiste has been in charge of the preparations for the Government's contingency planning across all Departments.  The Government is preparing for all eventualities.  The Cabinet has mandated that all Departments will give full priority to their plans for a no-deal Brexit or  a disorderly Brexit, if that were to happen.  It is important to recognise that we have seen some public demonstrations of contingency planning such as the hiring of customs officials.  The Government is committed to being ready.  There is no such thing as a good Brexit.  It is not good, and those are the fundamentals of that.</p> <p>Senators Boyhan and Norris raised the issue of vegetable production.  I will be happy to invite the Minister of State with responsibility for horticulture, Deputy Doyle, to come to the House in the new year.</p> <p>I congratulate all involved in the successful opening of the beds in the National Rehabilitation Hospital, as mentioned by Senator Boyhan.</p> <p>I will certainly consider the request that Senator Boyhan has made today on the Order of Business regarding the Order Paper or the scheduling of events.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800019#X00200"><p>What does that mean?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800019#X00300"><p>What does what mean?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800019#X00400"><p>The Leader referred to "the scheduling of events" on the Order Paper.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800019#X00500"><p>I was speaking about the ordering of the schedule.  The Senator should speak to Senator Boyhan about what-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800019#X00600"><p>I spoke to him about this specific issue before he left the Chamber.  His understanding is that the Leader is aware of time slots that should be brought to the House-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800019#X00700"><p>In fairness to the Leader, he has said he will consider it positively.  He should be allowed to do that before reverting to Senator Boyhan.  Otherwise, we are going to be-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800019#X00800"><p>I remind the House - I will say this again during the week - that there is very non-acrimonious co-operation by all sides, by and large, when the business of the House is being scheduled.  As I have outlined on the Order of Business today, the putting of times might mean we would not necessarily run into each other.  I will consider the request.  Since I became Leader of the House, I have been all in favour of making the House a better House in terms of how we do our business and allowing all sides to be heard.  I have a job to do as Leader.  There are others who want to be Leader.  Perhaps there are others who want to take over the running of the country.  That is their prerogative.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800019#X00900"><p>The Senator should not be worried.  We will protect him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800019#X01000"><p>The Leader is <i>in situ</i>now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800019#X01100"><p>Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in referred to the confidence and supply agreement.  I welcome the fact that he is alarmed that there will be no election this year or next year.  In light of the uncertainty around Brexit, all of us are pleased that the country will continue to have a Government in place without the threat of an election.  This will allow us to bring Ireland forward.  Incomes are up, unemployment is at an all-time low, and there has been a decrease in the poverty and deprivation index for the fourth year in a row.  We have challenges to face in health and housing.  I hope we will see progress in that regard over the next 12 months.</p>  <p>I join Senators &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in and Byrne in hoping that the 2020 women in sport targets will be met.  We all welcome the fact that high levels of participation and interest in women's sport, and attendances at women's sporting events, have been achieved.  Women's sport in Ireland has reached an all-time high.  I commend our hockey team on its victory in the RT&Eacute; sports star awards at the weekend.  Many fine individual female sports stars have become role models as part of our sporting galaxy of stars.</p>  <p>I take the point made by Senator Conway-Walsh regarding auditing.  Believe it or not, I share her views on the CMA recommendations.  We need to hold auditing firms to account.  It cannot be just one or two firms that are held to account; everybody must be held to account.  There are people who signed off on accounts even though they should not have done so.  It is important to highlight this issue.</p>  <p>Senator Lawlor spoke about the payouts associated with soft tissue injuries.  The Minister of State, Deputy D'Arcy, has done considerable work on that.  I would be happy for him to come to the House in the new year.</p>  <p>I commend the people of Ballybay, who have shown their community spirit and their spirit of entrepreneurship to ensure the town is open for business this Christmas, as mentioned by Senator Gallagher.</p>  <p>I join Senator Byrne in welcoming the decision to award EU transport corridor status to Shannon Foynes Port Company.  I congratulate those involved.</p> <p>I welcome that the Shannon Foynes Port Company has been awarded EU transport corridor status today.  It is one of nine ports across Europe awarded this status.  Senator Byrne has been a champion of Shannon Foynes Port in this House and has raised issues for it on a number of occasions.  I thank the Senator for that.</p> <p>With regard to Senator Devine, we had better put our swords back in their scabbards for a minute.  The issue of nurses' pay has come to the fore again through the decision of a number of unions to engage in industrial action.  I certainly hope this can be avoided.  I made the point earlier that engagement is the way forward.  All of us recognise that we have recruited more nurses, we have restored the financial emergency measures in the public interest, FEMPI, cuts and that there is a need for all of us to work together.  The Department of Health will meet the oversight committee this week to further engage.  I certainly hope that industrial action can be avoided.  It does not help any situation and I do not see how nurses going on strike can benefit the health system.  I understand that they have a democratic right to engage in industrial action but I hope that all sides will engage properly and meaningfully in order that we can avoid that at all costs.</p> <p>Senator Gavan spoke of today being International Migrants Day.  I have given an answer to the Senator before on the issues he has raised.  I am a person who does not stand up for what the Senator has described here today.  There is a duty on all of us, at national and at European level, to ensure that our parties are part of groupings that promote human rights at all times.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.130" nospeaker="true" time="14:55:00" ><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.131" nospeaker="true" time="14:55:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 2.30 p.m. and resumed at 2.50 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.132" nospeaker="true" time="15:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800021#DD00100">Consumer Protection (Regulation of Credit Servicing Firms) Bill 2018: Committee Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.133" nospeaker="true" time="15:00:00" ><p>SECTION 1</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="15:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800021#DD00300"><p>Amendments Nos. 1 and 2 are related and may be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="15:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800021#DD00400"><p>I move amendment No. 1:</p><blockquote>In page 5, to delete lines 8 to 19.</blockquote><p>I welcome the Bill, which will contribute to the solution to address the scourge of vulture funds.  However, it is only part of the picture.  Even this part of the picture may be incomplete if we fail to undo the provision inserted by Fianna F&aacute;il in the D&aacute;il.  Fianna F&aacute;il has chosen to exclude securitisation vehicles from the scope of the Bill.  Either we are regulating all owners of credit or we are not.  We all know why this is an issue and we have seen it in the case of Permanent TSB and Glenbeigh.  The State-owned bank is selling the mortgages of over 6,000 people who are meeting their restructuring arrangements.  However, we do not know to whom.  We could not get to the bottom of this at the finance committee.  We do not know who is behind Glenbeigh, who benefits from it or anything else.  It is a structure established in recent weeks but the Bill, as amended by the D&aacute;il, will not regulate its owner at all.  The Bill will not regulate the likes of Glenbeigh.  While Pepper will be regulated, as is already the case, the owners, whoever they are, will remain unregulated.  We should close this regulation gap, not open another.  The Minister and Fianna F&aacute;il state that passive securitisation may still take place but I wonder how passive it feels for the 6,000 families doing their best to pay what has been agreed.  I continue to receive correspondence from people who have been paying their mortgages but who were suddenly given written notice that their mortgages had been handed over to Pepper.  The key question is whether the Minister believes Glenbeigh will be regulated if we accept the Bill as it stands.  If it will not be regulated, why is that the case?</p><p>In 2015, Sinn F&eacute;in proposed amendments which would have regulated the owners of the credit.  Fine Gael and the Labour Party opposed the amendments in question.  We are now back here over three years later and I want to ensure we do not have to return again.  The Glenbeigh deal represents a new low for Irish banks but it is also a new phenomenon to which we must respond.  Amendments Nos. 1 and 2 address the same issue which is to ensure all owners of credit, whoever they are and wherever they are, are regulated.  One should not be allowed to own mortgages in Ireland if one is not regulated regardless of what tax efficient structure is used.  That is what the amendments set out to achieve albeit it may well be that even if they are made, Glenbeigh will still be excluded.  It is not clear when the prospectus was signed off but it was dated 29 November 2018.</p> <p>Deputy Michael McGrath removed securitisation vehicles from the scope in July, so one would imagine it was taken into account.  I do not discount the possibility that even further deeper amendments are required to capture the owners of all mortgages.  The real test should be perhaps the economic interest, that is, who benefits from it.  If one is making money out of Irish mortgages, they should be regulated.  That is the bottom line.  I want to see this Bill doing that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1364" speakername="Michael D'Arcy" time="15:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800022#EE00300"><p>These two amendments are being taken together and they remove the definition of securitisation for special purpose entities and the provision that securitisation for special purpose entities was not included in the definition of credit servicing firms subject to certain conditions.</p><p>The second amendment also removes the provision that a person authorised to carry on the business of a credit servicing firm before the coming into operation of this Bill is taken to be authorised to carry on the business of a credit servicing firm after the enactment.  The effect of this provision is that an existing authorised credit servicing firm does not have to go through a new authorisation process when the new activities become regulated.  This mirrors a previous provision in the 2015 Act.  It is hard to see why it is necessary that an existing authorised firm would have to go through a further authorisation process.  The additional authorisation requirement would create an administrative burden for the existing credit servicing firms and for other firms authorised to perform credit servicing activities.  It would also create additional work for the Central Bank in the processing of these applications.</p><p>From an operational viewpoint it could delay implementation because it would mean that existing authorised credit servicing firms would not be authorised to hold legal title.  There is no transition provision, however, to allow them to do so pending the additional authorisation which will be required.</p><p>Furthermore, the traditional provision in section 2 of the Bill refers to section 28(4), which is proposed to be deleted by this amendment, but there is no amendment to this Part of the Bill.</p><p>In addition the proposed amendments do not do anything to the definition of &quot;retain on an ongoing basis a material net economic interest in the securitisation of not less than 5 per cent&quot;, even though the Part which uses this definition is proposed to be removed.  These are technical issues but are nonetheless important.</p><p>I turn now to the policy issue of securitisation.  This is an important and ongoing aspect of the international financial system and passive securitisation vehicles do not have any implications for consumer protection.  As the legislation is structured, there is a specific exclusion for passive securitisation vehicles where:</p><blockquote>(a) the securitisation special purpose entity was established by or on behalf of the owner of credit as part of the securitisation arranged by or on behalf of that owner of credit,<br /><br />(b) the owner of credit retains the legal title to the credit so assigned or otherwise disposed of, and<br /><br />(c) the originator, sponsor or original lender of the securitisation is required to retain on an ongoing basis a material net economic interest in the securitisation of not less than 5 per cent;</blockquote><p>Furthermore, the definition of securitisation special purpose entity means a corporation, trust or other entity:</p><blockquote>(a) established for the purpose of carrying out one or more securitisations,<br /><br />(b) the activities of which are limited to those appropriate to accomplishing that objective, and<br /><br />(c) the structure of which is intended to isolate the obligations of the securitisation special purpose entity from those of the originator.</blockquote><p>We have drawn these definitions from the European Securitisation Directive and are satisfied that this Bill will allow passive vehicles which do not interact directly or indirectly with the consumer to avoid the need for regulation, but once they get involved in any active way, they will need to be regulated.</p><p>The Central Bank publishes some numbers which show the size of this market.  The total outstanding stock of securitised loans for house purchase at the end of September 2018 was &euro;23.9 billion.  Total loans for house purchase, which includes both on-balance sheet and securitised mortgages, stood at &euro;100.5 billion at the end of September 2018, so this is a significant proportion of overall lending.</p> <p>Irish and European banks use securitisation as a matter of course to raise funds for on-lending to the real economy, the mortgage borrowers and small and medium enterprises, SMEs, which need access to credit.  If securitisation vehicles need to be authorised and regulated, a number of unintended consequences could arise.  In the most dramatic scenario, such vehicles could find it impossible to comply with the regulatory requirements of the Central Bank and therefore could be forced out of the market.  Alternatively, they would have to take on staff and premises and adopt structures to meet these requirements and the costs of this would be factored into the price that buyers would be willing to pay for securitisation, increasing costs which are likely to be passed to consumers.  Either way, there is likely to be disruption to a well-established business model which does not impact customers at the moment.</p> <p>We have given very careful consideration to the Bill&rsquo;s current provisions for securitisation and consulted with the Central Bank to avoid unintended consequences.  At the very least, the amendments would inhibit securitisations with real consequences for the real economy.  It is not in any way clear how the removal of the provision that existing credit servicing firms do not need to seek additional authorisation would work or what benefits would arise from it.  The amendment also contains a drafting inaccuracy in that it does not address the impact of the removal of the proposed section 28(4) in section 2 of the Bill.  For these reasons, we will not be supporting the amendments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="15:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800023#FF00200"><p>I call Senator Horkan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="15:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800023#FF00300"><p>If Senator Conway-Walsh wants to speak first, I will come in at some point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="15:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800023#FF00400"><p>Fianna F&aacute;il is on the side of Government.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="15:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800023#FF00500"><p>The Government is on our side.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="15:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800023#FF00600"><p>Confidence and supply.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="15:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800023#FF00700"><p>This is a Fianna F&aacute;il Bill.  I welcome that we discussed it last week.  I can see why somebody might table these amendments and it is quite emotive with Permanent TSB and so on.  These amendments are trying to remove the sections relating to passive securitisation where the ultimate investor plays no role in the administration of the loan used in that model.  The bank uses the model for good loans and the investor is simply looking for the cashflow from those loans.  The bank will continue to hold the legal title in most cases and will continue to administer the loans.  For the purposes of this legislation, the lender will be regulated and not the passive investor.</p>  <p>Amendment No. 1 removes the definition of a securitisation special purpose entity.  That definition is there to legislate for passive securitisation.  It is important, if the passive investor starts to become active, that he or she is covered by the Bill.  It is important that we realise that if banks do not reduce their non-performing loans, NPLs, to the ratios being looked for by the European Central Bank, ECB, the Single Supervisory Mechanism, SSM, and so on, then they will not be in a position to lend to the economy.  That is an unintended consequence as far as I am concerned in that they have too many NPLs on their books.  I might not agree with the definition of NPL but it is there and is what they have to stick to.  People are sticking to a restructured agreement but do not qualify as having a performing loan because of the definition of NPLs.  A high level of NPLs restricts the ability of banks to lend to the wider economy, to small businesses, to people buying homes and to people trying to improve their lives through borrowing in a sensible and measured way.  If the passive investor decides to make key decisions, then he or she is no longer passive and is covered by the Bill.  This is used extensively by many banks in Ireland.  Approximately a quarter of the European securitisation market is in Ireland, with over 1,000 staff working in this industry.  I am concerned that these amendments would have that effect.  The Minister outlined that there are some drafting errors in how the amendments are worded.  There is an idea that everybody who has already been regulated and certified would have to reapply and re-administer what they are already doing.  They are regulated and will be regulated by this Bill.  It is important that this Bill passes as quickly as possible.</p> <p>I take on board the concerns of the party that has proposed the amendments.  As a member of the party that brought the Bill forward, it is a step in the right direction, as Senator Conway-Walsh has acknowledged.  The sooner we get this done, the better.  If and when this happens, how soon can we get it to take effect?  When will it come into operation?  Passive securitisation is not covered but anything involving active participation is covered.  All of the credit servicing firms will be covered.  The people who owe money to the institutions will be covered.  All the people they are dealing with will be covered by the Bill.</p> <p>I ask Sinn F&eacute;in not to press the amendments because I would like the Bill to be enacted as soon as possible for the benefit of everybody dealing with credit servicing firms in Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="15:15:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800024#GG00200"><p>My concerns remain.  They are genuine concerns.  Can the Minister of State answer the question now about whether Glenbeigh will be regulated as part of this Bill?  Will it be regulated?  My understanding is it will not as part of the Bill.  We are leaving a loophole that will come back to bite us.  The fact it will be administratively over-burdensome should not be reason to fail to address that loophole.  We are trying to put the responsibility on the people who benefit from all of this.  We need to be careful in what we do.  I support the Bill but we would be failing in our duty as the main Opposition party if we were not to point out the loophole.  I cannot see the difference between the securitisation and the selling off to vulture funds.  There is a six-month period but the end result is the same.  The end result will not be any different.  I refer to the machinations in terms of the different levels of companies and organisations that are involved in all of this.  At the end of the day, we have responsible homeowners, particularly the 6,000 we talked about in connection with PTSB whose mortgages are being sold off, and they are losing out.  We are doing it so we can make the banks look better in all of this yet we have a company that is one step removed.  We do not know who the owner is.  We do not know where the owner is based.  We know nothing about the owner yet we are leaving the loophole there which means he or she will not be held to account and that is concerning.  I do not know if there is another route we can go down.  We do not want to stop the Bill going through.  I ask the Minister of State's advice on how this loophole can be addressed.  I put on record the concern of the Sinn F&eacute;in Party about leaving things the way they are for Glenbeigh and its likes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="15:15:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800024#GG00300"><p>Senator Conway-Walsh did not address my concern that if we do not allow the banks to do some of this work and reduce their NPLs, we are restricting the amount available in the economy which can be lent to businesses and homeowners or people looking to buy houses.  It is important that we acknowledge that whoever is calling the shots is regulated under the Bill.  If passive investors decide they want to start calling the shots or become active in any way in calling the shots, they are regulated.  The regulation will apply to those calling the shots and those looking at the loans, examining how the loans need to be satisfied and paid off and so on.  This is what the Bill is trying to do.  We are trying to get regulation of the credit servicing firms that are dealing with borrowers who in some cases are in distress.</p> <p>We are trying to ensure that happens as soon as possible.  If anybody who is a passive investor gets involved and starts calling the shots, they are regulated.  Some 24% of the European securitisation market is in Ireland with 1,100 people in processing jobs.  Securitisation is much more than just Permanent TSB.  It incorporates a broad set of financial measures and products.  We are all concerned that the people are being regulated and that those, who are dealing with mortgage owners and people who have borrowed money, are regulated; that is the purpose of the Bill.</p> <p>I know Sinn F&eacute;in supports it as does the Government, for which I thank them.  It is important that we get the Bill passed.  It is somewhat of a red herring to suggest that the passive investors can make decisions.  They cannot and that is why they are passive investors.  As soon as they stop becoming passive investors, they will be regulated by the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="15:20:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800025#HH00200"><p>The high level of NPLs should not be used as an excuse.  The Senator is bringing the NPLs into it.  It should not be to reduce customers' rights.  The Bill was sold to us as covering the owners of the credit and it is not doing that, which is what really concerns me.  Credit servicing firms are already covered and this is what is confusing about the Bill.  As what the Senator is describing is already the case, what is the Bill supposed to be regulating if it is not regulating the owners?  The owners are the people behind the scenes.  When the Senator says that as soon as they become active they are not passive any more and then they are regulated, how do we know how active they really are?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="15:20:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800025#HH00300"><p>The Central Bank monitors it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="15:20:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800025#HH00400"><p>I am coming to this from a very genuine position.  I feel there are loopholes in it.  While people somehow believe this Bill will be the salvation of the selling off of mortgages to vulture funds and all that, I do not think it will do that.  It will leave gaping holes that will expose consumers and mortgage holders in the same way as they have been heretofore.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1364" speakername="Michael D'Arcy" time="15:20:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800025#HH00500"><p>Nobody questions anybody's bona fides on this issue.  The question is fair.  The Bill was not designed to regulate private equity funds.  Currently regulated by law are the agents, the credit-servicing firms.  Deputy Michael McGrath presented this Bill and the Department of Finance and others participated in a very collegiate way to try to do the best we can for these structures.</p>  <p>We have concluded that anybody who is participating is regulated.  A private equity fund that wants its money out in four years is regulated.  It is as simple as that.  It is one direction; they are now regulated.  Investors, who have others investing their money for them in a securitisation structure and have no further input apart from investing, are not regulated and will not be regulated.  They were not meant to be regulated.</p>  <p>It is not a question of a gaping hole.  It is a question of it doing what we wanted it to do, which was to regulate private equity funds that stand above the credit-servicing firm, which is the agent for the private equity fund and takes instruction from the fund and they are not passive.  Everything else that is passive - any other investor - is not regulated.</p>  <p>I am advising Seanad &Eacute;ireann that proceeding with this amendment would be a mistake.  There are other unintended consequences.  I will give another example.  If we require a person who is an investor in a securitisation structure to be regulated, he or she may not be able to invest not just here but in other areas of securitisation because he or she may not have an entity here but may simply provide capital to make an investment.</p> <p>If this is passed and if they are regulated, they will need staff and structures here, and they will need their entity based here, which many of them do not do and have no intention of doing.  That is the unintended consequence.  I accept the Senator's bona fides in questioning the matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="15:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800026#JJ00200"><p>I regret there is no Report Stage to tease this out properly because it warrants further discussion.  Securitisation is a loan sale through the back door.  It has the same impact on the consumer as a loan sale.  I have a feeling we will be discussing this in another forum but, as there is no Report Stage, I will withdraw the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.155" nospeaker="true" time="15:25:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.156" nospeaker="true" time="15:25:00" ><p>Amendment No. 2 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.157" nospeaker="true" time="15:25:00" ><p>Section 1 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.158" nospeaker="true" time="15:25:00" ><p>Sections 2 and 3 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.159" nospeaker="true" time="15:25:00" ><p>Title agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.160" nospeaker="true" time="15:25:00" ><p>Bill reported without amendment and received for final consideration.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.161" nospeaker="true" time="15:25:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That the Bill do now pass."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1364" speakername="Michael D'Arcy" time="15:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800026#JJ00900"><p>It is my intention the Bill will be commenced as soon as possible upon enactment, most likely in January of next year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="15:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800026#JJ01000"><p>I thank the Sinn F&eacute;in Party and Senator Conway-Walsh for their co-operation.  I also thank all other parties, the Department of Finance, the officials and the Ministers.  Deputy Michael McGrath has been looking for this for a very long time and has done all the work on it.  I am just making sure, as the party spokesperson on finance here, that it gets through the House as quickly as possible.  I thank the Minister of State for his responses and I thank all who participated.  I am looking forward to it being enacted as early as possible, hopefully in January, as the Minister of State outlined.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.164" nospeaker="true" time="15:25:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.165" nospeaker="true" time="15:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800026#JJ01100">Finance (African Development (Bank and Fund) and Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill 2018: Second Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.166" nospeaker="true" time="15:25:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That the Bill be now read a Second Time."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1364" speakername="Michael D'Arcy" time="15:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800026#JJ01300"><p>The Bill, if approved by the Oireachtas, will facilitate Ireland&rsquo;s future membership of both the African Development Bank and African Development Fund.  The Bill will provide for the approval of the agreement establishing the African Development Bank and the agreement establishing the African Development Fund, and for the payments to be made to the bank and fund, respectively.  Additionally, it serves to amend the International Finance Corporation Act 1958 and section 851A of the Taxes Consolidation Act 1997, respectively.</p>  <p>Most significantly, completion of Ireland&rsquo;s membership of the bank and fund will require the ratification of international agreements represented by the agreement establishing the African Development Bank and the agreement establishing the African Development Fund.  Membership shall also entail Ireland making capital payments to both the bank and fund.</p> <p>Article 29.5 of the Constitution provides, among other things, that &quot;the State shall not be bound by any international agreement involving a charge upon public funds unless the terms of the agreement shall have been approved by D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann&quot;.  The enactment of the Bill would confirm such approval.  Similar requirements applied when Ireland joined other international financial institutions such as the World Bank and, most recently, the Asian Infrastructure Investment Bank.<br/><br/>The mission of the African Development Bank and Fund is to reduce poverty, improve living conditions and mobilise resources for the continent's economic and social development.  Providing resources, advice and assistance to its regional member countries, the bank and fund will make a significant contribution to the improvement of the quality of lives in Africa.<br/><br/>The key driver in Ireland's seeking membership of the bank and the fund has been the bank's alignment and objectives with Ireland's development priorities.  While membership may enhance our relationship with the wider African economy, the primary motivation of joining is from a development perspective, in particular the focus of the bank in the areas of climate change, agriculture and nutrition, fragile states and jobs and economic development align closely with priority areas for action identified in Ireland's current international development policy.  Moreover the cross-cutting gender lens that the bank applies to its operations particularly resonates with development ambition for equality.  Ireland has had a long and positive relationship with Africa.  Strong links were built through the development work of aid workers, missionaries and the effectiveness of our aid programme.<br/><br/>Membership will reinforce and enrich our engagement and relationship with the region and its people.  Membership of the bank and fund will also be consistent with the priorities set out in the recently launched Global Ireland initiative, which seeks to double the scope and impact of Ireland's global footprint across the next seven years, in particular with regard to extending our influence in Africa.<br/><br/>As Senators will be aware, Ireland is in the process of developing a new international development policy to take account of the significantly evolving international development context.  Given the increasing interconnectedness and scale of the international agenda, the co-ordination of efforts and the combining of resources will be increasingly important. Hence, our partnership with multilateral institutions will be a key part of our approach.<br/><br/>Ireland's membership of the bank and the fund is consistent with our commitment to the UN 2030 agenda for sustainable development and, therefore, our membership of the bank and fund will be consistent with the whole-of-Government approach to implementing the sustainable development goals.  Finally, our membership will provide an opportunity for us to deepen trade relations with the African through creating opportunities for Irish businesses to tender for the delivery of bank and fund projects and services.  While this potential dividend is welcome, I would like to unambiguously state that Ireland's commitment to united aid remains unchanged with no strings or <i>quid pro quo </i>arrangements attached to this development contribution.<br/><br/>The operations of the bank and fund are underpinned by corporate strategy.  The African Development Bank's strategy for 2013 to 2022 focuses on two objectives: improving the quality of Africa's growth and facilitating inclusive growth and the transition to green growth.  In turn, the delivery of this work is to be achieved through five channels: infrastructure development, regional economic integration, private sector development, governance and accountability, and skills and technology.  These areas are in line with our own international development policy.  The bank and fund finances a wide range of projects and programmes covering areas such as health, education, agriculture, public utilities, transport and telecommunications and the private sector.  Furthermore, the bank finances non-project operations, including structural adjustment loans, policy-based reforms and various forms of technical assistance.<br/><br/>Regarding performance, the bank and fund has a strong record.  The success of the bank in delivering results for Africa has been recognised by the Multilateral Organization Performance Assessment Network, MOPAN, which is a network of like-minded donor countries that monitors the performance of multilateral development organisations and of which Ireland is a member.  A recent assessment from the network, which was conducted in 2016, concluded that &quot;the Bank is a robust and resilient organisation that, while operating in a particularly difficult environment, is able to continually adjust and improve to meet the changing conditions&quot;.  The bank and fund's financial resources are largely derived from subscriptions paid by member countries.</p> <p>The authorised capital stock of the bank is approximately &euro;79 billion, with approximately &euro;6 billion of paid-in capital.  In addition to member countries' subscriptions, like other multilateral development banks the bank raises capital on international markets at competitive rates through maintaining its AAA rating.  In the year 2017 we saw total disbursements peaking at approximately &euro;6.6 billion, with project approvals amounting to approximately &euro;7.5 billion across 249 operations.</p> <p>The bank and fund currently have 80 member countries, made up of 54 regional member countries, and 26 non-regional member countries, largely comprised of countries from Europe, America and Asia.  Non-regional member countries account for approximately 40% of the total shares and 40% of the total voting power at the bank.  On the basis of the terms offered by the bank, it is intended that Ireland will acquire 53,620 shares, equivalent to 0.799% of the bank&rsquo;s total shareholding, which is in the region of the shareholding held by Belgium and the Netherlands. which hold 0.65% and 0.8% of total shareholding, respectively.</p> <p>Ireland, like all other member countries of the bank, will be represented on the board of governors, which is the bank&rsquo;s highest decision making body.  As is the case at each of the other international financial institutions of which Ireland is a member, the Minister for Finance will be governor for Ireland.  The board of governors meets formally once a year for the bank&rsquo;s annual meeting and is responsible for electing the president, who is elected for a five-year term, once renewable.  The current president is Mr. Akinwumi Adesina, formerly Nigeria&rsquo;s Minister of Agriculture and Rural Development, who was elected as eighth president of the bank in May 2015.  Additionally, through our constituency membership Ireland will be represented at the board of directors, which is responsible for the bank&rsquo;s general operations.  The board of directors comprises 20 members who are neither governors nor alternate governors.  Thirteen members are elected by the governors of regional countries and seven by the governors of non-regional member countries.  Directors are elected for a term of three years renewable once.  The non-regional representation at board level is broken up into seven constituencies, four of which are led by EU member countries.  Negotiations regarding the constituency which Ireland will join following membership are ongoing.</p> <p>Subject to the passage of this Bill, and the completion of our membership application, it is intended that Ireland will acquire 53,620 shares, equivalent to 0.799% of the bank&rsquo;s total shareholding.  On this basis, the expected cost of Ireland&rsquo;s membership of the bank and fund will be approximately &euro;99.8 million, payable over eight years, or approximately &euro;12.4 million per annum, depending on prevailing exchange rates.  This is comprised of two components; first the paid-in capital associated with our proposed bank shareholding of approximately &euro;37.8 million or &euro;4.7 million annually; and second, our subscription to the fund in the order of &euro;62 million to be encashed in up to eight annual instalments amounting to approximately &euro;7.7 million annually.</p> <p>In capital terms, this shareholding in the bank equates to a capital allocation of approximately &euro;630 million, made up of &euro;37.8 million paid-in capital, with the remainder of the allocation, &euro;592.2 million comprising callable capital.  The callable capital element represents the capital which Ireland would be liable for if the institution encountered acute financial distress, while the paid-in capital element is the amount which we would contribute under normal circumstances.  </p> <p>Based on Ireland&rsquo;s experience with international financial institutions of which we are already a member, the probability of the callable capital being called upon is negligible.</p> <p>As is the case with our membership of other international financial institutions, Ireland&rsquo;s contributions to the bank and fund would be sourced from the Central Fund, with payments to be provided for in the legislation.  In accordance with OECD guidelines, our contribution to both the bank and fund will be reckonable in respect of the calculation of Ireland&rsquo;s overseas development assistance, ODA.</p> <p>I will now turn to the specific provisions of the six sections of the Bill.  Section 1 deals with the Short Title of the Bill.  Section 2 sets out the definitions used in the Bill.  Section 3 provides for the approval of the agreement establishing the bank, thereby enabling the State to be party to the agreement.  The agreement establishing the bank is in the Schedule to the Bill.  Section 4 makes provision for payments and receipts under the terms of the agreement establishing the bank.  Section 5 provides for the approval of the agreement establishing the fund, thereby enabling the State to be party to the agreement.  The agreement establishing the fund is in the Schedule to the Bill.  Section 6 makes provision for payments and receipts under the terms of the agreement establishing the fund.</p> <p> Section 7 provides for the amendment of the International Finance Corporation Act, which governs Ireland's relationship with the International Finance Corporation, IFC, a sister organisation of the World Bank involved in encouraging private sector development in developing countries.  The amendment will allow changes in the IFC's articles of agreement to be approved by way of D&aacute;il resolution rather than by primary legislation.  This will alleviate the legislative burden associated with Ireland's participation in the IFC and bring the legislation in line with that governing Ireland's membership of other international financial institutions, including the provisions now proposed in respect of the African Development Bank.</p> <p>Section 8 makes provision for amendment to section 851A of the Taxes Consolidation Act 1997, which relates to the confidentiality of taxpayer information, and will address a conflict between the legislative provisions of section 851A and those of the Freedom of Information Act.  This anomaly currently prevents the Department of Finance from providing records to the Office of the Information Commissioner, even when it is statutorily required to do so in the context of the operation of freedom of information legislation.  The proposed amendment to section 851A should address this legislative conflict and remove this anomaly.  It will ensure that the requisite records can be provided to the Information Commissioner in order that he can conduct his review and fulfil his statutory function without further delay.</p> <p>I strongly encourage Senators to support the Bill and Ireland's membership of the bank and fund.  I commend the Bill to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="15:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800029#MM00200"><p>Group spokespersons have eight minutes and all other Senators have five.  We will start with Senator Horkan.  He has eight minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="15:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800029#MM00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State for outlining, very comprehensively, what is proposed in the Finance (African Development (Bank and Fund) and Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill 2018.  I have quite a long set of briefing notes here but they are very much in line with what the Minister of State said.</p>  <p>This is a very important Bill, which my party supports.  In ways, it is quite similar the Asian Infrastructure Investment Bank Act 2017.  The overarching objective of the bank is to spur sustainable economic development and social progress in its regional member countries, thus contributing to poverty reduction.  In many ways, the development bank is similar to the European Investment Bank, with which we are more familiar.  The bank gets its money from the members' subscriptions and lends it out to projects.  The Minister of State has outlined that it is quite a sizeable organisation in terms of the amount of money invested, the capital stock being &euro;79 billion, with disbursements in 2017 peaking at &euro;6.6 billion for project approvals, amounting to &euro;7.5 billion across 249 operations.</p>  <p>There is also the African Development Fund, which is a concessional window of the African Development Bank Group established in 1972 and operational since 1974.  Administered by the bank, it has 32 contributing countries, benefits 38 countries and has cumulatively invested $45 billion over its 44 years of operation in Africa.  This is important as some people may ask why Ireland would get involved in this.  Investing in these institutions will reinforce our political, developmental, economic, trade and cultural relationships with Africa.</p>  <p>From a trade and economic perspective, Africa represents a growing market for Irish businesses.  Exports to Algeria increased to over &euro;100 million in 2017, to Nigeria to &euro;279 million and to South Africa to &euro;243 million.  Imports have also grown in recent years.  A growing and prosperous Africa will give rise to better business opportunities for Irish businesses.  I do not want to talk about Brexit all the time, but in the context of markets other than the UK, Africa is certainly there and we should look at it as a market for our products and indeed a source of raw material and products that we may want to buy.</p>  <p>Ireland has a long and proud history of missionary work in Africa, in which our various NGOs have been involved over the years.  I will not list them all but I refer to the likes of GOAL, Gorta, Tr&oacute;caire and everyone who has been involved in these organisations and indeed the religious orders, such as the Christian Brothers, which went to Africa and provided much education there over the years.</p>  <p>I do not want to delay by repeating almost all of what the Minister of State said.  My party will support the Bill.  We are in favour of it.  It is a good idea to be involved with the African continent and to try to promote its development and the reduction and eradication of poverty over time.  Whatever this bank can do, Ireland will play a small part in its overall operation.</p> <p>I support the passing of this legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.174" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1374" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="15:50:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800030#NN00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1364" speakername="Michael D'Arcy" time="15:50:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800030#NN00300"><p>I am here a lot.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1374" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="15:50:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800030#NN00400"><p>Too much for the Minister of State's own good.  The Bill has humanitarian and strategic aspects for Ireland.  It is important that we be involved in these projects worldwide.  In fact, this is probably long overdue.  Ireland will be one of 80 member countries of this body and it is important that we be seen to be operating on the global stage.  I welcome this.  Obviously, we will be a non-regional member.  Non-regional members will account for 40% of total shares and 40% of total voting power.  Are votes done via qualified majority?  How does that system work?  Our contribution, which will be in the order of &euro;12.4 million annually, will amount to just under &euro;100 million over an eight-year period.  Does that count towards our percentage spend on overseas aid?  This is a technical point, but it is important in view of the fact that we are trying to increase our metric.  All areas of spending should be covered by it.</p>  <p>The accountant is coming out in me so, in the interests of prudence, the callable capital element looks very structured financially.  In terms of our country carrying out some form of due diligence on the finances annually, is there a mechanism for us to peruse how the development fund and bank perform?  Will our Central Bank and-or the Department of Finance examine the figures to ensure there is a prudent eye on behalf of the &euro;100 million of Irish taxpayers' money that is going into this?  It is a worthwhile cause, but it is still taxpayers' money that we are spending, so there must be an element of prudence and probity.  That is the case regardless of the level of spending and is often missed in discussions.  This is the money of the worker and of the person on social welfare who is buying goods and paying VAT, so it must be accounted for when spent.  It is coming full circle.</p>  <p>I welcome this measure.  Are we taking all Stages?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.177" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="15:50:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800030#NN00500"><p>We are taking Second Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1374" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="15:50:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800030#NN00600"><p>I would have thought we could have dealt with all Stages today.  Perhaps the Minister of State will indicate when he anticipates that the Bill will be enacted and whether it will be implemented in its totality or via commencement order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.179" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="15:50:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800030#NN00700"><p>Sinn F&eacute;in supports the Bill.  It is right that Ireland should play a part in supporting development in Africa.  A different model is needed than that of the old foreign development aid, which tended to extract as much from African countries as it gave.</p>  <p>I note that most of the money given out by the African Development Bank is for key infrastructure such as roads, water supplies and communications.  There are parts of Africa where such infrastructure is desperately needed.  In the briefing note, the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade makes reference to the opportunities for Irish companies to take part in the development projects in Africa as a result of our membership of the African Development Bank.  We should be members of it on its own merit.  Hundreds of years of colonisation have left many parts of Africa severely underdeveloped.</p> <p>A cruel irony is that many of the parts of the continent experience the worst affects of climate change as well.  There is need for development capital to invest in renewable energy.  I note that during the debate in the Seanad on the Asian Infrastructure Investment Bank Bill 2017, serious questions were raised about human rights abuses in member countries of that bank.  I share the same concerns regarding this Bill and I hope that through regular appearances by the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Foreign Affairs at the Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs and Trade, and Defence and the Joint Committee on Finance, Public Expenditure and Reform, and Taoiseach, we can address any concerns in this regard.</p> <p>Ireland's contribution of &euro;62 million is small both from the perspective of our budget and the budget of the bank, with the eight instalments amounting to approximately &euro;8 million per annum for participation in the fund.  There is a paid-up contribution of in the region of &euro;37.8 million for membership of the bank, which is also payable over eight years and amounts to approximately &euro;4.7 million per annum.  The first instalment is to be paid on enactment of this Bill.  We need, therefore, to give the Bill full scrutiny.  In Ireland's case, the maximum capital under the agreement would amount to less than &euro;600 million.  While it is highly unlikely that this amount would ever be called upon, we should treat this Bill and its enactment as if it were a possibility.  </p> <p>Does the Minister propose to request that the annual report of the fund or the bank be laid before the Houses of the Oireachtas?  We should also consider the connected issue of Ireland's overall aid commitment to developing countries.  We still have a journey ahead of us to meet our overseas development aid obligations.  The recent report of the Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs and Trade, and Defence indicates that for Ireland to reach the 0.7% target by 2030 the overall aid programme needs to grow from &euro;707 million to &euro;2.5 billion or an increase of &euro;150 million per annum over the period, which amounts to an increase of approximately &euro;1.8 billion.</p> <p>Budget 2019 announced on 9 October provides an additional &euro;110 million for 2019.  The Government is, therefore, falling short in respect of what our trajectory should be.  The State's GDP is distorted but there are times, such as when meeting our fiscal targets, that this plays to our advantage.  We are still a long way from reaching our overseas development aid obligations.  There must be a clear trajectory and a roadmap from Government on how it proposes to do this.  It should be separated from the budgetary process to make it clear internationally that we stand by our commitments and that we meet them.  </p> <p>My colleague, Deputy Pearse Doherty, raised concern that a large portion of contributions to the development bank can be counted as overseas development aid.  What percentage will be counted?  We have to ensure that in investing, as provided for in this Bill, we are not double counting the money and claiming it is a donation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.181" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="15:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800031#OO00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House.  In principle, I support this Bill.  As others have said, we have previously discussed the relationship between Ireland and many African countries.  Africa is a young continent.  As many of the new approaches to development that are going to come out of countries of Africa will shape much of the next millennium, it is appropriate that the State engages in partnership with them.  I have concerns regarding how this Bill and our participation in the African Development Bank and Fund, which itself is positive, intersects with our other areas of partnership.  I am concerned to ensure that, for example, our contribution to participation in the African Development Bank and Fund will in no way be seen as contributing to or marked against our commitments in terms of international development funding.  That is important because in terms of our aid budget, Ireland has a strong record of untied aid.  We have won respect internationally because we have not, as many other countries have, attached conditionalities and commercial benefit for ourselves to our aid budget but have instead worked to ensure that the money which Ireland gives in aid is targeted at the most vulnerable.  For example, we work with Governments to ensure the education, health and front-line services are improved.  We have a strong record through our aid programme of supporting civil society such that it is civil society in the different countries of the African continent that is strengthened and able to hold Government to account in that regard.</p> <p> The Minister of State said that our international development policy is being reviewed and in that context.  I seek assurances that this financing, which has a very different approach and a very different set of conditions, will not be cited as a rationale for us not working to achieve the 0.7% goal in the context of our aid commitments.  This is different because it is in an investment framework and is not the same as aid.</p> <p>In terms of conditionality and the question of untied aid, one investor that has had a poor record in terms of the conditionalities that were attached to countries in the past is the World Bank.  I note the change to the Bill that was made in the D&aacute;il with regard to Ireland's participation in international finance co-operation which means that we are moving to a situation whereby our engagement with the World Bank could now be done via a motion in the D&aacute;il rather than by way of the legislative process.  This means that those of us in the Upper House will potentially have no opportunity to engage on any changes in policy.  That is a matter of concern because while the World Bank's recent research has taken it in a much more positive direction, it has had a very poor record of imposing conditions and development models on developing countries that have proved very damaging.  That has been shown by the bank's own research.  In that regard, I have some concern that we may not have the opportunity to engage on these matters in the future.  I ask the Minister of State to reassure me that we will have the opportunity to debate and discuss the way that Ireland engages with other investors such as the World Bank because I fear that such opportunities may be diminished by this Bill.</p> <p>The Minister of State talked about public investment and again, the devil really is in the detail.  Are we talking about investment in roads, water and infrastructure?  This is also where conditionality is important because in the past, particularly in the case of the IMF, we have seen conditions attached whereby investment must be done by private corporations.  There is a real potential for tension, as we saw with regard to water in this country and the debates around that.  In the context of sustainable development goals, we must ensure that there is flexibility for African governments to respond to civil society.  We must also ensure that they are accountable to their people for the way they deliver infrastructure and not just accountable to investors.  That space is important.  These are important principles which Ireland has always supported and I want to ensure that we do not slip away from them.  Our role in the context of governance is also important.</p> <p>I have a very specific concern with regard to fossil fuel divestment.  Under the provisions of the Fossil Fuel Divestment Bill, we must be satisfied on reasonable grounds that any indirect investment in which we engage, as per this Bill, is unlikely to have an excess of 15% of its assets invested in fossil fuel undertakings.  I am sure the Minister of State will be keen to satisfy this House that the African Development Bank and our investment in it is not compromised and satisfies the 15% condition.  Concerns around human rights have also been mentioned and I would like to add to them.  We know that a number of Irish companies are involved in the extractive industries and we must ensure, in line with our business and human rights policies, that the best practices are promoted.</p> <p>We want to ensure that best practices are promoted in line with our business and human rights policy.  For example a complaint has been made against San Leon Energy regarding its proposed extractive work in Western Sahara, an area in which there is currently not an actor who can agree to the work.  It therefore cannot satisfy the UN requirement that an authorised, recognised party engage in local consultation in respect of that extractive practice.  This is key because this is an Irish company.  It is the kind of Irish company that may potentially come looking for investment from the African Development Bank.  What are the safeguards in that regard?  What will Ireland's role be?  How does the Minister of State see human rights and the environment being safeguarded?  I thank the Minister of State for all of that.</p> <p>My last question is related.  The Minister of State has discussed green bonds and Ireland's recent sale of same in the House on a couple of occasions.  Will he commit to coming to the House and having a longer discussion on green bonds at a later stage, perhaps in January?  It is an important issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.184" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="16:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800033#QQ00200"><p>Before I call on the next Senator, I welcome Col&aacute;iste Bhaile Chl&aacute;ir, Claregalway College, and Ms Paula McDonagh, who are guests of Deputy Anne Rabbitte.  They are very welcome.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.185" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1438" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="16:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800033#QQ00300"><p>Like previous speakers, I welcome the Bill.  I have a couple of queries regarding Irish Aid.  Will the 0.7% be included in the current budget?  Will the Minister of State identify from where the funding for our membership of the organisation and for the various payments to be made to it over the eight years in the context of our full subscription will come?</p>  <p>There is one thing that always makes me nervous about vehicles of the sort proposed in the legislation.  The Bill digest states, "the overall objective and purpose of the Bank Group is to contribute to the sustainable economic development and social progress of its regional (African) members individually and jointly."  One often wonders whether an analysis has been done since the bank was established in 1962 as to whether this objective has been achieved or as to whether it is still one of the bank's objectives.  As far as many people are concerned, it has not achieved this objective.</p>  <p>I have a question about the bank and about those to whom it lends.  I was in Benin and saw a small credit union being set up.  I was fascinated by how whatever money was available was being lent at a very basic level.  It was all being lent to women who were operating within their own co-operative and lending money to one another.  The money was being used to set up small sustainable industries.  Money raised was used to educate their children.  To my mind, that is a very sustainable way of doing things.  I get concerned about big banks coming in and about whether they look at the sustainability of what they are trying to achieve.  Is there an opportunity for a farmer, either male or female, to access this to add value to his or her product?  Is funding available for small groups in communities to create their own industries so that they can send their children to school for further education?  That would be sustainable in the long term.</p>  <p>I have a concern that governments will end up deciding where the funding is going.  As we have seen in our own Irish Aid budget, when money is allocated to the general budget, there can be difficulties in the context of accountability.  Do we know it is going where it is supposed to be going?  I have always worked on trying to get African parliamentarians to discover where the money actually goes in their countries.  They find it extremely difficult to do so.</p> <p>Do African parliamentarians have access to the kind of scrutiny we have here to enable them to follow the money trail when they are examining where the money from the African Development Bank is going?  I suggest we should look at supporting an equivalent body to our own Committee of Public Accounts in African Parliaments to enable them to follow the money trail when money is being borrowed for public purposes.  The idea of providing sustainable sources of funding for African states is very important.  I believe the initial cost is small in comparison with the call.  Since 1962, there has never been a call on the funds that states have to provide.  I am disappointed that more countries are not involved in the African Development Bank.  We do not see countries in eastern Europe-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.187" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="16:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800034#RR00200"><p>The Senator has half a minute remaining.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1438" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="16:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800034#RR00300"><p>I thank the Chair for the warning.  It is possible that I will be the last person to speak.  It is disappointing that many countries in eastern Europe and the Middle East are not involved in the African Development Bank.  Other sources of funding could be used to broaden the scope of the funds in the bank.  Overall, I am supportive of this initiative.  Maybe the Minister of State can respond to the couple of queries I have outlined.  I am happy to see that we are eventually participating in this fund, almost 50 years after it came into existence.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.189" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1364" speakername="Michael D'Arcy" time="16:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800034#RR00400"><p>I assure Senator Higgins that I would be happy to address the matter of sovereign green bonds at any stage.  It is a question of when this House can facilitate me.  If there are any questions that I do not answer in these remarks, I will try to answer them on Committee and Report Stages.  The  African Development Bank and the African Development Fund make an important contribution to the improvement of the quality of lives in Africa.  This is the primary driver for our ambition to become a member of the bank and to participate in the fund.  Membership is consistent with the goals of Ireland's development policy.  I have no doubt that it will add to our long and proud development tradition of investing in Africa and investing in people.</p>  <p>Although membership may create new opportunities for Irish businesses - for example, to tender for the delivery of bank and fund projects and services - I reiterate that Ireland's commitment to untied aid remains unchanged.  We will be active members of the banking fund when we join it.  We will contribute to the discourse in the bank and the fund on policy, resource allocation, governance and such matters.  However, no restrictive conditions will be attached to our subscription.  The importance Ireland places on ensuring its operations are held to account against robust standards in human rights, social and environmental standards, gender equality and governance issues is central to our engagement with the bank and the fund.  In this regard, I am advised that the bank has strong operational frameworks and standards in place.  Of particular note is the bank's integrated safeguards system, which is the cornerstone of its strategy to promote growth that is socially inclusive and environmentally sustainable.  I am advised that the bank has operational safeguards and mechanisms in place to make sure vulnerable populations and the environment are not harmed by its projects.  I understand that these independent review mechanisms cover adverse impacts on the environment, society, labour conditions, health and safety, involuntary resettlement, biodiversity of ecosystems, pollution prevention, the control of hazardous materials and resource efficiencies.</p>  <p>From an accountability perspective, the bank's governance structures ensure there is transparency.  Its operations are open to the scrutiny of its members.  When Ireland joins the bank, it will be represented on the board of governors, which is the bank's highest decision-making body.  Through our constituency membership, we will be represented on the board of directors, which is responsible for the bank's general operations.  This will give Ireland ongoing access to channels of communication regarding the work of the bank and the fund and will enable Ireland to make an input into the decision-making process.  Another point of discussion which has emerged during the debates on the Bill to date relates to reporting arrangements in the Oireachtas.  I am sure the Minister will give full consideration to the views Senators and Deputies have expressed on Ireland's prospective membership of the bank of the fund and Ireland's dealings with international financial institutions more generally.</p> <p>I thank the Senators for engaging with their time in this legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.191" nospeaker="true" time="16:15:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.192" nospeaker="true" time="16:15:00" ><p>Committee Stage ordered for Thursday, 20 December 2018.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.193" nospeaker="true" time="16:15:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800035#SS00600">Social Welfare, Pensions and Civil Registration Bill 2018: Report and Final Stages</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.194" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="16:15:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800035#SS00800"><p>Amendment No. 1 has been ruled out of order as not being relevant to the subject matter of the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.195" nospeaker="true" time="16:15:00" ><p>Amendment No. 1 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.196" nospeaker="true" time="16:15:00" ><p>Bill recommitted in respect of amendments Nos. 2 and 3.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="16:15:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800035#SS00900"><p>I move amendment No. 2:</p><blockquote>In page 11, between lines 19 and 20, to insert the following:&ldquo;(2) The Minister shall, within six months of the passing of this Act, prepare and lay before the Houses of the Oireachtas, a report to include&mdash;<blockquote>(a) an estimation of the potential cost of calculating this scheme on the basis of 1,560 contributions rather than 2,080, and<br /><br />(b) a comparison of the likely difference between a 1,560 contributory requirement and a 2,080 in terms of weekly income levels for those affected.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote><p>This amendment is in respect of the 2012 changes that were made relating to the pension payments and the ongoing issues that the averaging system has caused in disadvantaging people, especially women.  This has resulted in many people being on a reduced rate despite high levels of contributions over the years.  There was much to welcome in the new proposals in respect of the 2012 changes, and I have welcomed those, but my key concern is that while the proposals in the new scheme for those pensioners address the issue of the gap by offering a preview of a total contribution approach that could be taken, the gap is addressed but the goalposts are pushed out.  While the system for calculating the contributions required may in fact prove to be fairer in many respects, and men and women who are affected can opt for previous ongoing system or for this new system, I am concerned at the decision to frame it not in terms of a 30-year contribution but in terms of a 40-year contribution.  Currently it is the case that 20 years is required to deliver a full pension.  We know that under the averaging system, it can be only ten-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.198" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="16:15:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800035#SS01000"><p>It is ten.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.199" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="16:15:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800035#SS01100"><p>It is only ten.  It can be accessed at ten years of credits but I had raised this issue previously with one of the Minister's officials and was told that technically it is 20, but it can be accessed at ten years of credits.  In any case, the current situation means that we knew in 2010 and from the 2010 pension proposals that there was a plan to move towards a total contribution approach of 30 years, which would require a total of 30 years' contributions.   In relation to this cohort we now have for the first time on the books a situation where people's pensions are calculated on the basis of 40 years' contribution.  I recognise that within that people can count carer credits.  I am concerned at the decision under this new scheme to set the bar at 40 years of contributions, rather than 30 years.</p> <p>I am worried about the signal that might send in terms of the intention in respect of the total contribution approach.  As we have heard from officials, no final decision has been made in respect of what the total contribution approach will look like.  The Minister will be aware that submissions from the Irish Congress of Trade Unions and many others have expressed concern at any attempt to move beyond the expected 30 year contributory threshold.  I am concerned about the example being set in going for 40 years in this instance.  This report is to provide an estimation and an example for us to look back on to determine what the cost of the scheme would have been if it had been calculated on the basis of a 30 year requirement rather than a 40 year requirement.  It would determine what the impact might have been on the women, primarily, who are affected, if it had been calculated on the basis of 30 rather than 40 years.</p> <p>There were some concerns about the consultation over the summer.  There are three or four areas of pension consultation under way at the moment and different approaches are being used in each.  With the Strawman proposal in respect of the supplementary pension scheme, people were able to see what the proposals were.  I had feedback from a number of people who tried to navigate the opt-in survey monkey system that was used during the summer for the total contribution approach.  It was never made clear that the issue of the number of years of contributions would be there.  It was quite a difficult consultation to navigate and that is why a number of NGOs ended up sending in supplementary documents in which they were able to unpack the issue in a way that the multiple-choice questionnaire did not allow for.  There is wider concern.  Is there scope simply to analyse what a 30 year option would have looked like on the 2012 changes?  In general I very widely welcome them, especially the care credit aspect.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.201" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="16:20:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800036#TT00200"><p>The Senator will have to excuse me for being confused.  In my head, I am hearing two separate issues here which do not relate to each other.  If I am answering the wrong one, I ask the Senator to give me the nod.  On the public consultations on total contributions, not a single decision has been made, not one.  If we arrive at 30 years with ten years' credits, it will be because we have deliberated on all the submissions that have been made and found that to be the best option.  If we arrive at 40 years with 20 years' credits, it will be because the submissions have guided us. Not one submission has been read by me.  Not one ounce of work has been done collectively in the Department to determine what the next generation of the total contributions model of pensions payments is going to look like.  The purpose of the public consultation was to gather all the different opinions.  The Senator has expressed hers and we have got hundreds of submissions under the public consultation.  All that is to determine the best and fairest approach for the people.  It will only apply to those who retire after 2020.  The people who retired after 2012 are not affected by the proposed changes for 2020.  They are being adjudicated under the current system, which is as fair as it potentially can be.  It is the 30 years, not 40 years.  It is the system with the ten years credit.  Those who were adversely affected by the 2012 changes, which we have changed in this legislation, will be getting their payments next year.  That is an interim model which will not determine what the new model will be and is not reflective of the old model.  It is a bit of the old model and a bit of the new model, and people are happy with it.  I think I told the House previously that approximately 70% of the people who were affected by the changes in the rates of 2012 will see their pension increase to a full pension come January, February or March of next year.</p>  <p>The Senator is asking me to do a report on the basis of an outcome that has not yet been reached.  I do not wish to be disrespectful to her.  We are in a deliberative process and have not completed it.  We have not determined what the new model of total contributions is going to look like.  The Senator obviously has decided in her head that we have determined what it is going to look like.  On that basis she wants me to do a report so she can prove to me that it should be something other than what she thinks I think it is going to be.</p> <p>We have not decided whether it will be ten years credits, 20 years credits or 30 years for total contributions for a full pension, or 40 years for total contributions for a full pension.  That deliberative process will be determined by the submissions that have been made.  There were hundreds of them, but the issue has not been determined yet.  Not only do I not have the money to do what the Senator is asking me to do, I do not have the staff to carry out an analysis that she believes will feed into something.  I have not made a decision yet.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.203" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="16:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800037#UU00200"><p>To clarify, the amendment specifically relates to the scheme up to 2020.  It is significant, and the two issues are related, but I am not asking for something that does not exist yet.  I am simply pointing out that a new precedent has been set.  This scheme represents the first time that a threshold of 40 years has been set, which is significant.  While I respect the fact that no decision has been made, and hope that the decision will take into account the many submissions received, it would not be appropriate if we ended up in a situation where there was a suggestion that there must be a trade off between recognising care or extending the gaps.  A scheme should be provided that accommodates both, and it should take the form I have proposed.  There will be different perspectives; the majority have suggested that it should fall within the 30-year threshold.</p>  <p>My amendment related specifically to the change in 2012.  The Minister is correct that the 2012 people will not be affected by the total amount envisaged in this approach.  However, the 40-year versus 30-year decision has relevance for 2020, which is why I sought that analysis.  The Minister told us that 70% of persons would qualify for a full pension under the new change, and that is welcome.  If there was a 30-year approach, would 85% or 90% have qualified?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.204" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="16:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800037#UU00300"><p>We introduced 20 years of credits for this interim period.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.205" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="16:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800037#UU00400"><p>And moved the requirement overall to 40 years.  The Minister told us about some of the issues on the table that have not been decided yet in respect of the total contribution, but two of those ideas are being trialled in this case, which is why it might have been relevant to look at it as a cohort that might provide an example.  With due respect, 2020 is only two years away, so it is significant.  If the threshold was to move to 40 years, there will not be enough time for people to prepare in any way, to change their life course or magic up new credits from anywhere.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.206" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="16:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800037#UU00500"><p>I understand what the Deputy means.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.207" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="16:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800037#UU00600"><p>It is a concern, and this was an opportunity to address it.  Next year is 2019, and the decision will clearly be made then.  It was a suggestion that modelling be done.  The Minister has said that 70% qualified when the requirement was for 2080 contributions.  My question is, of that cohort, how many might have been expected to qualify using the same projection?  The provision has not come in yet, so the 70% has been calculated on the basis of projection.  I would like to know the projection of the percentage of people who qualify if the threshold was 1,560.  I do not want to guess, which is why I hoped we could get the figure.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.208" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="16:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800037#UU00700"><p>The Senator was looking for the report to satisfy herself as to who was going to be excluded from receiving a full pension on the basis of not having either 20 years work with 20 years caring or 30 years work with ten years caring.  The difficulty I have with this is that it is not new.  The move to this model was flagged back in 1994, and the reason we changed from 260 initial contributions to qualify, increasing to 520 in 2012 - which is the adversity people speak about, and the changes to rate bands that affected people - was because people's work practices over the years had changed.  People had longer to apply for all of the years worked required to get a full pension.  If I understand the Senator correctly, she is suggesting that something that is worth &euro;300,000 to &euro;400,000 should be achievable after only ten years of work.  I am sorry, but I fundamentally and absolutely do not agree with her.  We have made the changes and are moving to a total contributions model because there are people in this country who are in receipt of full pensions with only ten years work, while, at the same time, there are people living here for 30 or 40 years who have gaps in their work records because of caring and who are not in receipt of full pensions.</p> <p>First, the actuarial value is recognised in so far as one cannot expect the State to provide somebody with a pension package of &euro;300,000 or &euro;400,000 off the back of only ten years' work.  That is the reason we are deliberating at the moment on whether it should be 30 years, inclusive of ten years caring credits, or 40 years, inclusive of 20 years of caring credits.  The premise of the deliberations is to make sure that we capture the most people we can for the highest rate, but doing the report that is sought will not feed into those deliberations.  If the report is looking for a backbone to stand down the fact that the minimum contributions should not be 520 but 260, then all of the previous Governments that have established the principles of the policy issues from 1994 to where we are today do not concur with the way the Senator is thinking.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.210" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800038#VV00200"><p>It is important that we are clear for the record of the House, the previous proposals referred to a total contribution.  The Minister is correct that the change has been very well flagged.  I have read the original proposal which always envisaged 30 years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.211" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800038#VV00300"><p>With ten years' credit.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.212" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800038#VV00400"><p>With ten years' care credits.  The question is whether we are recognising the contribution of carers because if the idea is to add ten years of additional care credit, if we push the goalposts out for everybody to 20 years we are not recognising more care, we are simply pushing the calculation out.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.213" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800038#VV00500"><p>No, because we are increasing the contributions to 20 years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.214" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800038#VV00600"><p>Thirty years has been well signalled.  As the Minister said, the debate was happening in the 1990s and in 2010.  People can see the signal there for a long time, but we are now at a point where we are one year away from the adoption of a total contribution approach.  The idea of introducing a ten-year further contribution at this point clearly has been thought about.  That is a concern and that is the reason I want a report.  I accept that we might not be able to get it and that perhaps there are other ways to get the figures.  We could go through parliamentary questions, for example, but we would need to know the calculations.  We talked about changing work practices.  Not many people in the State will fulfil the 40-year criterion given the broken work practices and periods that they have had and the unknown relationship in the future with the UK for those who travelled there and back.  There are many reasons for gaps.  I applaud some of the positive measures to address those gaps through a total contribution approach, but I am worried that the goalposts are being set too far out.  I am happy to leave the topic.  I am sure we will come back to it in the committee but I am concerned at the tone evident in the Joint Committee on Employment Affairs and Social Protection, which seems to be strongly pushing towards the further goalpost, and I believe many citizens will fall short of that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.215" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800038#VV00700"><p>I am sorry the Senator feels that way because I can genuinely tell her that we have not made any decisions.  I have not started reading all of the propositions that have come in to us from the various people who have made their views known.  I can say that categorically a week before Christmas.  If we stay at 30 years, then we will limit the caring credit to ten years.  If we move to 40 years, we will move the caring credit to 20.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.216" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800038#VV00800"><p>Both can surely be accommodated.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.217" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800038#VV00900"><p>We are not moving the goalposts.  The only reason we would consider moving to 40 years is because people who will retire from 2020 onwards will have had the opportunity to have had 20 full years plus working, because they will be 66 or 67 at that stage.  In addition, we are adding in the gaps for caring.  We changed the caring credit.  Historically, the homemaker's credit was only for women who stayed at home to mind their children but we recognise that families have changed in recent years and women do not just stay at home to mind their children any more.  We stay at home to mind our grannies, brothers and other extended members of our family.  That is the reason we changed the credit.  No decision has been made on whether it will be 30 and 10 or 40 and 20 years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.218" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800038#VV01000"><p>We can engage further on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.219" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800038#VV01100"><p>That is the way it sounds.  No decision has yet been made.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.220" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800038#VV01200"><p>Not for the new system.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.221" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800038#VV01300"><p>Is the amendment being pressed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.222" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800038#VV01400"><p>I will not press the amendment at this point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.223" nospeaker="true" time="16:40:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.224" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800038#VV01600"><p>I move amendment No. 3:</p><blockquote>In page 17, between lines 11 and 12, to insert the following:<br /><br />&ldquo;<b>Amendment of section 263 of Principal Act</b><br /><br /><b>27</b>. Section 263 of the Principal Act is amended by the substitution of the following subsection for subsection (3):&quot;(3) A person shall produce his or her public service card or other appropriate form of identification at the request of a specified body for the purposes of a transaction. No specified body shall make possession of a public service card or presence on the single customer view dataset a mandatory requirement for the purposes of a transaction.&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote><p>This amendment relates to another issue we debated previously, namely, the public services card.  I tabled a number of amendments on the issue but I will not press all of them.  We have heard the debate about the production of a card.  It was rightly pointed out by the Minister that it might not be a case of possession of a card but it might be presence on the single customer view dataset.</p> <p>It may be that there is a number of ways in which persons can be identified as being on the single customer view dataset.  That should not be made a requirement for any of the bodies specified under the social protection legislation, of which there is an extensive list.  While they may be entitled to use the public services card, which I do not seek to block them from doing, they should not be able to make it mandatory for services due to a couple of issues: the data-sharing legislation, that is, the legal provision for the sharing of information, has not passed through the D&aacute;il and there is an ongoing debate on the data-sharing commitment.  The data-sharing legislation is clear that information that relates to special categories of personal information cannot be held.</p> <p>On the debate about whether the new photographic database and the photographs which are now attached to the single customer view dataset are personal, I strongly believe they are personal data and a special category thereof.  The Minister will be aware that this issue has been the source of some controversy and concern within the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection, and it is a controversy which has deepened due to questions such as how "bio-metric" is defined or not defined.  The issue of the independence of the data protection officer has also been raised as a concern in that regard.</p> <p>I withdrew a number of amendments and I have not retabled all of them.  I am suggesting that we should be clear that, notwithstanding the internal dynamics of the Department and its processes, while specified bodies may choose to accept a public services card as something that would qualify somebody to access a transaction or service, they should make it mandatory at a time when there serious question marks over how data are shared, which categories of data are shared or how the data are defined.  We should not leave the State vulnerable to legal action on this matter.  I welcome that the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport has recognised the legal concerns and indicated that a public services card will no longer be mandatory and that it will accept other forms of identification for those wishing to take the driver theory test, which was the correct decision.  </p> <p>I hope the Minister will be open to taking on board the amendment.  It is the minimum to ensure we keep track of the specified bodies.  It does not address the concerns I have with the internal dynamics of the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection, but I know the Joint Committee on Employment Affairs and Social Protection is considering the issue of public services cards on an ongoing basis.  I am confident, therefore, that we will have other opportunities to address the matter as it relates to the internal affairs of the Department, but the amendment addresses the relationship between specified bodies and the Department.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.226" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="16:50:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800039#WW00200"><p>I do not think the Senator will be surprised by what I tell her.  She suggested that some people in the Department have concerns about the public services card but they do not.  There are some people in Ireland who consistently express their concerns with the public services card, but they do not come from the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection, and the Senator and I both know who they are.  We are aware of, and fully support, our SAFE 2 authentication process, the end result of which is the production of a public services card.  I do not propose, therefore, to accept the amendment, although I will make some important points about the public services card.</p>  <p>It is not mandatory for anybody to apply for a public services card, which is subject to much attention.  It is only the end result of the SAFE 2 registration process, which provides us with a substantial level of surety of a person's identity.  All it has done is replace older documents that showed that somebody had an entitlement to a benefit, which might have been the old social welfare services card or a paper travel pass that people used to have for the bus.  As was the case with those older documents, it is necessary to produce a public services card as proof of identity in certain types of transactions.  It is certainly not mandatory for all transactions but rather in some types of transactions, such as collecting one's welfare payment at the post office in order that it can be guaranteed that I am Regina Doherty when I present to say I am.</p> <p>Where someone is getting on a bus, he or she shows his or her pass to demonstrate an entitlement to access free travel.  It is exactly the same as when a person would have shown the bus pass previously with which no one had a problem.  The SAFE 2 process was introduced to protect the high value services of this and other Departments.  People will understand that the money we are talking about is taxpayers' money.  It is not surplus money or a question of random lottery winners and careful consideration of how we spend it is required.  With high value services, we must be assured that a person who presents seeking access to a scheme or service that costs a great deal of money is exactly who he or she says.  The SAFE 2 process was introduced to ensure we had the highest level of verification for people's identities.</p> <p>The SAFE standard has a number of levels.  SAFE 0 is no assurance of identity.  We do not have a clue who a person is.  SAFE 1 provides an indication on the balance of probabilities with a minimum authentication level, namely, the allocation of a personal public service number.  SAFE 2 provides substantial assurance and is the minimum authentication level to issue a PCS card.  SAFE 3 is a beyond-doubt standard and typically involves using things like fingerprints or biometric data, about which we have spoken before.  That is not on our books at the moment and it is not in our plans but it is one of the four levels of the SAFE process, of which we are currently at SAFE 2.  We are implementing SAFE 2 on a phased basis with our customers and the customers of other public services which require identity verification to a substantial level of assurance.  Until recently, many public services were provided to people who had been identified at a SAFE 1 level.  For example, the Senator has alluded before to identify documents like passports and driver licences which were issued to people following SAFE 1 registration.  Since the introduction of SAFE 2 registration in 2011, more services are moving their verification requirements to this level because it gives greater assurance that those to whom services or moneys are provided are exactly who they say they are.</p> <p>I cannot speak for other Departments, but my Department's fraud control measures show that we are now capturing people who are providing different identities with the same face in different locations and claiming twice and three times in some cases.  This assures us that one person with one identity can only get access to a scheme to which he or she is entitled.  I disagree with the Senator again about this.  I am not responsible for any other Department.  I am not responsible for the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport changing its mind or pulling back until it brings in further legislation.  What I guarantee is that the SAFE 2 identity process adopted by my Department is underpinned by legislation and is the safest way for us to ensure that the vulnerable people who need or deserve, on foot of their social insurance contributions, the &euro;20.5 billion we give out every year on behalf of the State are exactly the people they present as being.  If they are not we catch them to ensure we do not distribute taxpayers' money to people who are not entitled to it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.228" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="16:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800040#XX00200"><p>It is important to be clear because people might get the impression there was large-scale fraud whereas the figures have shown it is, in fact, at a low level.  In fact, according to the figures last year, the amount of money lost internally through error was been higher than the amount of money lost through fraud.  It is important to be clear about that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.229" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="16:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800040#XX00300"><p>The Senator is making my case for me.  The reason it is so low is that we employed SAFE 2 in 2011.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.230" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="16:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800040#XX00400"><p>The public service card scheme has been very high and that has been an issue of concern for the Committee of Public Accounts in terms of excess.  As such, I question whether there have been savings.  It is also the case that the roll-out of public service cards was intensified during the period in which it was under review by the Data Protection Commissioner.  There have been concerns about data protection and the section 10 investigation of the Office of the Data Protection Commissioner has been ongoing.  There were also concerns and complaints about changes around how "biometric" was defined.  I am not suggesting the concerns are within the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection, albeit they probably should be.  I note that when we are in an area in which we are not legally robust, we open the State to litigation, which also costs money.</p> <p>That is why I have endeavoured to ensure that we try to take whatever steps we can to minimise the vulnerability of the State.  The Minister is as attached as am I to Exchequer funding being there for what it is needed for.  That is why I do not like to see us taking certain risks in the way this is being approached and rolled out.</p> <p>I am aware that the Minister and I will not come to a point of agreement on this but this is not the same as previous arrangements.  Previously, we did not have photographs within that system that could be scanned.  Contracts have been given for software that can allow these photographs to be processed.  That is a concern.  If we have photographs that can be processed through biometric processing - I am not going to reopen that debate because we have had it many times - that is very different from previous information that was in place in respect of public service identity in the past.  It is not the same.  That is one reason there will be a need for different and separate storage mechanisms in the future for the different parts of the information that is currently in the single customer view data set.  Differentiations may need to be made within that data set, which is probably where we will end up in the future.</p> <p>The SAFE process has been cited here.  This is a process that Ireland has but it is not an international standard that has been set up.  There are many international measures and standards but lest people get the impression that there is an onus on us to get SAFE 1 or SAFE 2 or SAFE 3, these are names of a system that Ireland has put in place.  While we should strive for best practice, when doing so we should try to bring the best practice for data protection along with us.  We have not done that as yet. The Minister and I disagree on this and I am not going to press this amendment but I had to respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.232" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="17:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800041#YY00200"><p>I call Senator Warfield now.  Is this relevant to this point?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.233" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="17:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800041#YY00300"><p>Sinn F&eacute;in also has raised some concerns around the public services card.  We had called for the roll-out of the card to be suspended, in the main on foot of the grave concerns raised by the Data Protection Commissioner and we believe those concerns need to be dealt with.  We are concerned, as others are, that it could be a move towards a national ID scheme.  As others, albeit not in this House, have mentioned, these concerns have to be addressed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.234" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="17:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800041#YY00400"><p>I assure the Senator that there is no intention of anybody moving towards an ID scheme.  If there was, it would be a fairly poor one given that one is not obliged to show one's public services card, PSC, card to anyone, so it certainly would not work.</p>  <p>I regret that it appears that I am always fighting with Senator Higgins, because I have huge respect for her, but I cannot allow her to say there are investigations because the Data Protection Commissioner has grave concerns over the PSC.  She or her office does not.  The last complaint the Senator alluded to was a complaint that was made by somebody that is being investigated.  It has not been upheld or a finding made.  The definition of what we hold our policy to be has to be and can only be determined by us.  There is not an international body or organisation out there that tells us what definitions are.  We hold the definitions within our Department and we are perfectly entitled to do that.</p>  <p>Furthermore, the investigation the Data Protection Commissioner is undertaking is not against the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection.  I cannot actually speak about it because she has asked me not to, but I cannot allow the Senator put on the record of this House that the Office of the Data Protection Commissioner has grave concerns with the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection.  It does not.  That will be transparent when the Data Protection Commissioner issues her report.  </p>  <p>We need to come back and focus.  The SAFE authentication process is not some international standard that was robbed from New Zealand or Australia.  We are actually world leaders in the authentication process ourselves.  I believe that is great.  The Senator is absolutely correct in saying that the level of fraud is low and, thankfully, dropping.  This is happening because of this very verification process.  We are catching people who were claiming two, three or four and multiples of times of that in different locations and because of this verification process, one cannot do that.  One can present once, with one's facial image scanned to ensure that the person is the person with the two eyes, the nose, the freckle here or whatever it is that has been determined by that scan, and one cannot then present in a different location and pretend that one is somebody else.</p> <p>That is why we know that the bulk of the &euro;20.5 billion spent by the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection is going to the people who are either entitled to it or deserve it because they need our help.  On that basis, I fundamentally disagree that we should either stop, change, remove or withdraw this.  It is a good policy and it is working.  I stand behind the Department's support of it and will lend my support for as long as I am here.  I disagree with the Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.236" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="17:15:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800042#ZZ00200"><p>With respect, there is not a meeting of minds on this issue.  I must ask everyone who is present-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.237" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="17:15:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800042#ZZ00300"><p>I want to accept one point, which is that I am sorry if I used the words "grave concern" with regard to a body.  It is a section 10 investigation on the issue but I would not want to quote or appear to be quoting somebody in respect of grave concerns.  The grave concerns are perhaps mine.  One thing which I think is important to be clear on is this being compulsory or mandatory.  While we may say that people are not required to have this card or to produce it, for many people to access Student Universal Support Ireland, SUSI, grants that may enable them to go back to college or for others, it may be misleading to suggest that it is not becoming a requirement.  It is required to get a passport to leave the country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.238" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="17:15:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800042#ZZ00400"><p>None of that is in the remit of my Department.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.239" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="17:15:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800042#ZZ00500"><p>It is not simply a voluntary measure.  This has been made a requirement.  That is why I focused on those other bodies.  It has been made a requirement of engagement in society.  A photograph is taken which is accessible by 40 or more specified bodies.  There is very wide access to that database and I think we will end up returning to it in the future.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.240" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="17:15:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800042#ZZ00600"><p>With respect, the Senator and Minister understand one another and disagree.  Is the amendment being pressed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.241" nospeaker="true" time="17:15:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.242" nospeaker="true" time="17:15:00" ><p>Bill reported without amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.243" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="17:15:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800042#ZZ00900"><p>Amendments Nos. 4 and 5 in the names of Senators Conway-Walsh, Devine, Gavan, Mac Lochlainn, &Oacute; Donnghaile and Warfield are out of order since they are not relevant to the subject matter of the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.244" nospeaker="true" time="17:15:00" ><p>Amendments Nos. 4 and 5 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.245" nospeaker="true" time="17:15:00" ><p>Bill recommitted in respect of amendment No. 6.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.246" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="17:15:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800042#ZZ01200"><p>I move amendment No. 6:</p><blockquote>In page 22, after line 33, to insert the following:<br /><br /><b>&ldquo;Report on jobseeker&rsquo;s transitional payment supports</b><br /><br /><b>32.</b>The Minister shall, within six months of the passing of this Act, prepare and lay before the Houses of the Oireachtas a report on employment, training and educational opportunities and supports for those on jobseeker&rsquo;s transitional payment to include:(a) recommendations to improve casework and employment, training and educational opportunities for those on jobseeker&rsquo;s transitional payment, including high-quality part-time opportunities;<br /><br />(b) analysis of how childcare, transport and other public services may facilitate or support access to employment, education or training for those on jobseeker&rsquo;s transitional payment;<br /><br />(c) policy options around the extension of jobseeker&rsquo;s transitional payment to include one parent families with a child up to eighteen years of age; and<br /><br />(d) policy options around the extension of jobseeker&rsquo;s transitional payment to include a foster parent of a child up to eighteen years of age.&rdquo;.</blockquote><p>I hope we can make further progress.  There are areas of this in which we have had positive engagement.  I know the Minister was interested in the issue of supports for one-parent families.  We have engaged on that issue in the past.  The Joint Committee on Employment Affairs and Social Protection produced a report with a number of recommendations on supports for lone parents and one-parent families.  I recognise that the Minister has taken some of those recommendations on board.  It can be seen in the changes relating to partial restoration of income disregard and the increase in the qualified child payments in the budget.  I welcome those in the Bill.</p><p>A key concern for me relates to a fundamental principle of equality between families.  It is the current requirement for full-time availability of somebody who is parenting alone after his or her child reaches the age of 14.  Many persons, even those still on one-parent family payment who may have a child of six months to two years, may choose to return to work which may be the right option for somebody parenting alone, and we generally recognise that there is a balancing of care and employment that is done in different ways.  I believe there should be extended voluntary access to employment and education schemes for persons with children of any age.  Our system recognises that when a parent has children between the ages of seven and 14, the parent has access to back to education schemes and employment options.  I debated the question separately.  I have not included it here, but subsection (a) relates to case work on employment, training and education opportunities for those on that payment in that crucial period when their child is between seven and 14, including a provision for high-quality part-time options.</p> <p>It is something we have discussed before.  It should not be the case that because one is going to work part time it is assumed to be casual work.  It should be a ladder to further engagement and a ladder in one's career.  It is also crucial there are educational options on the table in that regard.  Our system has been designed on the assumption of full-time availability.  That is how our system was historically designed.  The jobseeker's transitional payment is an interesting opportunity to pilot other approaches to helping people build attachment to the workplace or ladders back into education in a quality way.  </p> <p>I have also suggested integrated connection between issues of childcare, transport and other public services.  While I accept that many issues of childcare are not within the remit of the Minister's Department, they are fundamental and crucial for those who are trying to build attachment to the workplace.  </p> <p>The proposals ask the Minister to look at ways we can make the jobseeker's transitional payment work better.  That is one key aspect of it.  The other key aspect is, as the Minister acknowledged with the increase to the qualified child payment, that teenagers are different.  The costs associated with teenagers can be higher.  All 14 year olds are not the same.  For one parent who is parenting a 14 year old alone, returning to work full time might be absolutely a positive option but another parent may feel the years between 14 and 18 are the crucial years in which they need to know they can come home at 3 p.m. or 4 p.m. and be there with their child in the evenings.  It might be crucial for them.  The system does not have the flexibility to respond to that because people are required to report full time for work and to be available full time for work while their children are between those ages.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.248" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="17:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800043#AAA00200"><p>The Senator should speak to the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.249" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="17:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800043#AAA00300"><p>I will suggest something that does not necessarily come with a high cost to the State.  Income disregard might continue to apply but besides that cost, it does not come with a high cost to the State.  It would simply allow the flexibility for an authentic engagement between case workers and lone parents, who are predominantly women, to ensure they do not find themselves on JobPath being told they have to consider a list of three full-time jobs when they know they cannot.  Even since we did our report, we have had very strong testimony on other issues.  People talked about how in the current system they saw themselves ending up taking a retail job, which would have been okay, but the jobseeker's transitional payment gave them time and scope and a chance for engagement with caseworkers and they ended up going back to college.  They took a different route.  We want to make sure that people find the best option which sets the best example for and provides the best support to their children.  I think the Minister has the same goal.  The system can be improved.</p>  <p>My final point is about the concern for foster parents of children up to 18 years of age.  People who are foster parenting may have children of their own and may also be acting as foster parents.  At present there is limbo with regard to where foster parents fall.  Their own children may have reached the age of seven but they may be fostering children who are slightly below that age.  Their own children might reach 14 but they may still be fostering an 11 or 12 year old.  Children who are being fostered need that support.  It is about looking at flexibility.  Perhaps there are opportunities for us to engage on this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.250" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="17:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800043#AAA00400"><p>Before I call on the Minister, I will allow Senator Warfield to make a contribution.  Is it relevant to the amendment?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.251" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="17:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800043#AAA00500"><p>Does the Leas-Chathaoirleach not trust me anymore?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.252" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="17:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800043#AAA00600"><p>I have to ask the question because I cannot allow anybody latitude.  We are on the amendments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.253" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="17:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800043#AAA00700"><p>The Leas-Chathaoirleach will be glad to hear I will be brief.  I support the amendment.  There is a need for specific measures to assist those in receipt of jobseeker's transitional payment when they are taken off the one-parent family payment when that is their wish.  I do not need to tell the Minister we must consider the fact that lone parents raise their children without the support of a partner so we cannot push them into finding employment when caring duties are, understandably, their priority.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.254" nospeaker="true" time="17:25:00" ><p>Additional debate to follow.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.255" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="17:35:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800044#BBB00100"><p>This must be respected.  I just wanted to add my voice to the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.256" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="17:35:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800044#BBB00200"><p>May I respond to something the Minister-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.257" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="17:35:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800044#BBB00300"><p>The Senator may not.  She may speak on Fifth Stage.  If it is not relevant to this amendment she should wait until Fifth Stage when she may make a brief comment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.258" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="17:35:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800044#BBB00400"><p>I just want to flag two things with the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.259" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="17:35:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800044#BBB00500"><p>Senator Warfield will also speak on Fifth Stage.  I call on the Minister to respond on the points relevant to this amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.260" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="17:35:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800044#BBB00600"><p>I am really glad that we are to finish on a positive note.  I ask Senator Higgins to withdraw the amendment because very selfishly I will be unable to complete the passage of the Bill today if she does not.  I share her views and concerns in the area.</p>  <p>In the coming days I will be able to furnish the Senator with a number of reports containing data of which she may not be already aware.  With regard to the proposed section 32(a), our case-management and activation unit that we set up for JST at the end of 2016 has now had its second full year.  I would like to provide the Senator with an analysis of how that case management has been effective in some areas and not effective in other areas so that we can learn what we need to change.</p>  <p>We will genuinely look at what is available to people.  Different Departments have set policies that reach 98% of people's requirements but the last 2% does not allow something to be done because something needs to be accessed from a different Department.  For example, our training model outlines a list of things that people can do on training.  However, why can people not go back and do certain courses in NUI Maynooth, Trinity College or wherever just because they happen to be on Springboard or they happen to be from SUSI?  There is no reason not to have cross-correlation.</p>  <p>I believe the Senator and I want the same thing which is that women - let us be honest that it is mainly women- during those years when their child is between seven and 14 are actually preparing for a career if that is what they want and not preparing to go and work for &euro;9.55 an hour.  I do not mean to diminish anybody who is working for &euro;9.55 an hour.  We need to ensure that they get continual training, support and employment opportunities to avail of &euro;15 an hour or &euro;55 an hour or whatever are their aspirations.  While recognising that different families have different expectations, limitations, parameters, childminding services, all the wraparound services from a case-management perspective, support perspective and educational support perspective need to be determined within that seven- to 14-year age bracket, and it needs to be flexible.  We are working on that.</p>  <p>On qualifying the data, the Senator knows Indecon prepared a report for us last year.  It is a great report and cost an arm and a leg and I do not have any money to repeat it.  However, I really think it would be valuable.  We have asked Indecon to carry out a review.  Its report looked at the changes made in 2012 and it went up to only 2016.  I have asked it to do a review up to 2018, which gives us two more years of practice and the economy recovering.  It also allows us to see the impact of the reversal of the cuts that were introduced at the same time as the policy was introduced in 2012 which made sure it could never be successful in its own right.  I will give the Senator that report.</p>  <p>We should have that report by the end of quarter 2.  As it is by Indecon it will be totally independent.  It will take into account the changes in case management, the introduction of the disregards as in the reversal of the income disregards and hopefully the impact of QCI so that we can have a real reflective picture of what the aspirations of JST was to be in 2012 and what it could have looked like if we had not introduced all the cuts at the same time.  I am doing that anyway.</p>  <p>Deputy Br&iacute;d smith brought my attention to the anomaly with foster carers.  I do not know if the Senator spoke to her at about the same time.  I need to look at this.  If somebody is foster caring they cannot be presenting as a jobseeker because they already have a job looking after a child on behalf of the State.  However, they should not be penalised from accessing the positive aspects of JST.  We need to look at that and recognise that there are exceptions.  There was another case of a lady whose child had grown up but she was fostering two young children on behalf of the State and we were penalising her.</p> <p>We need to look at foster carers as a separate group of service providers and very important people for the State.  I will come back to the Senator six to eight weeks after Christmas with regard to the anomalies in foster care and what we can do to fix them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.262" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="17:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800045#CCC00200"><p>I thank the Minister.  There was the question of the extension of the jobseeker's transitional payment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.263" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="17:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800045#CCC00300"><p>Does the Senator wish to withdraw the amendment?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.264" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="17:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800045#CCC00400"><p>With regard to the jobseeker's transitional payment, at the moment when the youngest child is 14 one moves from jobseeker's transitional payment to the live register and jobseeker's allowance.  The problem is this does not deal with many of the issues of balancing care with the bureaucracy that comes with having a child for any family, but especially for a one-parent family given there is only one person to deal with all of that.  To extend jobseeker's transitional payment from the age threshold of 14 to 18 would have a lot of merit.  It would allow women or parents of children who are at what can be a vulnerable age to still have the system engage with them and recognise that balance of care, of work and of ambition the Minister mentioned.  We agree very much on that.</p>  <p>There is currently a requirement for full-time availability for work.  While many people may be available full time and wish to be available full time, there are those who are parenting alone who will not be available full time when their child is between the ages of 14 and 18, and they are in limbo within the system at present.  That is why the potential shelter that is the jobseeker's transitional payment should be extended until the child is 18, with the cuts removed.  It would not apply to everybody and it would not be needed by everybody.  However, it would provide great reassurance for those with teenage children.</p>  <p>Of course, we want to ensure those teenage children have their potential recognised during those crucial years when the path may be set for the next generation.  We do not want a parent who is torn between satisfying the conditions of jobseeker's allowance and the welfare of the child.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.265" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="17:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800045#CCC00500"><p>Where stands amendment No. 6?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.266" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="17:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800045#CCC00600"><p>Every other point has been addressed by the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.267" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="17:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800045#CCC00700"><p>What is the Senator doing with amendment No. 6?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.268" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="17:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800045#CCC00800"><p>I am asking the Minister to respond to that point.  This has been debated within committee rules.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.269" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="17:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800045#CCC00900"><p>I cannot acquiesce to it.  I can certainly look at the options in regard to positively allowing people to continue to engage with their Intreo office, with case managers and so on.  However, from a policy perspective, what the Senator is asking me to acquiesce to is that it is okay to maintain lone parents on social welfare until their youngest child is 18.  I genuinely cannot acquiesce to that as it would undermine the entire fundamentals of the policy.  What we are trying to do is take women, when their children are in full-time education at age seven, albeit in primary school, and provide them with educational supports, activation and employment experience so they can be ready, if they want it, to move into either part-time or full-time education or work experience when their child is 14.  To change the policy to allow them to stay on one-parent payments until the child is 18 totally undermines the policy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.270" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="17:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800045#CCC01000"><p>They will be on jobseeker's transitional so they will still be encouraged into work.  When the changes came in, many people landed directly into that space of jobseeker's allowance or into the-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.271" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="17:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800045#CCC01100"><p>Can we look at it again when we get the Indecon report in quarter 2?  The data might say we do not need to do this.  If the data tell me clearly we have a problem, let us work out what that problem is.  However, if there is no problem, we should not undermine an entire policy.  There will always be a small number of people whom it does not suit and we need to make sure we support them.  Perhaps another payment needs to be looked at or maybe somebody is not available for work full time because of a particular family circumstance.  Let us have a look at it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.272" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="17:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800045#CCC01200"><p>The full-time availability waiver element could perhaps be taken forward or made an option.  I believe it would help a large cohort of persons, including qualified adults, and encourage them onto the live register.  That is something we can debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.273" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="17:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800045#CCC01300"><p>Let us look at the data after we get the report in quarter 2.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.274" nospeaker="true" time="17:45:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.275" nospeaker="true" time="17:45:00" ><p>Bill reported without amendment and received for final consideration.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.276" nospeaker="true" time="17:45:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That the Bill do now pass."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.277" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="17:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800046#DDD00100"><p>I will allow Senators Warfield and Mulherin to comment now.  I call Senator Mulherin.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.278" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="17:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800046#DDD00200"><p>I thank the Acting Chairman for the latitude.  My comment is relevant to a body of work that has been undertaken by the Minister.  She may have mentioned it but I am not sure, as I had to attend another committee and only had one eye on the television screen broadcasting this debate.  I refer to the total contributions approach.  I compliment the Minister on the way that she grabbed the bull by the horns and the fact that she is in the process of implementing the approach to ensure some fairness for women.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.279" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="17:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800046#DDD00300"><p>We had a lengthy debate on this matter in advance of the Senator's arrival.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.280" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="17:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800046#DDD00400"><p>Then I am spot on and thank the Minister.</p>  <p>First, I want to add to the cohort of people seeking equity.  Unfortunately, the stamp or social insurance contributions made by farmers on a low income but in receipt of farm assist prior to 2007 are not recognised.  That means that when they are assessed for a contributory old age pension, or part thereof, their contribution history prior to that is not recognised.  I know of one man who needed to have made ten years of stamp payments prior to his 66th birthday and he had made contributions for more than ten years.  However, he commenced making his contributions prior to 2007 and the years prior to 2007 were disregarded.  Notwithstanding the fact that he paid his stamp, only nine years of his contributions have been recognised.  He wants to know why he had to pay the stamp as it was never going to be recognised and he was in receipt of a farm assist payment.  </p>  <p>Second, people who were self-employed but became PAYE workers did not have their K class stamp, if that is the correct stamp, recognised.  I know of one gentleman who had a bakery and employed many people.  Times changed and the large multiples took over.  The man had to close his business.  He paid the redundancies and paid the class K stamp, or relevant stamp, as a company executive for the entire period, and then he became an employee.  The entire period for which he paid the class K stamp was not recognised.  I appreciate that the Minister has not been given notice about this case and I know that she will get back to me about these two issues.  Both cases relate to people who have paid into the system, in particular the latter individual who employed a considerable number of people.  His former employees will receive a full pension yet he only receives a partial pension so it is no surprise that he feels hard done by.  In the context of the total contributions approach, perhaps some of these matters could be considered in terms of the type of stamp to be paid by the farmer, the pharmacist and the self-employed company executive.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.281" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="17:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018121800046#DDD00500"><p>I had initially proposed amendments on this Stage and the previous Stage that attempted to clear up some typographical errors in the Children and Family Relationships Act 2015.  The errors were identified by the Minister and added to the long list of delays.</p>  <p>Sinn F&eacute;in recently called for these errors to be dealt with in stand-alone legislation that would remove any chance of those amendments being held up by unrelated matters.  I welcome the fact that we received confirmation from the Minister, in correspondence she sent to my party leader, Deputy Mary Lou McDonald, that she intends to provide for the technical amendments to Part 9 of the Children and Family Relationships Act, through a separate Bill and not on Committee Stage of the 2017 social welfare Bill, as originally indicated.  We are keen to give our full support and to do anything we can to ensure that this legislation has a safe passage through the Houses.  I am sure that the Minister understands the hurt and anxiety that has been caused to same-sex couples.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-18a.282" nospeaker="true" time="17:55:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>