<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.4" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#A00100">Gnó an tSeanaid - Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Fintan Warfield that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Employment Affairs and Social Protection to make a statement on the recently published living wage report and her plans to ensure workers will be paid a living wage.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Education and Skills to make a statement on the allocation of school hours for autistic students.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Colm Burke of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister of State with special responsibility for the Office of Public Works and flood relief to provide an update on funding for the Glashaboy flood relief scheme in County Cork.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Catherine Noone of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine to consider the allocation of funding to the Friends of Howth Maritime Museum to acquire the Department's property on the West Pier in Howth which is known locally as Mariners' Hall.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Victor Boyhan of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government to make a statement on the publication of the Land Development Agency Bill. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Michelle Mulherin of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government to consider the expansion of the Rebuilding Ireland home loan scheme to include owners of properties who lost their home during the financial crisis, have now settled their mortgage debt and are in a financial position to buy a new home and service a loan but to whom the banks will not lend.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator M&aacute;ire Devine of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister of State with special responsibility for the Office of Public Works and flood relief to make a statement on the proposals for the Phoenix Park in the Phoenix Park visitor experience strategic review.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Frank Feighan of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport to make a statement on major road schemes on the N4 between Sligo and Mullingar.</blockquote> <p>The matters raised by the Senators are suitable for discussion.  I have selected the matters raised by Senators Fintan Warfield, R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen, Colm Burke and Catherine Noone and they will be taken now.  Senators Victor Boyhan, Michelle Mulherin and M&aacute;ire Devine may give notice on another day of the matters they wish to raise.Senator Catherine Noone has withdrawn her Commencement matter which I had selected for discussion.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.7" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#A00300">Nithe i dtosach suíonna - Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.8" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#A00400">Living Wage Implementation</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#A00500"><p>Yesterday the living wage rose to &euro;12.30 an hour because of the cost of living and the housing crisis.  It is a measure designed to ensure people can afford the essentials in life.  Those earning below the living wage are forced to do without certain essentials, which affects their nutrition in providing an appropriate diet for their families.  That is one of the most important consequences.  Companies such as Aldi, Lidl and Ikea, the majority of non-governmental organisations, NGOs, to which I speak and many small and medium-sized enterprises, SMEs, are paying the living wage but the State does not.  In budget 2019 it could have brought childcare workers from a minimum entry wage to the living wage at a cost of approximately &euro;15 million.  It could have moved public sector and Civil Service workers to the living wage at a cost of &euro;34 million.  They are hard-working individuals employed by the State.  We learned today, for example, that 1,400 members of the Defence Forces quit last year.  In the private sector there are hospitality workers and shop assistants.  We could make a real difference to their lives.  However, the State, continues to pay workers poverty wages and maintains the <i>status quo</i>when it comes to low pay.  Rather than cutting taxes at a cost of &euro;350 million to the Exchequer and squandering money, the State could have moved to increase wages to the living wage.  Workers deserve to be paid fairly.  It is not acceptable that tens of thousands of workers have to endure poverty and a low standard of living as a result of low pay.  Will the Government reassess its approach to this issue?  Will it start to live in the real world by taking steps to put the living wage on a legislative footing? </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1337" speakername="Helen McEntee" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#A00600"><p>We should not confuse the living wage with the national minimum wage.  They are very different.  The living wage is an estimate made by a number of NGOs and academics who make up the self-appointed living wage technical group.  It does not engage with business or many other groups.  Its work is based on research to identify the income required to have the minimum essential standard of living by a single adult household in Ireland conducted by the Vincentian Partnership for Social Justice.  Achieving the 2019 minimum essential standard of living, as calculated by the group, would require gross earnings of &euro;25,198 for a single person, implying a living wage hourly rate of &euro;12.30 based on a 39 hour week over 52 weeks.  This represents an increase of 40 cent on the 2018 living wage of &euro;11.90.  The main drivers of the increase are cited as changes in the cost of living and the tax system; however, the main driver of the increase in the living wage is understood to be the current housing market pressures and associated increases in rent levels.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Helen McEntee:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2394"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2394&amp;amp;pid=HelenMcEntee&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is important that Ireland&rsquo;s statutory national minimum wage and the living wage concept are not conflated.  As a voluntary initiative, the living wage has no legislative basis and confers no statutory entitlement.  The national minimum wage, on the other hand, has a legislative basis and confers a statutory entitlement on employees and a statutory obligation on employers.  It is the legally binding lowest average hourly rate that can be paid by an employer to an employee.  The rate is set and governed by the National Minimum Wage Act 2000 which applies to all employees, including full-time, part-time, temporary and casual employees, with some exceptions.</p><p>The National Minimum Wage (Low Pay Commission) Act 2015 established the Low Pay Commission, an independent body which makes recommendations on the national minimum wage to the Minister for Employment Affairs and Social Protection, Deputy Regina Doherty.  Since its establishment, the recommendations submitted by the commission have all been accepted by the Government and represent an increase in the national minimum wage of 13.3% since 2015.  The national minimum wage has increased every year since the commission was established by Fine Gael and the Labour Party.</p><p>With effect from 1 January 2019, the current rate for the national minimum wage is &euro;9.80 per hour.  The national minimum wage approach seeks to find a balance between a fair and sustainable rate for low paid workers and one that will not have significant negative consequences for employers and competitiveness.  It can be seen as a pragmatic approach, providing a clearly defined minimum hourly rate for employers, giving them the freedom to pay higher rates, while concurrently providing a measure of security for low paid workers.  As it is legally enforceable, it provides that protection for workers.</p><p>More broadly, the setting of wages is a matter between employers and employees.  It takes place in the context of the market.  The Government does not and cannot interfere unduly in that process.  In the past three years the number of workers earning the national minimum wage has ranged anywhere between 6% and 9% of all employees.  On average, over the four quarters of 2018, national minimum wage employees accounted for 7% of all employees.  The average number of individuals earning the national minimum wage or less in 2018 as a percentage of the total labour force was 8.5%.</p><p>The Government has accepted and implemented the recommendations of the Low Pay Commission in respect of the national minimum wage since the commission was established in 2015 by a Fine Gael and Labour Party Government.  A Programme for a Partnership Government provides that the Government will rely on the annual recommendations of the commission.  Relying on an independent body such as the Low Pay Commission is the most appropriate approach to take to achieve the right balance and a yearly adjustment to national minimum wage levels.  The commission is working on its recommendations for this year and will report to the Minister for Employment Affairs and Social Protection in the coming weeks.  Any recommendation the commission makes will be considered by the Government in the context of the upcoming budget.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#B00200"><p>The Government can interfere in the market, as that is exactly what the national minimum wage does.  Sinn F&eacute;in is suggesting the legally binding lowest average hourly rate become the living wage of &euro;12.30 an hour.  Whom would it affect the most?  The majority on the national minimum wage are women, half of whom are young people, while 25% were born abroad.  We can interfere in the market, but in response to a question about the issue yesterday the Taoiseach said it would result in job losses and affect the number of hours of work available.  In 2016 the national minimum wage was increased from &euro;8.65 to &euro;9.15 an hour, a 50 cent increase.  The Economic and Social Research Institute, ESRI, found that there was no evidence that the increase had led to job losses.  It found that there had been no adverse affects on low paid workers and that it had not led to job losses.  They are the facts.  We need to increase the national minimum wage to the living wage in order that people will be able to afford to live in this city and across the State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1337" speakername="Helen McEntee" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#B00300"><p>There is a need to strike a balance.  The living wage technical group comprises representatives of NGOs and academics.  It does not engage with the business sector.  To strike the right balance, that engagement needs to take place.  On the basis of engagement, we have made sure the national minimum wage has been increased in the past four years.  It has been increased by 13.3%.  If a recommendation is made that it be increased this year, I am sure it will be taken on board by the Minister, but we would need to make sure there would be no unintended consequences, as the Taoiseach said yesterday.  The Senator rightly pointed to what the Taoiseach had said.  If we interfere with the market unduly - in my earlier contribution I spoke about interfering in the market unduly - and increase the national minimum wage above and beyond what has been recommended, we may see people's hours being cut and jobs being lost because it may not be possible for employers to keep them on.  We need to be sure we will strike that balance.  We need to make sure the lowest paid workers will be given the highest possible wages.  It will then be up to employers whether they want to go above and beyond the set national minimum wage.  We need to do this within the existing statutory framework which was established in 2015.  We will continue to engage with the Low Pay Commission to make sure any recommendation it makes in consultation with all sectors and bodies involved is taken on board.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.14" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#B00400">Autism Support Services</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#B00500"><p>This is not the first occasion in recent times on which someone has tabled a Commencement matter and then withdrawn it.  I see other Senators here such as Senators Boyhan and Mulherin who did not get a bite at the cherry.  When a Senator declines to raise a Commencement matter which has been selected for discussion by me, it is frustrating for those who are waiting to have matters selected.  That is not Senator Mullen's problem, but I am trying to be as fair as possible.  Senator Mullen has not had a matter selected for a while, which is why I selected his Commencement matter for discussion today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#B00600"><p>Is m&oacute;r dom sin.  T&aacute;im go m&oacute;r faoi chomaoin ag an gCathaoirleach agus cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it.  I thank the Cathaoirleach for allowing me to raise this important Commencement matter which deals with school supports for children with autism.  I thank the Minister of State for attending to take it.</p><p>As the Minister of State may be aware, in the past few years there has been an attempt to integrate children with an autism diagnosis into mainstream schools at both primary and secondary level.  I acknowledge that much of this work has yielded positive and transformative outcomes, not only for the children concerned but also the schools which have had their learning horizons expanded significantly.  That said, there remain significant and, to some extent, growing concerns about the curtailment of access to teaching hours through the application of what are termed as reduced timetables.  As I understand it, the Department&rsquo;s view is that reduced timetables should not be used as a behavioural management technique, or seen <i>de facto</i>as amounting to suspension or expulsion.  There is no legislative provision for their use for particular pupils or groups of pupils.  We are talking about a situation where the State is resourcing schools, but because of behavioural issues or whatever else, the children in need of support are not receiving it because they are being placed on reduced timetables.  The autism support organisation AsIAm made this clear in its submission to the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Education and Skills in late April and again at a recent briefing in the AV room.  From its consultation with parents, autistic children and teachers, it concluded that reduced timetables were being used <i>de facto</i>as a behavioural management option and had the obvious outcome that children were being denied access to class time.  It stated this was mainly down to the failure of the Department to ensure schools were sufficiently autism friendly.  It is one thing to provide funding and resources but another to ensure delivery.  AsIAm also noted that there were what might be termed regulatory lacunae,in the sense that while there was a commitment on paper to adapt the school environment to meet the needs of autistic students, it was not always given practical effect, either because of a lack of training or because of inadequate psychological support structures.</p><p>Pavee Point has independently arrived at pretty much the same conclusions in the case of Traveller children.  Ms Maria Joyce told the Joint Committee on Education and Skills on 30 May on the issue of Traveller children on reduced hours that it had almost reached the point where it had become policy, rather than an exceptional measure in dealing with a child with particular needs.  It is being resorted to far too easily and not being used as a last option.  Will the Minister of State accept, therefore, that exclusion from access to classroom time is almost at the point where it is becoming systemic within schools?  Will she also accept that unless and until more effective autism supports are put in place within schools, the problem is likely to become embedded and that it will become far more challenging to reverse it?<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2250"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2250&amp;amp;pid=RonanMullen&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This is ultimately a question of whether we are genuinely committed to ensuring that these children are made to feel welcome in the school environment, despite the challenges that often present for school staff who are, in fairness, committed and dedicated.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1337" speakername="Helen McEntee" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#C00100"><p>I will answer to the best of my ability.  Where I cannot answer today, I will certainly respond later to the Senator.  We all work with parents and try to provide the best care while ensuring that all students are given access to the supports they need and that are relevant and appropriate for them in any type of school.  It is important to note that the Government is committed to that, as is everyone in this House and in the D&aacute;il.  I thank the Senator for raising this issue, and in particular the challenges faced by children with autism in getting an education.</p> <p>The Joint Oireachtas Committee on Education and Skills will publish its report later on the use of reduced timetables by schools and its impact on children with special educational needs.  The Minister for Education and Skills and his officials will consider the views of the committee over coming weeks.  I am sure they will revert to the Senator Mullen and to every other Member.  Enabling children with special educational needs, including autism, to receive an education is a priority for the Government.  This year we will invest &euro;1.8 billion in providing supports for children with special educational needs, including additional teachers and special needs assistants, SNAs.  It also includes an allocation of more than &euro;300 million towards providing additional resources specifically to support students with autism in schools.</p> <p>The greater proportion of children with autism attend mainstream classes, but some may find it difficult to manage full-time placement in mainstream and, therefore, placement in a special class or special school setting is deemed more appropriate.  Enrolment of a child in a special class or special school placement is based on a professional assessment in consultation with the National Council for Special Education, NCSE.  The NCSE is responsible for planning, co-ordinating and advising on education provision for children with special educational needs.  It is planning to ensure that every child has a school placement appropriate to his or her needs for the 2019-20 school year and is working closely with the Department of Education and Skills in this regard.</p> <p>I will outline some facts associated with this issue.  Since 2011, the number of special classes has increased significantly from 548 in 2011 to 1,459 across the country now.  That is almost a threefold increase of which almost 1,200 are autism spectrum disorder, ASD, special classes.  In addition, there are 124 special schools, of which 20 cater exclusively for children with autism.  The NCSE team of special education needs organisers, SENOs, are locally based and are available to support families of children with special needs.</p> <p>The National Educational Psychological Service, NEPS, supports children with ASD, including those who may also present with anxiety.  This may involve in-depth consultation, an assessment or building schools' capacity to better understand triggers, interventions, solutions and strategies in response to the presenting needs.  The Department and the NCSE provide a range of supports, including professional development, advice and guidance for schools and teachers teaching children with special needs.  Schools are required to have policies in place to support students who experience difficulties that impact on their ability to fully participate in school life.  As we all know, intervention at an early stage is key.  </p> <p>Reduced timetables should not be used as a behavioural management technique, or as any kind of a de facto suspension or expulsion.  There are legal provisions relating to the exclusion and expulsion of students and these are the responsibility of Tusla.  Notwithstanding that, the Department of Education and Skills is aware that reduced timetables are being used in circumstances where that may not be considered the most appropriate means of dealing with a behavioural issue.  The Department is working with the Department of Children and Youth Affairs and Tusla on the development of guidelines for schools on this issue.</p> <p>I have spoken to the Minister in regard to this issue previously.  He is anxious that every child&rsquo;s entitlement to an education be vindicated.  This means that children are supported to ensure maximum attendance and participation.  I am satisfied that the necessary legislative framework and structures across both Departments and their agencies are in place to deliver on this important objective.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#C00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for her response.  There will always be a gap in all human affairs between rhetoric and reality; it is inevitable.  What we have to work to is narrowing that gap as much as possible.  I will be somewhat parochial for a moment.  In December 2018, the Galway Autism Partnership, which provides a service to 200 families, appealed to all Oireachtas Members to make representations to the Department on its behalf.  I understand that the unit, based in Athenry and serving Roscommon and Galway, had no service at all for people with autism for all of 2013.  Its most recent report is from 2017 and it highlighted the fact that it receives no State funding and relies on extensive fundraising, donations from members of the public and corporate sponsorship.</p> <p>I hope that can change.  The Minister of State will not have the information to hand but I would be grateful if I could be reverted to on this issue.  I raise this point because it highlights in another way the gap between the rhetoric of the State regarding autism supports and the reality on the ground.  I accept that there is a commitment to the principle of subsidiarity at play, which is commendable.  Parents and students, however, need the commitment at local level to be reciprocated at departmental level.  The issue I raise referred to reduced timetables.  It concerns how allocated resources are being used, but it links in with the issue of the allocation of resources in other situations.  Both of these issues concern the need to narrow the gap between rhetoric and reality on the ground. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1337" speakername="Helen McEntee" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#C00300"><p>I will have to respond later to the Senator regarding the funding of specific organisations.  It is not something I can comment on now.  Organisations throughout the country, including in my constituency of Meath East, do fantastic work supporting parents, families, teachers, schools and young children with autism.  It is important to acknowledge that and support them where we can.</p> <p>Regarding the specific concern raised by the Senator on the use of reduced timetables, I again stress that the Minister is aware of this.  Reduced timetables cannot, and should not, be used as a behavioural management technique or as any kind of suspension or expulsion mechanism.  The Minister and his Department are working with Tusla to try to address those concerns.  There has been a significant increase in the supports and funding available.  The Senator is correct that it is important that the money reaches the students who need it and that it is applied appropriately.  The Department is doing everything possible to ensure that is the case.  If there are concerns regarding specific issues, it is important that the Senator or anyone else can raise them and make the Minister aware of them as well.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.21" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#C00400">Flood Relief Schemes Status</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#C00500"><p>I thank the Minister of State for making time available to deal with this matter.  The seventh anniversary of the flooding of Meadowbrook in Glanmire was on 28 June.  More than 60 houses and businesses were flooded.  That flooding was 4 ft to 5 ft high in some parts of the estate.  Many houses were severely damaged.  The situation now is that it is impossible to get insurance for those houses and they have been devalued.  The damage cost people much money and brought them a great deal of grief as well.  The county council has done much work in preparing a flood relief programme for the Glashaboy river.  It carried out an environmental impact study, which was furnished to the Minister of State's Department.  I acknowledge that this project has to go through procedures and the environmental impact study has to be reviewed.</p> <p>When he was here previously, the Minister of State gave his full support to funding being allocated for the remedial work to be carried out.  We still have had no sign of that money being assigned.  Even if the funding was allocated today, it would be necessary to invite tenders.  That will take another three to four months.  It will then take another month or two to sign the contracts while the work itself will probably take a year to complete.  If we agreed to the funding today, it would probably still be February or March of next year before any work would start.  This issue is a priority for the people in the area, for the families living in Meadowbrook in Glanmire, for the immediate Glanmire area and for those businesses that suffered damage as a result of that flooding.  I am wondering about the current status of the project.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1363" speakername="Kevin  Moran" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#D00100"><p>I thank Senator Burke for raising this matter and I am pleased to provide an update on the Glashaboy flood relief scheme, Glanmire, County Cork.  He has raised this matter with me before and I am pleased to say that good progress is being made to advance this much-needed scheme.</p> <p>As the Senator will know, the locations identified in this scheme include Sallybrook Industrial Estate, Hazelwood Shopping Centre, Meadowbrook housing estate, Butlerstown, Glenmore and from Glanmire Bridge to O'Callaghan Park.  Following detailed assessment by the consultants, a number of measures were identified to address flood risk in the area, including direct defences such as walls and earth embankments, culvert upgrades, flood relief culverts, channel widening and road regrading.  The scheme will benefit 103 properties in total of which 78 are residential properties and 25 are commercial premises.  Two public information days were held in February 2014 and February 2015.  Following the development of the options and preparation of the necessary environmental and engineering reports, a formal exhibition of the proposed Glashaboy flood relief scheme took place in November and December 2016, which showed the preferred option developed by the design team.</p> <p>The Office of Public Works has submitted the Glashaboy flood relief scheme to the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform for formal confirmation under the Arterial Drainage Acts.  The Minister will undertake an environmental assessment of the proposed scheme over the coming months.  The assessment will be in line with required legislative requirements and will involve a public consultation.  Cork County Council will progress the appointment of a contractor for this scheme following ministerial confirmation.</p> <p>I praise Senator Burke on the work that he has done not only on behalf of the residents and the people he represents but also on the work that he has done with my Department, and we work closely with the county council.  This is an ongoing flood scheme that he brought to my attention.  This Government is very much committed and very much to the forefront in putting funding in place.  I have read recent reports saying that because there was a cut in funding for my Department money may go towards the children's hospital.  I assure the Senator that the money has been ring-fenced for this scheme.  I assure him and the people he represents that that is the case.</p> <p>Since I took up this job two years ago I have put huge emphasis on the Glashaboy scheme.  As the Senator will know, I have brought the scheme to the attention of the Department of Finance.  The project must go through an independent review.  As soon as I have the review the people in his area, and working with the local authority, will get the green light to start the project. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#D00200"><p>I shall allow the Senator to ask a brief supplementary.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#D00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  I fully appreciate and understand his role in the Office of Public Works.  I have found all of his staff in the office to be extremely helpful and supportive of this flood relief work.  I fully understand where the Minister of State is coming from.  Anything I said is not a criticism of him or his Department but local residents are frustrated with the situation.  I take on board what he has said about the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform.  I have expressed my concerns and will continue to do so to that Department about the allocation being provided and signed off.  I am sure that he will understand that if the allocation is signed off today work will not start for seven or eight months.  In the not too distant future we will face into another winter of high water levels.  Unfortunately, residents are extremely concerned and stressed out every winter because the necessary works have not been completed.  I thank the Minister of State for his work on this area.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1363" speakername="Kevin  Moran" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#D00400"><p>I appreciate that the temperature is rising and the sun is shining today.  However, I always say regarding people who have been affected by flooding and suffered the consequences of floodwater hitting their radiators, one is always only three days away from flooding.  When a new Garda station is announced seven years could elapse before there is a brick on the ground.  It is incredible the amount of work that must be done once flooding schemes have been announced.  It takes between three to five years to prepare a scheme.  I will work closely with the Senator from here on in.  I assure him that we are working closely together to make sure, for the people of Glashaboy that he represents, that there is funding and that the work starts thus easing the pressure on residents.  I cannot emphasise enough that the money has been ring-fenced for the Glashaboy scheme.  Therefore, it is wrong for people to say that the money has been diverted elsewhere.  Again, I assure the Senator that there is money for the scheme.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#D00500"><p>I thank the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#D00600"><p>I shall allow the Senator to raise the issue again in November if it has not been remedied.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#D00700"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.30" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 11.05 a.m. and resumed at 11.30 a.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.31" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#G00100">An tOrd Gnó - Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#G00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, motion re arrangements for the sitting of the House on Tuesday, 9 July 2019, to be taken on the conclusion of the Order of Business without debate; No. 2, statements on the Government's action plan to tackle climate breakdown, to be taken at 12.45 p.m. and to conclude at 2.15 p.m., with the contributions of group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes, those of all other Senators not to exceed four minutes, with time being shared where desired, and the Minister to be given not less than five minutes to reply to the debate; and No. 3, Citizens' Assemblies Bill 2019 - all Stages, to be taken at 2.15 p.m. with the contributions of all Senators on Second Stage not to exceed six minutes and the Minister to be given not less than six minutes to reply, and Committee and Remaining Stages to be taken immediately on the conclusion of Second Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#G00300"><p>I raise two issues today.  The first relates to the Ulster Bank sale of a &euro;900 million portfolio of mortgages.  I understand that 3,600 customers will be affected by the sale who have been engaging with the bank and made various short-term arrangements with it.  In January 2019, Fianna F&aacute;il's vulture fund regulation legislation was enacted by the Oireachtas.  The Consumer Protection (Regulation of Credit Servicing Firms) Act 2018 gives the Central Bank the authority to regulate vulture funds and to inspect and investigate the goings on within them.  It is now incumbent on the Central Bank to use the powers provided by the legislation.  While we cannot, unfortunately, stop this sale, it represents a dereliction of duty on the part of Ulster Bank, which should be dealing with poorly performing loans itself.  It should not farm poor loan books out to vulture funds.  Ultimately, it is Irish consumers and citizens who will suffer.  Fianna F&aacute;il calls on the Cental Bank to put the consumer first and to start to use the powers conferred on it by the Fianna F&aacute;il legislation to ensure the minimum of cruelty, upset and harm is caused to Irish mortgage consumers.</p> <p>The second issue I raise relates to the living wage and the fact that we do not have one in Ireland.  Unemployment is low at the moment but so are salaries, notwithstanding the epidemic of unaffordable rents.  For many young people, the prospect of owning a home is completely beyond the realm of possibility.  While new legislation has been implemented to extend rent pressure zones, many major urban centres, including, as Senator Murnane O'Connor has pointed out, Carlow have been excluded.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Catherine Ardagh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2473"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2473&amp;amp;pid=CatherineArdagh&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We need to do something to ensure that modest increases in salary are not completely taken up by the corresponding increases in rent.  It is unfair on young people who are trying to have a life for themselves.  The idea of having the security of somewhere to live is gone for many people.  The awful housing crisis is a shame on the Government.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#H00200"><p>Successive Governments have praised the loyalty and commitment of the Defence Forces but have largely ignored anything to do with their pay.  Today's edition of <i>The Irish Times</i>reports the Public Service Pay Commission as being constrained in what it was able to do when it reviewed Defence Forces pay.  Following years of neglect and poor pay, the Defence Forces deserve better than what is coming to them today.  While the Government&rsquo;s fear that opening the floodgates by increasing Defence Forces pay might encourage industrial unrest in other areas of the public sector, it should have the courage to address this matter, as the alternative scenario is far more serious.</p><p>A retention crisis in any other sector of the public service can be addressed by the use of agency or civilian staff but this is not the case with the Defence Forces.  Nor can the job of protecting the security of the State, our territorial waters and airspace be undertaken by any personnel other than members of the Defence Forces.  It is not possible to contract in somebody on a bomb-disposal mission tonight if an explosive device is found in Dublin, Cork, Limerick, Galway or anywhere else.  The only way to properly address the retention crisis is through a proper pay review - another Gleeson commission.</p><p>The widely and now loudly articulated concerns of Defence Forces members are not just for their own welfare but for the integrity of the Defence Forces and the very serious duties and missions they undertake.  This is the absolute minimum the Government can do.  While the report of the pay commission should be cautiously welcomed, an increase of 96 cent a day in the military service allowance is hardly something to be screaming from the rooftops.  Increases in allowances are welcome and long overdue but the bottom line is that core pay has not been addressed.</p><p>I believe the commission will suggest that core pay needs to be looked at.  There needs to be an immediate examination of everything to do with the Defence Forces.  The &euro;20,000 for pilots will be welcome, but what about the air traffic controllers and fitters to keep the aircraft in the air?  What about senior NCOs in infantry battalions who are core to the running of the battalion?  That will need to be addressed.</p><p>The Public Service Pay Commission did all it could, given its terms of reference and the constraints placed on it.  I hope that PDFORRA and RACO will accept whatever is on the table, but will do so as an interim offer.  I hope we will not have a long drawn-out debate while soldiers, sailors and airmen wait for whatever paltry few shillings come their way.</p><p>However, the Government can do many things that do not come in under pay.  On radio this morning, retired Commandant Cathal Berry spoke about paying out of his own pocket for an MRI scan for a soldier.  That is totally unacceptable.  Healthcare and family care need to be looked after as does accommodation in barracks.  Soldiers, sailors and airman should not have to sleep in their cars or on ships after being at sea for several weeks.  We cannot continue to have millions of euro worth of hardware tied up in Haulbowline or aircraft stuck on the ground because we do not have technicians to fix them.</p><p>The sad fact is that people in the know are saying that between now and Christmas, the pay commission's report will ultimately lead to an exodus of several hundred people and possibly up to 1,000.  We are struggling to meet the requirements of duties at home and abroad, while at the same time we are looking for a seat on the United Nations Security Council.  The two things just do not match.</p><p>At the end of the day we cannot continue to hope this will go away.  We urgently need a Gleeson-type commission to complete a root-and-branch examination of what is required to keep the Defence Forces going.  People argue that there is no need for the Defence Forces.  I wonder how it would be if a village in Donegal were to burn to the ground because there are no Defence Forces members to go out and fight fires, as nearly happened earlier this year.  What will we do when we get the next storm?  What will we do when the next natural disaster hits the country?  What will we do the next time there is a search for bodies?  Who does that?  The Defence Forces are always there 24 hours a day and seven days a week.</p><p>This has to stop.  Telling us that we are proud of the men in uniform is a thing of the past.  We will not even give medals to some of them who are deserving of them.  At the end of the day pride is expressed in the way we treat people.  I dread to think of the messages I will get today from the wives and partners of members of the Defence Forces.  I know how the PDFORRA representatives will struggle today when they get the outcome from the pay review body.  I know how the representatives of RACO, the commissioned officers' board, will struggle today.  I plead with them to accept whatever is on the table and let us follow on with it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#H00300"><p>Today sees the end of the biennial meeting of the Irish Congress of Trades Unions in Dublin.  I commend the comments of the secretary general of ICTU, Patricia King, yesterday when she responded to the address given by the Taoiseach.  Patricia King said it straight and she spoke on behalf of hundreds of thousands of workers.  She said that progress means nothing to many people.  Economic indicators and financial figures mean absolutely nothing to those who are struggling.  This recovery is false for them.</p> <p>Yesterday the Taoiseach said he still wants to reduce the higher rate of tax but he was wishy-washy and non-committal when he mumbled about whether the minimum wage would increase.  I take that as a "No".  When people have to check their bank balance every couple of hours to make sure that bills are being paid, that is not wishy-washy  That is final; it is certain.  I doubt any member of the Government or any Member of this House has to do that.</p> <p>If it is a real recovery, surely those who helped significantly in getting the country out of the mess can ask for a bit more.  However, that is not the case.  To ask for better conditions or an increase in pay is treated almost as treason.  Let us consider the nurses and healthcare workers in their recent disputes.</p> <p>Patricia King said yesterday that "workers' rights to bargain must be addressed as these powers had not advanced in more than 100 years".  I know the Leader will come back with the old Fine Gael cry, saying that that is the private sector.  Ms King also addressed the position of workers working on big State projects.  She said: "Contractors awarded significant state contracts were facilitating precarious work, including bogus employment contracts which avoid tax".</p> <p>During yesterday's debate on the Social Welfare Bill, most Members commended the Minister, Deputy Regina Doherty, on extending jobseeker's benefit to the self-employed.  However, we also discussed at length the bogus employment contracts.  The national children's hospital is the biggest health construction project in the history of the State.  We know that many bogus self-employed construction workers are employed there - whether forced or by choice.  I would like the Minister to come to the House to provide an update on that.  Las Thursday, Unite organised a protest outside the gates from 6 a.m. to 2 p.m., highlighting that the construction site of the shiny and much-needed new children's hospital is full of bogus self-employed workers.  Surely we cannot stand over that and we need to tackle it.  It is a cost on the public purse because they are not contributing what they should to the State.</p> <p>We need to stop talking about recovery for workers.  Today at 12.30 p.m., the paramedic branch of the PNA will hold a demonstration outside Leinster House ahead of the ambulance workers' 24-hour strike next week.  I urge every Member to support them.  It is about trade union recognition and the right to belong to a trade union of the workers' choice.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#J00100"><p>I wish to raise the issue of the drug decriminalisation.  I refer to the front page of today's edition of the <i>Daily Record</i>, a Scottish newspaper.  It states:</p><blockquote>Scotland is gripped by the worst drug crisis in Europe.  It is killing people and wrecking communities.  Our investigation has shown tough justice is not the cure.  We must target dealers but it's time to stop treating vulnerable citizens as criminals.  Our country needs powers to treat addiction as a health problem not a crime.  It is time to decriminalise drug use.</blockquote> <p>The same sentiments are expressed in an open letter from Stuart Clarke of <i>Hot Press</i>to the Taoiseach which notes that the Taoiseach has admitted to taking illegal drugs in the past but nobody would suggest he should have a criminal record as a result.  A document is due to be brought to Cabinet either this week or next week.  It is the result of the deliberations of a working group on drug decriminalisation established two years ago this month.  It was to report after 12 months but did not do so.  Two years later, we are still waiting for the publication of its report.  The decriminalisation of drugs for personal use is potentially the biggest game-changer in terms of equality in the State at this time.  It touches everything from poverty, disadvantage and homelessness to crime, violence and murder.  The Government, which is led by the Leader's party, has the opportunity to publish this report, take this issue seriously and to move, as have other countries in Europe, to a system in which those with an addiction are dealt with primarily and almost exclusively through the health system and treated as human beings rather than as criminals in the criminal justice system.  We have spoken about this issue for a number of years.  We are now at the point where the Cabinet is about to consider the working group's report.  The report needs to be published and we need to move on and take seriously the issue of decriminalising the use of drugs by people who have addictions.  I urge the leader to facilitate a debate in this House with the Minister of State at the Department of Health, Deputy Catherine Byrne, or the Minister for Health, Deputy Simon Harris, because we have waited too long for such a debate to take place in these Houses.  We also need to have that report published and acted upon.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#J00200"><p>I understand that the faltering structured dialogue between the Government and representatives of faith and non-confessional bodies is resuming temporarily today.  One item likely to be discussed is the new covenant between church and State, for which the Taoiseach called when he met Pope Francis last August.  Perhaps another issue that could be discussed is that of basic respect in public dialogue and utterances touching on church and State.  A teacher friend of mine, not a priest as it happens, was in touch to ask me to raise remarks the Taoiseach made about parish priests in the course of his exchanges with Deputy Miche&aacute;l Martin yesterday, remarks which my correspondent regarded as deeply stigmatising of Catholic clergy and insulting to most Catholics.  When I looked up the remarks, I was very surprised at the Taoiseach.  He compared Deputy Miche&aacute;l Martin to "one of those parish priests who preaches from the altar telling us how to avoid sin while secretly going behind the altar and engaging in any amount of sin himself." </p> <p>We all know that the Catholic Church, in particular because of its past prominence in Irish society, must live with the shame and disruption caused by its terrible failures over many years to deal with abusing clergy.  What some of us know is that a huge amount of change, reform, energy and resources are going in across the board to try to ensure that this will never happen again and this investment of human effort will benefit other institutions and society as a whole.  What most of us know, and some of us will admit, is that the vast majority of clergy and religious have been decent and selfless people who have been utterly ashamed of what happened.  What some of us know, and even fewer will speak about, is that some of these clergy and religious are now targeted for abuse on social media and in the street, and that the worst elements of Irish society are seizing on past scandals involving the guilty to inflict pain on the innocent.</p> <p>If the Taoiseach is mindful of this context, why would he invoke a trope, a stereotype of a hypocritical, sinning priest?  At best, it is playing to a very unpleasant gallery of anti-clerical people.  At worst, it is the expression of some deep-seated hidden dislike on his part.  It is not acceptable, at this moment in our history when clergy are fewer and older but continue to do good work, to make a mocking, stigmatising remark like that, whether for its own sake or in order to attack a political opponent.  I need hardly say that if somebody made a similarly stigmatising throwaway remark about gay community leaders or spokespersons for the travelling community, he or she would be rightly criticised.  I hope the Taoiseach will reflect on his remarks and come back with something more generous.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#J00300"><p>I will briefly raise two issues.  The first concerns the announcement of new terms and conditions for Defence Forces personnel which is due today.  I welcome that and hope it will make a start in providing better conditions for our Defence Forces personnel who serve this country so proudly throughout the world.</p> <p>I would also like to refer to the issue raised by Senator Mullen.  I, too, would welcome clarification from the Taoiseach on what he said yesterday.  I hope he will state clearly that his comments were not meant to sound as they did.  Otherwise, I will completely dissociate myself from them.  Criminal acts by priests, politicians, garda&iacute; or any other group need to be weeded out and subjected to the full rigours of the law.  It is not acceptable to tar everyone with the same brush.  I hope that is not what was meant and I would welcome and expect clarification sooner rather than later.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#J00400"><p>I raise the eye care report card for 2019, which features the results of an eye care survey carried out by the Association of Optometrists Ireland.  In Carlow-Kilkenny, children who are referred to HSE eye clinics must wait for 14 months for an eye examination which could be carried out immediately by optometrists in the community.</p> <p>Good vision is essential for children to participate and benefit from education.  The early years of visual development are key to ensuring that children do not have developmental problems that will restrict their ability to achieve their potential.  Children&rsquo;s eyesight develops from birth and as children grow so quickly, their eyesight can change rapidly.  While a small number of children develop serious conditions that require medical intervention and supervision, the majority who develop issues with their eyesight can be managed with regular eye examinations and prescriptions of spectacles.  However, early identification and management of children at risk of having a lazy eye or squint are compromised by the large number of children who need spectacles on the current waiting list for service.  In addition, the HSE has made a decision to abolish the sixth class vision screening and has not yet put in place a national policy to replace this.  This has been done for funding reasons.  Children over the age of eight should be seen in the community by optometrists and this policy should be implemented on a national basis.  This policy would reduce such unnecessary delay.</p> <p>Cataract surgery is a life-changing procedure that can restore the sight of elderly people, giving them back their independence and reducing the cost of preventable sight loss to the Exchequer, family members and carers.  Despite the merits of this operation, according to the report, people with cataracts in my constituency who are referred to a hospital's eye service due to reduced vision are waiting on average 29 months to have surgery to restore their sight.  Those who can afford to pay for the operation must only wait three months, whereas those without money to pay for it must wait 29 months.  While use of the National Treatment Purchase Fund can reduce waiting lists in the short term, it does not address the systematic inefficiencies in the system we have in place.  We need to address these issues and bring back the scheme that was in place.</p> <p>I support Senator Mullen's request that the Taoiseach clarify the unacceptable comments he made yesterday.  He must clarify exactly what he meant by them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" speakername="Gabrielle McFadden" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#J00500"><p>I feel as if I am repeating myself every week as I am raising the issue of the Defence Forces again today.  I welcome the fact that the Public Service Pay Commission's report into pay and recruitment in the Defence Forces is before Cabinet and that it will be finally released.  We have waited far too long for the report.  This is the 20th time in the past two years that I have raised the issue of pay and conditions in the Defence Forces.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Gabrielle McFadden:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2399"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2399&amp;amp;pid=GabrielleMcFadden&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Like Senator Craughwell, I, too, have raised a variety of issues pertaining to the Defence Forces which affect morale.  The major issue is pay.  Today's report will not solve all of our problems, but it is welcome that progress is being made.  The reversal of the cuts to allowances made back in the day is very important.  I also welcome the restoration of the duty allowance.  It is welcome that PDFORRA is supporting it.  It put the case to the Public Service Pay Commission and both it and the Government listened.  However, we need to ensure we will do more.  No soldier wearing the Irish uniform should work for less than the living wage which is greater than the national minimum wage.  No one should ever have to rely on family income supplement, as I have said on numerous occasions.  I hope today is not the end of a process.  I believe it is not but the first step in the next one.  I will continue to lobby on behalf of the members of the Defence Forces to ensure they are paid a fair day's pay for a fair day's work.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#K00200"><p>I raise a specific case, that of a 19 year old LGBT asylum seeker whose application for asylum based on his LGBT identity was rejected by the international protection officer at the Department of Justice and Equality.  The decision was posted on social media on Tuesday by MASI, Movement of Asylum Seekers in Ireland, and I encourage other Members to read it.  It is the assertion made by the international protection officer.  When asked if he was familiar with the Zimbabwean LGBT group GALZ, the applicant responded that he did not attend its services.  When asked why he had not sought its support, he responded by saying he felt more comfortable talking to his mum about it.  He also stated why he had not sought the help of support services in Ireland - he was trying to focus on his leaving certificate examinations.  The Department also asked whether he had ever been in a same sex relationship and, if not, why not.  He stated he was being bullied in schools because he was gay.  The Department concluded in its report that his contention that he was gay "is not credible".  Notwithstanding the fact that the State would never engage in that line of questioning or anything close to it with a heterosexual, the line of questioning used was insensitive, invasive, unnecessary and problematic.  We should consider that most Irish LGBT teenagers would not meet the burden of proof required by the Department.  I certainly would not have met it as a young teenager.  If the Department and the Minister want to march in the Dublin Pride parade, they should be honest and address this concern head on.  I hope that in the new term we can have a frank debate in this House on how we treat those seeking asylum, especially those who are LGBT.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#K00300"><p>I, too, agree with my colleague Senator McFadden on the need to deal with the pay issue in the Defence Forces.  In fairness to Defence Forces personnel, they have served the country well, both at home and overseas.  It is appropriate that we respond accordingly to recognise the work they do.  Many allowances were cut during the years and need to be restored.</p> <p>It is interesting to compare the situation in the Health Service Executive.  I know that my Sinn F&eacute;in colleague raised the issue of public sector pay.  The figures for the HSE show that from December 2014 to March 2019, a period of four years and three months, the number working in it has increased by 15,954, or by just 44 people short of 16,000.  That represents a significant increase of 15.46%.  The number of whole-time equivalents is now 118,984, but the interesting point is that the number of managerial and administrative staff increased by 24% in the same period of four years and three months, or 3,639.  That is a phenomenal increase in the public sector environment.  We need to put more money into public services, but there has been a disproportionate increase in the number of managerial and administrative staff.  My Sinn F&eacute;in colleague has constantly spoken about the need for more nurses, but I do not understand why that occurs.  Yesterday when the chairman of the new board of the HSE appeared before the Joint Committee on Health, I raised the issue of the disproportionate increase in the number of administrative and managerial staff.  One would not see it happen in the private sector.  Also in the HSE the number of nurse managers increased by 1,100, from 6,500 to 7,600, in the same period.  In the HSE one in every four staff is in an administrative-managerial role.  One could not afford to have that structure in the private sector.  I have serious concerns about the priority given in the employment of staff in the HSE.  Yes, the HSE has employed more nurses, consultants, junior doctors and care assistants, but the number of nurses recruited could be doubled, if the number of managerial and administrative staff was not increased to the same degree.  I do not accept that they are providing more back-up support for front-line staff.  I would like to have the issue debated in the House.  This is taxpayer's money.  I have worked out that it is costing an extra &euro;650 million a year and it is not a one off payment.  It represents nearly 50% of the cost of the natinal children's hospital in 12 months.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#K00400"><p>The acting Leader will now respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#K00500"><p>I thank Members for their contributions.  Senator Ardagh referred to the sale of mortgages by Ulster Bank.  The Central Bank of Ireland cannot stop the sale of this loan book to various vulture funds.  We need to put the consumer first.  For years we have had difficulties in the financial sector.  We are looking at the issues of the living wage, increasing salaries and rent increases, a significant issue which the Government has tried to address through the introduction of rent pressure zones.  Young couples find themselves priced out of the market.  We need to address the issue of their inability to buy a home.  Perhaps we might have a debate on various aspects of the housing issue as we may need to take a different approach in trying to sort it out.  When I was growing up, everybody aspired to owning his or her own home.  We were infatuated by it.  It is wonderful to own one's own home, but there are other mechanisms used elsewhere in Europe.  For example, in Germany people live their entire lives in a rented property.  Things have changed, but there is a cohort who still wish to own their own house.  We should be able to do more in that regard.</p> <p>Senators Craughwell, Colm Burke, O'Mahony and McFadden raised the issue of pay in the Defence Forces in the context of the report of the Public Service Pay Commission.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Frank Feighan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2014"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2014&amp;amp;pid=FrankFeighan&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The Senators felt that the commission stated that it was constrained by the terms of reference.  A valid point was made, especially about agencies and staff, as it is not possible for such staff to do a duty such as bomb disposal.  Defence Forces personnel have a difficult job to do.  It is a job I would not be able to do.  I will state how great the Defences Forces are, even if there has been a request to not do so.  We are very proud of those personnel, along with those who serve in the Garda.  They have served our State extremely well.  We are trying to reach a situation where we can address the prevailing issues.  This is a major step forward.  That was acknowledged in Senator Craughwell's statement but we need to do much more.  Senator McFadden has highlighted this issue as well.  The proposal is going before the Cabinet and the Government will give due consideration to the findings and recommendations arising from the work of the commission.  This is the start of a process and I hope that we can bring things that little bit further.  Senator Craughwell called for a Gleeson-type commission.  This is a process and hopefully today is a step in the right direction.</p><p>Senator Mullen spoke about a new covenant between the State and the church.  When the State was formed, we invited the church in and too close a link was developed.  I think that was corrosive both to the State and to the church.  I acknowledge the great work the church has done since the foundation of the State.  It provided education and health services.  It was rightly mentioned that decent and selfless people have stood up, admitted that wrongs were done and said that they wanted to right them.  The Senator hit on something when he said that in the past ten years, and this may have derived from abuses within the church, there was an emphasis on a "shame on you" sentiment.  In the past ten years, respect has diminished for politicians, members of the church, teachers and members of the Garda.  Those people provide a great service to the State, notwithstanding the issues of which we are rightly ashamed.  It might now be time to remember the selfless people as well.  I have only found out about the Taoiseach's remarks, which Senator O'Mahony raised as well.  Senator Mullen suggested it was time to reflect on those remarks.  While I did not hear them, I hope that in the coming hours, something will be clarified or there will be reflection on the statements made. </p><p>Senator Devine raised issues involving the Irish Congress of Trade Unions, ICTU, Ms Patricia King, economic indicators and the higher rate of tax.  The minimum rate has increased.  The bogus employment contracts at the national children's hospital need to be addressed.  I would have thought that mechanisms were in place with the unions in order that any abuses could be highlighted through various channels.  It would not, however, be any harm to bring in the Minister to talk about those contracts, as well as other aspects of this matter.  Senator Colm Burke made the point that politicians come and go but the public service continues.  It is worrying that there has been nearly a 25% increase in managerial staff in the past five years.  Perhaps those extra people are not helping the front-line staff.  It would be no harm to bring in-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#L00200"><p>That was not my issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#L00300"><p>Yes, but Senator Colm Burke has addressed this from another angle so perhaps-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#L00400"><p>It is nothing to do with the issue involving ICTU.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#L00500"><p>Perhaps, however, it would be no harm to bring in the Minister and we can discuss all of those issues.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#L00600"><p>That is for Senator Colm Burke and not for me.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#L00700"><p>Perhaps we can bring in the Minister, and, as a group, discuss all of these issues with the Minister and clarify many of them.</p> <p>Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in spoke about Scotland and tough justice.  I remember discussing the drugs issue many years ago, involving cannabis, crack cocaine and other drugs.  The Senator called on the Minister of State, Deputy Catherine Byrne, to come before this House to debate the matter and broader issues of crime and poverty, as well as for the publication of a report on-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#L00800"><p>It was a working group report on-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#L00900"><p>-----drugs decriminalisation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#L01000"><p>Yes, that is correct.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#L01100"><p>We can ask the Minster of State, Deputy Catherine Byrne, to come in and we can discuss that issue as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#L01200"><p>I thank the acting Leader.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#L01300"><p>Senator Warfield spoke about an asylum seeker from an LGBT background and indicated that the questions he was asked were inappropriate.  I am not fully aware of the situation but were the Senator to provide the details to the Minister, the matter could be investigated.  Senator Warfield stated that he felt that what happened was not credible.  We will see what is the position.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#L01400"><p>Did the acting Leader forget about me?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#L01500"><p>Senator Murnane O'Connor referred to the issue of waiting lists and sixth class vision screening.  She said that some people have to wait for more than three months.  She also mentioned that the National Treatment Purchase Fund, NTPF, has been very encouraging.  We again might bring in the Minister so that we could discuss this matter.  It could also be an issue for an Commencement matter debate and the Cathaoirleach might be kind enough to accept it for next week.  As I mentioned, Senator Colm Burke outlined the various issues regarding the public sector.  I come from a business and self-employment background.  An eye has to be kept peeled in business.  If the overheads are more than what is being taken in, then that business is in trouble.  The country and the economy are going extremely well but we need to keep an eye on it and check that all is well.  That could be another debate we might have.  I thank the Cathaoirleach.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#L01600"><p>Before I ask if the Order of Business is agreed, I am sure the House will join with me in wishing the acting Leader a very happy birthday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#L01700"><p>Happy birthday, l&aacute; breithe sona d&oacute;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#L01800"><p>I think Senator Feighan is 40 today, so enjoy the day.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#L01900"><p>I was very encouraged by the words of the Cathaoirleach last night and his good wishes on my birthday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#L02000"><p>I thank Senator Feighan. That set him in motion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#L02100"><p>Every year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.68" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.69" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#L02300">Sitting Arrangements: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#L02400"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That, notwithstanding anything in the Standing Orders relative to Public Business, the Seanad shall meet at 3.30 p.m. on Tuesday, 9th July, 2019 and the following arrangements shall apply: <br /><br /><i>(a)</i>Standing Orders 29 and 30 shall stand suspended;<br /><br /><i>(b)</i>the Order of Business shall be taken at the commencement of public business.&rdquo;</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.71" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.72" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 12.20 p.m. and resumed at 12.45 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.73" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#O00100">Teachtaireachtaí ón Dáil - Messages from Dáil</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#O00200"><p>D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann passed the Parole Bill 2016 on 3 July 2019, to which the agreement of Seanad &Eacute;ireann is desired.  D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann passed the Local Government Rates and Other Matters Bill 2018, changed from the Local Government (Rates) Bill 2018, on 3 July 2019, to which the agreement of Seanad &Eacute;ireann is desired.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.75" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#O00300">Climate Action Plan: Statements</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#O00400"><p>I thank the Senators for tabling this debate.  I do not need to tell people in the House that it is probably one of the most important challenges that face humanity.  As we reflect on a decade during which the country has achieved extraordinary things, as we reformed our Constitution, changed our outlook and brought an economy from bankruptcy back to full employment, which were fantastic achievements and show the resilience and capacity of people to reinvent themselves, we have to bring the same creativity to bear on this, which is the greatest challenge that faces humanity.</p> <p>We cannot avoid recognising that in recent years, since the recovery commenced, it is very clear we failed to break the link between economic prosperity and the emissions that are doing untold damage to the globe.  It is against this background that we developed the process in place.  It was part of the programme for Government to have, in the first instance, the Citizens' Assembly evaluate this challenge.  It came back with a very strident demand on the Oireachtas to reform in a range of areas.  We followed this up with a model that was used in some of those other very difficult changes that we had ask people to come with us upon, such as changing our Constitution.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Richard Bruton:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=119"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=119&amp;amp;pid=RichardBruton&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We followed them up with in-depth hearings held by Members of both Houses at the climate action committee which included Senator Lombard.  It laid very important foundations.  I will not say entire consensus was reached, but a great deal of common ground was found within thee Houses on the challenges and direction in which we had to travel.</p><p>I have produced a climate action plan which sets out in detail the targets on which we aim to deliver in the period to 2030.  I have adopted it on the precautionary principle which is in accordance with dealing with environmental challenges of this nature.  I have sought to achieve the 30% reduction without recourse to things like assuming the price of oil will be high which would make it much easier to achieve or that we will use certain flexibilities to transfer moneys that would have come to us in the ETS to offset credits because of our failure to reach our targets.  It is an ambitious plan which is consistent with our very strong support for the proposal that Europe adopt a net zero target by 2050.  We will undertake the work to see what it would imply in detail between 2030 and 2050.  In designing this set of proposals we have been conscious that they should be consistent with meeting a net zero target by 2050.</p><p>How we frame the debate is important as we move from a position where there is a great deal of common ground within the Oireachtas on what we should do to bring people with us.  While the Government has an obligation to lead this change, every sector of Irish society needs to come with us.  It is important for us to present it in a way that will bring people with us.  A number of features of the plan will help us to do that.  First, we have chosen measures that are both sensible and fair.  In using the word "sensible" we have evaluated the least-cost proposals to get us to our targets.  In what areas can we achieve them without creating the greatest burden on people and which ones would open the most opportunities?</p><p>The plan contains specific proposals such as eliminating non-recyclable plastics; establishing microgeneration; setting the 70% renewable target for the power system; having 950,000 electric vehicles which would amount to one third of purchases between now and then; expanding park and ride facilities; reinforcing public transport; having heat pumps in 400,000 homes;&middot;the specific accountability in each sector for carbon budgets of each of our ministerial colleagues who oversee transport, construction and so on; having very strong oversight driven by the Oireachtas which is very much at the heart of the plan; and retrofitting 500,000 homes.  We have chosen this approach to do the things that can help us to achieve our targets with the least burden and also to have governance and oversight to deliver on them.  We have been at pains to ensure they are seen to be fair in that we are demanding that every section of Irish society contribute.  That is why we have very strong sections on the obligations of enterprise, farming and the public service, as well as the changes we need to achieve on the roads, in our homes and the habits we develop.  We recognise the importance of supporting the people who are most exposed such as those in the solid fuel sector that will see a very sharp decline or the individuals who are least equipped in this transition such as those on very low incomes.</p><p>How we describe what we are trying to achieve is important.  Many people, including some colleagues, have asked what the cost and our targets will be.  If we start to present it that it is about hitting some global targets set for us by the United Nations and talk about imposing cost on people, we will have undersold why we are doing it.  We are doing it for the good of the planet, not because some UN body has happened to set a schedule in which we appear.  We are doing it because we are part of humanity, the love affair of which with fossil fuel has done enormous damage which will accelerate unless we redress it.  It is about the resilience of people in the future.  We need farms, homes and enterprises that are resilient because they have taken action now to protect themselves, instead of waiting and postponing when the cost of making these changes will be far greater and the damage will have been done to the planet we are seeking to protect.  This is very much about the responsibility and desire of every generation to protect the heritage it has received and pass on to our children something that is robust and resilient and will support them in the future.  Our current pattern will not do that.  We are, therefore, asking people to make the change for their children and coming generations.  That is at the heart of the plan and it is important to recognise it in that way.</p><p>I know that it is controversial to talk about putting a price on carbon, saying it is &euro;20 today and will be &euro;80 in 2030 and so on.  The reason we talk about putting a price on carbon is that it is doing enormous damage.  The 1 tonne or 10 tonnes of carbon a household issues each year is doing serious damage.  If it was seen as a big plume of smoke coming from the roof of a house, we would all recognise the damage, but because it is invisible and silent and its origin is not clear to us, we do not see it as damage.  With the price trajectory we are trying to ensure people, in making their decisions on whether they should use solid fuel, oil, gas or a heat pump, will recognise that their decisions will have a profound impact on the damage that will done to the planet.  Albeit they are doing it individually or making a small contribution, it is an essential choice and we can convey that message by putting a price on the damage caused.  It is the oldest approach that has always been taken: the polluter pays.  We need to recognise that there is damage and that the originator of that damage must in some way be responsible for it.  That is why we need a price on carbon.  We are not putting a price on it to gather money into the Exchequer to fund other things.  We will recycle it in a way that is best placed to help people in this transition.  It is a signal of the journey we need to take, but the money can be really valuable if it is redeployed to support people on the lowest incomes who have the biggest challenges to meet to fund the retrofit programmes needed on the journey.</p><p>Bringing it out into the community is important.  The Sustainable Energy Authority of Ireland, SEAI, has been doing great work in helping communities.  It has a really good programme, Sustainable Energy Communities.  There are now almost 300 programmes, but we need to increase that number to 1,500.  We need to explain and create opportunities for communities to participate in the transition.  That is why when we come to have renewable energy auctions, we will have a pot confined to community generation.  We will develop microgeneration.  We will try to make it real for people in order that they can see the plan as an opportunity for them to become more self-sufficient in using renewable sources to meet their needs and that if they have a surplus, they can sell it into the grid.</p><p>We need to support new technologies that are coming down the road in an appropriate way.  We have a &euro;500 million climate action fund in which we will be seeding new technologies.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Richard Bruton:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=119"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=119&amp;amp;pid=RichardBruton&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Members will already have seen from this year's allocation that biogas is one of the areas for which we have provided support.  This year, we are providing a grant for biomass to replace fossil fuels.  We have had a pilot for solar generation in homes.  We will move towards having a proper scheme for microgeneration.  It is very important, therefore, that we bring people together.</p><p>When considering greenhouse gas inventories, although the waste sector accounts for only 1 million tonnes and looks like it is trivial, we should realise the way in which we manage materials from their birth to the end of their life is crucial to the way we think about climate and climate change.  It is very important that people recognise the importance of preventing the generation of waste and moving towards a circular economy whereby one tries to maximise the use and reuse of materials rather than furthering the disposables culture that has been part of life in the past 25 years.  It is very important that we rethink this.  By doing so, we will rethink our set of habits.  I refer to how we use materials and fuels, how we create the fabric of our homes and how we travel.  It is important that, although waste might figure on a carbon inventory as very inconsequential, its significance is very great.  Some estimates suggest that 60% of all emissions come from materials and how we produce, use and dispose of them.  Getting people to think in this different way is a big part.</p><p>The Oireachtas has done a great job in creating a foundation on which we as a community can move forward together.  Of course there will be differences, arguments in favour of one instrument of policy over another, and scepticism, and we will be learning as we go, but we are using the approach that was adopted in the Action Plan for Jobs.  When I launched that plan, people said to me it was ludicrous and there was no way in which 100,000 jobs could be delivered.  They said they were expected to believe in the plan when there was no evidence to support it.  Now, with 500,000 jobs created in this economy, we reflect and see the benefit of being ambitious and bringing all the community together behind a set of actions.  They will not all be perfect but they will start a process that can act as a catalyst in making the change we need.</p><p>The position on the climate plan is the very same.  Members of the Government and Oireachtas have to start the process but it will be a catalyst to much wider change that we need to achieve.  That is why this is going to be a long journey.  We will be reflecting continually on, consulting on and amending the plan and introducing new policies where some have failed.  It is a journey but, at the end, the challenge will be well worth facing up to.  It will mean cleaner air, warmer homes and, more profoundly, it will mean our farms, enterprises and homes will be resilient for the future.  We will be putting our children into a position in which they can look to a decarbonised world with confidence because we have started and have not allowed ourselves to take the view that we should delay, wait for new evidence, wait for something else to happen or wait until we can afford it.  There are so many reasons for waiting but it is very important to start this journey.  We now have a plan that we can oversee through the new arms of the Oireachtas and hold Ministers to account in the years ahead.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#Q00200"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House and thank him for outlining the proposed plan on climate action.  Fianna F&aacute;il has a strong record on the introduction of climate change measures.  It recognises that the climate crisis is the defining global challenge of our time, and it is committed to ensuring Ireland does its fair share and meets legally binding commitments at EU and UN levels.  In May 2019, Fianna F&aacute;il ensured that the D&aacute;il declared a climate and biodiversity emergency and called for the issue of biodiversity loss to be considered by the Citizens' Assembly.  Global warming and associated biodiversity loss are already resulting in a range of adverse economic, environmental, health and social impacts, and the outlook is deteriorating.  Every action and every year of delay matters.  Future generations should not have to bear the brunt of the impacts.  Young people are very conscious of this.  Last Monday week, Roscommon County Council declared a climate and biodiversity emergency.  That was a decision proposed by Councillor Donal Kilduff and seconded by Councillor Orla Leyden.  It was agreed unanimously by the council.  It showed leadership at local level that demonstrates councillors are prepared to work together in each area to implement the plans of their authorities and the Government.  In fact, before the agreement drawn up by Fianna F&aacute;il, Fine Gael and two independents on Roscommon County Council, a majority of the councillors had put forward a plan on the environment.  That is very positive.</p> <p>We have diesel locomotives on all the main rail lines.  Surely it is not beyond the bounds of possibility to electrify them.  It is worth examining how exactly we can reduce the amount of diesel and petrol being used.  It would be worth investigating the feasibility of electrification of some of the lines, be it the Dublin-Belfast line or another.  I am not sure what the procedure would be or the work involved.  It would certainly be a step in the right direction as far as I am concerned.</p> <p>The Environmental Protection Agency, EPA, now needs to analyse the climate impacts of Government commitments and verify that we can meet the 2030 target without paying millions for carbon credits.  The Climate Change Advisory Council needs to assess independently the adequacy of all proposed measures and ensure that they are in line with our Paris Agreement commitments.  Climate action is not simply an all-of-government challenge.  It presents a cross-societal opportunity.  It is a national issue and should be dealt with not on a party political basis but on a united all-Ireland basis to bring about the changes required.</p> <p>This plan is merely the start of the process.  The litmus test of Government action will be how quickly Fine Gael moves to put necessary legislation and policies in place.  What we do in 2019 is far more important than where we say we will be in 2050.</p> <p>The main weakness of the 2019 climate plan is that it is not costed beyond Project Ireland 2040 commitments.  The costs of enabling infrastructure, such as the electric vehicle, EV, charging network, are not outlined.  The plan fails to put forward any annual costings for actions or to clarify how much would fall on non-Exchequer sources.  This plan outlines emissions reductions of 2% per annum up to 2030, with reductions of 7% envisaged thereafter.  This approach goes against the recommendations of climate scientists and economists who have emphasised that delayed efforts only increase the risks of disastrous impacts and serve to drive up the costs of the transition.</p> <p>Fianna F&aacute;il is concerned that certain actions and timelines from the cross-party Oireachtas report have not been incorporated.  By contrast with the position in other EU states, the plan excludes a commitment to introduce into legislation a new long-term net zero target to decarbonise the economy by 2050.  Necessary amending legislation on climate action is to be delayed until 2020, as are necessary new measures on how better to support those vulnerable to fuel poverty.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Terry Leyden:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=636"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=636&amp;amp;pid=TerryLeyden&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The plan principally focuses on those areas which put the responsibility on citizens, such as extremely ambitious targets for electric vehicles and home retrofits.  Even with additional grants and incentives, the high upfront costs associated with these measures will make them inaccessible to poorer households.</p><p>It is extremely disappointing that the guiding principle of climate justice is limited to multilateral processes.  The plan is extremely weak on necessary measures and community supports to achieve a just transition for communities and workers in carbon-intensive industries, particularly in the midlands.  It is very important the IDA and the Minister for Business, Enterprise and Innovation would ensure those jobs will be replaced in the regions.</p><p>I commend the Minister on his efforts.  He has taken a very definite approach.  By working together, I believe all of us can make a difference, which is the point.  I know from talking with my 12 year old granddaughter, Donata Maria, that she is very concerned.  Pupils in schools are deeply concerned and they are bringing about change, for example, in regard to plastic cups and so on.  That is a step in the right direction.  We need to bring into schools the plan the Minister is putting forward and encourage teachers to discuss climate change.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#R00200"><p>I welcome the Minister.  This is a very important debate in regard to the climate action plan and where we are going in this very important space.  The Minister is correct that this is a debate of our generation in order to ensure we have a planet to hand on to the next generation, which is a great responsibility on everybody who attends the debate today.  I am somewhat disappointed that only four Members out of 60 have come to discuss this issue, given it is one of the biggest issues we have to deal with.  To think we only have a handful of Senators present is quite disappointing.</p> <p>This is about trying to bring people with us, which is the point I wish to focus on today.  It is about how we get community involvement and get that bottom-up approach in order that we can ensure that all communities and all sectors can work together to deliver this.  We have talked about transition towns, one of which is Kinsale, where fantastic work is done.  However, there are only 250 to 260 transition towns and we need to promote the concept in every town in Ireland.  If we have that buy-in and input from the bottom up, then we will have real change because schools, community associations and society itself will come together and work to deliver what we have to deliver, which is a real change in our society and how we deal with such matters.</p> <p>While the bottom-up approach is very important, the all-of-Government approach is also very important.  The Minister rightly mentioned the jobs plan of some years ago, when vast numbers were brought into employment.  That came from an all-of-Government approach and that approach is very important in regard to this plan also.  It brings responsibility on all Departments to work together to deliver the ambition of this plan.</p> <p>Those are the two issues we need to ensure we get right.  If we can get all of Government working to deliver this and can get the communities involved at the bottom of the tree, we will, hopefully, see a major change in society.  There will be major change, whether in farming and the farming community, in energy or in how we drive our cars and what kind of cars we drive.  There will be significant change if we are to reach our 2030 and 2050 targets.  However, I believe there is buy-in.  Society has moved with us and it is really on this page.  Four or five years ago, one could argue the point, but there is no arguing now.  People want change and they actually demand change.  They want the Oireachtas and the Government to ensure that change happens.  We are in a different space.  Society has bought in and the Government is definitely buying in with this climate action plan.  We now need to make sure that we can get both the bottom-up approach and the whole-of-Government approach to work together to make sure we can deliver this plan.</p> <p>It will be an evolving plan and an evolving process.  The Minister is correct that not everything is going to work.  New technologies and new issues will come on board, and this is something we have to be open to.  Just because something fails does not mean the plan fails; it means that we need to analyse it and move on to something else.  We have to realise this will be part of this plan.  Just because one issue fails does not mean the entire plan fails.  This is about ensuring we evolve, change and build on the plan to ensure we deliver what we have to deliver for society.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#R00400"><p>Before we proceed, we have in the Visitors Gallery, Julia Donnelly, an intern from New York serving in the Houses of the Oireachtas.  As it is the Fourth of July, it is only right and proper that we should wish her and her colleague, Amber, and the other interns from the United States a happy Fourth of July.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#R00500"><p>She can take a message back to Trump.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#R00600"><p>She will take a message back to Trump about the Fourth of July and all that is good, positive and progressive about the United States.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#R00800"><p>I welcome the Minister.  I acknowledge the recognition by the Government that we are in a climate emergency.  It gives me no pleasure to remind people that this declaration has been made as Ireland trails behind our European partners.  Ireland's emissions have been rising steadily while other countries have been reducing theirs.  We are now playing catch-up and it is vital that we choose solutions that are evidence-based and based on science, as we no longer have the luxury of time to experiment with ideas.  Unfortunately, this is where I think the all-of-Government climate action plan runs aground.</p> <p>I say this while acknowledging the work that has been done by this House over the past year.  In July of last year, the special Joint Committee on Climate Action was established and I was honoured to be a member of it.  We considered the deliberations of the Citizens' Assembly.  It is fair to say that none of us at the time appreciated the scope and breadth of the problem, nor the scale of the challenge ahead.  The committee spent months scoping and quantifying the problems in agriculture, transport, housing and energy production, so much so that we had little time to adequately investigate solutions - proven solutions which were clearly evidence-based and verifiable.</p> <p>There is an absence of this in the climate action plan, which can be described as a melting pot of ideas, based on an approach of, "Let us try this and see what happens".  It is high on aspirations but we need to be much more specific.  It uses words like "investigate", "review", "examine" and "consider".  In my time here, I have learned that such words are not robust enough.  Second, it defers the bulk of our obligations until after 2030, which is 11 years away.  Third, it places a cost burden on the citizen while incentivising the market to sell the solutions.  I am not here just to be oppositional.  However, I want to be prudent and I want to go with the evidence that is available and that underpins what is positive and what is proven to work.</p> <p>Regrettably, it did not include an all-Ireland strategy despite the fact carbon dioxide and methane emitted in Strabane will not stop at the Border and will cross to Lifford.  While many of the individual actions in themselves appear laudable, there is no coherent, integrated strategy which we can say with any certainty will yield results.  The plans refers to banning the sale of combustion engine cars by 2030, stopping the burning of coal and peat, the increase of carbon tax by 500%, the deep retrofit of 500,000 houses, the shut-down of Moneypoint and the planting of more forestry.  These measure sound and are very laudable.  However, without any assessment of the availability, affordability or viability of alternatives, it simply seems to be a wish list of aspirational ideas.</p> <p>Let us look, for example, at the electric vehicle alternative to conventional cars.  When setting targets of almost 1 million EVs on the road by 2030, what consideration has the Government given to the affordability of this purchase?  In rural areas, many householders are two-car households so how viable is this target?  Indeed, given the housing pressures which have resulted in many adult children living back with their parents, many rural households have three or four vehicles.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator M&aacute;ire Devine:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2468"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2468&amp;amp;pid=MaireDevine&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The plan aims to incentivise single-car dependency across rural Ireland but it makes no provision whatsoever for a modal shift to public transport.  With six out of ten children travelling to school by car and only one out of ten children travelling to school by bus, the action plan makes no provision to shift tens of thousands of car journeys per day to public transport.  Let us assume for a moment that somehow or other, a two-car household managed to magic up the &euro;80,000 required for two EVs, and let us also assume that we get 1 million EVs on the road by 2030.  There is still no evidence that this will reduce emissions.</p><p>The Minister should look at Norway.  Norway has a similar population to Ireland and a similar level of emissions per capita.  It also has the second highest plug-in EV ownership in the world, at 300,000 units.  It has more land under forestry and it has a higher carbon tax than we do.  Despite all of this, Norway has failed to reduce its emissions at all since 2011.  On the other hand, neighbouring Sweden has almost twice the population of Ireland and has only 80,000 EVs, yet Sweden has exactly half of the emissions of either Norway or Ireland.  My point is that there is no concrete evidence that a transition to EVs would have any notable impact on our emissions over the next decade.</p><p>There are other environmental and ethical concerns about EVs, which have not been adequately cross-examined.  Over the next ten years, the powering of EVs will still be heavily reliant on coal, peat and gas.  We will still be using these fossil fuels to produce electricity.  Studies show that an EV powered by coal-burning electricity will not begin to return an environmental benefit until five years into its use.  There are also metrics which bring in the question of the environmental benefits, if any, of scrapping perfectly functional, low-emission combustion cars in favour of new EVs.  Just as we are complicit in the burning of blood coal at Moneypoint from the Cerrej&oacute;n mine in Colombia, we will now become complicit in the escalation of human rights abuses in cobalt mining for EV batteries in Congo.</p><p>It is fair to say there is no quantifiable or verifiable evidence that EV targets will have any meaningful impact on emission reduction, even if somehow or other, almost half of our current 2.6 million car owners could magically afford the outlay.  We cannot honestly predict whether a rolled-out charge network for EVs will not end up being a stranded asset by 2030, just like the electronic voting machines.  The aspirational target that 45,000 households per year, which after spending &euro;40,000 on an EV, will then borrow anything from &euro;30,000 to &euro;75,000 to do a deep retrofit on their homes-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#S00200"><p>The Senator needs to finish up soon.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#S00300"><p>I will.  Has the Minister identified who these homeowners are?  Of the 1.7 million private dwellings in the State, 500,000 are under mortgage and 30,000 are in distress and in danger of being sold to the vulture funds.  It is questionable whether these mortgage holders would be included in the retrofits that are due to happen in the next ten years because they are simply not affordable for them.  The only thing we know for certain is that we will fail spectacularly to meet our 2020 emission targets.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#S00400"><p>The Senator is out of time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#S00500"><p>I want to conclude by saying it is quite evident that &euro;430 million per year is collected in carbon tax and it will now be increased to &euro;600 million per year, yet we will be fined &euro;600 million per annum so if we do the maths, it is like we are raising taxes to prepare ourselves to be fined for our emissions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#S00600"><p>I call Senator O'Reilly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#S00700"><p>I thank the Acting Chairman-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#S00800"><p>Can I come in for a moment?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#S00900"><p>No, I am following the order and Senator O'Reilly is next.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#S01000"><p>I do not begrudge Senator O'Reilly his time but this is very unusual.  The Chairman usually takes representatives from each group.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#S01100"><p>I am just following the order on the paper.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#S01200"><p>I do not mind, I am happy to wait.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#S01300"><p>Senator O'Reilly is happy to wait.  I call Senator Norris.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#S01400"><p>The Acting Chairman is only following orders.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#S01500"><p>Yes, he is following orders like Corporal Hitler.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#S01600"><p>Senator Norris can take his eight minutes now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#S01700"><p>No, not at all.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#S01800"><p>Please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#S01900"><p>That is very civilised.  I was only trying to make a point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#S02000"><p>Come on, we are wasting time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#S02100"><p>I will not waste time arguing.  First, I want to say that we are lucky to have a Minister like this who is a highly civilised and cultivated man.  One of the interesting things about his presentation was that he spoke without reference to his notes and the entire speech was conducted clearly.  I would like to move a motion that if this does not happen automatically, the printed text of the Minister's speech, as issued to us, should also be included in the record of the House because it is important to have that detail.  I hope that can be done.</p> <p>It is interesting that there has been a small attendance, as has been mentioned.  For the first half an hour it was not even quorate.  We did not even have a quorum and the quorum has been reduced from 12 Members to six.  The Government has declared a climate-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#S02200"><p>I am surprised the Senator did not call a quorum.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#S02300"><p>-----emergency.  We used the word "Emergency" for the Second World War in this country.  If we really thought there was a war on, and there is, this House would be full, as it should be.</p> <p>On the tram on my way in today, I saw an advertisement for a gangster movie that said "The world's not going to save itself."  That is true.  We cannot await the planet coming to its own rescue.  We are all in this together and I would like to say to Senator Reilly that we discussed the Mercosur agreement yesterday and we were talking about Bolsonaro and the rainforests and so on.  Senator Reilly asked how we would like it if people started talking about our bogs and how we can say the rainforests in Brazil are our rainforests.  I want to say here and now that they are.  We are all in this together.  This is a planetary problem.  The rainforests do not belong to Brazil.  They were there long before the Spanish or the Portuguese conquered Brazil.  They are part of our inheritance and the bogs in Ireland are part of the world's inheritance as well because we are not alone and we have responsibility for the other life forms on this planet.</p> <p>As an aside, I would also like to say that we are only gradually becoming aware of this problem.  We did not think of it before.  I remember the hot summers in the 1950s and we thought it was glorious.  We had no idea of the damage that was being done even at that stage.  Some 25 years ago, I was on the transport committee and I remember raising the question of exhaust emissions from jet aeroplanes.  That has multiplied.  The Government is granting licences for fossil fuel exploration and that is a controversial area.  In every area where there are concerns we are not really living up to our responsibilities.  We are deliberately magnifying and investing in an enormous increase in air transport.</p> <p>I would like to look at the scale of the problem.  Of the assessed species living exclusively in Europe and Central Asia, 28% are threatened.  Among all the assessed groups of species living in the region, mussels and liverworts are particularly threatened.  Some 50% of mussels and liverworts are threatened, 37% of freshwater fish are threatened, 45% of freshwater snails are threatened, 33% of vascular plants are threatened and 23% of amphibians are threatened.  Three quarters of the land-based environment and about 68% of the marine environment have been significantly altered by human actions.  That is an extraordinary situation.  A recent and very dramatic report, which was compiled by an enormous variety of scientists, found that about 1 million animal and plant species are threatened with extinction, many within decades.  This is more than ever before in human history.  The average abundance of native species in most major land-based habitats has fallen by at least 20%.  More than 40% of amphibian species, 33% of reaffirming corals and more than a third of all marine animals are threatened.  These are staggering situations.</p> <p>Underneath it is something I have been trying to draw attention to, without any success, for all my political career, namely, the enormous expansion of the human population of the planet.  The global population, which is now three times what it was when I was born in 1944, is set to expand from today's figure of 7.3 billion to nearly 10 billion in 2050 and 11 billion by 2100.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator David Norris:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1758"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1758&amp;amp;pid=DavidNorris&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I do not see how the planet can sustain this.  It is underneath all of the difficulties, including climate change, and is something that cannot be ignored.  <br/><br/>The response of the fossil fuel industry is very interesting.  I have just read a report about how the industry responds to announcements about climate change.  Following the announcement that 2015 was the hottest year on record, CNN aired 23.5 minutes of advertisements by Vote for Energy, a project of the American Petroleum Institute, compared with approximately five minutes of coverage of climate change or the temperature records.  It is a five to one balance in favour of coverage sponsored by the oil industry.  In the week after the hottest year announcement, CNN aired less than one minute of climate-related coverage and 13.5 minutes of oil industry advertisements.  Following the announcement that February 2016 was the most unusually hot month ever, CNN aired four minutes of climate-related coverage and ten minutes of fossil fuel advertisements.  Coverage is hugely disproportionate.  The fossil fuel industry is trying to win the argument with the public and that is where we must be active.<br/><br/>Certain things are happening.  Government policy is frequently interrupted by considerations of, for example, the property rights that are enshrined in the Constitution.  In this regard, I have always said that no Government has ever taken into account the question of the public good.  I urge the Minister to take on board that we need to consider the public good as a primary motivating factor in legislation.  This is starting to happen in America, which has, for example, what is known as atmospheric trust litigation.  This is an approach that considers the atmosphere to be held in trust by government for the public.  It is not something to be dealt with by the government alone.Interestingly, a very significant case has been won in the American courts.  A Pennsylvanian Supreme Court decision relied on the public trust doctrine to hold that a law promoting fracking violated a state constitutional right to a healthy environment.  That is one example.<br/><br/>While I have praised the Minister, Deputy Bruton, I wish to put on record the response of the Taoiseach who made the following statement in January 2018 in the European Parliament: </p><blockquote>As far as I am concerned, we are a laggard.  I am not proud of Ireland's performance of climate change.</blockquote><p>That is an astonishing admission for the leader of the Government to make.  We have had the announcement, which is very welcome, that-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#T00200"><p>The Senator's time is up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#T00300"><p>I did not receive any notice of that.  With the indulgence of the Chair, I will make a couple of quick points.  The Citizens' Assembly gave a resounding call, which was echoed by the Oireachtas joint committee, which issued a landmark report with 41 detailed recommendations.  The D&aacute;il voted to declare a climate emergency and to accept and endorse the recommendations of the committee.  We are waiting to see if this will be fully implemented in law, which is the responsibility of the Minister. </p> <p>We have to ask three specific questions.  First, does the plan acknowledge the scale of the challenge and have we confronted the reality of what is facing us?  Second, does the plan commit to putting the Oireachtas joint committee's recommendations on governance into law by the end of the year?  This is the only practical way to address the issue.  Finally, does the plan commit to implementing the recommendations of the joint committee in full and on time to cut emissions in every sector?  I thank the Acting Chairman for her indulgence.  I also thank Senator O'Reilly.  I did not mean to delay his contribution.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#T00400"><p>It was my pleasure.  We could not deny the House the Senator's eloquence.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#T00500"><p>I genuinely compliment the Minister.  It was most interesting that he was motivated to speak without reference to his notes.  He made a passionate speech. I believe that he is committed and I hope that he gets support from his Government colleagues and the rest of Parliament.</p> <p>It will be a pity if this issue is reduced to party politics and accusations that Fianna F&aacute;il did this, Fine Gael did not do that and so on.  That is nonsense when we are confronting an emergency.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#T00600"><p>With respect, the Senator is well over his time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#T00700"><p>Rubbish.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#T00800"><p>We were talking about Bolsonaro.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#T00900"><p>I welcome my colleague, the Minister for Communications, Climate Action and Environment, Deputy Bruton.  If the Action Plan for Jobs, which he initiated, launched, supervised and managed, is a yardstick or indicator as to what will happen in this instance, we can be extraordinarily optimistic.</p> <p>It is good that we have clear objectives of meeting our 2030 target and reaching zero emissions by 2050.  We should not see this issue in purely punitive terms.  This can create great and very interesting healthy lifestyle changes and can also create new employment opportunities and a new quality of life.  It is not necessarily negative and should not be seen in those terms.</p> <p>Given that time is short, I will race through a few specific issues and proposals.  Charging points for electric vehicles are a major issue.  On "Morning Ireland" this morning, we heard that the lack of charging points is an issue in County Sligo.  It is also an issue in my county and everywhere else.  We need more charging points.</p> <p>Speaking of charging points and electric cars, which obviously form part of what we want to do, I proposed some time ago that a grant or an incentive be provided for first-time drivers who decide to buy an electric car.  If an electric car is their first car, they will continue to buy electric vehicles, develop a sense of ownership of the climate change agenda and adopt a lifestyle to match in which they will take pride.  We should incentivise first-time drivers to buy electric cars more than other drivers, as we do in the case of first-time buyers of houses.  I appeal to the Minister to consider that proposal. </p> <p>The Minister's plan to retrofit 500,000 homes has great merit.  The idea of doing this in clusters based on an agreed price with contractors is a very good one.  I suggest that this idea be expedited.  Easy payment methods and supports should be provided for poorer people.  The proposal has merit in that it will result in energy savings, reduced heating bills, less fuel poverty and so on.  It is a wonderful idea which could have a great outcome.</p> <p>I have the privilege of being a member of the Joint Committee on Communications, Climate Action and Environment.  The Minister will recall from his meetings with the committee that I often raise the issue of microgeneration and allowing people to sell electricity into the grid.  The Minister should run very quickly with that idea.</p> <p>He should also examine the model used by the creameries and co-operatives at the end of the 19th century and beginning of the 20th century and provide for community microgeneration where people in a village might own a microgenerator, just as they owned the creamery of old.  They would receive a reward from that.  This would get the whole climate change agenda into the public consciousness.</p> <p>I am told by people who know much more about this issue than I do that Ireland's new gold could be offshore wind.  We have the right tidal conditions to be a pioneer in developing offshore wind energy and become a world supplier.  I ask the Minister to comment on that specific issue.</p> <p>We must avoid fuel poverty.  While all of this is wonderful and laudable, if we introduce a carbon tax, people in receipt of the State pension or social welfare payments must be insulated from fuel poverty or a diminution in their living standards.  We should devote the money saved by not having to pay fines or purchase carbon credits to the poor and those who are not in a position to buy fuel.</p> <p>The Minister made an interesting point on eliminating single-use plastics.  That is a lifestyle change which should be introduced.</p> <p>We should encourage the health insurance sector to support people who adopt a healthy lifestyle by cycling, walking and so on.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Joe O'Reilly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1610"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1610&amp;amp;pid=JoeOReilly&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Insurance policies should provide credits for such activities.  People should be given better life insurance policies if they have evidence of undergoing health checks or of walking or cycling to work.  While that could present administrative difficulties, creative ways of doing it could be found.  This approach has been implemented in Singapore to great effect.  If it can be done there, why not here?  I appeal to the Minister to have his officials look at the example of Singapore in this regard.  </p><p>I will make one final point and in that regard I thank the Acting Chairman for her indulgence.  I live in the constituency of Cavan-Monaghan.  A small parcel of land that is not arable should be planted on every farm and farmers should be incentivised to do so.  When I was a child there was a kind of ribbon or shelter belt on every farm and there were trees around the house.  That should still be the case.  There are parts of every farm that are less arable and farmers should be encouraged to plant these.  I would like to hear the Minister's response to that proposal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#U00200"><p>A wise person whom I know is fond of saying that we should live simply so that others may simply live.  This sums up the view many of us aspire to have in respect of environmental matters.  We have a duty to act responsibly towards the environment out of respect both for the world around us and the well-being and survival of our fellow human beings now and into the future.  We should show solidarity across time and space in all our thinking in this area.  Even if there was no evidence of a changing climate or that climate change was caused by man or if there was no international movement on the issue, we should still be trying to change some of our more negative habits in our own interests and in the interests of the world around us.</p> <p>We have made significant progress and changed attitudes in many ways.  While there has been a sea change, a huge amount remains to be done.  I understand it is still the case that a large proportion of what goes into our green bins is not recycled and ends up being incinerated.  That is indefensible if true.  I am interested to hear what the Minister has to say about that.  Likewise, the outrageous prevalence of single-use plastics in packaging, which has been mentioned by others, is indefensible.  We should be thankful that there has been a big change in people's attitudes.  I am confident that in the years to come we will look back on our use of plastic in the same way as we now look back on the nonsensical use of plastic bags in supermarkets in the past.  </p> <p>We can also do more to reduce the carbon footprint of our imports by shopping locally, or at least within Europe, to the greatest extent possible.  With that in mind, it seems very difficult for the European Union to defend aspects of the Mercosur trade deal which could see 99,000 tonnes of South American beef transported across the Atlantic every year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#U00300"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#U00400"><p>That deal is the first policy proposal in history to unite farmers and environmentalists.  It is quite an achievement if one thinks about it that way.  Having said all of that, I simply do not buy into some of the more extreme rhetoric surrounding the issue of climate change.  For example, during the recent children's climate change protests I was struck by the comments made by many of the children in attendance.  Many seemed to think that they, along with the rest of us, will literally be dead due to climate change within the next 20 or 30 years.  No reputable scientist anywhere has made doomsday claims such as these and yet the idea appears to have gained some currency among younger people.  What kind of society are we fostering if children can have such a profoundly depressing and scientifically inaccurate view of where our world is heading?  While Greta Thunberg may be a very admirable young person in many ways, I wonder about the Greta Thunberg phenomenon.</p><p>I also wonder about the general phenomenon of people who govern us, while being adults in years, lacking maturity.  This may be partly due to many of them having no experience of a world outside politics.  There is a deference to children which does not really allow them to grow.  By all means, children should provoke us to thought but a failure of adult responsibility is evident in much of our public discussion, although the issues the children are prompting us to think about are important.  That is an aside.</p><p>There is also a small but vocal movement which advocates that humanity should start to voluntarily scale back our presence on the planet.  It suggests we should almost feel guilty for our own existence and that people should have fewer children.  Any debate on climate change in the media will usually have at least one reference to the supposedly exponential rate at which the population is increasing around the world.  I heard what Senator Norris had to say and I think that too was a load of Bolsonaro in some respects.  This movement ignores the fact that the populations of most European countries are now falling, particularly those in eastern Europe.  Birth rates in all parts of the developing world have plummeted in recent decades.  I recently read a book by Darrell Bricker, the current global CEO of the polling company Ipsos, and John Ibbitson, one of the most respected journalists in Canada, in which they suggest the global population will peak in 2050 and fall consistently thereafter.  The facts of this issue rarely get any proper focus.  They are certainly not <i>ad idem</i>with Senator Norris's comments.</p><p>To properly tackle the climate issue and our environmental problems we need to retain a sense of perspective.  That is all I am saying.  Overblown rhetoric does not help in the long run.  We need to exercise caution about accepting any one measure or set of measures as dogma that must be adhered to.  One of the extraordinary features of the debate on the environment over the last ten years has been that the path behind us is strewn with policies and measures which have had consensus support but have since been abandoned because they proved to be unrealistic or counterproductive.  I do not mean to single out the Green Party because on some issues, although only on some, it can act as our conscience or provoke us to necessary reflection.  I do, however, recall its past enthusiasm for bioethanol as an alternative to petroleum fuels.  The international green movement and governments have since abandoned this fuel because it diverts production away from food for human populations.  Diesel cars were once encouraged as an alternative and, accordingly, taxed at a lower rate but this stance has since been abandoned.  As the Minister knows, this State once gave generous grants for wood pellet boilers.  This has also been abandoned and many such boilers have been ripped out of homes.  I believe the company which carried out most of this work has gone bankrupt.  The list of past mistakes goes on.  My point is that we should be very slow to adopt any one measure or set of measures as an orthodoxy which must be followed unquestioningly because we risk making the same mistakes again.</p><p>Many of the 183 action points in the climate action plan are laudable but I worry that some of the proposals are unrealistic and risk becoming the broken promises and abandoned plans of the years to come.  For this reason, it does the Government no credit to advance them.  The proposal to have 1 million electric cars on our roads by 2030 seems very unrealistic.  There were fewer than 1,400 electric cars sold in 2018 and I do not see how that number will increase to more than 50,000 in the coming years, which is what would be required to meet this target.  This policy brings with it environmental concerns of its own.  More electric cars means higher demand for the lithium, cobalt and copper needed for their components.  We have heard about this already today.  These metals are mostly mined in Africa, often in very harsh conditions.  Tesla is already warning of a shortage of these materials.  As with bioethanol in the past, are we running the risk of adopting a policy which could lead to unintended consequences in poorer and developing countries?  </p><p>Is it really possible to cut our carbon emissions by 30% by 2030 and to be carbon neutral by 2050 in light of the national development plan which foresees growth in agriculture and transport?  These targets seem to be impossible to meet.  The action plan also seeks to retrofit 500,000 homes to a B2 building energy regulation, BER, standard.  This will involve massive expense which will be unaffordable for ordinary households.  Similar previous schemes for retrofitting insulation had relatively low take-up for that reason.  Would it not make more sense to demand minimum standards for new builds rather than expecting costly retrofitting of existing dwellings?  This has the hallmarks of an unrealistic Green Party policy of a decade ago, which may end up being abandoned.  </p><p>This is an extremely important agenda but we do not gain in the long term by making claims and setting targets out of a sense of panic which deep down we do not intend to meet or believe we can meet.  That is the challenge I pose in what I have to say today.  While I commend the Government on its intentions, as policymakers, great and small, we all have a duty to be truthful and realistic about what can be done.  My fear is that many aspects of this plan seem intended to give the appearance of radical action which our political system has no capability of delivering in the long term.  Rather than pretending that we can make radical changes to our way of life, we should instead work to achieve the best we can to alleviate the impact of climate change on those who will be worst affected.  Many people are much more comfortable with the idea that we will have to make great sacrifices to live in solidarity with the people who will be most affected by changes it is not possible to avoid.  That is where many people are and it is where our focus should be.  That is another way in which we could live simply so that others may simply live.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#U00500"><p>I wish to raise a number of important issues in the short time I have.  Do I have four minutes?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#U00600"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#U00700"><p>That is even less time than I had anticipated.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#U00800"><p>Senator Reilly could do a Norris.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#U00900"><p>I welcome the Minister and thank him for his speech and the accompanying written text.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator James Reilly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2180"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2180&amp;amp;pid=DrJamesReilly&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I want to pick up on a few comments colleagues have made.  Electric vehicles will become more affordable, not less affordable; that is the nature of all technology.  The Government is doing the right thing in supporting people who buy them.  As time goes by, the smaller city cars will become ever cheaper.</p><p>I try not to be political but I find it very difficult not to comment on Sinn F&eacute;in's approach.  It is the same old approach of describing the problem, giving out about the problem and protesting, but offering no solution.  There is a well-thought-out solution on offer from the Minister and the Government on climate action.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#V00150"><p>Science, evidence.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#V00200"><p>Nobody interrupted the Senator.</p> <p>The Minister has made it very clear that this process is flexible and can deliver, and from that delivery we can learn and from that learning we can refine and modify as time goes by; nothing stays stationary, as we know.</p> <p>Members referred to electric car technology and batteries.  A lot of research is being done on graphene, which will allow batteries to have a much longer charge without the need for cobalt and allow less lithium to be used.</p> <p>I support what Senator Joe O'Reilly said.  The idea of community generation of electricity is great.  The small wind turbines are far too expensive; the larger turbines are more efficient.  The whole community would gain from taking ownership of that and it could be successful.</p> <p>I particularly welcome the Minister's move on giving microgenerators access to the network so that they can sell their electricity.  This will be hugely important, not so much because of the volume of electricity it might generate but in sending a strong message that we are serious about this.</p> <p>We hear about all the problems that relate to climate change and the challenges that it poses, but the Minister has outlined significant opportunities in agriculture and farming, such as anaerobic digesters.  Solar farms have been trialled in Germany, with panels on 3 m stilts, and they got 90% productivity from the land on top of what they get from the sun.  I have mentioned several times encouraging farmers to have solar panels on their sheds and the need to review the limit that currently exists for solar panels on domestic dwellings.  Why is it such a small number?  What is wrong with having more?  The limit relates to solar panels for water rather than for electricity.</p> <p>There is very good news coming out of Fingal, which was asked to take the lead for the four authorities in Dublin on piloting charging points for cars on electricity poles.  It is now seeking expressions of interest to roll that out across Dublin city, including Fingal.  That could be a game changer and would make it far easier for people to make the jump to hybrid or fully electric cars.</p> <p>The issue of single use plastic is particularly important and I welcome the Minister's commitment on that.  There is also the issue of Styrofoam, which is difficult to dispose of.  Nobody wants to handle it and it is not recycled.  We have to address that.</p> <p>Others have raised the point that green bins are for hard plastic only and not wrapping.  That has to change to make it easier for people to follow and to recycle.</p> <p>Senator Norris talked about "our" forests in Brazil.  I stand over what I said: the Brazilians own their forests just as we own our bogs.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#V00300"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#V00400"><p>We, of course, have a shared interest in them because of their impact on the environment and we should listen to each other, but to suggest otherwise is not just disingenuous but plain wrong.</p> <p>Earlier, a Senator talked about educating young people on this.  Younger people have taken this on board in a major way and there is great potential for an educational facility in Skerries.  With its ancient mills from a couple of centuries ago, there is an opportunity to show the development through the centuries of windmills to the modern turbines we have now.  It is not just a tourist attraction but an educational facility for children.</p> <p>The Minister's well-thought-out plans for retrofitting are welcome.  Nobody is being forced to do it; we are encouraging people.  For those who are considering it, they are future-proofing their homes against what will be uncertain fossil fuel markets.  I thank him for the plan and for the opportunity to debate it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#V00500"><p>I welcome the Minister.  I rile against the idea of a policy of what we can do.  I firmly believe that this is a policy of what we must do.  On climate change, it has reached the stage that the policies that we must implement have to take effect next week, not next month, next year or in the distant future.</p> <p>I welcome the sensible approach of 180 actions and several sub-actions.  It follows on from the successful Action Plan for Jobs.  There has to be flexibility within the action plan because not every one of those 180 actions will work.  However, we can learn from what does not work and move on and improve until we get it right.  The mood in Ireland is that politicians and scientists cannot make mistakes.  We all make mistakes; it is about how we learn from those mistakes and improve.</p> <p>Many Members referred to the policy of having 950,000 electric cars on our roads.  We need to examine that.  Should everybody have a car?  Do we need cars or are they outdated, especially in urban areas?  Should we look more at car-sharing mechanisms?  Our major cities of Dublin, Cork, Limerick and Galway all suffer from massive traffic jams and problems for commuters.  If diesel and petrol cars are replaced with electric cars, we will still have the same problems and congestion on our roads.  We need a level of joined-up thinking on whether we should race into replacing  petrol and diesel cars with electric cars.  It is not a long-term, sustainable policy.  We have to re-examine our modes of transport.</p> <p>I asked whether everybody needs a car, especially in urban areas, and that leads on to the issue of how we plan our cities and towns and how we increase density and plan green areas in and around them.  There will always be a need for private transport in rural areas; it is just the nature of it that people will need a personal vehicle of some description.  However, does that personal vehicle need to be able to travel between Galway and Dublin?  Can we share cars for long-distance journeys and use small electric cars in the areas where we live?</p> <p>The transition to the future could be quite exciting, with new means of transport and fuels.  However, it has to be a just transition.  Many people will be frightened by this transition and many people will lose their jobs and have to change their way of life.  In a just transition, we would plan for that; people would see the support available and the alternative careers.  That has to be worked at and the trust and confidence of the public has to be won, otherwise there will be major resistance.</p> <p>The other element, which will be difficult for me and every other politician in the country, is that we will have to stand up to powerful interest groups both in our own country and externally.  We cannot tackle climate change alone.  We have to develop international agreements to assist other people transitioning to a low-carbon economy, and that will be difficult.  That is where international trade agreements will come in.  Some people will lose in those international trade agreements and some will gain, but as a benchmark, such agreements have to be tied to the Paris accord and to standards on the use of antibiotics in animals.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Kevin Humphreys:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2289"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2289&amp;amp;pid=KevinHumphreys&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We are running out of a range of antibiotics to deal with human health, never mind animal health.  It will be a difficult period.  I will also have to change my thinking.  I will have to look at the powerful interest groups who coming knocking on my door and most times I will probably have to say this is no longer in the interest of the climate, this country or the planet.</p><p>I wish the Minister well.  I give him a guarantee that I will not be politically opportunistic and will engage in a constructive way.  It is far too important for us to pander to individual interest groups.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#W00200"><p>The objective of EU countries, including Ireland, to net zero carbon by 2050 is noble and necessary.  In that context I very much welcome the Government's climate action plan.  It is a very important and serious document.  I have heard the Minister at conferences and elsewhere and he is the first to say that this will not be easy because we are talking about a complete overhaul of our lifestyles and how we are used to living with our modern conveniences and things we take for granted, all of which is at a cost.  It is important that we continue to discuss what is a just transition and where the cost will be borne.  Many times, people put their money where their mouth is.  We must protect vulnerable people who cannot afford it.</p> <p>In this context, I am concerned about the EU Mercosur trade deal announced last Friday.  I am concerned that it will undermine what we are trying to do at a macro level and what we are trying to become leaders on and implement.  I am concerned that our beef farmers are not being treated fairly under this deal.  It is clear that the beef coming from South America is cheaper.  Our farmers are under such pressure now, often having to sell cattle at a lower than cost price and there are fears of worse to come after Brexit.</p> <p>Our beef farmers have been highly regulated for years, pursuant to the Common Agricultural Policy, and our domestic implementation of the CAP allows us to stand over the claim that our beef is of the best quality and traceability on the world stage.  We are also high up in the international league tables for carbon efficiency, at fifth place, and are constantly striving to improve our ranking.  It has to be acknowledged that the will and desire to improve is there.  This is all at a cost, and makes our beef more expensive than South American countries, for instance, which do not adhere to these standards.  It is difficult to secure data on the carbon footprint of South American beef.  The data available show the rate of deforestation is linked to an increase in agriculture.  It has been shown that beef purchased in Europe and south-east Asia from South American countries comes from areas where the tropical rainforests have been felled.</p> <p>Last Monday we saw the surge in the price of shares of Brazilian meat packers since the announcement of the trade deal.  That gives an idea of what is intended for the beef industry there and that it is set for expansion on foot of the deal.  We only have to look at the track record of President Bolsonaro, a climate change denier, to see that issues such as climate breakdown and rights for citizens, including workers, are low on his list of priorities.  Often developing countries in South America are concerned with more immediate issues and find it difficult to achieve forward planning and change systems to accommodate carbon emissions reductions.  There is a compelling argument that climate and environment effects as well as the economic impact of the EU Mercosur deal need to be scrutinised, and I am calling for that today.  Otherwise we will be operating in a parallel universe when it comes to trade deals where we must climate-proof our policies and actions in everything else.  The EU claims to be leading the way in the latter and the growth of the circular economy in transnational and domestic affairs of the global village.  We owe it to Irish and EU beef farmers to ensure that this is done.  We are all interconnected.  That is the whole basis of debate.  Such a review would have to be done at a European level and would set a precedent for climate-proofing other trade agreements.  It would be complex.</p> <p>I have a question for the Minister which the Minister of Business, Enterprise and Innovation, Deputy Humphreys, could not answer yesterday when I asked her.  When I speak of doing a climate and environmental impact assessment on the deal, I do not mean only agriculture but also transport.  What type of vehicles will the Germans sell into South America?  Is it specified that they will be electric vehicles?  There is no evidence to suggest that the Paris climate agreement commitment tagged on to the EU Mercosur trade deal can or will be observed.  There are no monitoring systems to provide empirical data on climate destruction or climate action in South America other than the sure felling of raining forests.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#W00300"><p>I must ask the Senator to finish.  We are well over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#W00400"><p>If we do not have some satisfactory evidence that climate commitments under the deal are deliverable, then we are wasting our time tying citizens of our country and the EU to the expense of implementing climate action policies.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#W00500"><p>I thank all the Senators for participation in the debate.  I will respond to their points as best I can.  Senator Leyden suggested electrifying rail lines.  We will examine all technologies, but the point I tried to make at the outset is that we have looked at technologies based on what we know of them and how they will evolve over the next ten years and picked those that are most cost effective and the least burden on people to implement first.  It is not that technologies that are not immediately identified in the plan will not be considered but that they do not stack up as the cheapest and most effective thing to do at this stage.</p> <p>Senator Leyden also asked about the cost detail.  We set out a &euro;30 billion national development plan in climate action and sustainable transport.  It includes &euro;3 billion for retrofitting homes, &euro;13 billion for creating infrastructure for renewable energy on the grid, and so on.  There is considerable cost, but as Senator Mulherin was honest in saying, we must recognise that the public will have to share some of this cost.  The State or the taxpayer cannot fund all the change.  That is what makes this so challenging.  We can create mechanisms such as carbon pricing and refunding so there are incentives to make changes, but ultimately we either do regulation, which means the individual pays everything, or we have various market interventions where there is a balance, or we invest in new technologies and develop alternatives.  Those are the policy options.  The climate advisory group has told us bluntly that if, as Sinn F&eacute;in seems to suggest, we do not have carbon pricing, then we are trying to push water up a hill.  It will be far more difficult to deliver our targets if we do not have that mix.  This is not an ideological point but we must have a mix of regulation which creates a burden for people, but some regulations will be too burdensome so we must go the incentive route or develop other ways.</p> <p>I agree with Senator Lombard that getting communities involved is central.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Richard Bruton:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=119"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=119&amp;amp;pid=RichardBruton&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We will fail if this ends up as farmers against industry, urban against rural and if we pit this as the sort of a challenge where we all start pointing fingers at someone else who should move first.  It was Brendan Behan who referred to the first item on the agenda as being the split.  If that is where this ends up going, then we will fail.  I acknowledge the work of Senator Devine and others on the Oireachtas committee.  We have sought to be faithful to the work of that committee, particularly in the area of governance.  Senator Devine has criticised the plan for not focusing on having more done in the earlier period and not putting tougher demands on the system in the years to 2030.  She then cast extraordinary doubt on all of the things to which we are committing and doubting whether we can hit targets for electric vehicles or retrofits, and implementing those sorts of changes.  </p><p>The Senator cannot have it both ways.  She cannot demand that we do more, then find fault with everything and more or less suggest that we should not be undertaking the electric vehicles initiative.  They have been chosen because they are the most cost-effective and least costly way of abating our carbon impact.  They are cheaper than going for a higher level of renewables on our grid in the early period.  I know that Sinn F&eacute;in is advocating for more emphasis on the grid and less on vehicles.  That approach is more expensive, however.  We have tried to pick the things that are most cost-effective.  I dispute strongly that we cannot deliver on the target of one third of vehicles being electric.  Some 280,000 vehicles are purchased in Ireland each year.  Three million vehicles will be purchased over the next 11 years.  We are stating that one third of those vehicles should be electric and that is not outrageous.  </p><p>Some 12% of vehicles purchased now are already electric, if we include hybrids.  I admit that we have to move away from the non-plug in hybrids and just go for the others.  They are running at the moment at about 3.5% to 4%.  That is ramping up rapidly, however.  The purchases of pure electric vehicles are three times greater than last year.  That includes plug-in hybrid electric vehicles, PHEVs.  If we count just EVs, purchases are five times greater than last year.  There is no doubt, as Senator Reilly stated, that the price of batteries is coming down.  By 2023 or 2024, we are advised, that if all taxes are excluded, it would pay a person on a whole-life basis to shift to an electric vehicle.  When we add in the lower taxes on electric vehicles, including the lower vehicle registration tax, as well as the higher prices for fuel for diesel and petrol vehicles, that is a dramatic difference.  People will make that change.</p><p>It is already becoming clear that that is happening.  The advertisements on the radio every day are about electric vehicles.  Battery technology will improve, as the Senator said.  Many of those complaints regarding the high carbon impact of battery technology draw on battery production in countries where electricity is produced by burning coal.  It is not inevitable, however, that battery production is powered by coal-burning generators.  It can be done through renewables and that would dramatically bring down the carbon impact of batteries.  The key aspect is that we have to move to renewables.  Senator Norris has left the House, but he raised the issue of why we do not stop all exploration for fossil fuels.  The core reason we do not do that is that we are 85% dependent on the use of fossil fuels.  We are getting some very welcome sources of gas from the Corrib Field.  If there was another discovery beside that which provided us with more gas, then that would help us to make the transition. </p><p>We will still be 69% dependent on fossil fuels in 2030.  This is a tough journey.  Even if we hit the 70% target for the use of renewables in our power system, we will still need a gas standby.  I am not stating that we should not, in time, change our exploration operations.  There is a case for looking at exploration in the context of a transition and energy security.  That has to be done in a balanced way, however.  It is unreasonable to suggest that we should just stop exploration tomorrow without looking at the impact such a change would have.  We will have legislation.  Senator Mullen referred to living simply so that others can simply live.  Again, however, he was viewing everything we have put forward in the plan with a certain scepticism.  We have a choice to make.  We have to accept an obligation to make changes or accept that doing nothing will see the resultant consequences explode.  I have seen figures estimating that &euro;400 trillion is the damage that will be done by doing nothing versus the investment of nearly &euro;45 trillion to undertake changes.  It is nearly 10:1 in respect of the costs involved.  </p><p>The Senator, however, seems to be advocating that we should become very conservative about making the investments now and that we should instead wait and see.  If those figures are to be believed - there will of course be some scepticism - we will be waiting for ten times the damage to be done.  Let us take the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform, which is not, I suppose, the most radical source of information.  It is stating that a tonne of carbon that last year was priced at &euro;8 per tonne will be priced in 2050 at &euro;265 per tonne.  Measures taken to abate a tonne of carbon today, at whatever cost, saves us that dramatic escalation of cost.  Let us also not forget that carbon impact is cumulative.  Each year that we leave that tonne there, it is accumulating in the atmosphere and creating damage.</p><p>I acknowledge the support of Senator Humphreys.  It is very much on the money.  We do have to design new approaches in our cities.  That is not, unfortunately, an alternative to electrifying our car fleet.  It is complementary and it does need to be done.  Career changes will be difficult but let us not forget that we have been through a decade where we saw some 200,000 jobs lost in the construction industry.  We have, however, created 500,000 jobs elsewhere.  We have been through very radical restructuring of our economy but these changes will be done on a much more managed and time-based system.  I am confident, therefore, that we can do it.  </p><p>The Mercosur issue is not my brief.  I will observe, however, that this is the first time that I have seen a trade agreement where the obligations imposed by the Paris Agreement are written.  The Mercosur trade agreement will be torn up if those obligations are not honoured.  This is the first time that has happened.  As Senator Mulherin said, it is right that we should scrutinise that process and how it is executed.  Turning to the matter of beef exports, a figure of 99,000 tonnes is high but it was originally proposed to be 300,000 tonnes.  That 99,000 tonnes is 1.25% of the European beef market.  Protections exist, however.  Some 45% of the exports will be frozen and there will be no diminution of European food safety standards.  There are, therefore, protections for farmers who fear that this these imports are going to be low quality, hormone and antibiotic-treated meat.  The best position to take is to scrutinise and examine this deal and then making our decision.  </p><p>There is a danger of trying to include everything into a trade agreement.  I will take a simple example.  We might not like the fact that Poland has coal and predominantly coal-burning technology.  A just transition for Poland, however, requires that country to change gradually and meet its obligations under the Paris Agreement.  We cannot tell Poland that we are not going to buy its goods because the country has a coal-based system.  We have to bring people with us.  People started from wherever they were, they made commitments in Paris and now they have to meet their obligations.  That is how we get collective agreements.  We cannot state that we are worried about some sector and therefore that we will seek out the faults of another country so as to undermine its trade agreements.  That is not fair.  It would not be fair to the Poles if that approach was taken to Poland and it is not fair with other countries.  We have to ensure that each country meets its responsibilities.  That is the approach that should be taken.  I welcome that the Paris Agreement obligations are at least built into the Mercosur trade deal.  That is the first time that has been done in a trade agreement.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.139" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#X00200">Citizens’ Assemblies Bill 2019: Order for Second Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.140" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Bill entitled an Act to provide for the access and use of information contained in the register of electors established under the Electoral Act 1992 for the purpose of selecting citizens of Ireland to be members of certain citizens&rsquo; assemblies; and to provide for matters connected therewith.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#X00400"><p>I move that: "That Second Stage be taken now."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.142" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.143" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#Y00100">Citizens’ Assemblies Bill 2019: Second Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.144" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That the Bill be now read a Second Time."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1295" speakername="Eoghan Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#Y00300"><p>The Citizens&rsquo; Assemblies Bill 2019 is a technical Bill to enable the register of electors to be used for selecting members of the citizens&rsquo; assemblies which the Government agreed on 11 June to establish.  Two assemblies are being established, the Citizens&rsquo; Assembly 2019 and the Dublin Citizens&rsquo; Assembly.  The role of the Citizens&rsquo; Assembly will be to bring forward proposals to advance gender equality under a number of specific headings.  The role of the Dublin Citizens&rsquo; Assembly will be to consider the best model of local government for Dublin and, in particular, the issue of a directly-elected mayor and his or her powers.  These assemblies will operate under the aegis of the Department of the Taoiseach and will comprise a chairperson and 99 citizens selected randomly from local authorities&rsquo; registers of electors.  The same chairperson but a different selection of 99 persons from the Dublin local authorities' registers of electors will make up the Dublin Citizens' Assembly.  The assemblies are to be run consecutively, commencing with the Citizens' Assembly on gender equality at the end of October this year, and will take six months each to complete the work involved.</p> <p>The Government decision requires the establishment of the assemblies to be approved by resolutions of both Houses of the Oireachtas.  In order to proceed with the establishment of the assemblies as proposed, it is necessary to introduce legislation to allow the register to be used for the selection of assembly members.  This is because section 13A(3) of the Electoral Act 1992 provides that the use of the register of electors is confined to electoral and other statutory purposes.  Such a statutory purpose is provided, for example, in the Juries Act for the selection of members of juries.  A similar approach was taken previously in 2012 when arrangements were being made for the membership of the then proposed Convention on the Constitution and again in 2016 for the then proposed Citizens&rsquo; Assembly.  A polling company will be commissioned for the selection process.  Its brief will be the selection of a representative sample of the Irish electorate, with regard to gender, age and regional spread.  The selection process will be overseen by the independent chairperson of the assembly.</p> <p>I will outline the detail of the Bill.  Section 1 of the Bill provides that information in the electoral register may be used for the purpose of selecting citizens of Ireland to participate in both assemblies.  It provides in subsection (2) that section 13A(3) of the Electoral Act 1992, which confines the use of the electoral register, shall not apply in the establishment of these citizens&rsquo; assemblies.  In subsection (3) definitions are provided for "the Act of 1992", "the edited register" and "the register of electors".  Section 2 of the Bill contains standard provisions dealing with the Title and construction of the Bill.  In summary, the sole purpose of this Bill is to provide in statute for the use of the electoral register in the selection of members of the two citizens&rsquo; assemblies.  The Bill is required to facilitate the establishment of the assemblies, the calling of which will be approved by resolution of the House in due course.  I commend the Bill to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#Y00400"><p>This is a short, technical Bill and Senators can take an example from the Minister's short speech.  I call Senator Boyhan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#Y00500"><p>I am happy to agree with that.  I had not intended to speak.  I was not aware that the Minister would mention the Dublin Citizens' Assembly.  I know what the Bill is about, relating to citizens' assemblies generally.  I do not have a problem with public engagement.  I will not oppose this and will support every Stage of it today.  I will comment on matters raised in the Ministers' speech.  We have an assembly in D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann and in Seanad &Eacute;ireann, and an assembly of elected people in both city and county councils.  I do not have a problem with other layers of public engagement.  I am all for consultation, open government and engagement.  I will not get into the matter of the Dublin Citizens' Assembly because the scheme itself is not before us.</p> <p>I ask the Minister to look, in an imaginative way, at how we and the Minister's Department can tap into the expertise of Dublin's councils with regard to the Dublin assembly.  There is an important role for them.  I know that the cynics will say they do not want a new system of mayors or form of local government for the city and county but they are elected and have a mandate and a view.  It is important that that view feeds into this process, perhaps in parallel with this, and that it is a meaningful role, engagement and discussion.  These people are freshly elected.  They are there for a fixed term of five years.  Many are members of the Minister's party and I know he values them as he values all city and county councillors.  Specifically with regard to Dublin city and county, I ask the Minister to consider whether there is a meaningful way to tap into and engage with these elected members to feed into the Minister's and the Government's vision for local government reform, especially in the city and county of Dublin.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#Y00600"><p>This is important legislation.  Providing in statute for the use of registers of electors in selecting members of a Citizens' Assembly is not an issue in itself.  However, the register of electors is a shambles.  Dead people are still listed on the register, as are people who left the country decades ago and people with differing first names, middle names and even confirmation names.  These electors should not be counted in the same way as one living resident.  Incredible staff in local authorities worked very hard prior to the recent local elections to try to ensure that people were registered, including with new details if they had moved or changed their name.  There are terrific staff in my area and I am sure that it is the same countrywide.  However, across the country, I have heard many stories about people not being registered, being registered numerous times, and polling cards arriving for the deceased, which was a significant issue.  We talk about poor voter turnout relative to the electorate but there may be a record-keeping reason for that.  While, in principle, the use of the electoral register is fine with me, I have a problem with the state of the register.  To select 99 citizens at random, I believe that we need to ensure that the pool is in order first.</p> <p>I wholeheartedly welcome the Citizens' Assembly 2019 to bring forward proposals to advance gender equality.  I agree that, given the result of the recent plebiscite, having a Dublin Citizens' Assembly to consider the best model of local government for Dublin and the powers of a directly-elected mayor may not be a bad thing at all.  The Minister needs us to approve this Bill to allow these citizens to be assembled and I am fine with that.  I ask him to look at how we count people who can vote and perhaps consider linking it with one's personal public service, PPS, number.  All of this is interlinked.  Will the Minister look at PPS numbers?  There has to be a way to make it easier for people to vote with less paperwork.  I feel that there is such a low turnout because of the paperwork or mistakes made.  I cannot blame anyone.  Local authority staff are doing a great job.  We need to look at the broader picture.  This will all feed back into the process.  I thank the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1422" speakername="Paudie Coffey" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#Y00700"><p>I welcome the Minister and his officials to the House to deal with a technical Bill, addressing the requirement to select people from the electoral register to sit on the Citizens' Assembly.  I will be brief in my commentary.  I concur with Senator Boyhan regarding political assemblies.  In a democracy, we must recognise the voice of the people and public representatives, whether in local authorities, the D&aacute;il or the Seanad.  I also believe that citizens' assemblies are an important mechanism for democratic engagement.  As we have seen recently, it is a useful mechanism to gauge public opinion and inform the making of public policy and legislation.  It is a necessary requirement and it will have the support of the House.  I wish the Bill well and I think Members will pass it in the Seanad today.</p> <p>Since we are speaking about the electoral registers, the Minister will agree that it is the responsibility of local authorities to have their electoral registers up to date.  Some are better than others in this regard and it is important that we review and update electoral registers.  Where improvements are needed, it is important that they happen as quickly as possible.  In a democracy that we are all very proud of, it is important that, when people are entitled to vote, they have the vote.  There is nothing worse than seeing a member of the public going to vote and being turned away from the polling booth with disappointment because he or she is not on the register.  We need to deal with that.  I wish the Bill well.  It is necessary and the citizens' assemblies will play an important role in informing public debate and public policy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#Y00800"><p>On the topic that Senator Coffey mentioned, while I rarely get involved in debates as Cathaoirleach, there is an issue with the register of electors.  When I was a Deputy, I was struck off it.  This time, my son and his wife, who never left the Bantry area, were struck off.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#Y00900"><p>It is terrible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#Y01000"><p>Recently, in New York, I met a girl who left Ireland 28 years ago and still has a vote.  Her mother said her polling card still comes for her.  She is married and has been living in San Francisco for 28 years.  I think it is an issue with the council.  Fortunately when I was a Deputy, I checked myself and saw my name gone.  I was able to rectify it.  My son and his wife did not and they were told at the polling station that they had no vote.  I think it is a constitutional right.  People are getting a red card with no warning.  Maybe it is a matter for Cork County Council.  I have been struck off the register in Cork three times.  I was angry as a Deputy, though I was obviously able to rectify it.  I was obviously well-known in the area.  Why someone would strike me off is beyond belief.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">An Cathaoirleach:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1988"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1988&amp;amp;pid=DenisODonovan&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I normally do not speak, but my blood boils when I think of it.  The Minister might take those points on board.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#Z00200"><p>I was also reluctant to change my address during recent referendum campaigns because of a fear of being left off the register.  Sinn F&eacute;in will support the Bill.  As some have mentioned, it is a short technical Bill which is required to enable the selection of citizens for membership of citizens&rsquo; assemblies, particularly the upcoming assemblies on gender equality and local government in Dublin.  There is some cynicism about citizens&rsquo; assemblies and the preceding Constitutional Convention which were seen by some as a delaying tactic in the context of certain referendums.  They did delay them, but in hindsight they were good contributions to the national conversation.  I look forward to seeing the findings of the next citizens&rsquo; assemblies and hope the agendas will remain as ambitious as those of assemblies that have gone before.</p> <p>On local government in Dublin, I hope the city can be reimagined as a working and living city.  As tourism grows in Dublin, it becomes more difficult to refine and conserve its identity, housing and core amenities, particularly social and green spaces, cultural venues and so on.  We need to be mindful that local government in Dublin does not have sole control over how it grows and that local government in counties Kildare and Meath have a really important role to play in the development of the city.  Development is outside the control of many of the Dublin councils.  </p> <p>On gender equality, we need to be ambitious in the working agenda in order that the changes we suggest will not just be cosmetic but will have a lasting impact in eradicating gender imbalance and misogyny and highlighting the role of women in society.  We must hold a magnifying glass to the patriarchal elements of the Statute Book, both historical and current, and the effects they have had.</p> <p>I am dismayed by the slow pace of implementation of some the recommendations of both the Constitutional Convention and the Citizens' Assembly.  We can consider the Constitutional Convention to be the design of the last Fine Gael and Labour Party Government.  A certain complacency seemed to grow around recommendations that were not political priorities for Fine Gael.  There are a few examples.  A referendum to reduce the voting age to 16 years has been shelved by two successive Governments.  There are also the matters of citizen involvement in presidential nominations; the formation of citizens' initiatives to allow citizens to formulate legislation; the constitutional right to a home and the constitutional realisation of economic, social and cultural rights, on which we have seen a report produced that is languishing with the finance committee.  There is also the question of holding a further convention during the Government's term on Seanad and local government reform.  Whereas the establishment of an electoral commission and the holding of referendums on presidential voting rights and women's role in the home have been slow but moving, I hope we will see real progress soon.  As we commit to having more citizens' assemblies, we must be more open than we have been to their recommendations, regardless of whether we agree with them.  We must debate their merits in the Houses or put them to the people in referendums.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#Z00300"><p>I am afraid I oppose the Bill as I oppose the concept of citizens' assemblies.  At best, they represent an extraordinary abdication of responsibility by the Government, the Oireachtas, political parties and other political groups and, at worst, they have been a cynical device used by cultural elites to manipulate and condition public opinion without opening to full and searching public debate on the issues involved.  The experience of the two assemblies set up to date shows that they were established, managed and orchestrated by elites from the world of politics and academia, directed at all times by the Government with certain results in mind.  That issue is never discussed.  Their conclusions were presented as what ordinary voters wanted on the issues they had examined when the participants had been led to the conclusions involved.  They were billed as being merely a consultation process, but once their reports were published, their conclusions were not treated as a mere opinion poll or focus group findings, as they ought to have been, but they were held up as a conclusive instruction from the electorate as a whole to the Oireachtas, almost at the level of a result of a general election or a referendum.  How on Earth can we seriously say detailed positions on important issues can be formulated by 100 unelected people meeting in a hotel for a couple of consecutive weekends?  At best, this is an extramural, night course approach to public policy and in most western countries it would be laughed at, yet in Ireland it is how we intend to formulate national policy.</p> <p>The Bill aims to allow members of citizen's assemblies to be selected from the electoral register, whereas up to now, they were recruited by polling companies.  For the original Constitutional Convention, Behaviour &amp;amp; Attitudes was paid a handsome fee for the task, despite the fact that it completed it in shockingly poor fashion.  While recruiting 66 citizens, it somehow managed to recruit two people who lived on the same street, while it later emerged that one person who was selected had suggested one of her neighbours should also be recruited and, incredibly, Behaviour &amp;amp; Attitudes had agreed to this.  For the second Citizens' Assembly, it transpired that seven of the 100 members were acquaintances of one employee of RED C who had been hired to find the members.  I know that Ireland is a small place, as we often note, but that beggars belief.  That is how people were selected for membership of a body to discuss important national issues with major ramifications for all of us, yet we sit here discussing the establishment of another assembly with straight faces.</p> <p>The reality is that even if assemblies are selected properly, they are an unacceptable recreation of what the parliament is supposed to be.  They are designed, at best, to let elected representatives off the hook and, as I said, at worst, they are part of a process of cynical conditioning and manipulation of public opinion.  It is troubling to hear about citizens' assemblies being proposed in the United Kingdom on the Brexit issue and in Northern Ireland on the issues of abortion and same sex marriage.  There is a common thread to these suggestions, as those calling for a citizens' assembly are invariably in a democratic minority on a particular issue, at least when it comes to political representation in parliament.  Supporters of abortion and same sex marriage in Northern Ireland know that neither measure would be passed by the democratic representatives of the people of the North at Stormont; therefore, a citizens' assembly is being called for in order to pressurise or override that will.  Likewise, for good or ill, the citizens of the United Kingdom voted for Brexit and as the House of Commons demonstrates no willingness to override that decision, there are calls for a citizens' assembly from the Liberal Democrats and the Greens which both unashamedly want to stop Brexit.  The point is not whether we agree or disagree with the objective but rather what is going on and what is important.  The normal and proper democratic process is being usurped.  These examples illustrate how citizens' assemblies are used to corral opinion towards a predetermined outcome.  Would anyone in Britain or Northern Ireland be calling for citizens' assemblies if he or she thought for one second that they would recommend maintaining a ban on abortion and same sex marriage or a hard Brexit?  We know that the answer is "No".  Far from supplementing the work of national parliaments, citizens' assemblies are invariably used to supplant the views of parliament and attempt to railroad it into taking positions that it would not otherwise adopt and for which there is no democratic mandate.</p> <p>The Government intends to establish a citizens' assembly to discuss gender equality and local government in the Dublin area.  Is it really beyond the wit of the Oireachtas and its committees to formulate new policies on gender equality?  With over 10,000 people homeless, spiralling public spending and a health service in crisis, is the system of local government in Dublin really a burning issue on the doorstep?  We spend millions of euro in funding the Oireachtas and its committee system.  We give millions of euro to political parties and other political groupings - a practice that may be questionable - part of which is specifically to assist in the generation of policy.  In spite of this, policymaking on these two relatively uncontroversial issues is to be farmed out to a quango meeting in a hotel.  The net result of the additional millions of euro of expenditure on this assembly will inevitably be proposals that are already in the public domain, namely, the abolition of Article 41.2 of the Constitution and some window-dressing on gender quotas in politics and on State boards.  There will be no substantive examination of the issue of gender equality and its various aspects.  In fairness to the members of the assembly, how could there be?  It is simply not possible for 100 lay people meeting on consecutive weekends to formulate proper policy in these areas.  Instead, the results will be written by the expert academics and lobbyists recruited to shepherd them through the process and then have them rubber-stamped by the assembly membership.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2250"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2250&amp;amp;pid=RonanMullen&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->For these reasons, I am opposing this legislation.  This is no way for national policy to be formulated.  It should be done here in the Houses of the Oireachtas by the democratically elected representatives of the people and the committees.  I have absolutely no expectation of persuading a majority to go with me on these points but I will certainly be voting against the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1295" speakername="Eoghan Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#AA00200"><p>I thank Senators for their contributions and their brevity.</p><p>The Cathaoirleach mentioned a woman he met in America.  I hope she did not come back and vote because that would have been illegal but I understand the point the Cathaoirleach made about the electoral register and I will come back to that in a moment.</p><p>The citizens' assembly model has improved our public discourse and political decision-making.  I was asked about taking on the views of Dublin councillors and local authorities.  While their views will feed into the process, councillors will not be members.  Members of a citizens' assembly will be citizens.</p><p>The register of electors is managed by the local authorities and it is not a disaster.  We should be careful with our language because to say it is a disaster is to undermine the outcome of every election or referendum.  We know, however, that it can be improved and different local authorities are looking at different models for improving it.  Dublin local authorities have recently piloted the Dublin voter site, which uses <i>mygovid.ie</i>to register online and users can amend their details on the electoral register there.</p><p>Recently, we began the process of reform of the electoral register to improve it.  We had a public consultation to which 187 submissions were made.  I will go to Cabinet soon with a report on the next steps we can take to reform and improve the register.  I imagine we will put it on a digital footing.  We will also look at voter engagement and education as well as ideas around automatic registration for young voters as they come of age.  We want to ensure that the names of persons who can no longer be on the register because they have left the country or have, unfortunately, died will no longer be maintained on the register.  All of those matters are being addressed in the reform of the electoral register that is under way.</p><p>The chairperson of the citizens' assembly will oversee the work of the polling company to achieve the balance among the 99 members as per the Government decision.</p><p>Senator Warfield commented on the Government commitment to the work that comes from conventions and assemblies.  We are fully committed to that work.  A vote on extending the franchise in presidential elections was due to take place.  However, due to timing issues - chief among these was what was happening elsewhere - it has been delayed until later this year.  It could be held in October or November provided the legislation passes the Houses in good time.</p><p>A recommendation to provide for economic and social rights in the Constitution is with the Joint Oireachtas Committee on Finance, Public Expenditure and Reform, and Taoiseach.  The committee is not chaired by a Fine Gael member.  We are awaiting the outcome of that work on further constitutional change.</p><p>Local government reform is already under way.  The outcome of the recent plebiscite on the question of having a directly elected mayor of Limerick was positive.  I was in Limerick with Senator Byrne and we discussed how we will progress that quickly.  It is important that when we make a commitment to local government reform, we see it through.</p><p>Senator Mullen commented on the assembly and referred to more than 10,000 people being in emergency accommodation.  That is directly relevant to the structure of local government in Dublin because local government is at the front line in homeless services.  If we can better organise our local government and its operation and include more democratic accountability through a directly elected mayor - that will be a matter for the assembly - we will be able to improve the way in which we deliver services.  In that way we can have more joined-up services among the four Dublin local authorities.  They are joined up through the Dublin Region Homeless Executive but I believe more can be done to improve the services that are delivered in co-operation with our partners in the non-governmental organisation sector.</p><p>Senator Mullen spoke about academic elites.  He himself has an academic background and was elected from a university panel.  I am unsure why he is dismissing people with an academic background and their ability to come to informed judgments.  I do not understand why he is dismissing the ability of our citizens to come to informed judgments when information is given to them and they have the time and space to debate.  Characterising this as a group that gets together in a hotel at the weekend is highly unfair.  The two assemblies we have had have done fantastic work.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#AA00300"><p>I took part in them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1295" speakername="Eoghan Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#AA00400"><p>The Senator's characterisation of them is unfair.  He referred to the outcomes and said ordinary voters did not want them.  They did, because they voted for those outcomes overwhelmingly.  In that regard, the moves we are making now in respect of the citizens assemblies that are to be established on two important issues are welcome.  I thank the House for its support.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.160" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and declared carried.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.161" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#AA00600">Citizens' Assemblies Bill 2019: Committee and Remaining Stages</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.162" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Section 1 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.163" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>NEW SECTION</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#AA00900"><p>I move amendment No. 1:</p><blockquote>In page 3, between lines 26 and 27, to insert the following:<b>&ldquo;Annual implementation report of recommendations of citizens&rsquo; assemblies</b><br /><br /><b>2.</b>Within twelve months of the coming into operation of this Act and every twelve months thereafter, the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government shall produce an implementation report on the recommendations of the following:<blockquote>(a) Citizens&rsquo; Assemblies established&mdash;<blockquote>(i) pursuant to a decision of the Government made on 11 June 2019 (each such body having been described by that decision as a citizens&rsquo; assembly), and<br /><br />(ii) in accordance with resolutions of D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann and Seanad &Eacute;ireann passed before, on or after the commencement of this Act;</blockquote>and<br /><br />(b) Conventions on the Constitution established&mdash;<blockquote>(i) pursuant to a decision of D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann made on 10 July 2012 and Seanad &Eacute;ireann made on 12 July 2012 (each such body having been described by that decision as a Convention on the Constitution), and<br /><br />(ii) in accordance with resolutions of D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann and Seanad &Eacute;ireann passed before, on or after the commencement of this Act.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></blockquote> <p>As I noted on Second Stage, a number of recommendations of the Citizens Assembly have not been implemented.  The recommendation that the voting age in presidential elections be reduced to 16 years is a perfect example.  This is due to a lack of political priority.  I will side-track briefly on the question of presidential voting rights.  We needed to see that legislation yesterday.  It must be introduced as quickly as possible to give us the best chance of winning the referendum on the issue.</p><p>The amendment requires the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government to publish an annual report that would list all recommendations of both conventions on the Constitution and citizens' assemblies.  We should not allow a scenario to arise where we create assemblies and then allow only certain recommendations to debated by the Government or the people.  We can disagree with recommendations but we should not stop the public from having a full hearing either in the Oireachtas or by referendum, depending on the recommendation.</p><p>The eighth report of the Convention on the Constitution dealt with economic, social and cultural rights.  Following the report, the Government and Oireachtas made a mockery of one of its crucial recommendations, namely, the recommendation to introduce a constitutional right to a home.  The members of the Constitutional Convention recommended that the report be referred to an Oireachtas joint committee for analysis and the Joint Committee on Finance, Public Expenditure and Reform, and Taoiseach was delegated as the correct forum for this purpose.  Despite this, there have been no hearings on the report for more than four years.  This is simply not good enough and the amendment would ensure that a light is shone when such delays arise.  Delays undermine the true objectives the assemblies are created to achieve.  The Government and Oireachtas should hold themselves to account in this regard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1295" speakername="Eoghan Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#AA01000"><p>Reference was made to legislation to extend the presidential franchise to citizens outside of Ireland.  I know the Senator wanted to have it yesterday but the Cabinet will have the Bill next Tuesday.  We will then be able to publish it and begin work on it as quickly as possible.  We want to provide for the option of a referendum in October or November, depending on the time it takes for the legislation to get through both Houses of the Oireachtas.</p> <p>Reference was made to the question of a right to a home.  That recommendation came from the last assembly or convention but it was not unqualified.  That is why it needed consideration by the Oireachtas joint committee.  Consideration was required in line with other socio-economic rights that might be provided for at the same time.  That committee is not chaired by a member of Fine Gael.  Sinn F&eacute;in has representation on the committee and if the Senator wishes to try to progress the matter, that is the appropriate forum with which to take it up.</p> <p>I do not propose to accept the amendment - I offer my apologies for that - given the wording.  It will not fall to only one Minister to implement these recommendations.  Certainly, I will have a role in the first tranche of work that the citizens' assembly will do around gender but other Ministers will have more of a role given their briefs.  Adequate reporting mechanisms will need to be put in place, separate from my function of returning here at different intervals.  The best place to provide for reporting requirements would be through the various motions setting up the conventions, which will come before the Houses next week.  This is simply a technical Bill to allow us to use the electoral register when establishing the assemblies.  A motion would be more appropriate.</p> <p>There were reporting requirements for the convention when it was established but it had to report to both Houses of the Oireachtas within a four-month period.  The convention met those reporting obligations.  There were separate obligations or requirements depending on whether the Government sought to accept, approve or follow through on the recommendations.  That would be the more appropriate place for Senator Warfield's amendment and he might consider withdrawing it on that basis.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#BB00100"><p>Who proposes the motion?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1295" speakername="Eoghan Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#BB00200"><p>My understanding is that it will be brought forward by the Department of the Taoiseach as the lead Department in the establishment of the Citizens' Assembly.  If the amendment were withdrawn today, the Senator would need, through the whips, to seek an amendment to the motion if possible in advance of the motion being tabled.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#BB00300"><p>The Senator can table an amendment to the motion when it is brought forward.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019070400002#BB00400"><p>That is a helpful contribution to the debate.  I am happy to withdraw the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.170" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.171" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Section 2 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.172" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Title agreed to.</p><p>Bill reported without amendment, received for final consideration and passed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-07-04a.173" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>The Seanad adjourned at 2.55 p.m. until 3.30 p.m. on Tuesday, 9 July 2019.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>