<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.2" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 14:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.4" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.5" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200003#B00100"><p>I have received notice from Senator David Cullinane that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:<blockquote><br />The need for the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources to address concerns regarding the Grid Link project earmarked by EirGrid for Waterford and involving the installation of pylons, especially in view of the impact on the landscape and the advantages of under-grounding the power lines.</blockquote>  I have also received notice from Senator Colm Burke of the following matter:<blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to consider extending the time period for the issuance of emergency medical cards from six to 12 months.</blockquote>  I have also received notice from Senator Marie Moloney of the following matter:<blockquote>The need for the Minister for Social Protection to issue a reminder that recipients of carer's benefit will be reviewed after 12 months to avoid total stoppage of payment.</blockquote>  I regard the matters raised by the Senators as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment and they will be taken at the conclusion of business.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.7" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200003#B00200">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.8" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200003#B00300"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, statements on The One Percent Difference national giving campaign, to be taken on the conclusion of the Order of Business and to conclude no later than 5.15 p.m., with the contribution of group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes and those of all other Senators not to exceed five minutes, and the Minister to be called upon to reply no later than 5.10 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200003#B00400"><p>Will the Acting Leader ask the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government, Deputy Phil Hogan, to clarify whether the &euro;10 million announced for the pyrite resolution fund will, as we are now hearing, be closer to &euro;50 million over two years?  If correct, the increased allocation is a welcome development.  Will the Acting Leader also ask the Minister when he intends to publish the relevant legislation?</p> <p>We got an indication last week that he intends to introduce the Bill in the Seanad.  I welcome that and the progress made in this area under the tutelage of the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government, Deputy Phil Hogan.  I would be obliged if the Acting Leader can find out.</p><p>When will the social welfare Bill be published?  It is due to be debated in the D&aacute;il on Thursday but has not yet been published.  We have heard a lot from the Taoiseach, the T&aacute;naiste and the Government about Oireachtas and D&aacute;il reform but it seems that the social welfare Bill, with some of the cuts proposed, will be introduced on Thursday despite the fact that it is not published on Tuesday.  I understand the Bill will be guillotined in the D&aacute;il, with only two days of debate.  I welcome the commitment of the Leader, Deputy Maurice Cummins, that no guillotine will be used in the debate on the social welfare Bill, which is due to take place in the House on 5 November.  It gives an opportunity to Members to look at what is being done.  Some of the proposed cuts are savage in the extreme.  One need only talk to the people outside the gates of Leinster House.</p><p>I note with great interest the Government propaganda issued today about how the budget affects people.  The Government researchers in the press office were able to find six people in the country that the budget did not affect.  What was telling is that there is no mention in any of the examples of the cuts to the household benefits package, restrictions to the lone parents allowance, the removal of the single parent tax credit, a further reduction in medical card limits for those over 70 years of age and the removal of thousands of discretionary medical cards.  I ask the Acting Leader to find out the cost to the State in producing this work of fiction circulated to every Member of the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200004#C00200"><p>The document even boasts about Fianna F&aacute;il budgets.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200004#C00300"><p>Our debate on the social welfare Bill will be an honest one and I will be interested to hear people's views.  There are no easy decisions.  Talking about this budget being progressive is ironic.  When the ESRI and the OECD examined the two previous budgets of this Government, they found them to be the most regressive of the past six tough budgets.  I put it to Members that this one is even more so.</p><p>Can the Acting Leader give a commitment that, on the publication of the HSE service plan in two weeks time, a full debate will take place on it in this House?  What is the figure for cuts to the health service?  Is it &euro;666 million or is it &euro;1 billion?  What are people to expect from the Government?  It was unprecedented that, on the day of the budget, I warned Members opposite that the Department of Health was a timebomb waiting to go off.  Can the Acting Leader tell me specifically-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200004#C00400"><p>Senator Darragh O'Brien is way over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200004#C00500"><p>I will conclude on this important point.  Mr. Tony O'Brien and Deputy James Reilly cannot stand over these figures and they cannot tell me or, more importantly, the citizens-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200004#C00600"><p>Is the Senator looking for a debate?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200004#C00700"><p>I have asked for a debate and for a commitment that, when the service plan is published, a full debate takes place with the Minister for Health in this House.  What specifically is the figure for savings in the Department of Health next year?  Is it &euro;666 million, is it &euro;1 billion or is it somewhere in the middle?  We have the unprecedented situation where the Minister for Health cannot stand over his Estimates.  It is incredible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1114" speakername="Deirdre Clune" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200004#C00800"><p>The social welfare Bill will be taken this week in the D&aacute;il and next week in the Seanad.  The Leader of the House gave a commitment that the guillotine will not be used and I am sure he will follow through on that commitment.  It is a very important discussion and an important element of legislation.</p> <p>I remind Senator Darragh O'Brien that the budget is taking &euro;2.5 billion out of the economy and that does not happen easily-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200005#D00200"><p>It is &euro; 3.1 billion, actually</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1114" speakername="Deirdre Clune" time="14:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200005#D00300"><p>It is &euro;3.1 billion down to &euro;2.5 billion.  We are in a bailout programme-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="14:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200005#D00400"><p>It is &euro;3.1 billion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1114" speakername="Deirdre Clune" time="14:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200005#D00500"><p>We are borrowing to the tune of &euro;12 billion annually-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.23" nospeaker="true" time="14:40:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200005#D00700"><p>Senator Clune to continue, without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1114" speakername="Deirdre Clune" time="14:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200005#D00800"><p>The effects were felt across the board.  However, the response from those involved in business has been positive and this will contribute to the economic recovery that is under way.</p><p>I ask the Acting Leader to arrange a discussion on the issue of childhood obesity and to congratulate the Minister for Health on another initiative he undertook yesterday in leading a campaign on this issue.  He presented some very chilling facts, in particular, that we were in danger of becoming the first generation to bury our own children because of the levels of obesity in society.  The Irish Heart Foundation has been strong on this issue.  Two out of every five Irish adults are overweight, while one in three children is overweight or at risk of becoming obese.  These figures have been known for a long time and we need to take action now.  The billboard and poster advertising campaign is welcome.  I suggest the House support the Irish Heart Foundation, the Minister for Health and the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs in their efforts to tackle the levels of obesity.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="14:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200005#D00900"><p>It is welcome that the Taoiseach is coming to the House tomorrow.  I hope it will be the start of a very useful dialogue on the future of the House.  As the dust settles, some issues about the referendum require to be addressed.  How did the opinion polls get it so completely wrong?  I saw result predictions at figures of 44% to 27%, 62% to 38%, 64% to 36%, 59% to 41% and that only 29% of people in urban areas supported the continuation of this House when, in fact, some constituencies recorded percentages double that figure.  There was a prediction that only 24% of people in rural areas supported the continuation of this House when, in fact, the percentage was more than double that figure.  I ask the Acting Leader if we could have a professor of statistics investigate what went wrong in the opinion polls.  The danger to democracy is that these predictions could have seriously demoralised the "No" campaign.  They led to a series of articles based on incorrect opinion poll findings.  These were spin-doctored articles, with people saying that during the canvass they had struggled to find anyone in favour of keeping the Seanad.  The articles were based on faulty opinion polls which failed to find 52% of the population.  The credibility of market research in Ireland is at risk because of this research.  The House and the Government deserve an explanation as the Government is significant when it comes to commissioning opinion polls.</p><p>I also note with great caution commentators who effectively asked people to spoil their ballot papers by writing the word &quot;Reform&quot; on them.  This could have resulted in the country getting the exact opposite result.  We must ensure this does not happen in future referendums.  The country holds the most referendums of any country, apart from Switzerland and Italy.  The conduct of referendums and related opinion polls deserve some thought as we plan for future alterations of the Constitution.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Maloney" time="14:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200005#D01000"><p>I welcome the ruling in the challenge taken against the children rights referendum result.  I ask the Acting Leader if she will at some stage organise for the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government to come to the House as there is much speculation about the cost of water charges.  The mayor of Killarney said yesterday that people would have to pay &euro;600 and change their water meter every five years.  I can neither confirm nor deny this information because we simply do not know.</p> <p>It is time and people have a right to know what to expect with water charges, and they must budget for them.  The introduction of water charges has been flagged for a long time and there has been ample time to formulate the charges.  Will the Minister come to the House or could we get word from the regulator so we can have a debate on the issue?  He could advise us how he intends to introduce water charges.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200006#E00200"><p>I propose an amendment to the Order of Business, that No. 13 be taken before No. 1 today.  A child has been found in a Roma camp in Dublin in what is a serious issue, and I commend the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na for being so active in this regard and observing that the child is possibly not from the family with which she lives.  Child trafficking is a serious crime, which leads to trauma, worries, concern, grief and despair in families which lose a child in that way.  It cannot be comprehended.  Authorities are now seeking the parents of the child found in Greece, and perhaps everyone should be on alert, in a sense, as this issue could be far more widespread than people realise.  I hope that if the child was abducted, she will be returned to her rightful family.  I hope we can bring an end to this type of criminal trafficking.  A particular community seems to be involved in these cases but it is not the only one involved in the matter.  This is a serious crime that occurs throughout the world so we must be very observant.  Parents are worried and concerned about children and we should all look out to see who is accompanying certain families when they tour around the country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200006#E00300"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" speakername="Jim D'Arcy" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200006#E00400"><p>It is a topsy-turvy world indeed when we have Fianna F&aacute;il stating the health service is a timebomb when Deputy Martin created the HSE.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200006#E00500"><p>It ran quite well then.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" speakername="Jim D'Arcy" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200006#E00600"><p>I recall him asking Charlie McCreevy - Champagne Charlie - for &euro;1 billion for the health service but he was told to reform it.  He never bothered and now the task falls to Deputy Reilly, who is working very hard to do so.</p><p>Senator O'Brien mentioned the replacement of the one-parent family credit with the single person child care credit from 1 January next year.  The unintended consequence of this measure is to discriminate against separated fathers, as the designated principal carer is usually the mother, and I have no problem with that.  The measure does not recognise the increasing role played by fathers in the care of children, regardless of designation.  We spent a weekend at the Constitutional Convention speaking about the role of women in public life and we want to see that recalibrated.  We heard female Deputies say this week that the insertion in the Constitution of the &quot;special place&quot; of women in the home was insulting.  The necessary recalibration should bring about an increasing recognition of the role of fathers in private life.</p><p>I have spoken with the Minister for Finance about the matter and we could table amendments to the Finance Bill to have this provision examined to explore the division of the credit, or it could be shared in some way.</p> <p>I hope we can look at that during the debate on the Finance Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200007#F00200"><p>I second Senator Leyden's amendment.</p><p>I also propose an amendment to the Order of Business, that the Minister for Health come to the House today to give an explanation as to the current budget deficit in his Department and the budget for the year ahead.  The level of uncertainty is unacceptable.  Last Tuesday, Wednesday and Thursday I mentioned in the House that it was difficult to see &euro;666 million as the figure for savings and in all likelihood it would be &euro;1 billion.  This was picked up in the national media over the weekend and we have since called for the Minister's resignation.  There have been umpteen calls over the years for his resignation because of his headless chicken approach to managing our health service.  In the past number of days, it has been suggested in the media that a secret meeting took place in advance of the budget during which the Minister sought an additional &euro;1 billion, which did not include the &euro;666 million in proposed savings or the budget deficit.  In his Department in a &euro;2 billion hole?</p><p>Let us look at this from a business perspective.  Intel is similar to the HSE in size with 104,000 employees and &euro;14 billion in income.  If the chief executive officer of Intel said, &quot;I don't know how far out of budget I am this year.  I think I need &euro;1 billion.  My accountants think I have to save an additional &euro;1 billion next year&quot;, what would the company's shareholders think?  Would they think they have an incompetent on their hands?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200007#F00300"><p>The people who work for Intel are not unwell.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200007#F00400"><p>Senator MacSharry without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200007#F00500"><p>It is a spurious example.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200007#F00600"><p>Senator MacSharry without interruption.  Has he a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200007#F00700"><p>Would they have confidence in the leadership and management of a company with 100,000 employees and &euro;14 billion of the people's money?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200007#F00800"><p>Is the Senator seeking a debate?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200007#F00900"><p>I have called for the debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200007#F01000"><p>It is a remedial comparison.  The people who work in Intel are well; the people in hospital are unwell.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200007#F01100"><p>Senator MacSharry without interruption.  He is way over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200007#F01200"><p>I am way over time because I have been accused of being remedial by a Government Member.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200007#F01300"><p>I mean the Senator's argument, not himself, unless he wants to be tied to it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200007#F01400"><p>I am putting forward a legitimate point, which is that the current person managing the health service does not inspire confidence.  He has control of &euro;13 billion of the people's money.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200007#F01500"><p>The Senator can raise those issues during the debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200007#F01600"><p>By his own admission last week, he knows nothing of the foundation of the figures he proposes to cut from the health service budget yet the reality is he is proceeding to do that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200007#F01700"><p>The Senator is way over time.  I call Senator Noone.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200007#F01800"><p>In the meantime, he is giving out the old pack of cards in Government propaganda.  How many thousand people does the Government need outside the gates?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200007#F01900"><p>The Senator is way over time.  I call Senator Noone.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200007#F02000"><p>The reality is, remedial class or not, I am not housed in the gin and tonic belts of the world that the Government chooses to protect or has to defend in their jobs.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200007#F02100"><p>The Senator is way over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200007#F02200"><p>I want to know about the people outside the gates who the Government is saying it will take another &euro;1 billion from next year.  Senator O'Donnell is calling it a remedial example.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200007#F02300"><p>Senator MacSharry should resume his seat.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200007#F02400"><p>I said Senator MacSharry's example was remedial.  This is completely over the top.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200007#F02500"><p>The next time Senator O'Donnell is on the Pat Kenny show she can give me a mention.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200007#F02600"><p>This is hard to take.  Deputy Miche&aacute;l Martin, who created the ineffectual monster that is the HSE, is now one of the main protagonists calling for the resignation of the Minister for Health.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200007#F02700"><p>Is the Senator reading puff from her party's press office?  All her party members seem to be on message about this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200007#F02800"><p>Senator Noone without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200007#F02900"><p>How rich is it that Deputy Martin is calling for the Minister's resignation?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200007#F03000"><p>Has the Senator a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200007#F03100"><p>I will get to my question momentarily.  Fianna F&aacute;il is claiming all sorts this week and creating hysteria about medical cards.  This the same party with the same faces and voices who tried to take them away a few years ago.  It is hard to take all of this on a continual basis.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200007#F03200"><p>I am terribly sorry.  The Senator might give me a copy of her note from the press office when she finishes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200007#F03300"><p>Has Senator Noone a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200007#F03400"><p>On a more positive note, I compliment the Minister on the child obesity initiative.  A good advertising campaign is under way.  The more emphasis that can be placed on this important area, the better.</p> <p>It seems to me that it is a very good advertisement campaign so far.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200008#G00200"><p>Not this one.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200008#G00300"><p>The more emphasis that can be placed on this very important area, the better.  Senator Clune already alluded to the statistics on that.  As she said, billboards and advertising are a very effective way of reaching adults who are responsible for the diet of young children.  I suggest that we have a debate on childhood obesity, perhaps even as a public consultation.  The issue has been discussed in the Joint Committee on Health and Children.  It would be something that could be done in the form of a public consultation.  It has been very usefully done with alcohol and cancer and it is something that could be brought to the attention of the Leader to organise.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200008#G00400"><p>Thank you, a Chathaoirligh.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200008#G00500"><p>For the second time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200008#G00600"><p>Senator O'Donnell should be allowed to speak without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200008#G00700"><p>This is a different point of view.  It is as follows: I personally would like to thank the plain people of Ireland for the budget.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200008#G00800"><p>Plain?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200008#G00900"><p>No, for the budget.  Because without the &euro;405 million from the lottery, there would be no budget.  That is what the Government got from Camelot and An Post for the lottery licence - &euro;405 million.  Over the past 25 years the lottery has made &euro;12,000 million and every year it has given &euro;232 million after it has paid out to good causes.  Camelot got the lottery on the cheap for &euro;405 million.  That is what paid for the budget because, first, that is going to pay for a start to the children's hospital, and second, other projects such as the better energy one and the city of culture in Limerick, which I am pleased about, things in Cork, projects including a sports arena and the Atlantic way drive.  The lottery created the budget.  We do not know how much of the &euro;405 million we will have to pay back in interest.  I cannot get the information.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200008#G01000"><p>Is the Senator seeking a debate?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200008#G01100"><p>I am.  First, I want a Minister to come to the House to answer the question.  As I listened to the budget I felt as if I was becoming like a larger lemon every five minutes because we gave &euro;10 million to Priory Hall, which was the right thing to do for those people who were in that situation, but in spite of all the Priory Halls and ghost estates around the country, not one builder, county councillor, planner, architectural firm, engineering firm or anyone else has been brought to book.  Not one person has been made responsible yet the aged community are outside the D&aacute;il and we are asking them on a daily basis to take decreases and cuts.  How do we consider that to be fair play?  They have not seen one example of justice.  I would like a Minister to come to the House to tell me how the people who have created the situation where cuts are taken from 80 year olds and 90 year olds - cuts to their pension, lifestyle, telephone allowance and electricity - can do so.  How could one ask people to do that and to take any form of cut when we have not yet brought to book the people who brought the situation about?  I would like some Ministers to come to the House to answer that question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200008#G01200"><p>I second Senator MacSharry's amendment.  I wish to ask the Leader what happened the Protected Disclosures Bill that was due to be discussed on Report Stage today.  It was deleted from the schedule without any reference to the Whips, or certainly not to the spokespersons.  I do not think that is appropriate.</p><p>I wish to refer to the glossy brochure that landed in our pigeon holes today.  Senators Darragh O'Brien and MacSharry have already referred to it.  I understand that it is printed by the Department of Finance on the finest of cardboard.  It reminds me of the Department of Finance's budget this year for post and telephones.  It was increased in the Estimates by 33%.  While the Minister for Finance, Deputy Noonan, is getting an increase of 33% in his telephone bills, pensioners have to do with nothing.  That is the essential problem with the Government's approach.  It is completely unfair.  The only people who have been asked to give in the budget are the poorest and most vulnerable in society.  Those approaching the top have been asked to contribute nothing.  While the brochure refers to fairness, the only way the Government can get the figures to add up to show that budgets have been fair is by, as it said itself, going back to 2009 to the Fianna F&aacute;il budgets.</p> <p>That is written in the leaflet the Government produced.  Deputy Stephen S. Donnelly confirmed last week that Fianna F&aacute;il budgets had been fair.  He was a little slow coming to the conclusion considering that the ESRI had been stating it since the current Government had taken power.  We really should have a full debate on the issue of fairness.</p><p>The most recent budget and its two predecessors have been completely unfair.  Consider the pension levy, for example.  The Minister for Finance, Deputy Michael Noonan, slipped it in and blamed the pensions industry.  The 0.15% deduction from pension funds will mean a cost of &euro;120 a year for somebody on a pension of &euro;5,000.  That is what it will mean in practice.  Somebody who worked in Tara Mines and has a pension of only &euro;5,000 will face a cut of &euro;2.40 a week.  That is completely unfair.  For somebody on a pension of &euro;15,000 in 2015, it will mean a cut of &euro;810.  That is the reality of the policy the Government is proposing.  It is letting the wealthy and those who can take cuts off with nothing.  They are being asked to make no contribution whatsoever.  There is no contribution to which Members opposite can point that they have been asked to make.  When we were in government, we asked them to make a contribution as we made cuts affecting everybody proportionate to their means.  All the studies show this.</p><p>We need a debate on the issue of fairness.  The Labour Party has failed abysmally in the fairness test.  Its members may boast, as they have been doing, about &euro;37 million being set aside for childhood GP cards, but the Government is taking &euro;390 million through increased charges in respect of medical cards.  That is not fair.  I reiterate a point with which the Minister of State, Deputy Brian Hayes, agreed some days ago, that is, that the budget adjustment is &euro;3.1 billion, not &euro;2.5 billion.  It is about time the Labour Party copped on to this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" speakername="Jim D'Arcy" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200009#H00300"><p>It is &euro;2.5 billion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200009#H00400"><p>We had a budget dealing with nursing home charges that had to be refunded.  It amounted to &euro;500 million.  That sum would be very handy if it did not have to be refunded.  However, because there was a failure by successive Ministers to deal with the issue and no legislation in place to deal with the matter properly, the money was refunded.  The leader of Fianna F&aacute;il, Deputy Miche&aacute;l Martin, was a Minister when in 2001 the then Ombudsman, Ms Emily O'Reilly, advised him there was a need for action to be taken.  No action was taken until the matter was taken to the courts.</p><p>Senator Marc MacSharry should note that the Minister for Health, Deputy James Reilly, was at a meeting of the Joint Committee on Health and Children for three hours last week and anyone who wanted to raise questions could do so.  Issues were raised and the Minister dealt with them.  It is not the case that he is not available to Members as he is available at the committee, at which he must turn up.  He does turn up and deals with the issues raised.  At a meeting of the committee I raised an issue about which I am concerned, namely, the &euro;3.4 billion in the health budget paid to non-HSE organisations.  Some have section 38 status whereby all the rules in regard to pay and conditions must comply with HSE standards.  Some money, however, is being paid to organisations that fall under section 39 and the same set of rules does not apply.  I am being advised that a CEO in one of these organisations is earning over &euro;340,000 a year, which is in excess of the money earned by the Taoiseach, the Minister or anyone else in the country.  It is taxpayers' money.  Any organisation receiving money from the Department of Health or the HSE should now declare openly what its chief executive officer is earning and the proportion of this salary coming directly from the HSE.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200009#H00500"><p>Like many others, I regard as very difficult and distasteful the personal campaign against the Minister for Health, Deputy James Reilly.  To be quite honest-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200009#H00600"><p>The Government side did it in the Seanad referendum.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200009#H00700"><p>It is deeply personal, vindictive, bad minded, unfair and unjust.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200009#H00800"><p>Where is it coming from?  The answer is the Labour Party.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200009#H00900"><p>When criticism is deserved, like others, I give it, but, by God, when it is not deserved, I will defend the person being criticised.  What was said in the media over the weekend against the Minister was nothing short of a scandal.  People should begin to realise that we all have responsibilities as Members of the Oireachtas to do the right thing.</p> <p>Governments do not always get it right.  More often than not, they get it wrong.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200010#J00200"><p>Is the Senator looking for a debate?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200010#J00300"><p>When an effort is being made to do things right, people should appreciate it.</p><p>I agree with Senator O&rsquo;Donnell that we need to see people, not just in the construction sector such as engineers and architects who signed off on bad buildings, but also the bankers brought to book.  Will the Minister for Justice and Equality update the House as to how the investigations into bringing some of these bankers to court are going?  The people are looking for answers and for those responsible to be held accountable for the mess in which we find ourselves today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200010#J00400"><p>Will the Acting Leader ask the Minister for Education and Skills when he intends to sign the commencement order for the Further Education and Training Act 2013?  It is important it is commenced as soon as possible in light of the cut of &euro;45 to unemployment benefit for young people in the budget.  It is also important that the proper moneys are given for training courses to be provided for those vulnerable young people affected by this cut, as per the Government&rsquo;s policy, and that they are not forced to emigrate.</p><p>I agree with Senator O&rsquo;Donnell on the &euro;405 million the Government will realise from the sale of the national lottery licence which I regard as an important national asset.  While the money is welcome, we got a bad deal.  Some &euro;405 million over 20 years is not an acceptable amount of money.  While it is portrayed by the Government as a good price, I do not believe it is and we should be looking to get more for this important national asset.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" speakername="Susan O'Keeffe" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200010#J00500"><p>Will the Acting Leader ask the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine to inform the House if he has any more concerns about the horsemeat scandal from earlier this year?  I raise this because today's edition of <i>The Guardian</i> newspaper reported further allegations and information relating to this scandal.  It stated how meat used in the process was so old it was sometimes green while the workers tied towels around their faces to stop themselves being sick.  In a report I did many years ago, the same allegations were made about beef.</p><p>  We must remember that during the horsemeat scandal an assurance was given that the meat used was fit to eat.  It now appears from <i>The Guardian</i> report that this is not the case.  One of the suppliers was arrested for smuggling cannabis into Northern Ireland in his horsemeat lorries.  The horses he transported here and subsequently used in the production of burgers were unfit for human consumption being unwell with ailments such as chest infections and sepsis.  There are serious allegations raised in <i>The Guardian</i>.  Has the Minister any more information on this scandal?  The article suggests there is more information available and more will come out.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200010#J00600"><p>I support Senator Conway's support for the Minister for Health.  It is incumbent on all of us to support him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200010#J00700"><p>Why?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200010#J00800"><p>We all want to see a world-class health service with all our citizens having the best possible health facilities available to them.  All Members know well, however, the mess the Minister inherited two and a half years ago.  We know the monolith that was the Health Service Executive.</p> <p>We know the budgetary situation he faced.  He is a reforming Minister who is doing a good job and we need to be supportive of him at this difficult time.  Some of the commentary in the media is absolutely over the top.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200011#K00200"><p>Some of it is coming from his fellow Cabinet Ministers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200011#K00300"><p>Does Senator Mullins have a question for the Acting Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200011#K00400"><p>I do and it is totally unrelated.  To put things in perspective let us consider the appalling situation in Syria with the plight of children dying of starvation in some of the besieged towns.  Will the Acting Leader organise for the T&aacute;naiste to come to the House to update us on the situation?  We all read in the newspapers that medicines and aid supplies are being prevented from getting to the most deprived and suffering people.  The relief agencies are doing an amazing job in appalling circumstances but they are fighting a losing battle.  There is a lack of urgency among the international community to get this crisis resolved.  The death toll continues to rise and more refugees are moving to the surrounding countries.  The crisis is of enormous proportions.  More than 100,000 people have died so far and several million citizens have been displaced.  We have not had a conversation with the T&aacute;naiste in the House in recent times on the matter or with the Minister of State, Deputy Costello.  I ask the Acting Leader to organise this debate.  We are heading into winter and it is quite likely there will be significant loss of life in the coming months.  As a sovereign country and a member of the European Community, it is incumbent on us to up the ante and heighten pressure on other significant members of the international community to do something significant in Syria.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200011#K00500"><p>Senator O'Brien asked a range of specific questions.  In response to his first question on pyrite legislation, I agree it is welcome it is being introduced in the Seanad.  I am delighted and we should all put pressure on Ministers to do this as much as possible.  It is very good to have comprehensive debate here before the legislation goes to the D&aacute;il.  I am told it will be before Christmas but we do not have a specific date yet.  The social welfare Bill will be in our pigeonholes tomorrow morning.  The conduct of business in the D&aacute;il is a matter for that House but the Leader, Senator Cummins, has given an undertaking the Bill will not be guillotined when it comes to this House and I am sure he will hold to it as we all wish him to.</p><p>I understand the House will begin to consider the Bill on 5 November.  We will have all of next week in addition to the remainder of this week to prepare for the debate.  I know it will be an honest and robust debate, but given it must be so it is important we remember the facts of the budget.  We have had a huge amount of spin and hyperbole from the other side which is hard to take.  To respond in a factual and objective manner, basic social welfare rates were preserved, there was no increase in income tax and, it is fair to say, for the vast majority, particularly hard-pressed families and the squeezed middle, as it is often referred to, the budget has not had an adverse financial impact and this is a fair point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200011#K00600"><p>Mortgage interest supplement was abolished.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200011#K00700"><p>Health insurance.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200011#K00800"><p>I ask the Opposition, which speaks of a fiction of figures prepared, to be aware of some of the factual and objective findings.  This week I saw the findings of a study by the OECD on the progressive nature of the Irish tax system in which 19% of tax is paid by the top 1% of earners, 41% of tax is paid-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200011#K00900"><p>We made those changes to the taxation policy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200011#K01000"><p>-----by the top 5% and-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200011#K01100"><p>The Government made no contribution to this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200011#K01200"><p>-----77% is paid by the top 23%.  The Irish tax system according to the OECD-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200011#K01300"><p>Does it come from this document?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200011#K01400"><p>Senator Bacik is speaking about our budgets.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200011#K01500"><p>Senator Bacik, without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200011#K01600"><p>These are findings of the OECD.  Fianna F&aacute;il may not like these facts.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200011#K01700"><p>The Government had nothing to do with it.  It was Fianna F&aacute;il budgets.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200011#K01800"><p>It is coming from the OECD.  It may be reproduced in some documents but the OECD study has made this finding.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200011#K01900"><p>I am speaking about our budgets.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200011#K02000"><p>Senator O'Brien also asked about the HSE and the figure for cuts in health.  As he is aware, the health service savings target for next year is &euro;666 million, which is set out in the 2014 Estimates.  The HSE must prepare and adopt its 2014 national service plan for submission to the Minister for Health within 21 days of the publication by the Government of the Estimates for supplied services for 2014, which is Tuesday, 5 November.</p> <p>The national service plan must indicate the type and volume of health and personal social services that the HSE will provide during 2014.  Clearly, what is involved here is much more difficult than preparing an ordinary business plan.  Some rather ridiculous comparisons were made by those on the opposite side of the House in this regard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L00200"><p>Imagine being able to manage the Department's finances.  Is that not ridiculous?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L00300"><p>Senator Bacik, without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L00400"><p>Imagine being able to stick to a budget.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L00500"><p>Let us examine some objective facts.  The population of the State has increased by 8%, the proportion of persons aged 65 and over is increasing by over 20%, there has been a &euro;3.3 billion reduction in the HSE's budget since 2008 and a cut of 10%, or 11,000, in the number of health service staff and a 3%-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L00600"><p>A litany of broken promises.  There have now been deficits in two successive budgets in the area of health.  The Minister is a great man.  He is brilliant.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L00700"><p>Senator Bacik, without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L00800"><p>I suggest that Senator MacSharry listen to the figures I am providing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L00900"><p>The Minister should be given an award.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L01000"><p>Senator Bacik is trying to respond to questions that were raised earlier.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L01100"><p>When I was over there I would not listen to rubbish of this nature and I am not prepared to do so now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L01200"><p>The Senator is not over here anymore.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" speakername="Jim D'Arcy" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L01300"><p>The Senator did not even listen to himself back then.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L01400"><p>I was-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.130" nospeaker="true" time="15:35:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L01600"><p>Senator MacSharry may not want to listen-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L01700"><p>The sooner the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, Deputy Howlin, stops leaking information to the media and stands up to his ministerial colleague the better.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L01800"><p>Senator Bacik, without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L01900"><p>Senator MacSharry may not wish to listen to the facts but Senator Darragh O'Brien asked me some questions and I am trying to provide a fair response.  I suggest that Senator MacSharry consider the figures.  This year alone there has been a 3% increase-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L02000"><p>Is the Senator referring to the &euro;666 million or the &euro;1 billion?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L02100"><p>The Senator should attend the meetings of the Joint Committee on Health and Children if he wants to obtain the relevant information.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.137" nospeaker="true" time="15:35:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L02300"><p>On a point of order, it is my understanding that the House passed a motion to the effect that the Order of Business should take precedence over attendance at certain committees.  I call on Senator Colm Burke to withdraw his last statement.  The Senator might have taken time to correct the record in respect of the factually incorrect press releases issued by Deputy Harris in respect of my attendance at the meetings of the Joint Committee on Health and Children.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L02400"><p>That is not a point of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L02500"><p>This is a very important issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L02600"><p>The Senator already made his contribution to the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L02700"><p>I was in attendance at last Thursday's meeting of the joint committee.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L02800"><p>The Senator is completely out of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L02900"><p>No.  With respect, the person who is out of order is seated on the opposite side.  That individual is being highly mischievous in making-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L03000"><p>Senator MacSharry is completely out of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L03100"><p>-----incorrect statements about other people's attendance.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L03200"><p>I ask the Senator to resume his seat.  The Acting Leader is replying to the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L03300"><p>Are we going to invite Senator Colm Burke to withdraw his ridiculous assertion about a meeting at which I was present?  The Senator should check the record.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L03400"><p>Senator MacSharry should resume his seat.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L03500"><p>I did not-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L03600"><p>Senator Colm Burke was speaking in general terms.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L03700"><p>Check the record.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L03800"><p>I do not believe Senator MacSharry asked any questions at the meeting in question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L03900"><p>Senator Bacik to proceed, without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L04000"><p>Without wishing to speak for Senator Colm Burke, I believe he was suggesting that persons who wished to put questions to the Minister for Health might have posed them during the three-hour meeting of the joint committee which took place last week.</p><p>I am trying to provide answers to the questions posed earlier.  Among the facts provided by the Minister for Health to the Lower House is that which indicates that the HSE is being obliged to cope with a demographic challenge relating to the increase in population.  The latter is, of course, additional to the challenged posed by our economic situation.  As the Minister, Deputy Reilly has pointed out, in this year alone there has been a 3% increase in admissions to accident and emergency departments.  I am of the view that everyone will accept that circumstances of this nature are extremely difficult to budget for.  The Minister is presiding over an unprecedented reform programme.  Perhaps Senator MacSharry might want to listen when I inform him that last week I referred to changes to hospital governance in anticipation of the roll-out of universal health insurance and the end of the inequitable two-tier health system.  The Government is committed to this and the Minister and his Department have been working on it.  Many colleagues are not aware of that fact.  On previous occasions I asked the Leader to allow the House to debate the progress that has been made towards the roll-out of universal health insurance.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L04100"><p>What progress?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L04200"><p>Like many others, I have welcomed the extension of free primary care to children under six.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L04300"><p>When will that be introduced?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L04400"><p>I do not know but I can check the position for the Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L04500"><p>Will it be paid for out of the &euro;2 billion or the &euro;666 million?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L04600"><p>Senator Bacik, without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L04700"><p>I did not hear the matter being mentioned at last week's meeting of the Joint Committee on Health and Children.  I did not hear an answer being provided at that forum by either Tony O'Brien or the Minister.  They did not have a clue from where the figures came.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L04800"><p>It is interesting-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L04900"><p>Senator Bacik, without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L05000"><p>They did not have a clue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L05100"><p>-----that those on the other side spent a great deal of time asking questions about health and that they now do not want to listen to the answers I am trying to provide.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L05200"><p>The Deputy Leader clearly does not have them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L05300"><p>I have given a very clear answer-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L05400"><p>Senator MacSharry should allow Senator Bacik to conclude.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L05500"><p>What I am saying is hardly provocative.  Surely my questions deserve a response of a factual nature.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L05600"><p>If Senator MacSharry does not stop interrupting, I will put the question on the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L05700"><p>We should not be obliged to listen to this rubbish on a daily basis.  All hail the Minister for Health who does not know from where the figures come.  Hello?  Is it any wonder we are asking questions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.173" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200012#L05800"><p>Senator MacSharry should show Senator Bacik, who is trying to respond to questions put to her, some respect.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.174" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200013#M00100"><p>The Acting Leader should show respect to the people outside the gate who are asking whether the cutbacks in health will amount to &euro;666 million, &euro;1 billion or &euro;2 billion, and how the figure of &euro;113 million was devised.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200013#M00200"><p>I am asking the Senator, please, to respect the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200013#M00300"><p>One of the strengths on which we in this House have always prided ourselves is that we conduct debate in a respectful and courteous manner.  In fairness to Senator Darragh O'Brien, he has listened courteously as I tried to respond fairly to the questions he asked.  I cannot say the same for all of his colleagues.  I ask Members to treat whoever is standing in the Leader's position with the respect that position should be accorded and in line with the rules of the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.177" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200013#M00400"><p>The Acting Leader was fantastic at following those rules in her own day.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200013#M00500"><p>Senator MacSharry, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.179" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200013#M00600"><p>Senator Clune referred to the childhood obesity campaign and called for a debate on the issue.  Such a debate certainly would be worth having.  Senator Catherine Noone raised the same issue and suggested it might be a matter for the Seanad Public Consultation Committee.  I agree that it would be a useful follow-up to the previous debate and the report we produced on lifestyle and cancer issues.</p><p>Senator Barrett made several timely points regarding opinion polls and how wrong they can be in the context of referendum campaigns.  There is clearly a good deal of work to be done in terms of determining what changed in the week between the final opinion polls and the holding of the referendum to abolish the Seanad, or whether the opinion polls themselves were flawed.  This House has a proud tradition of spotting flaws in legislation on opinion polls and stopping that legislation from going forward.  On the issue of spoiling ballot papers, while people writing in newspapers can advocate anything they like, I agree with the Senator regarding the importance of educating people as to what can count as a spoilt vote and that anything written on a ballot paper may jeopardise the counting of that paper.</p><p>I join Senator Moloney in welcoming the ruling on the referendum on children's rights.  The Senator also asked that the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government, Deputy Phil Hogan, be invited to the House for a debate on water charges.  The Minister will be here this afternoon for statements on The One Percent Difference campaign, but we can certainly seek to arrange a debate on water charges in the future.</p><p>Senator Leyden proposed an amendment to the Order of Business that No. 13 be taken before No. 1.  I am happy to agree to that proposal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200013#M00700"><p>I thank the Acting Leader.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.181" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200013#M00800"><p>I agree with the Senator's comments in support of efforts by the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na to combat child trafficking.</p><p>Senator Jim D'Arcy called for a debate on the one-parent family credit changes and referred to a potential unintended consequence thereof in the form of discrimination against a particular group.  I agree with the Senator's comments, particularly in the context of the recent debate at the Constitutional Convention on the need to re-calibrate the role of women to take account of the increasingly strong caring roles being taken by fathers.  I absolutely agree that anything which impedes that progress would be troubling.  A debate on these issues is timely in a context where couples, even after separation, are dividing up child care responsibility in a very different way from what was common in the past.</p><p>I have already responded to Senator MacSharry.  Senator Noone referred to the childhood obesity initiative, which I covered.</p><p>Senator O'Donnell raised the sale of the national lottery licence.  That sale, and the money it generated, has had a strong impact on the budget.  The measures the Senator referred to, including progress on the development of the national children's hospital and initiatives such as the City of Culture, are job creation initiatives and it is very important that funding be provided for them.  We have had several opportunities to debate the awarding of the national lottery licence with the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, Deputy Brendan Howlin, but we certainly can seek another debate.</p><p>Senator O'Donnell also spoke of the failure to bring to book anybody who played a part in bringing about the economic crisis.  That is an ongoing issue which has been raised by many speakers in this House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.182" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200013#M00900"><p>I referred in particular to the construction industry.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.183" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200013#M01000"><p>Senator Conway made the same point more generally with reference to bankers.  As we know, trials are pending against certain individuals involved in the former Anglo Irish Bank, but I certainly agree that the Director of Public Prosecutions and the Office of the Director of Corporate Enforcement must be facilitated with any resources necessary to ensure prosecutions are brought for the type of conduct that led to Priory Hall and so on.  It should be noted, however, that the investigation and prosecution authorities of the State are independent of the Legislature.  Senator Conway called for the Minister for Justice and Equality to give us an update on investigations, but I am not sure whether that would be appropriate.  It would be appropriate, however, for the Minister to outline the State's machinery of enforcement and the resources provided for that purpose.</p><p>Senator Thomas Byrne referred to the Protected Disclosures Bill.  The amended schedule of business for this week was circulated last Sunday, which gave adequate notice to Members.  I presume the Bill simply was not ready to go to Report Stage, but I am  sure we will have it in due course.</p><p>The Senator also raised issues relating to the budget.  We will have plenty of time to discuss those issues in the context of the debate on the social welfare Bill and so on.  We have already had some debate on the budget.  There have been plenty of measures in this and previous budgets which have impacted on the higher paid, and rightly so.  We are seeing some signs of confidence returning, with two years of growth and the creation of 34,000 jobs in the past 12 months.</p> <p>There is no apology for focusing on job creation in this as in previous budgets.  </p><p>Senator Colm Burke pointed out that the Minister for Health had attended a meeting of the Joint Committee on Health and Children for three and half hours last week.  He also referred to the health budget allocated to non-HSE bodies.  That topic is worthy of debate.</p><p>Senator Martin Conway referred to the lack of accountability.  We might have the Minister for Justice and Equality in the Chamber to speak about enforcement mechanisms.  </p><p>With regard to the comments of Senator Diarmuid Wilson, I can check the commencement dates for the Further Education and Training Bill, but any delay in the commencement of the Bill should not delay the introduction of training places for young people.  Funding has been put aside in the budget and there is a commitment to the youth guarantee to ensure there are sufficient further education and training places available.</p><p>Senator Susan O'Keeffe referred to the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine and the horsemeat scandal.  The Minister will attend tomorrow for a wide-ranging debate and statements on the Common Agriculture Policy.  The alarming findings of the horsemeat scandal can be put to him.</p><p>Senator Michael Mullins referred to the need for a debate on the situation in Syria.  We will ask the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade to attend the House for a debate on that topic which a number of Senators have requested.  The conditions in which children and civilians are living are appalling.  I understand the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade will attend the Chamber on Thursday morning for some of the debate on the EU Scrutiny and Transparency in Government Bill.</p><p>An amendment was proposed by Senator Marc MacSharry and seconded by Senator Thomas Byrne, but I cannot agree to it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.185" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200014#N00150"><p>Senator Terry Leyden has proposed an amendment to the Order of Business: "That No. 13 be taken before No. 1."  The Deputy Leader has indicated that she is prepared to accept the amendment.  Is the amendment agreed to?  Agreed.</p><p>Senator Marc MacSharry has proposed an amendment to the Order of Business: &quot;That the Minister for Health come to the House today to give an explanation for the current budget deficit in his Department and the budget for the year ahead.&quot;  Is the amendment being pressed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.186" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200014#N00200"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.187/1" nospeaker="true" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200014#N00250"><p>Amendment put:</p><p>The Seanad divided: T, 12; Nl, 22.</p><p>Tellers: T, Senators Ned O'Sullivan and Diarmuid Wilson; Nl, Senators Aideen Hayden and Michael Mullins.</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.187/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2013-10-22" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200014#N00250">
            <divisioncount ayes="12" noes="22" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" vote="aye">Sean Barrett</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" vote="aye">Thomas Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" vote="aye">Terry Leyden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" vote="aye">Marc MacSharry</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" vote="aye">Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" vote="aye">Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1115" vote="aye">Labhr&aacute;s &Oacute; Murch&uacute;</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" vote="aye">Darragh O'Brien</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1142" vote="aye">Ned O'Sullivan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1154" vote="aye">Averil Power</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" vote="aye">Feargal Quinn</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" vote="aye">Diarmuid Wilson</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" vote="no">Ivana Bacik</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" vote="no">Terry Brennan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" vote="no">Colm Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1114" vote="no">Deirdre Clune</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1124" vote="no">Michael Comiskey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" vote="no">Martin Conway</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" vote="no">Jim D'Arcy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" vote="no">Aideen Hayden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1173" vote="no">Lorraine Higgins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" vote="no">John Kelly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1162" vote="no">Denis Landy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1167" vote="no">Fiach MacConghail</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" vote="no">Marie Maloney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" vote="no">Michael Mullins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1187" vote="no">Hildegarde Naughton</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" vote="no">Catherine Noone</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1169" vote="no">Mary Ann O'Brien</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" vote="no">Marie Louise O'Donnell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" vote="no">Susan O'Keeffe</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" vote="no">Pat O'Neill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" vote="no">Jillian van Turnhout</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1143" vote="no">John Whelan</mpname>
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.187/3" nospeaker="true" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200014#N00250"><p>Amendment declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.188/1" nospeaker="true" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200015#P00100"><p>Question put: "That the Order of Business, as amended, be agreed to."</p><p>The Seanad divided: T, 23; Nl, 12.</p><p>Tellers: T, Senators Aideen Hayden and Michael Mullins; Nl, Senators Ned O'Sullivan and Diarmuid Wilson.</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.188/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2013-10-22" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200015#P00100">
            <divisioncount ayes="23" noes="12" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" vote="aye">Ivana Bacik</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" vote="aye">Terry Brennan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" vote="aye">Colm Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1114" vote="aye">Deirdre Clune</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1124" vote="aye">Michael Comiskey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" vote="aye">Martin Conway</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" vote="aye">Jim D'Arcy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" vote="aye">Aideen Hayden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1173" vote="aye">Lorraine Higgins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" vote="aye">John Kelly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1162" vote="aye">Denis Landy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1167" vote="aye">Fiach MacConghail</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" vote="aye">Marie Maloney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" vote="aye">Michael Mullins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1187" vote="aye">Hildegarde Naughton</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" vote="aye">Catherine Noone</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1169" vote="aye">Mary Ann O'Brien</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" vote="aye">Marie Louise O'Donnell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" vote="aye">Susan O'Keeffe</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" vote="aye">Pat O'Neill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" vote="aye">Jillian van Turnhout</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1143" vote="aye">John Whelan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1176" vote="aye">Katherine Zappone</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" vote="no">Sean Barrett</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" vote="no">Thomas Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" vote="no">Terry Leyden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" vote="no">Marc MacSharry</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" vote="no">Darragh O'Brien</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1142" vote="no">Ned O'Sullivan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" vote="no">Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" vote="no">Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1115" vote="no">Labhr&aacute;s &Oacute; Murch&uacute;</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1154" vote="no">Averil Power</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" vote="no">Feargal Quinn</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" vote="no">Diarmuid Wilson</mpname>
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.188/3" nospeaker="true" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200015#P00100"><p>Question declared carried.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.189" nospeaker="true" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200016#R00100">Seanad Electoral (University Members) (Amendment) Bill 2013: First Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.190" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200016#R00200"><p>I move:<blockquote><br />That leave be granted to introduce a Bill entitled an Act to provide for the amendment of the Seanad Electoral (University Members) Acts 1937 to 2006 to provide for the provisions of the seventh amendment of Bunreacht na h&Eacute;ireann and to extend the franchise of the University Panel of Seanad &Eacute;ireann to all people who are over eighteen and legally resident in Ireland and are holders of an appropriate third level qualification from an Irish institute of higher education and to provide for related matters.</blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.191" nospeaker="true" time="16:05:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.192" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200016#R00400"><p>When is it proposed to take Second Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.193" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200016#R00500"><p>On Wednesday, 6 November 2013.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.194" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200016#R00600"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.195" nospeaker="true" time="16:05:00" ><p>Second Stage ordered for Wednesday, 6 November 2013.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.196" nospeaker="true" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200016#R00750">The One Percent Difference National Giving Campaign: Statements</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/967" speakername="Phil Hogan" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200016#R00800"><p>Thank you, Acting Chairman, for the opportunity to brief the House this afternoon on The One Percent Difference campaign, a major initiative of the Forum on Philanthropy and Fund-raising which was designed to play a key role in developing philanthropy and fund-raising in this country.  This campaign is all about asking the Irish people and business to give 1% of their time or income to a cause they care about, a campaign described recently by President Clinton during a visit to these shores as a good idea.</p><p>I have said this before, but it is no harm to say it again, namely, a successful society rests on three pillars: first, it needs sustainable businesses to create the goods, services and jobs for a decent standard of living; second, it requires good government to promote and foster a safe, just and equitable society and, third, and by no means the least pillar, is a dynamic civil society.</p><p>Civil society is where people voluntarily associate and come together to advance common interests for the well-being of the community and to promote the common good.  We all want an Ireland where individuals and their families, friends, communities and neighbours share responsibility with Government, the public and private sectors, community and voluntary organisations and civil society in a co-endeavour to realise everyone's capabilities and developmental potential.  Civil society makes an immense contribution to the quality of life of the Irish people.  There are almost 8,000 charities that do everything from medical research to search and rescue, but there are also sporting and cultural organisations such as the GAA, Comhaltas Ceolt&oacute;ir&iacute; &Eacute;ireann and the Abbey Theatre which provide the nation with its heart and soul.  Much of what makes us proud to be Irish is a product of the work of civil society.</p> <p>If there is a crisis anywhere in the world, one will find Concern and Tr&oacute;caire providing much-needed help and assistance for the local population.  Where there are poverty and hunger, one will find many other development aid charities supported by the Irish people.  In short, a huge amount of what we really value and are proud of is as a result of civil society.  It is the source of much of what makes Ireland a great country, a country of which, for all its faults, we are justly proud.  If we want to create a better Ireland, we need to invest in civil society.</p><p> The philanthropic sector is facing a very significant challenge in that two of the country's largest foundations, Atlantic Philanthropies and the One Foundation, are exiting the Irish scene, leaving a funding gap of between &euro;50 million and &euro;60 million per annum.  Both organisations have made a tremendous contribution to Irish life, but it is now time for Irish foundations and philanthropists to fill the gap.</p><p> There are very strong economic arguments for greater private investment in the not-for-profit sector.  The sector employs well over 100,000 people, more than the pharmaceutical and IT sectors combined.  Increased private investment in the sector will help to foster economic and social recovery and will, I am sure, generate an increased number of jobs nationally.</p><p> Ireland's not-for-profit organisations have the potential to play a significant role in economic renewal.  The One Percent Difference is all about generating additional investment to support the efforts of those individuals and organisations that are working for a better Ireland.  This is an inclusive campaign; it recognises that in these tough times not everyone can afford to give financially, but we can all give time and that is equally valuable and to be valued.  The campaign was launched in June 2013.  I am delighted to say former President Mary Robinson, sports star Ronan O'Gara, celebrity chef Clodagh McKenna, novelist Fran O'Brien and the president of the GAA, Liam O'Neill, gave freely of their time to help with the launch which was attended by many of the 600 charities that have already signed up to the campaign.</p><p> This House was also represented as Senator Fiach Mac Conghail made a very impactful contribution to a video played at the event.  He spoke about philanthropy and the arts.  He was joined by Dr. Ed Walsh who spoke about the impact of philanthropy on education and Kilkenny hurler Richie Hogan who spoke about the contribution of volunteers to sport and the GAA.  The GAA did not just attend the launch; it is a strong supporter of the campaign.  It gave it the opportunity to showcase The One Percent Difference logo during the all-Ireland semi-final between Mayo and Tyrone which was shown live by RTE and introduced by Michael Lyster.  Perhaps the Mayo lads might give 1% extra next year and finally win that elusive all-Ireland title.</p><p> I strongly believe Irish business needs to match the public's commitment to giving.  I recently addressed the national council of IBEC and in my speech urged companies to get behind The One Percent Difference campaign.  I am delighted to say business is responding.  Many Members may have seen and heard the latest adverts for the campaign which feature real people, not actors, talking about their attitudes and habits when it comes to giving.  One of the adverts features Anne O'Leary, CEO of Vodafone, who has a great message for business.  She stated:<blockquote>I think it's important for all business to give.  Our employees expect it.  Our customers expect it so I don't know how anybody could be in business without giving back to the community.</blockquote>That message is not just for corporate Ireland but also for all businesses, big and small.  Country Crest and DoneDeal, two Irish SMEs that are leaders in giving, feature in radio adverts urging other small businesses to give 1% to make Ireland a better place in which to live.</p><p> Just last week, former US President Bill Clinton delivered the sixth Annual Ray Murphy Lecture at the invitation of the Forum on Philanthropy and Philanthropy Ireland.  The lecture is held in memory of Ray Murphy, a former community worker from Cork who worked in Ireland and throughout the world supporting organisations working with disadvantaged and vulnerable people.  The lecture is very generously supported by the Charles Stewart Mott Foundation and Atlantic Philanthropies.  Mr. Clinton used the occasion of his address to support strongly The One Percent Difference campaign.  He stated:<blockquote>I think the one percent thing is a great idea for two reasons.  One is it raises a lot of money.  The second is that it would democratise giving further because everybody can afford it, and if you don't have any money you can give one per cent of your time and make a contribution.</blockquote>He also stated The One Percent Difference campaign &quot;is a good and noble thing to do.  It is in the Irish tradition and you can do something that I would really appreciate. You can organise and execute it in a way that would enable other people to learn from you.&quot;</p><p> I urge this House to get behind the campaign.  I ask Senators to visit <i>onepercentdifference.ie</i>to find out what 1% of their income is and a cause to support from the more than 600 organisations that have signed up for the campaign or any of the good causes in which they believe.  I ask them to urge civil society organisations with which they work to sign up to participate in the campaign and use The One Percent Difference logo and messaging in their fund-raising.  The One Percent Difference campaign is the first major step in delivering on the plans of the Forum on Philanthropy and Fundraising to grow the sector.  I thank the forum for its work to date.</p> <p>It is a collaboration of the philanthropic and fund-raising sectors and a range of Departments.  My Department will continue to facilitate its work and I look forward to further initiatives from it in the coming months and years.  By implementing the forum's plans, the full potential of Ireland&rsquo;s tradition of giving will be realised as the culture and infrastructure of Irish philanthropy and fund-raising will be transformed in the next four years.  I have no doubt that increasing the investment in good causes in Ireland will make a tangible difference to the lives of the people and ensure a better future for our children.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.200" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1115" speakername="Labhr&aacute;s &Oacute; Murch&uacute;" time="16:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200018#T00200"><p>I welcome the Minister.  Nobody could disagree in general with his statement.  There are two choices in a time of challenge.  First, one can become negative and not respond to a challenge in a positive way.  The other choice is to realise there is a challenge and a responsibility on everyone to respond to it in a positive way.</p><p>We have had some exceptionally good times in Ireland.  During the Celtic tiger period we saw the arts and cultural infrastructure grow in a significant way.  Added to this is voluntarism.  We often underestimate what it means in many of the great projects we have had.  While one cannot put a monetary value on voluntarism, there is a sense of ownership which volunteers have when they are involved.  One can point to progress made on the road and rail networks and employment levels.  However, to have real quality of life and people happy and constructive, one needs to have arts and cultural events in the greater community.</p><p>Mention was made of Senator Fiach Mac Conghail and the Abbey Theatre.  The high standard of drama productions there has had a good-feeling impact on the wider community and visitors to the country.  If one is promoting a business, the worst that can happen is people feel they do not get value for money.  Having a visitor to Ireland have a good cultural experience is very important.</p><p>Ireland is very good when it comes to donations to charities.  Between 2009 and 2011, in the midst of the recession, there was still a major increase in donations to charities.  The main donations are for emergencies.  If one looks at the American system of giving - that is why I understand the former US President Bill Clinton believes it is a good one - one will see up to &euro;300 billion coming from corporate bodies for the promotion of the arts and culture.  Ireland's corporate donation rate is less than 1%.  There is a need for education in this regard and for corporate Ireland to understand what it means to develop civil society, as well as how important it is to its work and the happiness of its employees.  It is interesting how infectious this becomes.</p><p>The One Percent Difference campaign is a practical idea that provides a focus.  What is important is getting the message across to the broader public.  I am sure the Minister will not mind if I take one small example from Comhaltas Ceolt&oacute;ir&iacute; &Eacute;ireann.</p> <p>This year 430,000 people turned up in Derry for the Fleadh Cheoil.  What were important were the messages which went with it, as for the first time the PSNI marching band was able to play in public.  I regarded it as a privilege to go to the Waterside to meet the loyalist bands and present them with an award on the platform.  We have been toing and froing since.  I refer to this because one can have all the plans, policies and megaphone diplomacy one likes, but what is important is interacting with the community.  Approximately 9,000 people were listening to the loyalist bands when they were performing on stage.  A member of one of the bands told me that it was a good experience for them and stated they would show the lads in Belfast how to behave themselves.  That was interesting coming from one member of a loyalist band speaking about another issue.  I will not make any judgment on what is happening in Belfast.</p><p>The same applies to community arts activities with regard to interaction.  When a play is staged in a local community, the entire community gets involved, not just the people on stage.  In the same way that people speak about the all-Ireland hurling and football finals for days afterwards, they will speak about the play and the characters.  The same applies to a local museum or heritage centre.  There are such ideas and they are not pie in the sky.</p><p>The Minister is right to exhort us as legislators to get business to back civil society.  This means engaging with the community.  We should get communities speaking about this concept.  These are not unrealisable goals and the bar has not been raised too high.  It is doable.  It may be a new approach, but most of it is already followed in essence and the question is how to build the structure.  We should find some way of engaging with corporate Ireland and I do not mean through begging letters.  To do this, we must come up with a message which is productive in order that people will see the value of increasing their contribution.  The only reason they have not been doing so to any great extent is it has not been part of our culture.  It is part of the culture in the United States, from where we have so much to learn.  Those of us who travel back and forth to meet the Irish community see how they have bought in to the culture when it comes to corporate giving to civil society.  This should be our first port of call, as well as approaching individuals.</p><p>I have no doubt that corporate Ireland would respond positively if this were put to it in a cogent and constructive way.  There is something in it for businesses.  We must also ensure they are acknowledged.  No one can blame any business or firm wanting acknowledgement.  We must be generous in our acknowledgement, depending on where the money goes.  I have often seen businesses giving money and it has just been taken.  There are very simple ways of providing for an acknowledgement locally and it should be possible to do this.  Television programmes such as the weather forceast have a product attached to it; in this case I believe it is Avonmore cream.  This has become part of how television services raise money.  I do not suggest we should be quite this extreme, but there are subtle ways of providing for an acknowledgement.</p><p>I compliment the Minister.  I hope everything will be positive in our response.  I would, however, go one step further.</p> <p>In that context, as a united political grouping we should seek to sell this back to the wider community in a proactive way.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.203" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="16:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200020#V00200"><p>I welcome the Minister, Deputy Hogan.  I assure Senator &Oacute; Murch&uacute; that The One Percent Difference campaign is designed to encourage, in a targeted and focused way, businesses, companies and corporations to start giving.  The Irish people are known for their generosity but  we have not co-ordinated our efforts in the context of how we might procure money from them.  The Government has put in place a number of very successful initiatives.  Two highlights in this regard are the jobs initiative and The Gathering.  The One Percent Difference campaign is similar to both of these in that it is targeted, focused and professional in the context of encouraging people to donate money to charity.</p><p>This matter is not all about money, the question of time also arises.  One cannot buy time.  If people are not in a position to donate 1% of their incomes, and I accept that many individuals find themselves in difficult and challenging financial circumstances, they may still be in a position to give of their time.  The time of those who have resources could still be extremely valuable because they may possess a certain expertise which could be very useful to either a voluntary or a charitable group.</p><p>It is a matter of concern that some major philanthropists are reaching the end of their engagement with this country.  I am sure that engagement has been very successful and that some of the projects they have initiated have made a difference to the lives of Irish people.  I am aware of some of the work done by Atlantic Philanthropies and I know it has had a profound impact on many individuals.  On Wednesday last, a number of people I invited to Leinster House gave a presentation in the audio-visual room on restorative practices.  I only discovered during their briefing that some of the funding their organisation receives comes from Atlantic Philanthropies.  The position is similar with regard to the One Foundation.  We need to learn from what has been done by these organisations in the context of their engagement with Ireland.</p><p>The One Percent Difference campaign will bring matters to an entirely new level and will facilitate companies which may not have a tradition of giving on a professional basis.  Such companies will now have an opportunity to donate, as will individuals of high net worth who may be seeking projects in which to invest or to which to donate.  If those to whom I refer visit the campaign website, I have no doubt they will receive guidance in respect of some very worthwhile projects which could benefit from their money.</p><p>Some sections of the Charities Act, which was passed in 2009, have been activated but there are others which remain to be brought into force.  I suggest that the Minister consider, in his own good time, establishing a charities regulator because such an individual could prove extremely useful.  Such a regulator could easily be funded by using a small proportion of the incomes of the various charities in the sector.  There are many charities which do a great deal of good work but there is much duplication.  Issues also arise in the context of the collection of cash.  The appointment of a regulator would bring a great deal of confidence to those operating in the sector.  A regulator would establish what is best practice, introduce checks and balances and ensure that charities operate in accordance with the principles of best corporate governance.  I refer, in particular, to the smaller charities which might not necessarily possess the resources required to put in place such checks and balances.</p><p>I am of the view that this campaign is going to be a fundamental part of our recovery.  Senator &Oacute; Murch&uacute; referred to the 450,000 people who visited Derry for Fleadh Cheoil na h&Eacute;ireann.  Everyone is aware of the massive economic boost which Dublin, particularly the north side of the city, recently enjoyed from the two all-Ireland finals, one of which went to a replay.  I am of the view that there may be scope to consider whether sporting organisations should be granted charitable status or something similar.  Such a development might encourage more businesses to donate money to sport.  Sponsorship of sporting events by alcohol companies is eventually going to come to an end and this will give rise to particular challenges.</p> <p>There is a great deal of change taking place in that sector.</p><p>I compliment the Minister on implementing the recommendations that were put to him and ensuring it is done professionally.  In The One Percent Difference campaign, we have an initiative that is easily understood and has a very clear message.  I hope it will result in a mass movement throughout the country of people who want to do good by society, make a difference, promote equality and ensure that those who are less well off can benefit from their generosity.  It is a challenge for us all, whether in terms of time or money, but it should be embraced on a national basis by as many people as possible.  I look forward to welcoming the Minister back in the future for a review of the difference the campaign is making.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.205" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1176" speakername="Katherine Zappone" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200021#W00200"><p>I welcome the Minister, Deputy Phil Hogan.  It is a pleasure to follow Senators Martin Conway and Labhr&aacute;s &Oacute; Murch&uacute;, both of whom spoke with great passion on this important issue.  The launch of The One Percent Difference campaign is an important step towards the development of a culture of strategic giving in Ireland.  As I understand it, it effectively represents the implementation of the first recommendation in the report of the forum on philanthropy and fund-raising, which the Minister convened soon after taking office.  It is great to have an opportunity to celebrate the launch of the new campaign and reflect on what is happening.</p><p>It is absolutely crucial for this country's recovery that the Minister maintains a high-profile leadership role in the promotion of a culture of strategic giving which calls on the civic, ethical and financial resources of all citizens.  Government leadership is vital in a context where all the research demonstrates that Ireland is behind in this regard.  That research offers various analyses as to why it should be so.  One of the greatest barriers is the belief or ideology that it is a matter solely for government to fulfil the cultural, social and economic needs of its people.  On the contrary, in a progressive, post-modern, 21st century country we require a robust and growing partnership between citizens and government.  Mr. Bill Clinton, former President of the United States, spoke a great deal about this when he was in Dublin.  Irish culture must embrace partnership between citizens and government to support the wealth of - and the wealth generated by - the non-profit, social, civic and cultural sectors.</p><p>As colleagues and the Minister observed, for the initiative to succeed we need everybody to give and, moreover, to do so strategically.  In fact, we need people to give back and give forward.  The One Percent Difference campaign, it its awareness-raising and media activities, is presenting the Irish people with this message in a straightforward and effective way.  Philanthropy Ireland helpfully circulated information to Members, including links to some of its excellent advertisements, in case we had missed them.  I welcome the Minister's leadership in encouraging and supporting the campaign.</p><p>It is important to emphasise the urgency of the challenge to grow the culture of strategic giving.  We are all aware of the tremendous number of charities, non-profit organisations, cultural agencies and initiatives and community-based organisations - many of which Senators are engaged in - that have had to find ways to continue to operate despite being stripped to the bone of past resources.  They have been obliged to do more with less and largely succeeded in that regard, but their spirit and motivation have been significantly impacted by the long period of financial crisis.  We have a responsibility as law makers, policy makers and public leaders to ensure the spirit of cultural and social innovation is not damaged beyond repair.  We have not yet come to that, but I am deeply concerned that if more resources do not come on stream soon, then we may start to lose one of the Irish people's greatest assets, namely, the ingenuity and idealism which can create the social and cultural conditions for the recovery of our economy.</p> <p>We need cultural resources too.  With the launch of The One Percent Difference campaign, I want to affirm two critical elements of its message.  The first is the encouragement for everyone to give, a point on which two previous speakers spoke eloquently.  The Minister referred to President Clinton speaking about democratising the culture of giving.  That point hit home.  Secondly, the message going out is to think about giving in a more strategic manner.  At the beginning of the report of the Forum on Philanthropy and Fund-raising is a message: <blockquote><br />Philanthropy is a particular kind of charitable giving.  It is focused on the root causes of problems and making a sustainable improvement, as distinct from contributing to immediate relief.</blockquote>We want people to give in an efficient and effective way yet we also want people to give because to give, to give back and to give forward is one of the most human things to do.  We want to find ways to encourage people to touch the great human capacity of empathy as well as creativity.  I was taken by a recent article from the international edition of <i>The New York Times</i>about the philanthropy of Ralph Lauren and recalling his most recent philanthropy project, which was restoring an amphitheatre of the <i>&eacute;cole nationale sup&eacute;rieur des beaux-arts</i>.  The article quotes him: &quot;I don't like the word 'philanthropy,' because it separates me from the emotion of how and why I did things.&#8221;.  Is philanthropy a foreign word?  I actually like the word but I am struck by the fact it is a difficult word in our culture.  Is it a word devoid of emotion?  Yes, we need to be strategic, thoughtful and results-oriented and we need to use our logical models to plan the change we want to bring about but we must never go so far into that territory that we divide ourselves and our people from the emotion and the heart of giving.</p><p> I have a number of questions on the campaign.  Senator Conway referred to looking forward to reviewing some of the results of the campaign.  The forum report refers to setting a target to increase private giving by 10% year-on-year to 2016.  Are there plans on how to measure the increase in giving related to this campaign?  How will we know if the forum and the national giving campaign has been successful?</p><p> As I read the recommendations of the forum, which is effectively a roadmap to develop a culture of strategic giving in Ireland, I noted the four primary recommendations are interlinked.  Any one will not work too well without progress on other fronts.  I phoned people yesterday to put together some reflections and they made this point.  Let us remind ourselves of some of the other recommendations.  Can the Minister indicate to us, today or later, if there have been developments on the forum's fiscal and infrastructural recommendations on tax reform?  I understand a social innovation fund is being set up and some moneys have been granted by the Government and philanthropic organisations.  Has there been progress in setting up the &euro;10 million fund for the establishment and growth of social innovations?</p><p> I am mindful of our budget.  In his speech about entrepreneurship, innovation and investment, the Minister for Finance, Deputy Noonan, referred to measures to encourage the business initiative.  In the Action Plan for Jobs, there was a recommendation for Forf&aacute;s to publish a report on how social enterprise can contribute to our sector.  The report was published and the Minister of State, Deputy Sherlock, set up an intergovernmental group to determine how to progress the recommendations of the Forf&aacute;s report.  I am concerned that one report will follow another.  I wish the budget had contained an announcement about investment in social enterprise as well as in the business sector.  Perhaps it is coming soon and perhaps the Minister can comment on this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.207" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1162" speakername="Denis Landy" time="16:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200023#Y00100"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House and I also welcome the fact that the House is giving this issue a further airing.  The Minister launched this campaign in June 2013 and the campaign is now being giving greater publicity.  The radio advertisements to which Senator &Oacute; Murch&uacute; referred are giving the people of Ireland a greater understanding of the campaign.  Irish people have a long tradition of giving to charity but this is usually done in a sporadic fashion.  We have donated in a reactive way rather than in a regulated way.  I agree with the previous speaker on the point that Irish people are not comfortable with the notion of "philanthropy".  I always associate philanthropy with America rather than with Ireland.  However, the Irish people give generously in comparison to other countries.  A total of 89% of Irish people have given to charities but only on a sporadic basis.  We need to change that mindset.  Only 15% of Irish people make regular donations to charity while across the water in the UK, 36% of people donate on a regular basis.  Senator &Oacute; Murch&uacute; also referred to corporate donations.  The Irish level of corporate donations is at only 1%, a very low level.  I will give an example from my own area.  Merck Sharp &amp;amp; Dohme is based outside Carrick-on-Suir.  That company gives a phenomenal amount of money to the local community.  I do not have a figure but practically every local organisation gets money in some shape or form from that company.  I would like to see a marrying of the local donation and the local community benefit under The One Percent Difference, in order to make a difference.</p><p>Seamus Mulconry is the head of Philanthropy Ireland and he spoke recently about the amount of money which it is hoped to be raised by this project.  He said we need to raise &euro;800 million by 2016.  That seems to be a significant amount of money but with the corporate donation level at 0.1% of pre-tax profits it is not such a great amount of money when one takes into the amount of money earned by foreign direct investment companies and traditional and indigenous companies.  In my view the plan is very achievable and I commend the Minister on his work.  More work is needed in the communities on this issue.  We need to show local businesses how they can enhance their business.  Senator &Oacute; Murch&uacute; referred to the weather forecast advertisement.  Many local businesses need to be supported by the local community in order to survive.  Such businesses can contribute to their local communities as part of The One Percent Difference.  It not necessarily a national-level programme.  In my view, it will have more of an effect if implemented at local level.  Very little has been made of the fact that one per cent of a person's time and effort can be committed locally.  It is not all about money.  We are living in difficult times and some people will not be able to contribute a percentage of their net income because they do not have an income.  However, people can contribute one percent of their time and that time can be translated into voluntary work or into helping to fund-raise for an organisation.  This part of the campaign should be emphasised more.  I ask for the Minister's comments.</p> <p>We are a great nation to give our time, and several speakers have referred to the number of hours given at a local level by people to our national sports of hurling and football.  Many hours are also given to music and the arts by people at a local level.  This garners goodwill in a community, bringing happiness and joy, and it costs no money at all.  This should not just be about money and it should also consider the giving of time, which can be translated into a feel-good factor for communities.</p><p>This campaign also offers people an opportunity to stand back and look at what we have done in this society.  Nobody in the world is better at donating when there is a disaster and we are the first to give money to donation campaigns.  Nevertheless, we must change our thought process regarding charity and providing money to the likes of this campaign.  The campaign must steer a message on what it is doing, and people must be aware of the facts.  I ask for the Minister's thoughts on the second part of the campaign, which should be about what will happen with money and emphasise the voluntary time element of the effort.  If those could be achieved as part of the overall campaign, we would reach the &euro;800 million target set by the chief executive of Philanthropy Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.209" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200024#Z00200"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House and I am glad to have the opportunity to make a few points about this campaign.  We all agree with the ambition of The One Percent Difference campaign, although sadly, the first I heard of it was when this debate was scheduled.  I am regularly on-line and read newspapers, although I am clearly not sufficiently well-read.  If I am admitting the first I heard of this was when this debate was scheduled, we must raise the campaign's profile.  For that reason, we should celebrate the fact we are holding the debate, and I hope the other House has a similar debate.  We should use the opportunities we have, through the media and otherwise, to promote the campaign.</p><p>  I am sure everybody will mention that Irish people are world renowned for contributing to charity and as Senator Landy has mentioned, perhaps we are more renowned when there is a global or international crisis or major event where lives are lost and money is needed.  We are <i>per capita</i> bigger contributors than anywhere else.  The point has been well made, and 89% of Irish adults give to a charity, compared to 58% in the UK and 40% in Germany.  As Senator Landy - and I am sure Senator &Oacute; Murch&uacute; - mentioned, at 0.1% of profit, it seems the top 500 companies in Ireland could do more in contributing to charity.</p><p>  Coming from the sector, I know these companies are putting together a budget for philanthropy; a company like United Drug might give &euro;100,000 annually to philanthropic and charitable organisations but many companies have basic rules such as stipulating that all recipients must get &euro;200.  I do not know if that kind of approach has the kind of penetrative impact it could, especially if a campaign like The One Percent Difference campaign could indicate areas of focus.  I know we are focusing heavily on the arts, and I will speak on that in a moment.  We could have a government-guided approach on the issues funded - perhaps by up to &euro;800 million - on an annual basis, with a menu of areas that we would like people to support.  We could also stipulate tangible outcomes to be achieved in that respect, which might help focus minds in the corporate sector.  If they see an initiative that they wish to support, it would be better than the approach I outlined as taking place now.  I picked United Drug but I am sure there are countless companies, including multinationals and the larger publicly quoted indigenous companies, that could be involved.  It would be a better strategic approach.</p><p>  As Members of the Oireachtas, I imagine many of us far exceed the 1% target in our donations.  Quickly totting up the organisations with which I am involved and support, the contribution comes to 6.5% or 7%, and I am sure I am at the lower end of contributions made by Members of both Houses.</p> <p>Getting everybody up to 1%, even in these difficult times, would be good.  We need in selling that idea to highlight the tangible outcomes that can be achieved.</p><p>Governments have consistently been penny wise and pound foolish regarding the arts.  It is an easy target and a few million euro is taken from the sector every year.  For example, &euro;3.1 million was taken from the Irish Sports Council in the budget.  These are headings we do not automatically acknowledge as being huge contributors to the revenue of the State with great potential.  We need to examine this issue.  The arts sector provides 80,000 jobs and contributes approximately &euro;5 billion to the Exchequer, but it has scope to generate tens of billions of euro, if targeted correctly.  We can generate larger returns for small investments in the arts.  This does not jump out at people as a sector that can create many jobs, but it can and we should think outside the box in this regard.  There may be low hanging fruit in the sector to create jobs.</p><p>I have raised the issue of sports tourism previously.  With others, I championed the Rally Ireland project.  The Volvo Ocean Race and Tall Ships events have since been held and run well throughout the country.  Rally Ireland generated &euro;50 million following a small investment, while the return was similar for the Volvo Ocean Race.  Yesterday I spoke to somebody in Sligo who was involved in the hosting of the world championships in paddleboarding.  That event could attract an infinite number of visitors.  According to his calculations, it will be worth more to Ireland than the boat race.  If we were to target ten events worldwide to bring to Ireland which would be worth &euro;50 million each, that would generate &euro;500 million in revenue.  Every &euro;1 million spent on such events equates to 13 jobs.  If we produced a list of events such as the fleadh hosted by Comhaltas Ceolt&oacute;ir&iacute; &Eacute;ireann which has a number of spin off events, we could target them to generate more revenue.  That would not take from the small amounts given to other needy charities.  Along with being the right thing to do in terms of being philanthropic, charitable and donating to organisations, such events can create jobs and additional revenue streams for the State.</p><p>I am grateful for the opportunity to contribute.  I hope the Minister will up the ante to raise the profile of this campaign, as we all should.  I will try, notwithstanding the fact that yesterday was the first time I had heard about it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.211" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="16:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200025#AA00200"><p>I welcome the Minister and thank him for the work done to date on this valuable proposal.  It is important to develop this concept.  Companies look for specific projects to sponsor rather than giving a set amount to a number of voluntary organisations.  There is an interesting connection between expenditure and what it is used for.  A member of my family works in Kenya where in a local school there is one teacher for every 70 pupils.  It is being suggested companies should sponsor a teacher, which would cost &euro;1,200 a year.  This would mean a direct link with specific expenditure, as opposed to the company providing &euro;1,200 for the school generally.  This approach to projects needs to be developed in the State.</p><p>I am involved in a project where 30 children who have dropped out of school are provided with one-to-one teaching by 18 teachers on a voluntary basis.  These 18 people are giving more than 1% and as a result of their voluntary contribution last year, six of the young people sat the leaving certificate applied, while another six sat the junior certificate examinations.  It is expected that 14 young people who had dropped out of the education system will sit examinations during the coming year.  This is the result of the voluntary contribution made.</p><p>I refer to third level colleges.  I graduated from UCC.</p> <p>It is interesting how in the past ten to 15 years UCC has brought in &euro;87 million in voluntary contributions for projects it specifically targeted to sell to people.  One donation alone was for more than &euro;5 million.  UCC has adopted a proactive approach to getting in money for projects.  Without getting such funding, the college would not have been able to proceed with projects.</p><p>One of the interesting things that has been evident in the United States for some time is that when people leave a third level institution, one member in each class has the role of keeping track of 14 or 15 students within the class and he or she must feed back the information on their location in the United States or another part of the world.  Each graduate pays $100 a year for the first ten years after leaving college.  For the next ten years they pay $500 a year and for the following ten years they pay $1,000 a year.  If we applied these figures to the Minister, this year he would pay &euro;1,000 to UCC as a graduate of the institution.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.213" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/967" speakername="Phil Hogan" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200026#BB00200"><p>How does the Senator know that I am not?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.214" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200026#BB00300"><p>It is a system used in many universities and something we should consider and encourage in universities in this country.  Irish graduates are doing well, regardless of what part of the world they are in.  It is a question of giving back and helping our institutions, especially in the area of research and development.  With money coming into third level institutions, research and development is a very important part of job creation.  It is one area on which we should work and in which we should make a significant effort.  </p><p>I thank the Minister for the work he has done in this area.  We have much work to do and much catching up to do.  We all have a part to play in this regard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.215" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1167" speakername="Fiach MacConghail" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200026#BB00400"><p>The Minister is building a strong reputation.  I give him credit for taking the political lead on philanthropy.  Whether we call it philanthropy, giving or supporting, it is something that should be considered as a strong legacy.  I do not say the Minister is going anywhere soon, but he should consider it in that way.  He has shown courage and moved the agenda forward.  He listened to people involved in the industry.  The reason I say this - Senator Labhr&aacute;s &Oacute; Murch&uacute; might concur with me - is that we plough a lonely furrow.  I am just back from the United States where I was fund-raising for the weekend.  I am going back on Sunday for ten days to meet people.</p><p>What we sometimes lack is the public congratulations, not to the Abbey Theatre or Comhaltas Ceolt&oacute;ir&iacute; &Eacute;ireann but the people who give money, and a governmental acknowledgement, whether it is inserted in a speech or mentioned otherwise.  That is of benefit because it endorses a culture and what we are talking about is a cultural shift not only when it comes to giving 1% but also to the Diaspora.  We are aware that through the Global Irish Economic Forum there are a lot of significant members of the Diaspora and also friends of Ireland who want to support us, not necessarily in a transactional way such that in giving something they get something back but on an emotional level.  There is nothing stronger than public commendation, public praise or an acknowledgement.  That would help people such as me.  For instance, I am going to Boston next weekend.  We will have the great privilege of meeting Thomas O'Neill, son of Tip O'Neill, who is the president of The Abbey Theatre Foundation chapter in Boston.  He is hosting a dinner which I will attend for 30 potential prospects for us in Boston.  The Government can support us without putting its hand in its pocket by endorsing us.  One of the recommendations that emerged from the Global Irish Economic Forum two weeks ago was a simple one, namely, that if trade delegations or Ministers travel abroad, they should ask the Arts Council, Comhaltas Ceolt&oacute;ir&iacute; &Eacute;ireann or the Abbey Theatre whether we have an interest in these cities because there is nothing like a Minister, not just the Minister for Arts, Heritage and the Gaeltacht or the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade but any Minister, acknowledging the connections for cultural, sports or social activity in which we are involved in the United States because that increases leverage.  It makes sense.</p> <p>People give money and that can actually cause leverage for us to create employment and, more important in terms of my business, improve access to culture and the arts and further the right of citizens to gain access to the arts for as little money as possible, or none.</p><p>Let me outline what is interesting about the differences between Ireland and the United States.  In Ireland, corporate giving is actually quite strong.  In fairness to the corporate companies here, the level is quite high.  The challenge concerns individual giving.  As Senator Zappone asked, how can we encourage people to become more strategic in their giving, be it through direct donations or volunteering.  We need to encourage not only a cultural change but also a more mature approach.</p><p>I welcome the measures in this year's Finance Bill to simplify the tax incentive for charity donations.  We operate in a declining public funding environment in which the cumulative effect of yearly decreases in funding is taking hold.  The cultural shift that the Minister is spearheading is one that I acknowledge wholeheartedly.</p><p>One of the recommendations of the report of the forum, which Senator Zappone mentioned, was for a yearly increase of 10%.  We must be careful that the Minister is not hoisted with his own petard regarding a particular figure.  The target is far too ambitious and not based on specific data.  We are missing data.  Senator O'Brien will outline how we can try to have a baseline regarding data and the number of charities so we will be able to be clear about this.  We must tie in metrics as we do not have accurate data.  By way of support, I caution the Minister not to repeat the 10% target year on year.  By 2016, we are talking about a 60% increase, up to roughly &euro;800 million.  That is a very ambitious target.  I deal with ambitious targets in that I have raised &euro;800,000 already this year through private giving.  Having targets and being realistic are separate, however.  We need to communicate that better so the Minister will not be put in a position in which he must defend an approach that is still not sufficiently accurate.</p><p>This week is Best Will in the World Week, a week in which people are encouraged to leave some funding in their legacy.  This is an area of future growth.  Some might find the subject too delicate and sensitive.  The Abbey Theatre benefited twice from it.  One of our former artistic directors, Lennox Robinson, left the rights of all his plays to the Abbey Theatre when he died.  Therefore, the Abbey Theatre makes money as a consequence.  George Bernard Shaw is an extraordinary example.  He left one third of the royalties from his plays to the National Gallery of Ireland.  When we put on &quot;Major Barbara&quot; this summer, a significant proportion of the money made at the box office went to the National Gallery of Ireland.  That is really smart move.  There are very inventive ways of leaving a legacy.</p><p>I congratulate the Minister and support Senator Zappone's question.  We must ensure the metrics are right.  How can we evaluate the success of the campaign?  While the aspiration is correct, we need actual figures by which to assess the campaign, which I believe will be a success.  I have one small concern, based on data reported to us.  The One Percent Difference website had 25,300 unique visitors but only 722 clicked onto a cause.  That is somewhat disappointing.  We need to be clear on the metrics so we can actually share the legacy of success in a couple of years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.217" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1143" speakername="John Whelan" time="17:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200027#CC00200"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House.  He has shown great leadership, vision and reforming zeal.  This is a superb intervention.  It is good that a Minister of Deputy Hogan's calibre and reputation is endorsing the campaign in the Seanad and giving it his imprimatur.  That is important for public confidence and trust.</p><p>  I beg to differ with the esteemed former President of the United States, Bill Clinton, who said the campaign is a good idea.  He is wrong; it is a fantastic idea.  He is underrating it entirely.  The Minister should let the former US President know that Senator Whelan is keeping his eye on him just as <i>The Skibbereen Eagle </i>was keeping an eye on the Tsar of Russia.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.218" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/967" speakername="Phil Hogan" time="17:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200028#DD00100"><p>I will let him know that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.219" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1143" speakername="John Whelan" time="17:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200028#DD00200"><p>From childhood, we are taught to donate and give.  I recall from my school days when we made donations for the nuns on the missions overseas.  It may have become a little more fancy and sophisticated now with the word &ldquo;philanthropy&rdquo;.  However, I accept Senator Zappone&rsquo;s point that everyone can be a philanthropist.  The message of The One Percent Difference campaign is that everyone can give a little which can help a lot.</p><p>As Senator Mac Conghail said, people also want to be thanked for their donations but also want to see the end result.  It is nice to have a gesture of recognition for donations.  Never before in living memory have we needed to dig deep and show real social solidarity whether it is for the arts, culture, education or charitable work.  People and families are struggling.  Those of us who are more fortunate can certainly do with a little less.  We could also give up a little and make better use of what we have.  Sometimes I am ashamed at how much we have and at how much is wasted such as household food waste.  We could organise ourselves better to prevent such waste.  A significant difference would be made with just a small donation through a weekly direct debit to a charity, sporting or educational organisation.  We must dig deep and help those less fortunate.</p><p>I commend the Government on the progress it has made in this area.  The Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Shatter, has made significant progress in the establishment of a charities regulator.  This, however, needs to be expedited.  There is a direct link between people giving and public confidence in that donated moneys are put to best use.</p><p>I commend those who give freely of their time to activities such as the GAA or caring for others through meals on wheels.  They are an inspiration and great example to us and really put us to shame.  Many organisations would fall apart if it were not for their volunteers, people willing to give up their free time.</p><p>Going into the winter with its long evenings, no one should go cold, lonely or hungry for the want of us having a bit of extra thought, care and compassion.  Irish people are generous but now is the time to dig a little deeper until we get over this hillock of a recession.  The One Percent Difference campaign, which the Minister has fronted, is to be commended and supported.  All Members of the Seanad support it and will ensure it is driven on in our local communities.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.220" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1169" speakername="Mary Ann O'Brien" time="17:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200028#DD00300"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House and congratulate him on all his work on philanthropy.  One of my main passions since I became a Senator has been interacting with the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Alan Shatter, on the need for a charities regulator.</p> <p>I wish to speak about this issue.  There have been two main constants, namely, the public and the charity sector itself.  Everybody knows donations to charity are falling on a yearly basis, primarily due to the public having less disposable income to donate to worthy causes.  Never before has it been so important that we put in place a framework of regulation covering transparency and checks and balances.  To return to a point made by Senator Mac Conghail, we do not have a list, and I would love to see a website where anyone can see a beautiful list of charities, what they do and where their giving is.  The main word is &quot;transparency&quot;.</p><p> Like Senator Mac Conghail I am fund-raising all the time, in my case for the Jack &amp;amp; Jill Foundation.  I am glad to say we are doing well but what we find with regard to corporations, particularly foreign direct investment companies, is that my gosh golly one must have one's house in order before one goes near them because they want to audit one and need to know one is squeaky clean.  We have no regulatory framework.  The Minister, Deputy Shatter, is superb but he cannot get the regulator up and running fast enough.  We might have put the cart before the horse because we need this for the initiative of the Minister, Deputy Hogan, to go forward in a powerful way.  I hope he agrees with me.  The two Departments need to work hand-in-hand.  I know they are working hard on it.</p><p> Last year, the media, God bless their hearts, damaged the sector by the way it was portrayed.  We had &quot;Prime Time&quot;, <i>The Sunday Times</i>and the <i>Evening Herald</i>discussing the secrecy of salaries.  Even last week I read in the <i>Irish Examiner</i>that donations from the public to a large Irish charity decreased from &euro;8.1 million to &euro;2.8 million in 2012, and there was a 45% drop in donations in 2011.  The good news is the charity in question received a 4% uplift in the Government's donation which was &euro;50 million.  What upset me is the charity spent &euro;1.4 million on fund-raising in 2012 as opposed to &euro;1.3 million in 2011, which is a 13% increase.  Explaining the massive drop in donations, the directors of the charity stated no major appeals for funds were made in 2012 but it spent &euro;1.4 million on fund-raising.  This particular charity has &euro;31 million in the bank on deposit.  When people read such things in the newspapers they wonder why they should give to such a charity.  As I stated to the Minister, Deputy Shatter, no charity should keep more than two years of what it needs on deposit in a bank account.  Many big charities in the country have in excess of &euro;300 million or &euro;400 million.  This is hard for those of us with a smaller social entrepreneur charity organisations but it should not be allowed.</p><p> I have moved away slightly from the actual subject but I am making this point because we need regulations and transparency so the public can be confident and feel their money is going to the right place and is being looked after correctly in a very transparent and responsible way and they know they are getting value for money.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.222" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" speakername="Terry Brennan" time="17:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200029#EE00200"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire go dt&iacute; an Teach.  While monetary planned giving in Ireland is low, Irish people are among the highest donors to charity in the developed world, as has already been mentioned by some of my colleagues.  A total of 89% of Irish adults give to charity compared to 58% in the UK and 40% in Germany.  Although most Irish people give to charity, only 15% do so in a planned regular way.  By contrast in the UK 36% of donors make regular donations.</p> <p>The contrast in Ireland between the widespread readiness to give spontaneously and the relatively low levels of personal and corporate giving in a more proactive, purposeful and engaged way represents a major opportunity to harness the untapped potential to widen the extent of planned giving and the amount given by the public and businesses.</p><p>Philanthropy is not a word Irish people use often.  In our history, we have benefited a great deal from philanthropy.  Anybody can be a philanthropist because it is the intent, not the amount, that makes someone a philanthropist.  We have many philanthropists in this country.  Philanthropy, in essence, is about committed investment in solving social problems and building a more vibrant civil society.  It is a particular form of charitable giving that is characterised by taking the time to think through how one can best use resources to solve social problems and make a real difference.  There is an appetite among the public for a cultural turning point to restore national pride, self-confidence and a renewed sense of community values to replace the rampant individualism of the Celtic tiger.</p><p>Research shows a commitment to the principle that in tough times we all need to give a bit more and that Ireland's recovery is everybody's business.  We all have a part to play.  Despite the recession, research indicates that if properly asked, Irish people are willing to increase their donations.  Some need more encouragement than others.  Research shows that Irish people respond best when they can see the need and all of us can now see the need for our communities.  Not everyone can contribute financially but we can all pull together to give time to a local community or to a cause we are all passionate about and that makes a tangible difference.  This should be not just for a few days or weeks but for a lifetime.</p><p>The Minister and Senator Whelan mentioned contributions made by voluntary organisations in the country.  I acknowledge the time and effort of many voluntary organisations.  They are all philanthropists and they have given much more than 1% of their time.  GAA clubs have already been instanced, along with the 850 tidy towns groups in the country that are enhancing their towns and villages to make them better places to live in or visit.  They receive support from local businesses but there is an opportunity to increase support to our towns, villages, GAA clubs and sporting organisations.  We also mentioned the arts and Comhaltas Ceolt&oacute;ir&iacute; &Eacute;ireann contributing to a better Ireland.  I congratulate the Minister on this initiative and I assure him of my full support.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.224" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="17:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200030#FF00200"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire.  Ar nd&oacute;igh, t&aacute; an-&aacute;thas orm labhairt ar an &aacute;bhar seo maidir leis an One Percent Difference agus an feachtas seo at&aacute; ar bun.   Tagaim le cuid mhaith d&aacute; bhfuil r&aacute;ite ag mo chomhleaca&iacute; anseo.  According to the dictionary, philanthropy is the performance of charitable or benevolent actions but the root of the word comes from the Greek and means the love of mankind.  We all ask for more philanthropy on that basis.  From my understanding of philanthropy, there is a general sense that it comes from a person or an organisation with a lot of wealth who or which is therefore in a position to give more.  In Ireland we have a reputation of citizens giving a lot to charitable causes.  Much of what has been discussed is volunteerism.  There is a huge sense of volunteerism in the country, where people give freely of their time.</p><p>  Philanthropy has been important here in the past number of years.  It is important to put the debate in the context of these difficult financial times.  Many NGOs are almost completely dependent on the contributions of philanthropic organisations to keep the ship afloat during these difficult times.  A number of large philanthropic organisations are ending their engagement with us and it will cause a lot of angst.  It is important that the money from the campaign is used to support those organisations to ensure we have continuity.  There is a difference between philanthropy and sponsorship.  This country has had a lot of sponsorship by large organisations but the nature of sponsorship is that there is a <i>quid pro quo</i> and that the companies or organisations look for some form of return.  My understanding of philanthropy is that an organisation will give without strings attached, although there must be oversight.</p><p>  Ireland does not have a great record on philanthropy and it is something new to us.  Sinn F&eacute;in welcomed any plans to increase giving.  It is important that any proposals to increase investment in philanthropy are discussed and fully teased out, particularly in respect of taxation.  At the outset, Sinn F&eacute;in has serious concerns about proposals attempting to change the country's tax residency laws under the guise of the giving campaign.  People availing of such laws are tax exiles.  They are Irish residents but they do not stay here for more than 182 years per day and do not pay taxes on global profits, only their Irish interest profits.  We know many of them and it has been reported that they will go to the limit, remaining here for 182 days a year or 280 over two years.  We saw an abuse of the system until 2008.  In 2009, we got rid of the Cinderella clause, where jets took off from Dublin Airport at 11.59 p.m so that the day was not counted.  Sinn F&eacute;in has serious concerns that any attempt to link the national giving campaign with tax breaks for those in exile could lead to the view that we are selling tax residency.</p><p>  However, that does not throw cold water on the whole concept.  The previous Government introduced the domicile levy, which had a lower threshold in terms of what people had to contribute.  The domicile levy is &euro;200,000, which can be written off against tax on Irish interests.  Only seven people paid the domicile levy in the last year for which we have figures.  Some 11,307 people made income tax returns in 2011 and claimed they are not tax resident.  The pool of people to which this could apply is 11,307.  From the domicile levy, we see it is a very low number.</p><p>  Sinn F&eacute;in welcomes the national giving campaign but we are wary of any tax breaks for exiles that may be seen as a way of abusing it.  We are also concerned that philanthropy should never be seen as a replacement for State support.  The State should not abdicate its responsibility in respect of charities, NGOs and arts bodies.  We note concerns brought to our attention that there must be some form of regulation of the bodies in receipt of funding.  In some organisations, there are fears that money donated or given on a philanthropic basis can be swallowed up in structures and administration costs.  Many people would like to see more money spent on projects on the ground.  Go ginear&aacute;lta, f&aacute;ilt&iacute;onn muid roimh an obair at&aacute; ar bun ag an Aire.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.225" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/967" speakername="Phil Hogan" time="17:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200030#FF00300"><p>That is what I am trying to do in the community sector.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.226" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="17:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200030#FF00400"><p>Feicfimid c&eacute;ard a tharl&oacute;idh ansin leis an d&iacute;osp&oacute;ireacht l&aacute; eile.  I am sure we will have a robust debate on the issue when it comes up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.227" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1121" speakername="Paul Bradford" time="17:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200030#FF00500"><p>I welcome the report and the work of Mr. Flannery and his colleagues to bring us this far.  Ronald Reagan described the following sentence as the most feared in the American political language: "I am from the Government and I am here to help."  We are trying to encourage civic participation to a greater level.  It would be a wonderful thing if the old Irish spirit of community help and community giving could be formalised by this and other structures.  The Irish tradition was one of giving and of communities coming together to help.  One of the great victims of the Celtic tiger was that type of approach but now that we are in a different economic place, many more people are reflected on what really matters in society.  The structures presented by the Minister can make a meaningful difference.  Much work remains to be done to change our mindset.</p><p>We can contrast western Europe and the United States.</p> <p>Western Europe has a general policy of high taxation and high state involvement, a policy that produces certain results in the United States as a result of these types of schemes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.229" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1173" speakername="Lorraine Higgins" time="17:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200031#GG00200"><p>The Senator must conclude to allow the Minister to respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.230" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1121" speakername="Paul Bradford" time="17:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200031#GG00300"><p>Great work, not just charitable work, across educational and health services is done as a result of greater public involvement.  I hope we can learn from this and bring about the policies the Minister, from his contribution, and the forum's report are trying to produce.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.231" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/967" speakername="Phil Hogan" time="17:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200031#GG00400"><p>I thank the significant number of Members of the House who have made a contribution to this debate.  I thank them for sharing their personal experiences in so many cases but also for their suggestions to ensure we are going in the right direction and for their proposed changes to make it a better strategy.  There is no better person than Senator Labhr&aacute;s &Oacute; Murch&uacute; who has spent a lifetime involved in voluntary activity and developing a brand for Ireland through the Irish language and music that is second to none in terms of its attractiveness to the Diaspora.  Together with Senator Fiach Mac Conghail who is involved in literature and the arts, the House has two very experienced Senators in the world of philanthropy who have been getting on with the job in advance of a structured approach such as the forum on philanthropy some years ago.</p><p>As I described in my opening contribution, we are in a difficult position.  Atlantic Philanthropies and The One Foundation are leaving the field of philanthropy.  This will create a financial gap for many organisations that are currently beneficiaries and which have benefited significantly, including in Northern Ireland.  I am surprised that Senator Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh has expressed concerns and created a diversion on matters relating to exiles and which have nothing to do with this debate.  He and his organisation, Sinn F&eacute;in, have had many dinners in recent weeks in the United States - political and otherwise; therefore, he and Sinn F&eacute;in, more than any other organisation represented in the House, know the value of securing foreign direct investment through these sources-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.232" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="17:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200031#GG00500"><p>They were very happy to give it to Sinn F&eacute;in.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.233" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/967" speakername="Phil Hogan" time="17:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200031#GG00600"><p>How Sinn F&eacute;in channels and spends the money is its own business, but in the case of the arts, literature and music there are rules which perhaps might not comply with the normal political fund-raising Sinn F&eacute;in carries out in the United States-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.234" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="17:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200031#GG00700"><p>Fine Gael organised a dinner in New York.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.235" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/967" speakername="Phil Hogan" time="17:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200031#GG00800"><p>I know it is a sensitive matter for Sinn F&eacute;in, but what we are trying to do-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.236" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="17:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200031#GG00900"><p>Not at all; it is not.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.237" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/967" speakername="Phil Hogan" time="17:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200031#GG01000"><p>-----is to have a general conversation about how we can improve matters in order to benefit disadvantaged communities, the arts and the music world and to deal with educational disadvantage.  We plan to generate a not-for-profit sector which is transparent and regulated.</p><p>I take on board Senator O'Brien's point on the charities regulator.  I will have a conversation with the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Alan Shatter.  The charities sector was part of the Department responsible for community issues, but for some reason it ended up in the Department of Justice and Equality.  I do not know how that happened in 2011, but we are working closely together with the Minister who has made some progress in the past year.</p><p>Training of fund-raising staff is part and parcel of what we are seeking to do.  Many speakers have observed that the public must have confidence that fund-raising personnel are not doing it for personal gain but are fund-raising for an organisation and that the information on their identification document meets the statutory requirements we wish to put in place.  That is the remit of the charities regulator and the charities legislation.  It is important to have confidence in the system of fund-raising.  We have established a diploma course for people who wish to train in fund-raising.  Dublin City University is the principal provider of this course to train and improve fund-raisers in order to attract inward investment into organisations experiencing financial difficulties.  As Senator Katherine Zappone said, it is a partnership between the citizen and the Government, including the not-for-profit sector.  We are seeking to build on that partnership.  The Minister for Finance has already implemented some of the fiscal recommendations made in the report.  We will not get the extra &euro;300 million unless we can make it an attractive proposition and compete with the US companies that have a greater incentive in their home country to give philanthropic donations.  We need to level the playing pitch in this regard to encourage these companies to participate in Ireland</p><p>The company established for the purpose of developing the social innovation fund has been incorporated recently.  The Minister of State, Deputy Sean Sherlock, will chair an interdepartmental group on how that project can be advanced.  I acknowledge that the comparative data are required to show that what is being done stands up to scrutiny and in order that the contributions can be valued.  Particularly with regard to finance, we need to reinforce the confidence of the general public and organisations generally in order that they know their donations are going to the desired beneficiaries.</p><p>Senator Denis Landy spoke about donations which were regular and consistent.  We are hoping to develop this form of donation and it will mean a cultural change.  It could be that the meaning of the word &quot;philanthropy&quot; has not been understood by the public.  We may need to talk more about national giving rather than philanthropy.  It is a word that conjures up the notion of exiles, as Senator Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh has tried to describe it.  That is not our intention-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.238" nospeaker="true" time="17:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.239" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/967" speakername="Phil Hogan" time="17:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200031#GG01200"><p>-----rather it means giving by ordinary people on a national level.  We want a situation where everyone's contribution of time or money will be valued and every contribution is valued equally.  That is our mission statement.  I will take on board the Senator's point on the use of the word "philanthropy".</p><p>I am curious that Senator Marc MacSharry had not heard about The One Percent Difference campaign.  We will again circulate all Oireachtas Members with the details of the campaign for those who might have missed them.  We are very anxious that people are informed about the full extent of the campaign.  Our policy is very open and transparent.  </p><p>Senator Colm Burke referred to opportunities in the area of research and development and their extension into the area of enterprise.  The Minister of State, Deputy Sean Sherlock, will consider these opportunities for more philanthropic donations as part of his role as Minister of State in the Department of Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation.  This has been done successfully in places such as the Dublin Institute of Technology, the University of Limerick and University College Cork.  The universities and third level institutions cannot survive without the donations they receive from international high net worth individuals and for which we are very grateful.</p><p>I agree with Senator John Whelan that acknowledging contributions is as important as receiving them.  We will consider how to publicise the names of the programme beneficiaries and acknowledge the donors in the true sense, by their being recognised in the community or project involved.  The diploma in fund-raising will help to raise public confidence in how donations are dealt with.</p><p>Senator Terry Brennan spoke about the value of voluntary effort such as the work of the GAA and the Tidy Town committees.  The work and contribution of such organisations are invaluable and sometimes intangible.  We recognise that work by holding national competitions.  The GAA organises itself and the Tidy Town committees are helped by means of substantial sponsorship and money from my Department in an effort to motivate people to make their home place better and more environmentally pleasant.  This sponsorship will continue.  The 2014 Estimates will not see any reduction in the financial support for these initiatives.</p><p>I have covered most of the issues raised by Senators.  I thank everyone for his or her contribution to the debate.  We are anxious to meet the gap by 2016, even though Senator Fiach Mac Conghail is correct that this is very ambitious.  However, it is achievable, given the traditional generosity of Irish people.  If we can match that generosity with open and transparent structures, that will make it more attractive for donors and give them the extra fiscal incentive.  If we can meet these requirements, The One Percent Difference campaign will be regarded as quick-starting a new community initiative that will meet requirements in so many areas of life to make Ireland a better place in which to live, work and take part in recreational activities.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.240" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1173" speakername="Lorraine Higgins" time="17:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200031#GG01300"><p>When it is proposed to sit again?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.241" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="17:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200031#GG01400"><p>At 10.30 a.m. tomorrow.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.242" nospeaker="true" time="17:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200032#HH00025">Adjournment Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.243" nospeaker="true" time="17:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200032#HH00050">Electricity Transmission Network</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.244" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="17:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200032#HH00100"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House.  I have no objection in principle to the new Grid Link project for the south east and the necessary enhancement of supply and expansion of the electricity grid in the region.  As the Minister knows, the project will involve identifying a number of feasible 1 km wide route corridor options for a new 400 kV overhead power line linking Leinster and Munster.  The Grid Link project will help secure a future electricity supply for homes, businesses, farms, factories and communities in Leinster and Munster, providing a platform for economic growth and job creation in the south east and helping Ireland meet its 40% renewable electricity target.  That is the object of the EirGrid, which is laudable.  Nevertheless, I cannot support EirGrid's determination to use overground pylons and wires for the entire length of the routes and rule out the underground option.  In the coming weeks I intend to meet EirGrid representatives, including its chief executive, to discuss my concerns in some considerable detail.</p><p>The Minister is aware that a number of community-based groups have been established to help inform communities about the project and voice the many genuine and serious concerns that people have about it.  I intend to compliment in every way the community-led campaign of opposition that has manifested across the length of the proposed new power lines.  We are at one with campaigning communities across all affected counties and we will continue to use our influence to enhance this community-led effort to secure a rethink of the approach to these planned power lines by EirGrid.</p><p>It appears that despite the clearly expressed opposition of thousands of families living close to the proposed routes of these power lines and support pylons, EirGrid remains fixed on the overhead approach to these projects.  Communities along the length of the proposed power lines are vehemently opposed to the installation of unsightly pylons and rightly fear for the health of all exposed to high-voltage power conduits.  They are fearful for themselves, their families and for the children of these communities.  It is essential that we recognise the reality of the Planning and Development (Strategic Infrastructure) Act 2006, which the Minister and my party voted against.  This legislation facilitates the forcing through of projects, regardless of the expressed wishes of communities, and there is real fear and absolute opposition to the overground approach, which has been voiced along the entire route through County Waterford and other counties in the region.  Large public meetings have been held in several centres and points across Waterford and the south east and the concerns know no political boundaries.  People of all opinions and none are coming together as concerned communities endeavour to ensure that EirGrid takes a different approach.</p><p>There can be no question whatever that there is significant information on record, with eminent, professional and well-researched opinion stating that there is every reason for genuine health concerns.  That fact is indisputable.  These communities are also conscious of the visual impact on the environment of the proposed unsightly string of pylon structures stretching across the beautiful and scenic Comeragh area in County Waterford.  I am not sure if the Minister has ever been in that part of Waterford but if he has been, he would agree that it would be unsightly and not very popular for any State agency to put pylons through this scenic route.</p><p>There are many fears and I am sure the Minister is familiar with many of them.  I hope he will take on board these views.  What role will there be for communities in the planning process, including the first stage that is ongoing?  What supports will be given to communities to raise objections and lodge submissions?  EirGrid has much money at its disposal but local communities do not.  What supports will the Minister put in place to ensure local communities can have a real voice in the planning process?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.245" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/947" speakername="Pat Rabbitte" time="17:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200032#HH00200"><p>Development of the high voltage electricity grid as planned in EirGrid's GRID25 strategy is critical to our long-term economic recovery.  Energy policy has a pivotal role to play in creating the conditions for an economic recovery and for the job creation we need.  We all require access to an affordable and dependable energy supply and the businesses that sell goods and services and provide quality employment need a reliable energy supply that enables them to compete.  Ensuring secure, reliable and safe supplies of electricity, gas and oil is critical to Ireland's ability to attract inward investment and retain and create jobs.</p><p>EirGrid's GRID25 national programme, and specifically the Grid Link infrastructure project, is vital for future socioeconomic progress in Ireland.  The Grid Link project is a key initiative under GRID25 and the project consists of a new 400 kV overhead power line linking Leinster and Munster.  Without this project, the grid in the south and east of Ireland would not be sufficient to meet the region's future electricity needs.  The project will facilitate both conventional generation and renewable energy projects, reinforce the grid in Leinster and Munster, and support future interconnection with grids outside of Ireland.  It is a significant upgrade of the electricity grid across the south and east and is the largest project under the GRID25 programme.</p><p>The Grid Link project will help enable a secure supply of electricity for the region well into the future.  It will empower growth in the south and east of Ireland and involve an estimated &euro;500 million investment.  It will also enable Ireland to meet its 40% renewable target and reduce our reliance on imported fossil fuels.  The Government wants to be able to give a strong consistent message to Irish business and multinationals, and our citizens, that Ireland's electricity networks are robust, modern and safe.  This project is part of EirGrid's programme and is a practical illustration of our collective and continuing commitment to large-scale investment in electricity infrastructure.</p> <p> Currently the EirGrid project team is undertaking detailed analysis of the study area to identify the best possible corridors for development.  As part of this process, on 3 September EirGrid published the stage 1 report on the grid link project identifying a number of route corridor options for the new 400kV power line.  The publication of that report coincided with the beginning of a 12-week public consultation period.</p><p>In the Government Policy Statement on the Strategic Importance of Transmission and Other Energy Infrastructure of July 2012, the imperative for the State companies and all developers of energy projects of early, transparent engagement and consultation with local communities and stakeholders was emphasised.  EirGrid is committed to public consultation and it has engaged in a comprehensive process in regard to the grid link project, which has involved opening five regional information centres, a lo-call project information telephone line and local radio advertising, backed up by national and local print advertising.  The company will take on board information and views on the project, which is still at an early stage.  The identification of route corridor options is a key opportunity for public input, as no decisions have been made regarding the final route of this electricity line.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.247" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="17:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200033#JJ00200"><p>There have been many public meetings in counties Waterford and Kilkenny and elsewhere about the proposed route.  Does the Minister agree that tourism could be curtailed if the landscape is blighted with these pylons, especially in the Comeragh area in County Waterford?  Does he further agree that householders and landowners could experience a reduction in the value of their properties if unsightly pylons are erected up to 50 m from private dwellings and livestock holding areas?  The Minister will agree there are large farming counties and highly populated areas with livestock and wildlife habitats along this route.  How will they be protected?  Does he concur that the proposed pylons would represent a blot on the landscape?  What supports will be put in place to help communities make submissions, especially when the proposals go to An Bord Plean&aacute;la, but also to propose alternatives to overhead power lines?  Why is the underground option not being examined by the company or supported by Government?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.248" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/947" speakername="Pat Rabbitte" time="17:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200033#JJ00300"><p>I have a very good idea of what Sinn F&eacute;in is opposed to but I am having great difficulty finding out what the party is in favour of.  The Senator said he acknowledges that we cannot have economic development without energy and power.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.249" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="17:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200033#JJ00400"><p>This is about communities, not Sinn F&eacute;in.  The Minister should address their concerns.  Will he address the communities?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.250" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1173" speakername="Lorraine Higgins" time="17:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200033#JJ00500"><p>The Minister without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.251" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/947" speakername="Pat Rabbitte" time="17:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200033#JJ00600"><p>I did not interrupt the Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.252" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="17:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200033#JJ00700"><p>I did not get party political.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.253" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/947" speakername="Pat Rabbitte" time="17:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200033#JJ00800"><p>The Senator said he acknowledges that we cannot have economic development without energy and power and I agree with him but he seemed to say we cannot run lines near areas of tourist beauty or across farmland where cattle or horses might graze.  Where will we run them?  The Senator cannot have it both ways.  He cannot say we have to have power lines but not in my backyard.  What is going on in Waterford and along the possible corridors of this essential transmission connection is a public consultation programme where a number of offices have been opened along the way by EirGrid to hear from stakeholders and to stimulate debate but we should not scaremonger about blighting the landscape and blotting the countryside or say, like Hanrahan, "Och&oacute;n, och&oacute;n, before the year is out we will be all ruined".  How are we going to develop a modern economy in this country if we do not have power?  It is essential-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.254" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="17:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200033#JJ00900"><p>Are the communities scaremongering then?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.255" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/947" speakername="Pat Rabbitte" time="17:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200033#JJ01000"><p>No, but I suspect that they are being stoked up by guys like the Senator to cause them to fear.  He even dragged in health issues.  We have had power lines in the country since the late 1940s.  My colleagues and I, especially me because of my equable personality, tend to agree with Sinn F&eacute;in too often and let the party away with things.  The Senator cannot come into the House opposing the provision of power to the regions in the interests of economic development and then say he acknowledges the necessity for the power lines but they should be erected somewhere else.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.256" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="17:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200033#JJ01100"><p>We are addressing concerns and we are asking the Minister to address them and consider the alternatives, which he has not mentioned once.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.257" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/947" speakername="Pat Rabbitte" time="17:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200033#JJ01200"><p>We have established in respect of the North-South grid that it is approximately three and a half times as expensive to put the lines underground.  If we were not here in an adversarial context in this very reflective Chamber and we were outside the House, the Senator would agree it is difficult to find investors to put &euro;500 million into this project, never mind to invest three and a half times that.  This is a welcome investment.  I agree with the Senator that the Comeragh Mountains are a beautiful area and I sincerely hope that whatever happens, they are not in any way despoiled.  I do not think they will be.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.258" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1173" speakername="Lorraine Higgins" time="17:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013102200033#JJ01300"><p>Unfortunately, a Minister is not available to take the matters to be raised on the Adjournment by Senators Burke and Moloney.  I am informed they will be deferred until tomorrow when the Cathaoirleach will select both matters again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-10-22a.259" nospeaker="true" time="17:50:00" ><p>The Seanad adjourned at 5.40 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Wednesday, 23 October 2013.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>