<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.2" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 14:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.4" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.5" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Colm Burke that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:<blockquote><br /><br />The need for the Minister for Health to engage with the Nursing and Midwifery Board of Ireland with a view to resolving the long delays that currently exist in the registration process.</blockquote>I have also received notice from Senator Diarmuid Wilson of the following matter:<blockquote>The need for the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation to address urgently the loss of jobs announced by Liberty Insurance in Cavan, Enniskillen and Dublin.</blockquote>I have also received notice from Senator Averil Power of the following matter:<blockquote>The need for the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine to develop a comprehensive strategy for Howth Harbour that maximises its potential not only as a fishing harbour, but also as a tourism, sports, leisure and community resource, and for the Department to avoid taking steps, such as the proposed introduction of paid parking, that would seriously undermine the harbour's overall benefit to the local economy and community.</blockquote><!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">An Cathaoirleach:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=1866"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1866&amp;amp;pid=PaddyBurke&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=30"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I have also received notice from Senator Higgins of the following matter:<blockquote><br /><br />The need for the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources to explore additional funding streams for the roll-out of natural gas in areas of strategic importance. </blockquote><b></b>I have also received notice from Senator Bradford of the following matter:<blockquote>The need for the Minister for Finance to outline the effort being made by Ireland and its eurozone partners to ensure that Greece will remain a member of the eurozone. </blockquote>I regard the matters raised by the Senators as suitable for discussion.  I have selected the matters raised by Senators Burke, Wilson, Power and Higgins and they will be taken now.  Senator Bradford may give notice on another day of the matter he wishes to raise.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.8" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#B00200">Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.9" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#B00300">Nursing Staff Recruitment</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#B00400"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Gerald Nash, to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#B00500"><p>I, too, welcome the Minister of State and thank him for coming to the House to deal with this matter.  My understanding is that more than 700 applications for registration with the Nursing and Midwifery Board of Ireland are pending.  Earlier in the year I received representations from an Irish person who, following completion of her training in England, had returned to Ireland to take up a job but was unable to do so for 14 weeks even though the hospital needed somebody urgently.  The Minister of State, Deputy Lynch, is reported in today's <i>Irish Examiner</i>as saying that a unit in Cork cannot be opened because the 40 nurses required are not available.  Much of the funding for this unit was raised voluntarily.  However, because of a lack of nursing staff, it cannot open.  I am not suggesting that this is connected to the delays in registration with the Nursing and Midwifery Board but it must be a contributory factor.</p><p>I understand from Nursing Homes Ireland that the HSE is recruiting nurses currently working in private nursing homes and that this is resulting in a significant shortage of nurses in the private nursing home sector.  The private nursing home sector proposes to recruit an additional 300 nurses over the next couple of months, some of whom may be Irish nurses working abroad wishing to return home, which will result in the number of nurses awaiting registration with the Nursing and Midwifery Board increasing to 1,000.  The registration body has cited the cost of employing staff as the reason for the delays.  This issue needs to be addressed.  We need front-line staff and competent nurses.  If we cannot register these staff within a reasonable period, they will continue to go to other jurisdictions such as Canada, the US, the UK, New Zealand, Australia and so on.  People will look to other alternatives if there is undue delay in the process here.</p><p>My understanding is that for people coming here from outside Europe, registration takes six to eight months.  It is horrendous that people have to wait that length of time to be registered and as a result are looking to other jurisdictions.  I am asking that the Minister engage with the board to see if a solution to this problem can be found such that anybody who applies for registration can be registered in a timely manner.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#B00600"><p>I thank Senator Burke for raising this issue.  I am taking this matter on behalf of my colleague, the Minister for Health, Deputy Leo Varadkar, who is not available this afternoon due to Government business.</p> <p>I wish to advise the Senator that Department of Health officials met with the president and chief executive of the Nursing and Midwifery Board of Ireland, NMBI, last week to discuss a range of operational issues, including the current delays in registration.  The NMBI is keeping the current situation under review.  The Senator may wish to know that the NMBI has been allocated additional resources to address the issues which he outlined.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Gerald Nash:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=2281"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2281&amp;amp;pid=GeraldNash&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=30"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> Delays in processing nurse registration applications are directly connected to the volume of requests arising from current initiatives to attract and retain nurses in the health services.  The Department of Health and the Health Service Executive are collaborating to find solutions to meet the issues arising in regard to nurse recruitment and retention.  The background to this issue is that nurses who trained in a country outside of Ireland and wish to work in Ireland are required to apply to register as a nurse with the Nursing and Midwifery Board of Ireland, NMBI.  In assessing an applicant for registration and in order to protect the public, the NMBI seeks evidence from applicants of comparable standards of education and practice.</p><p>According to the NMBI, the timeframe for completion of the assessment of qualifications for registration is up to a maximum of 90 days provided all necessary documentation has been supplied by the applicant.  The main difficulty in expediting timely applications, as reported by the NMBI, is the failure by the applicant or third parties to furnish the documentation required to assess eligibility for registration, or the delay in so doing.  The board, following assessment of qualifications by an applicant, may require him or her to undertake a six to 12- week period of adaptation and assessment.  This period of adaptation is designed to make up for differences in education and ensure competence to work in the Irish health service.  If such adaptation is required, it must be successfully completed as a prerequisite to registration.</p><p>There are two remaining HSE adaptation courses available this year, in June and August.  These courses are six to 12 weeks in duration and facilitate the integration of global nurses to nursing in an Irish context.  Since the nationally co-ordinated pilot adaptation programme commenced in June 2014, 151 candidates have completed the programme, 58 are currently undergoing assessment, and 126 are due for assessment up to the final programme in August 2015.  Outside of the current provision for placements in 2015, there are 293 requests for placements by employers.  These numbers are not reflective of a national total as some hospital sites run independent adaptation programmes.</p><p>A collaborative group, including the Department of Health, the HSE and Nursing Homes Ireland, NHI, representatives, continues to explore options to facilitate adaptation.  In this regard, some hospitals will respond to local need from local nursing homes, and this has been encouraged within the hospital group structures.  Other hospitals will continue to support placements pending funding from NHI, although not at peak undergraduate student times.  In addition, some hospitals are withdrawing from the provision of clinical placements to facilitate their own internal international recruitment initiatives.</p><p>It is important to note that the NMBI is dealing with very significant volumes of applications at present.  It is processing all applications as quickly as possible, while ensuring appropriate procedures and checks are adhered to with a view to ensuring protection for the public.  As I said at the outset, the chief executive officer of the board met with departmental officials last week to discuss a range of operational issues, including the current delays in the registration process.  The NMBI is keeping the situation under review and has been allocated additional resources to address the issues the Senator outlined.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#C00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his comprehensive reply.  He indicated that registration takes up to a maximum of 90 days provided all necessary documentation is supplied.  The complaint I have had from applicants is that it is six to eight weeks after submission that they are being told their documentation is not in order.  That leads to a delay in the process.  I am proposing that all applications be assessed within a very short timeframe, preferably within a week of their being submitted, and if any documentation is missing, the candidate should be notified immediately rather than having to wait six to eight weeks for such notification.</p> <p>In regard to the adaptation courses, my understanding is that Nursing Homes Ireland intends to seek to expedite the provision of those courses by putting its own funding in place, with the co-operation of hospitals.  It has no choice in the matter, and the Department needs to understand the urgency of this situation.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Colm Burke:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2353"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2353&amp;amp;pid=ColmBurke&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=30"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->More than 23,500 people are accommodated in private nursing homes.  While these homes are well run by competent staff, when staff shortages occur, the downside is that patients suffer.  This is the reason I seek to have this matter prioritised.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#D00200"><p>I thank Senator Colm Burke for his remarks on this important issue which all of us have encountered locally or in our constituencies, especially in areas that are coming under significant pressure in terms of demographic demand and access to health care facilities.  The Senator is correct that the private nursing homes industry plays an important role, alongside the public service, in providing top-class health care for older people in residential settings.  I am familiar with the needs of private health care providers of nursing home care in my constituency.  I am also aware that in recent years some leading providers of private health care have had to go as far afield as India to try to access appropriately qualified nurses to work in their homes and provide the type of health care we expect.</p> <p>There is good reason for the standards we have put in place through the Nursing and Midwifery Board of Ireland and State agencies to ensure health care is provided to those who need it in a safe and effective manner.  However, I accept Senator Burke's point on the validation of documentation which, in the normal course of events, is provided to the Nursing and Midwifery Board of Ireland.  As I indicated, it takes a maximum of 90 days to have the application process completed, provided all necessary documentation has been supplied by the applicant.  While 90 days appears to be a reasonable period, it can be frustrating if an applicant learns further down the line, having submitted documentation, that there is a problem.  We expect all State agencies and other relevant actors engaged in this sector and other areas to ensure the first step in such application processes is to ensure key paperwork and documentation is validated and checked and early engagement takes place with applicants to ensure the system is as streamlined as possible.  </p> <p>We should always be mindful that the health service is under extreme pressure.  If there are obstacles or roadblocks that can be removed early in the process, it is a matter for the relevant agencies to ensure this is done.  I will communicate the Senator's concerns to the Minister for Health and ask him to ensure the issues he raises are addressed.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.17" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#D00300">Job Losses</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#D00400"><p>I welcome the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, Deputy Richard Bruton, to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#D00500"><p>I, too, welcome the Minister and thank him for coming to the Seanad to discuss this important issue.</p> <p>As Members will be aware, on Thursday, 25 June 2015, Liberty Insurance announced it would make 270 workers redundant, 135 in Blanchardstown, 115 in my home town of Cavan and 20 in Enniskillen.  These redundancies are in addition to 285 job losses in the company in November 2012.  Liberty Insurance, formerly known as Quinn Insurance, has been an important and major employer in Cavan town since its operations commenced in the mid-1990s.  The sale of Quinn Insurance to Liberty Insurance was concluded in October 2011 when, I understand, the latter purchased 51% of the former for &euro;1.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Diarmuid Wilson:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2017"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2017&amp;amp;pid=DiarmuidWilson&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=30"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->While I understand there were some debts involved, in common with the people of County Cavan and surrounding counties, I still believe that Liberty Insurance got a good deal on that occasion and that it has an obligation to maintain jobs in that area of the country, as well as in Blanchardstown and Enniskillen.  In a statement issued last Thursday, my colleague, Deputy Brendan Smith, called on the Minister to engage immediately with Liberty Insurance with a view to retaining the maximum level of employment in this company and I join him in that call.  He also stated clearly that when Liberty Insurance purchased the former Quinn Insurance in October 2011, at that time the company stated it would maintain more than 1,000 people in employment in the three areas.  At that time, the Minister for Finance, Deputy Noonan, stated with regard to the sale of Quinn Insurance that he welcomed the positives of the proposed agreement in that almost all of the 1,500 jobs in Quinn Insurance would be retained.  That figure speaks for itself when one now is talking about 950 jobs in the three locations.  The company has stated the redundancies will take place over an 18-month period but I understand it has given employees two weeks in which to make life-changing decisions without providing the necessary advice and support to them to make such decisions.  The staff were told that assistance will be provided once the voluntary process was complete but that is not acceptable.  Once the process is complete will be too late to offer advice and assistance to these workers, as they need assistance now.</p><p>Although the company has offered voluntary redundancy, people have concerns that by accepting it, they will make wrong decisions that could have an impact on their social welfare and mortgage protection entitlements.  Moreover, in the case of up to 40 workers who work as claims staff in the Cavan office, the decision really already has been taken out of their hands because their roles are being relocated to Blanchardstown.  This decision makes absolutely no sense, given the collective experience of these people and that new people must be trained for these roles should the staff in County Cavan not relocate.  Moreover, I understand the vast majority of them are not in a position to so do.  I understand that the decision to move these claims jobs was made by the new head of claims, as he believes all claims staff should be based in the Dublin office and yet there is a mix of staff from other areas throughout all the sites.</p><p>Unfortunately, this company has been through this process before.  The same human resources team and many of the senior management team are in place and yet the current process is flawed with no empathy or concern being shown for the employees.  Liberty Insurance purchased the remaining 49% of the former Quinn Insurance in December 2013 and now has 100% ownership of this company.  I ask the Minister to use his good offices to try to maintain the jobs in these three centres.  I am particularly concerned with regard to the site in Cavan, which is the one I know best, but people in Enniskillen and Dublin also depend on this company for their jobs.  Morale is at an all-time low in these three offices and the big fear is that Liberty Insurance is preparing to downsize, move jobs elsewhere and eventually to sell off the Irish operation.  This is not good enough and if these jobs cannot be saved, I ask that the Minister have the statutory agencies to work with these workers as a matter of urgency.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#F00100"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this matter.  Our sympathies are most definitely with the workers in Cavan, Blanchardstown and Enniskillen at this very difficult time.</p> <p>This is a very disappointing development.  The Senator has outlined what will be the impact in the three locations, namely: 135 job losses in Blanchardstown; 115 in Cavan; and 20 in Enniskillen.  The company has given the reasons behind its decision to withdraw from the British market and to make significant changes to its operations in Ireland.  It has experienced a difficult trading period and is now going to focus on the Republic of Ireland market.  I do not believe it is fair to say that the company is preparing for an exit.  That is by no means an accurate reflection.  I am encouraged by the company's statement to the effect that it is fully committed to Ireland, that it will be seeking voluntary redundancies in the first instance and that the process in this regard will be phased over an 18-month period.  That is encouraging and I hope that when it is offering terms to workers, the company will recognise the contribution they have made over a long period by offering them a good package.  On the positive side, Liberty has confirmed that it is continuing with its IT initiative, which was the basis for the announcement of the creation 150 jobs in 2013.  This initiative is located at the Blanchardstown office and it shows that the company continues to be committed to Ireland.  We will ensure that the relevant agencies work closely with Liberty in order to see to it that any future opportunities relating to the company can be maximised as it evolves.</p> <p>My immediate focus rests on the instruction I issued to IDA Ireland and Enterprise Ireland to redouble their efforts in respect of job creation in County Cavan and to explore all options in the context of replacing the jobs that have been lost there.  The past couple of years in Cavan-Monaghan have been good.  It is particularly encouraging to see the very strong performance of a number of Irish-owned companies in recent times and quite a number of them across the two counties, including Lakelands, Combilift, Glanbia, Swift and Lagan Brick, have expanded their operations.  It is encouraging that in 2014 the IDA Ireland and Enterprise Ireland job base grew by 9% and that there was an 11% increase in the number of jobs created by means of the local enterprise office, LEO, network.  We are enjoying some successes and I am currently developing a regional enterprise strategy.  The latter will be for every region but it will have particular focus on the Border region, which has a number of significant strengths upon which we hope to build.</p> <p>If the employees of Liberty require the assistance of the National Employment Rights Authority, NERA, or other State agencies, in dealing with their current circumstances or making particular decisions, I will be quite happy ensure that it is made available to them.  I recognise that this is a difficult time for the people involved.  I will ensure that we redouble our efforts.  We have witnessed the potential of enterprise in the region and we need to build on that in order to try to replace lost jobs and ensure that opportunities emerge for those people who have been so badly impacted upon by this decision.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#F00200"><p>When 285 redundancies occurred in 2012, the statutory agencies worked very well with the employees involved.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Diarmuid Wilson:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2017"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2017&amp;amp;pid=DiarmuidWilson&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=30"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I would like the Minister to give a commitment - I acknowledge that he alluded to this in his reply - that the same emphasis will be placed on these people who will potentially lose their jobs in all three centres.</p><p>I am most familiar with the Cavan centre.  While it is unfortunate that jobs were lost a few years ago, which should not have been the case, following a commitment by the company to retain them, assistance was provided by the statutory agencies, including the Cavan and Monaghan education and training boards, the Minister's Department and various other Departments.  I would like him to give a commitment that he will co-ordinate a similar approach as a matter of urgency.  I reiterate that the spin on this is that the redundancies will take place over 18 months, but workers have been given 14 days to make a life-changing decision for themselves and their families.  These decisions will also affect the communities they live in.  In 2012, when there were 285 redundancies, Liberty Insurance issued a statement saying, "This development is necessary to secure the future of the company."  However, last Thursday, there was an announcement that 270 jobs would be lost, and the president of Liberty International issued a statement saying, "Liberty Mutual remains fully committed to building a successful business in Ireland."   If 270 redundancies on top of 285 redundancies on top of 150 redundancies equates to "building a successful business in Ireland", then there will be serious concerns for the remaining workers down the line.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#G00200"><p>I am happy to give the Senator a guarantee that the resources of the State, through my own Department, NERA, the Department of Social Protection and the education and training boards, will be available to workers.  The company is in a 30-day consultation period and it has obligations during that period to consult its workers.  I do not propose to comment on those consultations but, obviously, the resources of the State, such as the Labour Relations Commission, will be available to assist if there are issues on which advice could be given.</p> <p>This is a difficult reminder of the challenging competitive environment in which every industry operates.  There will always be reverses, and one cannot put one's hand on one's heart and say about any sector that there never will be a challenge and everything will be perfect.  There will always be change, and the difficulty is that the changes that have occurred in the UK insurance market have caused difficulties for this company.  It is a battle every day in respect of our approach to supporting companies that are facing threats while also supporting companies that are considering opportunities.  It is positive that in Cavan and, indeed, in the country as a whole, we are winning more of those battles than we are losing.  A total of 105,000 additional people are at work since we commenced the Action Plan for Jobs in 2012, with approximately 19,000 of those in the Border region.  More companies are expanding than are getting into difficulty.</p> <p>However, this is a timely reminder that we have to always be vigilant and make sure that we make the changes and create the competitive environment in all our areas of endeavour to support growth, because there are always challenges around the corner.  I thank the Senator for raising this issue and I assure him that I will talk to the agencies to ensure timely support is available for the people affected.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.25" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#H00050">Harbours and Piers</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#H00100"><p>I welcome the Minister of State at the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine, Deputy Hayes, to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1200" speakername="Averil Power" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#H00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Hayes, to the House.  As he is aware, last week the Committee of Public Accounts published a report into the six fishery harbour centres.  On reading the report, I share the committee's concern that the harbours are managed properly and that the employment potential of our fishing, seafood processing, boat repair and other industries are maximised.  The report gives a good account of the issues and challenges present and what the Department needs to do to address them.</p> <p>I also support the recommendation that the Department improve its relationship with harbour users to ensure they genuinely engage with them, listen to their concerns, support people and work with them to maximise the potential of their businesses and ensure vacant properties are put to best use from commercial and community points of view.</p> <p>I was very concerned about one of the report's recommendations, which is that the Department consider introducing paid parking in Howth.  This is an issue about which I have written to the Minister, Deputy Coveney, on several occasions in the past since January 2013.  I also tabled a Seanad debate on this two and a half years ago to highlight the very damaging impact that paid parking would have on Howth.  I had hoped that as this has not been implemented in the intervening two and a half years, the Department had listened to the issues I had raised and the feedback from various stakeholders in Howth, looked at the fact that one in three local authority paid parking schemes loses money and had seen sense on this issue and was not going to proceed with it.  I was very concerned to see the Committee of Public Accounts make this suggestion again last week.</p> <p>I am also concerned the committee looked at it from a very narrow approach.  It only considered the issue of paid parking from the perspective of the Department, and Howth as a fishery harbour.  Howth is not just a fishery harbour.  It is unique in that fishing is just one of the activities which takes place there.  It is also a major tourism, sport, leisure and community resource.  As a representative from the area, it has always frustrated me to see the harbour in the broader sense not utilised as well as it could be.  One visits places on the Continent with half the natural resources and beauty of Howth which are used to full advantage where State authorities work with all stakeholders to ensure this happens, but in Howth there always seems to be a difficulty and a lack of ambition and support for local initiatives.</p> <p>My concern about paid parking is activities such as tourism, local restaurants, marine leisure and walking are very dependent on the availability of free parking.  Howth is not somewhere one pops into for an hour or two.  It is difficult enough to reach.  Unfortunately, our public transport connections are not great, and particularly at weekends there can be a 30 or 40 minute gap between DARTs.  Unfortunately, if people want to get there, they need to be able to drive.  People going for a walk do not know whether they will walk for two or four hours.  When they get to the top of Howth Head, they do not want to be in a rush to go back to feed the meter.  When they get to the top of the hill, they want to sit down and enjoy the view.  It is the same when people go out on the water.  If they are sailing, they are highly dependent on weather and do not know how long they will be.  When they are out on the water, they cannot have the anxiety of being clamped.</p> <p>Paid parking does not make sense in Howth.  I appreciate it makes sense in areas where there is a shortage of parking, such as in Dublin city centre, and the only way to control it is to have a system which discourages people from constantly driving and taking up the limited number of spaces.  In Malahide, local businesses sought paid parking because they had a concern about people parking all day from first thing in the morning, and anybody who wanted to go in and out of a local business during the day could not get a space.  This is not the case in Howth, which has plenty of parking spaces.  We do not have a shortage unless a major event is taking place, and we have one or two major events during the summer.  This is the only time there is a shortage of spaces.</p> <p>I have tabled this debate to highlight yet again the negative impact paid parking would have on Howth and I ask the Minister of State, who is representing the Minister, Deputy Coveney, to bring this message back to him.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Averil Power:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2351"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2351&amp;amp;pid=AverilPower&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=30"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The issue needs to be considered in the round not just having regard to the narrow fisheries perspective from which the PAC viewed it.  The Department must consider the fact that paid parking would put people off travelling out to the area to shop, eat in restaurants, go walking and take part in sports activities.  Any economic analysis must take account of the loss to the broader local economy and the impact on jobs and not just the fisheries aspect.</p><p>I reiterate the call I have made previously in the House for the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine, Fingal County Council and tourism and other major Government agencies with an interest in Howth to work together to maximise its potential from a fishing and employment point of view, but also from a tourism and community resource perspective.  That is badly needed and I urge the Minister of State to bring that message back to the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1089" speakername="Tom Hayes" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#J00200"><p>I am standing in for the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine, Deputy Simon Coveney.  I thank Senator Power for raising this important issue and acknowledge her interest in Howth and the contribution she has made there.  Howth fishery harbour centre, or FHC, is one of the six designated fishery harbour centres which are owned, managed and maintained by my Department under statute.  All six fishery centres are first and foremost working fishery harbours.  However, each centre has unique features which facilitate a broad range of other diverse activities which are important from both an economic and social perspective.  The Department is conscious of the importance of both fishing and non-fishing activities at the harbours and endeavours to facilitate and develop both.  This involves day-to-day operational support by harbour staff and management and development and repair of infrastructure subject to available financial resources.</p> <p>Howth fishery harbour centre is no exception to this diversity.  In addition to fishing, there is a wide range of recreational users of the harbour, including the yacht club, sport fishermen, walkers, tourists and other social users.  There is a significant number of businesses, particularly restaurants, operating in the harbour centre.  Notwithstanding the prevailing economic environment in which we operate, I am happy to advise that in excess of &euro;5.3 million has been invested in maintenance, development and upgrading works at Howth FHC as part of the Department's fishery harbour and coastal infrastructure development programme from 2006 to 2014.  However, the volume of capital investment in Howth has increased significantly in recent years with the bulk of this capital investment, or &euro;3.78 million, being made in the 2012 to 2014 period.  This investment will result in a significant improvement in the traffic management system, access for persons of reduced mobility and the electrical infrastructure.  In addition, it will act as a catalyst for the enhancement of facilities available to the marine leisure and tourism sector, boat repair facilities and, indeed, business generally in the harbour.</p> <p>The increased level of capital expenditure in Howth in recent years is being maintained.  In March 2015, the Minister approved further funding of &euro;1.584 million for the maintenance and development of Howth FHC.  Major works for 2015 include the provision of a small craft pontoon and the continued upgrading of the electrical system.  The development and upkeep of Howth as a state-of-the-art fishery harbour centre supporting a broad range of marine related and other activity will remain an ongoing process.  The property portfolio in Howth includes a diverse range of properties.  My Department reviews the portfolio on an ongoing basis to maximise returns for the Exchequer.  The two properties at issue were made available by competitive public tender on 15 June 2015.</p> <p>The Senator referred to the question of the introduction of paid car parking at Howth Harbour.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Tom Hayes:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=1807"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1807&amp;amp;pid=TomHayes&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=30"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I can inform her that this matter remains under consideration as part of an overall review of traffic management arrangements.</p><p>In a special report by the Comptroller and Auditor General, and the related report of the Committee of Public Accounts of 24 June 2015, the Department is asked to review the position regarding paid parking in Howth, in conjunction with other fishery harbour centres, with a view to increasing income generation possibilities.</p><p>However, income generation is not the only factor to be considered in deciding whether paid parking should be introduced in Howth.  There is a broad range of other factors to be taken into account before a final decision will be made on the matter.  Most importantly, the safe operation of the harbour is of paramount concern.  In this context, traffic management and parking is recognised as an issue, particularly, though not exclusively, during the busy holiday periods.</p><p>As I said, while Howth Fishery Harbour Centre is first and foremost a working fishery harbour, the Department is conscious that it is also a very important tourist destination, as well as a major venue for leisure activities.  With that in mind, the Department is anxious to increase the profile of the harbour for the betterment of the wider community.  To this end, the harbour regularly approves applications for events, yacht races, local celebrations and various functions within the harbour precincts.  For example, in April 2015, the Dublin Bay Prawn Festival was held at Howth Harbour over three days.  It is estimated that this event alone attracted more than 25,000 visitors to the harbour.  In July 2014, a similar number of visitors attended the Asgard centennial celebrations, which were held at Howth Harbour, with the keynote address delivered by President Higgins.  Various marine leisure events, such as national and international races and regattas, also attract thousands of visitors each year.  In addition, the Howth tourist information office opened within the confines of Howth Fishery Harbour Centre in July 2014.</p><p>I want to assure the Senator that my Department will continue, where appropriate, to facilitate initiatives to promote Howth and to liaise with key stakeholders on an ongoing basis as required.  Balancing the needs of the fishing industry with those of the wider range of harbour users, while delivering on a public service remit, will be foremost when considering future developments in the harbour.  Any new developments will be done on the basis of available Exchequer funding and competing national priorities.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1200" speakername="Averil Power" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#K00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State's acknowledgement that Howth is more than just a fishing harbour, and he listed some of the major events held there that help to attract people to the area, including the prawn festival, the Asgard celebrations and major leisure events, but I cannot stress strongly enough how central the availability of free parking is to the success of such events.  Howth Yacht Club has made that very clear in its submissions to the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine about this issue.  Parking availability is essential if Howth is to win bids for major sporting events, because people heading out to sea are hugely dependent on the weather and cannot determine whether they will return in an hour, two hours or three hours.  It is important to stress that the reason we have had those successes is that we have sufficient availability of free parking.  The implementation of paid parking in other areas such as D&uacute;n Laoghaire has been a disaster from the point of view of holding marine leisure events.</p> <p>I welcome the fact that the Minister has recognised that there are broader issues involved, but I am disappointed that the issue is still under consideration.  I had hoped, as it has not been implemented over the past two and a half years, that the Department had considered it in the round and was backing away from the disastrous impact this would have on Howth.  The Minister of State mentioned the reports of the Committee of Public Accounts-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#K00300"><p>Senator, have you a question?  We are way over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1200" speakername="Averil Power" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#K00400"><p>-----and the Comptroller and Auditor General.  I ask him to reiterate to the Minister that the issue needs to be considered from a broader perspective and not just from a fishing point of view, which was the approach taken by the Committee of Public Accounts.  That approach is deeply flawed.  We need a proper cost-benefit analysis to show that the proposal stands up, and I am fully confident that if such an analysis were done, the Minister would change his mind.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1089" speakername="Tom Hayes" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#L00100"><p>I will be brief and respond on the paid parking issue.  The Senator is correct in that paid parking is a concern in many areas, and she is not alone in her views about it.  Right across the country there are other projects dealing with the issue.  I will relay the Senator's points about paid parking to the Minister as I know how passionate she is about it and how strongly she feels about the topic.  I understand her concerns and there is a place in my constituency where we have to deal with the paid parking issue as well.  However, if resources are required, one must get money in and, in the overall context, anything that is done will be in the best interests of the harbour.  I will make those points to the Minister.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.35" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#L00200">Natural Gas Grid</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#L00300"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy McHugh, to the Chamber.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1173" speakername="Lorraine Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#L00400"><p>I request the Minister for Energy, Communications and Natural Resources to explore additional funding streams in order to provide for the roll-out of natural gas areas of strategic importance.  Extending our gas network requires Government-level support and an obvious starting point would be to use some of the profits from the sale of the Bord G&aacute;is energy division to bring gas to our smaller towns, providing for above-ground installation.  This would go some way towards reducing our dependence on imported fuel and protecting our environment, which will be of much economic and social importance in the years ahead.</p> <p>Natural gas is a clean, an efficient and a cheap alternative to fossil fuels and it helps to eradicate the scourge of fuel poverty for low-income families.  Major multinationals, like pharmaceutical companies, for example, rely on gas lines, and from a foreign direct investment standpoint, access to gas networks makes Irish communities all the more attractive to those considering basing themselves here.  As Ireland begins to rebuild after austerity, we need to do everything possible to attract corporate heavy hitters to our shores, and a well-serviced and widely available gas network could really assist with such endeavours.</p> <p>As somebody based in Galway East, I take my home town of Athenry as an example.  Putting Athenry on the gas network would not require major investment and it would reap many rewards for the locality, especially with Apple's arrival on the horizon.  In the first instance, the work required would create short-term employment but local residents and businesses could enjoy the ease of having the option to use a gas network if they so desired.  In light of the Apple announcement, demands for homes in my area is likely to rise, and being on the gas network would further increase that demand.  The entire community, from small businesses to home owners and large corporations, stands to benefit, offering a major return on the initial investment.  I certainly hope the Minister of State will pass this message to the line Minister.  We should consider finding alternative revenue streams.  For instance, we could get a portion of funds from the sale of the Bord G&aacute;is energy division to ensure that places like Athenry and towns right across the island can access the gas network to the benefit of local citizens.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#L00500"><p>I thank the Senator raising the matter, which I will address on behalf of the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources, Deputy Alex White.  I will certainly convey the Senator's concern today.</p> <p>I will cover in my remarks how Ireland's natural gas network infrastructure is assessed, planned, rolled out and funded under our own and EU-compliant gas regulatory framework.  The development and expansion of the natural gas network is in the first instance a commercial matter for Gaslink.  Gaslink is mandated under section 8 of the Gas Act 1976, as amended, to develop and maintain a system for the supply of natural gas that is both economical and efficient.  Gaslink receives revenues from gas consumers to fund its operations and functions, including the development of the gas network.  The Commission for Energy Regulation, CER, is statutorily responsible for all aspects of the assessment and licensing of prospective operators who wish to develop and operate a gas distribution system within the State under the Gas (Interim) (Regulation) Act 2002.</p> <p>As regards the development and rolling out of the natural gas network, the CER approved a gas connections policy in 2006 that enabled assessment of the feasibility of connecting new towns to the gas network.  In order for any town to be connected via new infrastructure to the gas network, certain economic criteria must be satisfied.  The policy provides that the construction and operating costs of connecting a town, or group of towns, to the network are recovered through the consumption of gas and the associated network charges on consumers.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Joe McHugh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=2018"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2018&amp;amp;pid=JoeMcHugh&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=30"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The distance of a town from the gas network is the major factor in determining the cost of building a gas pipeline.  The anticipated industrial or commercial gas usage in the town largely determines the revenue from gas network charges, which must balance the connection costs.  Uneconomic gas pipeline projects would unfairly increase energy costs for all gas consumers.</p><p>Gaslink has completed three comprehensive studies of nearly 80 towns in the context of connections to the gas network, resulting in more than 20 new towns having been connected in recent years.  The key factor which would qualify a town or a group of towns in any future review would be a significant increase in demand for natural gas, probably resulting from the addition of a new large industrial or commercial facility.</p><p>As regards funding streams for the roll-out of natural gas, energy infrastructure is usually financed by the market and through tariffs paid by users.  However, in order to meet the challenge of interconnecting all EU member states by 2020, the European Union has established funding to leverage the investment needed.  The most prominent of those funds is the Connecting Europe Facility, CEF.  I can go into more detail separately on these new funding streams and their implications for Ireland, if the Senator wishes.</p><p>While I would again stress that energy infrastructure is usually financed by the market and through tariffs paid by users, both CEF funding and the recently proposed European Fund for Strategic Investments, EFSI, are very important for, and welcomed by, Ireland as additional funding streams and will assist in ensuring the correct balance is struck between cost burdens and cost benefits in further developing our electricity and gas infrastructure.  I am conscious that my response is broad but it was provided in response to the broad question put forward by the Senator.  In regard to the Senator's reference to the new investment in Athenry, the consultation process, which is under the authority of CER, is currently reviewing submissions and hopes to conclude its work in this regard in the coming weeks.  I am sure it will consider all areas that may warrant investigation.  This is about demand and not impinging on the price in the marketplace for the consumer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1173" speakername="Lorraine Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#M00200"><p>I accept the role of Gaslink in all of this.  However, the Government and, in particular, the Department of Communications, Energy and Natural Resources, have an obligation to fund Gaslink to enable it to expand the network.  In regard to Athenry, there is currently a large volume of industry in the region and this is set to increase following the granting of the planning permission for the Apple project.  There is also a strategic investment site earmarked for development by the IDA.  Athenry is also a nodal point in Galway, with motorway and rail networks making it attractive to people seeking housing.  I expect the population in Athenry to increase into the future, leading to a potential increase in the demand for natural gas.  I would ask that consideration be given to my proposal that funds from the sale of the Bord G&aacute;is energy division be allocated to the roll-out of natural gas in strategic locations across Ireland - Athenry, my home town, being one of them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#M00300"><p>I will convey the Senator's message to the Minister.  However, I must reiterate the importance of strategic decision-making.  Athenry, Craughwell, Headford and Tuam in County Galway and Ballina, Ballyhaunis, Castlebar, Claremorris, Crossmolina, Knock and Westport in County Mayo were included in phase 1.  Construction on this &euro;40 million project has been completed and the towns of Craughwell, Tuam and Headford in County Galway and Ballina, Castlebar, Claremorris and Westport in County Mayo have been connected to the gas network.  The Senator will be aware that connection in respect of the three remaining towns of Athenry, Ballyhaunis and Knock is uncertain, which is the reason she has raised this issue today.  I am sure the representative bodies from Athenry have made representations regarding existing industry and potential future industry in the region to the consultation process.  The report of this process, commissioned by the Commission for Energy Regulation, is awaited.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Joe McHugh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=2018"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2018&amp;amp;pid=JoeMcHugh&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=30"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> Official statutory responsibility for these matters was given, via legislation, to the Commission for Energy Regulation in 2006.  The commission has a responsibility to decide which towns have sufficient demand and ensure that decisions made are economic and strategic.  If we bring gas into towns where it does not make economic sense to do so, we are into a situation where there will be additional costs for consumers.  Those are the mitigating factors.  I take the Senator's point, however, that if extra moneys were available, there would be scope to balance the demand versus supply issue.  I will convey that message to the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.43" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 3.30 p.m. and resumed at 3.35 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.44" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#O00100">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#O00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, motion re referral to committee of Education Research Centre (Establishment) Order 2015, to be taken without debate on the conclusion of the Order of Business; No. 2, Industrial Relations (Amendment) Bill 2015 &ndash; Second Stage, to be taken at 4.45 p.m. and to adjourn not later than 7 p.m., with the contributions of group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes and those of all other Senators not to exceed five minutes; and No. 3, Consumer Protection (Regulation of Credit Servicing Firms) Bill 2015 &ndash; Committee Stage, to be taken at 7 p.m. and to adjourn not later than 9 p.m., if not previously concluded.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#O00300"><p>On behalf of my party, Fianna F&aacute;il, I extend my deepest sympathy to the families of those who were brutally murdered in the savage terrorist attack in Tunisia, in particular, those of the three Irish victims and our fellow countrymen, Laurence Hayes, Martina Hayes and Lorna Carty.  It is disgraceful that people enjoying their holidays with their families were gunned down in such a callous fashion.  My thoughts and those of my party colleagues are with them and all the victims of this terrible tragedy, and, indeed, the Tunisian people in dealing with this terrible threat of Muslim extremism.  On another day, it would be important that, outside of a terrorist atrocity, we have a debate here on Muslim extremism and extremism in this country.  As we speak, there are Irish citizens in Syria and in Iraq fighting for Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant, ISIL, and that is something that needs to be addressed.  It is not only a problem in France; there are issues here in Ireland as well.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Darragh O'Brien:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2178"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2178&amp;amp;pid=DarraghOBrien&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=30"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Today is not the appropriate day but we should certainly have a debate on that with the Minister for Justice and Equality.  </p><p>Members may not be aware that today another &euro;140 million has been taken out of people's private pension pots by the Government.  This is the fourth year that has been done, raising the total to about &euro;2.4 billion.  People were doing what they had been asked to do by successive Governments, namely, making provision for their retirement.  The irony is that anyone who has a pension is paying the levy, including the Aer Lingus pensioners who are losing 60% of their pensions, those in Tara Mines, the Waterford Crystal workers and all of these badly funded pension funds that are in grave difficulty.  The Government needs to accept responsibility for the pensions crisis.  This Government has done more than any other to undermine the basic premise and the safety of pensions and is the first one to actually take people's savings by way of a pension levy and has, in fact, taken more than it said it would.  The pension levy was supposed to be abolished last year.  It is another broken promise.  The Government has let it go on for another year because it is easy money.  </p><p>There are people in AXA and in Tara Mines who have had their pensions and payments reduced by 10% and 15% simply to pay the levy, which the Government said was used to bring new jobs into the retail and hospitality sectors.  I accept it has done that but at what price?  That the Government has decided to continue the levy for another year is a disgrace.  </p><p>I heard the T&aacute;naiste speak about compulsory pensions and how she would like to reform the pensions sector.  When I heard that I laughed.  The T&aacute;naiste, as Minister for Social Protection with responsibility for pensions, has done more than anyone to undermine pensions.  We need a debate on pension provision and how we can bring back confidence into the pensions sector.  Should this Government or Fine Gael be re-elected, will it hit the pensioners again?  Is it not ironic that the 15,000 Aer Lingus pensioners, about whom we have had debates, who have lost 50% and 60% of their pensions are paying this levy today out of their fund?  It is disgraceful.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#P00200"><p>I express my deep sympathy to the families of the Irish citizens and all those who were murdered or injured in the appalling attack in Tunisia on Friday.  It was a most disturbing and brutal day.  Not only were 38 people killed in Tunisia in that barbaric attack on the beach but also on the same day, a large number of people were killed in Kuwait, also apparently by ISIS extremists, and there was the particularly brutal killing of a man in France.  It is fitting that we would express sympathy to all those affected by those dreadful atrocities.</p> <p>I express the hope, even at this eleventh hour, of some success in the attempts to forestall Greek default and a resumption of negotiations.  The Taoiseach has written to the Greek Prime Minister in those terms.  The President of the Commission, Jean-Claude Juncker, has been attempting to resume negotiations.</p> <p>I call for a debate on crime given the publication today by the CSO of crime statistics.  It is a welcome publication as these are the statistics which had been delayed while the CSO addressed issues that had been raised about the reporting and recording of crime statistics by the Garda Inspectorate in last year's report.  The CSO has remedied a number of the defects in the reporting and recording of crime that appeared in the Garda Inspectorate report.  It is welcome that decreases are recorded in most categories of crime, such as a 40% drop in homicide and an 8% decrease in burglaries in the 12 months ending on 31 March 2015.  There is a great deal of material in the Garda Inspectorate report around the reporting and recording of crime and it would be good to have a debate on that in due course.</p> <p>I note the CSO has recorded today that unemployment figures are down to the lowest level, 9.7%, since 2009.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Ivana Bacik:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2248"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2248&amp;amp;pid=IvanaBacik&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=30"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is still too high, but it is a major improvement on last year's figures.  It shows a steady decrease in unemployment and is very welcome.</p><p>I ask the Leader to find time over the next two weeks to commemorate the genocide in Srebrenica.  The 20th anniversary of that appalling genocide is 11 July.  It was the single largest atrocity on European soil since the Second World War, when 8,372 men and boys were systematically murdered.  I have written to the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade to ask for an official Irish commemoration of the twentieth anniversary.  There will be a commemoration in Belfast on 5 July and on 11 July Srebrenica memorial day will be commemorated across Europe.  Quite a number of commemorative events are planned across Britain and Northern Ireland, and we might look for some event here.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#Q00200"><p>I want to raise a particularly urgent matter, namely, the imminent fate of a Palestinian village which I know well and to which members of the Committee on Foreign Affairs and Trade have travelled to visit, that is, Sousia in the south Hebron hills.  I ask the Leader to write to the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade and ask him to intervene in the situation and make a statement on the matter.  I will provide the Leader with the information and would be most grateful if he would make that contact.  </p> <p>The village has been in existence for 200 years.  In 1983 an Israeli Jewish village called Sousia was established and three years later the Israelis declared the Palestinian Sousia an archaeological site and moved in to demolish it.  The people reconstructed their houses but on 10 May the civil administration of Israel moved in and started taking photographs, recording GPS positions and engaging in legalistic military stuff.  It is quite shocking to see the cold, unrelenting military precision of the way in which it acts.  It is like the early days of the Nazis.  A synagogue has been built in Sousia and the idea is to demolish the Palestinian village, wipe it off the face of the map where it has been for 200 years and join up Sousia synagogue and Sousia village.</p> <p>One of the villagers said: "I am afraid of a silent demolition, that they will come and take our village apart one at a time."  The whole idea is to make this area Palestinian free, another echo of the 1930s, when Judenfrei was a policy.  This will involve the destruction of a series of structures that were put up with European money, including money from Ireland.  There has been very considerable European Commission human aid and civil protection department funding.  The Polish, German, Australian and Irish Governments have all contributed money.  What is going on is utterly illegal.  </p> <p>Article 53 of the 1949 Geneva Convention states: "Any destruction by the occupying power of real or personal property belonging individually or collectively to private persons, or to the state, or to other public authorities, or to social or co-operative organisations, is prohibited, except where such destruction is rendered absolutely necessary by military operations."  There is no such pretence by the Israelis.  </p> <p>According to Article 49 of the fourth Geneva Convention, forcible transfer of the protected population is prohibited and is considered a grave breech of international humanitarian law.  Israel is moving and behaving in a brutalised fashion.  It is breaking two of the most significant elements of the 1949 Geneva Convention.  I have to go to a meeting of the Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs and Trade, but I will give the relevant documents to the Leader.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1187" speakername="Hildegarde Naughton" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#Q00300"><p>I refer to hospice care, in particular an announcement made in Galway this week, where a Galway hospice is planning to submit an application for planning permission for a 26 bed future-proofed unit in Merlin Park which it plans to have open within five years.  It is currently planning a fundraising drive to support the capital costs.  Even when the country was awash with money under previous Governments, end-of-life care was under-resourced.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Hildegarde Naughton:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2395"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2395&amp;amp;pid=HildegardeNaughton&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=30"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Hospice units like this are badly needed in Galway and right across the country.  Those involved are raising capital funds without Government assistance.  This situation is playing out in other areas of the country as well.  While I appreciate that finances have been constrained since this Government got into office, I suggest that a relatively small investment in this area would yield substantial benefits.  The failure to invest in hospice care throughout the country is a case of penny wise and pound foolish.  I do not doubt that if a cost-benefit analysis of investment in hospice care were done, it would come down heavily in favour of such investment because it makes financial sense to take pressure off our acute hospitals.  I ask the Leader to invite the Minister for Health to come to the House so that we can impress on him the practical benefits of making this area a priority in his Department.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#R00200"><p>I would like to raise the appalling rustling of cattle that happened near Tyrrellspass and Kilbeggan in recent days.  It is important for this House to be aware of the significance of this issue.  Approximately 100 cattle worth in the region of &euro;100,000 were taken from a young farming couple.  The obligation for every animal to be tagged at birth is significant because it allows for traceability from the birth of a calf or a lamb all the way through to the table.  With this traceability in mind, and having regard to the devastation this theft has caused this young couple, it is important that we raise the matter in this House.  I ask the Leader to convey my abhorrence of what has happened to the Minister, Deputy Coveney, and the Minister for Justice.  How could such a number of cattle disappear overnight?  The strong level of cross-Border co-operation on agricultural issues was very noticeable at an event in Abbeyleix last Sunday.  I was fortunate to attend the event, which was organised by a group that is trying to reduce the number of farm deaths.  This House was complimented at that function for the work that was done at the Seanad Public Consultation Committee and on the report it produced.  Ministers from Northern Ireland and from this country attended the event to show solidarity with the farming community.  While I am not looking for an urgent debate on this matter, I urge the Leader to take it seriously.  It boggles the mind that 100 animals could be taken from a farm and disappear without trace overnight.  It is a serious issue.  If these people can get away with such theft - it may have been night-time robbery rather than daylight robbery - it is appalling.  The devastation caused to a young farming couple who are probably not in a position to rebuild their stock is an extreme worry to me and to the farming community.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" speakername="Jim D'Arcy" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#R00300"><p>The people of Haggardstown are getting a bit worried about the Greek crisis.  They asked me to put a couple of questions in this Chamber.  First, are members of Sinn F&eacute;in still backing the Syriza-led Greek Government and are they still pally with the guy who visited their Ard-Fheis?  Second, what does-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#R00400"><p>They have turned the lights out.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#R00500"><p>That shows the power of Sinn F&eacute;in.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#R00600"><p>I think they would be appalled in Haggardstown.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#R00700"><p>They are stealing the electricity in Greece.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" speakername="Jim D'Arcy" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#R00800"><p>The people of Haggardstown want to know what "debt write-down" means.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#R00900"><p>The lights are back in action.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" speakername="Jim D'Arcy" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#R01000"><p>They want to know whether it means we will pay the money the Greeks have not paid.  As the Taoiseach has said, at the end of the day all things should be sorted out at the table.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Feargal Quinn:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=1972"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1972&amp;amp;pid=FergalQuinn&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=30"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is a couple of years since I introduced a Bill in the House regarding the provision of defibrillators.  The Minister accepted the point, said he would check with the Health Information and Quality Authority, HIQA, but found it would be too expensive.  The reason I raise it is that Dublin Airport has been very successful in the use of defibrillators, with 25 lives having been saved.  However, HIQA said it would be too expensive to implement the Bill.  Consider what happened last week when somebody needed a defibrillator on a Ryanair flight.  There was none on the airplane, as is the case with most Irish aeroplanes, and the person died.  It is outrageous.  Given the minor cost of defibrillators, they should be available.  British Airways, EasyJet, Monarch Airlines and Thomas Cook Airlines have defibrillators on each of their aeroplanes, but Irish aeroplanes do not have them.  I believe this is an essential item.  The debate on the Bill I introduced was adjourned.  I would love if it was debated again in the House and if its provisions are too expensive, let us make amendments to it.  However, let us ensure that Irish aeroplanes carry defibrillators in future.</p><p>Some of the stories that have been told are outrageous.  A coroner is asking for aircraft to carry life saving equipment after Davina Tavener died of an undiagnosed heart condition on a flight to Lanzarote.  The consultant surgeon said, "I did ask for a defibrillator, because if it's a cardiac issue that's the best chance of survival, but it was quite a surprise this wasn't there."  The coroner, Alan Walsh, said he would write to the European Aviation Safety Agency, the Civil Aviation Authority and the Irish Aviation Authority about the possibility of installing defibrillators on board.  I believe this is urgent and that it must happen.  We have put if off long enough.  It is a few years since I introduced the defibrillator Bill and I am stunned that we have not taken any step forward.  I understand the Minister saying he will get around to it, or words to that effect.  On that basis I believe it will happen.</p><p>Another Bill that was introduced is the Employment Permits (Amendment) Bill.  It was adjourned as well.  The reason for that Bill being introduced was that a relatively young man, Muhammad Younis, was earning 55 cent per hour for a 70 hour week for seven years in Ireland.  When he made a claim it was found that he had a good claim but that, unfortunately, he only had his work permit for one year, so he lost the case.  He brought his case to the High Court and lost it, but then brought it to the Supreme Court and won it.  However, let us ensure we are not obliged to rely on such processes for such people.  Last Thursday, he won his claim.  </p><p>Let us ensure we consider these legislative measures and complete them.  They are very simple.  The Bill was discussed in the House and nobody disagreed with it.  However, it was adjourned with one minute to go.  Let us bring it back to the House and ensure it is passed, along with the legislation on defibrillators.  We need both measures very badly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#S00200"><p>To follow Senator Quinn's comments on the need for defibrillators on aeroplanes, which is an important issue, I wish to raise an issue regarding people on holidays.  Sadly, there has been a great deal of focus on people on holidays in the last few days due to tragic events, but the issue I wish to raise is the consumption of alcohol by people on holidays.  I recently spoke to a colleague who told me that on their way back from a holiday a person went through withdrawal symptoms on the airplane.  Obviously, the person was drinking excessively while on holidays.  When it was suggested that the only solution available on the airplane was to give the person a drink, the response was that he could not be given a drink because he had to drive others home from the airport.  It is important when people go on holidays to keep the issue of alcohol consumption in mind because excessive drinking can cause problems.  It certainly caused problems in that case, and caused problems for the airline as well.</p> <p>The other issue I wish to raise, and I raised it as a Commencement matter earlier, is the current difficulties with the registration of nurses and the shortage of nurses.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#T00100"><p>That was discussed as a Commencement matter and should not be raised on the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#T00200"><p>At present there is a shortage of nurses, while nursing homes involved in providing care are having to recruit abroad.  The cost of doing so is in the order of &euro;10,000 per person for retraining and so on.  It is time we looked at creating a tax incentive for Irish nurses working abroad to come home if they want to come back.  It is not attractive enough at the moment and we need to examine what can be done to make it attractive.  If it is costing an Irish company &euro;10,000 to bring in someone who is not an Irish citizen or an EU citizen, we should be providing an incentive for Irish people to come home.  That should be in the upcoming budget.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1196" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#T00300"><p>I supported a motion last week about the funding of Rape Crisis Network Ireland.  I wish to put on record the view of the Dublin Rape Crisis Centre that its funding has not been cut, although it is under-funded.  The centre asked me last night to put that on the record.  I apologise for any injury caused to the Minister.  The Dublin Rape Crisis Centre is, however, looking for additional funding and asks that Tusla be better funded to that purpose.</p> <p>I also wish to raise the lone parents issue.  I have heard this kicked around town and around the Houses for the last couple of weeks.  I received e-mails today suggesting that, for example, a woman working as a cleaner in a school for 2.5 hours a day or 12.5 hours a week does not qualify for family income supplement.  The loss of income to her family is &euro;142 a week.</p> <p>Somewhere along the line, somebody has got this wrong.  It would take great courage for somebody to come in to the House and admit he or she got it wrong and needs to go back and address the legislation.   The Government side has got it wrong and 10,000 families are going to lose money.  I am proposing an amendment to the Order of Business, that we take No. 17 before No. 1.  The very least we owe lone parents is our interest in their welfare and that of their children.  For God's sake, we hear what is going on in Greece, with families eating out of dustbins and things like that.  A woman who is doing decent work, spending 2.5 hours a day cleaning a school, is losing &euro;142 a week.  It is nonsense.  Let us be honest with ourselves and with those who are suffering.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#T00400"><p>I have good news on an issue which I have raised numerous times before.  I am delighted an agreement has been reached on the abolition of roaming charges between the European Commission, the European Parliament and the Council.  It is due to come into effect in June 2017.  From April 2016 we will have surcharges for roaming capped at &euro;0.05 per minute for calls.  There will also be reductions for SMS and for megabytes.  It is a far cry from where we were just a few years ago.  In 2010, the charge was &euro;7 per megabyte of data when roaming, 140 times what it will cost in April 2016.  It seems extraordinary, looking back.  In 2010, a call cost &euro;0.52 per minute, ten times what it will cost in 2016.</p> <p>This is a positive change from the EU.  It still has to be voted on by the European Parliament but I gather that agreement has been reached.  A few months ago, it looked as though the issue would be stalled entirely but it is now likely to come to pass.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#U00100"><p>I second the amendment to the Order of Business proposed by Senator Craughwell.  As the Leader will be aware, we have repeatedly raised this issue since the time of the original debate with the Minister, Deputy Burton, in 2012.  Her comments at that time will haunt her and her party into the general election.  She said she would be opposed to introducing this measure until there was a Scandinavian model of child care in this country.  She has not resiled from that statement nor has she made any comments about it since then.  Obviously, she felt strongly enough about it at the time to put it on record that she was opposed to the introduction of this measure and yet she has been spinning justification for it ever since.  Like Senator Craughwell, I and other Members have been receiving plaintive e-mails from lone parents who will be significantly affected by this measure.</p> <p>I am somewhat concerned that Ireland would not be seen to be beating the Greeks over the head over what is happening.  I appreciate that the idea of their debt and a write-down of it would be anathema to this Government and many people in this country would feel the same, considering that the European Commission and the European Union left us swinging in the wind with our own debt.  However, it is not in anybody's interests, and certainly not in the interests of the European Union, that Greece should exit the euro.  I hope wise heads will prevail and that Greece will come back to the negotiating table.  I also hope the sympathy and empathy many Irish people have for the Greek people will be highlighted.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Ca&iacute;t Keane" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#U00200"><p>Like Senator Bacik, I also call for a debate with the Minister for Justice and Equality.  The Minister stated today that she welcomed the resumption of publication of the recorded crime statistics.  We should have a full debate on that issue.  As the Minister stated, it is vital that we have access to accurate information and reliable data on crime.  I welcome her statement that the work of both the CSO and the Garda Inspectorate has identified common issues of concern in relation to the crime.  She went on to state that technology has failed to keep up with the demands of policing in a modern society and that she will be announcing new improvements in technology.  It is very difficult for garda&iacute; to do their work if the technology and recording systems with which they are provided are not up to scratch.  Sometimes one cannot even send an e-mail to a garda.  All garda&iacute; should have hand-held devices where everything is recorded there and then.  There should also be a back-up system in place.  Restaurants have such a system so why can the Garda not have it?  Technology has failed the Garda.  That is the message I want to get across.  That issue should be included in the debate as well as the crime statistics.  The recording of statistics is now done on computer but if one has to write the information on paper and then record it on computer, it defeats the purpose.</p> <p>I wish to raise another issue, which was raised by a councillor in Galway recently, namely, that a garda who goes on maternity leave is not replaced.  Teachers on maternity leave are replaced and there is a rota system in place for teachers.  However, when a garda goes on maternity leave, the other garda&iacute; in the unit have to pick up the slack.  I have some statistics on this.  By the end of the year, one garda in three will be female.  As we all know, men do not have babies-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1196" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#U00300"><p>That is all changing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Ca&iacute;t Keane" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#U00400"><p>-----but women do.  Only a handful of the retirees will be female for the simple reason that in 1983 of the 400 recruits, only 20 were female.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#U00500"><p>That would be a good subject for a Commencement debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Ca&iacute;t Keane" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#U00600"><p>The retirees will be men.  I would like that issue included in the debate.  I ask for an all-encompassing debate covering the availability and updating of IT facilities for all garda&iacute; on the beat and maternity leave.  I know the Government is bringing in-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#U00700"><p>Is there anything else?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Ca&iacute;t Keane" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#U00800"><p>Child care, maternity leave and shared paternity leave should also be included.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#U00900"><p>The Senator is way over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Ca&iacute;t Keane" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#U01000"><p>We have to consider all aspects concerning the force as well the issue of crime statistics and how they are matched.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#U01100"><p>I ask the Leader to arrange for a debate on the need for a debt conference, which we have repeatedly requested in this House.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator David Cullinane:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2357"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2357&amp;amp;pid=DavidCullinane&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=30"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The issue has come into sharp focus again as a result of developments in Greece and the demands being made by the Greek Government.  While we all want a solution for Greece, it must be a fair and sustainable one, which will require some level of restructuring of the country's debt.  Any economist worth his or her salt will agree with the statement in recent weeks by a Nobel Prize winning economist that without a debt write-down or restructuring of debt for Greece, there cannot and will not be a solution.  Even if the Greek Government were to sign up to such a proposal, we would be back at the table in a short period. </p><p>A twin track approach has been required throughout this process.  On one side, it is necessary to deal with fiscal problems.  The Greek Government has made proposals in this area and broad agreement has been found on some of these.  However, no agreement has been found on the need for a restructuring of debt.  I understand last minute efforts are under way to reach agreement and debt restructuring may or may not be on the table, although we do not have any details.  If that is the case, it will be a welcome development.  Debt restructuring could have been done a long time ago as the bones of a deal have always been in place.  The problem has been that, for political reasons, governments in Europe were not prepared to give Greece what its economy and citizens need because they were fearful of the political consequences such an agreement would have for emerging left parties across Europe.  This was a wrong move by the Irish Government and some of the leaders of the European institutions.  </p><p>I ask again that the Leader arrange a debate on a debt conference.  Let us discuss what needs to be done to restructure debt and ensure the burden of debt placed on taxpayers and citizens in many countries across the European Union is lifted in a manner that allows the economies in question, including the Greek economy, to benefit and grow.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#V00200"><p>The Senator from Haggardstown asked some pertinent questions today and it is interesting to hear Senator Cullinane following on from them.  While we all empathise with the Greeks, as Senator Jim D'Arcy stated, nothing will be resolved without dialogue and the parties involved sitting around a table.  The problem will have to be solved eventually through dialogue.</p> <p>I wish to briefly discuss another issue, namely, the growing concern about the number of unlicensed auctioneers who are practising.  Auctioneers and others must register with the Property Services Regulatory Authority.  It appears, however, that these unlicensed individuals have not been in contact with the PSRA and the authority, which was established for a specific purpose, does not appear to have been in contact with them.  I presume these unlicensed auctioneers are not bonded or insured, thus placing members of the public at risk.  The Leader will probably inform me that this matter would be suitable for discussion in a Commencement debate.  Perhaps I will raise it as a Commencement Matter.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1189" speakername="Paul Bradford" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#V00300"><p>I join previous speakers in proposing that the Leader arrange a debate on the broader aspects of the Greek crisis.  Senator Jim D'Arcy, in his usual entertaining manner, recounted the questions being posed to him by people in his locality.  I am pleased he brought this matter to our attention.  The appropriate response would be to hold a broad debate on the Greek crisis at the earliest opportunity.</p> <p>I thank the Cathaoirleach for allowing me to raise this matter by way of the Commencement debate tomorrow morning.  Perhaps we have not fully recognised the prospective scale of the economic, political and regional damage a Greek exit from the eurozone could cause.  Everyone must act responsibly as there are no easy answers.  As Senator Paul Coghlan stated, it is a matter of trying to negotiate a solution.  As with all difficulties of this nature, neither side has all the answers and we must listen to the arguments made by both sides.  A debate would be a useful exercise for Senators who will, I presume, have something to say on the matter and have an interest in and concern about it. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#V00400"><p>I join colleagues in extending my deepest sympathy to all of those who lost their lives in the Tunisian terror attack at the weekend.  We think, in particular, today of the family of Lorna Carty from County Meath and Larry and Martina Hayes from Athlone.  The Hayes family has many connections in my home town.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Michael Mullins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2368"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2368&amp;amp;pid=MichaelMullins&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=30"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->What we saw was an act of terrorism and racism of the worst kind, which obviously was designed to inflict as much damage as possible on the economy of Tunisia.  Members must stand in solidarity with that country, which is struggling to maintain its democracy and to move its economy on.  In particular, this proves how vulnerable we all are.  The people who were on that beach had no agenda, except to get a bit of a rest and a break.  They were no threat to anyone but were killed in cold blood.  A debate is needed in this House on the threat being posed by Islamic State and what can be done collectively with our European Union partners to deal with this major threat to civilisation and to democracy.  I also share the concern expressed by a previous speaker who referred to the possibility that there may be Irish citizens fighting in Syria with Islamic State, a matter about which Members should be deeply concerned.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#W00150"><p>There are.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#W00175"><p>I also support strongly Senator O'Donovan's remarks on what the Dillon family in Kilbeggan is going through.  They lost 100 head of livestock over the weekend, and apparently a cross-Border rustling gang, which pays protection money to paramilitaries, is behind this particular activity.  This is all part of the cross-Border activities such as fuel smuggling, diesel laundering, cigarette smuggling and the drugs industry, all of which are doing immense damage to the economy.  I will go so far as to ask the Leader to organise a debate with the Minister for Justice and Equality about how the PSNI and the Garda can co-operate better in trying to tackle this major threat to the economy, both North and South of the Border.  Moreover, if it is necessary to strengthen legislation to tackle this issue, Members should do so, because this cannot be allowed to continue.  The livelihood of that young family, the Dillon family from Kilbeggan, has been destroyed absolutely overnight.  This also is happening on a smaller scale in other parts of the country, including the west of Ireland.  These people, because of the new and enhanced road network, can now get across the Border frequently.  This is a major issue that requires debate in this House and I look forward to the organisation of such a debate by the Leader, if not before the recess then immediately afterwards.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" speakername="Terry Brennan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#W00200"><p>I welcome the Connecting for Life initiative, Ireland's new national strategy for suicide prevention for the next five years, launched recently by An Taoiseach.  Connecting for Life sets out a vision of an Ireland in which fewer lives are lost through suicide and in which communities and individuals are empowered to improve their mental health and well-being.  This initiative is an ambitious strategy that sets a target to reduce suicide and self-harm by 10% over the next five years.  There is no one-size-fits-all in mental health, and the range of services reflects this.  As part of the suicide strategy, we need to connect with ourselves, our families, our communities and the services that are on offer.  I seek a debate with the Minister for Health on these proposals and on how we can play our part individually in ensuring the success of the national strategy in reducing the number of people, young and old, taking their own lives.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#W00300"><p>Two weeks ago, I called on the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport to engage in genuine consultation with farmers and landowners in east County Galway about the proposed greenway cycle route project.  It now transpires that the Minister has written to around a thousand landowners in a bid to work out a feasible route.  However, I am concerned that this may not be a genuine consultation, because I have had sight of the letter sent to landowners and it is clear that their legitimate concerns still are being ignored.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2250"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2250&amp;amp;pid=RonanMullen&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=30"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->First, the threat of compulsory purchase orders, CPOs, is still on the table.  Where the Department is proposing to run a new public right of way through family farms, using the threat of a CPO or such proceedings against farmers is absolutely outrageous.  CPOs are designed to be used in the context of vital national infrastructure.  Such infrastructure does not include cycle paths.  Second, the Department seems determined to proceed with the route it has selected.  No consideration is being given to an alternative route along the train line, where the land is actually owned by the public.  Further, the Minister proposes that two of his officials will meet and visit farmers individually to discuss, among other things, the possibility of CPOs being made in respect of their lands.  This is a regrettable development.  I agree with the IFA to the effect that farmers should be able to meet the officials in groups rather than on an individual basis.  There is an inherent inequality in outnumbering any given farmer with two officials who have been told to push the implicit threat of the use of a CPO with a view to obtaining agreement.  This type of behaviour on the part of the Department is unfair and unreasonable.</p><p>There are other matters which must be addressed, including farm safety issues.  A farm is a working environment.  Imagine if a factory owner was informed that a cycle path was to be run through his yard or across his factory floor.  Such a development simply would not be tolerated.  However, farmers are expected to assume the risk of members of the public having access to their lands, where potentially dangerous livestock may be located.  One farmer to whom I spoke pointed out that the planned route dissects his land and that his dairy herd will have to cross the greenway four times each day.  There are obvious safety concerns arising.  There are also privacy concerns, particularly with people being obliged to come to terms with a public right of way running close to their private dwellings.  It is extremely regrettable that measures to protect privacy are entirely absent from the Minister's proposed consultation process.  People in rural areas, as is well known in this House, are concerned about crime.  They are particularly worried about the increase in the number of crimes at isolated properties.  Garda stations have been closed and it is now rare for people in rural areas to receive a visit from local garda&iacute;.  In the current climate, people are rightly concerned about the creation of a public right of way close to their homes.  In order to prevent this greenway project from turning from a mess into a fiasco, the Minister needs to offer meaningful measures relating to safety and privacy to landowners.  This has not yet been done.  No farmer should be threatened with a CPO in order to facilitate a cycle path.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#X00200"><p>I join those Members who expressed their sympathies and condolences to the families of Lorna Carty and Martina and Larry Hayes.  The attacks in Tunisia were savage in nature and the atrocities carried out elsewhere were dreadful.  I assure Senator Darragh O'Brien that I will certainly ask the relevant Minister to come before the House to discuss terrorist and extremist threats in this country.  I note the Senator's points - he has made them on several occasions - in respect of the pension levy, which will be brought to an end this year.  I am sure he will be glad to hear that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#X00300"><p>I am sure you will be glad as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#X00400"><p>Senators Bacik and Keane referred to crime statistics.  Senator Keane inquired about the possibility of having a debate on the greater use of technology, in which could be included the issue of maternity leave for garda&iacute;.  I will try to arrange for the Minister for Justice and Equality to come before the House to debate these matters in early course.</p> <p>Senator Bacik welcomed the fact that the the unemployment rate has fallen to 9.7%.  I am sure that fact will be welcomed by all Senators.</p> <p>I have been passed the information that Senator Norris provided in respect of the Palestinian village of Sousia.  I will certainly raise the matter in question with the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade.</p> <p>Senator Naughton referred to the 26-bed hospice care unit that is planned for Galway and the fact that public investment will be needed in order to supplement the capital funds being raised by those involved with the project.  The position is the same in Waterford, where construction on a major palliative care centre is due to begin later in the year.  Some &euro;6 million is going to be provided for the latter project by means of fund-raising by the public.  The amounts involved are very large in the context of public fund-raising.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Maurice Cummins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2003"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2003&amp;amp;pid=MauriceCummins&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=30"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It has been done there but I am sure it will be done in Galway.  I stress the need for further Government funding for the hospice and palliative care services.</p><p>Senators O'Donovan and Mullins raised the issue of cattle rustling and the devastating blow to the Dillon family.  This is a serious matter and, as has been stated, there is further need for North-South police co-operation to address the question of paramilitary involvement and money being siphoned off for paramilitaries and others as a result of these acts over the past number of months.  The issue will have to be debated.  The only time we heard about cattle rustling in the past related to the Wild West but it seems to be like the Wild West here at the moment because there is little control as regards policing on both sides of the Border.  While there is co-operation, there is a need for further action and legislation, if necessary, to curb these acts.</p><p>Senator Jim D'Arcy put the number of questions that he received from the people of Haggardstown.  They were salient questions, which Senator Cullinane did not proceed to answer.</p><p>Senators Mooney, Cullinane, Coghlan, Bradford and others raised the issue of Greece.  There is no question that we must have empathy with the Greek people when we see elderly pensioners queuing outside boarded up banks and clutching their deposit books wondering whether they will have access to their money or will be able to put food on the table.  This is a serious situation for the Greek people, which can be averted if the Greek Government decides to return to talks on how to keep Greece in the eurozone by agreeing a new support programme.  There were signs of economic recovery in Greece in 2014 with a small increase in GDP, falling unemployment and the regaining of access to financial markets but they have gone.  There cannot be jobs and investment without economic stability and, similarly, there cannot be economic stability without political stability, which is obviously not there either.  Yesterday, the Taoiseach wrote to the Greek Minister and outlined Ireland's support for the objective of a sustainable and mutually beneficial agreement acceptable to all concerned, which will return Greece to growth within the eurozone.  The Taoiseach stated that it had been very much his hope that, in line with the approach agreed, an agreement would have been achieved at the Eurogroup meeting on 27 June on the basis of negotiations between the Greek Government and the institutions but, unfortunately, the decision of the Greek Prime Minister to unilaterally break off these negotiations meant agreement could not be reached at that time.  The Government continues to urge a return to negotiations as quickly as possible and the Taoiseach reiterated to the Greek Prime Minister that Ireland, along with the rest of the eurozone, remains open to dialogue in a spirit of solidarity and responsibility.  There is a need, even at this stage, for the Greek Government to return to the table and to negotiations in respect of the dire situation the country faces.</p><p>Senator Quinn raised the need for defibrillators on Irish aeroplanes.  This is a serious matter and perhaps we can resume debate on the Bill he introduced two years ago.  With regard to the point he raised on employment permits, Second Stage of the Industrial Relations (Amendment) Bill 2015 will be taken later and I hope the Senator will take part in the debate.  The employment permits issue he mentioned could be incorporated into that Bill and I ask him to consider that.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Maurice Cummins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2003"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2003&amp;amp;pid=MauriceCummins&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=30"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Senator Burke spoke about excessive drinking and the shortage of nurses, which he raised on the Commencement debate.  I take his point on incentives to bring back Irish nurses because there is a dire shortage.</p><p>Senator Craughwell clarified that funding for the Dublin Rape Crisis Centre was not cut, as I mentioned last week.  I do not propose to accept his amendment to the Order of Business that No. 74, non-Government motion No. 17, be taken before No. 1.</p><p>Senator Noone spoke about roaming charges, and it is very welcome that these charges will have ended by 2017.  It is a matter that has been raised in this House over many years and it is great news that eventually we will see the end of these very exorbitant charges.</p><p>Senator Mullins spoke about the terrorist attack in Tunisia and the Dillon family farm.</p><p>I note Senator Brennan's point on the national strategy for suicide prevention, and I will try to arrange a debate on this with the Minister of State, Deputy Lynch.</p><p>Senator Mullen spoke about a greenway project in east Galway.  The greenways throughout the country have been very successful.  They have been achieved through negotiation between local authorities, farming institutions and others.  I suggest that the Senator table a Commencement Matter on the specific greenway project he mentioned.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#Z00200"><p>Senator Gerard Craughwell has moved an amendment to the Order of Business: "That No. 74, non-Government motion No. 17, be taken before No. 1."  Is the amendment being pressed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1196" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#Z00300"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.96/1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#Z00400"><p>Amendment put:</p><p>The Seanad divided: T, 17; Nl, 20.</p><br/><br/><p>Tellers: T, Senators Gerard P. Craughwell and Diarmuid Wilson; Nl, Senators Ivana Bacik and Paul Coghlan.</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.96/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2015-06-30" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#Z00400">
            <divisioncount ayes="17" noes="20" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1189" vote="aye">Paul Bradford</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" vote="aye">Thomas Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1196" vote="aye">Gerard Craughwell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" vote="aye">David Cullinane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" vote="aye">Mark Daly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1119" vote="aye">James Heffernan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" vote="aye">Terry Leyden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" vote="aye">Paschal Mooney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" vote="aye">R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" vote="aye">Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" vote="aye">Darragh O'Brien</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" vote="aye">Denis O'Donovan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1200" vote="aye">Averil Power</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" vote="aye">Jillian van Turnhout</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" vote="aye">Mary White</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" vote="aye">Diarmuid Wilson</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1176" vote="aye">Katherine Zappone</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" vote="no">Ivana Bacik</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" vote="no">Terry Brennan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" vote="no">Colm Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" vote="no">Eamonn Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" vote="no">Paul Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1124" vote="no">Michael Comiskey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" vote="no">Maurice Cummins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" vote="no">Jim D'Arcy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1152" vote="no">Imelda Henry</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1173" vote="no">Lorraine Higgins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" vote="no">Ca&iacute;t Keane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" vote="no">John Kelly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1162" vote="no">Denis Landy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" vote="no">Mary Moran</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1134" vote="no">Tony Mulcahy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" vote="no">Michael Mullins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1187" vote="no">Hildegarde Naughton</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" vote="no">Catherine Noone</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1163" vote="no">Tom Shehan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1143" vote="no">John Whelan</mpname>
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.96/3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#Z00400"><p>Amendment declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#BB00200"><p>I am sure the Members of the House would like to join with me in welcoming to the Visitors Gallery Councillor Paschal Fitzmaurice, Councillor Nigel Dineen, Dr. Greg Kelly, Mr. Liam Walsh, and a former councillor and former GAA representative from Roscommon - I know they had a bad day - Mr. Danny Burke.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.98" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.99" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#BB00300">Educational Research Centre (Establishment) Order 2015: Referral to Joint Committee</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#BB00400"><p>I move:<blockquote><br /><br />That the proposal that Seanad &Eacute;ireann approve the following Order in draft:Educational Research Centre (Establishment) Order 2015,copies of which were laid before Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 11 June 2015, be referred to the Joint Committee on Education and Social Protection in accordance with Standing Order 70A(3)(<i>j</i>), which, not later than 14 July 2015, shall send a message to the Seanad in the manner prescribed in Standing Order 73, and Standing Order 75(2) shall accordingly apply.</blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.101" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.102" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#CC00100">Industrial Relations (Amendment) Bill 2015: Second Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.103" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That the Bill be now read a Second Time."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#CC00300"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#CC00400"><p>I am pleased to introduce the Industrial Relations (Amendment) Bill 2015 for the consideration of the House.</p> <p>The Bill, in its totality, represents a significant step forward for workers and employers in providing clear, workable and constitutionally robust frameworks within which workers remuneration and conditions of employment can be discussed and determined.  I am confident that the framework proposed will fit Ireland's constitutional, social and economic traditions and its international obligations, and importantly, will ensure continued success in creating jobs and attracting investment into the economy.</p> <p>The purpose of the legislation is twofold.  First, it will provide for the reintroduction of the registration of employment agreements between employers and trade unions in individual enterprises, and will provide for a new statutory framework to replace the former sectoral registered employment agreements.  Second, the Bill will put in place the legislative amendments required to give effect to the programme for Government commitment to reform the Industrial Relations Acts 2001 and 2004.</p> <p>Before moving to detail the various sections of the Bill, I will give Senators an overview of what the Bill achieves.  Part 2 of the Bill provides for the registration of employment agreements between an employer or employers or a trade union of employers and trade unions of workers governing remuneration and conditions of employment in individual enterprises.  The content of these agreements will be a matter for the contracting parties and they will be legally binding on the subscribing parties.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1196" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#CC00500"><p>Gabh mo leithsc&eacute;al n&oacute;im&eacute;ad amh&aacute;in, do we have a copy of the speech?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#CC00600"><p>I believe that is on its way.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1196" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#CC00700"><p>I thank the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015063000002#CC00800"><p>Part 2 also provides for the making of sectoral employment orders, SEOs.  The Labour Court may initiate a review of the pay and pension and sick pay entitlements of workers of a particular class, type or group in a particular sector and, if it deems it appropriate, make a relevant recommendation to the Minister.  Such a review will be initiated at the request, separately or jointly, from organisations substantially representative of employers and-or of workers.</p> <p>Where the Minister is satisfied that the process provided for in the new legislation has been complied with by the Labour Court, he or she shall make the order.  Where such an order is made, it will be binding as regards the class, type or group across the sector to which it relates, and it will be fully enforceable.</p> <p>There is broad acceptance that the re-introduction of REAs and a sectoral pay and conditions framework in a constitutionally robust manner will be of benefit to both workers and their employers.  From a worker and employer perspective, the agreements and orders will provide certainty around what pay and conditions will be into the future, and the very real pay-off of industrial peace.  These are critical for workers planning their future and for employers when tendering for and working through contracts.  They will also maintain skill standards and help avoid races to the bottom that, in the end, are of no lasting benefit to employers or workers.  In addition, there is no doubt but that REAs and SEOs will address the uncertainty around pay and conditions that has arisen since the McGowan ruling and should assist in resolving industrial disputes or potential disputes that have occurred following that decision.</p> <p>Part 3 of the Bill marks the fulfilment of a significant commitment in the programme for Government to ensure that Irish law is consistent with recent judgments of the European Court of Human Rights.  It will provide a clear and balanced mechanism by which the fairness of the employment conditions of workers in their totality can be assessed where collective bargaining does not take place.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Gerald Nash:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=2281"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2281&amp;amp;pid=GeraldNash&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=30"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It will ensure that such workers, aided by a trade union, can advance claims about remuneration and conditions of employment and have these determined by the Labour Court based on comparisons with similar companies.  It provides definitions of key terms as well as guidelines to help the Labour Court identify if internal bargaining bodies are genuinely independent of their employer, and policies and principles for the Labour Court to follow when assessing the comparability of the remuneration and conditions in dispute.</p><p>The Government knows that workers in some employments may feel exposed in seeking to improve terms and conditions and that making themselves known may have unwanted and unwarranted consequences.  The legislation will bring in significant protection against such consequences.  This will be done by way of interim relief in the Circuit Court where a dismissal is challenged by a worker who believes that he or she was victimised as a result of his or her participation in the invoking of the processes of the Act.  Worker and employer stakeholders have played a critical role in assisting Government developing this clear and workable framework and I wish to acknowledge the huge contribution of the representatives of both sides of industry in this regard.</p><p>Part 4 of the Bill provides for a number of amendments to the Industrial Relations Acts in a number of important areas.  Taken together with the National Minimum Wage (Low Pay Commission) Bill that has already been passed by this House, I believe that this suite of legislative reforms represents a unique opportunity for the Oireachtas to bring about the most significant shift in the industrial relations landscape seen in many years.</p><p>Part 1 of the Bill deals with the Short Title, citation, constructive provisions and commencement date and certain definitions.  Part 2 of the Bill deals with REAs and SEOs.  Chapter 1 of Part 2 provides for definitions of key terms to be used in Chapter 2.  Chapter 2 of Part 2 deals with registered employment agreements.</p><p>Section 7 provides for the register of employment agreements to be maintained by the Labour Court, including the provision that the details of REA registration, cancellation and variation be published on the Internet.</p><p>Section 8 provides that where an application is made to register an employment agreement, the court shall register it only where it is satisfied that there is all-party agreement that it should be registered, and it is satisfied that it is desirable or expedient to have a separate agreement for the class, type or group of workers covered by the agreement.  Similarly, the court shall only register the agreement where it is satisfied that the trade union of workers is, or trade unions of workers are substantially representative of such workers, and that the agreement provides that, if a trade dispute occurs between workers to whom the agreement relates and their employer, industrial action or lock-out shall not take place until the dispute has been submitted for settlement by negotiation in the manner specified in the agreement.</p><p>In addition, the court shall not register any such agreement unless it is satisfied that registration of the agreement is likely to promote harmonious relations between workers and their employer, and the avoidance of industrial unrest.  It is important to note that an REA will not prejudice any rights as to rates of remuneration or conditions of employment conferred on any worker by or under this Act or any other Act.</p><p>Section 9 provides for the variation of REAs.  This may arise where all parties so agree or where one party wishes to vary the agreement but the other does not.  In the latter case, the court, after the exhaustion of the agreed dispute provisions, may refuse or grant such a variation as the court deems appropriate.  Provision is made for a party to withdraw from an agreement following a variation where the agreement provides for a party to do so.</p><p>Section 10 provides that the court may cancel the registration of an employment agreement at the request of all parties or on the application of any party, where the registration of an employment agreement has continued after the finishing date and consented to by all parties.  This is to ensure that all parties are aware that a termination date is imminent.  It may also cancel the registration where it is satisfied that the trade union of workers, or trade unions of workers, who were party to the agreement are no longer substantially representative of the workers concerned.</p><p>Section 11 provides for the incorporation of the terms of any REA in respect of remuneration or conditions of employment to be incorporated into a worker's contract of employment.  Section 12 provides that the Labour Court may, where asked, give its decision on any question as to the interpretation of an REA or its application.</p><p>Chapter 3 of Part 2 of the Bill deals with the new mechanism dealing with SEOs.  These will encompass pay and remuneration, pension schemes, sick pay schemes, or a combination of any or all three.</p><p>Section 13 provides for definitions of key terms to be used in Chapter 3.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Gerald Nash:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=2281"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2281&amp;amp;pid=GeraldNash&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=30"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Section 14 provides that a trade union of workers or a trade union or organisation of employers which is substantially representative of workers or employers of a particular class, type or group of workers in a particular economic sector may, separately or jointly, request the Labour Court to examine the terms and conditions relating to the remuneration, sick pay or pension of workers of that particular class, type or group and request the court to make a recommendation to the Minister.  The court may not consider a request where the Minister has made an employment order for the same workers in that sector in the previous 12 months, unless there are exceptional and compelling reasons.  <br/><br/>Section 15 provides that the Labour Court shall not undertake an examination unless it is satisfied that the trade union of workers or trade union or organisation of employers are substantially representative of workers in the economic sector and, in satisfying itself, the court will take into account the number of workers represented by the trade union and the number of workers employed in the sector by employers represented by the trade union or organisation of employers concerned.  Section 15 also provides that the court will have to be satisfied that it is normal and desirable practice to have separate rates of remuneration, sick pay and pension provisions in the class, type or group of worker in the sector concerned and that any recommendation is likely to promote harmonious relations.<br/><br/>Section 16 provides guidance to the Labour Court on the principles and policies that it must take into account before making a recommendation to the Minister, including the requirement to ensure that the recommendation would promote harmonious relations, promote and preserve high standards of training and qualifications and ensure fair and sustainable rates of remuneration in the sector.  Section 16 also provides that the recommendation by the court may provide for a minimum hourly rate of pay in excess of the national minimum wage; not more than two higher hourly rates of basic pay based on length of service in the sector or enterprise concerned or the attainment of recognised standards or skills in the sector concerned; and minimum rates of pay in respect of young workers as provided for, and in accordance with, the relevant percentages set out in the National Minimum Wage Act.  The recommendation may also include a minimum rate of remuneration for apprentices, any pay in excess of basic pay in respect of shift work, piece work, overtime, unsocial hours worked, hours worked on a Sunday or travelling time.  Recommendations in this respect are at the discretion of the court.  A recommendation will include the procedures to apply in the case of a dispute concerning the terms of a sectoral employment order, SEO.  <br/><br/>Section 17 provides for the submission by the Labour Court to, and consideration by the Minister of, the Labour Court recommendation.  The Minister shall refuse to make such an order if not satisfied that the process has been complied with, otherwise the Minister shall make the order.  There will be a requirement for a positive Oireachtas resolution before any order is made.  <br/><br/>Section 18 provides that if an order has not been amended or revoked within three years, the Minister may request that the court undertake a review of the terms and conditions of the previous order.  <br/><br/>Section 19 provides that an SEO shall apply to all workers of the class, type or group in the relevant sector, regardless of whether the worker and his or her employer were party to the request to the Labour Court and for the incorporation of the terms of any SEO in a worker's contract of employment.<br/><br/>Section 20 provides for anti-penalisation measures to protect a worker who invokes any right conferred on him or her by the Act or takes other specified actions under the Act.<br/><br/>Section 21 provides for a mechanism to allow an employer experiencing financial difficulties to apply to the Labour Court for a temporary derogation from the requirement to pay the remuneration provided for by an order.<br/><br/>Section 22 provides for a requirement for employers to whom an REA or a SEO applies to keep such records as are necessary to show whether they are compliant with the terms of the REA or SEO.<br/><br/>Section 23 provides for the functions of an adjudication officer of the workplace relations commission and the Labour Court on disputes regarding the penalisation provisions under section 20 of this Bill, breaches of an REA and breaches of an SEO.<br/><br/>Section 24 provides for the amendments to the Workplace Relations Act 2015 to accommodate the necessary compliance and enforcement requirements regarding REAs and SEOs.  <br/><br/>Part 3 of the Bill addresses the Government commitment on collective bargaining.  Section 25 provides for definitions of key terms to be used in Part 3.<br/><br/>Section 26 amends the principal Act to provide for the insertion of a number of relevant definitions regarding collective bargaining and excepted body.  <br/><br/>Section 27 amends the principal Act by the insertion of definitions of collective bargaining and excepted body.  These definitions apply only to the principal Act and have no meaning in terms of other legislation.<br/><br/>Section 28 amends the principal Act to remove the right of access of an excepted body under section 2(1) of the 2001 Act.Since the decision of the Supreme Court in larnr&oacute;d &Eacute;ireann <i>v. </i>Holbrooke and Others it is clear that a body can only be an excepted body within the meaning of the Trade Union Act 1941 if it actually conducts consensual negotiations with an employer.  The existence of a genuine excepted body means that a fundamental requirement of the Act, that is, the absence of collective bargaining negotiations, cannot be met.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-30a.112" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Additional text to follow.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>