<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.2" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 14:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.4" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.5" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Tim Lombard that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Housing, Planning, Community and Local Government to create specific national guidelines pertaining to solar farms to help local authorities deal consistently with applications.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Aidan Davitt of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Housing, Planning, Community and Local Government to address the Seanad on the serious issue of serial objectors delaying planning permission applications across Ireland.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Robbie Gallagher of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine to provide immediately a special support package through the Common Agricultural Policy market support measures to the affected providers in the Irish mushroom industry for whom the decision of the United Kingdom to leave the European Union has had an immediate and negative economic impact.  </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator John O&rsquo;Mahony of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport to set out the timeline for the next round of sports capital funding.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Colm Burke of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to confirm that the recommendations set out in the report of the investigation into the safety, quality and standards of services provided by the Health Service Executive to patients in the Midland Regional Hospital, Portlaoise, have been implemented and, in particular, in respect of the appointment of a director of midwifery in each of the 19 maternity hospitals throughout the country.</blockquote> <p>I regard the matters raised by the Senators as suitable for discussion.  I have selected the matters raised by Senators Lombard, Davitt, Gallagher and O&rsquo;Mahony and they will be taken now.  Senator Colm Burke may give notice on another day of the matter he wishes to raise.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.7" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#A00300">Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.8" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#A00350">Alternative Energy Projects</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#A00400"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach for the opportunity to raise this very important issue.  I call on the Minister for Housing, Planning, Community and Local Government, Deputy Coveney, to create national guidelines pertaining to solar farms to help local authorities deal with the applications that have come before them.</p> <p>There has been a major uptake in applications for solar farms throughout Ireland.  In my local area and across the State, planning applications for solar farms have gone through the roof.  One source recently claimed that more than 20,000 acres of land are being tied up in contracts for solar farms.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Tim Lombard:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2466"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2466&amp;amp;pid=TimLombard&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->That raises the question of where the local authority is in terms of dealing with such planning permissions.  Council planners are ill equipped in respect of the national strategy to make a formal decision over these very complex planning permissions.  We need to move away from once-off planning permissions to overall guidelines, with a Government vision and a strategy going forward.  At the moment, planning applications are being made not with regard to suitability or guidelines but where, realistically, the nearest substation is.  That is becoming a major driver in the vast number of planning applications at the moment.  County development plans and regional planning guidelines have all stated where a wind farm should be but, in the case of solar farms, it is <i>ad hoc</i>and on a once-off basis.  We need to tie everything in together in a national strategy.<br/><br/>We are in favour of solar farms and the issue needs to be looked at because we have guidelines regarding the Paris Agreement and those targets need to be met.  However, at national, county and regional level we need to put together an overall framework, which we are lacking at the moment.  What happens consistently in one county does not happen consistently in the next.  Some of these planning permissions have now gone to An Bord Plean&aacute;la, which has held hearings on the first and has moved on.  The communities are at a loss as to what the national strategy is regarding solar farms and it is an issue with which we need to deal.  I will call on the Minister to ensure we have the necessary guidelines in place and a framework under which we can move forward to inform both our local authorities and our communities of where and when these solar farms can be viable.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1264" speakername="Damien English" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#B00200"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this issue.  There are no specific planning guidelines in place in respect of solar farms and I have no proposals to bring forward such guidelines at the present time.  Under the Planning and Development Act 2000, as amended, each planning authority's development plan is required to set out an overall strategy for the proper planning and sustainable development of the area concerned.  Section 10 of the Act requires a development plan to include, among other things, objectives for the provision or facilitation of the provision of infrastructure, including energy facilities and infrastructure.  Many local authorities have developed renewable energy strategies for their areas in this context.  Proposals for individual solar farm developments are also subject to the statutory requirements of the Planning and Development Act 2000, as amended, in the same manner as other proposed developments.  Planning applications are required to be submitted to the relevant local planning authority with a right of appeal to An Bord Plean&aacute;la.</p> <p>In making decisions on planning applications, planning authorities and the board must consider the proper planning and sustainable development of the area, having regard to the provisions of the development plan, any submissions or observations received and relevant ministerial or Government policies, including any relevant guidelines issued by my Department.  Planning authorities must then make their own decision, based on the specific merits or otherwise of individual planning applications.</p> <p>I am satisfied that the planning code is sufficiently robust to facilitate the assessment of individual planning permission applications for solar farm developments.  However, the matter will be kept under review, in consultation with my colleague, the Minister for Communications, Climate Action and Environment, and his Department, which is the lead Department on renewable energy policy, in the context of the Government's White Paper on Energy Policy in Ireland, published in December 2015, the development of a renewable electricity policy and development framework, REPDF, and the launching of a new subsidy support scheme for renewable electricity by the Department of Communications, Climate Action and Environment, expected in late 2017.  My understanding is that such a new subsidy support scheme is required in order for the development of solar farms to become economically viable, which is not the case at present.  The recently published energy White Paper acts out a vision to accelerate the development and diversification of renewable energy in Ireland and a draft REPDF has been formulated, aimed at optimising the opportunities for producing electricity from a variety of renewable energy sources in projects of significant scale on land, which will be subject to further public consultation prior to its adoption in 2017.</p> <p>The Programme for a Partnership Government contains a commitment to facilitate the development of solar energy projects in Ireland, which builds on the energy White Paper and recognises that solar has the potential to provide a community dividend, thereby also enhancing citizen participation in Ireland's energy future.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Damien English:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1781"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1781&amp;amp;pid=DamienEnglishFG&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Consequently, solar photovoltaics - also known as solar farms -are one of the technologies being considered in the context of a new subsidy support scheme for renewable electricity generation being developed by the Department of the Minister, Deputy Naughten.  This will require Government approval and state aid clearance from the European Commission before it can come into operation.</p><p>We have no proposals to bring forward specific planning guidelines for solar farms at present.  However, the matter will be kept under review pending the development of the various initiatives by the Department of Communications, Climate Action and Environment to which I have referred.  I am conscious that, as the Senator said, quite a high volume of applications have begun to be received.  I will raise this issue with both Departments for it to be monitored more closely.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#C00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for this response, which has been helpful in clarifying the position.  However, I am disappointed there is not a proposal in this respect.  We should be addressing this issue but the Department is not considering such guidelines.  We are working in a vacuum.  These applications for planning permission are coming in off the back of a subsidy that will be introduced in 2017.  The applicants are speculating on questions of when and how and what the rate will be.  That is the reason such a vast number of applications are coming through.  The figure of 20,000 acres being currently tied up in contracts is a significant one.  Because of the speculation in the market, such guidelines are needed now more than ever before.  The planning decisions are literally one-off decisions, in that what happens in County Cork might not happen in County Kerry or in County Limerick.  We need to re-examine this issue because of the speculation in the market.</p> <p>Some of the planning granted will have conditions attached with respect to funds from which the community will benefit while others will not have such conditions attached.  We need to examine these guidelines to ensure that communities across the board can benefit from having such a development in their localities. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1264" speakername="Damien English" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#C00300"><p>As I said, this is kept under review.  I will discuss it with the Ministers, Deputies Coveney and Naughten.  I am conscious that there has been a ramp up in the applications received in recent months or certainly in the past year, and it appears that many more will be submitted.  We will closely monitor that.</p> <p>I draw the Senator's attention to guidelines for key infrastructure, including energy infrastructure that were introduced in July 2012 by the previous Minister in the then Department of Communications, Energy and Natural Resources, Pat Rabbitte.  Those recommendations from the Government set out that any organisation involved in bringing forward such an application should involve the community and have regard to best practice, which would involve community and planning gains.  The Senator might have look at that and we might be able to inform some local authorities of that.  We can also drop a note to the Senator on that.  I will liaise with my two colleagues and report back to the Senator. </p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.15" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#C00350">Planning Issues</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#C00400"><p>I have a serious problem with serial objectors to the granting of planning permission, particularly for one-off houses.  People who apply to build one-off houses have to go to great lengths to prove they have intrinsic links to the area.  They are hoping to build in rural areas and in some towns but objectors can come from any corner of Ireland or even outside the State.  There are no hard and fast criteria for them to make an objection or to be required to put a statement on the file.  Why should someone with no links to an area have the right to object to young people starting out in their lives who are hoping to build a family home and have security for the future?  A suitable amendment could be made to some of the incoming Bills from the Minister of State's Department, of which quite a number are going through the Houses.  That would reintroduce some balance in the planning process.  It is very unevenly keeled towards people with no direct involvement or link to an area.  It is crazy what some people can get away with and how we protect them under legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1264" speakername="Damien English" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#C00500"><p>I thank Senator Davitt for raising this issue.  As a Deputy who represents rural areas and who shares some common ground with the Senator, I understand the logic and motive behind this and I also understand the frustration that is often experienced with the planning system.  I accept the Senator's point and know he has asked for this proposal to be made in good faith.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Damien English:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1781"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1781&amp;amp;pid=DamienEnglishFG&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->As Minister, my role in the planning system is primarily to provide the policy and legislative framework that comprises the Planning and Development Act, the planning and development regulations and the planning guidelines, to which planning authorities and An Bord Plean&aacute;la are obliged to have regard in the exercise of their statutory planning functions.  The Planning and Development Act 2000, as amended, sets the overarching legislative framework for the planning system, including the procedures for preparing and reviewing regional planning guidelines, development plans and local area plans, in addition to the basic framework for the development of the management consent system or, as it is more commonly known, the planning permission system.</p><p>Public participation is an important and integral part of an open and transparent planning system in Ireland and will remain so.  In this regard, the planning system is in full compliance with the requirements of the UNECE Convention on Access to Information, Public Participation in Decision-making and Access to Justice in Environmental Matters, commonly referred to as the Aarhus Convention, with EU Directive 2003/35/EEC on public participation in environmental decision-making and EU Directive 2011/92/EU on the assessment of the effects of certain public and private projects on the environment, normally known as the environmental impact assessment, EIA, directive.  All of these international requirements lay down basic rules to promote citizens' involvement in environmental decision-making with a view to enhancing the accountability and transparency of the planning decision-making process.</p><p>In the light of these international requirements, the Planning and Development Act specifically provides for public involvement and the opportunity to make submissions and observations on individual planning applications.  It further provides that, in making decisions on planning applications, planning authorities, including An Bord Plean&aacute;la, as appropriate, must consider the proper planning and sustainable development of the area, having regard to the provisions of the local development plan, submissions or observations received from the public, relevant ministerial or Government policies or objectives and relevant planning guidelines issued by my Department.  Planning authorities must then make their own decision based on the specific merits or otherwise of individual planning applications.</p><p>The Act also provides that an applicant for permission and any person who made submissions or observations in writing on the planning application to the planning authority may, within four weeks of the date of the decision of the planning authority, appeal to An Bord Plean&aacute;la against a decision of the planning authority.  In addition, a decision made by a planning authority or An Bord Plean&aacute;la may be subject to judicial review, with any such judicial review applications having to be submitted within an eight-week period from the date of the planning decision, or the doing of an act by a planning authority or the board.  These judicial review provisions which are aimed at enhancing transparency and accountability in the planning decision-making process are in accordance with relevant UN and EU requirements, in addition to relevant European Court of Justice judgments.</p><p>I am satisfied that the comprehensive arrangements I have outlined for public participation in the planning system are appropriate, balanced, reasonable and in line with our international obligations.  We have as of yet no proposals to change the legislation in this regard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#D00200"><p>The Minister of State has said there are several iterations regarding public participation.  I have no problem with this, but we should introduce some criteria for public participation.  There are strict criteria in every other part of the planning process, as the Minister of State knows only too well as he has been a champion in this regard in respect of one-off planning.  People have to jump through hoops to meet the strict criteria applied if they seek planning permission for a one-off development.  All stakeholders should have some ties, involvement or expertise, if nothing else.  Anybody who wants to do so can lodge an objection or make a statement on a file.  He or she could be from the other side of the world and have no ties to the area in question.  There should be some criteria attached.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1264" speakername="Damien English" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#D00300"><p>I understand the sentiments expressed.  I will compare our position with that in other countries to determine whether we could address the issue without infringing the criteria for public participation.  Legally, we cannot infringe on them and do not want to do so, but I know exactly what the Senator is trying to say.  I will discuss the issue with our experts on planning to determine whether there are criteria on which we could work in this regard.  I am not saying there are, but I will look at the issue and know what the Senator is trying to achieve.  The difficulty lies in ensuring genuine public involvement.  If there are certain criteria that could be applied, the question of how they would be fixed and judged is very complicated.  We are constantly examining the planning system to see whether we need to adapt or change it.  On the criteria applied, I will determine whether there is any gap I might be able to address.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#D00400"><p>That would be appreciated.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#D00500"><p>I suggest to the Senator that if an appropriate Bill were to be brought before the House, he could table an amendment to it.  Alternatively, if he feels passionately about the issue, he could introduce a Private Members' Bill to deal with it.  He can reflect on this suggestion.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.23" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#E00050">Brexit Issues</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#E00100"><p>I want to raise the issue of Brexit and, in particular, the effect it is having on the mushroom industry in Monaghan and elsewhere.  The mushroom industry provides a stark warning to the rest of the country's economy about Brexit and the damage a sustained weakness in sterling can inflict.  It really is the canary in the coalmine for the Irish agribusiness.</p> <p>Ireland's mushroom industry, the fifth largest in the European Union, has an annual production worth &euro;120 million and employs 3,000 people throughout rural Ireland.  One in every two mushrooms sold in the UK is Irish, while 43% of production costs are labour costs.  Our mushroom growers rely on the UK for approximately 80% of their sales.</p> <p>However, they have been losing money since the referendum sent sterling into a downfall.  Several mushroom farmers have already gone out of business with the loss of 130 jobs, most of them in rural Ireland.  A further six mushroom farms are under serious pressure with the potential loss of a further 300 jobs, again all located in rural Ireland.  The potential impact of further closures is enormous, especially when one considers many of these jobs are heavily concentrated in counties such as Cavan and Monaghan.</p> <p>Producers pinned their hopes on the Government's so-called Brexit-proof budget.  They have now joined other business groups in criticising it as totally inadequate.  They say they are not looking to be propped up indefinitely, but that they certainly need some help in the short term.  Contracts were entered into when sterling was strong.  Now they just need to get into next year when these contracts will be up for renewal again.</p> <p>The mushroom industry made a detailed presentation to the Joint Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine in advance of the budget, which I attended.  The industry pinned its hopes on measures being introduced which would alleviate its difficulties.  The committee made recommendations along those lines but, unfortunately, none of which was implemented.  Mushroom farmers have called for a cut in the level of social insurance tax levied on employers and the provision of emergency funds to exporters.  Instead, they were offered cheaper loans and small tax relief measures.</p> <p>It is a concern that exporters who shift 44% of their product to Britain are reporting they are starting to encounter some issues in accessing credit from banks concerned about their currency exposure.  Some firms with a high proportion of sales in Britain are also considering shifting their production there with obvious implications for jobs on this island.  The Minister for Finance, Deputy Michael Noonan, suggested the budget measures would likely not be the last to cushion the impact of Brexit.  He spoke about the need to wait until he sees the shape of Britain's exit negotiations next year.  This will be cold comfort if exporters have already closed down.</p> <p>The lack of breathing space in the budget is in fact likely to speed up the increased mass closures.  Options from the industry have been suggested, including the provision of more funding for firms breaking into new markets, a partial State guarantee of their credit exposure to suppliers, as is available in other countries, and the reactivation of a fund set up in 2008 that offered up to &euro;500,000 to viable firms facing exceptional difficulties.</p> <p>Brexit is the greatest economic challenge facing Ireland in this generation.  The outcome of the US elections adds to this volatility.  The Government, so far, has shown a lack of interest in issues affecting Border areas.  A serious change of direction is now needed to confront the problems we face arising from Brexit.  Our retail sector is also suffering, underlying no country is more affected than Ireland, and no part of Ireland is more affected than the Border counties, as a result of Brexit.</p> <p>Some people believe Brexit will not happen until Article 50 is triggered.  If one lives in the Border counties, one knows Brexit is here now.  Without action, thousands of jobs will be at risk.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1356" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#F00100"><p>I reassure Senator Gallagher that I am acutely aware of the challenges the mushroom sector is experiencing in the aftermath of the UK referendum decision to exit the EU, particularly in light of recent fluctuations in currency.  I am focused on working with the industry to meet these difficulties in the months and years ahead.</p> <p>The impact that the devaluation of sterling is having on mushroom producers and growers is a problem that has happened over a very short space of time.  Grower production of this highly perishable product must be well aligned with demand and the mushroom sector, like many other exporting sectors, is particularly at risk because of the high dependency on the UK market.</p> <p>I am monitoring sterling fluctuations closely and my Department has established a dedicated unit considering the impact of Brexit.  Additionally, Bord Bia is working closely with the sector on market intelligence, UK consumer research and quality-assurance measures.  It recently held a currency and negotiation workshop, specifically targeted at the sector, which I understand was very well received by the mushroom industry.  In the coming weeks, the chief executive officer of Bord Bia and the Minister, Deputy Creed, will continue to meet senior executives from the UK retailers to highlight the obstacles that producers are facing.  Bord Bia is also running a marketing intensification programme, which aims to provide targeted marketing supports to companies with high dependency on UK markets.  Grant supports will be prioritised to assist companies in strengthening their position in that market and in their efforts to identify new markets.</p> <p>As announced in last month's budget, an extra &euro;700,000 has been secured for capital investments in the commercial horticulture sector.  This will increase the budget for this scheme to &euro;5 million in 2017.  Additionally, the horticulture sector will have access to the &euro;150 million low-interest cashflow-support loan fund announced in the budget, providing access to highly flexible loans for up to six years for amounts up to &euro;150,000 at an interest rate of 2.95% with an option to pay interest only over the first three years.  There have been significant expressions of interest from people in the mushroom sector in that product.</p> <p>I also draw attention to the ongoing support being provided to the industry through national and EU schemes.  Under the National Development Plan 2007-2013 my Department implemented the scheme of investment aid for the development of the commercial horticulture sector.  During this period, my Department paid over &euro;4 million in grant payments to mushroom growers, supporting &euro;10.1 million in investment.</p> <p>To ensure ongoing support for the sector, the Department extended, under EU sanction, the scheme of investment aid for the development of the commercial horticulture sector to run until the end of 2019.  In 2014 and 2015 a total of &euro;1.635 million in grant aid was paid to mushroom growers.  The grant aid paid supported some &euro;4.1 million in investment by these growers.  Under the 2016 scheme of investment aid, my Department issued approvals amounting to &euro;1.33 million in aid to growers in the mushroom sector, supporting &euro;3.3 million in proposed investment.</p> <p>The EU producer organisation scheme is also vital for mushroom growers, with 65% of Irish growers in a producer organisation at present.  This scheme provides an important mechanism for growers to achieve greater bargaining power in the marketplace by becoming part of a larger supply base.  In the ten years from 2005 to 2015, a total of &euro;39.8 million was paid to mushroom producer organisations as part of the scheme.  Recently, my Department delivered a payment of just under &euro;1.57 million to one of the mushroom producer organisations.</p> <p>I fully recognise the challenges for food exporters to the UK market arising from the fall in sterling and my Department and its agencies will continue to work positively with the industry during this challenging time.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Andrew Doyle:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2170"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2170&amp;amp;pid=AndrewDoyle&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We are always trying to figure out new ways to help people.  The mushroom sector is in the eye of the storm, being the most exposed to the short-term ramifications of what has happened with sterling.  We are not neglecting the Border area or any rural area in that regard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#G00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his comments and I am heartened by his sincerity in trying to find solutions to this acute problem.  The industry is one in which we have achieved worldwide recognition.  We are a world beater in the production of mushrooms.  The aid scheme we are seeking would be a temporary measure to get people over the hump.  The &euro;1.5 million in EU funding through the banks the Minister of State mentioned is welcome.  My understanding is the banking sector is tightening up, as many businesses are aware.  Sterling has also weakened.  Businesses' credit providers are gauging the survivability of the mushroom industry and we are looking for a more immediate jolt.  Employer's PRSI was mentioned.  Perhaps payments might be frozen for a six-month period to get people out of this problem.  As I said, I am heartened by the Minister of State's comments and hope some immediate measures will be put in place in order that jobs which are hard to come by because they are to be found in rural Ireland, as I am sure the Minister of State is aware, can be sustained.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1356" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#G00300"><p>This industry is worth fighting for.  There is no question about the quality and seamless service customers in the United Kingdom are getting.  That is one of the messages the Minister and the CEO of Bord Bia will be impressing on retailers.</p> <p>I will address a point that is not directly related to my Department.  We have engaged with major players in the industry who have asked that we set up a new Lean programme to improve harvesting techniques.  According to my note, a pilot programme on Lean processes that is being implemented by Bord Bia with financial assistance from Enterprise Ireland is commencing with mushroom growers to assess the level of efficiency across all aspects of the business, including the supply chain, innovation, marketing and logistics.  While it crosses over from the Department into the Department of Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, it is an important add-on to other efforts that are meant to assist the industry.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.29" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#G00400">Sports Capital Programme</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#G00500"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach for selecting this important topic and the Minister of State for attending to reply.  It is a simple issue.  </p> <p>As everyone knows, sports capital grants were suspended in 2008 and resumed by the previous Government in 2011.  As far as I am aware, there has been a round of sports capital grants every year until 2016.  Is there a timeline for an announcement of a further round of applications for sports capital grants?</p> <p>Many clubs and organisations that did not receive funding previously or which are undertaking upgrades on a phased basis have been in contact with me and other Senators.  It is around this time of year that sports clubs and organisations hold their AGMs.  They want to put their plans in place.  For an application to be successful, they must have matching funds and so on.  I would appreciate it, therefore, if the timeline could be clarified.</p> <p>The sports capital programme represents excellent value for money for the Government.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator John O'Mahony:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2202"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2202&amp;amp;pid=JohnOMahony&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->They provide opportunities for everyone from children up to senior citizens, from recreational and leisure level to elite sports level, which leads to healthier people and savings in the health area.  They also encourage young people to have dreams and ambitions and this helps to keep them out of trouble.  We are all aware of this.</p><p>This is a rich time for sport in Ireland.  We are punching above our weight at local, national and international levels.  In the last few weeks, we had the famous win against the All Blacks and the soccer victory last Saturday night.  The GAA is in every parish in the country.  I heard at the weekend that a club in Longford is in the Leinster Club Championship semi-final.  The GAA has its tentacles in every parish in the country.  There is a great feel-good factor around it.  We have enough to be down and out about.  Sport always uplifts us.  I know that the Minister of State, Deputy O'Donovan, is aware of that.  The ambitions of our sporting heroes of today started when their parents enrolled them in their local clubs and organisations at six or seven years of age.  Money spent in this area is money well spent.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1267" speakername="Patrick O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#H00200"><p>I thank Senator O'Mahony for raising this issue, which I know is one in which he has a particular interest.</p> <p>The sports capital programme, SCP, is the Government&rsquo;s primary vehicle to support the development of sports facilities and the purchase of sports equipment.  The most recent rounds of the programme were in 2012, 2014 and 2015.  So far this year, over &euro;22.8 million has been paid out to 680 organisations. </p> <p>The sports capital programme aims to foster an integrated and planned approach to developing sports and physical recreation facilities throughout the country.  More than 10,000 projects have benefitted from sports capital funding since 1998, bringing total allocations since that time to over &euro;900 million.  The programme has transformed the sporting landscape of Ireland with improvements in the quality and quantity of sporting facilities in virtually every village, town and city in the country.  The facilities that have been funded range from the smallest clubs to national centres of sporting excellence.  The Government is committed to ensuring that this progress continues.  We recognise that sport plays a hugely positive part in Irish society.  Its benefits are numerous, from health benefits to the social side of sports both in the participative and volunteering spheres to the huge contribution sport makes to the Irish economy. </p> <p>Following the conclusion of the 2017 Estimates discussions, a total of &euro;52 million has been provided for sports capital projects next year.  This will meet all existing commitments under previous rounds of the sports capital and local authority swimming pool programme commitments, to the P&aacute;irc U&iacute; Chaoimh redevelopment project in Cork, the Kerry Sports Academy at IT Tralee and existing commitments relating to the development of the national sports campus.</p> <p>There will also be sufficient funding for a new round of the sports capital programme to be opened for applications, which is the most important point in so far as Senator O'Mahony and I are concerned.  In this regard, I have previously stated that the new round will be open for applications soon and this remains the position.  Prior to inviting applications, I want to ensure that a number of improvements are introduced to the application process.  In this regard, the application form will be significantly shortened and a number of additional supports will be available for clubs to complete the application process. </p> <p>The new programme will include a revised online portal which will make the process more user-friendly.  Other supports will include a comprehensive written guide for applicants as well as an online video guide.  Staff in the relevant section of my Department will also be available to assist clubs by phone and e-mail and it is also planned to hold regional seminars to assist clubs who are preparing their applications.  It is hoped that these measures will greatly assist in reducing the level of invalid applications which are submitted to the Department.  As previously stated, the new round will be open for applications soon and obviously clubs will have to be given a number of weeks to complete the application process.  Based on previous rounds of the programme, the assessment process takes a number of months to complete so I expect that actual grant allocations will be made during summer 2017.  I will be announcing more comprehensive details of the new round shortly, including all of the relevant deadline dates.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#H00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his reply, which will enable me to communicate to clubs and organisations that the process will commence early in the New Year.  </p> <p>During the previous Administration the Minister of State with responsibility for sport was Deputy Michael Ring.  Will the Minister of State, Deputy O'Donovan, clarify if he has responsibility for sport in this Administration?<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator John O'Mahony:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2202"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2202&amp;amp;pid=JohnOMahony&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Recent media reports have cast doubt on that but having served on an Oireachtas committee with the Minister of State during the last administration, I know of his deep knowledge and interest in sport.  I have read many of his speeches on the topic and it is clear that he has a deep knowledge of sport at all levels.  I ask him to clarify the situation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1267" speakername="Patrick O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#J00200"><p>When the Taoiseach appointed me as Minister of State at the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport, he asked me to fulfil the same role as my predecessor, Deputy Michael Ring, and I am working on the basis of that continuity.  The responsibilities that were devolved to Deputy Ring as Minister of State at the time are now my responsibilities.  The sports capital programme is one of the areas of responsibility that the Cabinet has delegated to me and that has been agreed within the Department itself.</p> <p>Very little legislation covers our Department relating to tourism and sport and so people often wonder about the statutory basis for our actions.  If there are very few statutes pertaining to a Department, it can look as if a Minister or Minister of State's statutory responsibilities are narrow.  Ministers of State are appointed by the Cabinet as opposed to the Taoiseach and their responsibilities, which are agreed internally within the relevant Department, are actually quite wide ranging, covering tourism promotion right through to sport.</p> <p>In terms of the issue before the House today, I would point out that I have had a number of meetings with departmental officials over the last few months to discuss the sports capital programme, which is of huge significance to me.  I insisted that it be included in the budget speech by the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform.  The sports capital programme for 2017 is now with the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform for final sign off.  I hope it will be signed off in the next couple of weeks and then we will be in a position to open the applications process.</p> <p>I am sure Senator O'Mahony would agree that it is important to empower as many people as possible to get the maximum number of valid applications.  I have no interest in invalid applications.  The more valid applications the Department receives, the more money it can request from the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform going forward.  Another crucially important part of the next sports capital programme is the fact that it is annualised, as per the commitment in the programme for Government.  As the Minister of State with responsibility for delivering that element of the programme for Government, I am absolutely committed to ensuring that the programme will not be rolled out on a haphazard basis any more.  The question of whether the Government will or will not fund another programme will not arise.  There is a firm commitment from the Government in that regard.  It is part of the programme for Government and it is my job to make sure that the commitment is fulfilled.</p> <p>Finally, I draw the attention of the House to today's launch of Ireland's bid to host the Rugby World Cup in 2023.  This is a fantastic opportunity for the island of Ireland.  As Minister of State with responsibility for sport, I really value the work of the IRFU on the bid and crucially, the co-operation of the GAA in facilitating it.  I would urge the House to use the opportunity on the Order of Business, when it is discussing matters of importance, to raise that crucial issue.  It is wonderful to see the IRFU and the GAA working together in a collaborative way alongside the Northern Ireland Executive and the Irish Government to deliver what will be a phenomenal sporting occasion for the island of Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.36" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 3.15 p.m. and resumed at 3.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.37" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#N00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#N00200"><p>Before I call the Leader, I want to update Senators on developments in regard to the temporary relocation of the Seanad Chamber to the Ceramics Room of the National Museum.  A lot of people have concerns, and some Senators have raised the matter in the House.</p> <p>It is important to stress at the outset that the need for the Seanad Chamber to move temporarily arises because much-needed essential work has to be done to the historic part of Leinster House.  We have been asked by the Office of Public Works, OPW, to relocate to facilitate work on this building and other buildings such as the old offices of the Cathaoirleach and Ceann Comhairle which have already been vacated.</p> <p>Leinster House is 270 years old and is badly in need of refurbishment, and we have a duty to maintain it properly.  I am glad to say that final agreement has been reached with the National Museum on the arrangements for the temporary relocation.  The location of the temporary Chamber was not chosen lightly, as some people may think and as public perception may be.  A wide range of locations were considered, including Dublin Castle, the Mansion House, the D&aacute;il Chamber, committee room 1 and local cultural institutions.  In fact, a total of 13 venues were exhausted before the decision was made.</p> <p>Account had to be taken of key criteria such as security, accessibility for Members, adequacy of space, access to technical and support services, the impact on core parliamentary activities, such as committee meetings, accessibility for visitors and, of course, cost.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">An Cathaoirleach:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1988"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1988&amp;amp;pid=DenisODonovan&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Taking all of these into account, the museum was identified as the most suitable option and approved by the Committee on Procedure and Privileges.  Naturally, the museum had a number of concerns about the relocation and I am pleased that we have been able to find practical ways to meet its needs.  Additional exhibition space and an AV room will be developed.  A lift to allow universal access will be installed in the museum; alarm systems will be upgraded and financial assistance for project management provided.  It has also been proposed that the Ceramics Room be available to the museum for seminars and lectures when the Seanad is in recess.</p><p>Last week the Ceann Comhairle met staff of the museum and, in order to promote relationships further, a forum involving the Houses of the Oireachtas and the neighbouring national cultural institutions will be set up.  Last week the Committee on Procedure and Privileges agreed that a visit to the Ceramics Room should be organised for group leaders and Whips and that visit will take place tomorrow.  Because of the fact that Senator David Norris is in a certain vacuum, he is also invited to take part.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#O00200"><p>Thank you.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#O00300"><p>A detailed briefing by the OPW in the AV room is also being organised for all Senators.</p> <p>I pay a sincere tribute and give thanks to the board of the National Museum of Ireland and its staff for their co-operation with the project and in being neighbourly in allowing it to go ahead.  I greatly appreciate the flexibility and pragmatism they have shown and look forward to maintaining the excellent relations that have developed between us in the course of our discussions.  </p> <p>I am not allowing any debate on the matter.  I just wanted to confirm that agreement had been reached, which is hugely important.  I emphasise that we have no choice but to vacate the Chamber.  This issue has been ongoing for some years and I am delighted that an agreement has finally been made.  A press release was organised for last week by the Houses of the Oireachtas and the National Museum of Ireland but, because of certain events in other parts of the world, it went unheeded and seems to have been neglected.  I hope the visit tomorrow to the museum and the briefing in the AV room will help to put a lot of issues to bed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#O00400"><p>I seek clarification.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#O00500"><p>I would like to ask a question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#O00600"><p>No.  I have made a statement and we will now move to the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#O00700"><p>Can the Cathaoirleach give a guarantee that when the works are completed, the museum will be vacated?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#O00800"><p>That has already been done.  I am not allowing any further debate on the matter.  I took a risk in making a statement.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.47" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#O00900">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#O01000"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, Statute Law Revision Bill 2016 - Order for Second Stage and Second Stage, to be taken at 4 45. p.m. and conclude not later than 6.15 p.m., with the contributions of group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes each and those of all other Senators not to exceed five minutes each and the Minister to be called on to reply to the debate nt later than 6.10 p.m.; and No. 2, Criminal Justice (Suspended Sentences of Imprisonment) Bill 2016 - Order for Second Stage and Second Stage, to be taken at 6.15 p.m., with the contributions of group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes each and those of all other Senators not to exceed five minutes each.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#O01100"><p>If I am not mistaken, we are exactly 40 days from Christmas Day.  In recent days Sr. Stan Kennedy has been quoted as saying it breaks her heart that up to 2,500 children may be homeless on Christmas Day.  This is a real indication of how bad the homeless crisis is.  At a time when they should be happy in their homes and celebrating Christmas, up to 2,500 children will be homeless.  In launching its Christmas appeal last week Focus Ireland stated 2,400 children in 1,200 families were homeless.  This can only be described as an appalling indictment of us as a society.  I am sure many in this Chamber are aware of the death of a homeless 31 year old mother of two, Louise Casey, whose body was found last week under a stairwell in a derelict building.  Unless action is taken quickly, sadly, more children and their families will end up without a roof over their heads and there will be more Louise Caseys losing their lives in this winter period.  As well as her tragic death and the stories of all the children and their families on the streets, others not in such dire circumstances are just about surviving.  The severe lack of rental properties means people are paying huge rents and have little or nothing on which to survive at the end of the month.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Catherine Ardagh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2473"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2473&amp;amp;pid=CatherineArdagh&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> We in Fianna F&aacute;il have advanced several proposals to the Department on a housing rental strategy.  We firmly believe that positive action needs to be urgently taken to alleviate the pressure on people and ensure they avoid a situation where they find themselves homeless.  Most people are only one month away from a situation of homelessness.  One measure we advocate is the introduction of rent certainty regulations that would tie rent to a rental index based on five-year historic rents in each area.</p><p>Rent inflation in Dublin and other cities is hammering disposal income and pushing people into homelessness.  The introduction of a rent certainty regulation would anchor the rent to the locality and would provide some certainty and stability to the market.  In order to comprehensively tackle some of the challenges I have addressed, the supply of rental units in the market must be increased.</p><p>We in Fianna F&aacute;il believe that a range of incentives must be introduced, including, but not limited to, allowing property tax be calculated as a deductible expense for the purpose of income tax, changing the tax code such that accidental landlords who bought property between 2000 and 2009 would be able to offset rental income for a period of three years, directing the strategic investment fund to provide low cost finance to people who will deliver purpose-built rental accommodation and encourage landlords to enter into long-term leases with local authorities and housing associations.</p><p>Census 2016 indicates that there are 260,000 vacant homes across the market accounting for 15% of the total supply.  The vacancy recorded in urban areas such as Dublin and Galway is recorded at 10%.  We need to incentivise landlords to keep the stock on the market and we need to ensure that the threat of homelessness is alleviated for people living in rental accommodation.  I ask the Leader to invite the Minister to come into the House to urgently address this matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#P00200"><p>Today the IRFU released further details of its bid for the Rugby World Cup in 2023.  The Minister of State with responsibility for sport, who was in the House about a half and hour ago, suggested that a Senator might raise this issue.  The Leader was in the House at the time.  Sport plays a critically important part in the health and well-being of citizens.  I mention tourism and the economic prosperity that this would bring.  It is an amazing challenge.  It is also amazing what can be achieved by co-operation between the IRFU and the GAA in terms of the venues.  I mention also the synergies and the co-operation in terms of fostering goodwill.  This could bring many benefits to this nation.</p> <p>There is a long list of capacity and the following venues have been included: Croke Park, the Aviva Stadium, the RDS arena, Nowlan Park, Thomas Park, Fitzgerald Stadium, Pearse Stadium, McHale Park, Casement Park, Kingspan Stadium and Celtic Park.  All those are serious options that would provide stadia for this championship.  It is important this House wishes those involved in this bid well and that Members do everything they can, through their political and sports contacts, to push for this.  Hopefully, we will be successful.  There are two other countries bidding, namely, South Africa and France, but it is a challenging and exciting time.  I know a number of Ministers and senior politicians were in attendance today when this was announced and we should wish them well.  Did we ever think that the GAA and the IRFU would work so successfully together?  It is important that Members of this House wish those involved well in this bid.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#P00300"><p>I dtosach b&aacute;ire, t&aacute; fim&iacute;nteacht Fhianna F&aacute;il maidir le c&uacute;rsa&iacute; tith&iacute;ochta dochreidte ar maidin i nd&aacute;ir&iacute;re.  The hypocrisy of a Fianna F&aacute;il Senator standing up to call for rent certainty when only a few weeks ago its Members voted down a Bill that would bring in rent certainty is unbelievable, but that from Fianna F&aacute;il does not surprise us.</p> <p>On a different matter, I welcome to the Gallery Harriett Bruce, her mother, her aunt and former Ballinasloe town councillor, Johnny Walsh.  The only person missing from the picture is Harriett's husband, Kleber Medeiros, whose case I have raised previously in the House.  Harriett and Kleber were married lawfully.  A spurious allegation was made against them that their marriage was a sham marriage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#P00400"><p>Disgraceful.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#P00500"><p>It was an absolute disgrace.  On foot of that, Kleber was taken from his home and deported to Brazil.  Harriett returned recently from Brazil where she spent a number of weeks with Kleber.  The ongoing scandal is that even though the Health Service Executive has now admitted that there was no reason to block the marriage, that the marriage was lawful and that there was no impediment, Kleber Medeiros still has not been allowed to return home to his wife, his home and his job.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2363"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2363&amp;amp;pid=TrevorOClochartaigh&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Kleber Medeiros has still has not been allowed to return home to his wife, home and job.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#Q00200"><p>The HSE should pay.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#Q00300"><p>Do I understand that the Senator has submitted this for Commencement Matters tomorrow?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#Q00400"><p>No.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#Q00500"><p>There is a meeting in the audiovisual room.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#Q00600"><p>I was going to see if it was an appropriate matter for a Commencement debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#Q00700"><p>Absolutely.  If the Cathaoirleach wants me to submit it, I will.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#Q00800"><p>The Senator cannot have two voices so I will allow the Senator to continue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#Q00900"><p>Go raibh m&iacute;le maith agat, a Chathaoirligh.  In fairness, there have been efforts across these Houses involving politicians from all political parties.  I thank Senator Maura Hopkins, who today accepted from Harriett Bruce a letter for the T&aacute;naiste and Taoiseach .  The Senator has been working on this case, as has Deputy Eugene Murphy, Senator Denis Landy, Deputy Anne Rabbitte and others.</p> <p>Harriett and Kleber have a very bona fide case.  The issue at present, however, is that the Minister is still sitting on the application for Kleber to return home.  I ask the Leader to use his good offices to contact the offices of the Minister and Taoiseach to try to have Kleber's application to return home before Christmas expedited so he can be brought home to his wife.  I call on all Senators to join us in the audiovisual room as soon as possible after the Order of Business to listen to Harriett telling her own story, giving the background and explaining the legal position in which she has found herself and the nightmare she has faced over recent months.  T&aacute; s&uacute;il agam go mbeidh siad in ann br&uacute; a chur ar oifig an T&aacute;naiste agus oifig an Taoisigh leis an &eacute;ag&oacute;ir ioml&aacute;n seo a chur ina cheart ar&iacute;s.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1408" speakername="Frances Black" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#Q01000"><p>I want to talk a little about recognising Traveller ethnicity.  Last Wednesday morning at a meeting of the Joint Committee on Justice and Equality, we heard a presentation on recognising Traveller ethnicity from a group of people who work in and are part of the Traveller community.  Ms Ronnie Fay, Mr. Martin Collins, Mr. Thomas McCann and Dr. Robbie McVeigh gave a powerful presentation.  It is time we all realised that recognising Traveller ethnicity means recognising that Travellers experience racism and discrimination.  It is only by fully recognising the problem that we can work towards a solution.  The dominant view on Travellers in Ireland has been that they are some sort of deviant settled people.  The solution to the Traveller problem has been to try to turn Travellers back into settled people.  In other words, it is contended that if Travellers are not part of a distinct community, they should be treated the same as the general population and assimilated into it.  By doing so, however, their specific needs will not been met.  They become invisible to policymakers and service providers, and the community suffers.  The idea has always been rejected by Travellers themselves since it involves faulty analysis that has never worked.  Despite the prevailing policies and strategies, Travellers have not disappeared and remain as much Travellers as ever before.  Not including Travellers' needs, however, has resulted in very poor living conditions for them.  Some 800 families live at the side of the road with no running water or sanitation.  There are low outcomes in education.  Some 55% of Travellers leave school before the age of 15 and only 1% of them attain a third level qualification.  Long-term unemployment-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#Q01100"><p>Is the Senator calling for a debate?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1408" speakername="Frances Black" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#Q01200"><p>No.  I really just want to highlight this issue.  It is absolutely vital.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#Q01300"><p>I wish to point out, in a nice way, that it is not allowed on the Order of Business to make statements on issues.  One either calls for a debate or raises something.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1408" speakername="Frances Black" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#Q01400"><p>I call for a debate, if that is what the Chair is proposing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#Q01500"><p>No.  What I am saying is that it is not appropriate to read statements on the Order of Business.  That is in the rules of the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1408" speakername="Frances Black" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#Q01600"><p>I just want to highlight the issues that the Travellers have come up against.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#Q01700"><p>I am just suggesting it might be appropriate for the Senator to call for a debate on the issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1408" speakername="Frances Black" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#Q01800"><p>I call for a debate on the issue but I would also like to say I believe it is time that we started to recognise the circumstances of Travellers.  It is an absolute disgrace that they are treated with such little dignity and respect as human beings in this country.  Traveller ethnicity has already been recognised in the North and the rest of the United Kingdom.  I do not know why it is not recognised here in the Republic.  I would like a debate on this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#Q01900"><p>I support Senator Black's call for a debate on the recognition of Traveller ethnicity.  The previous justice committee, on which the Cathaoirleach sat with me, Senator Mac Lochlainn and others, recommended unanimously that Traveller ethnicity be recognised.  It is important and timely to have the debate.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Ivana Bacik:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2248"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2248&amp;amp;pid=IvanaBacik&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I welcome Harriett Bruce and former Labour Party councillor Johnny Walsh, who were in the Gallery a moment ago and who Senator Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh mentioned.  Senator Denis Landy and others have been working with them and they were here today to meet the Labour Party leader, Deputy Brendan Howlin, who has also taken up their case and the issue of the deportation already mentioned.  There will be a briefing in the AV room at 4 p.m., which I know all colleagues will be interested in attending.</p><p>I also welcome the Cathaoirleach's clarification in respect of the move to the National Museum, especially in light of all of the concerns expressed to us.  It is welcome to hear an agreement has been concluded.</p><p>I thank colleagues for their support on a cross-party basis for the passing of the Competition (Amendment) Bill 2016 last Thursday.  We should note the historic achievement that this was the first Private Members' Bill to pass either House of the Oireachtas under the current Government.  That was a good day for the Seanad, being the first House to pass a Private Members' Bill in full.  Will the Leader ensure it receives a speedy passage through the D&aacute;il?  I certainly will be doing what I can to ensure that also.</p><p>I also ask colleagues for their support for the other Bill the Labour Party is introducing on Second Stage tomorrow, the Protection of Employment (Uncertain Hours) Bill 2016.  We see it as an important component of a package of measures to protect workers' rights.  Just as our Bill last week will allow freelance workers to have collective bargaining rights, tomorrow's Bill will ensure protections for those on uncertain hours or so-called flexible contracts.</p><p>Will the Leader organise a debate on domestic violence and law reform to provide for greater protection for victims and survivors of domestic violence?  Could we have the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Justice and Equality provide to the House the timeframe for legislation on domestic violence?  I was privileged to attend and speak at a SAFE Ireland summit organised yesterday and today in the Mansion House in Dublin, at which we heard speakers with international profiles on domestic and gender-based violence on the need to ensure greater protections for victims and survivors.  Some powerful testimonies were also given.  Will the Leader organise such a debate?  The Seanad has led on this and there have been justice committee reports before.  We do, however, now need legislative reform in this area.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#R00200"><p>I also join with Senator Victor Boyhan in welcoming today's launch of the 2023 bid for the Rugby World Cup for Ireland.  We are experiencing a rich vein of and a golden era for sport in Ireland at local, national and international level.  We have seen this in rugby, soccer, GAA, rowing, sailing, and newer sports.  Last week, I visited the new upgraded sports campus in Abbotstown.  The facilities there are wonderful.</p> <p>Sport has a tremendous capacity to unite people.  I compliment all the stakeholders involved in this bid for the Rugby World Cup.  The Government, the Stormont Administration, the GAA and the IRFU are coming together to back it, headed up by the former T&aacute;naiste, Dick Spring, as well as many others, including Hugo MacNeill.  It shows sport has an ability to unite in a way that politics sometimes struggles with.  Will the Leader invite to the House the Minister of State with responsibility for tourism and sport, Deputy Patrick O'Donovan, who today announced a new round of sports capital funding to be open in January, to explain the timeline for this bid as it goes along?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#R00300"><p>I want to raise the issue of broadband provision in rural areas and the great urban-rural divide that exists in this respect.  A report issued today by <i>Switcher.ie</i>, a price comparison website, shows broadband speeds in rural Ireland are 36 times slower than in towns and cities.  This is a serious issue.  Longford and Monaghan, to name but a few, were listed as black spots.</p><p>To give a practical example of this divide, downloading a two-hour film in Dublin would take approximately six minutes, whereas it could take two and a half hours in Monaghan.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Robbie Gallagher:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2471"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2471&amp;amp;pid=RobbieGallagher&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->That gives an example of the challenges that businesses and individuals face every day.  The sad thing is that the gap is getting bigger.  A quarter of households have broadband speeds of less than the Government's guidelines.</p><p>We have been told that the broadband issue will be fully solved by 2020 or 2022, which is little consolation for businesspeople and families in rural areas.  The biggest obstacle to job creation in rural areas is lack of access to broadband.  I plead with the Leader to ask the Minister to come to the House to address this serious issue so that rather than having to pack their suitcases to leave, people will find a future for themselves and their families in rural Ireland where they can grow up and live and work for as long as they wish.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#S00200"><p>I support Senator Bacik's call for the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Justice and Equality to come to the House to discuss legislation on domestic violence.  I commend Safe Ireland and the other organisations that organised the conference on domestic violence but unfortunately I could not attend.  It would be timely for the T&aacute;naiste to come here as we come up to the 15 days of action opposing violence against women.</p><p>Today we have seen another report on the lack of broadband in rural areas.  The report by the comparison website, <i>switcher.ie</i>, has confirmed what many of us who live and work in rural areas have known for a long time, namely, that broadband coverage and connection speeds are wholly inadequate in rural areas.  Drimnagh in Dublin has a connection speed that was up to 36 times faster than that in rural areas.  The national broadband plan was launched in 2012.  Recently we learned that the procurement contract will not be signed until 2017.  However, the Minister recently failed to confirm the 2017 date, meaning that the completion date may now be put back to 2022.  Every delay in the roll-out of the plan prevents small businesses from setting up or expanding and denies real people opportunities.</p><p>To concentrate the wonderful minds in the Fine Gael-Fianna F&aacute;il Government, it is now time for businesses that do not have the minimum 100 Mbps to get an exemption from paying rates.  The economic apartheid caused by leaving whole swathes of Ireland, including small towns, without this essential means of communication is devastating.  In my case it takes the best part of six months to secure even the basic communication tools from my Mayo office.</p><p>The severe social exclusion imposed on individuals, families and communities as a result of not having adequate broadband is intolerable.  Government services and information are blocked from reaching the population of rural areas because they cannot access the Internet.  It means that people cannot reliably access online banking or pay bills online.  This is important in a climate where many utilities have almost entirely switched to online payment systems.</p><p>We want immediate action on rural broadband.  We need the national broadband plan to be commenced urgently.  It should start at the remotest rural areas and work towards the towns.  I call for an urgent debate on the issue of social and economic apartheid as a result of the deprivation caused by inadequate broadband speeds in rural areas.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#S00300"><p>I join Senators Gallagher and Conway-Walsh in addressing the broadband question.  Some Senators may have heard on "Today with Se&aacute;n O'Rourke" a businessperson from Keenagh in County Longford moving out of their current premises and moving very significant jobs from the village of Keenagh owing to the absence of broadband.  In Cavan and Monaghan there are villages and whole tracts without adequate broadband.  I propose to the Leader that we should have a constant monitoring of this.  It is one of the most current and immediate issues we face.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Joe O'Reilly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1610"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1610&amp;amp;pid=JoeOReilly&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We should debate it regularly as a stock-take, so to speak, and invite the relevant people to discuss it.  Will the Leader arrange for this soon?</p><p>I have constantly raised the need for the decentralisation of jobs and a regionalisation of inward investment.  The only silver lining to the Brexit dark cloud is that we can now do that, but only if all rural areas have broadband.  We must bring high-speed broadband to all towns and villages.  It is the country's starkest infrastructural deficit at the moment.  Will the Cathaoirleach and the Leader ensure that it is placed at the top of the agenda?  We discuss Seanad reform constantly, but what people really want is Seanad relevance, and nothing could be more relevant than addressing this great deficit.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1404" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#T00200"><p>Will the Leader call on the Minister for Health - perhaps it is the Minister of State with responsibility for drugs, although I believe it is the former - to attend the House to debate methadone protocol and the General Medical Services, GMS, contracts?  In places around Ireland, for example, Newbridge in County Kildare, there is an 18-month waiting list for a methadone service.  The farther one goes from Dublin, the more difficult it becomes to get into a methadone programme.  General practitioners, GPs, refuse their patients what is viewed as a medical intervention.  If we were to change GMS contracts so that doctors could not refuse to prescribe their patients methadone, it would reduce the waiting list because more stable clients could be moved from clinics and back to their GPs while the more chaotic heroin users who are only starting their treatments could be moved to the clinics.  People are dying while on waiting lists, but the lists could be squashed.  I would like to be given the chance to discuss this matter with the Minister so that we might get people off heroin and onto methadone programmes in rural Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#T00300"><p>I congratulate Senator Feighan on the birth of his new baby girl, Francesca, on Saturday, 12 November.  It happened to be my birthday, so it was a particularly good day as far as I was concerned.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#T00400"><p>I am not sure that congratulations are in order, but the Senator has given them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#T00500"><p>I have.  I asked whether it was in order because we had congratulated someone on getting married.  I did not realise that this matter was not, so apologies if that is the case.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#T00600"><p>We must comply with protocol and decorum in the House.  I am sure that the Senator has a question to ask.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#T00700"><p>I have another couple of points.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#T00800"><p>No civilities in here, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#T00900"><p>I agree on the point about broadband.  I was the chair of the regional assembly at one stage.  It had 53 members right across from Fingal to Clare and covered the southern and eastern parts of the country.  During one debate on broadband, half of the room said nothing and the other half was incredibly agitated.  One half took broadband for granted because its service was perfectly fine, but not so for the other half.  We must view broadband like electricity.  It must be the same, it must be good quality and it must be available everywhere.  It would change a significant number of people's lives.</p> <p>Perhaps my next point is not in order either, but I attended a function yesterday evening commemorating 20 years of the Islamic Cultural Centre of Ireland, which was opened on 14 November 1996 by the then President, Ms Mary Robinson.  A beautiful function was held.  Representatives of the al-Maktoum family, which funded the centre originally, visited from the United Arab Emirates.  Archbishop Martin was present, as were an Assistant Garda Commissioner and other significant dignitaries.  It was a wonderful celebration of 20 years of that institution in Irish public life.  It has made a great contribution to Irish life and the House should congratulate it.  The centre is holding an exhibition week for ten weeks starting today.  I advise Senators and anyone in the area to visit Clonskeagh and see the contribution that culture has made to Ireland and the world.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#T01000"><p>I pay tribute to everyone involved in the 2016 Remembrance Day ceremonies in Northern Ireland and the Republic to commemorate those soldiers who fought in the First World War.  Some 9 million soldiers and 7 million civilians lost their lives in the four-year war.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Michelle Mulherin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2309"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2309&amp;amp;pid=MichelleMulherin&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This is a stark reminder of the personal price paid and ultimate sacrifice made by individuals and families.  As 49,500 of those killed on the battlegrounds of Europe were Irish men, the loss was deeply felt across Ireland, not just in the United Kingdom.  It also serves as a reminder to us that the seeds of division in the future are sown when a war is entered and the Great War was supposed to be the war to end all wars.  There had never before been a war of its type in terms trench warfare and people being slaughtered on battlefields.  The treaty the arose from the First World War was a significant contributory factor to the Second World War.  The commemorative events should serve to strengthen our resolve to ensure war will not be seen as the way forward.  </p><p>Will the Leader raise with the Minister for Arts, Heritage, Regional, Rural and Gaeltacht Affairs, Deputy Heather Humphreys, the possibility of directing decade of centenaries funding towards local communities for the erection of monuments to people from the locality killed in the First World War?  I pay tribute to the many communities throughout the country who have held such ceremonies.  A total of 154 people from Ballina and the surrounding area lost their lives during the First World War.  There were many casualties in the Connacht Rangers.  My point is that up to now most of the commemorative ceremonies have been held in Dublin and elsewhere in Europe.  While I understand the reason for this, there is need for recognition of all of the communities that were affected and paid a price and which up to now have been written out of history.  As I said, a commemorative ceremony was held in Ballina, but many people from Foxford and other towns in the west also lost their lives.  I ask the Leader to bring this matter to the attention of the Minister to ensure proper recognition of the totality of Irish people who died in the First World War.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#U00200"><p>I am sure everyone was taken aback this morning when he or she saw the ice sculptures on display outside Leinster House.  They really brought home the fact that our planet was melting.  This morning I also attended a briefing in Buswells Hotel organised by the Stop Climate Chaos group.  It was an eye-opener.  The format was great in that Deputies and Senators from particular electoral areas were asked to sit with constituents from them.  This led to the formation of small intimate groups which allowed people to be educated a lot easier and quicker.  The United Nations' report which was published yesterday declared 2016 to be the hottest year on record.  Despite the belief of some Independent Members of the Oireachtas and triumphalist leaders worldwide, we all have to face up to the fact that we are damaging our future and that of our children and generations to come through our selfish behaviour.  We need to act.  Climate change has massive repercussions for the world.  The Stop Climate Chaos group has made three recommendations, including that a fair payment be introduced in the case of solar power, with supplies produced by households and businesses in excess of what they need being returned to the national grid at a price that benefits the owner; that taxpayers' money be divested from the use of fossil fuels and that there be increased investment in cycling initiatives and the use of clean public transport.  We need to be forward-thinking.  On the massive housing programme required, we all hope the State will ensure green planning will play its part to ensure energy efficient buildings will become the norm.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator M&aacute;ire Devine:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2468"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2468&amp;amp;pid=MaireDevine&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Communities need to be supported through green planning and the building of efficient, green transport systems.  This issue crosses almost every Department and I call on the lead Department of Housing, Planning, Community and Local Government to climate proof everything the Government does, across all areas.</p><p>It is simply unforgivable that the Government is investing taxpayers' money, through the Ireland Strategic Investment Fund, in harmful fossil fuel industries which we know are destroying our world.  Like the plastic bag tax and the smoking ban, this is an area in which we can lead by example and protect our homes and our planet.  Ireland is known as the emerald isle, the country of 40 shades of green; let us have a green economy and environment to match.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1423" speakername="Ray Butler" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#V00200"><p>I would like to follow up on Senator Mulherin's comments on the Great War memorial events that were held all over the country last weekend.  It was fantastic to see the Taoiseach attend an event in Northern Ireland.  I would also like to congratulate the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade, Deputy Charlie Flanagan, for remembering the French people who lost their lives in Paris one year ago.</p> <p>I was in Trim, County Meath, laying a wreath on behalf of the Taoiseach and the people of Ireland.  I would like to thank the Trim commemorative committee for its wonderful work and the other committees all over the country.  We have come a long way in this country in remembering our war dead.  I echo Senator Mulherin's comments about funding for the commemorative committees which are operating with very small budgets.  It would be great to see some funding being made available to them.  </p> <p>When I was growing up in the 1970s and 1980s my family had a supermarket in Kells.  There was a photograph of my great uncle, Peter Laffey, on the wall of the mineral shed because my parents were afraid to display it in our house.  As the song goes, "In an old photograph, torn battered and stained, and faded to yellow in a brown leather frame".  He was 25 when he died in France and I was honoured to honour him on Sunday as well as all of the other Irish men and women who lost their lives in the two world wars.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#V00300"><p>I would be very grateful if the Minister for Education and Skills would come into the House to address a particular injustice being inflicted on teachers who are not members of any trade union but who are being subjected to the financial emergency measures in the public interest, FEMPI, legislation.  I have been contacted by one such teacher in a designated community college who is not a member of any trade union.  This individual, like many other teachers, continues to engage in supervision and substitution duties and to complete the additional hours required under the Croke Park agreement.  However, like approximately 1,000 other teachers, this person is being financially penalised every month because he is not a member of a trade union.</p> <p>When the Department of Education and Skills went to apply the FEMPI penalties to members of the Association of Secondary Teachers of Ireland, ASTI, it did not consider that it was allowed, under data protection legislation, to access information about which teachers are members of the ASTI, even though the Department would have such information for payroll purposes to allow for the deduction of ASTI dues and so forth.  Therefore, the Department decided to ask teachers in designated community colleges, for example, who were members of the TUI, to identify themselves as such to the education and training boards or to the Department itself so that the benefits of the Lansdowne Road agreement could be applied to them.  Any teacher who did not indicate that he or she was a member of the TUI was treated as not subscribing to the terms and conditions of the Lansdowne Road agreement and faced the penalties of the FEMPI legislation.  This is simply unjust.  It seems to me that there are constitutional issues involved here when one considers that one has a right to associate and indeed, not to associate or be a member of a trade union.  For teachers not to have been given the opportunity to opt out of the FEMPI legislation simply because they were not members of a designated union is, quite frankly, invidious.  </p> <p>I have been in touch with the Department about this and I got what I can only describe as a Sir Humphrey-type response to the effect that there is no proposal at this time to treat teachers separately based on the fact that they are not members of a trade union.  That answer is simply not good enough.  We are talking here about teachers who did not want to be precluded from enjoying the benefits of the Lansdowne Road agreement, who carry out their substitution and supervision duties but who, because they do not fit the Department's easy model and are not in a particular trade union, have been denied their rights.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2250"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2250&amp;amp;pid=RonanMullen&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This is a serious matter.  I call on the Minister for Education and Skills to come to the House to explain the position and, more important, to set out what the Department proposes to do to rectify this injustice.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#W00200"><p>I support the call made by Senators Black and Bacik on Traveller ethnicity.  The debate on this issue is critical and badly needed for all the reasons the Senators outlined.  It is an issue to which I will return in the coming period when, I hope, the Minister appears in the House to have this debate for the reasons eloquently outlined.</p> <p>It is important, given the week that was in it, that a number of Senators reflected on remembrance and it is right that we remember.  We are in a climate of great maturity about how we approach this issue, North and South and between Britain and Ireland.  I am proud that republican leaders have played a key role in reconciliation and engagement with those on this island who come from a British and Unionist tradition and have such a stake in the issue of remembrance, particularly around the First World War.  The Seanad should examine how we can contribute positively to this theme.</p> <p>Notwithstanding this, I urge caution because remembrance is a complex issue which gives rise to much hurt.  If it was solely concerned with the tragic and unnecessary slaughter of the First World War, it would be a straightforward matter.  As I stated, however, the issue is much more complex than that.  The legacy of the British army and British presence is still felt acutely and with great rawness.  While we can and should discuss this theme, the debate must be broader and include the legacy of conflict that persists to this day.  For example, the issues of justice and truth recovery are being hindered by a British Government which seeks to use national security to veto progress on matters such as the Dublin and Monaghan bombings in which the British army and its intelligence services were up to their necks.  Let us have a debate and let us remember and reflect responsibly on the loss to this island.  There is a serious sense of self-loathing in evidence when calls are made to the Minister to erect memorials to British soldiers while, at the same time, Moore Street lies in rack and ruin.  We need to take a universal and inclusive approach to this issue, one which reflects all traditions and experiences.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#W00300"><p>In the past four or five years, I have raised many issues related to junior doctors about which an issue has arisen in recent days.  One of the concerns I raised previously was the withdrawal of education grants.  A large number of junior doctors are on training programmes.  It is important that they have available to them a clear career path in order that they can see where they will be in five, six, eight or ten years.</p> <p>Junior doctors are constantly attending courses and conferences to acquire new skills but many of the grants available to them previously have been withdrawn.  I understand this issue forms part of the ongoing negotiations between the Department and the Irish Medical Organisation, which unfortunately are not making progress.  The Minister should come to the House to set out his proposals for dealing with the issue of junior doctors over the next 12 months.  Some 38% of doctors working here did not graduate in Ireland.  We are losing a large number of good doctors to other jurisdictions and they will not return.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Colm Burke:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2353"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2353&amp;amp;pid=ColmBurke&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We need to set out a clear path on how to deal with this issue.  I ask that the Minister come into the House to set out how he proposes to deal with the exodus of so many graduates from the State, especially when one considers the &euro;90 million per annum the State spends on medical education.  Within a very short period of time some 50% to 60% of the money invested by us has disappeared out of the State.  It is something we need to deal with.  I wish to mention one other issue-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#X00200"><p>The Senator is over his time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#X00300"><p>Could I just mention one issue?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#X00400"><p>If I allow Senator Burke in when I am trying to stick to two minutes the Senator must be very brief.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#X00500"><p>With regard to the broadband issue, we are losing sight of an important point.  The State has set out clear guidelines on planning applications for development; there must be access to roads, water and sewage services.  We have not made it a planning condition that there must be access to broadband services and it is now a key ingredient in any housing development.  It should now be part of the planning process.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#X00600"><p>I remind Senators that as second speakers they are entitled to two minutes in which time they can raise one item.  This is clearly indicated in the Standing Orders but some Senators take advantage.  I try to be fair to everyone.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#X00700"><p>I wish to speak on an issue which I previously raised in 2013 around the use of old telephone boxes as locations for defibrillators that would be easily identifiable in a town or a city.  I want to congratulate the Heart of Killarney project which has actually reconstructed a telephone box and installed a defibrillator.  It would be a really good idea to replicate this around the State.  Unfortunately, since I raised this matter initially - and I had done quite a bit of work on the proposal at the time - many of the telephone boxes have been destroyed.  Local authorities do not always know what to do with unused telephone boxes and this would be a really good use.  They could be constructed at a relatively cheap cost.  I am sure they would be easy to design and construct.  It would mean there would be 24 hour access to a defibrillator by way of calling the emergency services so a person could be allowed access outside of nine to five hours.  People might say that the place for the defibrillators is on GAA premises but they also need to be in other areas.  It would be a really good idea and it is linked to the issue of technology and broadband which, I suppose, is part of the reason telephone boxes have become obsolete.  </p> <p>I join with Senators Rose Conway-Walsh, Colm Burke and Joe O'Reilly who raised the broadband issue.  I was shocked to hear the statistics and the fact that there are some serious black spots around the State.  Children in rural communities are being denied access to vital online mental health services and so on.  I like Senator Burke's idea that broadband provision be included in planning permissions because it is a basic, fundamental necessity that we have broadband throughout the State.  As Senator Joe O'Reilly has said, we need to get the matter to the top of the agenda.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#X00800"><p>I thank the 18 senators who made contributions to the Order of Business the afternoon.  I will begin with Senator Ardagh's contribution on housing.  All of us involved in politics recognise the importance of the Government's strategy around housing and the priority the Government has given to the issue of homelessness and getting people out of emergency shelters, especially young children and young families.  The Minister for Housing, Planning, Community and Local Government, Deputy Coveney has been in the House repeatedly, and will be again tomorrow, to discuss expediting the infrastructure around housing supply.  It is a legacy issue on which the Government is working but we all agree that the action plan for housing and homelessness has ambitious targets to deliver residential homes.  We need to start building houses and we need to start creating supply.  The Government has made a number of changes and they will be outlined again by the Minister in the House tomorrow.  We must support him in that and acknowledge the work he has been doing as Minister with the action plan for housing.</p> <p>Senators Boyhan and O'Mahony raised the Rugby World Cup.  It is important to congratulate and salute the IRFU on this very ambitious bid to host the Rugby World Cup in 2023.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It would be of huge economic importance to the country and a massive fillip to our tourism industry.  It would certainly be of added importance to us in terms of our sporting prowess as a nation throughout the world.  It will not be easy to secure the hosting of the Rugby World Cup.  It will require all of us, if I may, to stand shoulder to shoulder, to unite both North and South and to bring together all sporting codes that have the capacity in terms of their stadia to host matches and to be part of the bid.  I wish the IRFU well.  The Taoiseach and many Ministers were at the launch this morning.  We should all stand together to see this delivered.  It is of absolutely importance for us.  The hashtag #SupportTheBid has already been started.  We should all support the bid.</p><p>Senator Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh raised the issue of Harriett Bruce and her husband.  I expect the Minister is aware of the facts.  It is a matter for the Minister.  The briefing this afternoon by Senator &Oacute; Clochartaigh is welcome.  Arising from it and his contribution today, the Minister could look at the case again.</p><p>Senators Frances Black, Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile and Ivana Bacik raised the issue of Traveller ethnicity.  The Minister of State, Deputy David Stanton, is committed to the implementation of the national Traveller and Roma inclusion strategy.  This will be done on an interdepartmental basis and will encompass cultural identity, education and housing.  The closing date for submissions on the strategy was 30 September.  The Minister of State is committed to reverting to the House on the issue.  I commend Senator Black on her work on Traveller ethnicity.  We will have a further debate on it.</p><p>Senators Bacik and Rose Conway-Walsh raised the issue of domestic violence.  This is a matter of huge concern.  One in four women suffer physical domestic violence or abuse in the country and one in two are sexually harassed.  Those figures are far too high.  It is not acceptable.  All of us involved in politics and civic life, along with different organisations, must work together to ensure we end this scourge in our society.  I commend the SAFE Ireland conference that was attended by 35 global leaders yesterday.  That it was so attended speaks volumes about the importance of the issue and the scourge that it is in society.</p><p>The T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Frances Fitzgerald, is committed to the domestic violence Bill, which, as she stated at the conference, will put domestic violence at the centre of our justice system.  It is important to acknowledge that we can all play a role in ensuring we treat people with respect and that language does matter.  Whether it is that of the President of the United States of America or that of a teenager in school, our language and behaviour is important.  We must send a positive signal to women of all ages and young girls, in particular, that they are to be respected and can live their lives without fear of any type of abuse.  This applies to everyone from the leader of the free world to the youngest person in our society.  </p><p>Broadband was mentioned by Senators Robbie Gallagher, Rose Conway-Walsh, Joe Reilly, Gerry Horkan, Colm Burke and Catherine Noone.  I agree fully with Senator Burke on the absolute importance of broadband to attracting and locating industry in rural Ireland.  This should form part of planning criteria.  Planning officials, in tandem with suppliers of broadband, should ensure that broadband is available to those in rural Ireland.  Senator Horkan is correct that many of us in urban areas take it for granted.  However, when we go beyond the Pale, as we did in the Seanad campaign, and visit other parts of the country, we see that telephone connectivity dips.  This happens even on the Cork-Dublin motorway.  The same applies to broadband.</p><p>The Minister for Communications, Climate Action and Environment, Deputy Denis Naughten, is committed to the national broadband strategy and to increasing the service to 1,000 Mbps per home and premises in rural Ireland.  Its roll-out will begin shortly with the majority of it being done prior to 2018.  It is important to recognise that there will be issues with regard to some of the more rural and isolated communities but there must be a process in which we can roll out broadband to the majority of the country.  All of us agree that broadband is currently a missing part of the infrastructure that is necessary to attract people economically to locate in the country and to allow people to stay and live in their own communities.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The Minister is committed to that.  We have a national broadband strategy which the Minister is anxious to see introduced.  The survey Senators mentioned was conducted over a 12-month period from July or August 2016.  It shows improvements in broadband speeds and reflects investment by the telecoms industry in upgrading the network over the past four years.  However, we all agree that there is a digital divide and there are certain parts of the country that cannot access high-speed broadband, which is unacceptable.  The Minister and the Government are committed to incentivising and accelerating the use of broadband through the national broadband strategy and plan.  I would be happy for the Minister to come before the House again to discuss the matter.</p><p>Senator Ruane raised the issue of drugs.  I would be happy for the Minister of State, Deputy Byrne, to come before the House to discuss the issue.  </p><p>Senator Harkin referred to the Islamic Cultural Centre and congratulated it on its anniversary.  It is important that we build an inclusive society which respects people of all faiths and none.  I very much welcome the celebration.  I join with the Senator in congratulating Senator Feighan and his wife, Elaine, on the birth of Francesca.</p><p>Senators Mulherin and &Oacute; Domhnaill referred to the commemoration day.  I will not get into a war of words with Senator &Oacute; Domhnaill because we can all remember the legacy of violence on our island.  Many of us wish that blight had not affected the legacy that has been left by the Troubles.  It would be disingenuous to do what he said in his remarks.  Senators Mulherin and Butler referred specifically to the commemoration and remembrance day last Sunday.  The men and women of our country fought and should be recognised.  There is a national commemoration day in July, which we all attend.  We are proud to support the men and women of our Defence Forces who represent us most admirably across the world in many troubled areas.  It would be unfair and wrong to associate last Sunday with particular issues North and South.  I understand the day is about the commemoration of those of Irish descent who served.  I welcome that the Taoiseach laid a wreath at Enniskillen.  Senator Mulherin's suggestion regarding centenary funding should be considered as a way to acknowledge those who have died from around the country.</p><p>Senator Devine raised the very important issue of climate change and referred to ice sculptures outside the Houses today.  Unfortunately, I was not able to attend the briefing.  The Minister of State, Deputy Naughten, will be in Morocco tomorrow to address the UN's COP22 meeting.  He will reaffirm our position that we must, as a nation, individually and collectively, take responsibility for tackling climate change.  We owe it to future generations to do so.  Like Senator Devine, unlike some in the other House, I do not believe that this is an act of God.  It is not.  We all have a duty of care to the Earth and are stewards of its creation, and must make the Earth we inhabit better, not just for ourselves but for future generations.  Tomorrow, the Minister of State will speak about our commitment to becoming a low-carbon economy and having a consultation process for a national plan to mitigate the effects of climate change, building on the Paris agreement from last year.  It is important that we put that on the agenda and I am happy for the Minister of State to come before the House, following his visit to Marrakesh, to have a debate.</p><p>Senator Mullen referred to non-union members.  It is predominantly a matter for the Minister for Education and Skills.  At the risk of upsetting the Senator, perhaps he could table a Commencement matter.  As a former active member of the ASTI, I suggest that the teachers involved might be able to sign the agreement with the Department separately if that is their desire.  We all have to incur the wrath of FEMPI.  If he is willing to provide more information, I would be happy to revert to the Minister.</p><p>Senator Burke referred to junior doctors.  He has been a stalwart in championing their plight.  I hope junior doctors who, through the IMO, are party to the Haddington Road and Lansdowne Road agreements will reflect on that.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The Government is committed to engaging with the INMO on matters regarding junior doctors.  I am a former chairperson of the health committee and we were very proactive in commissioning a report on the working conditions of junior doctors and the relevant European directive.  They are a pivotal part of our health system and they should not be disrespected or undermined in any way.  The living out allowance is under consideration and should be considered in the context of a public sector agreement on pay.  I certainly hope the INMO will engage in further talks with the Department.</p><p>Senator Noone raised an important issue concerning a defibrillator being made available in many parts of the country and I share her view.  I welcome her suggestion that old telephone kiosks be used and we could take this up with the relevant Ministers and Departments.  I will convey to Senator Coghlan her congratulations on the Heart of Killarney project.  I am sure he will be delighted that Senator Noone mentioned Killarney on the Order of Business today.</p><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach for the role he has played in the relocation of the Seanad.  I know he said he would not hold a debate on it but I thank him for the role he has played in shepherding us from this Chamber to the Ceramics Room in the National Museum.  He is right that work on this Chamber is essential.  We will be welcome tenants on a temporary basis.  I hate the use of the term "temporary arrangement" but we have to move and we are conscious that we are using the workspace of the people in the National Museum.  I acknowledge the huge amount of work by all sides in this House, and particularly by the Cathaoirleach.  He has facilitated a briefing tomorrow and it is important we recognise that there are needs on both sides of the compound.  The idea of a forum established by the Ceann Comhairle is one we should all welcome.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.109" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.110" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 4.40 p.m. and resumed at 4.45 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.111" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#CC00100">Statute Law Revision Bill 2016: Order for Second Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.112" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p></p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1380" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#CC00300"><p>I move: "That Second Stage be taken now."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.114" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.115" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#CC00500">Statute Law Revision Bill 2016: Second Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.116" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Question proposed" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#CC00600"><p>  Question proposed: "That the Bill be now read a Second Time."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1264" speakername="Damien English" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#CC00700"><p>It is a pleasure to bring the Statute Law Revision Bill to the House.  Its purpose is to repeal spent and obsolete public general Acts passed between 1922 and 1950.  As the first comprehensive review of Acts passed by the Oireachtas, the Bill will result in a significant reduction in the size of the Statute Book for this period.  In total, some 297 Acts, accounting for 42% of the 707 enforced Acts passed between 1922 and 1950, are proposed for repeal.  </p> <p>The Bill is the latest in a series of measures to be enacted to overhaul the Statute Book.  Previous Statute Law Revision Bills were brought before this House in which they received cross-party support.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Damien English:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1781"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1781&amp;amp;pid=DamienEnglishFG&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The statute law revision programme was initiated in 2003.  It formerly operated within the auspices of the Office of the Attorney General and is now contained in the government reform unit of the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform.  Its purpose is to enhance public accessibility to the Statute Book.  There has been a particular need for such revision in Ireland because our unique legislative past has left us with a complex stock of legislation with enactments from the Parliaments of Ireland, England, Great Britain and the United Kingdom, as well as the Oireachtas.</p><p>The statute law revision programme is already responsible for five distinct but complementary Statute Law Revision Acts between 2005 and 2015.  These have successfully repealed all obsolete primary legislation enacted prior to Independence and, in addition, have revoked all obsolete secondary legislation made up to 1 January 1821.  To date, over 60,000 items of legislation have been either expressly or implicitly repealed under the programme.  This Bill, when enacted, together with the five previous Statute Law Revision Acts, will collectively be the most extensive set of repealing measures in the history of the State and the most extensive set of statute law revision measures ever enacted anywhere in the world.</p><p>The benefits of statute law revision are well documented.  These include the creation of certainty as to which laws remain in force; the modernisation of the Statute Book; the enhancement of public accessibility to the Statute Book; and the codification or consolidation of the statute law of the State.  It is in the public interest to proceed with this Bill in that these proposals will assist in reducing the regulatory burden for business, industry and citizens by simplifying the complex stock of legislation on the Statute Book, as well as helping to provide legal clarity to the area.  The importance of simplifying this complex stock was noted with approval by the OECD review of better regulation in Ireland 2010, which reported that initiatives, such as the Statute Law Revision Acts, were impressive efforts to address the challenge and improve accessibility.  In addition, the programme is a specific element of the public service reform plan 2014 to 2016 and feeds into broader public governance initiatives such as Ireland's participation in the global open government partnership.</p><p>The Statute Law Revision Bill 2016 repeals 297 public general Acts, which, following detailed examination and consultation, have been determined to be spent and obsolete.  The identification and examination of primary legislation has proceeded chronologically and this Bill deals with Acts enacted by the Oireachtas between 1922 and 1950.</p><p>As our decade of centenaries moves closer to the anniversary of the foundation of the State, it is particularly appropriate we are examining and removing some of its earliest legislation that has long since served its purpose.  In doing so, we pave the way for the next 100 years of legislative growth.  The legislation of this period shows our nation in its infancy developing its own legislative framework.  It follows the transition from the Irish Free State to the fully independent Republic of today, while capturing several of the birth pangs felt along the way.  The obsolete Acts listed for repeal include the Public Safety (Emergency Powers) Act 1923, enacted following the outbreak of the Civil War, which granted far-reaching powers and additional offences aimed at ensuring public safety.  It included the imposition of the death penalty or penal servitude for anyone found guilty of an armed revolt against the Government of Saorst&aacute;t &Eacute;ireann or certain associated offences.</p><p>Several Acts are repealed, which amended the now defunct 1922 Constitution of Saorst&aacute;t &Eacute;ireann, including the Constitution (Removal of Oath) Act 1933, which repealed Article 22 of the Free State Constitution, which required Members of the Oireachtas to take an oath declaring their faithfulness to His Majesty, King George V, and his heirs and successors.  The Constitution (Amendment No. 24) Act 1936, which abolished the Senate of Saorst&aacute;t &Eacute;ireann is also repealed.  A new Seanad was, of course, established by the 1937 Constitution.</p><p>Other Acts to be repealed include the League of Nations (Guarantee) Act 1923, which provided for Ireland to join the League of Nations; the Telephone Capital Acts 1924 to 1938, which authorised expenditure of funds to develop the telephone system of the Saorst&aacute;t &Eacute;ireann; and the Emergency Powers Act 1939, which granted wide-ranging powers at the outbreak of World War II, including the power to suspend the operation of any law.</p><p>The Bill has been accompanied by a process of consultation, which included the publication of a draft list of Acts to be repealed on the website of the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform.  All Departments and relevant local authorities were consulted and advised on Acts of relevance to them, as well as given an opportunity to provide observations on the proposed approach to those Acts.</p><p>Section 1 is the central feature of the Bill, providing for the repeal of the 297 Acts listed in the Schedule.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Damien English:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1781"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1781&amp;amp;pid=DamienEnglishFG&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It includes a small number of Acts that were listed for repeal in previous Bills, but the repeal, for a variety of reasons, was never commenced.  Following consultation with officials in the relevant Departments, it was confirmed that these Acts were suitable for repeal and will now be repealed in this Bill.</p><p>The provisions of section 1 depart from the approach that has been taken in the previous four Statute Law Revision Acts.  These earlier Acts would have provided for all statutes within the category of legislation under consideration to be repealed with the exception of the statutes listed in the Schedule to the Act.  This approach was taken for reasons of clarity; these earlier Acts repealed thousands of pieces of legislation, leaving only a handful of statutes in force.  It was reasonable, therefore, to list only the legislation that was being retained on the Statute Book.  In this case, it is more reasonable to list the spent and obsolete Acts in the Schedule and provide for their repeal in the Bill, and that is what we have done in this section.</p><p>Section 2 provides a number of savings clauses.  Section 2(3) provides that the inclusion of an Act in the Schedule shall not be construed as meaning that the Act, or any provision of it, was of full force and effect immediately before the passing of this Act.  Section 3 provides for a Short Title for this Bill when enacted and collective citation for all the Statute Law Revision Acts to date.</p><p>The Schedule lists the specific Acts identified in the course of the review as appropriate for repeal because they have ceased to be relevant or have become unnecessary.</p><p>I wish to outline an amendment to this Bill, which I intend to introduce on Committee Stage.  The old Irish Parliament passed a public Act in 1800 entitled, "An Act for Incorporating the Association for Discountenancing Vice and Promoting the Knowledge and Practice of the Christian Religion".  This association was formed as a voluntary society in 1792.  The Act provided for the incorporation of the association, conferring its rights to purchase and own property, to sue and be sued, to have a common seal as well as other key provisions governing the association, including the right to make by-laws in respect of its internal governance.  This Act was repealed in its entirety by the Statute Law Revision Act 2007.</p><p>It has since come to our attention that this association is still in existence and continues to function.  The association is registered as a charity under the name of the Association for Promoting Christian Knowledge, APCK.  It supports the publication and distribution of religious educational material and provides religious educational support for the Church of Ireland.  We have confirmed that the APCK is one and the same association as the Association for Discountenancing Vice and Promoting the Knowledge of the Christian Religion.  It appears that the organisation has used both names interchangeably throughout the years.  However, the name of the association was not officially changed.  This change of name may explain why there was no connection made between the Association for Discountenancing Vice and Promoting the Knowledge of the Christian Religion and the APCK in the consideration of the repeal for the purposes of the Statute Law Revision Act 2007, despite a widespread campaign of consultation and advertisement in the national press at the time.</p><p>The effect of the repeal is to abolish the association's existence leaving no body or persons who can deal with its affairs or property.  The individual members of the association still exist but they do not have the power to act on behalf of the abolished association to organise its affairs.  It is not clear with whom the former association's rights and obligations, including its property rights, vest.</p><p>It is clear, therefore, that the Act establishing the association was repealed in error by the Oireachtas because the association is, in fact, alive and continues to function.  Had we been aware that this was the case, the Act would never have been repealed.  The legal limbo in which the repeal leaves the association is an unfair and unconstitutional interference in the property rights of the association.  The association is entitled to remain in being according to its 1800 form and, in the circumstances, the association should be reinstated by statute.</p><p>It is proposed, therefore, that the best way to put the association back in the position in which it was prior to the enactment of the 2007 Act would be to repeal the repeal effected by the 2007 Act and to deem it never to have taken effect.  This will ensure that there was no interruption in the life of the association and things done by it between the enactment of the 2007 Act and the new legislation would thus have been validly done.  The Attorney General is satisfied that such a retroactive provision would not be constitutionally objectionable because the Oireachtas would not be declaring any act to be an infringement of the law.  The wording of the proposed amendment to reinstate the association will be tabled on Committee Stage in the Seanad.</p><p>Since the publication of the Bill, we have identified a further four Acts that are suitable for repeal.  It is proposed to add these to the Schedule on Committee Stage.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Damien English:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1781"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1781&amp;amp;pid=DamienEnglishFG&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The Bill is a rather technical piece of legislation but an important and necessary one.  It represents another step in the journey we are on to tidy up and simplify the Irish Statute Book.  The enactment of the legislation will deliver benefits in facilitating the process of public governance reform and in reducing the regulatory burden on businesses and citizens.  It will also ensure that our Statute Book is significantly more modem and will enhance public accessibility to the laws that govern our people as they go about their business in their daily lives.  I commend the Bill to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#FF00200"><p>I welcome the opportunity to speak on this Statute Law Revision Bill 2016.  Fianna F&aacute;il will be supporting the Bill.  It is part of a process to create a modern and streamlined Irish Statute Book which is more accessible to citizens and to businesses.  The process of condensing the Irish Statute Book and making it more relevant and accessible was started in 2005 under a Fianna F&aacute;il-led Government and it will clear away the dead wood of thousands of redundant and obsolete Acts that are clogging the Statute Book.  The Statute Law Revision Acts 2005, 2007, 2009 and 2012 repealed many Acts enacted between 1751 and Irish Independence in 1922.  Previous Acts in this regard have dealt with Acts enacted pre-1922 or pre-Independence.  This Bill focuses on public general Acts enacted between 1922 and 1950.  A total of 1,124 were reviewed and of those, 297 have been selected to be repealed.  Many of the Acts are monotonous and ordinary, but some of them are interesting to note.  Number 33, from 1924 is the Telephone Capital Act 1924, "an Act to grant further money for the development of the telephonic system of Saorst&aacute;t &Eacute;ireann".  Number 7 from 1932 is the Eucharistic Congress (Miscellaneous Provisions ) Act 1932, "an Act to make certain modifications in the law for the purposes of the Eucharistic Congress to be held in the month of June 1932".  Number 1, from 1937, is the Spanish Civil War (Non-intervention) Act 1937, "an Act to carry into execution the international obligations of Saorst&aacute;t &Eacute;ireann in relation to the civil war now being waged in Spain, and to make such provisions as are necessary or expedient for that purpose, and in particular to prohibit citizens of Saorst&aacute;t &Eacute;ireann from participating in that war".  We can see there is quite a lot of legislation that is past its sell-by date at this stage.</p> <p>When Ireland gained independence in 1922, it passed an Act to inherit all laws that had previously applied to the jurisdiction.  This means that many ancient laws, including those passed in Westminster while Ireland was part of the UK, still apply today unless they have been repealed in some way.  The continued presence of redundant legislation is misleading for the user who may believe that it is still relevant and in force by virtue of it simply remaining on the Statute Book.  The user of the Statute Book may have to undertake the time-consuming task of carefully analysing a statute, only to come to the conclusion that it no longer applies.</p> <p>As was noted in previous debates on the subject, it is not appropriate that laws from the pre-Independence era remain in force here indefinitely.  The volume of old legislation is so great that the only way to approach the question of statute law revision is to proceed in stages.  The Statute Law Revision Act 2012 repealed all statutes enacted before Irish Independence on the 6 December 1922, with the exception of statutes specified in Schedule 1 to the Act and to the Statute Law Revision Acts of 2007 and 2009.  Previous phases of the statute law revision project reviewed public general Acts, local and personal Acts up to 1850 and private Acts up to 1750.  This Act complements that process by repealing all local and personal Acts enacted after 1850 and before 6 December 1922 and all private Acts enacted after 1750 and before 6 December 1922, with the exception of a &ldquo;white list&rdquo; of Acts that are specifically preserved.  The Act repealed an estimated 2,900 obsolete Acts enacted between 1751 and Irish Independence in 1922.  The list of Bills covered is fascinating and represents a slice of Irish history in the pre-Independence era.  Examples of the old laws that were repealed are private divorce Acts, designed to dissolve marriages in the days when there was no judicial divorce jurisdiction in Ireland.  The Act also repealed obsolete statutes relating to conferring of citizenship on non-nationals, again dating back to a period where Ministers had no power to confer naturalisation and it had to be carried out by Parliament.  The Act also specified around 790 pieces of old legislation which are still relevant and which are being specifically kept in force, including the Saint Stephen&rsquo;s Green Act 1877, which formally opened Saint Stephen's Green to regulated public use, and which gives the Chief Secretary or Under Secretary to the Lord Lieutenant - now the Minister for Finance - the authority to issue bye-laws relating to its use.</p> <p>As part of the current programme of statute law revision initiated in 2003 - under a previous Fianna F&aacute;il Government - a total of almost 5,000 old Acts have already been eliminated.  One similar previous law, passed in 2005, removed the 700 year obligation for every citizen of Ireland to own a bow and arrow, and to practice archery - but also withdrew the law which abolished pillory, the act of locking someone into stocks so that they could be pelted with tomatoes.  The Adulteration of Tea Act was passed in 1776, two years after the Boston Tea Party which triggered the American revolution.  When this Act was enacted, the total rose to nearly 8,000, which - together with an additional 40,557 Acts - are implicitly repealed by the legislation.  Fianna F&aacute;il will support this Bill as it proceeds through the House and I offer my commendations and recognition to the staff who have worked diligently in bringing the Bill to fruition.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1380" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#FF00300"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House and I welcome this legislation.  We all must welcome anything that makes life easier for the citizen or for the public when accessing legislation.  I congratulate and thank the people in the Departments who have gone through all 297 Acts that are obsolete.  It was a very tedious job to go through all of those pieces of legislation to see that they are not being enacted at the moment.  The Minister of State referred to one particular Act that had been done away with in 2007, it had been brought to the attention of the Department, and it is now going to be restored to the Statute Book.  I welcome this because it shows that the process does work.  Perhaps the Minister of State could clarify when this was brought to the attention of the Department and how long it took to put it back in to focus.  I understand it will not be put back until this legislation is passed but was there any hardship involved for the group that it affected? I presume there are no other pieces of legislation involved in this issue.</p> <p>I welcome the Bill.  It is great for those who are working in the courts and who work on legislation on a daily or weekly basis.  The last time this was done it was one of the biggest pieces of revision of legislation in the world.  I remember when that legislation was passed.  It was very interesting and we went through many of the Acts that were being removed from the Statute Book at the time.  It was greatly appreciated by those in the law business.  More importantly it is to be welcomed for the citizens many of whom, especially people who are retired, go through legislation and they find it very interesting - even if it is not they who are affected - and this is going to make it much easier for them.  When I go through some of the Acts that we are going to repeal with this legislation it is interesting to note that the opening and closing hours of shops and other trades in the Dublin district were covered by law.  Any type of business can choose opening and closing times whenever they want now.  There have been quite a lot of changes since 1922 and since 1950 with regard to many of those laws and with the advent of the Internet.</p> <p>Some of those laws made provision for funding the telephone system in 1923.  We now have a much more advanced world where the Internet is important to every household.  In a short period of time life moves very quickly; from the basic telephone - which very few people had - at that time and the Government making a provision to set up telephone lines to today where we have Wi-Fi and very modern technology.  It is unbelievable what can happen in a short time.</p> <p>I note that in 1937 there was a repeal of legislation with regard to the Clerk of the Seanad.  That piece of legislation, since this House received the confidence of the public, will not need to be used again.</p> <p>I welcome the Bill and I wholeheartedly support it.  It is in the interests of the law and of the public.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#GG00100"><p>I welcome this Bill and commend all the staff behind all the hard work.  Sinn F&eacute;in will be supporting this legislation.  While for some this is a fascinating historical project, I am also sure it was quite a laborious task to go through our Statute Book, assessing what needed to be kept and revoked.  It is important work and I welcome the fact we are, again, updating our Statute Book to ensure it is as relevant and accessible as possible.</p> <p>When one takes a look at the Acts involved, one really gets a sense of the turmoil and chaos this State has been built upon.  We are dealing with Acts between 1920 and 1950, laws passed during times such as our own Civil War, the Spanish Civil War and the Second World War.  It was a time of war and uncertainty, evident in the range of emergency Acts passed during those 30 years which we are now repealing.</p> <p>It is also fascinating to see de Valera's ban on Irish citizens participating in the Spanish Civil War will be repealed.  We should not forgot the decision taken by Eoin O'Duffy's Blueshirt brigade to defy that law and to stand shoulder to shoulder with Franco's fascists, while the Connolly Column, led by Frank Ryan, fought for a republic.  It is a nice little reminder of where some of the parties in this Chamber actually came from and their heritage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1264" speakername="Damien English" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#GG00200"><p>What about the Senator's party's history?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#GG00300"><p>However, while all this work is undoubtedly useful and necessary, is it really that urgent?  Why exactly are we spending our time repealing laws from 90 years ago, Acts that are effectively dead, when there are laws today affecting people's lives that need repealed?  Laws that need to be dealt with are being pushed down the road for six months here and eight months there.  Why is it that 12-month civic committees are being set up to look at laws, while we repeal redundant laws?</p><p>I have a concern about who actually carried out this extensive body of work.  In 2015, the most recent round of this historical project, the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform revealed to us that the State was using people off JobBridge to do the work.  Will the Minister of State clarify if the same system was used to fill these positions?  I have this concern not only because JobBridge was a scandalous scheme whereby workers were exploited by doing a day's work for little over &euro;3 an hour, but also because JobBridge sold itself as an avenue to enter a business and earn oneself a long-term job.  However, on this occasion there was not even a carrot and stick for a sustainable, stable long-term job on offer at the end.  Overall, this was a difficult and onerous job and it should have paid a fair wage to those who were qualified to do the work.</p><p>The Official Report during the passage of the Spanish Civil War (Non-Intervention) Act 1937 makes for fascinating reading.  The Act set out the international obligations of Saorst&aacute;t &Eacute;ireann regarding the civil war waged in Spain and prohibited citizens of Saorst&aacute;t &Eacute;ireann from participating in that war.  The then Deputy, Patrick Belton, the famously anti-communist leader of the Irish Christian Front and who was politically close to Michael Collins, spoke at length on Second Stage, berating the then Government for being allegedly sympathetic to the &quot;Red Government of Spain&quot;, declaring that &quot;99.9 per cent. of the Irish people stand for the recognition of General Franco, and there should be no equivocation about it.&quot;  Although a vocal and forthright supporter of Franco's fascism, he did not support Eoin O'Duffy's Irish brigade participating in anti-communist fighting in the Spanish Civil War, believing its place was better in Ireland to combat any domestic sympathies for socialism or left-wing politics.  He was at pains to point out, however, that he believed that a law preventing Irish Catholics from fighting for Franco was worse than the penal days when Irish Catholics were not prevented from joining European armies to fight for their religion.</p><p>The then Deputy, James Dillon, at the time favoured a policy of non-intervention in Spain because he and his Fine Gael colleagues believed that policy would in the long term contribute to the advantage of General Franco and the Burgos Government.  Interestingly, there were lengthy and substantial attempts during the D&aacute;il debate to defend General Franco from accusations of being a fascist, deeming that to be a slur simply put about by the godless communists.</p><p>These bear thought-provoking parallels to some of the defences of the US President-elect Donald Trump's policies in some mainstream media outlets now.  They would have us believe that his calls for the indiscriminate deportation of minority communities are simply new, sensible and strategic immigration controls, and that accusations of racism are simply lefty histrionics.  The Irish media of the 1930s was similarly pro-Franco.  The year before the passing of that Act in 1936, <i>The Times</i>judged the Spanish Civil War as being irrelevant to modern Europe.  Clearly, this was incorrect given that it is recognised by many as the beginning of a war against fascism within Europe, leaving open to severe criticism the many states which stood aside while a group of fascists overthrew an elected government.</p><p>That said, it was stated during the debate on the Spanish Civil War (Non-Intervention) Act 1937 that were Irish people to go and fight in Spain, the majority would have been on the Franco side.  Despite the high regard in which we hold the members of the Irish International Brigade of the Connolly Column these days, this is actually correct.  That is not to say that, while we are in the business of repealing the Spanish Civil War (Non-Intervention) Act 1937, that we cannot use the opportunity to commend the small number of left-wing republicans and communists who decided to fight fascism in Spain, despite D&aacute;il Members at the time depicting a narrative of a holy war being fought to protect Catholicism from eminent destruction and the evils of the communism.  I want to put on the record of the House the six heroic men from Limerick who fought on the republican side in Spain: Gerard Doyle, Joe Ryan, Emmett Ryan, Paddy Brady, Frank Ryan and Jim Woulfe.</p><p>It was believed the Act would aid Franco in the long term.  The political and religious establishment's fear was that if Franco failed, Ireland would be facing a similar conflict within a decade and that left-wing politics, even secular inclinations, must be denounced at every opportunity.  As it transpired, this did not happen.  While Ireland's religious community did not manifest in the same manner in which it did in Spain, we still witness the strong influence of Catholicism on our society in our schools, our hospitals and our non-governmental sector.  It is for this reason that it is important to note and discuss the context in which Acts were passed, such as the Spanish Civil War (Non-Intervention) Act 1937.</p><p>Had the fight against Franco succeeded, the course of the 20th century could have unfolded in a far more positive way.  Those who fought fascism were not only against something, they fought for liberty and a society without inequality and wars.  The renowned anti-fascist Buenaventura Durruti summed this up in his oft quoted statement:</p><blockquote>We carry a new world here, in our hearts.  That world is growing in this minute.</blockquote> <p>There are other Acts which need to be repealed.  My D&aacute;il colleagues will address those on Committee Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#GG00400"><p>I did not think I was going to have a lecture on the Spanish Civil War when I came in here today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#GG00500"><p>We did find it interesting.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#GG00600"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House.  I thank the staff for the work they have done on this matter.</p> <p>I counted 40 Acts, passed between 1922 and 1924, to be repealed.  This indicates the dedication and commitment of the people who worked in the brand new Civil Service and State who were starting from scratch.  There were also many more Acts passed in that short time which are still in place.  This gives an idea of the dedication and commitment of those in establishing the State and ensuring there was a transition.  There was a Civil War with horrendous atrocities.  When it was over, people settled down to dealing with the issues which affected them every day and making sure the proper structures were set up.  Acts such as Valuation (Postponement of Revision) Act 1923, the League of Nations (Guarantee) Act 1923 and the County Courts (Amendment) Act 1923 set up the structures for dealing with the whole civil and criminal process.  The Beet Sugar (Subsidy) Act 1925 shows the development of State enterprise.  It is important we give recognition to those involved in the founding of the State who ensured it progressed and developed.</p> <p>The Minister of State referred to an error made in the 2007 Statute Law Revision Act regarding a voluntary society from 1792.  The only concern I have is that if there were ground rents acquired during that period and the association in question was the owner of property.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Colm Burke:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2353"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2353&amp;amp;pid=ColmBurke&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I am just wondering if the legislation is adequate in covering decisions that might have been taken since 2007 or if we could end up with further litigation in that area.</p><p>I remember being in the High Court and subsequently in the Supreme Court in the 1980s in connection with an annulment case and relying on laws dating from the 1800s.  Likewise, when I was national chairperson of the youth section of Fine Gael, we started a campaign to abolish the status of illegitimacy.  At the time, a child born outside of marriage was illegitimate and had no right to his or her father's estate.  Our campaign relied on legislation dating back to 1800s.  We started the campaign in 1980 but it took us seven years to get a change in the law in that area.  Thankfully we have moved on from the slow pace of change, particularly in areas where there is total inequality.  In terms of inequality in legislation, one can take the example of women being prohibited from sitting on juries.  That had to be taken to the courts to be challenged.  At least when a Department or a Minister identifies a defect in legislation, it is dealt with in a timely manner.  </p><p>I welcome this Bill, which takes a large amount of legislation out of the system.  It is also a recognition of times past when people put in the effort, both at Civil Service and political level, to develop the State and make sure that we had a safe and secure place in which people could live, work and grow up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1264" speakername="Damien English" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#HH00200"><p>Before I begin my closing remarks I thank the Members for their co-operation.  I also thank them for the very informed and topical discussion, as well as the history lesson in which I will not get involved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#HH00300"><p>We will not have a repeat of that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1264" speakername="Damien English" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#HH00400"><p>The Bill we have been considering this evening proposes to repeal spent and obsolete Acts enacted between 1922 and 1950.  This is the first comprehensive review of Acts enacted by the Oireachtas and will result in a significant reduction in the size of the Statute Book for that period.  This Bill is the sixth statute law revision Bill in a programme which aims to ensure that Ireland has a modern and accessible Statute Book.  To date the programme has produced the following: the Statute Law Revision (Pre-1922) Act 2005, which repealed a selection of pre-1922 statutes; the Statute Law Revision Act 2007, which was a comprehensive revision of pre-1922 public general Acts; the Statute Law Revision Act 2009, which revised all private Acts up to and including 1750 and all local and personal Acts up to and including 1850; the Statute Law Revision Act 2012, which revised all private Acts from 1750 to 1922 and all local and personal Acts from 1850 to 1922; and the Statute Law Revision Act 2015, which revoked secondary instruments made before 1 January 1921.</p> <p>By tidying up all of the spent and obsolete legislation enacted between 1922 and 1950, this Bill will contribute significantly to the improvement of the overall regulatory environment in Ireland.  It will simplify and modernise our laws and make the Statute Book more intelligible.  This will save time and costs for lawyers and others who need to know what laws are in force and will make it easier for the public to access justice.  </p> <p>Before concluding I will address some of the concerns raised during the debate.  Senator Colm Burke asked when the error was noticed.  It was noticed during the summer and the Department is not aware of any other errors.  The Senator will accept that to have only one error, which was due to a name change, in the context of 60,000 items is not bad.  Every other Senator has complimented the work of the Department and all involved in this, including those on the JobBridge scheme who have done great work.  I thank all of those who were involved and reiterate that one error in the context of 60,000 items is quite good.  Senator Burke also expressed concern that this may have implications in the context of ground rent.  The Bill will have the effect of negating the original repeal, so we will be back to where we started.  Therefore, there should not be any complications arising with regard to ground rent but I will double-check that and revert to the Senator on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#HH00500"><p>That is a nice challenge.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1264" speakername="Damien English" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#HH00600"><p>It is the case that JobBridge scheme, participants were involved in the work on this Bill a few years ago and they did great work.  The scheme was very successful and I understand that all of the participants went on to secure full-time jobs.  I do not share Senator Paul Gavan's views on JobBridge and believe the scheme was quite successful in many cases.  While I would accept that the scheme was abused in some cases, I would argue that in general it was effective, with over 60% of participants securing full-time work on completion of the scheme.  In that sense, it was time well spent for the participants.  If I had a choice between sitting at home or taking part in the JobBridge scheme, I would be happy to choose the latter.  I accept that there was not a lot of extra money for the participants but they got great work experience and in some cases the scheme led to excellent careers.  I am a firm believer in people getting experience and on-the-job training and we need to see more of that.  I hope that we will see a revised version of JobBridge in the future.  I am not denying that there were flaws in the scheme.  It was introduced with great speed in 2011 during the emergency but it was useful in some cases.  In the case of the work on this Bill, JobBridge participants were involved but not in the last year.  All of those involved went on to secure full-time work.</p> <p>I thank all of the Members for their contributions to this debate and look forward to further deliberations on Committee Stage next week.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.135" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#HH00800"><p>When is it proposed to take Committee Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1380" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#HH00900"><p>Next Tuesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.138" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Committee Stage ordered for Tuesday, 22 November 2016.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.139" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 5.25 p.m. and resumed at 6.15 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.140" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#NN00100">Criminal Justice (Suspended Sentences of Imprisonment) Bill 2016: Order for Second Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.141" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p></p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#NN00300"><p>I move: &quot;That Second Stage be taken today.&quot;</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.143" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.144" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#OO00100">Criminal Justice (Suspended Sentences of Imprisonment) Bill 2016: Second Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.145" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That the Bill be now read a Second Time."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1214" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#OO00300"><p>I am bringing forward this relatively short but technical Bill to address Mr. Justice Moriarty&rsquo;s High Court judgment of 19 April which found certain provisions of section 99 of the Criminal Justice Act 2006, which provides for the suspension and subsequent revocation of sentences, to be unconstitutional.  Suspended sentences are an integral part of the judicial sentencing regime and the criminal justice system in general.  They can be used as an alternative to the imposition of a custodial sentence where the court considers that the person might benefit from a second chance and that justice might be better served with the imposition of a suspended sentence.  Suspended sentences are a valuable sentencing mechanism for the courts and a deterrent to the commission of further offences since the threat of the original sentence imposed and the inevitable prison sentence remains.  A suspended sentence is imposed for a certain time period and subject to a number of conditions, the primary condition being that the person must keep the peace and be of good behaviour.  A breach of this condition results in automatic revocation of the suspended sentence.</p> <p>The statutory regime for the imposition and revocation - essentially, the activation - of suspended sentences is provided for in section 99 of the Criminal Justice Act 2006.  The High Court has, however, found the provisions in section 99(9) and(10) to be unconstitutional and these provisions have been struck down.  The subsections provide that a person who is subject to a suspended sentence and subsequently convicted of another offence is, before sentencing for that subsequent offence, automatically returned to the court which made the order imposing the suspended sentence for revocation of that order.  The difficulty identified by the High Court is that the person concerned does not have the opportunity to appeal the second triggering offence before the case is referred back to the revocation court, resulting in a differing treatment so far as the rights of appeal are concerned.  This means that a person could serve some or all of a revoked suspended sentence because of a second offence, the conviction for which may be quashed on appeal.  It is necessary, therefore, to amend the legislation to provide that an appeal may be taken in relation to a second triggering offence before revocation of the suspended sentence is considered by the revocation court.  An alternative mechanism provided for in subsections (13) and (14) is being used on a case by case basis, pending enactment of this amending legislation.  It is appropriate that we use this measure in the meantime which will restore the automatic court-driven revocation process.  While this alternative mechanism ensures suspended sentences may still be revoked, it is important from a procedural point of view that the provisions which have been found to be unconstitutional should be revised and replaced in order that the system of automatic revocation of suspended sentences can be restored.</p> <p>The implications of the High Court judgment have been considered in consultation with the Attorney General and this amending legislation has been prepared to address the particular difficulty identified in order that procedures relating to suspended sentences can operate as efficiently and effectively as possible.  The Bill also deals with a number of related matters.  I take the opportunity to outline the main provisions contained in this short Bill.  </p> <p>Section 1 clarifies that references to &ldquo;the Act of 2006&rdquo; mean the principal or parent Act, the Criminal Justice Act 2006.  </p> <p>Section 2 provides for amendments to section 99 of the Criminal Justice Act 2006 as follows.  Paragraphs (a) and (b) are technical amendments and provide for transmission of copies of court orders to suspend sentences by electronic or other means.  The amendments clarify that modern means of document transmission can be used.  </p> <p>Subsection (8A)(a) provides that where a person commits a triggering offence during the period of a suspended sentence and is subsequently convicted of that offence, the court concerned will, after imposing sentence for the triggering offence, remand the person in custody or on bail to a sitting of the court that imposed the suspended sentence no later then 15 days after the remand, or, where there is no sitting of that court within the 15 day period, to the next sitting of that court.  If for whatever reason the court to which the remand is made does not sit on the date of remand, the person will be remanded to the next sitting of that court held after that day.  This provision ensures a person will be remanded as soon as possible once sentence for the triggering offence has been imposed to the revocation court to have the matter of the suspended sentence dealt with.  </p> <p>Section (8A)(b) is a permissive provision which provides that a court may remand a person to a  special sitting of the revocation court.  This is to cover situations where a special sitting takes place sooner than a scheduled sitting.  </p> <p>Subsection (8B) clarifies that the remand process provided for in subsection (8A) applies following conviction for a triggering offence once proceedings are instituted against the person concerned within a reasonable timeframe following commission of the offence.  This is technical legislation.  It is important it be enacted in order to provide clarity.  Although the provision on which we were relying was perfectly within legal limits, we took the view that we should address the issue identified.  </p> <p>It may be useful at this point to outline the most significant differences between section 99(9) of the 2006 Act and the revised subsections (8A) and (8B).  The requirement that the conviction for a triggering offence be handed down during the period of the suspended sentence has been removed.  A second key difference between section 99(9) and the amending subsections is the bringing together of conviction and sentence.  This bringing together of conviction and sentence for the triggering offence will allow a person to lodge an appeal against a conviction or sentence for a triggering offence prior to determination of the revocation issue.  This also means that the court, in considering revocation of the previously suspended sentence, will be aware of the sentence imposed for the triggering offence and will, therefore, be in a  better position to assess the gravity of the breach.  </p> <p>A third important difference relates to providing a more workable and realistic timeframe for consideration of revocation of a suspended sentence.  As I said, remand to a sitting of the court will now take place no later than 15 days after such remand or, where there is no sitting of that court, within that 15-day period to the next sitting of that court.  The notable difference between subsection (8C) and the original section 99(10) which led to the difficulties is that the revocation proceedings will be adjourned pending determination of the appeal process.  The adjournment of the proceedings to consider revocation of the suspended sentence ensures the procedural difficulty identified by the High Court is effectively dealt with by allowing a person to appeal conviction or sentence for a triggering offence before returning to the revocation court to have the matter of the suspended sentence dealt with.  Revocation of the suspended sentence will not be considered until such time as the appeals process in relation to conviction or sentence for the triggering offence is complete.  </p> <p>The other subsections in the Bill deal with the various issues that arise subsequent to that in regard to the various proceedings.  I do not propose to go into the detail of all of the subsections, but it is provided in the speech circulated for those who wish to avail of it, except to say a new subsection (13A) has been inserted which gives the Director of Public Prosecutions a power, similar to that of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, the prison governor and the Probation Service to make an application to a court to consider revocation of a suspended sentence where a condition under subsection (3) has been breached.  This provision will strengthen section 99 by providing for an additional subsection (13) or (14)-type referral to ensure any breach of a condition of a suspended sentence is captured by the section, as is the policy intention.  </p> <p>Two new subsections, (19) and (19A), have also been inserted.  These subsections take account of the situation where a person has committed a number of offences and is subject to a number of sentences which are to be served consecutively.  Subsection (19B) ensures District Court sentencing provisions are maintained and that the maximum term of imprisonment which can be imposed by the District Court in respect of sentences passed at the same time cannot exceed two years.  There are also a number of other sections included in the Bill.  This amending legislation is a necessary response to the High Court's finding of unconstitutionality in relation to some of the suspended sentencing provisions.  The primary purpose of the Bill is to address the difficulty in relation to the differing treatment so far as rights of appeal are concerned, as highlighted by the court, and to revise the procedure to ensure the suspended sentencing system can again operate efficiently and effectively.  I trust that Senators will appreciate the need to bring forward this technical legislation to deal with the issue highlighted by the High Court and clarify the original intention of section 99.  I commend the Bill to the House and ask Senators for their support for it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#PP00100"><p>I welcome the Minister, a former Senator and former Leader of the Opposition in this House, back to the House.  Justice is not my portfolio so I am delighted to be able to take this matter on behalf of my colleague, Senator Clifford-Lee.  I think another former Senator who is now a Minister will be here tomorrow, so it is great to see all these former Senators doing so well in Cabinet.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#PP00200"><p>It works the other way as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#PP00300"><p>We have a few former Cabinet members here.  To put the Minister at ease, Fianna Fail supports this Bill, which results from an April 2016 High Court decision declaring unconstitutional the law governing the power of the courts to activate suspended sentences.  I welcome the opportunity to speak relatively briefly about the Criminal Justice (Suspended Sentences of Imprisonment) Bill 2016 because the Minister has given us a very comprehensive review of the legislation.  The main purpose of this Bill is to amend section 99 of the Criminal Justice Act 2006, which is the power to suspend sentence, in respect of the activation of a suspended sentence in the event of the commission of another offence by a person who is subject to a suspended sentence.  The amendments are designed to clarify the procedures to be followed by the courts in such cases.  The need for amending this legislation arises from a High Court judgment of 19 April 2016 which found certain provisions of section 99 to be unconstitutional.  Mr. Justice Michael Moriarty declared key subsections of section 99 of the  Criminal Justice Act 2006, as amended under the 2007 and 2009 Acts, unconstitutional on certain grounds, including those allowed for significantly different treatment of persons before the law as far as their rights of appeal are concerned.  In his judgment, he said that the fact that there were weekly challenges arising from the operation of section 99 showed that lay and professional persons involved in the criminal law arena simply do not know at present where they stand and that the striking down of the subsections would affect the operation of the criminal justice system on a daily basis and is likely to lead to immediate challenges by affected persons.  It was claimed that legislation will have to be urgently enacted to remedy the situation.</p> <p>This Bill provides that where a person who is subject to an order for a suspended sentence commits a subsequent "triggering" offence during the period of the suspended sentence and is convicted of that triggering offence either during or within a certain period of the suspended sentence, he or she will, following sentencing for the triggering offence, be returned to the court which imposed the order for the suspended sentence to have the matter of activation of the suspended sentence dealt with.  It also provides that where a person is returned to the court which imposed the order for the suspended sentence, the court will revoke the order and activate the suspended sentence unless it considers, in all the circumstances of the case, that it would be unjust to do so.  The Bill further provides that where a person appeals his or her conviction or sentence for a triggering offence, the court which imposed the order for the suspended sentence will not consider revocation of the order and will adjourn the proceedings until the appeal for the triggering offence has been determined.  Under the Bill, the sentences of imprisonment will be served consecutively with the suspended sentence consecutive to the sentence for the triggering offence and where a suspended sentence is activated in part, a new order may be made suspending the remaining part of the suspended sentence.  In cases where a suspended sentence is imposed by a court on appeal from another court, the court from which the appeal was taken will consider revocation of the suspended sentence.  I appreciate the Minister may have said much of this already but I want to put on the record that my party has considered the Bill and we are happy to support it going forward.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#PP00400"><p>I also welcome the Minister to the House.  She held the position of Leader of the Opposition prior to her entering D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann and the heights of ministerial power.  She brought much to this House and is bringing a lot to it as regular visitor.  This legislation is simply a technical amendment that is necessary as a result of Mr. Justice Moriarty's ruling in the High Court this summer.  In respect of what he identified as a difficulty in the legislation, when it is analysed in the cold light of day, it makes absolute sense.  Natural justice needs to and will prevail and the constitutional issues highlighted in the court case will be dealt with when this technical Bill, or Bill of a technical nature, which is probably the best way to put it, passes through the Houses.  I do not think we even need to debate it because all of us are agreed that this is necessary.  If anybody on a suspended sentence is charged with a further crime, natural justice must prevail and the option of appealing must be available.  This should not interfere with the issue of the suspension of a sentence until such time as due process has been "maxed out" as such.</p> <p>We have a duty to adopt this legislation.  I commend Senator Horkan, my old college friend, and his adviser in justice matters, Senator Clifford-Lee, for seeing the sense in this and not even engaging in debate because it does not warrant debate.  It makes absolute sense.  With that, I have nothing further to say except to again welcome the Minister to the House.  I hope we will not delay her here because she has a tremendously busy schedule.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#PP00500"><p>The Minister will be glad to hear that I do not think I will need to use my eight minutes either but I will put on record our position.  I welcome the opportunity to speak on this important Bill.  As has been said, this Bill essentially amends the legislation to activate a suspended sentence in the event of the commission of another offence by a person who is subject to a suspended sentence. This is necessary as a result of a decision by the High Court earlier this year.  This Bill means that where a person is convicted of an offence during the term of his or her suspended sentence, he or she may be returned to the court which imposed the original suspended sentence to have that activated.  Where the person is returned to the court, it will, unless it considers it unjust, activate the suspended sentence and the sentence will be served consecutively.</p> <p>We support the Bill in so far as we believe that the constitutional matter that gave rise to the decision that required it needs to be rectified.  However, we are concerned about compelling the court to sentence a person convicted to a consecutive sentence and believe that this is close to a form of mandatory sentence.  As a result, we believe that this should be amended to allow the sentencing judge the flexibility to decide whether the sentence should be served concurrently or consecutively.  Sinn F&eacute;in believes that suspended sentences should be used by the courts, where appropriate, as an alternative to custody.  The use of suspended or conditional sentences should be placed on a statutory footing and consideration given to creating more specific guidelines regarding their use.  We believe that the Minister should use this opportunity to look at sentencing as a whole.  In particular, consideration should be given to introducing a legislative requirement, save for exceptional circumstances, for its use for the types of offenders currently sentenced to custody for a period of one year or less.  Conditions imposed in respect of sentence suspension should be in all cases preventative as well as restorative, where possible and appropriate.  We have a concern regarding the proposition that a person returned to serve an activated part of their suspended sentence may have to do so consecutively in respect of the other sentence.  While we are in agreement that there must be a facility to have a sentence activated, we are unconvinced that removing flexibility from a judge regardless of context is necessarily the most appropriate way to achieve this.</p> <p>While we have the opportunity, let me place on the record our concerns regarding mandatory sentences of a different nature as this is something that arises time and again in the course of our work here and is very often something that is proposed by other individuals believing that this is a mechanism to reduce crime.  It has previously been proposed that mandatory consecutive sentences for certain specified bail offences be introduced.  However, the Law Reform Commission was unequivocal in its finding in 2013 that it has not been illustrated that mandatory or presumptive sentences for repeat offending achieve their intended sentencing aims and, as a result, that these regimes are likely to reduce criminal conduct.  The commission recommended that the use of mandatory or presumptive minimum sentences should not be extended to other forms of repeat offending.  The strategic review of penal policy group was equally clear in its finding that there is concern as to the impact of presumptive minimum mandatory sentences on prisoner numbers as well as questions as to the extent to which these sentences have contributed.  The Irish Penal Reform Trust also published a paper in 2013 on mandatory sentences which concluded that mandatory sentences were ineffective as a deterrent, gave rise to injustice and were not cost-effective.  Given the lack of evidence that mandatory sentences reduce crime and the consensus of both law reform and penal policy experts that there should be no extension to existing presumptive schemes, there appears to be little rationale for the inclusion of such a provision.  We support the Bill to allow the activation of suspended sentences, however, we believe that sentencing guidelines for the courts would be more appropriate than a mandatory consecutive sentence.  We will allow the Bill to go forward but we wish to see our concerns addressed.  Otherwise, we would need to re-evaluate our support for this Bill.  At this stage, I am sure the Minister is coming here with an open ear and is certainly prepared to listen to some of these concerns.  </p> <p>Furthermore, it is our view that a conversation about the increasingly carceral nature of society is overdue.  In most cases, prison does not work if the goal is to eradicate or deter crime.  We have had prisons for hundreds of years and we still have crime.  To quote Michel Foucault, "there is no glory in punishing."<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2477"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2477&amp;amp;pid=NiallODonnghaile&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Clearly, in the sentencing guidelines it would have been better to take action State-wide and at local level to prevent crime from happening in the first place.  What is necessary from the point of view of the Government, if it is serious about reducing crime levels, is treating violence and intimidation in the community as a public health concern, introducing evidence based drug laws, focusing on prevention and early interventions to address inequalities and systematically targeting investment in communities, while ensuring ex-offenders have access to secure employment and housing.  In the absence of these initiatives, we will continue to tinker at the edges of actions that talk about building a better society rather than getting on with the business of doing it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#QQ00200"><p>I welcome the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Justice and Equality.  She is always welcome, particularly when she is commencing Bills, for which I thank her.  It is good to see this Bill starting life in the Seanad.  Like others, I am happy to express the support of the Labour Party for the Bill which is technical in nature to address the High Court judgment of April 2016 of Mr. Justice Moriarty.  It should be noted that in his judgment he referred to the relatively chequered history of section 99, the fact that it had been amended twice and the subject of criticism from a number of courts at different levels, particularly by the late Supreme Court judge Adrian Hardiman who in 2015 spoke about the section as having given rise to innumerable practical difficulties and problems and being in need of urgent and comprehensive review.  The difficulties with the provision had been signalled.  There had been litigation prior to the six joint cases that were the subject of the judgment of Mr. Justice Moriarty.  In one of these cases Mr. Justice Hogan, in the High Court in 2014, had given a very clear rationale, on which Mr. Justice Moriarty's judgment was based in striking down the relevant provisions of section 99.</p> <p>As the Minister said, the Bill seeks to address the core issue, namely, discrimination.  According Mr. Justice Hogan and Mr. Justice Moriarty, what was wrong with section 99 was that it offended the principle of equal treatment of similarly situated persons within the criminal justice system.  Mr. Justice Hogan made the point that, as far as the rights of appeal were concerned, the provision allowed for significantly different treatment of otherwise similarly situated accused persons.  It seemed to preclude a right of appeal for those in respect of whom a suspended sentence was to be revoked.  The Minister described this as a procedural difficulty identified by the High Court, but, to be fair, it is more than that.  It was a very fundamental constitutional difficulty that the court had identified, that is, the effect of section 99.  As the Minister said, the constitutional breach identified by the High Court is being dealt with in the Bill by allowing the person concerned to appeal the conviction or sentence in the triggering of the second offence before he or she returns to the revocation court to have the matter of the suspended sentence dealt with.  That is very welcome.</p> <p>In the broader context, I welcome any provision that make the operation of suspended sentences more effective and workable.  The Minister will be well aware of the report of the Joint Committee on Justice and Equality on penal reform which predated the strategic review report of the expert group, to which my colleagues have referred.  In our 2013 report, produced under the chairpersonship of the Minister of State, Deputy David Stanton, we recommended that significant penal reforms be adopted by the Government, in particular a decarceration strategy with an intention of reducing the prison population by one third over ten years.  We were cognisant of the fact that we had heard from numerous experts, organisations and statutory bodies, including those with first-hand experience of working with prisoners and ex-prisoners every day.  The consensus that emerged in the hearings was that prison was not working to prevent reoffending, protect victims of crime or keep society safe.  It also emerged that prison overcrowding had had a pernicious effect on the conditions in which inmates were living and any effort to try to rehabilitate them.  We were particularly concerned about end-of-sentence strategies and the fact that prisoners were being released in an unstructured way with a lack of real sentence management.  Our recommendations sought to take on board what had been done in Finland, where effective measures had been adopted through a change in political decision-making.  It had adopted a strategy that had led to reduced prisoner numbers, from about 4,000 in 2005 to 3,000 in 2013, in a jurisdiction with similar numbers to those in Ireland.  We believed a similar policy should be adopted here.  We spoke about the need to increase the use of community-based sanctions, increasing standard remission from one quarter to one third and introducing incentivised remission schemes and legislation for structured release, temporary release, parole and community return.</p> <p>We are very heartened to hear about some of the initiatives being taken by the Irish Prison Service, including on community return.  They have shown strong measures of success in addressing and reducing recidivism rates.  These measures are welcome and the Irish Prison Service was very receptive to some of the recommendations we had made.  It was among the bodies that had given evidence to us.</p> <p>Overall, we set out recommendations that we should seek to achieve a penal policy which would see prison as genuinely a sanction of last resort and use alternative means of sanction and sentence for those convicted of minor non-violent offences.  That was the overarching theme of the report.  Crime rates and prison numbers have fallen, which is very welcome.  The figures show that there are just over 4,190 people in prison today, including those in custody awaiting sentencing and those on remand.  We still need to ask ourselves, however, whether all of these people need to be in prison and whether their imprisonment is serving any purpose, particularly where they are serving short sentences for minor non-violent offences.  We should consider whether, in the case of such minor offences, the interests of victims and society at large might be better served by focusing on rehabilitation efforts in the community rather than simply locking people up.  Suspended sentences have an important role to play in a more enlightened and progressive penal policy, as we discussed at the committee.  I understand the Department and the Irish Prison Service are embracing that view.  I look forward to the Bill being part of a package of measures to try to achieve a more enlightened policy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#QQ00300"><p>I, took, welcome the Minister.  I also welcome the Bill which responds to the High Court decision of Mr. Justice Moriarty in which he found part of the Criminal Justice Act 2006 to be unconstitutional.  The Bill aims to ensure an individual who receives a suspended sentence will find that it will not be triggered, except in accordance with due legal process, as provided for in the Constitution.  No one should be deprived of his or her liberty without being subject to the checks and balances of the criminal justice system.  Apart from providing comfort for an individual facing the loss of his or her liberty, these checks and balances allow us to have confidence in the system.  The general public must know that a person will only be incarcerated when it is just.  The judgment was handed down last April and it is important that we pass the Bill.</p> <p>There is general consensus on the Bill.  I ask that, with the Bill, we consider other aspects of the criminal justice system.  Senator Ivana Bacik has been involved with the Law Reform Commission and referred to a report produced in 2013.  The criminal justice system is not just about reforming people; it also acts as a deterrent and ensures people have a sense of justice.  Victims and those who belong to them are important, but there must also be a balance.  We have to be very careful.  When an order for incarceration is made or it is decided that someone is to be sent to prison, it must mean something.  These orders need to be followed through.  That consecutive sentences should not be pursued is not something with which I would agree.  I highlight the murder of Sharon Whelan, which case has been before the Court of Criminal Appeal and which has been mentioned in the media.  She was raped and murdered in her home, with her two children, on Christmas Day 2008.  Following the initial trial, the man convicted of the murders received three consecutive life sentences.  Arising from the appeal last Friday, his sentence was reduced and the sentences will now run concurrently.  The criminal justice system is not very nuanced.  As I understand it, the ruling means that after seven years the man convicted will be able to go before the Parole Board to have his pathway to freedom set out.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Michelle Mulherin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2309"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2309&amp;amp;pid=MichelleMulherin&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The individual in question may serve a sentence of as little as 12 years, which would be devastating to the Whelan family.  It offends everyone's sense of justice that such a short sentence could be served for taking three lives.</p><p>A report produced by the Law Reform Commission in 2013 suggested that mandatory life sentences remain in place and judges rather than parole boards set out minimum terms of imprisonment in such cases.  Such a change would make the system much more transparent because the judge in the case would also set out the reasons for the minimum sentence.  The Irish Penal Reform Trust, which advocates for prisoners' rights, also sees merit in changes that would provide for differing circumstances to be taken into account as mitigation or factors making a case more serious.</p><p>The Whelan family are not the only people affected by these types of cases.  Sharon Whelan's brother, John Whelan, is now the head of AdVIC, an organisation that advocates for victims' rights.  Society cannot stand over this type of sentencing because it sends out the wrong message.  While it may be considered progressive to speak about rehabilitation, people must want to be rehabilitated.  Another aspect of sentencing is the seriousness of the offence that has been committed.  The prospect of a person who has committed murder being released after 12 years is sickening to the core.  </p><p>The report of the Law Reform Commission also notes that people who commit murder do not have an incentive to plead guilty.  Only 10% of accused persons in murder cases pleaded guilty in 2015.  This means the State and families incur legal costs and expenses and most people do not plead guilty as doing so is of no benefit to them.  This is wrong and the system needs to be reformed to address this issue.  </p><p>While the Minister has many issues on her plate, the case of the Whelan family offends everyone's sense of justice.  I would like justice to be served for the family and other families in similar cases.  People can rehabilitate all they want but if they take a life, they should serve more than 12 years in prison.  While I appreciate that the Minister may wish to have these matters considered further by the Joint Committee on Justice and Equality or in another forum, reports have already been produced on the issue.  It is important also that victim and prisoner groups agree that reform is necessary. </p><p>Life should mean life and failing that, judges in murder cases should be able to specify minimum sentences.  Murder cases are harrowing and it is wrong that concurrent sentences can be imposed in a case where three lives were taken.  </p><p>I am a little concerned by the lax attitude to justice shown by Sinn F&eacute;in Senators.  The view that threatening and intimidating behaviour should not be viewed as criminal would not be accepted by reasonable persons.  We should ask people who live with such behaviour what their views are on the issue.  If people cross a line-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#RR00200"><p>I know all about it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#RR00300"><p>People should be very clear about when they cross a line.  It is not acceptable in any shape or form that-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#RR00400"><p>Will the Senator point out where I made such a comment?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#RR00500"><p>The Senator showed a very lax attitude as far as I am concerned.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#RR00600"><p>What did I say?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#RR00700"><p>It does not surprise me that Sinn F&eacute;in has a warped view on justice given that it engaged in and supported organisations that carry out their own justice.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#RR00800"><p>The Senator's time has concluded.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#RR00900"><p>I ask that the Minister-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#RR01000"><p>On a point of order, will the Acting Chairman rule on whether it is in order for me to be misquoted?  Where exactly did I make the statement the Senator alleged I made?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#RR01100"><p>That is not a point of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#RR01200"><p>It is a point of order because it is not in order to be lied about.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#RR01300"><p>This is a debating Chamber.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#RR01400"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#RR01500"><p>If Senator Mulherin misinterpreted what Senator &Oacute; Donnghaile said-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#RR01600"><p>She lied.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#RR01700"><p>-----there will be an opportunity to address that at a later stage.  Senator Mulherin must conclude.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#RR01800"><p>I thank the Acting Chairman for his forbearance and for allowing me to speak.  This is good legislation and I ask the Minister to address the issue of a minimum term for murder and reform the system to bring some justice.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.173" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1214" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#RR01900"><p>I thank Senators for their support for the Bill.  As several speakers noted, it is short but important legislation, which specifically addresses the High Court finding of unconstitutionality in respect of certain provisions relating to the revocation of suspended prison sentences.  It does so by explicitly ensuring there is an opportunity for an appeal against conviction or sentence for a triggering offence prior to consideration of revocation of a suspended sentence.  There are other procedural changes to related elements of the suspended sentencing regime to enhance its operation and effectiveness.  The overall effect of this amending legislation is to ensure the procedural and sequencing aspects of the suspended sentencing system can operate correctly in the interests of the courts system and those who come before it.  Senators have recognised this in supporting the Bill, for which I thank them.</p> <p>Senator Mulherin raised a particular case, which I do not propose to discuss, other than to point out that the average time served for a life sentence has been increasing in recent years and currently stands at 17 or 18 years.  I recognise the circumstances the Senator describes in respect of a particular family.  It is important that we are aware of such issues and that I give serious consideration to the views of victims.  The victims directive is coming through and we will have victims legislation very shortly. </p> <p>Various reports have been produced on mandatory presumptive minimum sentencing, an issue on which views are divided.  I will take heed of the points made by Senator Mulherin and revert to her on some of them.</p> <p>In developing sentencing policy, it is very important to strike the right balance to achieve an effective and fair sentencing system.  In general, the right to go before a parole board after serving seven years of a sentence does not necessarily lead to release.  The parole board has a very important job to do in making a risk assessment and examining all factors when taking a decision on parole.  Many people come before the parole board multiple times without being released.  The recommendation of the parole board depends on the risk assessment and the views of a victim's family play an increasingly strong role in the board's decision making.  </p> <p>I thank Senators again for their contributions. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.174" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#RR02100"><p>When is it proposed to take Committee Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#RR02200"><p>Next Tuesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.177" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Committee Stage ordered for Tuesday, 22 November 2016.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#RR02400"><p>When is it proposed to sit again?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.179" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111500002#RR02500"><p>At 10.30 a.m. tomorrow.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-15a.180" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>The Seanad adjourned at 7 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Wednesday, 16 November 2016.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>