<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.2" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 14:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.4" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.5" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Lorraine Clifford-Lee that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, she proposes to raise the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Education and Skills to provide an update on the status of the urgent works required at St. Molaga's national school, Balbriggan, County Dublin, which is on the Department of Education and Skills major building works programme for 2019 to 2021. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade to provide an update on the number of passport applications from the North of Ireland in the last year and on whether he will consider cross-party and community calls to open a passport office in the North to meet the demand.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Gabrielle McFadden of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister of State at the Department of Health with special responsibility for mental health and older people to provide an update on the current status of the integrated care programme for older persons.</blockquote> <p><!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">An Cathaoirleach:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1988"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1988&amp;amp;pid=DenisODonovan&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=01&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I have also received notice from Senator Tim Lombard of the following matter: </p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to review the SouthDoc services in Cork in light of growing public demand for reinstated services in Kinsale.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Maria Byrne of the following matter: </p><blockquote>The need for the Minister of State at the Department of Health with special responsibility for disability issues to provide an update on the number of children with disabilities in the Limerick and Tipperary area waiting to be placed in residential care homes.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Rose Conway-Walsh of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Communications, Climate Action and Environment to provide an update on the threatened closure of a post office in Ballina, County Mayo.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Gerard P. Craughwell of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Education and Skills to outline his plans for the continued implementation of the anti-bullying procedures for primary and post-primary schools; and if he will guarantee that the funding of the National Anti-Bullying Research and Resource Centre in Dublin City University, DCU, will be continued.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Colm Burke of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister of State with responsibility for the Office of Public Works and flood relief to outline when it is proposed to commence work on the Glashboy flood relief scheme, Glanmire, County Cork.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Kieran O'Donnell of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to include the building of a 96 acute bed unit at the University Hospital Limerick in the new ten year national capital plan. </blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Robbie Gallagher of the following matter: </p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to review the use of existing facilities at Monaghan General Hospital to help alleviate the bed and trolley crisis; and if he will consider visiting the hospital to see the potential of the facility at first hand.</blockquote><p>Of the matters raised by the Senators suitable for discussion, I have selected Senators Clifford-Lee, &Oacute; Donnghaile, McFadden and Lombard and they will be taken now.  I regret I had to rule out of order the matter submitted by Senator Rose Conway-Walsh on the ground that the Minister has no official responsibility in the matter.  The other Senators may give notice on another day of the matters that they wish to raise.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.8" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#B00200">Schools Building Projects Status</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#B00300"><p>St. Molaga's senior national school has 463 pupils.  It is in the town of Balbriggan, County Dublin.  Balbriggan is the fastest growing town in Ireland, it has the youngest population in the State and has the capacity to expand much more.  Since 2000, over half the pupils and half the teaching staff have been housed in 16 prefabricated buildings.  These are now in a desperate state of repair despite the best efforts of the principal, Pauline Costello, and her staff.  They are overcrowded, and cold and damp in the winter and too hot and stuffy in the summer.  The conditions are intolerable.  The school is at bursting point and, given the projected enrolment from the feeder school, Sts. Peter and Paul junior school, and the drop in the pupil-teacher ratio, extra capacity is urgently needed in St. Molaga's.</p> <p>The school is on the major building works list for 2019-2021 but nothing is imminent.  I brought forward this matter on the Commencement on 26 October last.  The Minister of State at the Department of Education and Skills, Deputy Halligan, told me on that day that substantial progress would be made on this project before the Christmas break.</p> <p>Christmas came and went and no word came to the principal.  This prompted the principal to apply for additional prefabs due to the urgent capacity issues.  She did so very reluctantly due to their cost and the fear that the ultimate goal of permanent school structures being put in place would be put on the back burner for a further 17 years.  In early January the Department made contact with the principal, organising a meeting to discuss the extension.  I believe that 7 February was finalised as the date for this meeting.</p> <p>This afternoon Pauline Costello got word that approval had been granted for prefabs for two mainstream and one special education classrooms.  This was less than she had requested but it is welcome.  The focus, however, should remain on the extension which needs to be delivered immediately.  Can the Minister give me a clear outline today of the appointment of a design team and planning permission application or will this be given to the team that is meeting the Department on 7 February in Tullamore?</p> <p>I am also looking for a guarantee that the granting of additional prefabs does not mean that the extension date will be pushed out because 17 years is too long to wait and we need this permanent structure in place for the children of St. Molaga's and of Balbriggan who will enter the school in the future.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#B00400"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this matter.  I can understand what a frustrating experience it is for any school that is struggling.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Richard Bruton:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=119"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=119&amp;amp;pid=RichardBruton&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=01&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->My Department is planning on delivering 20,000 school places every year.  We are facing the need to meet very strong population challenges across both primary and secondary level.  It is a challenging area for my capital Department.  </p><p>On the wider issue of the planning area of Balbriggan, it is indeed one of 314 planning areas across the country in which the Department is currently carrying out a demographic exercise to identify whether there is pressure for additional accommodation to be built in the longer term, that is, to extend the total number of places available in the area.  That result should be available within a reasonable period although it is not yet available.</p><p>On the specific situation in respect of St. Molaga's school, I recognise that what the Senator says is correct.  The school has had a permanent building and temporary accommodation.  It has survived for a very long period on a mixture of the two, with eight classrooms in temporary accommodation as well as two special needs classes.  The school is absolutely and rightly on the Department's building programme.  I do not want to get into a dispute about timings.  However, the note I have says there was contact during the summer months regarding a project brief for the school and the longer-term projected staff requirements, and that the Department is currently preparing the project brief following that discussion.  As the Senator correctly stated, a meeting has been scheduled for early February to bring that discussion further, with a consultation with the school authorities.  The completion of the project brief will facilitate the project to be progressed into architectural planning, which includes the appointment of a design team.  This is a positive movement for the project.  There is a project brief close to completion.  There is this meeting and it will proceed then to the design phase.</p><p>I assure the Senator that my Department does recognise the importance of this.  Providing additional prefab accommodation does not mean that the school will lose its position or the importance that is assigned to the work.  As the Senator did, I also commend the principal, Pauline Costello, and the staff on the work they are doing in the school.  I hope these scheduled meetings will assist the school in its planning and delivery of the service to which it is giving such commitment at present.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#C00200"><p>The principal and teaching staff are doing an excellent job there, despite the challenges they face.  I am sure they will continue to do an excellent job.  However, the children and staff deserve a decent and safe work and learning environment.  The contact during the summer months was merely in the form of acknowledgement letters to the letters Pauline Costello submitted.  There was no information contained in them.  The contact in January that was the first of a substantial nature.</p> <p>I am glad to hear that a project brief is being prepared.  I hope details of it will be delivered to the board of management at the meeting on 7 February.  I re-emphasise that this really is a priority at this stage.  I understand there are other priority areas around the country but this is of urgent priority because of the census data and the desperate conditions in which the pupils and teaching staff have had to subsist for the past 17 years.  Could the Minister tell me when we will see the extension being completed?  Is the projected date in 12 months or 18 months?  In the Minister's experience, what is the time scale between the project brief being completed and the actual delivery?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#C00300"><p>Unfortunately, I cannot give any such projection because every project genuinely does differ.  There can be delays in a planning process or a design team.  There can be issues around reconsidering some elements of the design when it is seen.  There can be issues around tender.  It is a process we have to go through and I would only be misleading the Senator if I said one phase will take X amount of time and another will take Y amount.  It would be construed as a commitment which I simply cannot make.</p> <p>The Deputy referred to the census data.  It is being very closely examined at present to see if there is an expectation of additional capacity being needed in the Balbriggan area.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Richard Bruton:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=119"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=119&amp;amp;pid=RichardBruton&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=01&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The project predominantly involves replacing capacity which has been provided on a temporary basis.  As I understand it, at this point it is not based on trying to increase the overall enrolment numbers for the school or area.  I will convey to my Department how the school community and the Senator feel about the project.  I recognise that virtually every area to which I go has projects that are very urgent.  It is the product of the fact that we are experiencing population growth which up to now has mainly been in the primary school system but which is now occurring in the secondary school system.  We have to make sure we meet the needs of the school population every year. </p><p>It is heartening that the overall number of children accommodated country-wide in temporary prefab accommodation is reducing.  Undoubtedly, to some degree, after a lost decade of investment in many public service areas we are catching up.  The Department has been able to protect investment in the education sphere in order to provide for children.  It will have to continue to do so within tight financial constraints.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#D00200"><p>The Minister has touched on the fact that this is not about creating extra capacity in the school.  Extra capacity has been created in many other schools in the town of Balbriggan in the past few years, which is to be welcomed.  However, the pupils and teachers of St. Molaga's who have built a great history and served the community in Balbriggan feel they have been left behind because the school has been allowed to run down and is falling apart.  It is very important that the existing capacity be protected and that the pupils and teachers be given a decent school.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#D00300"><p>The Minister has responded as best he can.  I should not have allowed the Senator to speak again, but she said she wanted to clarify something.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#D00400"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach for his indulgence.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.18" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#D00450">Passport Services</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#D00500"><p>Gabhaim bu&iacute;ochas leis an Aire St&aacute;it as a bheith linn don phl&eacute; seo inniu.  'S&eacute; an f&aacute;th a chuirim an cheist n&aacute; go bhfuil r&aacute;chairt agus feachtasa&iacute;ocht ollmh&oacute;r ag dul ar aghaidh uirthi, go h&aacute;irithe &oacute; Thuaidh.</p> <p>I thank the Minister of State for taking the time to come to speak to me about my request.  I refer to the concerted call made by citizens and those in the North applying for Irish passports for a dedicated office and facility to meet the growing demand.  The Minister of State will know that last year over 82,000 passport applications were received from the North and even more from Britain.  The increase in the number of applications received from the North was almost one fifth on the number of applications made in 2016.  The levels in 2016 were an increase on the numbers of applications made in 2015, while the levels in 2015 were an increase on the numbers of applications made in 2014.  There has been a concerted pattern in the past few years.  </p> <p>First-time applicants for Irish passports accounted for almost one half of the requests received last year alone.  The call comes not just from Sinn F&eacute;in, although we are proud to lead in the institution of the campaign, but also from other political parties in the North.  The SDLP agree with us, while Fianna F&aacute;il has indicated that it would like to see something located in the North.  The Alliance Party has stated there is merit in looking at the opening of a service.  It is about the interest shown in improving infrastructure and service delivery across the country.  There are two passport offices.   I the opportunity to commend the staff who have worked under immense pressure to deliver a vital and important service across the State.  The offices in Cork and Dublin service those parts of the country very well.  There has been incremental growth in demand not just from the Six Counties but also the broader north-west region.  There is, therefore, merit in the Government considering how it can improve the infrastructure across all 32 counties.  When Guy Verhofstadt addressed us a number of months ago, he highlighted the commitment to protect our rights as full Irish and EU citizens.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2477"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2477&amp;amp;pid=NiallODonnghaile&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=01&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> I call on the Government to put its money where its mouth is and to make a practical infrastructural service investment in the northern part of our country.  The Taoiseach rightly said that on his watch no longer will Irish citizens in the North feel abandoned.  I ask that the Government does not abandon us, that it shows us that the preparations and work are under way as the unwanted and negative impact of Brexit is rolled out, and that the Irish Government remains steadfast and that it is here to stay in terms of citizens' rights in the North.  One way to do that, which would certainly be hugely symbolic, would be the opening of a passport office.  It would also help immensely with service delivery and the practicalities of the increasing demand for Irish passports from Irish citizens in the North.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1241" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Cannon" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#E00200"><p>The year 2017 was a record breaking one for the passport service, with approximately 780,000 passports issued.  This was an increase of over 6% compared to 2016 and an increase of over 15% since 2015.  That strong demand for Irish passports includes an increased demand from Irish citizens in Northern Ireland and Great Britain - overall, almost 20% of the total number of applications received by the passport service last year were from Northern Ireland and Great Britain.  As the Senator pointed out, a total of 82,274 applications were received from applicants in Northern Ireland and first-time applicants represented approximately half of all those applications from Northern Ireland.</p><p>We predict that increasing demand will continue to be a feature of our work in 2018, bearing in mind a range of factors, including a growing population and economy.  Between 1 and 21 January 2018, the passport service has already received 53,554 passport applications.  Of this total and in the same period, we have received 4,446 applications from Irish citizens in Northern Ireland; 4,020 of these applications have been made via the Northern Ireland passport express service, while 425 have been received via the passport online renewal service.</p><p>In anticipation of increased demand my Department has commissioned research to try to better understand the potential demand for passports from citizens who have not yet applied for a passport.  That study will assist the Department in formulating plans on the resources required into the future.</p><p>Responding to this significant and growing demand, the passport service offers a range of convenient channels for submission of passport applications by Irish citizens at home and abroad.  Advice and guidance on these channels and other useful information on passports is available on the Department's website at <i></i>.  </p><p>The Department has worked exceptionally hard to ensure we provide a modern, secure and efficient passport service.  An ambitious reform programme is in place to meet the unprecedented demand for passports from Irish citizens at home and abroad, and to continuously strengthen systems guarding against fraud and protecting the integrity of the Irish passport.</p><p>The award-winning online passport renewal service was launched in March 2017 and offers the convenience of an online application system 24 hours a day, seven days a week for adult Irish citizens anywhere in the world, without the need for application forms, printed photos or witnesses.  The introduction of online service not only offers improved customer experience but is also resulting in efficiency gains which are assisting my Department to manage the large volume increases in applications.</p><p>Citizens who cannot or do not wish to apply online have the option of applying through their local post office.  In 2017, over 400,000 citizens availed of this option and submitted their passport application through the network of more than 1,000 post offices across the State.  The Northern Ireland passport express service offers an equivalent service to those living in Northern Ireland from more than 70 of its post offices.  We are keenly aware of the importance of our post office network on this island and I want to acknowledge the valuable role it plays in administering the passport express service, offering a convenient and cost-effective option for citizens across the island of Ireland.</p><p>Bearing in mind the availability of both the online and postal application channels, very few citizens living on the island of Ireland are required to travel a significant distance in order to apply for their passport.  In the relatively small number of cases where citizens need to travel very urgently and do not have a valid passport, the passport offices in Dublin and Cork offer an appointment service, including where necessary a rapid renewal one-day service.  The passport service keeps passport demand under review on an ongoing basis.</p><p>To address the increased demand for passports during peak season, the passport service is this year employing over 210 temporary clerical officers to assist in processing.  These staff have been hired and the roles are currently being filled.  My Department has also been working closely with the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform to fill permanent positions across all passport offices and I am pleased to say that over 20 permanent staff have joined the passport service in the past month.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Ciar&aacute;n Cannon:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2253"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2253&amp;amp;pid=CiaranCannon&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=01&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Furthermore, it is already planned to further extend the online application facility to all citizens, including first-time applicants and children by 2019.  That will be a very significant step indeed in terms of enhancing the service for all citizens.  That will allow additional efficiency gains and improvements in customer service.  People who cannot or do not wish to apply online will still be able to submit their applications through a service provider with an extensive network of contact points throughout the country.</p><p>In all the circumstances, I am satisfied that the range of service options available meets the current needs of passport applicants and projected demand and I do not see a compelling rationale to open an additional passport office in Northern Ireland at this time.  I should clarify that any new office would need to have the capacity to provide a rapid renewal service to applicants with urgent travel needs, such as that available through the passport office in Dublin.  That would require an on-site passport production machine in a specially controlled and secure environment.  The purchase cost of a new passport printing machine alone would be approximately &euro;1.7 million.  That is without security, technical, fit-out, staffing and rental costs.  An outreach office without production facilities could not offer a significantly faster service than the online option and it would do no more than duplicate the passport express service already offered through local post offices.</p><p>In all the circumstances, I am convinced that with the existing and future range of services, including passport express, rapid renewal and online services, my Department will continue to more than adequately meet the needs of all passport applicants, wherever in the island of Ireland they are living.  My Department is also working on an outreach public awareness programme, to inform the general public of all the services available in terms of applying for a passport.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#F00200"><p>The response might not be entirely to the Senator's liking but I will allow him a brief supplementary.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#F00300"><p>T&aacute; s&eacute; sin iontach sp&eacute;isi&uacute;il.  I do not disagree with most of what the Minister of State said.  The passport service is first class.  The staff in the post office network and in the passport office provide an immensely worthwhile service for citizens right across the State.  I am disappointed that the associated cost is seen as a reason for not locating the service in the North.  The Minister of State cited &euro;1.7 million as the cost for the print facility but I am sure all 82,274 people who applied for a new and renewed passport paid for the service so I do not believe cost is necessarily the best case to make.  This is about investment, future planning and meeting a clearly identifiable need.  In the broader political context, which we cannot ignore, this is about saying to Irish citizens north of the Border that we are investing in them and we see them as part of the life of this State and this country overall and we will meet the need with a service delivery to which they are entitled.  While I agree that the service at this stage is first class, as the Minister of State rightly outlined, there is a growing demand which I expect will continue to grow.  The very broad political call for this service will not go away.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1241" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Cannon" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#F00400"><p>Could I respond to that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#F00500"><p>The Minister of State can but we are out of time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1241" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Cannon" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#F00600"><p>It is critical to point out that the rights of our citizens on the entire island of Ireland to apply for and to retain an Irish passport is at the very core of the work that we do.  I fully agree that significant challenges will arise in terms of what Brexit will bring but the service is available through the network of 70 post offices and increasingly online.  Last year if one were to avail of the online service one had to be over 18 and renewing one's passport but we will shortly allow the service to be accessed by everybody applying for a passport, including for the first time.  That is a significant development.</p> <p>The purchase cost of the machine would be &euro;1.7 million.  The number of applicants submitting their applications through any additional or new office would not be sufficient to keep the machine running for more than half an hour a day, as it can print approximately 500 passports per hour.  If we channel our resources through enhancing all the services that already exist on the island which are available to all citizens of the island, that would be a far more appropriate use of those resources.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.28" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#G00100">Care of the Elderly</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" speakername="Gabrielle McFadden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#G00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House again and thank him for coming here so often.</p> <p>We are all too aware of the problems with overcrowding that affect many hospitals around the country, particularly at this time of the year.  We are all deeply concerned about this.  None of us wants to see our relatives, or anybody&rsquo;s, lying on a trolley, especially if they are elderly.</p> <p>This problem has been with us for over 20 years.  I acknowledge that there is no quick-fix solution.  The issues are complex and require creative solutions.  We know it is not just a matter of throwing more beds at the problem, and this becomes even clearer when one talks to people working at the coalface.  It requires a multifaceted approach.  An initiative I believe would lead to a significant reduction in hospital referrals is the rolling out of geriatric teams working specifically in the community.  Such teams, led by a community-based consultant geriatrician and including specialist and prescribing nurses, could play an important role in supporting the management of the health needs of older people in community settings and in providing services that avoid the necessity for a hospital admission.  There are regular admissions to the Midland Regional Hospital, Mullingar, of elderly people presenting with various needs, such as a requirement for intravenous medication.  With more community geriatric teams, many of these elderly patients could be assessed and treated in the community.  The team would visit local nursing homes, day care centres, community nursing units or people's own homes to assess and treat elderly patients without the need for the hospital admission in many cases.</p> <p>People over 65 make up 13.5% of the population but currently account for significantly more than half of all the inpatient beds.  This segment of the population is projected to grow significantly in the coming years.  Many older people admitted to emergency departments, once assessed by a triage nurse, end up spending prolonged periods awaiting treatment.  HSE statistics show that patients over 75 years spend three times longer in emergency departments than those aged 65 or younger.  Up to 40% of those waiting for more than 24 hours are over 75 years of age.  Would it not be significantly better to bring the care to these people rather than bringing them to the care, where they have to wait for long periods exposed to additional infection and putting pressure on an already strained emergency department?</p> <p>Such an outreach service, provided in an integrated manner, would be a significant support in maintaining older people in their own homes and communities, where we all know they do better.  This would not only help to reduce overcrowding in hospitals, such as that in Mullingar, but also, and just as important, preserve the dignity of older people and reduce the stress on their families.  I have been in communication with Nursing Homes Ireland and it has assured me that this initiative is one it would very much support.</p> <p>When I raised this issue previously with the then Minister of State, Ms Kathleen Lynch, she informed me the HSE was to put in place an integrated care programme for elderly people that would examine the variety of ways that health care services could be delivered to older persons and determine the most effective way to do so.  Therefore, I ask the current Minister of State to update the House on the status of the integrated care programme for elderly people and, in particular, outline whether he believes a sufficient number of teams, each comprising a geriatrician and specialist nurses working in the community, could provide a more appropriate service to older users and help to relieve the pressure on emergency departments in hospitals, particularly at times of overcapacity.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1261" speakername="Jim Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#G00300"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this issue, which she has been raising for some time.  There is nothing more impressive in politics than consistency.  The Senator is certainly consistent, and she certainly has been consistent on this topic.  She has been following it for a number of years.  She referred to the predecessor of my predecessor, Ms Kathleen Lynch.  Therefore, it is quite a while since the Senator first proposed what she is now proposing.</p> <p>It is the role of public representatives, including Senator McFadden in her role as a Senator, to continue to challenge the system.  The HSE manages the delivery of services to elderly people and the entire population.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Jim Daly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2328"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2328&amp;amp;pid=JimDaly&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=01&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is up to us as public representatives to continue to challenge how things are done.  If we continue to do what we always did, we will not bring about the real change demanded by the people we represent.  I thank the Senator for raising this matter because it gives my officials and I the opportunity to refocus our efforts on getting geriatric teams into the community to deliver health care.  The last place for the elderly is in an emergency department or acute hospital.  The health challenges they face in such environments are enormous.  It is important we continue to help people to live longer and better lives in their own homes where it is safer.</p><p>The integrated care programme for older persons, working in conjunction with the national clinical programme for older people, is leading on the development of cohesive primary and secondary care services for older people with a specific focus on those with more complex needs and frailty.  To date, 12 pioneer sites have been supported and are in development nationally.  Six were commenced in 2016 and a further six in 2017.  These sites are working to a ten-step framework informed by a local population based approach, delivered by multidisciplinary teams working across traditional service boundaries and adopting a case-management approach.  The integrated care team for older persons in the pioneer sites works, in partnership with community services, primary care, social care and health and well-being services, to promote healthy outcomes and reduce morbidity to enable older people to lead independent and purposeful lives in their communities.</p><p>The integrated care programme for older persons pioneer sites have focused on developing improved care pathways which address areas of older persons care such as integration across acute and community services, emergency department older persons flow and inpatient flow.  While delivery of the pioneer sites is in the early stages, initial indications are positive with the integrated care programme for older person teams demonstrating they are providing multidisciplinary interventions for the majority of older persons in their own homes or in a community day hospital setting.  There is substantial emerging evidence, locally and internationally, to show that approaches that use the models of care outlined in the national and integrated care programmes for older people demonstrate improved outcomes, particularly with regard to frailty.</p><p>Further evaluation is ongoing to better understand the impact of integrated care on outcomes for older people in the Irish context.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" speakername="Gabrielle McFadden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#H00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his reply.  I acknowledge and welcome his support and encouragement as it is refreshing.  The elderly have worked all their lives, paid their taxes and never got anything for nothing nor looked for anything for nothing.  They deserve the best.  I urge the Minister of State to look at a system whereby geriatrician and nursing teams go specifically to nursing homes, community centres and elderly people's own homes to stop them having to go to hospital.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1261" speakername="Jim Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#H00300"><p>It is important we get to air these issues and continue to challenge the system.  The Senator is 100% correct in what she is looking for which has been proved beyond any doubt.  I look forward to working with her to bring it about.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.34" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#H00400">General Practitioner Services Provision</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#H00500"><p>I have raised this matter concerning the SouthDoc service in Kinsale, County Cork, because of a public meeting held there several months ago.  The lack of a dedicated SouthDoc service in Kinsale has not been addressed since 2014 when we lost it due to a merger between two existing services in Bandon and Kinsale.  Since then, the community in Kinsale has not had a dedicated SouthDoc service based in the town itself.</p> <p>SouthDoc services are a key part of the social and economic fabric of Kinsale and how it does its business.  It is a large town with a significant urban hinterland and a thriving tourism industry which sees the town's population quadruple in the summer months.  Due to the age profile of some of these tourists, the lack of the SouthDoc service has become an issue over the past several years.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Tim Lombard:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2466"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2466&amp;amp;pid=TimLombard&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=01&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->At a public meeting I attended with other public representatives, it became apparent that it is a major issue in the town.  I want the Minister and the Department to look at where we are going with the SouthDoc service for the people of Kinsale.  There are genuine concerns not only for the residents but also for the tourism industry.  It was taken away in 2014 because of financial constraints, but it is now appropriate to look at reinstating this service.  The physical infrastructure, the building, is still there.  All we need is the will on the part of the Department and I hope I might get some news on that today in order to progress this very important issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1261" speakername="Jim Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#J00200"><p>I thank the Senator for raising the issue.  The Government is committed to enhancing primary health care services - including GP services - throughout the country.</p> <p>Patient needs for health care can arise at any time and GPs contracted under the GMS scheme must make suitable arrangements to enable contact to be made with them, or a locum or deputy, for emergencies outside normal practice hours.  While GPs are not obliged to participate in out-of-hours co-operatives as a means of meeting the contractual requirement, such services have been developed and expanded over time and are now an essential part of our primary care services.  This helps to ensure that, to the greatest extent possible, that urgent care needs are met in the primary care setting.</p> <p>SouthDoc operates and provides out-of-hours GP services in Cork and Kerry.  The HSE provides funding to support this service including the costs of triage nurses, call centre, treatment centres, drivers, cars and receptionists.  Of more than 215,000 patients that SouthDoc dealt with in 2016, approximately 10,000 were from the Bandon and Kinsale area.  In 2013, SouthDoc undertook a review of the service across the Cork and Kerry area.  The review considered issues such as levels of activity, availability and sustainability of GPs in each area as well as value for money.  This review resulted in changes to service delivery in a number of areas, including Kinsale.  SouthDoc took the decision to establish the main centre for this area in Bandon, and base the doctors there on weekdays from 6 p.m. to 11 p.m. and for the weekend service, while retaining a treatment centre in Kinsale.  After 11 p.m., one doctor on-call is based in the Bandon treatment centre and travels out as required.  If a backlog remains at the 11 p.m. handover, the second doctor will remain on duty as required to deal with the patients waiting to be seen.  The levels of activity in this area and the access to an alternative location within a distance of 19 km were key considerations when making the decision.</p> <p>The HSE has advised that at least two doctors continue to be on duty in the area, supported by additional doctors when necessary.  The doctors are also backed up by the wider SouthDoc infrastructure and resources including triage nurse team in headquarters.  For all those in Cork and Kerry who contacts SouthDoc, a patient's condition will dictate the appropriate treatment and its delivery location in line with clinical protocols.  Patients are contacted directly and given a suitable appointment time in the appropriate location which may be in either treatment centre or could be a home visit in the case of a patient being unable to travel.  At all times, the progress of each patient is clinically managed on an individual basis in line with that patient&rsquo;s condition.  The HSE has advised that 80% of all patients are treated within 90 minutes of initial contact.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#J00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his very detailed response on what is a very serious issue for the people of Kinsale.  I hope there will be a review at some stage into the service to see if this station could be reopened, particularly at night.  That is the key issue.  There is a feeling in the town that this needs to be looked at.  If the Department were doing a review, it might consider Kinsale in light of that review.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#J00400"><p>I am sure the Minister of State will be only too glad to accommodate the Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1261" speakername="Jim Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#J00500"><p>Of course.  The HSE primary care division is carrying out a review of all out-of-hours GP services and obviously this issue will be looked at in line with others.  Obviously, it is in my constituency and I am very familiar with it.  I have also sought engagement with GPs in the Kinsale area to ascertain their feelings on it and to see what issues arise.  As it is in my constituency, I will be more than happy to progress the issue.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.41" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#K00100">Message from Joint Committee</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#K00200"><p>The Joint Committee on Justice and Equality has completed its consideration of Directive 2013/33/EU of the European Parliament and of the Council of 26 June 2013 laying down standards for the reception of applicants for international protection (recast).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.43" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 3.15 p.m. and resumed at 3.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.44" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#N00100">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#N00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, motion re EU (recast) Reception Conditions Directive 2013, back from committee, to be taken at 4.45 p.m. and to conclude no later than 6 p.m., with the time allocated to all Senators not to exceed six minutes and the Minister to be given no less than four minutes to reply; and No. 2, Life Saving Equipment Bill 2017 - Second Stage, to be taken at 6 p.m., with the time allocated to the debate not to exceed two hours.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#N00300"><p>I welcome the Cathaoirleach back to the House and wish him a happy new year.  Although the Government seems to be making a large number of announcements regarding housing figures - many of which have contradicted previous announcements - the harsh reality is that there is a cohort of people, including families with children, who are living on the verge of homelessness having being served with termination notices by their landlords who are, in many cases, selling up.  This week alone two such families have called to my office and to the council looking for assistance.  I am very disappointed by the services on offer by the various local authorities for those who are not homeless yet but who are on the verge of homelessness.  People in these circumstances are turning to organisations such as Threshold or the Mercy Law Resource Centre which are filling in the gaps left by the State.  In a situation where the Government is claiming false wins in terms of allocations to those who move from rent allowance to the housing assistance payment, HAP, it is disgraceful that the local authorities are not doing more to help those in receipt of HAP to navigate the process with private landlords.  We know how difficult it can be to get private landlords to accept HAP tenants in the first instance but more involvement on the part of local authorities with landlords could build trust and confidence for both tenants and landlords to ensure that the HAP system works better.  It is important that we question to use of HAP to demonstrate an increase in social housing allocations as many local authorities are simply moving people from rent allowance to HAP.  They are not actually increasing the allocation but simply changing how the figures look.  I call on the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government to come to the House to address these matters, particularly how local authorities could facilitate those in receipt of HAP.  Obviously, I am not saying that HAP is the solution - we need to ensure that we have a State-wide house building programme - but it is what is available at the moment.</p> <p>The second issue I wish to raise relates to the backlogs and waiting lists at the Property Registration Authority of Ireland, PRAI, and the probate office.  Applications in both offices are taking up to 11 months to process.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Catherine Ardagh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2473"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2473&amp;amp;pid=CatherineArdagh&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=01&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->In circumstances in which housing construction is set to increase, support will be needed from the PRAI and probate office.  There appears to be a resource issue in these offices.  I ask that the Minister outline to the House what he proposes to do to ensure that the backlogs in both offices are addressed and the time for processing applications reduced.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#O00200"><p>I refer to the passing of Lieutenant General Gerry McMahon, who was the Chief of Staff of the Defence Forces in 1995 and who gave 45 years of distinguished service to his country.  Lieutenant General Gerry McMahon will be missed by many veterans.  Ar dheis D&eacute; go raibh a anam.</p> <p>I have spoken many times on homelessness and housing.  I congratulate the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government, Deputy Eoghan Murphy, on the initiative he announced yesterday.  As has been stated many times in the House, it is not possible to resolve the homelessness problem overnight.  There is no magic bullet for building housings and apartments at the rate at which they are needed.  However, the Minister's initiative provides people who are in rented accommodation and wish to buy a home at realistic prices with an opportunity to do so.  However, the initiative has one slight downside, namely, the requirement that participants make a deposit of 10% of the purchase price of the house.  While I acknowledge that we cannot fix everything, this requirement is a problem.  I am familiar with a case, one with which I have a personal connection, involving someone who has paid &euro;87,000 or &euro;90,000 in rent in recent years.  It will be difficult for this person to save a deposit of 10%.  I ask the banks to consider the possibility of offering a loan at favourable rates to cover the 10% deposit.  While I am aware that this would involve a return to 100% loans, this issue needs to be addressed.</p> <p>If people outside the Pale who are in trouble with their mortgages could remortgage based on the new scheme proposed by the Minister, they might avoid losing their homes.  If I am not mistaken, the 2% or 2.25% interest rate announced by the Minister would mean a couple on a joint income of &euro;75,000 would not spend more than 25% of their income on mortgage repayments.  If the interest rates announced by the Minister were to apply, it could result in fewer people being added to the homeless list.</p> <p>I appreciate that the &euro;200 million sanctioned by the Minister for the new scheme was probably for new homes only.  He could take a further incremental step that would prevent people from becoming homeless.  I compliment the Minister who has been getting a great deal of stick for purportedly either doing nothing or doing this, that or the other.  He is making slow but sure progress and made one announcement after another.  The problem has not been completely fixed, nor will it be completely fixed.  The Leader and I will be long gone from the House or, I hope, back after an election before-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#O00300"><p>We will be in a different House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1374" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#O00400"><p>The big House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#O00500"><p>Homeless will not go away but we have to acknowledge the incremental steps the Minister has taken.  I compliment him on what he has done.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#O00600"><p>Like many other people, I was shocked on Saturday to discover that the US Vice President, Mike Pence, had taken part in a military photo opportunity with American troops at Shannon Airport.  This incident raises a number of concerns.  Ongoing concerns about the use of Shannon Airport for military transfer, which have been well aired in this and the Lower House, have not yet been addressed.  There are also specific concerns, including that this military photo-op on Irish soil was for the administration of another country and involved troops who are taking part in actions far outside the triple lock and normal UN conventions.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Alice-Mary Higgins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2480"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2480&amp;amp;pid=AliceMaryHiggins&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=01&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It was also concerning because it was being used at a divisive time in Irish politics.  The tweets and messages sent out by the political figures at the time were used as a source of division and were being used in respect of the shutdown in American politics.  They were also concerning because - so far away are we from the triple lock now - the mission that the US Vice President, Mike Pence, was on was not a mission in any way related to any kind of UN mission but a mission to promote the active disregard of UN resolutions.  It was his mission to travel and promote the opening of an embassy in Jerusalem and several stops thereafter.  We have several layers of concern around this trip.  I would like to know and I would like the Leader to find out, if he can, the answer to several questions.  Was the Government aware of this?  How was the Government aware of it?  What decision-making took place around allowing such a media opportunity to take place in Ireland on Irish soil?<br/><br/>Again, this points to wider concern in the House around the slow erosion of neutrality.  We are keeping the word but we are chipping away.  We saw homelessness being chipped away as an issue.  We have this chipping away now.<br/><br/>Questions arose at another moment.  An article in the <i>Irish Examiner</i>before Christmas told us that the numbers being rescued by Irish naval missions in the Mediterranean are going down.  Again, I applaud every front-line member, every staff member and every member of the navy.  I am proud of them and their unique mandate.  We knew that the decline in numbers would materialise because it was signalled clearly by the Minister of State at the Department of Defence, Deputy Kehoe.  He told us that humanitarian search-and-rescue was moving down the line as a priority.  Now the interception of all supplies to Libya has become different and more of a concern.<br/><br/>A motion on permanent structured co-operation, PESCO, was passed before Christmas.  It contained no mention at all of peace, peace-keeping or peace-building.  I believe it was a mark of disrespect to the House when the Minister of State directly refused to answer questions on whether joint military procurement between Ireland and other countries would be subject to the triple lock, whether it would have appropriate scrutiny and whether we would ensure that when we buy military equipment, it would be used within a UN mandate.  He said he would answer questions in the D&aacute;il.  I hope he has the opportunity to answer the questions, but I believe those of us in this House are entitled to ask these questions as well.<br/><br/>We know the public supports neutrality.  I am calling again on the Leader to communicate to the Government the importance of an active passionate engagement, not only vigilance around our neutrality but passionate embracing of Ireland's role in peace-building.  This requires such vigilance and it requires us taking ourselves seriously.  It is an important time.  It is a hawkish time.  Let us step up to that role.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#P00200"><p>I wish to extend my congratulations to the 2018 Mayo person of the year, Sr. Maureen Lally.  It is a well-deserved award.  I have known Sr. Maureen well for many years.  She has worked tirelessly to empower communities throughout Mayo as well as with individuals to enable them to fulfil their capacity.  She is an absolutely wonderful person and a well-deserved recipient.  The Mayo young person of the year is Michaela Walsh from Swinford.  She has broken all Irish records and set new records in hammer-throwing.  She is a wonderful example to young people throughout the country.  The meitheal award went to Blacksod and Eachleim community for the part they played in the rescue of the R116 crew and the tragic events last March, as well as to those in the emergency services who worked for many days on the project.  I wish to congratulate all of them and say that we are very much looking forward to them receiving the awards on 10 February.</p> <p>Today, the issue of flooding is again in the news ahead of the predicted heavy rainfall and strong tides in the coming days.  People living in areas in Mayo such as Crossmolina, Ballina, Carrowholly, parts of Ballcroy and other coastal communities are deeply anxious about what is going to happen in the coming 48 hours and what will happen to them, their families and their livelihoods.  These communities and others have never left the headlines when it comes to the destruction caused by flooding.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Rose Conway-Walsh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2462"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2462&amp;amp;pid=RoseConwayWalsh&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=01&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->In many areas, even through the good weather, homeowners, farmers and business owners are left fearing freak weather conditions and the impact of the heavy rainfall.  I know that along with the local authorities, the Office of Public Works, OPW, is currently developing the catchment flood risk assessment and management plans.  Out of this work will come the flood risk management plans, but now is the time to act.  Now is the time to provide funding to these communities, and to listen to them on the solutions they have put forward to prevent flooding in the future.  It is too late for Ministers to stand in front of the press outside the flooded premises and homes and promise humanitarian aid and assistance.  Why are the plans taking so long to finalise?  The year 2021 is a long way off.  There are another four winters for people to endure first.  Is it a question of staff or capacity?  If so, what are the plans to address these issues?  The plans will not only identify areas at risk, but will also inform developers, farmers and the local authorities in selecting suitable sites for builders.  Without these plans we will continue to suffer the consequences of poor planning decisions. </p><p>My colleague, Matt Carthy, MEP, has highlighted again and again that Ireland is in danger of being in breach of the EU floods directive.  The EU may well impose sanctions until the plans are published.  The timeframes for the production of reports do not have to be final.  The Government can put pressure on the administrative deadlines when it wants to, and I urge it to do so in this case.  It will certainly have Sinn F&eacute;in's full support both in these Houses and at local authority level.  I ask the Minister to appear before the House to have another debate on the flooding issue, and to discuss how we can listen to these communities and directly provide funding to solve the problems there.  I wish everybody well over the next 48 hours.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#Q00200"><p>I wish to let colleagues know that next Tuesday we will be launching the V&oacute;t&aacute;il 100 programme of events here in Leinster House.  That is the programme of events to commemorate the centenary of women's suffrage in Ireland.  This year, 2018, marks the 100th year since women achieved the right to vote in 1918.  I wish to thank the Cathaoirleach, the Ceann Comhairle and members of our steering committee for all the great work that has been done in producing great publicity materials and putting together a programme of events around women's suffrage.</p> <p>I would particularly like to thank the Committee on Procedure and Privileges, CPP, for allowing the use of the Seanad Chamber for a series of events.  I know that the Leader is well aware that we will be holding the final of a transition year debate in this House on 17 April.  That is just one of many events.  I thank Senators McFadden and Higgins in particular for all their work on the committee.  We will be launching the programme next Tuesday at lunchtime.  All Oireachtas Members will receive information about the events and one of our special commemorative badges marking the centenary of this important commemoration.</p> <p>I wish to commend the leader of Fianna F&aacute;il, Deputy Miche&aacute;l Martin, for his speech in the D&aacute;il last week on the report of the Joint Committee on the Eighth Amendment of the Constitution, and to say just how impressive I thought the debate in this House on Wednesday evening was.  It was extremely respectful and dignified, and there were so many contributions from so many.  The Labour Party has always had a consistent record on seeking repeal of the eighth amendment.  It is really positive to see the leader of Fianna F&aacute;il coming out with similar words last week.  It is time for the Taoiseach to say where he stands on this issue and to show leadership.  I very much hope that he will endorse the excellent recommendations of the committee so ably chaired by our colleague, Senator Catherine Noone, and that he will also support the repeal of the eighth amendment in the way that Deputy Martin has done. </p> <p>I call for a debate on housing, as others have done.  While it is welcome to see the Government announcing further initiatives to ensure greater access to affordable housing, there is a fundamental problem of lack of supply.  I am very glad to see Bob Jordan, the former Threshold chief executive, being appointed national director of the Housing First summit.  That is very positive.  However, I think Patricia King of the Irish Congress of Trade Unions, ICTU, has it right when she says that there is still a lack of urgency and coherence about the initiatives the Government is announcing on housing, and in particular a lack of coherent response to the problem of supply.  Deputy Jan O'Sullivan, the Labour Party housing spokesperson, has called for the 700 sites across the country in public ownership to be put to use in the provision of housing as a matter of urgency.  There is no issue around ownership.  Those sites are already publicly owned.  That is the very minimum that should be done as a starting point. </p> <p>Finally, I wish to echo the words of Senator Higgins on the recent visit to Ireland of Vice President Pence of the United States.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Ivana Bacik:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2248"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2248&amp;amp;pid=IvanaBacik&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=01&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I call on the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade to go somewhat further than we have done to date and for Ireland to recognise the state of Palestine in light of the comments by Vice President Pence that the US Embassy would be relocating to Jerusalem by the end of 2019.  We have already seen nine European Union member states give formal recognition to the state of Palestine.  Ireland should also do so.  I know the Minister, Deputy Coveney, will be in this House next week and I will be making that point to him at that time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1423" speakername="Ray Butler" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#R00200"><p>I would like to talk about social protection for the self-employed.  The Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection carried out a survey of 20,000 self-employed people last year.  In that survey, 76% of self-employed people said they were in favour of a new stamp.  The majority wanted it to be voluntary.  I would prefer if it was mandatory but I am happy to get it one way or another.</p> <p>I have fought for the last six or seven years to get this stamp in place.  Through the Joint Committee on Employment Affairs and Social Protection, we have the Mangan report.  The report is ready to go.  A self-employed person pays 4% in PRSI at the moment.  The Mangan report says that it would have to increase to 5.5% for the new stamp but it would provide for sick pay and disability pay for self-employed people for the first time.  That is very important.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#R00300"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1423" speakername="Ray Butler" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#R00400"><p>I thank Senator Norris.  The Department is dragging its feet on this issue.  The new Taoiseach, Deputy Leo Varadkar, was the Minister formerly.  He was pushing it.  We have a new Minister now and I feel that it has been pushed to the back burner, which is not good enough.  I appeal to Fianna F&aacute;il, our partners in government.  It is in the programme for Government that we progress this new stamp for the self-employed.  We are the only country in industrialised Europe that does not have a stamp for the self-employed.  That is an absolute disgrace.  I welcome all the changes that have happened for the self-employed in the last 12 months.  There have been new dental benefits, new access to eye checks and tax equalisation for the self-employed, but this has been dragging on and on.  We are talking about a stamp that should have been put in place 30 or 40 years ago, perhaps even 50 years ago.  There are 400,000 self-employed people in this country who go out to work every day and who have no cover if they get sick in the morning or - God forbid - if anything happens to them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#R00500"><p>Their employees do, however.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1423" speakername="Ray Butler" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#R00600"><p>Absolutely.  It is always the case that the self-employed person is the last to be looked after.  He is paying his taxes, his PRSI and his VAT, and he gets nothing if anything goes wrong.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#R00700"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1423" speakername="Ray Butler" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#R00800"><p>We have to put something in place.  I ask the Leader whether we can have the Minister in to discuss this again.  Can we stop kicking the can down the road?  Let us put a new stamp for the self-employed in place in the next budget.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#R00900"><p>Absolutely.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#R01000"><p>At the outset I would like to remind the previous speaker that, unfortunately, Fianna F&aacute;il is not in government.  If we were, I can assure him that we would not be having this conversation because we would have already had it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1423" speakername="Ray Butler" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#R01100"><p>It is in the programme for Government.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#R01200"><p>Moving on-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1423" speakername="Ray Butler" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#R01300"><p>Whether Fianna F&aacute;il is in or out, it is in the programme for Government.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#R01400"><p>I would like to move on without interruption.  I would like to raise an issue which I have raised here on a number of occasions, namely, the chronic shortage of teachers throughout our schools.  I have highlighted this issue in the House on a number of previous occasions but, unfortunately, nothing has happened on it to date.  I understand that our party, Fianna F&aacute;il, has a Private Members' motion tabled for debate in the Lower House tomorrow evening which will again highlight this issue and bring forward what the party sees as solutions to it.  I have no doubt that all Members of the Lower House will support that very worthwhile motion.</p> <p>It has been clearly apparent for a long time that schools are finding it extremely challenging to obtain and retain teachers in the right subjects so that students in our schools are able to select the subjects of their choice.  I recently heard a statistic in respect of the subject of physics.  There are only six physics teachers due to graduate over the next two years.  That highlights the problems we have in that subject alone.  We have the ongoing cruel situation whereby young, newly-qualified teachers, who are doing the same job as their more experienced colleagues in the staff room, are being paid less money.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Robbie Gallagher:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2471"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2471&amp;amp;pid=RobbieGallagher&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=01&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Their colleagues in the staff room are being paid less for doing the same job.  That is very unfair.  It has been around too long and needs to be addressed.  School principals say that it is nearly impossible to find a substitute teacher when the need arises.  Will the Leader invite the Minister for Education and Skills to this House to outline how he intends to address this issue?  It has reached a critical stage.  We need to retain the teachers we have and to put packages in place to encourage the young teachers, who have emigrated for financial reasons, to come home.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#S00200"><p>I welcome the fact some progress has been made on the issue of people whose pensions were detrimentally affected by the Act passed in 2012.  I have raised the issue many times.  The Minister for Employment Affairs and Social Protection, Deputy Regina Doherty, has been working hard on this and received Cabinet agreement on allowing post-2012 pensioners choose between their current rate and that to be introduced under the total contribution approach.  In most cases, people will gain and those who might not gain will not have to change over.  I know there is work to be done on correcting the losses sustained over recent years.</p> <p>Yet again I raise the need for a competent independent regulator to rule on operating conditions at Dublin Airport.  Passenger numbers hit 30 million last year, up from 18 million in 2011 when Fine Gael came into Government.  This is a great success story for tourism but the Dublin Airport Authority, DAA, and local residents need clarity on planning conditions at Dublin Airport where a new runway is under construction.  If the existing planning conditions are applied, traffic at Dublin Airport will be restricted to 27 million passengers which is 3 million fewer.  The impact of that on Dublin Airport, with Brexit looming, is there for everyone to see.  Each job at Dublin Airport is followed by nine ancillary jobs.  Transatlantic passenger figures are up as well because we have USA pre-clearance and there were 3.5 million passengers last year.</p> <p>Dublin Airport is one of the most important economic assets in the country.  It supports or facilitates 117,300 jobs and contributes &euro;8.3 billion to the national economy.  It was 78 years old yesterday.  It supports 20,000 jobs directly.  The Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport needs to come back in here.  He cannot go on ignoring this problem.  A regulator needs to be put in place and if there is a need for legislation to do it, we need to fast track that.  We cannot leave this matter hanging in the balance and creating uncertainty for the people who live around the airport and the important jobs created by the airport and the potential to create more.</p> <p>I ask the Leader to call the Minister in to explain his plans.  He has had ample opportunity to address this issue.  He promised us that the Irish Aviation Authority would rule on this and then decided this would not be the case.  He owes it to the people around the airport and to the Irish economy to rule on this and do so quickly. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#S00300"><p>Both sides of the House might need counselling to prevent the fracture in the harmonious marriage between Fine Gael and Fianna F&aacute;il.  I welcome the closing of the pensions gap as announced by the Minister for Employment Affairs and Social Protection, Deputy Regina Doherty.  I attended a briefing on this by Age Action and other organisations last week, and their protest outside this House.  The main concern is that the pensioners will not receive the money they have lost since 2012.  This has been confirmed.  They have been wrongly receiving the reduced State pension since 2012 but none of that money will be returned.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator M&aacute;ire Devine:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2468"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2468&amp;amp;pid=MaireDevine&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=01&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->In the solution brought forward today, the Government has failed to do this and to give them back the sum of about &euro;30 per week that they were losing.  The new system is to be implemented from March of this year without back money.  As a means to address the impact of the 2012 change on over 42,000 people, the Government is bringing forward a total contributions model for these people.  They will now have their pensions reviewed based on their own entire working lives.  I do welcome the review as well as the introduction of the new home caring credit for up to 20 years to assist workers who took time out to raise families and care for others.  The long-awaited action by the Government on this matter is welcome.  We must also recognise, however, that pensioners will be bitterly disappointed not to receive what was taken from them and what was rightly theirs since 2012.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#T00200"><p>I agree with the previous speaker.  Even though we are delighted with the changes, there needs to be a lot more done.  I firmly agree with that.</p> <p>I would like to raise an international issue that has very disturbing local consequences.  The UK construction and service company, Carillion, which is involved in six projects in Ireland, collapsed this month.  The six Irish projects include five schools, one of which is the Carlow Institute of Further Education.  Carillion employed 43,000 people globally and was, until its troubles, a 200 year-old company.</p> <p>The issue I have is in my own home county of Carlow.  Carillion is a 50% shareholder in the company constructing Tyndall College and Carlow Institute of Further Education.  Although the Department of Education and Skills assures me that 90% of the project is complete, what about the last 10%?  What is left to be completed?  Is it the doors, floors, or walls?  What is not finished?  Every time I drive by, I see that there is a lot of work still to be done.  The last time I checked, 90% was not the same as 100%.</p> <p>This is very worrying for parents, teachers, managers, students and for the future.  We have no timescale.  Carlow needs this project to be finished and I would like the Minister to tell us when and how that will occur.  If the company contracted for the project has been forced into compulsory liquidation, will the Department roll up its sleeves and finish the last 10%?  This is crucial.  We have a fabulous college that needs to be finished.  I am aware that the Minister for Education and Skills was in Carlow last week.  However, as of yet we have got no commitment.  I am asking for a full commitment that the last 10% will be finished and that the college will be completed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#T00300"><p>I wish to express sympathy on the passing of the late Dolores O'Riordan, a native of Ballybricken in Limerick.  I attended the funeral over the weekend.  Dolores sat behind me in school so I knew her then. She was a very fine person and a great ambassador not only for Limerick but for Ireland.  She was a great performer.  I offer my sympathies to her mother, Eileen, her siblings and the rest of the family.</p> <p>On the pension announcement today, in the past I have raised the issue of ladies and the marriage bar and the number of people who lost out in their pensions.  It is a welcome announcement by the Minister for Employment Affairs and Social Protection today that people's accumulated contributions are going to be taken into account and also that there will be 20 years allowed for the homemakers and carers and those who stayed at home to rear their children.  This is very welcome news.  People do not have to contact the Department.  The Department will contact those whom it thinks are affected.  It will be effective from March 2018, which is most welcome.  As has been said already, 42,000 people have been affected by this in the past.  The development is most welcome.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#T00400"><p>I call Senator Norris.  I congratulate him at the outset on winning "Celebrity Home of the Year".</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#T00500"><p>Thank you very much.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#T00600"><p>It was last weekend that the Senator was on the Ray D'Arcy programme and people thought he was getting notions again for higher office.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#T00700"><p>No, I can-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#T00800"><p>It is appropriate to offer congratulations where they are deserved.  The Senator has spoken about his home and that part of Dublin with great affection and sincerity.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">An Cathaoirleach:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1988"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1988&amp;amp;pid=DenisODonovan&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=01&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is a great honour for a Senator to have one of those accolades.  As Cathaoirleach, I want to put on the record my congratulations to you.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#U00200"><p>You are very kind, a Chathaoirligh.  I really do appreciate it.  It also gave me the opportunity to divide the money between the homeless, Sr. Stan and a charity which stops young gay people from being bullied.</p> <p>At the weekend there were reports in the newspapers of the settlement of an action in the courts.  In this case a pedestrian was knocked down by a cyclist who was cycling on the pavement and was seriously injured.  A settlement was made.  However, although in the United Kingdom cycling on the pavement is illegal it is not so in this country.  I ask the Leader to request the Minister to give an opinion on whether it is his intention to introduce such legislation.  If not, I will certainly set about drafting and introducing it.  It is extremely dangerous for cyclists to cycle on paths.  Very often they are cycling very fast on pavements.  There are elderly and blind people and it is very easy to knock them down.  I have almost been knocked down on several occasions when I have been walking on pavements in Dublin.  I do not think it is right, particularly when there is increasing provision for cycle paths.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" speakername="Gabrielle McFadden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#U00300"><p>I rise today to raise my reservations ahead of the opening of the new family hub in Dublin next week.  Lynam's Hotel is due to open as a family hub next week and 38 families will be accommodated there.  They will have kitchen and laundry facilities, as well as play facilities for children and places for them to do homework.  While all of this is welcome, it is not ideal.  My concern is that it is being operated by a private company.  I understand Dublin City Council is leasing the hotel from the owners.  The State will pay the owners to run the facility.  I would like to ask the Minister to come to the House because I would like to know how much it costs to provide this service per family and per person and how much the company will make.  I have raised this issue on numerous occasions because up to &euro;400 million was spent on companies operating direct provision centres around the country over the past seven years.  To my mind, they were never run properly and were never humane.  It was not good value-for-money.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#U00400"><p>Hear, hear.  Well said.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" speakername="Gabrielle McFadden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#U00500"><p>I have always disagreed with it.  I believe very firmly that if a family hub centre is going to be run it should be run by a charitable organisation because they know how to do it.  The midlands Simon Community in my area has been deemed as the most cost-effective organisation in the country in the provision of homes for homeless people.  That is the sort of organisation which should run family hubs.  I ask the Leader to invite the Minister to the House to discuss how much this is costing and how much the State will pay.  I do not agree with the decision.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#U00600"><p>I welcome the announcement from the so-called dissident republican group, &Oacute;glaigh na h&Eacute;ireann, that it is ending its armed actions.  This is very welcome.  The group carried out an horrific attack on the Catholic PSNI member Peadar Heffron in 2010.  The group comprises former Provisional IRA members and carried out its first action in 2009.  I would like to pay tribute to the men who helped to end it, trade unionist Peter Bunting, Conal McFeely and Fianna F&aacute;il Deputy Eamon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v.  I also wish to pay tribute to the work of Deputy Maureen O'Sullivan and many others who worked with dissident republicans in Maghaberry Prison and elsewhere.  The work is very valuable.  It is another move in the right direction and towards the normalisation of peace in Northern Ireland and our country.  There is no place for violence on the island of Ireland.  I hope other dissident groups will follow suit.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Frank Feighan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2014"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2014&amp;amp;pid=FrankFeighan&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=01&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> I pay tribute to my neighbour and friend, Paul Young, from Cartoon Saloon who received his third Oscar nomination today for the film "The Breadwinner".  His father was Sean Young, a bank manager who came from Ballymaguigan, County Derry and lived across the street from me.  We are very proud in Boyle of our two movie stars, Paul Young and Chris O'Dowd.  Boyle was also the home of Maureen O'Sullivan who lived up the street from me and played the role of Jane in the "Tarzan" series of films.  Boyle is a town from which many film stars have come, which I hope will be recognised.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#V00200"><p>Well done.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#V00300"><p>I refer to the health service and note that the Minister for Health today presented the bed capacity review to the Cabinet.  It is extremely important that there has been a full review and that the agreed number of new beds that are considered to be necessary be opened to deal with the challenges health services face.  In opening new beds there is also the challenge of making sure wards will be adequately staffed.  When I raised this issue last year, I pointed out that the HSE had been well able to recruit more than 2,000 administrative and managerial staff in a very short period.  In responding to the needs highlighted in the bed capacity review I hope we will also be able to employ the additional staff required to provide adequate care for the patients who will occupy those beds.</p> <p>The negotiations on the GP contract have been under way for more than 12 months.  I firmly believe this issue needs to be given priority and that GPs need support to deal with the increased demand.  There has been a major change in the demographics which will continue over the next ten to 20 years.  We need to be ready to face the challenges presented by an older population and many more people being retired.  There will also be an increased demand on the health service.  If sufficient progress is not being made by the National Association of General Practitioners, the Irish Medical Organisation, the Department of Health and the HSE, we should seriously consider looking for an independent chairperson to chair the negotiations.  The issue needs to be given priority.  We also need to have targets and deadlines to make sure comprehensive health care support will be provided in the community.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#V00400"><p>I apologise for arriving late.  I was listening to the Order of Business on the monitor.  </p> <p>I want to raise a point that is relevant to the one raised by Senator Ray Butler about the self-employed and it is one I have raised on a few occasions.  Members of the Oireachtas are not entitled to parental leave, be it maternity or paternity leave.  That is a serious issue because we are trying to implement policies that are family friendly in circumstances in which we do not have our own house in order.  Senator Ray Butler rightly mentioned the self-employed in this context and has been consistent on the issue.  Self-employed women and men who wish to take paternity leave are precluded from doing so because of the reality of their jobs.  In many instances, they are providing employment and contributing to the Exchequer in a major way.  We need to prioritise policies that are family friendly, given that there are professions other than politics that do not necessarily attract many women.  They include surgeons, for example.  I believe only 7% of surgeons are women who find the position very difficult.  It would be very helpful, therefore, to have a discussion in the House in the near future on this issue and link it with the one raised by Senator Ray Butler, with the Minister for Employment and Social Protection, Deputy Regina Doherty, in attendance.  Perhaps it was something the Leader had intended to suggest.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Catherine Noone:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2354"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2354&amp;amp;pid=CatherineNoone&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=01&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> I commend Aldi on introducing a restriction on the sale of high-sugar energy drinks to those aged under 16.  These drinks have been linked to sudden cardiac death in some instances, but also feed in - pardon the pun - to the obesity problem.  It has been long established by experts that the one thing they feel that we, as policymakers, could do is reduce the amount of sugar-sweetened drinks that young people drink.  That is a huge driver of the obesity problem with which we are faced.  What is proposed is not a panacea and it will not solve the obesity problem.  However, measures of this sort are very helpful in the overall scheme of things.  I am conscious as well that we are having a discussion on obesity on Thursday so I will leave it at that for now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#W00200"><p>I thank the 16 Senators who contributed to the Order of Business.  I join Senator Byrne in paying tribute to Dolores O'Riordan and remembering her today when she is being buried this afternoon in County Limerick.  We remember her as a talented musician, a wonderful person, a mum to her children and, as Senator Byrne rightly said, a wonderful ambassador not just for Limerick but for Ireland.  We extend our deepest sympathies to her mother, Eileen, her siblings and her children on their tragic loss.  I join Senator Craughwell in expressing our sympathies to the family of the late Lieutenant General Gerry McMahon, retired Chief of Staff, on his death. Ar dheis D&eacute; go raibh a n-anam d&iacute;lis.</p> <p>Senator Ardagh raised the issue of housing and HAP.  It is important that we put it in context today that the Government's objective is to reduce the number of people who are homeless and those who are sleeping rough and in emergency accommodation and to provide more social housing.  The figures have increased from 700 to 2,000 in 2017 to, hopefully, 4,000 this year.  We need to continue activation measures to improve the supply of housing, not just in the private market but also in the area of social housing.  As the Taoiseach said in the D&aacute;il today, it is important to recognise that the vast majority of citizens own and buy their own homes.  It is also important, as Senator Craughwell said, to praise the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government, Deputy Eoghan Murphy, for the work he has done to date.  The Minister is committed to ensuring that housing affordability will be a central focus of his work.</p> <p>The Government is determined that the housing stock will be increased to 50,000 by 2021 under the Rebuilding Ireland programme.  When the T&aacute;naiste, Deputy Coveney, was Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government, he received multi-annual and ring-fenced funding, as does the current Minister, Deputy Eoghan Murphy, in respect of the task at hand.  If it was just a case of increasing the budget to solve the problem, that would be the end of it.  There are some in the House who believe that the solution is to throw money at everything, but that does not always work.  What we must ensure is there is a multi-agency approach involving the Government, the HSE, the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection and local authorities to ensure that people are able to move from their current situations, whether they are homeless or in temporary accommodation, into social housing.  We must also ensure that we can have an affordable purchase scheme and an affordable rental scheme.  That is why the Government took the initiative outlined yesterday.  I commend the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government, Deputy Eoghan Murphy, on the work he has done in respect of the measures outlined yesterday.  It will take time.</p> <p>We must never forget that the construction sector experienced a lost decade.  I will not go back over the reasons for that but those Members who know should recognise that certain parts of that jigsaw have not disappeared.  Let us look at what IBEC said recently about those involved in trades and apprenticeships.  The Government must prioritise apprenticeships in the construction sector as a matter of urgency because there is a deficit in terms of some of the skills that are needed now to address the housing problem.  We have some work to do and we are doing it.  I commend the Minister, Deputy Eoghan Murphy, on what he is doing.</p> <p>I am not familiar with the second issue Senator Ardagh raised but I would be happy to get the details from her and to talk to the relevant Minister.  She is correct that we must put all the building blocks in place together to ensure a collective approach to tackling the matter she raised.  I thank her for raising the matter and I will be happy to speak to her about it afterwards.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=01&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> Senator Craughwell also raised the issue of mortgage arrears.  There is merit in what he is suggesting, namely, taking a collective, new approach to addressing the issue.  It includes the Government, banks and various individuals involved working to address it.  I am concerned about the need to have a 10% deposit.  Young people working in many parts of Cork and elsewhere in the State claim it is a major issue which I hope will be addressed in the future.</p><p>Senator Alice-Mary Higgins referred to the visit of the US Vice President, Mr. Pence, to Shannon Airport last weekend.  The use of the airport has been well documented, articulated and debated in this House.  I do not share the views of the US Vice President on many matters, but I do not believe he was being deliberately provocative in using the opportunity to visit troops heading to Kuwait.  He was on a three-country visit.  It is important, however, that we keep our neutrality in context.  I certainly would not want to see it being chipped away.  I will be happy for the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade, Deputy Simon Coveney, to come to the House in the near future to discuss the issue.  Perhaps as a matter of expediency, the Senator might table a Commencement matter because in that way she might obtain a quicker answer.  The Minister will, however, be in the House in the coming weeks.  I sincerely share the Senator's view that we should not allow anything to chip away at our neutrality, but I do not believe that has taken place in this case.  I share the Senator's view that we should not allow the US Vice President to use any of our airports as a bully pulpit to lecture different parties in the US House of Congress, but in saying that, there is nothing to preclude the Taoiseach or Ministers from being interviewed and doorstepped in other parts of the world.</p><p>I join Senator Rose Conway-Walsh in congratulating the Mayo person of the year Sr. Maureen Lally and also Ms Michaela Walsh and the Blacksod-Aughleam community rescue services on their victories in Dublin last week.  Those who volunteer and provide services are the heart of communities, for which I commend all of them.</p><p>The Minister of State, Deputy Kevin Boxer Moran, and the Office of Public Works have been very proactive in tackling flooding throughout the country.  We saw their success last week in Bandon, County Cork.  There are plans in many parts of the country to put flood defence barriers in place.  We all want to ensure communities, towns, villages and homes are secure.  I am sure the Minister of State will work with all of us to have this matter addressed as a matter of urgency.</p><p>On the comments of Senator Ivana Bacik, I am not sure I know where to start in commending Deputy Miche&aacute;l Martin, but I am sure there are many in the Fianna F&aacute;il Party who do not share his view.  I thank all Members for their participation in the debate in the House last week which was very measured, responsible and respectful.  To give him credit, I commend Senator Gerry Horkan who chaired much of the debate in the absence of the Cathaoirleach for doing a very fine job.</p><p>I join Senator Ivana Bacik in commending Senators Gabrielle McFadden, Alice-Mary Higgins and all members of the V&oacute;t&aacute;il 100 group for the work they are undertaking to celebrate the centenary of universal women&rsquo;s suffrage.  It is great that the Seanad Chamber will be the forum in which the debate will take place on 17 April.  I certainly hope it will be a year of celebration.</p><p>Senator Ivana Bacik should note that the Taoiseach has always shown leadership.  It is prudent that, as Head of the Government, he take time to listen and engage before announcing his own decision and making his statement on the eighth amendment.  I am sure he will do so.</p><p>I will be very happy to have a debate on housing and the approach taken by the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government, Deputy Eoghan Murphy.  I join the Senator in congratulating Mr. Bob Jordan, a former adviser to the former Minister responsible for housing, Deputy Simon Coveney, on his appointment to Housing First.</p><p>Senator Ivana Bacik also aired her views on the visit by the US Vice President, Mr. Pence.</p><p>Senators Ray Butler and Catherine Noone referred to the self-employed.  It is an important issue that Senator Ray Butler has consistently championed in this House and one on which we need to see continuing work, building on the Mangan report.  I will be happy to have a debate in the House on the issue in the coming weeks.  I agree with the Senators on the need for the self-employed to have greater rights and entitlements.</p><p>Senator Robbie Gallagher referred to the teacher shortage.  It is worth noting that there will be a debate on the issue in the other House this week and that since 2012, 8,900 more teachers have been employed in schools.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=01&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->There is an issue regarding substitution and replacement.  The Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy Bruton, has been proactive with the different teaching unions with regard to the recruitment of teachers in physics, home economics and other subjects.  There is a need for recruitment to continue but also to change the way we recruit and advertise teacher training.  The number of people applying for teacher training has remained consistent over the past several years.</p><p>Senator Gallagher also raised the issue of pay inequality among teachers.  I share his view but a significant amount of work needs to be done on pay equalisation.  I hope the basis for change can be made in the coming months.  I would certainly be happy for a debate on that matter in the House.</p><p>Senators Reilly, Devine, Byrne and Murnane O'Connor raised the issue of pensions.  Senator Reilly has always been to the fore on this matter, raising it in the House frequently.  I welcome today's announcement by the Minister for Employment Affairs and Social Protection, Deputy Regina Doherty, on this matter.  It is the beginning of the next phase of the Government's work in this area.  The Government has agreed to allow post-2012 pensioners to choose between their current rate and that to be introduced under the total contributions approach.  A new total contributions approach will be available to pensioners affected by the 2012 changes and will include a new home caring credit of up to 20 years.  Back money will be given to people.  The approach is expected to significantly benefit many people, particularly women whose work historically included an extended period outside the paid workforce at home while raising families in a caring role.  I very much welcome the work done by the Minister, Deputy Regina Doherty.  I commend Senator Reilly, who has always raised this matter, and thank all Members for their contributions on it today.</p><p>I agree with Senator Reilly on the issue of Dublin Airport.  It is the main airport of the country and a new runway needs to be built there.  As Senator Reilly quite rightly said, there is an obligation on the Minister to come forward to reveal the plans for this and, if necessary, a new independent regulator to take on board the issues raised about it.  We need to see it happen immediately as a matter of concern.  We do not want to choke Dublin Airport any further.  While some of us would argue for other airports, such as Cork and Shannon, to be given a priority, Dublin is our main hub and international airport.</p><p>Senator Devine raised the issue of counselling.  The confidence and supply agreement between Fianna F&aacute;il and Fine Gael is going quite well.  We would be happy not to take any counselling from the Sinn F&eacute;in Party which needs to look at other issues as well.</p><p>Senator Murnane O'Connor raised the issue of the liquidation of Carillion and the site for a new school in Carlow.  Last week, the Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy Bruton, issued a statement on the matter.  The National Development Finance Agency is the body responsible for the management of public private partnerships on behalf of the Department.  It is actively engaged in the projects for six schools on four sites.  I would be happy for the Minister to attend the House on the matter.  It is important we have these projects completed and that the six schools in question are delivered, particularly the one in Carlow referred to by Senator Murnane O'Connor.</p><p>I join with the Cathaoirleach in congratulating Senator Norris on his victory in "Celebrity Home of the Year" and commend him on his generous act of donating his prize money to charity.</p><p>I am not familiar with the court case regarding cyclists to which Senator Norris referred.   I would be happy to have the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Ross, or the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government, Deputy Eoghan Murphy, come to the House on the issue of cycling and the use of footpaths.  It is important we have a debate on this issue.  As more cyclists are using our roads, a harmonious relationship between cyclists, motorists and pedestrians needs to be developed.</p><p>Senator McFadden raised the issue of the new family hub in Lynam's Hotel, O'Connell Street.  She raised valid points regarding the allocation of moneys.  It is important we get this right.  It is important the local authority and the Department work together to deliver for the families who require this service.  I would be happy to have a debate on this issue in the House.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=01&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> I join Senator Feighan in commending the work of Oireachtas Members and other people in ending &Oacute;glaigh na h&Eacute;ireann's existence.  All of us, who want to promote peace and want to see peace in Ireland, recognise that it took an amount of work to get to today and we commend all involved on that.  I also join him in congratulating Paul Young on his nomination for an Oscar award.  The Minister, Deputy Madigan, will be in the House tomorrow for a debate on arts and culture.  I did not realise Boyle was such a hotbed of talent.  The Senator outlined the history going back to the original Tarzan almost and Chris O'Dowd.  I commend everybody involved in nurturing that talent.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#Z00200"><p>There is still a lot of talent there.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#Z00300"><p>There sure is and it includes Senator Feighan, let me add.</p><p>Senator Colm Burke spoke about the health budget and recruitment.  It is important to recognise that the Minister, Deputy Harris, has received the biggest allocation in the history of the State in this year's health Vote and more people are employed.  The country is in the top five <i>per capita</i>in the world.  I agree with the Senator that it is about ensuring that we retain staff.  We need to understand it is not just about spending money, but about how we recruit staff, where we recruit them from and where we put them.  There is a need for accountability and responsibility in the health budget.  It is important to have an honest debate on the health budget.  Some people think that allocating money to everything solves the problem; it does not.</p><p>The Senator is right on the GP contract and I would be very happy to facilitate a debate in the House on it.  In my opinion primary care is the most important part of our health budget and our health process.  It is very important to get the new GP contract right.  I agree with the Senator on the need for that to be prioritised.  If there is a need for an independent chair, let us bring it in.</p><p>Senator Noone spoke about Aldi's banning of the energy drink, which I welcome.</p><p>Mar fhocal scoir, I welcome our former colleague and friend, Mr. Jim Walsh, to the Public Gallery.  He is certainly looking well in his retirement.  I know he is probably not retired.  I wish him well.  It is good to see him.</p><p>I thank Members for their participation in the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#Z00400"><p>The Leader anticipated my welcome - I do not want to repeat it - for our former colleague, friend and long-standing Member of this House.  When he served in the Chamber, it was not in this venue, obviously.  I wish him well.  It is nice to see him come back to pay a little homage to the current Seanad.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.100" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.101" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 4.35 p.m. until 4.45 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.102" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#CC00100">Reception Conditions Directive: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#CC00200"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That Seanad &Eacute;ireann approves the exercise by the State of the option or discretion under Protocol No. 21 on the position of the United Kingdom and Ireland in respect of the area of freedom, security and justice annexed to the Treaty on European Union and to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, to accept the following measure:Directive 2013/33/EU of the European Parliament and of the Council of 26 June 2013 laying down standards for the reception of applicants for international protection (recast),a copy of which was laid before Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 22 November 2017.&rdquo;. </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018012300002#CC00300"><p>I am very pleased to be in the Seanad this afternoon to present the proposal of Government that the State opts into the EU, recast, Reception Conditions Directive 2013 under the terms of Protocol 21, annexed to the EU treaties.  Last Wednesday, the opt-in proposal was broadly welcomed and supported by the members of the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Justice and Equality.</p> <p>Opting into this directive will align the supports that we provide to international protection applicants fully with EU norms and standards.  It will be an important step.  This is a progressive step.  It reaffirms our commitment to continue to implement our programme of reforms to Ireland's international protection regime.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Charles Flanagan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=414"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=414&amp;amp;pid=CharlesFlanagan&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=01&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Reforming the protection process began in 2014 with inviting Judge Bryan MacMahon and a group of experts to review our protection system, including supports for applicants.  I want to acknowledge the role of Judge MacMahon, his interest in this issue and his continued active engagement in what is an important aspect of Irish life.  He and his group made a total of 173 recommendations.  The Government committed to undertake a process of reform that has seen positive actions across many Government Departments and services in order to improve what we do for people in need of protection and the way in which we do that job.  <br/><br/>I want to take this opportunity to also acknowledge the hard work of Seanad&oacute;ir&iacute; and the support I have received from them.  I acknowledge, in particular, the work of Senator Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in during his time as Minister of State in the Department of Justice and Equality.  He is passionate about these issues, as are many in this House and that is why I am always anxious to continue to listen carefully to the views of Members of Seanad &Eacute;ireann.<br/><br/>Like many Senators, I am concerned about the length of time that applicants spend in the protection process awaiting a final determination.  In order to address this issue, the previous Government undertook the biggest single reform of our legislation by introducing a single applications procedure under the International Protection Act 2015.  Ensuring that we have a simplified and efficient independent protection process is one part of our commitment to reform.<br/><br/>The other part is to ensure that we continue to improve the living conditions and the opportunities for regular family life for applicants and their families, in so far as possible, while they await a final decision on their application for protection.  We have responded positively to the MacMahon recommendations to enable enhanced family living in our accommodation centres and in the range of supports and services that we provide to international protection applicants.  That is not to say that everything is perfect or that there is an element of complacency here.  We must continue to make progress.  I want to acknowledge the work of my departmental colleague, the Minister of State, Deputy Stanton, who engages on these issues on a daily basis.  Further, members of the MacMahon group continue to be actively involved in the process of reforming the direct provision system, including by playing a role, for example, in the standards development process which is currently well under way.  <br/><br/>The Supreme Court gave its judgment in the NVH case on 30 May last and declared section 16(3)(<i>b</i>) of the International Protection Act, which prohibits access to employment without any temporal limit for applicants, to be unconstitutional.  The Government did not interpret this decision narrowly by simply amending the provision prohibiting access to the labour market in the Act.  Instead, it listened to the calls from Deputies and Senators, the MacMahon group and NGOs that Ireland should align its bespoke system with European norms and standards.<br/><br/>The Government decided that the State would give effect to the judgment by way of opting in to the European Union's recast Reception Conditions Directive.  The Government has chosen to be ambitious and to enhance and protect the rights of international protection applicants and their families.  The directive not only provides a framework for effective access to the labour market but also reaches into many other areas which the Government feels it is timely to be validated by the European Commission in order to ensure that we do reach and comply with European standards.<br/><br/>In addition to labour market access, the directive also includes important provisions on children's rights, rights for unaccompanied minors, as well as in the areas of health care and education.  The directive also defines the required material reception conditions for applicants.  Participation in the directive will place the provision of these material reception conditions for applicants on a statutory basis underpinned by EU law for the first time.  If approved by the Oireachtas, the State will be required to demonstrate its compliance with all of the provisions of the directive to the European Commission before it confirms our participation.  This will be a rigorous process but it will also be a transparent one.  I want to assure Seanad&oacute;ir&iacute; that we will continue to make any changes required of us by the European Commission.  My Department is leading an implementation group established by Government to oversee the opt-in procedure and the compliance process within the timeframe set out by the Commission, a period of four months.  <br/><br/>The directive provides for access to the labour market for applicants who have not had a first-instance decision within nine months of making their application and provided that the delay cannot be attributed to the applicant.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Charles Flanagan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=414"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=414&amp;amp;pid=CharlesFlanagan&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=01&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->In determining the level of access to be provided to applicants the implementation group, membership of which is drawn from across a wide range of Departments and services, will be mindful of a number of important factors.</p><p>The State already has a functioning employment permits system for third country nationals, which we must be careful not to undermine, nor must we take any action that would be detrimental to our legal migration system.  The court's judgment acknowledges our role in setting these parameters.  However, we all recognise that the Supreme Court has adjudged that protection applicants have a constitutional right to seek employment, one which is not conferred on other third country nationals who are legally residing in the jurisdiction.  While the court was also clear that this is not an unfettered right, the Government considers that it is appropriate to apply a balanced approach under the scope of the directive where the level of access required will be in excess of that provided under the employment permits system.  Once the State's participation in the directive is confirmed, I intend to provide for access for eligible applicants by way of an immigration permission, which would exempt applicants from the employment permits system and the associated fee.</p><p>In determining the list of sectors of employment to which access will be granted, regard will be had to labour market gaps as well as the skill set of applicants and the expert advice of front-line Departments.  We must also be cognisant of maintaining the integrity of the common travel area and the possible impact of the withdrawal of our nearest neighbour, the United Kingdom, from the European Union.  The Government has agreed that eligible applicants will also have access to self-employment and eligible applicants may now qualify for further vocational training, which was previously unattainable.  The operation of these arrangements will be reviewed after 12 months and we will be open to amendments, having reviewed its operation.</p><p>At the Supreme Court hearing of 30 November last, the State outlined its plans to the court to opt in to the directive, subject to Oireachtas approval, and the four-month process necessitated by the European Commission to confirm the opt-in following formal notification of our wish to be bound by the directive.  We respectfully asked the court to adjourn the making of its final order until this process was complete.  However, the court decided that the prohibition on international protection applicants accessing the labour market under the International Protection Act 2015 would be struck down on 9 February 2018.  The participation of the State in the directive will not be confirmed by the court's deadline as we await the conclusion of the Oireachtas approval process, which is well under way, before we can begin the Commission mandated compliance procedure.</p><p>The decision of the court means that access to the labour market for applicants must now take place under a two-stage process.  With the best will in the world, it simply will not be possible for us to have completed all of the procedures required to confirm our opt-in to the directive by 9 February.  For this reason, the Government has today decided that a temporary interim solution will apply from 9 February until the date of entry into force of the directive, whereby applicants can access the workforce in two ways.  The first entry point under the temporary solution is via the employment permits system of the Department of Business, Enterprise and Innovation.  All applicants will be able to access this system on the same basis as other non-EEA nationals.  In practical terms, this means applicants will be entitled to apply, or have their prospective employer apply, for an employment permit on their behalf to the Department of Business, Enterprise and Innovation in the sectors where the employment permit scheme applies.</p><p>In addition, to bring some clarity to the matter of self-employment I will use my discretionary powers to introduce an administrative scheme during this period to allow for access to self-employment for eligible applicants.  This scheme will apply to applicants who have been nine months or more without a first instance decision and will broadly mirror the legislative access provisions to be put in place for access to self-employment once the State opts in to the recast EU reception conditions directive.  This is important as I want a smooth and efficient transition into the measures giving effect by the directive in the coming months.</p><p>In tandem, intensive work is under way across government to provide for the implementation of the directive pending its formal entry into force.  In making this process a success, I want to work with Members of both Houses, employers and all other stakeholders.  A further information campaign will be launched nearer the time of entry into force of the directive to communicate the new and enhanced access to the workforce arrangements that will apply once we are participating in the directive.  Senators may wish to assist in getting the message out to eligible applicants and I will be delighted to work with them in this regard.</p><p>Participation in the directive would be a very positive step in bringing our international protection system and supports for applicants more closely in line with EU norms and standards.  There are some areas of the directive, particularly around health and education and State support for unaccompanied minors where we already apply more favourable provisions than would be required and these will be maintained.  As I stated, the operation of all the arrangements we intend to implement to give effect to the directive will be implemented after a period of 12 months to ensure they are effective and working properly.  I look forward to the debate and I will be pleased to engage further with the Seanad in the context of proceeding towards complying fully with the directive, which I expect will take place in June 2018. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-01-23a.107" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Additional debate to follow.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>