<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.4" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#A00100">Teachtaireacht ón Dáil - Message from Dáil</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#A00200"><p>D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann has passed the Electricity Costs (Domestic Electricity Accounts) Emergency Measures Bill 2022, to which the agreement of Seanad &Eacute;ireann is desired.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.7" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#A00300">Gnó an tSeanaid - Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.8" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#A00400"><p>I have received notice from Senator Eugene Murphy that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Enterprise, Trade and Employment to make a statement on the delays in processing work permits through the employment permits online system. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Barry Ward of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Transport to permit category B licence holders to drive category AM vehicles. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Lynn Ruane of the following matter: </p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister of State with responsibility for law reform to provide an update on the impact of the youth justice strategy on processing times for young people interacting with courts and the youth justice systems. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Lorraine Clifford-Lee of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Health to make a statement on the extension of free general practitioner care to children aged six and seven years. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Malcolm Byrne of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sport and Media to provide an update on the introduction of a basic income scheme for artists. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Fiona O'Loughlin of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage to make a statement on the regeneration of St. Patrick&rsquo;s Park, Rathangan, County Kildare. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Miche&aacute;l Carrigy of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Health to make a statement on the relocation of the Phoenix Centre in Longford. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Victor Boyhan of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Transport to make a statement on the cancellation of major national road projects. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator John McGahon of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for the Environment, Climate and Communications to make a statement on the Government's launch of a hydrogen strategy in 2022. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Maria Byrne of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Health to make a statement on progress in the roll-out of the programme on women&rsquo;s health announced in budget 2022. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Erin McGreehan of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for the Environment, Climate and Communications to make a statement on measures to reduce fuel poverty, such as utilising surplus renewable energy on the grid. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Martin Conway of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Health to provide an update on resourcing at the adult metabolic service in the Mater Hospital and resourcing for response testing to new innovative therapies for phenylketonuria, PKU, treatment. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Mary Seery Kearney of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Children, Equality, Disability, Integration and Youth to make a statement on progress on the employment regulation order to determine terms and conditions of employment for childcare workers. </blockquote> <p>Of the matters raised by the Senators that are suitable for discussion, I have selected those of Senators Murphy, Ward, Ruane and Clifford-Lee, and they will be taken now.  I regret that I had to rule out of order the matter raised by Senator McGahon as the Minister has no official responsibility in that matter and it is a repeat of a Commencement matter raised on 27 January 2022.  The other Senators may give notice on another day of the matters they wish to raise.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.9" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#A00500">Nithe i dtosach suíonna - Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.10" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#A00600">Work Permits</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#A00700"><p>I welcome the Minister of State at the Department of Enterprise, Trade and Employment, Deputy English.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#A00800"><p>A Chathaoirligh, I appreciate you giving me the opportunity to raise this matter.  I know from listening to all the requests that have been made to you that it is hard to include everybody.  We all understand that you have to make these decisions.</p> <p>I welcome the Minister of State.  I am sorry I missed meeting him at the battle in Navan last Sunday when the Rossies, Roscommon, took down the Royals, Meath.  I only realised when I was talking to the Minister of State earlier that he was there, but I am sure there will be further battles.  It was all good and friendly in the end despite the little bit of ruaile buaile.</p> <p>Before I outline an example of the serious situation I am raising, I wish to acknowledge that the Minister of State is working hard on this matter.  We will have a friendly discussion about it and I am sure the Minister of State knows where I am coming from on this issue, which is the serious delay in processing work permits through the employment permits online system, EPOS.  It should take six to eight weeks to process work permits online.  Employers are encouraged to use online systems, and there is a trusted partner status for business which is supposed to make it faster.  I will give the Minister of State an example of a local business.  I am sure the Minister of State has such examples in his county and that he is aware of them throughout the country.</p> <p>This company has trusted partner status.  It applied for permits last October.  It desperately needs workers.  It is a huge firm and it is expanding nationwide all the time.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Eugene Murphy:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2444"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2444&amp;amp;pid=EugeneMurphy&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It looked for permits last October.  The good news is that two of the permits came through in recent days but 18 weeks later it is still waiting for a number of others to come.</p><p>The online system states it is processing applications from 29 September.  This is at a time of unprecedented difficulty for business in accessing staff.  We would think that we should really be speeding up the process.  I note the Minister of State announced some decisions last autumn.  As he knows, business is crying out for staff.  The latest CIF survey found that 83% stated there had been a year-on-year increase in the cost of labour in the past quarter.  A similar proportion expects this trend to continue.  Almost three quarters of those surveyed in the CIF report stated they had difficulties in accessing staff.  The one thing that strikes me, whether in a small town, Dublin city or a major regional town, is the number of notices that can be seen in windows of small and not so small companies crying out for staff.  It is very noticeable.</p><p>In the current circumstances we need to speed up the processing times for standard and trusted partner applications.  The Minister of State knows as well as I do, and perhaps better, that between 30,000 and 40,000 jobs are needed in hospitality.  We have issues with carers.  The money is there and the Government has provided significant money but we cannot get carers.  Haulage companies cannot get drivers.  In virtually every area of Irish business life today the jobs are not there.  We desperately need these jobs as quickly as possible to fill the vacancies.  Our economy will be very strong.  All the indicators are that over the coming three to four years we will be in an extremely strong position.  It would be a pity if it were to be destroyed by a lack of jobs in a number of sectors at present.  I know it is a challenge for the Government.  I know it is not easy.  I appreciate the Minister of State is doing his best.  I look forward to hearing his reply.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1505" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#B00200"><p>I am more sorry for the result in Meath then missing Eugene at the match.  I hope we will get a chance for revenge.  I am also sorry I was not able to meet Senator Murphy on the day he was in Navan.  I was supporting Meath against Roscommon and supporting Trim in Dublin.  We lost on both occasions.  We will recover and get back.</p> <p>We have discussed this issue quite a lot in the House.  Most Senators were on the ball and raised it last autumn before others knew it would be a big issue.  At the time we tried to respond and I gave commitments that we would make changes to staffing levels and put a plan in place to deal with it.  Those plans are in place but we cannot see the results just yet.  To be very clear and honest, we are not happy with the time limits.  Nobody could stand over timelines of up to 16 to 18 weeks, and 20 weeks in some cases, to deal with a permit.  It is a complicated system.  We are trying to improve that situation.  The sheer volume of applications is part of the difficulty.</p> <p>We are not happy with it.  I am not happy with it, the T&aacute;naiste is not happy with it and neither is the Department.  We are putting in place plans to fix this once and for all.  I am not trying to defend it but I will give the background to what is behind it.  Staff have been working extremely hard.  They have been working overtime and at weekends to try to get these applications processed.  We will get there but it will take a few more months for the timelines to reduce.  There will be improvements from this month on.</p> <p>I thank Senator Murphy for raising the matter.  Ireland's employment permit system continued to operate throughout the pandemic.  The Department made a Covid-19 contingency plan in March 2020, moving the employment permit operations seamlessly to a totally remote working environment.  It adjusted operations to accept all documents and applications electronically.  This in itself was a major change and we handled it at the time.  Ireland is one of the few countries that has managed to keep the employment permit system fully operational throughout the crisis.  The Department agreed with the immigration service delivery in the Department of Justice soft-copy arrangements for issuing employment permits as a temporary measure.  We tried to respond immediately to the challenges that Covid brought to us.</p> <p>From the outset of the crisis in order to assist the HSE and all other medical providers in the State to respond to and assist with the public health response to the threat of Covid-19, all doctor and nurse employment permit applications were expedited.  This is ongoing and it is a priority.  Last year, there were close to 5,000 permit applications for medical personnel.</p> <p>The Department has seen unprecedented increases in the volume of applications for employment permits over the course of 2021.  In total last year, 27,666 applications were received.  This represented a 69% increase over the same period in 2020 and a 47% increase on 2019, which in itself represented an 11-year high.  The Department issued 16,275 employment permits last year and also processed a total of close to 18,000 applications.  There has been a serious ramp up of activity and volume.  Quite a high number of applications are still being processed.  This reflects that there is a strong employment market out there and we are correct to say there will be a jobs-led recovery.  This brings with it complications such as these that have to be teased out.</p> <p>In addition, the extension of categories of employment permits following the latest review of the occupation list has increased availability of employment permits for these roles.  This was in response to wishes raised here with regard to horticulture, food production, meat processing plants and other areas highlighted in the Seanad.  I gave a commitment we would respond to this and we did so last October.  This has resulted in thousands more applications.  Processing times have been impacted by this increase in demand and because of the HSE cyberattack.  As a result of the cyberattack, employment permit applications associated with doctors' rotation, which occurs twice yearly in January and July, had to be submitted manually or through other non-standard methods.  This resulted in a significant additional administrative burden dealing with these applications requiring staff to be temporarily reassigned to assist in the process.  This had a direct impact on wider processing times for other permit applications.  This had a knock-on effect throughout 2021.</p> <p>I and officials in the Department recognise the impact delays in processing times for employment permits have for businesses and their workers.  A plan of action is being developed to meet the challenges and reduce the backlog built up in recent months.  The plan includes additional staffing and systematic changes.  The staffing actions being taken include the recruitment of additional permanent and temporary staff.  This is an increase of 69% of our permanent capacity and 125% including temporary staff to deal with the backlog.</p> <p>On 2 February additional approval was granted to increase permanent capacity by 125% and to increase overall capacity by 225% from the original yearly base of early November.  This means the processing team will have more than tripled in size by late March compared with last November.  The temporary reassignment of staff from other areas in the Department with relevant skills is also something we are implementing.  We also have maximum hours of overtime for the existing team and former processors.  We are trying everything to deal with these applications.  There is a backlog now and we predict there will be ongoing demand for these permits.  Many sectors are under pressure to find the staff they need.</p> <p>We will review the sectors again in the coming weeks.  We will start that process.  We have tried to respond to genuine proven needs where the evidence is there.  Senator Murphy mentioned carers and they are dear to the heart of everyone here, particularly carers in the home.  There is an issue with gathering all of the evidence we need to prove we need to use the permit system to solve it.  At present they are not within the permit structure.  We are willing to look at this.  We have engaged over the past year but evidence has not been gathered.  I ask any sector or employer having difficulty to engage with the Department of Enterprise, Trade and Employment and the sector's parent Department.  Employers should also engage with the Department of Social Protection, which can identify through the high numbers of people on the pandemic unemployment payment or jobseeker's payments whether people are available to do some of these jobs.  Training is taking place.  Anybody who is short of staff should look at the Pathways to Work document that sets out the policy.  It brings together all of the Departments in an approach to assist employers and employees to fill some of these jobs, if at all possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#B00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  He has given a very honest assessment of the situation that exists.  I should, of course, have mentioned the whole area of construction and retrofitting.  When the one-stop shop gets up and running many people will see they will be able to carry out this work.  I hope there will be low-cost loans.  We will need extra workers in this regard.  I accept we have a massive apprenticeship programme that will mean more trained people coming on line before too long.  I accept the Minister of State and the Government appreciate the difficulty in this situation.  It is very important for the economy that we get these workers.  I look to progress in the future.</p> <p>This year, the Government has provided a lot of money for mental health support.  In my county one of the problems is that where, for example, seven consultants and special nurses are required, four of the positions can be filled but the other three positions cannot be filled because there is nobody to backfill the jobs of those who take them.  This means the service cannot get up and running.  This is another area in which we should be making every effort to try to get people into the sector.  I appreciate the reply of the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1505" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#B00400"><p>I will keep it short this time.  The Senator has identified another area of concern.  We made changes in the list last year to reflect demand.  The Senator identified the area of construction.  We made changes to the scheme last year whereby the majority of jobs in the construction sector are eligible for permits or do not need them at all.  The Senator also flagged the retrofitting plan.  We know we need to go from having 4,000 people in that sector to 17,000 people.  We have the potential to achieve this from within the country and within the EU through training programmes that are in place through the education and training boards, the further education and training sector and throughout the education system.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Damien English:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=1781"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1781&amp;amp;pid=DamienEnglishFG&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Employers and potential employees have to engage in that system and work together.  We have responded by doubling the number of potential areas in which people can achieve an apprenticeship over the past couple of years.  The number of apprentices has increased from 1,000 to nearly 8,000 per year, and we want to increase that figure to 10,000.  This is all achievable, if the system and employer organisations work with us and use the education system which is there to be used.</p><p>I stress again that there are supports available for people who are out of work and want to retrain and take up a new career.  There are supports for employees and employers.  The pathways to work that are in place are not being fully utilised.  If any sector asks me to make changes in departments, I will ask them whether they have engaged with the systems and departments that try to solve these problems which are of a more local nature.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.18" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#C00200">Driver Licences</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" speakername="Barry Ward" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#C00300"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House.  The issue I raise relates to driver licensing.  Until 2006, it was standard in this country that the B category licence people hold, that is, an ordinary car licence, also included other categories, namely, the W category for work vehicles and the AM category for mopeds.  On the back of the driving licence the categories people are qualified to drive in are listed, and AM and W were automatically added when people passed a driving test and received their licence to drive a car.</p> <p>That stopped from 2006 onwards.  There was no fanfare or publicity about it.  The change meant that people who did their car test still received a W licence, but no longer received an AM licence for mopeds.  These categories are important because they allow people living on family farms to drive tractors and so on without having to do a separate test.  It means that young people, in particular, especially those in urban areas, cannot now use mopeds.</p> <p>Mopeds are a very effective means of transport, in particular in urban areas and for people in younger age categories who may not have the means to go through the process of getting a licence to drive or to buy a motorbike.  The cost involved is not insubstantial.  People who want to drive a moped, or any kind of motorbike, which is the A category, must go through the process of having 18 hours of lessons, doing a theory test, passing a driving test and getting a licence.  The costs involved for lessons alone, even at &euro;50 an hour, are nearly &euro;1,000.  On top of that, it costs &euro;85 to do a test, &euro;35 for a learner permit, &euro;55 for a licence and &euro;45 for a theory test.  That imposes additional costs of over &euro;1,200 on people, which they would not have to pay if the AM category was automatically included on their licences to allow them to drive mopeds.</p> <p>At a time when we are saying we want to take cars off the road and reduce emissions, mopeds are a very effective tool for people to do exactly that.  They are much more fuel efficient than cars and create far fewer emissions.  They also take cars off the road.  They are an opportunity for younger people from the age of 17 upwards to avail of a private transport model that does not involve the expense, pollution and traffic congestion caused by cars.</p> <p>The only reason I have ever been given for the change is that there may be a road safety element, in that people need special training to drive a motorbike.  I do not dispute that.  However, the reality is that anybody who has passed a driving test for a B licence, that is, the ordinary licence we all think of as a driving licence, has already done a theory test, undergone 12 hours of driver training and taken the test.  That person has a level of expertise in terms of road safety, understanding other road users and the importance of behaving in a responsible manner on the road.  </p> <p>I do not think there were a large number of accidents involving those who hold B licences driving mopeds without the road safety expertise required to drive a motorbike.  While I accept that there might be a case in terms of road safety, I do not think the decision has been properly thought out.  Nobody has ever shown me evidence to suggest that people with full driver licences are not capable of driving a moped.  I do not necessarily accept that is the case.  There is no evidence that I am aware of to suggest there has been a certain number of accidents in this regard.</p> <p>The major problem is that this change specifically targeted particular groups in society, namely, younger people, people without means and people who cannot afford to run a car.  It was a retrograde step but, perhaps most important, it is out of step with our European neighbours.  Most countries in Europe provide an AM licence with other licences automatically.  We do not, and I do not know why that is the case.  I hope the Minister of State will consider changing that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1505" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#C00400"><p>I thank the Senator for raising awareness of this issue.  I was not aware of the change made in 2006.  It was not up in flashing lights, but it has certainly had an impact.  It has affected people, mainly of the younger generation, as the Senator said.  It is worth examining the matter and the Senator has made a very compelling case for doing so.</p> <p>I will provide some background on this matter.  Prior to October 2016, as the Senator said, full category B licence holders, on passing a driving test, were permitted to drive category M moped vehicles.  This practice ceased for new category B licence holders with the implementation of the third EU driving licence directive.  As it stands officially, the Minister has no plans to change this policy, but the Senator has made a strong case for doing so, which I will feed back to the Minister and Department of Transport.  It is an issue that can and should be considered.  </p> <p>The provisions of the third driving licence directive state that licences granted for any category shall be valid for vehicles in category AM.  However, for driving licences issued on its territory, a member state may limit equivalences for category AM to categories A1, A2 and A, if that member state imposes a practical test as a condition for obtaining category AM.  Prior to the directive, the category AM for mopeds, that is, a motorcycle with an engine of less than 50 cm&sup3; capacity, was not recognised across the EU and may not have been issued as a category of licence in many countries.  In Ireland, category AM could always be obtained by obtaining passing a driving test in the category B up to October 2006.</p> <p>Before October 2006, the driver theory test was confined to cars and motorcycles.  Since then, it has been split into two examinations covering motorcycles and cars separately.  Initial basic training, IBT, was introduced for motorcyclists from 6 December 2010 for first-time learner permit holders.  This is part of the national policy following the recommendations made and accepted by the Department of Transport and the then Minister prior to its introduction.</p> <p>IBT recognises the vulnerability of motorcyclists as road users who need additional training to keep them safe on our roads.  A driver must complete a programme of IBT with an improved IBT instructor before taking a motorcycle out on a road.  The IBT programme is a minimum of 16 hours' duration and a certificate of satisfactory completion is issued to each learner after completing the training.  There are situations where a learner can do what is known as a conversion module, which is a modified version of the IBT programme.  This is available for people who have completed the IBT on a smaller motorcycle and then take out a separate permit for a larger motorcycle.</p> <p>While motorcycles in the heavier category are clearly more powerful and capable of much higher speeds than category AM motorcycles, the Road Safety Authority, RSA, considers the risk associated with riding any type of motorcycle to be similar and the deaths and serious injuries to be disproportionate to those related to category B.  The IBT modules that relate to motorcycles encompass all aspects relevant to higher powered machines and category AM.  There is no doubt that the learnings from the IBT course are relevant and beneficial to riders of category AM motorcycles and contribute effectively to the goal of having a fuller learning experience and greater understanding of the risks and dangers associated with this vulnerable road group.</p> <p>Although those who have category B licences have road experience which, undoubtedly, is of significant benefit to the driving of a category AM motorcycle, such drivers will not have had the learning specific to riding a two-wheel vehicle.  The Minister for Transport is confident that the position that exists now is the correct one and that a person must be tested specifically on the moped before being granted a full licence.</p> <p>The Senator, in raising this issue, accepts there needs to be some extra training, but there are difficulties in terms of costs and requirements.  It is something that could be pursued in conjunction with the RSA and the Department of Transport.  I will bring back to the Minister the points the Senator has raised, which are valid and feed into this argument.  It may be a matter that can be looked at again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" speakername="Barry Ward" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#C00500"><p>I thank the Minister of State and appreciate his remarks.  I am sorry the Minister does not have plans to change this rule.  I hope we will be able to convince him otherwise.  There are still inconsistencies.  I acknowledge the road safety imperative involved and that being on two or three wheels is different from being cocooned in a car, and we can see that in the way the respective drivers behave.</p> <p>However, the W category for work vehicles and tractors is still included in category B licences.  We know there are frequent accidents on farms involving these vehicles, yet people who passed their driving test in a car do not have to do any extra or separate training to reinforce safety protocols for work vehicles.  We have excluded the category of moped.</p> <p>The Minister of State is correct that the position is not consistent across the European Union.  In Denmark, for example, there is an LK category for smaller mopeds.  We could have something like that, or we could include something in the driving or theory test or require some other theory test to be done.  We have an unnecessary penalisation of certain categories, in particular young people.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1505" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#D00100"><p>I again thank Senator Ward for raising this issue.  I will certainly talk to the Minister of State, Deputy Naughton, who is sorry she could not be here today, and to the Minister, Deputy Eamon Ryan, about it.  I might not be in a position to convince her but I have no doubt that, with the arguments he has just put to me, the Senator will be able to if he gets a chance.  I will encourage her to take some time to listen to this debate and perhaps to meet the Senator to tease the issue out.  It is certainly worth looking at.</p> <p>The Senator flagged an issue in the area of agriculture.  We are making changes with regard to aspects of farm safety, particularly in respect of off-road vehicles on farms.  There are concerns in that area.  We are working with the farm partnerships, through the Health and Safety Authority, to make changes and bring in extra training, mainly in the area of quad bikes.  There will be lead-in time for this over the next year or two.  This is an area in which we can prevent unnecessary loss of life.  We need an ongoing conversation about safety.  From the Senator's contribution, I know he totally buys into the safety aspect.  It is a matter of how to achieve it.  I will urge the Minister of State to engage with him on this matter.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.23" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#D00150">Departmental Strategies</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1681" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#D00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State, Deputy Rabbitte, for being in the Chamber.  I wanted to speak with the Minister today about the Youth Justice Strategy 2021-2027 and the progress made so far in addressing the serious delays in processing times for young people interacting with the courts and youth justice systems.  For context, an article was published in <i>The Irish Times</i>a number of weeks ago which highlighted the stark reality for many young people engaging with the criminal justice system.  It spoke of an &quot;endless series of delays&quot; that pose a serious barrier which can negatively impact a young person's mental health and which breaks the temporal connection between an offence and a concluding outcome.  In some of the cases referenced in the article, young people have been waiting up to seven years for their cases to come to a conclusion.  The UN Convention on the Rights of the Child states that children facing criminal charges have a right to have the matter determined without delay but our youth justice system does not currently facilitate this.  I know the Department is aware of the issue and that there are various actions within the latest youth justice strategy targeting the minimisation of these delays but the young people and young adults at present interacting with the youth justice system cannot wait until 2027.</p><p>I ask for an update on the impact of the youth justice strategy on waiting times.  I know that we are only in year 2 of the strategy but we need to provide reassurance to those impacted by delays.  The strategy promised to establish a national governance and strategy group to guide its implementation but I am unclear as to whether this has been achieved.  If it has, what is the make-up of the group's membership?  A mid-term review is promised in the third year of the strategy's lifetime but, without the ongoing oversight of a governance and strategy group, the strategy risks repeating the same mistakes.</p><p>Community representatives have tentatively welcomed the 2021 youth strategy but they are not without concerns because history has shown that many of our young people have not received the investment and attention they require.  In budget 2021, &euro;6.2 million was allocated to interventions under the youth justice strategy.  I notice the same figure has been referenced in respect of funding for youth diversion projects.  While greater investment in youth justice is welcome, there needs to be a clear delineation between the work of youth diversion projects, which are overseen by An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, and the work of the community-based youth organisations.  The solutions to the problems at the heart of youth justice lie within the communities affected by them.</p><p>There are a number of specific areas covered by the youth justice strategy that I would like to get some clarification on today.  The first is the issue of the offence committed as a minor being dealt with as an adult.  If young people turn 18 while awaiting the conclusion a particular charge, they lose the protections offered by the Children Act 2001, including the right to anonymity.  In addition, if handed down a custodial sentence, they will be detained in an adult prison for a crime they committed as a child.  The youth justice strategy suggests that an amendment to the Children Act could be considered so that its provisions could apply to the processing of an offence with reference to age at time it is committed irrespective of the age of the young person when the case actually comes to court.  Has this suggested amendment been advanced at all?</p><p>I have heard some anecdotal reports from youth workers that some young people committing first-time offences involving the possession of small amounts of drugs are being charged as a first port of call rather than being referred to a juvenile liaison officer, JLO.  This completely contradicts the Government's commitment to a health-led approach on drug use.  The youth justice strategy advises that the Department should prioritise research, discussion papers and pilot initiatives on the prevalence and impacts of trends on issues such as drug use.  Will the Minister of State clarify where we are in that process?  I strongly believe that we need to view and respond to drug use in a very different way than we currently do.  We cannot right all the wrongs of the past but we can chart a very different path for our children and young people.  I would welcome clarification from the Minister of State as to how the youth justice strategy will support this journey.  I thank the Minister of State again for her time.  I look forward to her response.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1484" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#D00300"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this issue today.  I am taking this debate on behalf of the Minister of State, Deputy Browne, who sends his apologies.  I hope his office contacted the Senator's before this debate.</p> <p>As the Senator will be aware, the courts are independent in their functions under the Constitution and the law.  The matter of scheduling court cases is administered by the Courts Service in consultation with the Judiciary.  With the exception of more serious offences, criminal prosecutions involving children are generally heard in the District Court, which operates as the Children Court, with procedures specified in the Children Act 2001.  The Minister for Justice plays no role in these independent functions.</p> <p>The Youth Justice Strategy 2021-2027, published by the Minister, Deputy McEntee, and the Minister of State, Deputy Browne, last year, contains a range of actions that aim to improve the interaction between the justice system and those young people who come into contact with it.  As the Senator has noted, the strategy contains a strategic objective, objective 3.4, to prioritise processing of children and young adult cases to minimise delays, including with regard to the role of Garda case managers.  This will include specific actions on how the case manager role and other mechanisms can be used to reduce delays in bringing cases to court, to minimise the number of court appearances for each child or young person, to ensure effective practice so that young persons are fully informed and aware of what is involved in the court process and to provide appropriate review mechanisms.  I assure the Senator that these actions will be taken forward as part of the implementation of the strategy. </p> <p>More broadly, the Government is committed to ensuring the courts are adequately resourced to ensure the efficient administration of justice and continues to commit substantial resources to enable this.  There is a total gross allocation of &euro;164 million for the courts Vote, which includes an allocation of a further &euro;1 million for the new courts modernisation programme, building on the &euro;8 million already provided in the Estimates for 2021 and retained for 2022.</p> <p>Significant and sustained efforts have been made to minimise disruption to courts due to Covid-19, with priority continuing to be given to urgent matters such as domestic violence applications.  Throughout the pandemic, the Judiciary and the Courts Service have worked closely and innovated through the use of technology to maintain the highest level of court activity possible.  Addressing the waiting times built up in some areas during the pandemic while at the same time meeting the goals set out in the Courts Service modernisation programme will be a significant challenge for the courts.  The Courts Service management, both nationally and locally, continues to work closely with the Judiciary to deal with the consequences of the pandemic and to look to schedule extra sittings to deal with delays within the system.  However, it is likely the pressure on the courts system will remain a feature for the short to medium term.</p> <p>I take on board the Senator's suggestions regarding the amendment of the Children Act and offences committed as a minor being dealt with when the person in question is a young adult.  I will also bring what the Senator raised regarding juvenile liaison officers to the attention of the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1681" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#D00400"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  Even though I am always happy to see her here in the Chamber, I was unaware that the Minister would not be here today.  It is not the Minister of State's fault but, historically, I have always looked to withdraw my Commencement matters in such instances in order to ensure that nuanced questions, such as those around the JLO and timing out of the system, can be answered on the spot by the Minister.  I just want to put that on the record.  That is not a criticism directed at the Minister of State.</p> <p>Timing out of childhood is obviously a significant issue and Covid has not necessarily been the thing to delay these cases.  Some children have faced delays of six or seven years.  That is a long delay in dealing with a charge in anybody's life.  If anything, not having the matter dealt with encourages the continuation of criminal behaviour because you are just waiting on something, you are not really sure and your life is on hold.  Has the governance and strategy group been set up and what is its make-up?  I have one more suggestion for the Minister.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Lynn Ruane:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2481"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2481&amp;amp;pid=LynnRuane&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It involves my spent convictions legislation that will, hopefully, make its way through the D&aacute;il.  The youth work strategies and legislation acknowledge a young person up to the age of 24.  This is what we need to do when we are looking at youth strategies.  A person does not just become an adult when he or she turns 18.  We should be extending this up to the age of 24.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1484" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#E00200"><p>Yet again, I thank the Senator.  The Minister of State, Deputy Browne, says he welcomes the additional &euro;6.7 million provided for in budget 2022, representing an increase over one third in support for the youth justice service.  This budget funding provides the resources to kick-start delivery of key objectives in the youth justice strategy and, in particular, the programme to expand and deepen the range of supports made available through local youth diversion project services.</p> <p>The potential expansion of youth diversion projects to young adults aged 18 to 24 is designed to reduce the time a young person spends within the system and to improve the positive outcome for that young person.  These actions will also have an impact on the number of cases brought before the courts, further helping to reduce the delays currently being experienced. </p> <p>Dedicated cross-agency structures have been established to guide the implementation of the youth justice strategy, including the matter raised by the Senator, as well as expert research support to assist in developing enhanced policies, programmes and practice.  In addition, the Minister of State, Deputy Browne, chairs a youth justice advisory group, which includes a broad range of community and expert stakeholders, that provides advice and expert insights to help pursue the wide range of objectives contained in the strategy.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.29" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#E00300">General Practitioner Services</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1643" speakername="Lorraine Clifford-Lee" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#E00400"><p>I thank the Minister of State for coming to the House to discuss the very important issue of GP visit cards for six and seven year-olds.  As she knows, GP visit cards for those aged under six were introduced a number of years ago and have been a very helpful mechanism for parents to access free GP healthcare for their children.</p> <p>Children can get very sick very frequently when they are young.  Having free GP visits ensures that no family has to work out how sick a child is before it must bring him or her to the doctor and pay a significant fee of &euro;60.  This might happen twice or three times in one week.  Children can get very sick very rapidly.  If a parent is making a judgment call that the child is not sick enough to warrant the spending of an extra &euro;60 from a family budget, the child could get very sick very rapidly.  It is a position no family wants to find itself in.  No family should have to go without fuel, food, heating or petrol to get to work or school.  Those are the decisions families make every day.</p> <p>In June 2020, legislation extending GP visit cards to all children under 12 was passed.  It was announced in budget 2022 last October that free GP visit cards for six and seven year-olds would be introduced this year.  This has not yet happened.  Given the severe pressures on families and the rising price of electricity, gas, motor fuel and food, I am appealing to the Minister of State to announce today that the commencement of GP visit cards for six and seven year-olds will take place imminently.  Parents cannot wait any longer.  There is a significant squeeze on families.  I know the Minister of State is very aware of what families up and down the country are facing and the real impact of introducing a measure like this on families and health provision for children.  It would be a very welcome measure if it was announced today.</p> <p>I spoke with the Minister for Health this morning about this issue.  He understands the urgent need to relieve costs for families.  I believe talks with the Irish Medical Organisation, IMO, are ongoing but I think we should prioritise this matter.  Things happened overnight during Covid because it was a crisis.  The cost of living for families all around the country is also a crisis and needs to be prioritised.  I also believe we need to move beyond those aged six and seven quite urgently but given that the commitment regarding six and seven year-olds was in the budget, that needs to happen this year without any further delay.  I look forward to hearing the Minister of State's response.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1484" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#E00500"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this matter, which I am taking on behalf of the Minister for Health.  As the House will know, the Government is committed to increasing access to GP care for more children.  Following the provision of GP care without charges for all children under six years of age, the Government plans to expand GP care without charges to all children up to and including the age of 12 on a phased basis, beginning with all children aged six and seven.</p> <p>Having a healthy childhood can provide the basis for having good health in adult life.  Removing cost as a potential barrier for more children will reduce the financial burden on young families in accessing GP care.  Improved access to GP services can help build the relationship between the GP and the patient and help increase the likelihood that conditions requiring ongoing care are identified at an earlier stage.  The Senator made a valid point.  A normal temperature in a child can spike rapidly so it should not be cost-prohibitive for families to access GP care.  I reared three children.  All three could get sick in one week and I could have three visits very quickly, not to mention 12.  </p> <p>Currently all children aged under six years have automatic eligibility to a GP visit card and therefore have access to GP services without charges.  Legislation enacted in 2020 provides for the phased expansion of GP care without fees to all children aged 12 years and under in three phases - children aged six and seven, children aged eight and nine and children aged ten, 11 and 12.</p> <p>It was previously intended to commence the first phase of the expansion - the provision of GP care without charges to all children aged six and seven - from September 2020.  However, it was necessary to reconsider the commencement date due to the emergence of Covid-19 and in recognition of the increased pressure that this expansion could place on GPs.  General practice continues to play a vital role in combating the Covid-19 pandemic.  There has been an increased demand for GP services during this time and the provision of those services has been made more difficult.  In addition, GPs have been called upon to provide additional services, including referring patients for Covid-19 testing, as appropriate, and helping to administer Covid-19 vaccinations, largely to older and more vulnerable persons.  It is important to ensure that additional pressures placed on general practice do not limit its capacity to meet the needs of all patients in the community.</p> <p>Notwithstanding that, I am pleased to say that budget 2022 has provided for the expansion this year of GP care without charges to children aged six and seven.  The Department of Health and the HSE are now working on the roll-out of the expansion.  This will, of course, require consultations with the IMO to agree the contractual terms.  When commenced, it is estimated that this first phase of the expansion will provide GP care without charges for up to approximately 80,000 additional children aged six and seven.</p> <p>More generally, the Government has taken numerous steps to increase capacity in general practice to allow for the expanding of GP care without charges over time and on a phased basis, as proposed by Sl&aacute;intecare.  In particular, expenditure on general practice has been significantly increased under the 2019 GP agreement and measures have been introduced to make general practice more sustainable.  It is also worth noting that the number of entrants to GP training increased from 120 in 2009 to 233 in 2021, with further increases planned.  That is the answer the Minister gave to me.  I am conscious the Senator had conversations with him since I received my script and I hope he had positive news for her.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1643" speakername="Lorraine Clifford-Lee" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#E00600"><p>I know the Minister of State would be very much aware of the pressures on families and how important free GP visits have been for families to date.  I am disappointed that no date has been given for this expansion.  It is very welcome that it is acknowledged that it needs to happen urgently.  I know negotiations can be sensitive and I am also aware of the pressures faced by our GPs over the past 12 months but these children are patients of those practices and will be accessing the service in any event.  All we are doing is providing relief for families.  It is not as if families will suddenly start flooding into GP practices if they get the card.  They are deciding between putting food on the table or bringing a sick child to the GP.  When they do not access primary care, they end up in accident and emergency, which costs the State even more, so we really need to prioritise this measure.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Lorraine Clifford-Lee:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2461"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2461&amp;amp;pid=LorraineCliffordLee&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I will be back in contact with the Minister about it.  I want to get a date for this.  The families are waiting for this and need it urgently.  I have been in contact with many families about the matter.  They have been asking about it specifically.  They are very conscious of this.  There are children who timed out when they turned six and are now in a lacuna.  Those children are eight years old now and have been without free GP visits.  This matter is very important, and I will be back in contact in respect of it.  This is a very practical measure that can relieve the rising costs for families.</p><p>I thank the Minister of State for attending.  I hope she will have a word with the Minister about this matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1640" speakername="Pat Casey" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#F00200"><p>The Minister of State has the last word.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1484" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#F00300"><p>I thank the Senator.  She is being very rational in the context of her proposals.  If we do not do that early intervention piece, it has a knock-on effect whereby it is more costly in the long run to our health system.  I urge the Department of Health and those with whom it is having consultations , be it the HSE or GP practices, to talk about the same cohort of people who need that care.  Now is a timely opportunity, especially when all the other talks are taking place in the context of how we can support families.  Now is the time to have that conversation in the round and to look at GP care for children aged six and seven.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.36" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar fionra&iacute; ag 11.21 a.m. agus cuireadh t&uacute;s leis ar&iacute;s ag 12.02 p.m.

Sitting suspended at 11.21 a.m. and resumed at 12.02 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.37" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#K00100">An tOrd Gnó - Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#K00200"><p>Today's Order of Business is No. 1, motion regarding the address to Seanad &Eacute;ireann by MEPs representing the European Parliament South constituency, to be taken on the conclusion of the Order of Business, without debate; and No. 2, Private Members' business, Safe Access to Termination of Pregnancy Services Bill 2021 - Committee Stage, to be taken at 1.15 p.m. and to adjourn after two hours if not previously concluded.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1641" speakername="Shane Cassells" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#K00300"><p>I support the Order of Business as outlined by the Leader.</p> <p>There is a lot of excitement and pent up anticipation among politicians in these Houses today about the imminent announcement of sports capital funding for our sports clubs, which will allow for much-needed development.  Such is the excitement one would think guys in here will be donning tracksuits and showing their own sporting prowess.  I am confident that the Minister of State with responsibility for sport, Deputy Chambers, will don his Santy costume and deliver handsomely for sports clubs.</p> <p>When the euphoria from this dies down, however, we will require a reappraisal of the funding models we apply and how best to use the resources we have at our disposal.  We have the crazy scenario in towns and villages across the country of GAA, soccer and rugby clubs all trying to develop facilities independently.  They are fundraising among the same local people who probably have kids in two or three of the clubs.  The concept of municipal sports grounds, so prevalent across Europe, including just across the water in England, is considered alien here.  It is almost as if we cannot even consider it.  Of course, that is due mainly to historical reasons, including the application of a ban by the GAA on people competing in other sports and on the use of facilities by other sports.  We have got past that, however.  I have made this point before and have been told by sporting commentators that I am crazy and so forth, but for 20 years I stood as a sports supporter on the sidelines and I have seen some really bad facilities.  I have seen really good ones as well.</p> <p>I believe it is not too late, especially when clubs are growing, in particular in the sphere of ladies' sport, whether soccer, GAA or rugby.  The concept of municipal sports grounds should still be embraced and developed, especially given that we will see huge population growth in certain areas.  We should have a proper debate in this Chamber on the whole model of sports funding and how best to apply it.  As I have said before, sports get discussed in these Houses only if there is a major announcement or a bad news story.  We should embrace sports and discuss how best to use the resources.  I look forward to the announcement by the Minister of State, Deputy Chambers, this week about sports capital funding.  I congratulate all those who will be in receipt of this funding.  I hope they get the best use out of it to deliver for our children and adults, but I think we can do even more in how we look at it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#K00400"><p>Today the Cabinet is meeting to discuss what will happen in the inflationary situation in which we find ourselves as a country.  This is not just an Irish problem; it is an international problem.  I want to see the squeezed middle as well as the most vulnerable in society benefit.</p> <p>I was talking yesterday to a person who has a very large mortgage and who told me that childcare is extremely expensive, that the cost of filling the car with diesel to go to work has increased by a third and that they find it very difficult to make ends meet.  I welcome the electricity bonus or rebate that is due and hope that it is significantly increased, but we need to look at doing something in the areas of childcare, transport and fuel.</p> <p>I also call on the financial institutions to be flexible with people, to give them breaks in their mortgages if they need them and to facilitate them with interest-only repayments for a period.  We all hope that what is happening at the moment with our economy and the inflationary situation in which we find ourselves is temporary.  The Government certainly will do its bit, but no matter what it does, I have no doubt but that it will not be enough and will not be welcomed.  All other stakeholders, including utility providers and financial institutions, need to step up to the plate as well.</p> <p>I have raised in this House before the issue of the cost of public transport in rural Ireland versus the cost of public transport in urban Ireland.  It is an awful lot cheaper to get the train from Maynooth to Dublin than it is to get the train from Ennis to Galway or from Ennis to Limerick.  There needs to be a fundamental rethink of the cost of public transport.  It should be equal throughout the country.  The people living in Ennis who commute to work in Limerick or Galway should have equal access and should not pay any more than the people in Maynooth who work in Dublin.  I would like a debate on the cost of public transport at some stage because I believe that the intentions are good.  We see what is happening with greenways, investment in public transport and upgrading of the train and bus fleets.  The improvements that have been made to the Bus &Eacute;ireann timetables in recent years have been fantastic, but there is an inequality there and it needs to be addressed.</p> <p>I agree with Senator Cassells about the sports capital grants.  We need a fundamental debate on the methodology used in respect of the grants.  For every club that gets a sports capital grant, there should be an audit of its accessibility for people with disabilities in using its services.  If the State is funding projects and programmes in clubs around the country, they should be accessible to everybody.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#K00500"><p>Yesterday we had a very interesting engagement in this House with three Galway Senators all sitting along the same bench, which was interesting in itself, as was the dynamic of the debate.  The issue was about engagement.  Senator Pauline O'Reilly talked about Galway and the bypass road.  What provoked me to think more about it was that I saw &quot;Oireachtas Report&quot; last night and An Taoiseach engaging in the D&aacute;il Chamber on people's record of objections.  We need to clarify this once and for all.</p><p>In today's edition of <i>The</i><i>Irish Times</i>there are two major stories.  In one, Project East Meath Limited is pursuing a planning issue through the High Court.  Then there is a story about Drogheda SouthGate Shopping Centre.  Then we have Balbriggan Community Council seeking to overturn approval for 95 apartments.  Then we had Government Members opposing wind energy in County Clare.  I make the point that they are entitled to do that.  Today's edition of <i>The Irish Times</i>carries another story of a Cork city apartment scheme on Lower Friars Walk, which five county councillors are opposing.  I agree that they have a right to engage.  I support that absolutely.  By the way, the opposition comes from all political parties and none.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Victor Boyhan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2463"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2463&amp;amp;pid=VictorBoyhan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->On one hand, we are hearing some criticism of people engaging.  All of us are representatives.  We represent communities.  I sound a note of caution.  The Minister of State, Deputy Peter Burke, is coming to the House with legislation and I fully accept that.  I am supportive of reform of the planning process in terms of making it faster but I am not in support of anything that would curtail the right of our citizens or elected representatives to make representations regarding planning.  There is a subtle difference.  We want a faster process but there is a mood out there that citizens, Deputies, Senators and city and county councillors are somehow objecting to housing for the sake of it so we need to be clear about it.  I went to the trouble of looking on the board and saw that various Government Ministers are putting in objections.  I have no problem with that either.  We need to be clear.  We do not need to talk out of both sides of our mouths.  The point I am trying to make is that we must enable and encourage our citizens to participate in the planning process.  I look forward to the new legislation but the focus must be on a faster system.  We must have due regard for everyone's opinion.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1661" speakername="Pippa Hackett" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#L00200"><p>This morning, the Minister for Agriculture announced the launch of a tender process for the management of co-operation projects as part of the CAP's agri-environmental scheme.  That all sounds like a bit of a mouthful but what it actually means is that we are on the cusp of doing things in a different way - a way I believe will be hugely beneficial to the environment, land and farmers.</p> <p>Members may all be familiar with the term "EIP", which stands for European innovation partnership.  Over the past few years, many farmers in Ireland have been involved in EIPs.  They include projects like the Burren, hen harrier, pearl mussel and Duncannon EIPs.  These are projects in which a landscape-level approach is taken and farmers work collectively to deliver whatever that land, the rivers that flow through their land or the species common to their land require.  Thanks to the knowledge, buy-in and belief of those farmers, these projects developed local solutions to local problems.  Our EIPs are hugely successful.  Indeed in Europe, they are hailed as ground-breaking.</p> <p>I am really proud of the fact that we are extending this locally-led approach in the upcoming CAP.  Eight areas have been identified as having a particular environmental characteristic.  Farmers in those areas will be invited to engage in a new agri-environmental scheme through the co-operation project teams.  The tender announced this morning is to put those teams in place.  It is a large undertaking so I thank all those involved.  I encourage farmers in the relevant areas to engage in the coming months.  </p> <p>This week also represented a positive week for Offaly tourism.  F&aacute;ilte Ireland announced yesterday that it has expanded its footprint for Ireland's Hidden Heartlands to include Offaly along with Cavan, Westmeath and part of Tipperary.  The Hidden Heartlands brand is centred around Ireland's natural rural beauty, untouched heritage and outdoor activities - things Ireland's hidden gem Offaly has in abundance.</p> <p>I am delighted Offaly is being recognised for all it has to offer.  At the Slieve Bloom Mountains, the most unspoiled and uncontested in the country, people will find a walking trial to suit every ability as well as 35 km of mountain bike trails and forest roads.  At Lough Boora Discovery Park, a wealth of floral displays and wildlife can be spotted among the grasslands, lakes and wetlands.  One can explore the 50 km of trails and see the natural recolonisation and pasturelands in the Midlands Bog and see how it provides a new habitat for the park's biodiversity.  Offaly has an abundance of bogs.  While we all know the importance of preserving our bogs in the battle against climate change, they also offer a unique habitat for wildlife and biodiversity.  At the raised bog in Clara, one can walk the boardwalk and experience 10,000 years of history in 10 sq. km.  Where else holds such an honour?  While this is just a snapshot, I hope I have raised awareness of this beautiful region and shown what Offaly, a county with nature and communities at its heart, has to offer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#L00300"><p>The first issue I would like to raise is a request for the Leader to schedule time for the Amnesty International report on apartheid in Israel.  The findings of this report will come as no surprise to those of us who have visited the country.  The Seanad should be afforded the time to debate the findings of that report.</p><p>The main issue I wish to raise is related to the cost of living.  Something we often lose sight of is the cost borne by schools, which are also feeling the pinch through the rising cost of electricity.  Unfortunately, we know there is a &quot;no brainer&quot; solution to helping schools cover the costs of their electricity, that is, allowing them to generate their own electricity with solar panels on roofs.  A simple change in the regulations exempting schools from the need to apply for planning permission for solar panels would unleash massive demand that is currently blocked with unnecessary red tape and planning costs.  I know there was a commitment in the climate action plan that by quarter 1 of this year, we would have those planning regulations but the latest parliamentary question response in January is now setting a timeline later in 2022.  We are already seeing slippage in the climate action plan, the annexe of which was launched in December.  </p><p>This morning, we opened <i>The Irish Times</i>to see that the Dublin Airport Authority is lodging an application for planning permission for a new solar panel farm.  Any of us who have been following the solar panels on school debacle are bewildered and dismayed because the excuse the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage has given to schools about why they cannot be exempted from having to apply for planning permission was that the Department of Housing, Local Government and Heritage needed to carry out a study to make sure the solar panels would not interfere with planes flying into airports.  They then reached a compromise and said we would get interim regulations that would allow schools to put solar panels on their roofs once the schools were nowhere near airports while they worked on this airport study.  The interim regulations have taken longer than the full regulations would take and in the intervening period, Dublin Airport Authority is now applying for permission to build a solar panel farm.  Members can see where I am going.  It is farcical.  Schools are crying out for the ability to put up solar panels without spending thousands of euro on applying for planning permission.  They want to be part of the transition to a decarbonised future.  </p><p>It also does not bode well for the implementation of the climate action plan if the Government cannot get the simple things right.  This is low-hanging fruit.  These are simple win-win measures so what hope do we have of halving our emissions by 2030 if we cannot get this sort of stuff over the line?  The national climate action delivery board whose role is to hold each Department and public body accountable for the delivery of actions set out in the climate action plan did not even meet in 2020 despite a commitment that it would meet on a quarterly basis.  Could the Leader write to the Taoiseach to explore what action can be taken and for heads to be banged together to remove these unnecessary blockages and allow schools to generate their own electricity?  I also ask that she give consideration to scheduling time for a debate on the Amnesty International report on Israel.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" speakername="Mark Wall" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#L00400"><p>I welcome the long-awaited report by the Commission on the Future of the Defence Forces, which was published yesterday.  I welcome the emphasis on personnel.  It is vital that the Minister for Defence immediately agrees with the recommendation in the report that the representative associations be allowed affiliate with ICTU, an outcome that I, on behalf of the Labour Party, have been calling for in this House over the past number of years.  This should be the first important step in delivering the outcomes of this report and can be done immediately.</p> <p>The recommendation of the commission that the blanket exclusion of the Defence Forces from the Organisation of Working Time Act be removed is also to be welcomed.  For serving members, getting rid of what many describe as free labour by rigorously enforcing the working time directive with appropriate compensation for those who work longer hours would be welcomed.  I also welcome the emphasis placed on women and indeed men who want flexible and remote working opportunities.  The bottom line is that in order to build our Defence Forces, we must retain the expertise and skills that exist in the Defence Forces and in doing so, pay, allowances and flexible work practices must be the first outcome of this new report.  I would have liked to see more emphasis on accommodation for those who enlist and serve.  This is an issue of retention of those who serve given the housing crisis.  </p> <p>We in the Labour Party welcome the report.  I look forward to discussing its findings with the Minister, as previously indicated.  There is a need to look at how this report will be implemented.  I believe, as does my party, that we must ensure that the Minister of State is at the head or driving this report forward such is its importance and how critical it is to the future of our national security.  Government must consider releasing him from other important jobs he has.  Given the serious workload of the senior Minister, we believe this is critical.  We cannot allow this report to sit on the shelf.  This must be the watershed moment about which the Minister spoke when he was in the Seanad last week.  There can be no turning back.  We must invest in our Defence Forces and, critically, the representative associations of those who serve must be front and centre of the implementation of this report.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Mark Wall:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=MarkWall&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> I welcome the report on gambling that was published yesterday by the Health Research Board.  It is essential that we see the promised Government legislation on gambling.  The report in question highlights that we could have 137,000 people on the gambling spectrum, and 12,000 problem gamblers.  It also states that this figure may be an underestimate in light of the lack of responses from young males.  Whatever the true figure, we cannot allow those estimated 137,000 people to continue to be at risk of gambling addiction and to have the potential for 120,000 of them to develop an even more serious habit.  This is a public health issue and those affected need help.  They also need legislation straight away.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1632" speakername="Frances Black" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#M00200"><p>I wish to raise the issue of the Police Ombudsman for Northern Ireland's report into the collusion of state forces and unionist gangs in the murder of innocent people only 100 miles from here.  The report by the ombudsman details how informers were retained even after they were suspected by the RUC of having been involved in murder.  The use of murder gangs by the British was a tactic in many of their colonies, so it should not be surprising there was a policy of state collusion with loyalist gangs.  The report states, "police prioritised intelligence gathering and protection of sources, over the detection of serious crime and their obligation to bring the perpetrators of those crimes to justice".</p> <p>The ombudsman's investigation identified eight Ulster Defence Association-Ulster Freedom Fighters members who were linked, through intelligence, to the murders or attempted murders of 27 people.  All eight of these individuals were found to be police informants.  Weapons were donated to these killers by the British Army and police gave weapons back to these killers after they were confiscated.  Another very worrying finding of the report is that the police did not warn people of real and imminent threats when doing so may have saved lives.  The report shows that the state colluded in the murder of innocent people and there was routine destruction of evidence and documentation, as well as failure by the RUC special branch to share information on murder suspects.  It is devastating and horrific.  The report demonstrates just how rotten the actions of RUC special branch, and, without doubt, the British Army force research unit and MI5, were in terms of the use of murder gangs to carry out the assassination of innocent people.</p> <p>It is now apparent why the British Government is proposing a Troubles amnesty.  This must be opposed and the demands of the families that someone is held accountable for the murders of their loved ones must be upheld.  It is not only the perpetrators of these crimes who must be held accountable, but the people at the highest level who sanctioned these murders.  My heart goes out to the families who lost loved ones and who now realise the very police who were supposed to be investigating these murders were actually colluding with those responsible and even supplying them with weapons.  I would like the Minister to comment on the report.</p> <p>Like my colleague, Senator Boylan, I reiterate my call for a debate on Israeli apartheid in light of the publication last week of the report on the matter by Amnesty International.  This week, Michael Ben-Yair, a former Israeli Attorney General, also concluded that the government he previously served is an apartheid regime.  We cannot allow for the sting to be taken out of Amnesty's declaration and we must acknowledge the role we can play in keeping this issue front and centre of the work in this House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1671" speakername="Erin McGreehan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#M00300"><p>I did not get a chance to speak in the debate on the matter on Tuesday, but I wish to highlight and congratulate the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine on the new scheme permitting the planting of up to 1 ha of native Irish trees without a licence.  Anyone who knows me is aware of my absolute gr&aacute; for native Irish trees.  This is the month of the rowan tree - the mountain ash - which provides protection for one's home, so I recommend that all Senators plant a rowan tree, also known as mountain ash.  It is a beautiful tree that protects your home.  That is the power of native Irish trees.</p> <p>An issue in the news this morning, and one on which I have previously called for a debate, is hedgerow management and, indeed, the eco-schemes within the new Common Agricultural Policy, CAP.  I refer to the power that is vested in hedgerows the length and breadth of the country.  The penal laws left a positive legacy in the context of fields and lands having to be walled off with hedgerows.  They are biodiversity highways that sequester thousands of units of carbon every single year.  There are so many farmers who are carbon neutral because of hedgerows.  It is time to start talking about how to manage that and protect it.  There is a need to educate farmers to allow them to protect our beautiful hedgerows because there is so much rich biodiversity - flora and fauna - within them.  We should harvest that power.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1629" speakername="Garret Ahearn" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#M00400"><p>I wish to raise an issue that I bring up quite a bit, namely, childcare.  I wish to raise it again because almost every week it is getting worse for childcare on three levels.  Parents are at their wits' end because they cannot get childcare for their kids.  Parents who have been working from home for the past two years but who are now going back into the workplace and need to get childcare are being told they cannot get it until August at the earliest.  Some are being told it will not be available until next February.  They are at their wits' end and are panicking.  There is also the issue of people who work in childcare deciding to leave it because the money is just not worth it.  They cannot be paid enough.  These are people who went to college for four years and want to be in childcare and work with young kids and babies but, for financial reasons, they are deciding they have to leave.   There is also the fact that management are now at their wits' end because they cannot find replacements for people who are leaving, so the management themselves are deciding to leave.</p> <p>I acknowledge that the Minister for Children, Equality, Disability, Integration and Youth, Deputy O'Gorman, is doing a phenomenal amount of work in his Department.  He is a fantastic Minister and has made changes.  Supports put in place by this Government in the past two years have been recognised and appreciated by the industry.  They are clearly not enough, however.  Plans that are to be brought forward by next September will dramatically change the childcare sector.  That is really important but there are many businesses that will not survive until then.  I have spoken to numerous childcare providers and they really do not think they will make it to September.  We need emergency funding for the sector to keep them going.   It just does not make sense that people cannot get their children in because there are not enough spaces, while people are leaving the industry because they cannot get paid.  Until we recognise childcare providers as educators and pay them the correct wage as such, this issue will not be solved.  Every week I see the work done in the Play and Learn cr&egrave;che in Clonmel, which my child attends.  These people are educators.  I see my child develop and grow on the back of what they do.  They need to be paid a fair wage and management need to be supported to be able to pay them that wage to retain the employment in these businesses.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1691" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#M00500"><p>I rise to ask the Leader to facilitate a debate on the issue raised by my learned colleague, Senator Wall, namely, the recent report on the Defence Forces.  It is sad to realise that the Chief of Staff of the Defence Forces, the Minister and the conclusions of the White Paper all basically acknowledge the serious shortcoming in the Defence Forces.  Numbers are declining.  The Chief of Staff mentioned this morning that some Naval Service vessels have put to sea without a full complement of men or women.  There are declining numbers.  The pay situation is poor and there are poor job and promotion opportunities.  Morale is very low.  We are supposed to have a Naval Service and an Army that might protect our State and coastline but, regrettably, we rank last in the world compared with countries of a similar size and population.  That is very sad.  Yesterday, I spoke on the issue of penalty points for fishermen and masters of seagoing vessels in the context of fishing infringements, yet not alone is the Naval Service, which is already very compact and relatively small by international standards, obliged to police Irish boats, of which there are many - some of the fishermen say they are over-policed - but there are significant numbers of fishing vessels from Spain, France and Germany coming into Irish waters.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Denis O'Donovan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=1988"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1988&amp;amp;pid=DenisODonovan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->There is no way whatsoever that our relatively small naval fleet can do that work.  This matter was raised in a more professional and knowledgeable way by Senator Wall.  I want to concur with his remarks.  If something is not done shortly about our Defence Forces and Naval Service, morale will suffer and the numbers involved will get smaller and smaller.  A significant amount of money will have to be put into this, but I appreciate that the Minister has put his hands up and agreed that what the report says is correct and true.  Changes must be made sooner rather than later.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1695" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#N00200"><p>I welcome the announcement in the D&aacute;il from the Minister of State, Deputy Butler, that there will be an independent review at University Hospital Limerick carried out by HIQA.  This is very welcome news because it is something I have been looking for for quite some time.  I would like the support of the Leader for the publication of the report when it is produced.  It is important that HIQA makes unannounced visits to hospitals because once people know it is coming things happen.  It is important that it sees the hospital operating under normal circumstances.  People are still waiting on trolleys there and the situation is very difficult not just for patients but staff.</p> <p>Film in Limerick has been involved in the filming of "Smother" and "Hidden Assets".  The project has been funded through F&Iacute;S and Screen Ireland.  This is welcome news because there is in apprenticeship programme under TUS in Limerick.  Film in Limerick is also funded by Innovation Limerick.  A combination of the local authority and education sector is involved.  This shows that Limerick and the mid-west are open to the film industry.  Troy Studios, one of the largest film studios in Ireland, is on our doorstep in the old Dell factory.  It is good to see funding being provided to local areas and trainees being involved in the making of films of such a high standard.  There is an opening in that area.  I encourage people to get involved in the industry.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" speakername="Mary Seery Kearney" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#N00300"><p>I want to share with the Senators an extraordinary witness contribution at the Joint Committee on Disability Matters, Mr. Craig Kelly, who is president of Ability@Work, which is aligned to the Cope Foundation in Cork.  He wants to work with employers and prepare them to employ people with disabilities.  He has an intellectual disability but, to use his own words, that does not define him.  He submitted applications for jobs.  In the course of an interview he declared that he had a disability by speaking about his support worker and could see the faces of the people interviewing him drop.  He shared his very personal experience of that.  He used that experience to empower him.  After more support and work, he worked with employers and his aides and supports and turned that around and was able to say he did not want to work with an employer that did not want to employ people with disabilities.  That is very powerful.</p> <p>We have a duty to ensure that all employers are open to proofing their job descriptions so that people with disabilities realise they can apply for jobs.  One example that was given at the committee today was the use of terms in job advertising such as "excellent communicator" or asking for a driver licence when a job does not involve any driving.  There are some ridiculous things that prohibit people from even applying for a job.  We should turn that on its head to ensure that every job is proofed so that somebody with a disability can apply because we want workplaces to be places of inclusion.</p> <p>I welcome that we have an opportunity to speak about the cost of disability.  People with disabilities face poverty.  Anything that aids the pathway to work for a person with a disability is important.  Any employer out there should engage Mr. Kelly in order to prepare its workforce to work with people and have a diverse and fantastic workplace.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1639" speakername="Miche&aacute;l Carrigy" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#N00400"><p>St. Patrick's Day parades will take place throughout the country in 2022.  I have spoken to local parade organisers in Longford, including Ms Fiona Fenelon, the president of the local chamber of commerce, with regard to having a quiet street on the parade for those who cannot or have not been able to go to parades in recent years because of the noise, including sirens and music.  I refer in particular to those in the autistic community who are not able to attend such events.  Their needs should be taken on board.</p> <p>Parade organisers in Longford have agreed that this year a section of the parade will have no music or sirens so that families can attend in the knowledge that they will be able to watch the parade at a certain area.  I ask that every parade organiser in the country takes this idea on board and has a quiet street or section, and make it known that families can enjoy the parade, something they have waited a couple of years to do.</p> <p>I also want to raise the issue of family resource centres and the lack of funding for additional centres.  In my county, Longford, centres in Granard and Ballymahon have done significant work.  They have expanded and been supported by the local authorities.  However, Edgeworthstown, the second largest town in County Longford, with a population of 10,000, does not have such a facility.  My colleague, Councillor Paul Ross, in Edgeworthstown is working hard to develop such a centre.  In the previous round of funding two years ago, funding for 11 additional centres throughout the entire country was announced.  I ask that the Minister, Deputy O'Gorman, put extra finance in place.  If he comes to the Chamber, it is something we should discuss.  These centres are invaluable resources in all of our communities across the country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1648" speakername="Emer Currie" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#N00500"><p>I want to talk about a serious incident that happened in Blanchardstown a few weeks ago, where two teenagers were involved in a fight and there was a stabbing.  Thankfully, the injuries were non-threatening according to reports.  In the context of Safer Internet Day, I want to talk about cyberbullying.  We are all aware of cyberbullying, and it is to be hoped it comes into focus more when we discuss the Online Safety and Media Regulation Bill, part of which addresses the harmful content around cyberbullying, self-harming and eating disorders.  We will have a rigorous debate about that.  The attack in Blanchardstown shows how bad cyberbullying can get.  We have seen the tragedy of bullying.</p> <p>Social media can become unsocial media very quickly.  Things can escalate very quickly.  There is a new trend, for want of a better word, on social media forums which is translating into real fights that are filmed and posted on platforms.  We have all been in such situations involving relationships, an image and our whole life, and that can impact the rest of our lives.  Garda&iacute; are aware of this trend and are engaging with schools in Dublin 15.</p> <p>Given the severity of the issue, garda&iacute; are trying to get the message out to parents.  Garda&iacute;, schools and parents who know about this phenomenon are doing their bit.  I hope that under the Bill to which I referred we can strengthen what we can do.  There needs to be awareness about this issue.  I hope the individual complaints mechanism that is being considered is implemented.  Identities need to be verified.  There needs to be a step change in online safety.  I want to raise awareness of how incidents like this are increasing in frequency.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#N00600"><p>I welcome the home energy scheme that is being rolled out.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Aisling Dolan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=AislingDolan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->There is going to be 100% support for people in need.  That is all across the country.  We saw that there were supports being put in place, in particular for just transition areas that were especially vulnerable and affected, maybe, by changes in traditional industries.  Now we are going to be seeing this home energy upgrade scheme to reduce costs.  When people can put insulation into walls, attics and cavity areas they can reduce costs by two thirds.  Under the general scheme, people can get up to &euro;25,000 in grants.  Many people are interested, particularly for their parents.  I am getting queries about how people can reduce heating costs for their parents.  They may be living alone and are older in age.  This is particularly the case in the west of Ireland where housing stock is a lot older.  It is absolutely wonderful to see it.  We are going to see &euro;8 billion invested up to 2030.  Of course, we need an apprenticeship scheme in order that we might scale up and have people in place to do this retrofitting.</p><p>The second fund I would like to mention is the seed innovation fund, which was announced this week.  There will be more than &euro;90 million available through this fund to support early-stage companies.  It is basically venture capital for early-stage companies that are more high-risk.  We have great talent in Ireland.  All across our universities we are seeing campus-based start-ups in fintech, pharma, medtech and so many areas, particularly in green technologies and healthcare.  In order for these start-ups to roll out from campuses, we need the support of seed capital.  The fund is going to launch later this week and will be managed by Enterprise Ireland.  It is part of the European Investment Fund.  It seeds matched funding, &euro;30 million from the Department of Enterprise, Trade and Employment and another matched fund from the Ireland Strategic Investment Fund in conjunction with the European Investment Fund.  It is phenomenal to see this injection of money.  We have the talent, researchers and entrepreneurs out there.  We are seeing all of this coming together and now we have the funds to match it.  I look forward to seeing the companies and indigenous start-ups coming from Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#O00200"><p>I want to return to the issue of crime against our older people.  I am sorry I have to raise this today.  Let me at the outset say we are not here to frighten people but we have to deal with the facts.  I am just quoting from a piece from today's edition of the <i>Irish Independent</i>about the most recent attack in Kildare:</p> <blockquote> 	The incident in Kildare happened at around 9.30 p.m. on Tuesday night when the three-man gang broke into the homeowner&rsquo;s shed.<br /><br />He was alerted to the break-in by the sound of his dog barking and was attacked when he confronted them.<br /><br />It&rsquo;s understood his wife locked herself into their home for her safety and alerted emergency services. </blockquote> <p>The Garda is saying that there is an increase in such attacks and that these roaming gangs that did so much damage before are back on the beat.  I have confidence in the Garda tackling these gangs again.  I know the Minister is concerned about this as we all are.  As Oireachtas Members, we all have a job to do.  The definition of a civil rights violation is any offence that occurs as a result of the use of force or the threat of force against the victim by the offender.  I am sure Senator Ward and others will be able to speak far better about that than I can.  We have to stop those attacks.  People are frightened.</p><p>Even in my own county which is one of the safest counties in the country as per a survey from the <i>Irish Examiner</i>last year, there is a notable frequency of those attacks where a back or side window of a house has been broken and even when older people are sitting down having their tea, their houses are being ransacked.  It has to stop.  We all have a responsibility here.  We cannot allow this to go on.  We have a huge duty not just to talk about it.</p><p>I urge all community groups to be on alert.  They must work within the law.  I am not talking about vigilantism  here.  They must contact the Garda.  We have a duty to drive around our areas in the evening time.  This is happening at six, seven or eight o'clock in the evening, not late at night or early in the morning.  I do not want to lecture people because politicians seen to be lecturing people nowadays get into bother.  For God's sake, though, if we are out for the evening in a restaurant of whatever can we stop putting it up on social media?  It is letting people know that the house is vacant or whatever.  It is not a good thing to be doing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1666" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#O00300"><p>I wish to comment on Transport Infrastructure Ireland, TII, and how effective it is at delivering projects.  A debate is required in the House with the Minister responsible for transport regarding these issues.  Bandon in west Cork has had an unfinished bypass for the past few decades.  There is currently a process of putting forward proposals for a new extension to this bypass, which is badly needed.  I met representatives from TII last Friday to discuss the project.  It is at stage 2 of a six-stage process and it could take another five or six years to deliver the project on the ground.  In the meantime, Bandon is choked up.  Thousands of articulated vehicles go down South Main Street and past my office every day.  They are absolutely choking the town.  The town wants to breathe and to be part of this vibrant energy that we have in west Cork.  Because of the infrastructure we have, it is literally crumbling.  Yesterday, one of the articulated lorries on the half-finished bypass lost its load and there was chaos for several hours.</p> <p>The need for TII to deliver these projects in a more time-efficient manner is urgent.  We need to make sure that the legislation is changed, if required, in order that we can have processes that are more effective and appropriate to what is required by society.  Society wants these infrastructure projects to be delivered.  Nobody wants thousands of articulated vehicles going through the town of Bandon every week.  They do no good regarding safety of pedestrians, the toxic fumes they are producing or anything else.  Even when it comes to motorists being held up in the gateway of west Cork in Bandon in traffic jams every morning, it makes no logical sense.  We need to find a process so that TII can work more effectively.  A debate with the Minister would be a healthy start.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" speakername="Barry Ward" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#O00400"><p>I want to raise the issue of hyperemesis.  Morning sickness is an unfortunate and unpleasant part of pregnancy for many women but hyperemesis is much more serious.  It is a condition that results in very severe sickness and renders women malnourished and dehydrated at times.  One in 100 pregnancies will result in hospitalisation of the expectant mother because of hyperemesis.  There are drugs available to treat it.  People may be aware of the media having covered high-profile cases of celebrities suffering from this condition.  In Ireland, those drugs are currently not covered by any scheme.  While some expectant mothers may be able to cover the cost of the medication, many cannot.  For those who have to pay for it out of their pocket, it creates enormous anxiety and extra stress during pregnancy.  For those who cannot, it creates enormous problems with the pregnancy.  In all the circumstances that is wrong.  It is unfair on the women involved.  It endangers their pregnancies.  This needs to be addressed.</p> <p>I understand the medicines management agency has been given the task by the Minister to look at this in some detail.  We hope it will come to a conclusion about that.  Hyperemesis Ireland is running a campaign with the hashtag #HG2costly to highlight this and put pressure on the appropriate authorities to bring the drugs under a scheme that allows them to be given to women who need them.  The House should also be supporting that campaign by perhaps having a debate and bringing the Minister in to help put this front and centre, deal with a real issue and make sure that the women who need the drugs can get them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#O00500"><p>On the Commission on the Defence Forces, I wish to thank the 15-member commission and the chair, Aidan O'Driscoll, for their work.  It is noteworthy that there were 500 submissions.  About 1,000 military personnel were interviewed.  The report is going to foster real debate about the Defence Forces that Ireland needs as a modern European country.  There are 69 recommendations in the report, many of them very significant changes.  The Minister is seeking the views of other stakeholders and will return with an action plan, which absolutely needs to be time bound.  However, he should not wait for that to start discussions and engagement with the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform.  Without a shadow of a doubt, it is essential that a permanent pay review body for the military is put in place.  That must begin here and now, along with the recommendation that those within the Army can affiliate to ICTU and that there is a progression towards proper pay and resources for the Army.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Fiona O'Loughlin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2441"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2441&amp;amp;pid=FionaOLoughlin&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I will mention one other matter.  Councillor Michael Sheehan from Gorey contacted me yesterday evening to tell me an horrific story about a young woman from New Ross who put her phone for sale on the <i>donedeal.ie</i>website and invited to meet a buyer in Castledermot in County Kildare.  She was to meet an individual at 7.30 p.m. on a dark evening in a relatively lonely place.  Luckily, she brought her boyfriend with her.  When she got out of the car, a man jumped out with a hammer and tried to pull her into another vehicle.<br/><br/>There are a number of lessons to be learned from this.  The operators of the <i>donedeal.ie</i>website were contacted, along with the Garda, but there was no legitimate phone number for the individual in question.  Any community-based organisation such as the <i>donedeal.ie</i>website must do due diligence in this respect.  It must ensure it can work on behalf of people.  If somebody is selling or exchanging something, they should not do it late at night and in darkness in a place they do not know.  There is a lesson for all of us here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1670" speakername="John McGahon" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#P00200"><p>It has probably been mentioned but the one-stop shop element of the announced retrofit programme is even better than I expected.  The concept of a one-stop shop in this respect is absolutely incredible, as it will organise and project manage the work.  It will carry out an assessment of the home and tell people exactly what is the best type of stuff to go into that home.  These people will come back out after the work is completed to ensure the work is up to a very good standard.  We are achieving two goals with this retrofit scheme.  We are making the process financially attractive and viable for people, which is very important.  We are also facilitating ease of access, making it so simple for people to retrofit their home, whether it is a deep retrofit or smaller work.  These two characteristics are what make it such a good and attractive scheme.</p> <p>I have a query on one aspect that I would like to raise with the Minister.  It is very important because this is a radical scheme that has been introduced.  It will be similar to what happened in the 1960s, when over the space of 15 or 20 years everyone switched from open fires to central heating.  This will be a radical programme and it deserves a very detailed debate in the Seanad at some stage.  I would like to see that.</p> <p>On the street where I live in Dundalk, many of the houses are protected structures.  They may be 100 years old and we are not talking about ancient buildings.  We need a dedicated policy between the appropriate Department and the Heritage Council to deal with how somebody in a protected structure would be able to retrofit a home.  It is a section of society that could be forgotten about in a general retrofit scheme.  If a person lives in a protected structure, retrofitting can nevertheless happen and it is possible to make that home warmer, but it must be done in a managed way.  The sooner we get that guidance published on how to make this happen, the better.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#P00300"><p>I thank Senators for their comments.  Senators McGahon and Dolan spoke about the home energy scheme announced this week and it really is a momentous amount of money being reinvested.  It is taxpayers' money and it belongs to all citizens but it is about reinvestment in citizens' lives and making their homes much warmer, cosier and a less costly place in which to live.  I am old enough to remember when we went from back boilers in the 1970s to central heating, and it took years for all the houses to make that change.  This is really another generational change and I hope it does not take too long, particularly with respect to the houses most in need.  We all know older couples in particular who are absolutely perished with the cold in their houses.  These are the houses we should start with, as opposed to places that may be less in need.  I look forward to the day all of us can get our houses retrofitted.  Senator McGahon made a valid point about protected structures and I will contact the Minister to ensure the relevant bodies speak to each other about that.</p> <p>Senators O'Loughlin, O'Donovan and Wall mentioned the Defence Forces report published yesterday.  I have already requested a debate time from the Minister and I have no doubt I will get told that we should wait until the Minister and his departmental officials have the opportunity to consider the report and respond.  I genuinely believe very valid points must be made by Members in this House to feed into the Minister's response so I will keep pushing to get that debate on the report.</p> <p>Senator Ward spoke about the very serious impact that hyperemesis has had on women.  It is welcome we are talking about this a bit more.  The Senator raised the matter this morning and other colleagues have mentioned it in the past number of weeks, probably as a result of the campaign to ensure it can be included in the medical scheme of drugs acceptable to be paid for.  This might seem like a fool's errand because the women who are lucky enough to be able to afford this treatment pay for it and it is very costly.  Far fewer women can probably afford it than we might think, and the cost to the State from women who end up in hospital as a result of this condition is probably far in excess of what it would cost to provide the medicine to try to keep the women safe, well and out of hospital in the first place.  I support the campaign and thank the Senator for raising the matter.</p> <p>Senator Lombard mentioned Transport Infrastructure Ireland and the very frustrating multiple-stage processes we have to get any very large infrastructural project done in this country.  He spoke about Bandon and the bypass that is only on its second stage, despite the project being years old.  We all know such projects.  In my constituency we have been talking about metro north for 20 years and we will still be talking about it for another ten or 15 years.  It makes no sense that we will spend two and a half years getting planning permission before waiting another two and a half years before we start procuring the products we need.  Does anybody really think we are not going to get planning permission for something we have been talking about for 20 years?  We must look at these processes.  One of the debates we have under Seanad reform is to engage with interested bodies and this might one to look at.  Perhaps we will bring it up in the Committee on Procedure and Privileges.  It is definitely something to be looked at.</p> <p>Senator Eugene Murphy spoke this morning about crimes against older people.  I do not know if it is just me but since Christmas, all I seem to be reading in the newspapers are stories about violent crimes against young women and really violent crimes against our older generation.  I do not know if they have just massively increased in the past number of months or whether my awareness of these incidents has been heightened.  I am not really sure.  There is a 73-year-old pensioner fighting for his life in hospital and the Senator spoke about a couple this morning.  I cannot imagine how frightened that lady must have been to lock herself in her own house with her husband being taken on by three thugs and gurriers in the back garden.  We really have a problem where people do not feel safe in their homes or castles.  It is not acceptable.  Perhaps we need to have another debate or conversation around that.  I will get back to the Senator and let him know.</p> <p>Senator Currie mentioned the new age practice of organising fights so we can get them on video and put them on social media.  I do not know what is going on in the world, to be honest.  We must reflect on a couple of points.  The culture we are living in is changing and perhaps it is because the deterrents are not keeping up with crimes as they move.</p> <p>On a much nicer note, Senator Carrigy relayed a really lovely suggestion of having quiet spots along the route of the St. Patrick's Day parade.  I know we are all welcoming back parades this year because we have not had them for the past number of years.  It is a lovely idea to have a quiet spot where families of children with special and extra needs can enjoy what most of us take for granted in a special way.  Perhaps we could write to local authorities before they start planning for these parades and make them aware of this idea.  I had never heard of it before the Senator mentioned it this morning.  It is a lovely idea.  We might take it on ourselves, with the Senator's permission, to write to local authority chief executive officers and make them aware that we want to be inclusive and allow everybody to enjoy what is our national holiday.  I thank the Senator for bringing this matter up.</p> <p>Senator Seery Kearney spoke about a young man, Mr. Craig Kelly, who sounds remarkable.  He spoke at this morning's meeting of the Joint Committee on Disability Matters.  I am aware from my days in the Department of Social Protection that there are grants and forms of encouragement for companies to take people of all abilities into the workforce.  It does not quite work out as well as it might on paper and this is certainly something we should return to.</p> <p>Senator Maria Byrne spoke about the independent review into University Hospital Limerick, which is very welcome not just by the Limerick Members in this House but by all the people in the surrounding areas who rely so heavily on University Hospital Limerick.  I absolutely agree with the Senator that the report must be issued and published so we can discuss it.  It must be acted upon and HIQA must make unannounced visits.  We know there is a systemic problem in University Hospital Limerick as the same issues that occur periodically in other hospitals seem to arise daily in Limerick.  Something is seriously wrong and we look forward to getting to the bottom of it and maybe fixing that, please God.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Regina Doherty:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2295"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2295&amp;amp;pid=ReginaDoherty&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Senator Ahearn talked about access to childcare and the fact that there are no places.  We changed the industry number of years ago to make level 7 the minimum education requirement but we did not change the funding to pay these women - and they are women.  We need to have a debate again on how we value care.  The Committee on Gender Equality that was established a number of weeks ago is certainly going to try to implement the recommendations from the Citizens' Assembly.  We have a long time been talking about these kind of things and we need to start acting on them.</p><p>Senator McGreehan raised the issue of native Irish trees.  It is clear from how she talks about them that she has a real gr&aacute; for them and it reflected on the debate we had this week.</p><p>Senator Black brought up the Police Ombudsman for Northern Ireland report.  Marie Anderson was on the radio on Tuesday.  She also is a remarkable woman.  The word "shocking" is not serious enough to reflect what she is uncovering.  What I took solace from is that she said she is only warming up.  This certainly will not be the end of what she will try to shine a light upon.  I genuinely say that how we reflect on the past obviously reflects on ourselves.  There is dignity required for all of the people who died and all of the families who lost loved ones.  Sometimes that gets a little bit lost.  I thank Senator Black for bringing that up.  I have asked for a debate on it, just to let her know.  As I have also asked, as Senator Boylan brought up this morning and Senator Black did last week, for a debate on the Amnesty International report.  Senator Chambers contacted me this morning to ask for the debate.  I suggested to her that I had already done so last week on Senator Black's request, but I will chase up and try to get a debate and a time.</p><p>I sit here and think, "Only in Ireland," on certain occasions, such as this one.  Senator Boylan also talked about how the ability for schools to put solar panels on their roofs in order that they can provide some of their own electricity and perhaps sell it back is being halted by the obligation to do a report into whether those solar panels will affect the airports around the country, in respect of planes landing and taking off.  Yet, Dublin Airport is applying for a solar farm.  It beggars belief.  I will send a letter highlighting that to the Taoiseach on her request.</p><p>Senator Wall, apart from speaking on the report on the Defence Forces, spoke about the gambling report that was issued yesterday.  The research being done is very welcome and it will feed into the new regulator office being established.  However, I was concerned that people who do a weekly lotto of two lines were included with people with gambling addictions.  I thought this was odd.  I do not know about everybody else, but I am assuming nearly everybody the lotto once in a blue moon or on a weekly basis.  Therefore, I thought it was odd.  </p><p>However, what was more concerning was that people who have serious addictions but have money and, therefore, their gambling does not impact on household finances, were not included as those who are at risk and needing help.  That should be irrelevant.  The outcome of the illness would obviously impact people with less income in their households than people with more income.  However, if it is an illness, then we need to measure, monitor and help everybody who has the illness, and not just say, "Well, sure, they have loads of money, so they are grand."  That was a bit odd.  The welcome report and research is timely and it will feed into the establishment of the regulatory body. </p><p>The Minister of State, Senator Hackett, talked about the new European innovation partnership, EIP, process in the Common Agricultural Policy, CAP, which is still in its infancy.  It is very welcome and it will only grow with time.</p><p>Senator Boyhan spoke about the ability of people to make observations on and, indeed, object to planning where they think the planning is not suitable or required in their own areas.  Obviously, nobody will ever curtail anybody from making observations or, indeed, objecting to bad planning.  In the past number of weeks, the Taoiseach has been speaking about how, when there are serial objectors, we have to question what is at the root of the serial objections.  We are all aware that there are certain people who do not live anywhere remotely close to something and yet they object.  We probably need to find out why and address the issues, as opposed to complaining about it.  We certainly will not ever curtail anybody's ability to object to bad planning.  We have all seen and experienced bad planning, unfortunately. </p><p>Senator Conway asked for a debate on the cost of public transport, which I will certainly do. </p><p>Senator Cassells opened our contributions today by talking about something that we will all welcome in spades when we get the clubs' announcement of money and funding in the next couple of days, which is very good.  He is absolutely right.  Whether a person live in rural or urban Ireland, we see competing clubs all wanting to have their own Astroturf pitch or dressing rooms.  One can say that is a hangover from years gone by and the way clubs used to compete with each other.  There is absolutely nothing stopping us from putting in new clauses whereby new Astroturf pitches that go into towns have to be shared facilities and, indeed, as they grow, they become municipal sporting campuses.  Where there is a will, there is a way.  </p><p>What we currently have in the country is everybody trying to compete with everybody else, without having the shared facility and shared mentality of that.  The Senator is right.  My kids are older now but when they were smaller, I would be running from Billy to Jack and from one club to another.  All of our kids play more than one sport and enjoy more than one local activity.  We should be funding and putting together schemes that look for best value for money.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.66" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.67" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#Q00300">Address to Seanad Éireann by Members of the European Parliament: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#Q00400"><p>I move:</p> <blockquote> 	That, in accordance with Standing Order 57(1) and the approval of the Committee on Parliamentary Privileges and Oversight, Seanad &Eacute;ireann agrees that, in respect of the European Parliament South Constituency, Ms. Deirdre Clune MEP, Mr. Billy Kelleher MEP, Mr. Se&aacute;n Kelly MEP, Ms. Grace O&rsquo;Sullivan MEP and Mr. Mick Wallace MEP, may attend and be heard in Seanad &Eacute;ireann on Wednesday, 23rd February, 2022, and that the following arrangements shall apply:<br /><br />The proceedings shall commence at 2 p.m., shall not exceed two hours, and shall consist of&mdash;  	(a) a speech of welcome by the Cathaoirleach;<br /><br />(b) an opening address by each MEP which shall not exceed six minutes in each case;<br /><br />(c) a contribution not exceeding three minutes by a spokesperson from each Group;<br /><br />(d) a single response not exceeding three minutes by each MEP to the combined issues raised by the Group spokespersons;<br /><br />(e) questions from all other Senators in accordance with the sequence set out in the Schedule to this resolution, which shall not exceed one minute in each case, and a reply not exceeding two minutes from each MEP;<br /><br />(f) a final concluding statement of not less than four minutes by each MEP;<br /><br />(g) a speech of thanks by the Leader of the House; and the members of the European Parliament may take seats on the floor of the Seanad Chamber. <div>Schedule</div>Fianna F&aacute;il Group<br /><br />Fine Gael Group<br /><br />Independent Group<br /><br />Green Party<br /><br />Sinn F&eacute;in Group<br /><br />Labour Group<br /><br />Civil Engagement Group. </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.69" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.70" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar fionra&iacute; ag 1.07 p.m. agus cuireadh t&uacute;s leis ar&iacute;s ag 1.18 p.m.

Sitting suspended at 1.07 p.m. and resumed at 1.18 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.71" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#R00100">Safe Access to Termination of Pregnancy Services Bill 2021: Committee Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#R00200"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire go dt&iacute; an Teach.  Ar nd&oacute;igh, beidh d&iacute;osp&oacute;ireacht fhi&uacute;ntach againn.  I remind Members, as a courtesy, that Committee Stage will be adjourned in two hours, so they should be conscious of that as they contribute.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.73" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>SECTION 1</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#R00400"><p>Amendments Nos. 1, 3 and 10 are related and may be discussed together, by agreement.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#R00500"><p>I move amendment No. 1:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 3, between lines 12 and 13, to insert the following:   	&quot; &quot;authorised trade union&quot; means a trade union which holds a negotiation licence under the Trade Union Acts 1941 to 1990;&quot;.   </blockquote> <p>The Minister is very welcome.  I thank him for taking the time to attend.  I am really pleased to be able to move to Committee Stage of the Safe Access to Termination of Pregnancy Services Bill 2021.  While Sinn F&eacute;in is very proud to be supporting it, I must stress the cross-party nature of the campaign behind it.  The Bill has been co-signed by members of Sinn F&eacute;in, the Labour Party, the Civil Engagement Group, the Green Party and Fianna F&aacute;il, as well as by the father of the House, Senator Norris.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paul Gavan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2469"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2469&amp;amp;pid=PaulGavan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> A Bill has been commissioned and drafted by Together for Safety, a national campaign group working for legislation that would enforce safe access zones around all family planning centres, maternity hospitals and healthcare facilities in Ireland that provide or give information on abortion.  All credit for this legislation belongs to Together for Safety and its tireless campaigners across the country.  I am thrilled to have three of the many activists from Together for Safety in our Chamber this afternoon, namely, Karen Sugrue, Yvie Murphy and Victoria.  I thank them so much for the work and the tireless campaigning that they brought to this Bill and for the broad coalition of support for this Bill, which was built by Together for Safety.  It is a tremendous achievement.</p><p>I will be brief because we have just a couple of hours to progress this legislation through Committee Stage.  I want to be clear that we need this legislation without further delay, because women and pregnant people are entitled to access essential healthcare, including access to termination of pregnancy services, in privacy and dignity, without being subject to intimidation, harassment and the subtle but deliberate chilling effect that anti-choice protestors bring to hospitals, family planning and GP settings across the State.  I know that the Minister was informed in the past week of a disturbing new development in my home city, Limerick, where the timing of these anti-choice protests is now coinciding with the timing of appointments for terminations.  It is clear, from a number of people who have spoken to Together for Safety, that information is being leaked.  These protestors are now targeting women and pregnant people as they arrive for their terminations.  That is disgraceful, and it speaks to the urgency required in respect of this Bill.  We introduced this Bill three months ago.  I was delighted by and appreciate the fact that the Minister allowed the Bill to pass Second Stage.  He said that we are all on the same page.  I believe we are.  It is important to move this Bill forward.</p><p>I look forward to the remainder of this Committee Stage debate.  A number of the amendments are in response to concerns the Minister raised on Second Stage.  We look forward to working with him in order that we can move the legislation forward as a matter of urgency and give women and pregnant people the protection that they deserve, which is already in place in a number of jurisdictions across the world.  We need to deliver that as quickly as possible for our people in this State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#S00200"><p>I welcome our distinguished visitors in the Gallery.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1693" speakername="Pauline O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#S00300"><p>I welcome the Minister and our guests from Together for Safety.  What Senator Gavan said is important.  This Bill has been drafted by Together for Safety and the work that it has done in reaching out to all of us is welcome.  When we operate on a cross-party basis in the Seanad, as we have on a number of issues, particularly with regard to women's healthcare, contraception, the stalking legislation dealt with yesterday and the new legislation about character references in sexual assault cases that was launched yesterday, it is beneficial to politics and society.  I ask the Minister to address, in response to these amendments, where matters are at present.  The legislation was supposed to have included safe access zones in 2019.  That was expected.  I know the Minister has previously said that he has a commitment about this, which is welcome.  We need to pass this legislation and we need to hear what the Department will do, including a timeline for safe access zones.  Senator Gavan has listened to what came up last time.  I see from the first amendment that he also listened to concerns from trade unions and other groups and tabled that amendment on the basis that it would address some concerns.  That is an important point that the Minister might take into consideration when allowing it to progress, although it is up to us to allow it to pass, and from the Government's perspective.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#S00400"><p>I welcome the Minister.  It is great to see visitors back in the Public Gallery once again.  People who have engaged in and led the campaign relating to this Bill have filled the Gallery.  It is a relief to see citizens back in their Parliament.</p> <p>It is glaring that there are no Government amendments to the Bill.  There should always be an onus on Government to proactively engage in respect of Private Member's Bills, particularly in view of the fact that they represent the opportunity for citizens and parliamentarians bring forward legislation.  I am somewhat disappointed not to see any Government amendments.  The principle behind the Bill is about providing unencumbered access to facilities that provide legal termination of pregnancy services and protecting individuals who provide such services and allowing citizens to access those services, as is their right.  I wanted to give my support to the Bill again.  I hope to speak on other amendments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#S00500"><p>I will be brief because I am conscious that we want to finish Committee Stage today.  I am glad to see this being progressed and to see the support across the House.  It is important to remember that in the debate prior to the referendum, it was extremely difficult for people to come forward and to talk about their experiences.  We had decades of silence when people were intimidated with regard to talking about their experiences, realities and the challenges and choices that they faced.  It was powerful when people stepped forward, particularly when one bears in mind that they had criminal offences hanging over their heads at the time.  It should not be the case that after that referendum and those hard conversations, when people made their children, that people again face intimidation, harassment or fear in stepping forward, when they are trying to access the health services that they are entitled to and need.  It is not acceptable to have any lingering of this dimension of intimidation, silencing and pressure.  We had long enough of that.  The people chose to change it.  We are now at the point of ensuring that the ancillary recommendations related to contraception and the promise about safe access zones are delivered.  We knew that these would be issues.  The committee anticipated them and made recommendations.</p> <p>There is a concern that there are still hospitals in Ireland that are not providing people with the care they need.  It is a real concern if there are hospitals where people are being pressured indirectly.  This Bill is not just about hospitals, it is also about GP practices.  I was moved when I heard about the practical implementation of access.  Many rural GPs have their offices where their homes are.  They have been subjected to protests outside their homes, which is not acceptable.  It is important that we create a space which is safe, supportive and where people can access what they need, and in order that people can deliver the services they want and are bound to deliver by good ethics.</p> <p>I am glad that the Bill is moving forward.  I am not sure if we are speaking on amendments Nos. 1 to 3, inclusive, at this point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#S00600"><p>We are discussing amendments Nos. 1, 3 and 10.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#S00700"><p>The amendments reflect the fact that Senator Gavan and the many lawyers and academics working with Together for Safety, as well as the campaigners themselves, have listened to the concerns raised.  I imagine that because there has been a collegial spirit in the approach to this legislation and that because that approach has been so cross-party in nature, then if there are further thoughts, this is a clear message that we are happy to listen to and reflect the Government's concerns.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Alice-Mary Higgins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2480"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2480&amp;amp;pid=AliceMaryHiggins&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> What if there are concerns about, for example, the narrowing piece?  The phrase &ldquo;services provided for the provision of contraception or advice in relation to contraception&rdquo; might be too wide and is being narrowed.  If that is too narrow, let us know because we still have Report Stage in which to refine the legislation further.  We are all keen to get this exactly right; likewise in the case of the powers of members of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.</p><p>There is a clear engagement here.  If there are further questions either on these amendments or the Bill, I urge the Minister to work constructively with us between now and Report Stage to ensure we are all completely happy with the wording that goes through.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1663" speakername="Annie Hoey" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#T00200"><p>As co-signatories, we fully support the amendment.  I welcome and thank Together for Safety for all the work it has done on this legislation.</p> <p>The Bill is about patient safety and well-being and also the safety and well-being of doctors, GPs and their staff.  We are not just talking about the people who want to access reproductive healthcare but also the staff.  As Senator Gavan alluded to, the fact that some of these protests have been timed to take place at the same time as appointments is extremely concerning situation for staff and patients.  It is also very frightening and worrying for prospective patients.  People who will have no choice but to avail, unfortunately, of healthcare in Limerick hospital know there may potentially be a timed protest when they go into the hospital.  That is a terrifying fact and I hope the Minister is taking it very seriously.</p> <p>I hope the Bill will address the chill effect that these protests are designed to achieve.  The actions of the protestors are rooted in judgment and not in compassion.  The strategy has been used for decades in the US, UK and elsewhere in Europe.  I cannot comprehend that people feel they have a right to cause hurt and upset instead of showing care and compassion for fellow people.  There are legitimate means to express disquiet over abortion in Ireland, which do not hurt, impede, insult or upset people as they access necessary healthcare.</p> <p>The main purpose of this Bill is to provide dignity while obtaining healthcare.  The vote on this matter four years ago was resounding and we have waited four years for this legislation, which was promised a long time ago.  As Senator Warfield noted, the Government has not tabled any amendments.  Is that because the Government is happy with the legislation and does not see a reason to make any changes or does it plan to write its own legislation?  If the latter is the case, why are we proceeding in the way we are?  Will the Government support the passage of the Bill through the Houses?  Has the Government not tabled amendments because it agrees with everything that has been said?</p> <p>To speak to the amendments, I love to see the strengthening of references to trade unions.  The stronger the reference, the better.  We will support all the amendments. </p> <p>Amendment No. 11 deals with the power of a member of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na to give direction.  If there is an issue with that, I ask the Minister to give us guidance.  Is the amendment written in a way that reflects what the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na believes it would be able to do?  There have been some concerns expressed about the powers of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and what garda&iacute; will and will not be able to do, and whether it is appropriate.  I am interested in hearing the Minister's thoughts on the proposed new section.  I specifically want to know whether it is moving in the right direction?  Does the Minister or An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na have concerns about whether this guidance and legislation are appropriate?</p> <p>This Bill has been a long time coming.  We need to get our act together.  We had a very clear "Yes" vote in the referendum and a very clear promise that there would be legislation.  It is time that we got it done.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1643" speakername="Lorraine Clifford-Lee" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#T00250"><p>It is great to be in the Seanad among like-minded colleagues who have worked for many years to improve women's healthcare.  It is also great to have our guests from Together for Safety in the Gallery.  I thank them for all of the work they have done, not only on this legislation but also on keeping this important issue on the political agenda.</p> <p>I look forward to getting a timeline from the Minister setting out how we can protect workers and the people who seek to access services.  We must make sure we have a fit-for-purpose healthcare system in Ireland.  We passed legislation on termination services but there are a number of gaps.  I hope we can speedily close those gaps.</p> <p>I know the Minister is deeply committed to this issue.  Its inclusion in the programme for Government was a recognition that it is a very important issue and one that needs to be solved.  We have been promised this legislation for a long time, as Senator Hoey said.  Four years is too long.  The Minister took up the mantle when he went into the Department because no work had been done on the issue by the Department or his predecessor.  Notwithstanding that the Minister had to deal with difficult health issues, he has put an awful lot of work into this issue.  I hope that by virtue of his deep commitment, we will be able to move this legislation forward and get it across the line.</p> <p>I look forward to hearing the Minister outline how he will approach this issue.  Members of this House and the other House are deeply committed to solving this issue.  People should not have to face the terror experienced in Limerick, as has been outlined.  That is absolutely horrendous and similar situations have occurred in other parts of the country.  In large swathes of rural Ireland services are not available because of this intimidation.  That is not on and we cannot stand for it any longer.  I and colleagues across the House will not stand for it.</p> <p>I appreciate the opportunity to contribute on this legislation.  I thank the Senators who brought this issue before us for allowing us an opportunity to debate this matter again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" speakername="Mary Seery Kearney" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#T00300"><p>I welcome and support the Bill.  How could I not do so?</p> <p>We last debated this issue in October and it is now February.  What progress has been made?  I hope the Government is not minded to leave this matter inextricably linked with the review of the operation of the primary legislation for termination services because too much harm is being done daily in the meantime.  I am concerned that too few people are prepared to offer services for fear of their own safety.  I thank the Together for Safety group for all its work and welcome its members to the Gallery.</p> <p>The timing of protests to coincide with clear red-circled appointments is a sinister development on a number of fronts.  It suggests there is activism somewhere within the hospital.  That being the case, while this is a matter for the individuals involved, from a GDPR perspective it is horrific that such personal and sensitive information is being released.  There is no reason action cannot be taken within the hospital.  Such action should be of a very radical nature because if this happened in any other service or with respect to access to any other medical treatment, it would be viewed very badly.  The particular nature of this case suggests there is political activism taking place, and that is unreasonable.  It is not our place to hold a review but I am anxious to know - perhaps Senator Gavan knows - whether the Data Protection Commission is involved.  Is there an active investigation.  If not, there should be one?  Has the commission been properly notified?  It should investigate this matter.  From my experience of data investigations and breaches, I know they can be incisive investigations.  That is what is needed here.  The obligations on a data controller to preserve and safeguard information are onerous.  Both sides of that are engaged.</p> <p>In June, this Government will have been in power for nearly two years.  There is no excuse for not having legislation on this matter.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Mary Seery Kearney:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=MarySeeryKearney&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Either we completely support this all the way through, or, if there is some other plan, we need to know about it.  We need to know the timeline as to when it will be operated.  I refer to safeguarding the providers of termination services and those who need to access them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#U00200"><p>The Minister is welcome to the House to take this important Bill.  I welcome it, and I commend all those, in this House and outside it, who have brought us to this point.  We need to legislate for safe access zones at abortion clinics urgently.  This issue is about respect and dignity.  It is concerned with supporting women&rsquo;s right to make these decisions and about supporting their dignity and their privacy.  Sadly, legislation in this regard is undoubtedly needed.  It is sad to think that we are in a position where we must bring this Bill before the House, but this is the situation.  People&rsquo;s right to protest is, of course, of paramount importance.  We must support that right.  There is, however, a distinct difference between registering a protest about something and hiding behind one&rsquo;s right to protest in order to intimidate people from accessing healthcare.  That is what this legislation is concerned with.  It is about intimidation.</p> <p>Safe access zones are needed to protect the right to protest and people&rsquo;s right to access healthcare.  They are already used in other countries, including parts of Canada, Australia and the US.  We must follow suit.  This is already an incredibly sensitive and upsetting time for women.  They deserve our respect and protection and that of the State.  I am concerned that protests at these clinics will deter people from exercising their right to access healthcare, many of whom are in crisis pregnancy situations and do not need extra pressure or stress.  As the chair of the Women&rsquo;s Caucus, I will continue to work with my colleagues to ensure that people&rsquo;s access to healthcare is protected.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#U00300"><p>Senator Gavan can have another word shortly.  I call the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1623" speakername="Stephen Donnelly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#U00400"><p>I thank the Senators for their contributions.  I particularly welcome the group, Together for Safety, that has come here today.  I acknowledge the great work its members have done and the advocacy and the energy the group has brought to this important issue.</p> <p>The most important thing to state is that we are legislating for safe access zones.  That is happening.  It is in the programme for Government; we are doing that.  It is for the Oireachtas to decide whether it will be a version of this Bill, which would require significant changes, and we can go through those points later, or whether it happens in the form of a new Bill being brought in on an all-party basis.  We are, however, legislating for these safe access zones.  This is happening.  Termination of pregnancy services are legal.  They were agreed by an overwhelming majority in a referendum.  It is completely unacceptable for any woman to be harassed and intimidated in accessing such services.  It is completely unacceptable for any clinician to be harassed or intimated, or worse, in providing these services.  We are not going to stand for that.</p> <p>A view has been expressed to me through the avenue of legal opinion, and it is also held by An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, that additional powers are not required.  The current powers are sufficient.  It is not a view I agree with and not one that I have accepted.  It is not the view of this House or, I believe, of the Lower House.  We are legislating.  This is happening.  These sorts of tactics and intimidation are not okay.  I have spoken to GPs who have been on the receiving end of this type of treatment, in cases where they had their clinics are beside their homes, with entry through the same gate.  I have been on the receiving end of this type of behaviour as well, although not relating to the termination of pregnancy services.  My children have been on the receiving end of it.  I know what it feels like and I know what it feels like as a parent when one's home is targeted.  We will not stand for women in this country being intimidated, attacked, abused and moralised at when accessing healthcare services.  The only question I am concerned with is determining the quickest and most robust way to get us to enacting the legislation.  That is it.  That is all I am interested in.</p> <p>For us to do this, though, we must be really honest with each other.  This is complicated.  This measure was promised years ago.  It was not legislated for by the previous Government, and that was partly because the previous Minister was presented with a significant amount of legal opinion which said that this type of provision was unnecessary and unconstitutional or would have too much of a chilling effect on civil liberties.  We hold civil liberties to be sacred in this country and a delicate balance must be found.  An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na informed my predecessor and the Department at the time that these powers, this law and the fulfilment of this promise was not necessary.  It is a complex subject.</p> <p>In responding to this legislation, I have pages and pages containing legal opinion on why various parts of it would not work.  We discussed much of what I am referring to on Second Stage.  Therefore, I reiterate that we must be honest in this regard.  What we are trying to do here is difficult.  If it had been straightforward, an Act would have been passed by now.  It is not easy to do this, and some trade-offs are required.  We are pushing up against civil liberties when we do this.  We all take this point deadly serious.  We must, therefore, get this legislation right.  What we need to enact is legislation that is legally robust.  I think it will be challenged in the courts.  It will certainly be assessed to see if a constitutional challenge can be taken.  The legal advice I have is that the Bill before us, as it stands, or even with minor amendments, would not survive a constitutional challenge.  We must, therefore, make some root-and-branch changes to this Bill or draft something else.  Both those options are possible.  First and foremost, however, the resulting legislation must be legally and constitutionally robust.  </p> <p>The legislation must also be effective.  We must be clear regarding our policy intent.  Are we talking about safe access zones around maternity units?  We are.  Are we talking about safe access zones around GP clinics?  I believe we are.  Are we talking about safe access zones around pharmacies?  I am not sure we are, but this Bill would bring that about.  Are we talking about safe access zones around the offices of students' unions?  I do not think we are.  The legal opinion I have, though, is that this legislation would do many things which I do not think many of us want.  For example, if 100 m safe access zones were to be created in somewhere like Dublin city around every pharmacy, GP and family planning clinic, etc., then we would end up in a situation where we could not have legitimate protest or demonstrations, either for or against aspect of the termination of pregnancy.  </p> <p>This is not to critique the Bill.  This is an incredibly complicated subject.  It is why we do not have such an Act in place now.  I am only saying that we must find a delicate and legally and constitutionally robust balance.  The legislation we enact in this regard must be enforceable and it must be cognisant of civil liberties.  That is something we, as legislators, hold sacrosanct.  We have important and significant protections for our civil liberties in Bunreacht na h&Eacute;ireann and in European law.  Any time we seek to make an exception to those provisions, and this is what we would be doing, we would be carving out an exception in this regard and we must be cognisant of doing so in the appropriate way.  </p> <p>We need a Bill that fulfils the policy objectives here and we must be clear about what those objectives are.  Is it intended to cover GP clinics, pharmacies, family planning centres and so on?  What kinds of protests and demonstrations and what type of expressions of freedom of speech will be acceptable in those zones?<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Stephen Donnelly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2336"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2336&amp;amp;pid=StephenDonnelly&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Is any kind acceptable?  Are some kinds acceptable but not others?  We need to be really clear on the policy objective.  This needs to a cross-party decision to the greatest extent possible.  </p><p>I was asked, correctly and very directly, what has happened since October.  A lot of work has gone on.  There has been a lot of analysis of this Bill.  I have been pushing this very hard within the Department.  The unit has also been working on assisted human reproduction, which I know the Senator is also very interested in.  It has been pushing both and has run up against some very serious legal challenges as to how to put this in place.</p><p>We have also instigated the review of the legislation on the termination of pregnancy.  I take the point that we should not tie the publication of the heads of a Bill or the passing of this Bill to the outcome of the review of the termination of pregnancy legislation but we are in the middle of a really comprehensive consultation with women who are using these services, clinicians who are providing them and the wider public and civil society.  This has been discussed directly with the chair of the review group and access to services is within the scope of the current consultation.  I am not going to wait months for a final report on phase 1.  As has been discussed with the team and the chair, we also need to draw in those experiences and those testimonies.  It is very important that we do so.  We should not finalise a Bill and then listen to what this big consultation has said and realise that we have missed things.  It is a shorter-term thing.  It is not a matter of pushing it out to the end of the year or anything but we need to do that as well.  </p><p>Yesterday, I wrote to the Chair of the Joint Committee on Health and we also had a chat earlier on today.  I told him that I want to bring the officials in the Department of Health who are immersed in the legal challenges, the opportunities and the different options that are available to a cross-party group.  That could be the Joint Committee on Health.  I have written to the committee asking whether it could free up time within the next four weeks.  I am not talking about a session of one or two hours; this is going to take a bit of time.  The committee is going to consider my request and come back to me very shortly.  If it cannot free up time, and it may not because I know it is flat out and is meeting three times this week, we are going to convene an all-party group to bring together people who are interested in this.  The group will have a detailed conversation with officials from the Department of Health.  We have received detailed advice from the Department of Justice and could potentially bring in other officials, as required.  We need to spend a bit of time, on an all-party basis, deciding what we want to achieve and identifying the genuine legal challenges we need to overcome to make sure this is robust, stacks up and will survive any challenges.  We then need to decide how to roll it out.  That is what I am proposing to do.</p><p>The Government will not be opposing the Bill before the House.  There is support for this Bill right across the House, which is very welcome to see.  I will also not be opposing any of the amendments.  Colleagues have asked why the Government has not tabled amendments.  The reason I have not tabled any amendments is that the officials are still working through exactly how this can work.  We all need to be honest with one another.  The advice I have been given is that it is hard to get this right.  If it was easy, there would already be an Act.  Rather than tabling amendments, we need to have this conversation in the coming weeks.  We need to agree on the policies, be honest with each other and listen to the officials with regard to legal challenges, operational challenges and enforcement challenges.  We then need to figure out a way forward and then either table very significant amendments to the Bill or redraft it.  From my perspective, it is a matter of determining the quickest route to getting the right legislation on the Statute Book.  That is my contribution for now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#V00200"><p>I thank the Minister for that clear explanation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#V00300"><p>I will be brief.  I thank the Minister for his response and for again being very clear on the fact that we need to legislate and that we will do so.  That is a very important measure and I want to acknowledge it.  However, I am concerned.  To be clear, my concern does not relate to the Minister.  He has been very consistent in his messaging on this matter from day one.  I am concerned that, as recently as last August, his Department was saying there was no need for this Bill.  I am concerned because we are now four years on from the promise that safe access zones would be legislated for and yet Department officials are apparently saying more time is needed.  I am concerned by the lack of timelines.  I agree with the Minister's point about an all-party approach but I think that is what we have here.  I could not be more positive about the contributions of my colleagues from the Government parties here today.  We have the ability to do that here.</p> <p>This is a good Bill.  It has been drafted well.  I accept that the Minister's officials have concerns.  I suggest that, after today, we meet with his officials.  Let us make sure that is done on an all-party basis because no one is trying to claim the crown in this regard.  Let us work through those concerns as quickly as we can because my concern is that, in 12 months' time, Senator Clifford-Lee, Senator Conway or I might still be asking where the legislation is.  Where are we going to be at that point?  In the meantime, there are women going to appointments in Limerick today and being targeted by these anti-choice protestors.  These women have waited too long.  Collectively, we need to do better.  We can absolutely deal with the questions the Minister has raised.  He made a point about registered premises.  We can have that conversation.  We are restricting it more here but we can look at it again on Report Stage.  We have time between Committee Stage and Report Stage to strengthen this Bill and to take on board concerns in order to deliver a Bill that almost everyone here knows is necessary.  That is what we have to do today.  </p> <p>I am not going to say more than that but I will briefly refer to those first three amendments because it is important to do so.  They are very simple.  They simply acknowledge the fact that we need to tighten up our definition of trade unions to recognise an "authorised trade union" as one "which holds a negotiation licence under the Trade Union Acts 1941 to 1990".  These three amendments, Nos. 1, 3 and 10, deal with that.  They are proposed under the advice of our colleagues in the trade union who just want to make sure that spurious groups do not present themselves as trade unions, which we know is entirely possible.  I hope we can deal with these amendments swiftly.  Let us do the business we are here to do today and then work constructively together.  Let us start that work as soon as this committee hearing is over.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#V00400"><p>I too welcome the visitors in the Gallery.  Of course, I do not agree with them or with what they seek but it is politicians who should primarily be held responsible for bringing forward legislation that is neither constitutional nor necessary and for doing so on the basis of claims about decent, harmless people that we already know to be very untrue.  It is about honesty.  There are deeply held feelings on both sides of the abortion debate.  I do not need to rehearse them here.  One third of the electorate voted to recognise that an unborn child has a right to life and that this right should be protected by the law and society.  That argument was lost, at least as far as numbers are concerned, but that cause will endure and see better days because the true human rights position is that we ought to treasure every human being.  Once we single out any section of society and deny them the protection of the law and the care of society, we are on a very bad road and, sadly, others will suffer in due course.</p> <p>With regard to this Bill, I will not rehearse what I said on Second Stage but there are serious questions about its constitutionality.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2250"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2250&amp;amp;pid=RonanMullen&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->If it were passed it would diminish the fundamental rights and freedoms of a particular group of Irish citizens, namely people who want to witness to the welfare of the unborn and to offer help to those who might be changing their mind and may be in doubt about whether they want to have an abortion, and to offer that help, if asked for it, in a respectful and decent way.</p><p>When this Bill was introduced last November, I pointed to the statement made by Garda Commissioner Drew Harris in which he confirmed that existing public order legislation was satisfactory to deal with any incidents related to protests, should they arise.  The Commissioner also placed on record at the time that protests outside facilities where abortions are carried out had not contravened the law and were peaceful.  There is nothing to suggest that the situation has changed since the Commissioner wrote to the then Minister for Health in 2019.  There is, in fact, more evidence that such witnessing, as has been going on, is a relatively small amount from everything I am told.  People have busy lives and it is quite a sacrifice to give of one's time to witness peacefully to the dignity and welfare of mothers and babies outside facilities where abortions may or may not be taking place at a given time.</p><p>I have met members of the pro-life movement who are dismayed and upset at the unfair way people like them are misrepresented and depicted, particularly when politicians and certain sections of the media seek to besmirch and sully their good names.  It is important to put on record their concerns particularly in the light of what the Minister has just said.   They would argue the motivation behind Bills like this has nothing to do with ensuring access to facilities to avail of services that are now legal.  It has everything to do with silencing any dissent around abortion, and it has everything to do with trying to create a false and misleading impression of the pro-life movement in order to strengthen that case.  Sadly, it seems to be that when it comes to pushing the case, whether it is activists, politicians or a Government Minister, the truth about what is actually going on does not seem to matter.</p><p>I listened to the Minister's very well-worded speech.  It was incorrect for the Minister to suggest that there is support all across the House for this Bill, which I believe are the words the Minister used.  The Minister must have known that there was at least one person in the Chamber who thinks this is seriously violative of human rights and human dignity, and it speaks to the Minister's carelessness around language.  What struck me was the amount of taxpayers' money that must go into the Minister preparing a convoluted argument in order to be seen to be fully on board with everything that the movement for abortion rights demands.  I believe this is a terrible dereliction of the Minister's duty as the Minister for Health.  I believe that the Minister has a higher duty to represent all citizens not just those who have different views about abortion, but also those who would expect that the Minister would only spend time advancing legislation that is constitutional, those who would expect the Minister to come in with a full grasp of the picture of what actually happens in relation to those small number of cases where people are witness to the rights of the unborn in circumstances where they are near facilities for such procedures as violate and deny those rights take place from time to time.</p><p>When the Bill was first introduced in November, part of the justification cited for its introduction was supposedly intimidatory protests outside abortion facilities in Limerick city instigated, it was claimed, by abortion opponents.  My colleague, with whom I get on with very well personally, Senator Gavan, repeated that allegation and more today when he talked about people targeting other people who are going into facilities to access abortion.  Everything he says, and everything behind this Sinn F&eacute;in Bill is designed to suggest that there are some very unpleasant people out there doing some very unpleasant things.  In fact, we are talking about decent people.  One of them - and I am not referring to Limerick in particular - I know to be a relative of a Government Minister.  They are democrats and, in many cases, are religious people.  I do not make religious arguments around abortion generally because I believe it is a human rights issue for people of all faiths and none.  There are many, however, who invoke the power of prayer in private, quiet and discreet ways, to hope for a better outcome.  Those quiet and mainly elderly people, who hardly raise their voices, are being portrayed here as menacing and targeting types.</p><p>I must say to Senator Gavan that it is one thing to say that on the basis of information he believes to be correct, but one month after the Senator said what he said in December 2021, the University of Limerick Hospitals Group issued a public statement confirming that they had received no complaints about protests outside the hospital.  The hospital spokesperson acknowledged that they were "satisfied that there is no issue with regard to safety of access at University Maternity Hospital Limerick".  It was not just the Garda Commissioner, it was also the Limerick hospital.  I would have expected then that Senator Gavan would correct the record, but I recall no effort being made to correct the record by Senator Gavan or others who disseminated the false and unfounded allegations against, let us call them, the pro-life supporters in the first instance.  I wonder if this is because it suits a political agenda to allow a lie to go halfway around the world because the truth will still not have its boots on?</p><p>When I hear further claims being made, suggestive of some kind of collusion, and suggesting that people's personal data is somehow being leaked to those who have concerns about abortions, I am inclined to disbelieve the people who make those claims.  I would urge any responsible politician to say "let us see the evidence".  We already know of one lie that was told and that was used in this case by a Sinn F&eacute;in Senator to advance the legislation at an earlier date.  How do I know, or how does any decent citizen know, that we are not being told another lie, and that Senator Gavan either wilfully or na&iuml;vely is, as it were, colluding?  This is a word that Sinn F&eacute;in members understand.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#W00200"><p>Senator Mullen is making an allegation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#W00300"><p>The Senator needs to withdraw that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#W00400"><p>I am asking people to be very careful about taking claims and using them for political purposes, claims that may in fact be fully mendacious and untruthful, and may be lies.  If they are true, then there is a breach of personal data that must be investigated.  It is not those people who are witnessing to the dignity of the unborn outside the clinics who need to be investigated-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#W00500"><p>I am sorry to interrupt the Senator but we did have a really respectful debate and the Senator is contributing to that.  We want everyone to feel that they can come into this Chamber and speak from any perspective.  I just want to draw the Senator's attention to one Standing Order in relation to suggesting that another Senator might have lied to the House.  That is all.  Perhaps Senator Mullen could withdraw that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#W00600"><p>I would not want to say that-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#W00700"><p>I would appreciate everyone here understanding the sensitivity of this issue and respecting everybody's position.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#W00800"><p>Absolutely.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#W00900"><p>We are doing that.  This is why I am being tolerant.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#W01000"><p>I am certainly happy to clarify that because, as I have said, I get on well with personally with Senator Gavan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#W01100"><p>Sure, absolutely.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#W01200"><p>I think what I said - and I am happy to check the record - but I think that what I said was that he had failed to draw attention to the House that the information on which he based the legislation, the claims about intimidatory behaviour that were contradicted by the University of Limerick Hospital Group, was actually shown to be untrue.  I think that I also said, or communicated in such a way as to make clear, that I was unaware of whether he had knowingly or unknowingly passed on that untruth.  The only claim I make is that he has not corrected the earlier untruth that he unwittingly or otherwise brought to this floor.  He has constructive knowledge now and he knows, or ought to know, that this was shown to be untrue.  My point is that when I hear further allegations here today, I worry that politicians are - na&iuml;vely or intentionally I do not know - doubling down on dishonesty in order to advance a certain political goal.  It would be wrong for a Government Minister to do that, it would be wrong for a Senator to do that, and it would be wrong for any citizen to do that.  I think I have made my position clear.  I do not know whether Senator Gavan was in a position to know that what he relayed to the House on a previous occasion was false but he owes it to the House to correct the record now that we all know that it was false.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2250"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2250&amp;amp;pid=RonanMullen&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->My point is that it is important to correct the record when we come to know that something is untrue.  People must not be surprised, then, that some people will find it hard - me included - to have any faith in the claims of those making the original unfounded allegations.  If claims are made, let us take them very seriously, but let us seek evidence.  Let us not seek to use unsubstantiated claims in order to advance the case of legislation that is in all likelihood unconstitutional and when people in the hospital in Limerick and the Garda Commissioner have communicated to leave us in no doubt that it is unnecessary.</p><p>Of course, there are things I can see in this legislation that I would be horrified to think would go on.  Words like "intimidation" and so on are contained in the legislation.  However, it was made very clear at an earlier stage that the law necessary to deal with any such unacceptable behaviour, which, not surprisingly, does not appear to be happening, is already in place.  It is considered bad political practice to duplicate legislation when we have the necessary legislative provisions in place to deal with it.</p><p>It is obvious to me why such intimidatory behaviour is not taking place.  The mainly elderly people who gather in small numbers to witness quietly to the dignity of the unborn are people who believe in human dignity.  That means they have respect not just for the unborn, but for the mother of that child and the people whose actions in ending that child's life they so passionately disagree with.  That is what respect for human dignity is about.  It is about respecting everybody.</p><p>However, it is also about demanding truthfulness.  The Minister's words today show that he and his officials are investing a lot of time and energy in order to, as it were, cosy up to this legislation, despite its non-necessity and probable unconstitutionality.  The idea that the Minister would be spending so much taxpayers' money to deal with a problem that in fact does not exist in order to placate a particular activist group is repugnant to me and many others.  I say that knowing that the Minister has claimed, on the record, that he would hear from and consult all sides in relation to abortion.  He has not done so.  Last week, I quoted the Minister in the Seanad and I also quoted Ms Geraldine Luddy and others addressing the meeting of the Joint Oireachtas Committee on Health on 8 December.  The Minister said he would advertise openly for an independent chair of the three-year review of abortion services.  The issue of honesty and consistency-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X00200"><p>That is a different issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X00300"><p>I will conclude with this.  The Minister said he would advertise openly.  Not only did he not do so, but he never put it on the record that he was not doing so until it was dragged out of him by parliamentary questions in recent times, when he revealed that a small number of people were invited to express interest in the role of independent chair.  He then appointed somebody who had engaged previously in a pattern of tweets suggestive of the fact that they supported repeal.  One must wonder-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X00400"><p>The Senator is straying from the point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X00500"><p>I am not.  I think the issue is-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X00600"><p>The issue was raised as a Commencement matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1643" speakername="Lorraine Clifford-Lee" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X00700"><p>On a point of order, an independent chair means independent of Government, not independent of the issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X00800"><p>Thank you.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1643" speakername="Lorraine Clifford-Lee" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X00900"><p>I think most people who would have a knowledge of medical concerns would agree with-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X01000"><p>That being said-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X01100"><p>We are trying to keep this debate calm.  If the Senator could-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X01200"><p>I am finishing up.  All I would say is that is the latest spin.  That is the first I have heard of that new definition of independent.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1643" speakername="Lorraine Clifford-Lee" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X01300"><p>It is independent of Government; that is what it is.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X01400"><p>So we are being told.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X01500"><p>Please allow Senator Mullen to finish without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X01600"><p>I am concluding.  This is important because what I am putting on the record is that claims that we know to be false in some cases, and may well turn out to be false in the case of the most recent claims that have been made, are being used to bolster legislation.  The Minister is not standing athwart those claims.  In everything he is doing, he is seeking to facilitate and express clear support for legislation that is neither necessary nor constitutional.  This is a Minister who, with his officials, has a record of not pursuing true even-handedness.  An abortion review has to look at the operation of legislation, including-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1643" speakername="Lorraine Clifford-Lee" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X01700"><p>A Leas-Chathaoirligh, you are going to have to ask the Senator to withdraw his comment about the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X01800"><p>I ask Senator Mullen to finish.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1643" speakername="Lorraine Clifford-Lee" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X01900"><p>I am sorry, we need to intervene.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X02000"><p>We are having a circular argument here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1643" speakername="Lorraine Clifford-Lee" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X02100"><p>We cannot allow Senator Mullen to say that about the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X02200"><p>I ask Senator Mullen to conclude-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X02300"><p>I am very close to concluding.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X02400"><p>-----because it is the same point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X02500"><p>It is as difficult for me to listen to things that I know and believe are harmful for our society and which, in some cases, I believe to be untrue, as it is for others to hear my carefully reflected upon and honestly held views about what I think is going on here.  I ask colleagues to respect the fact that as far as they know, I speak for at least one third of those who voted in 2018.  There may have been many other consequences of the 2018 legislation, which people who voted for repeal did not foresee, for example, the increase in the number of abortions and questions about pain relief being needed for the late-term abortions that sometimes take place.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1643" speakername="Lorraine Clifford-Lee" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X02600"><p>This needs to stop.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X02700"><p>My point is that is why we need somebody-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1643" speakername="Lorraine Clifford-Lee" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X02800"><p>Are we speaking to the amendments?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X02900"><p>That is why-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1643" speakername="Lorraine Clifford-Lee" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X03000"><p>I am sorry, a Leas-Chathaoirligh-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X03100"><p>I know.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1643" speakername="Lorraine Clifford-Lee" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X03200"><p>-----but we are not having this deeply-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X03300"><p>I ask Senator Mullen to conclude now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1643" speakername="Lorraine Clifford-Lee" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X03400"><p>The Senator needs to speak to the amendments; we are on Committee Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X03500"><p>I will let other people-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X03600"><p>I have listened to all the contributions and considerable latitude has been given.  My points are-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X03700"><p>We are trying to that here and we have done it to a large extent.  I think the Senator knows that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X03800"><p>As an Leas-Chathaoirleach knows, I would be finished by now if I had not been heckled.  The attempt, of course, is to prevent the point being made.  My point is that an independent person is not just somebody, as Senator Clifford-Lee stated, who-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X03900"><p>The Senator has made the point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X04000"><p>I did not get to make the point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X04100"><p>Thank you, Senator Mullen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X04200"><p>Please, a Leas-Chathaoirligh.  I want 30 seconds.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X04300"><p>It is not relevant.  We had a Commencement debate on the issue, to be fair.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X04400"><p>It is relevant because it is about-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X04500"><p>I indulged the Senator, as he knows.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X04600"><p>It is relevant because it is about-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X04700"><p>I wanted to keep this debate respectful.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X04800"><p>It would be very respectful if people would just let each other finish.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X04900"><p>I ask the Senator to finish now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X05000"><p>It has never been claimed that the only meaning of independent is independent of Government.  It is obvious to any reasonable person looking in that in order-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X05100"><p>Again, this is not relevant.  Sorry, Senator, but we can revert to the issue on another day.  It is not relevant in the sense that it is about a different issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X05200"><p>A Leas-Chathaoirligh, if you-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.159" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X05400"><p>The Senator is filibustering.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X05500"><p>Can I just make a point?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X05600"><p>The Bill is not about that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X05700"><p>He just wants to wind down the clock.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X05800"><p>The Bill is not about the Chair.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X05900"><p>I am about to finish.  If the Leas-Chathaoirleach stops me from making my point, allows the heckler to make her point and prevents me from responding, that cannot be correct parliamentary practice.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X06000"><p>We have given you a long time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X06100"><p>Let me just answer the point then.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X06200"><p>Okay.  I ask the Senator to finish his final sentence.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X06300"><p>Please, a Leas-Chathaoirligh.  You know what is going on here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1643" speakername="Lorraine Clifford-Lee" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X06400"><p>Yes, you are----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X06500"><p>Let us be fair.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1643" speakername="Lorraine Clifford-Lee" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X06600"><p>I am sorry-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.173" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X06700"><p>No, there is nothing-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.174" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X06800"><p>I am not going to go on until-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X06900"><p>In fairness, I ask Members to be quiet and respectful.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1643" speakername="Lorraine Clifford-Lee" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X07000"><p>We are on Committee Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.177" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X07100"><p>He said that five minutes ago.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X07200"><p>I ask Members to allow Senator Mullen finish.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.179" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1643" speakername="Lorraine Clifford-Lee" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X07300"><p>He cannot continue to call people liars in this House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X07400"><p>Senator Gavan will be able to respond in a minute.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.181" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X07500"><p>I did not call anybody a liar, as the Leas-Chathaoirleach knows.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.182" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X07600"><p>Can we abandon the discussion at this point?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.183" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.184" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X07800"><p>I ask for the protection of Leas-Chathaoirleach against the misrepresentation of what has just been said.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.185" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X07900"><p>I ask Senator Mullen to conclude.  He was given a lot of time and did very well.  We are making the same arguments in circles.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.186" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X08000"><p>The point I was trying to make was that in all of these months until now, it has not been suggested by anybody that the only meaning of independent is independent of Government.  Anybody looking at how legislation is operating would know that it would have to be somebody who does not have skin in the game.</p> <p>I conclude by asking the Minister to reflect on the fact that he does not just do his duty to the people of Ireland when he represents what he believes to be the majority opinion.  He has an obligation to full truthfulness about the necessity, purpose and constitutionality of legislation.  Just as importantly, he has an obligation to be truthful with others and with politicians.  He did not do what he said he was going to do about the way he was advertising.  He has not come on the record to explain it.  Everything has been done, as I put it last week, in ways that suggest a dishonest approach by the Government.  I am sorry to have to use that word.  I ask the Minister, even at this stage, to change that approach and to-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.187" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#X08100"><p>The Minister will respond later.  Thank you, Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#Y00200"><p>-----start to listen to both sides on the abortion issue.  I say that as respectfully as I can, but the situation is very serious and regrettable.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.189" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#Y00300"><p>I appreciate that.  I wish to make it clear to Members that because of the gravity and sensitivity of the issue, I was trying to achieve a respectful and calm debate so that it did not turn into something it should not, and we are doing our best.  We are trying to achieve that.  Before Senator Hoey takes the Chair, it would be in order to let Senator Gavan respond to the specific issue relating to him, followed by Senator Boylan.  I ask Senator Gavan respond only to the specific issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.190" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#Y00400"><p>Absolutely.  The specific issue Senator Mullen raised was in relation to University of Limerick Hospitals Group and its statement.  I have nothing to apologise for.  I have no reason to correct the record of the House because what the hospitals group said was that it did not record any complaints.  We know a great number of complaints were made - indeed, the people in the Chamber today are witnesses to those complaints.  Therefore, there is no need for me to correct the record of the House.  I must say on the record that in the six years I have been here-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.191" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#Y00500"><p>Does the Senator want the full report?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.192" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#Y00600"><p>-----I have never accused anyone in this Chamber of telling lies.  I am disgusted such a charge was made against me today.  The Minister can see what is happening here.  It again emphasises the importance of working with the Bill.  We have just 40 minutes left in this debate.  This is what we will all face unless we collectively come together and work this Bill through to its conclusion and deliver what we need to in order to protect women and pregnant people approaching hospitals today across the State.  Let us get going and do that.  Let us work through these amendments now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.193" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#Y00700"><p>I do not want to take up time.  We have seen a filibuster here before us and we know exactly what is playing out in the Chamber.  I wish to welcome those from Together for Safety who are present and have done an enormous amount of work in getting this Bill as far as they have.  I ask the Minister to share the legal advice he referred to, which he said in October he had and about which he spoke again today.  The people who drafted this Bill are legal people.  They ask that he share this advice.  They are prepared to work with the Minister on this Bill but he must share what he believes are the stumbling blocks.  He cannot continue to hide behind that argument and not allow those who are trying to help him to do so.  Will the Minister share that legal advice with Together for Safety and the people who have help craft this Bill?</p> <p>I cannot but mention Senator Mullen's comments.  He continuously comes into the Chamber and talks about having respect for the people who voted "No" in the repeal the eighth amendment referendum.  He is right.  Absolutely everybody has a right to their democratic vote and to be respected for that vote.  However, he is not listening to what the women who are trying to access healthcare are telling him.  We recently had a debate in this Chamber about violence against women.  We all talked about how women's voices need to be listened to.  People need to listen to the experiences of women.  Women are telling us they are intimidated and frightened, and there is a chilling factor in accessing healthcare.  Senator Mullen is entitled to his opinion on this - that is absolutely fine - but I am asking him to open his ears and to listen to what women are telling him.  They feel intimidated.  </p> <p>Senator Mullen can refer to those involved as decent people, mainly older people, or say they are reflecting in quiet prayer.  He can say all of that.  It does not matter what they are doing.  The reality is that the feeling of the person they are doing it to is one of intimidation.  I ask Senator Mullen to reflect on that and to listen to what those experiencing it are telling him.  That is all I ask him to do.  I fully support him in saying we have to respect people's different views, but when women are telling him they are being intimidated, he must listen to the voices of the women who are being intimidated.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.194" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1663" speakername="Annie Hoey" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#Y00800"><p>I remind everyone we are discussing amendments Nos. 1, 3, and 10 on trade unions and the different amendments proposed.  I ask that we bear that in mind.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.195" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#Y00900"><p>I presume the Acting Chairperson will give me the same latitude other speakers have been given.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.196" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1663" speakername="Annie Hoey" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#Y01000"><p>Of course.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#Y01100"><p>Thank you.</p> <p>On the specific point Senator Mullen raised regarding the UL Hospitals Group not being notified, it does not mean An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na was not notified.  If there was activity outside the hospital, the more appropriate people to contact on that issue would have been the garda&iacute;.  I respectfully suggest there is more than one source to which a complaint can be made.  If the hospital said what it said, I do not argue or dispute it.  However, I believe complaints have been made in other ways.</p> <p>People protest in different ways and people are hurt in different ways.  People who are availing of a termination are at a vulnerable stage in their lives.  It is not appropriate, even if people do not engage with them.  Their mere presence, be it in quiet reflection, prayer or whatever it may be, is not appropriate.  People are intimidated in many different ways.  I suggest it is a form of intimidation.</p> <p>I spoke to the Minister when he was before Joint Committee on Health last December.  I asked him specifically about this legislation.  He said it was a priority, that he was hoping to produce the heads of a Bill and bring a memo to Cabinet, and that this would be done before the end of March.  I have a clear question.  I presume the Minister will honour that timeline, which was made on the record of the health committee last December, because time is important.  This needs to happen.</p> <p>This Bill is before the House today and it will return whereupon Senators will be asked to vote on it.  It is a matter of conscience as was the eighth amendment.  Members of Government who voted in a certain way, for or against, did not lose the Whip.  I am putting the Minister on notice that I consider this legislation as being in the realm of conscience.  As such, I believe the Whip should be loosely imposed and that if a Member from the Government's side decides to vote for this legislation, he or she should not lose the Whip.</p> <p>In order to avoid that situation, I strongly urge the Minister to bring his legislation to Cabinet and send it to the health committee, where pre-legislative scrutiny will happen very quickly.  Senator Hoey and I, and others, are on this committee.  We will ensure this happens.  The Minister will then be in a position to bring his legislation to the House.  He pointed out today that there are issues with the Bill and that his legal advice states there are flaws in it.  I encourage him to publish that legal advice.  He told the health committee before Christmas that he had already spoken to the Attorney General and the legal people in the Department concerning his own Bill.  I note that it is on the priority list of legislation.  It is now the beginning of February.  The Minister gave a specific time commitment at the committee.  I questioned him on it on a number of occasions so that we would be clear and there would be no confusion.  He said the Bill would be referred to the Joint Committee on Health no later than the end of March.  Will the Minister give his assurance that this time commitment will be honoured?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.198" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1663" speakername="Annie Hoey" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#Y01200"><p>As no one else has indicated, the Minister might like to respond to the questions or statements.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.199" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1623" speakername="Stephen Donnelly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#Y01300"><p>A few direct questions have been asked.  Absolutely, we will share the advice.  There will be legal advice.  We cannot share Attorney General advice.  My understanding is that we can share departmental advice.  It is an analysis as opposed to a lawyer's opinion, and what we would all understand to be legal advice.  I am happy to share whatever I can in that regard.  What is probably more useful to us is the departmental advice.  It has gone through it section by section and has worked through many of the challenges there are with the Bill.  As I said, it has done much work and is engaging with the Department of Justice.</p> <p>I want to go further than sharing the advice.  As I said at the start, I want to go through the Joint Committee on Health in the first instance.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Stephen Donnelly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2336"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2336&amp;amp;pid=StephenDonnelly&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->If the Joint Committee on Health has not the time we will convene an all-party group to meet to not only share the advice, but I want the officials to present the advice, present the challenges, and I want a very open conversation across the parties, both those who agree and disagree.  This is complex, so share the advice, yes, but let us go much further and get this either in public session or closed session, I do not mind.  Whatever moves this quickest.</p><p>Of course we can share it outside the Oireachtas.  We want to get as many people involved in solving this as quickly as possible.  I agree with Senator Boyhan's point in regard to listening to women.  We have to listen to women and to our clinicians.  That is one of the reasons it is very important that some initial feedback on the consultation on the review of termination of pregnancy is important.  It is quite a wide consultation and we would be well advised to make sure that we are getting that in for consideration, so that we are hearing from women and from clinicians.  </p><p>For anyone in civil society or anyone outside the Oireachtas, one of the strands of the termination of pregnancy review is a public consultation so anyone can have an input and have his or her voice heard through that strand.  I reiterate that it is important that, where women are being intimidated, or feel threatened, they contact the Garda.  In some cases they may not do so.  These are situations where women are going through incredibly difficult situations, they are under intense pressure and it is not an obvious thing.  They might just want to get in or get out and get home.  I fully understand that.  For those who can, it is very useful to contact the Garda.  Indeed there may well be cases, if An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na is contacted it allows a complaint to be responded to.  An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na believes it has comprehensive powers right now.  I encourage anyone that where it is appropriate - and I know it is not always so - to contact the Garda. </p><p>In regard to the timing, we are not going to be in a position to do pre-legislative scrutiny.  There is a step before that which is what we have been discussing today.  I have asked the Joint Committee on Health to meet within the next four weeks.  As soon as I hear back from the Joint Committee on Health, if it is not possible for the committee to meet, within a week or two we will convene an all-party group straightaway.  I would say in about four weeks from now.  I will ask the Department to put together some detailed notes that can be shared for that discussion and then either the Joint Committee on Health or an all-party group will convene and meet in about four weeks to move this along.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.201" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.202" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#Z00200"><p>I move amendment No. 2:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 3, lines 13 and 14, to delete &ldquo;services provided for the provision of contraception or advice in relation to contraception&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;the prescribing of contraception&rdquo;. </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.203" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.204" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#Z00400"><p>I move amendment No. 3:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 3, to delete lines 19 and 20. </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.205" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.206" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Section 1, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.207" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Section 2 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.208" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>SECTION 3</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.209" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1663" speakername="Annie Hoey" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#Z00900"><p>Amendments Nos. 4 to 6, inclusive, are related and may be discussed together by agreement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.210" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#Z01000"><p>I move amendment No. 4:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 4, line 15, after &ldquo;person&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;or a series of persons&rdquo;. </blockquote> <p>I will briefly comment on amendment No. 2.  I supported it but again it was an example of the question about pharmacies and the question about students' unions.  Those concerns no longer stand now that the amendment has been agreed because it is very clear that it is only the prescribing, so it is only around medical practices and not around places for example where contraception is available or sold.  That is an example of how a concern can be addressed and has been addressed.</p><p>I am a little concerned.  The Minister talks about the quickest way but I am not sure what he is outlining is the quickest route.  I would prefer if the Joint Committee on Health was just looking at pre-legislative scrutiny.  Why not a heads of Bill?  We at least know the policy thrust that we want.  However, there is the idea that the Joint Committee on Health would have to have a pre-stage, then a pre-legislative scrutiny stage, and then it will have its chance when there is legislation to amend it appropriately as a committee.  It seems to me that we have a Bill, which is a discussion point.  I will be delighted if Government legislation comes in quickly and outflanks that but I am concerned at delays.</p><p>The Minister talked about the fact that it was not dealt with in the last Oireachtas.  We might end up with a scenario where we do not deal with it in this Oireachtas, or even in this term.  We had hoped to see Government legislation by March.  I certainly do not think we should be starting a conversation about the possibility of legislation in March.  We need to be in a conversation that is hard and is about legislation.  It needs to be specific.  We should be having legislation, be it our legislation - the Minister can hear the support that is in the House from many Members for it - or be it Government legislation.  We should not be going into the summer and into another two- or three-month period where women cannot access the services without facing that situation.  Let us be clear, we place a very tight constraint on those who are seeking to access abortion.  They face that 12-week constraint.  Many people will be affected and continue to be affected.  Older people were mentioned.  I worked with older people in a previous job for many years.  Many older people are very keen for this to be done too.  Many older women in particular in Ireland suffered under the previous systems and regimes.  They want to know that the full change to an Ireland which actually supports women has fully happened and this is part of that.  </p><p>My amendments were around &quot;a series of persons&quot; - as a &quot;person&quot;,  &quot;or a series of persons&quot;.  I have that concern around when one has intimidatory and harassment activity, if it is happening, maybe not to the same person multiple times but to a series of people.  I have actually had engagement.  As an example of that engagement with the lawyers and the legal advice of those who put the Bill together, they have assured me that the &quot;person&quot;, singular here, will have relevant effect in terms of the person plural, so in that context I do not need to press my amendment.  I have been satisfied with the legal response.  It is yet another example, like amendment No. 2, of the fact that we can tease these issues out.  We can work together.  Let us work together inside a frame of legislation rather than moving the issue outside legislation to another general topic discussion.  It has to be within a legislative frame.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.211" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#Z01100"><p>I appreciate everything that Senator Higgins has said.  I acknowledge the fact that she is going to withdraw those amendments.  That is absolutely fine.  The points she makes are very important but under the Interpretation Act 1937 we are actually covered already in regard to that.  To reiterate to the Minister in regard to amendment No. 2, we are pleased to see that moved but we are open to further discussion in regard to that issue, so that we can tease it out together and happily revisit it on Report Stage if necessary.  We just need to move this process on.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.212" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#Z01200"><p>I thank Senator Higgins for her constructive contribution.  Can I clarify with the Minister exactly what he is proposing in terms of the Joint Committee on Health?  In December my understanding was that the Minister then intended to bring a memo to Cabinet in regard to the heads of the legislation, and then to refer the heads of the legislation to the committee for pre-legislative scrutiny, and this would happen at the end of March as the latest possible date.  I am looking at the exact quotes, but I have more or less paraphrased the commitments the Minister gave.  Why has that changed?  I do not understand that.  Why has the structure of what he proposed in December changed now?  Is there a reason for it?<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Martin Conway:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2347"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2347&amp;amp;pid=MartinConway&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Maybe I just do not understand what the reason for this is, but I was very clear in my view that we were to have the heads of a Bill on which to carry out pre-legislative scrutiny quickly by the end of March at the latest.  The Minister might explain again what he proposes to do in four weeks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.214" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1663" speakername="Annie Hoey" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#AA00200"><p>Does the Minister wish to respond?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.215" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1623" speakername="Stephen Donnelly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#AA00300"><p>I am more than happy to do so.  I want an all-party discussion on this matter.  I have been presented with opinion by the Department, which spent a lot of time looking at this.  The Department got a very clear instruction from me to provide the heads of the Bill to me.  It has been working very hard to that effect and has come back to say that this is very difficult to do.  I am sure that if it were easy to do, Senator Conway's party would have done it in the previous D&aacute;il, during the term of the previous Government, but it did not.  One of the reasons it did not was that An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na said it did not need this measure and had very strong advice stating that it was not necessary, would not be constitutional, would not survive a challenge and so forth.  I have given very clear instruction to the Department to find solutions to the very serious challenges.</p> <p>I want to make sure that there is a discussion on a cross-party basis that shapes this legislation.  If I were to come up with heads of the Bill and send them to the committee for pre-legislative scrutiny, that would significantly narrow the debate, as we are all aware.  The committee can respond only to what is before it.  I want a broad conversation.  There has to be all-party input to this from both those who agree and those who disagree with the legislation, which is absolutely fine.  In the context of what we are legislating for, this is unlike a lot of the other health Bills we see, where there is a very clear policy intent, heads of the Bill are created and the detail can then be discussed.  In this case, the advice I have back from the Department is that, potentially, some quite significant trade-offs must be made here.  We are looking at constitutionality, civil liberties, freedom of speech and so on.  It is appropriate, given the magnitude of that to which I refer, that this is discussed in the coming weeks, that we find a way forward and that we then present the heads of the Bill.  I would then bring a memorandum to the Government and that would then go to the health committee for pre-legislative scrutiny.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.216" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#AA00400"><p>I thank the Minister for that.  I have no doubt but that this is difficult.  As he stated, if it were not, one would hope it would have been done before now.  What is the timeline, though?  Obviously, the Minister will provide all the advice he has got from the Department which has resulted in his having to make this decision on a way forward.  What is the absolute end date by which he expects the legislation to be passed in the Houses of the Oireachtas?  That is what people want.  Clearly, the process is complex, difficult and challenging - I totally understand that - but I would like the Minister to put on the record an end date by which he expects the legislation to have passed both Houses of the Oireachtas.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.217" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1663" speakername="Annie Hoey" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#AA00500"><p>We are discussing an amendment that will be withdrawn-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.218" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#AA00600"><p>I know.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.219" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1663" speakername="Annie Hoey" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#AA00700"><p>-----and I have given the Senator a great deal of latitude on the matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.220" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#AA00800"><p>Sure.  I appreciate that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.221" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1663" speakername="Annie Hoey" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#AA00900"><p>Perhaps this could be tabled as a Commencement matter or followed up with the Minister.  I will see if the Minister wishes to respond, but we have limited time left within which to get through the amendments to the Bill.  I appreciate that the Senator seeks an answer to his question.  Does the Minister wish to come in or is he happy for us to-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.222" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1623" speakername="Stephen Donnelly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#AA01000"><p>We can discuss the matter on another date.  I have given the Senator everything I can at this point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.223" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.224" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendments Nos. 5 and 6 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.225" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1663" speakername="Annie Hoey" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#AA01300"><p>Amendments Nos. 7 and 8 are related and will be discussed together.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.226" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#AA01400"><p>I move amendment No. 7:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 4, line 30, to delete &ldquo;six months&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;one year&rdquo;. </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.227" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.228" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#AA01600"><p>I move amendment No. 8:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 4, line 30, after &ldquo;both&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;or on indictment to a fine not exceeding &euro;5,000 or imprisonment for a term not exceeding 5 years&rdquo;. </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.229" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.230" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#AA01800"><p>I move amendment No. 9:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 4, line 32, after &ldquo;of&rdquo; where it firstly occurs to insert &ldquo;supporting access to or&rdquo;. </blockquote> <p>With amendment No. 9, I am seeking to ensure that somebody who might be accompanying somebody else - for example, a spouse - would not inadvertently fall under the text of the Bill.  However, I am happy to withdraw the amendment now and address the issue on Report Stage.  Clearly, we will tease out these issues in the meantime.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.231" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.232" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#AA02000"><p>I move amendment No. 10:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 4, line 36, to delete &ldquo;a registered&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;an authorised&rdquo;. </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.233" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.234" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That section 3, as amended, stand part of the Bill."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.235" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#AA02300"><p>I wish to speak to this section.  My question is prompted by the meaning of a part of the section.  I listened very carefully to what Senator Boylan had to say about listening to women.  I agree 100% that we must never tire of listening to people on all sides of this issue and to people who have had personal experiences.  I am certainly open to that, and I can understand that people might feel intimidated by the very presence of a person whom they know to have a different view.  That is a problematic thing in a democracy and something we need to think about very carefully.  We need to think carefully about the extent to which we silence disagreement in such situations.  What prompts that comment is a certain passage in the Bill.  I am very open to being assisted by Senator Gavan on this, although obviously I oppose this Bill and will vote against this section anyway.  I am asking about section 3, which states:</p> <blockquote> 	(1) While in a safe access zone established under <i>section 2</i>of this Act, a person must not:  	(a) express or demonstrate support for or opposition to a person's decision to access ... or facilitate the provision of termination of pregnancy services or contraceptive services;  </blockquote> <p>I ask that I be corrected if I am mistaken.  There may be something else in Senator Gavan's Bill that would prevent such an outcome, but if you are, let us say, sitting in a coffee shop and having a conversation with a person and that person discloses in the course of that conversation that he or she works across the road in the hospital and is sometimes involved in abortions in some way, and if you then say, &quot;Gosh, I am very sorry to hear that; I do not believe abortion is right&quot;, would you be in breach of the legislation?  On my reading of it, you would be in breach of the legislation.  That is why I ask the question.  How can the Minister come in here and - if I am right - not comment in detail about ramifications such as that, or are we in some kind of parallel universe?  I have noticed this only now, so I am completely open to being told that is not the meaning of the section.  As far as I can see, however, if someone is within the zone and not there for any organised purpose or to witness, as I said, the dignity of the unborn or anything like that but happens to end up in conversation with somebody who might be involved in providing abortions, and if that person happens to express a view on the matter, perhaps in a coffee shop, perhaps to somebody he or she knows or an acquaintance of somebody he or she knows, that person might be in trouble under this legislation.  I would be very grateful for the Senator's assistance on that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.236" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1693" speakername="Pauline O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#AA02400"><p>I was watching some of the proceedings from my office.  I think there is an awful lot of purposeful confusion, dare I say.  I am sure of what Senator Mullen is trying to do here.  Fundamentally, he is voting against the Bill, which means it is not really these things that he has an issue with.  We need to be all very clear on that.  If there were clarity around that matter, would he vote in favour of the Bill?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.237" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#AA02500"><p>No.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.238" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1693" speakername="Pauline O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#AA02600"><p>No.  Exactly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.239" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#AA02700"><p>It would still highlight something very dramatic, though, would it not?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.240" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1693" speakername="Pauline O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#AA02800"><p>These amendments will have to go to the D&aacute;il anyway-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.241" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#AA02900"><p>So it does not matter how wrong we get the legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.242" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1693" speakername="Pauline O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#AA03000"><p>-----so I am sure some of the Senator's colleagues will table an amendment in the D&aacute;il that will make him feel more comfortable with the legislation.</p> <p>To go back to one of the issues raised earlier in the debate, when, as I said, I was listening in my office, I heard Senator Clifford-Lee give us all some clarity on independence.  What does independence mean?<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Pauline O'Reilly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=PaulineOreilly&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We have had a referendum in this country.  The people have spoken and we do not need to go back and do it again.  The issue around the independence of a chairperson relates to independence from Government.  It is not about going back and redoing the entire legislation.  I wanted to put my view on that, as I have done many times.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.244" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#BB00200"><p>There is a lot of space in the middle between those two extremes.  I think Senator O'Reilly will agree with that and take my point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.245" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1693" speakername="Pauline O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#BB00300"><p>Senator Mullen and I can discuss this ourselves elsewhere, maybe over a coffee or something stronger.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.246" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#BB00400"><p>I am up for that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.247" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#BB00500"><p>I assure Senator Mullen that he is safe in his coffee shop.  That is not covered by the legislation and such a situation would not arise.  The meaning of the phrase "express or demonstrate" is very clearly, and in a nuanced way, set out and categorised under subsection (2).  The latter describes exactly what is included, for the purpose of subsection (1), within the phrase "express or demonstrate".  It includes behaviour such as persistent, continuous or repeated actions and interfering with, intimidating, harassing or trying to persuade or inform somebody.  It is not about a person expressing his or her opinion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.248" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#BB00600"><p>What about advising?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.249" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#BB00700"><p>Advising and seeking to influence are at issue but it is not around a person expressing his or her views.  Anybody can sit in a coffee shop and express his or her views but not with the intention of either influencing or intimidating another person.  The issue is spelled out in some nuance and with some thought and detail under subsection (2).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.250" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#BB00800"><p>I thank Senator Higgins for trying to give me reassurance and I respect what Senator Pauline O'Reilly has to say.  However, if it were to be the case that only people who are in favour of legislation in some form would ever make observations about the unsought side effects or unforeseen consequences contained in a particular legislative proposal, we would not be doing our job at all.  I am entitled to test these provisions and try whatever intellect I have in applying it to them.  It is the same for everybody here.</p> <p>I disagree with Senator Pauline O'Reilly's point about what is meant by an independent chairperson in this context.  As I have said before, where legislation might have unforeseen consequences - which could be raised, in this instance, by those who might argue in favour of extending abortion services or those who might say something was not foreseen or discussed when the Bill was introduced - that is all within the remit of a review of the legislation and, therefore, independence really requires somebody who does not have an expressed personal ideological preference about any of the issues.  That is always what we look for when we look for independent people.  It is not just about being independent of Government; it has never thus far been described as such, so far as I can see.</p> <p>In response to Senator Higgins and the point about people expressing a view, she points out that there is a whole set of subcategories that seek to define what "express or demonstrate" means, but that includes advising, persuading and informing, or attempting to advise, persuade or inform, any person concerning issues related to termination of pregnancy services etc., with references to "by any means" and "without limitation".  In other words, if I am in a conversation in a coffee shop and I discover that somebody is involved in the provision of abortion, these provisions might include a situation where I were to say, "Do you know there is now a significant debate about the capacity of an unborn child to feel pain in the course of an abortion and that it should not be happening without precautionary pain relief being legislated for or ethically?", or "I would encourage you to think about whether you should be involved in providing abortions".  That is all in there and I think Senator Higgins has been too rash in trying to allay the concern I have expressed.  I ask her to read the text again.  I think I read English as well as she can.  She is a very good and powerful advocate for her point of view and I credit her with that.  However, it seems clear to me that anybody who would seek to advise or even inform somebody about the injustice of abortion, if that conversation is happening within a so-called safe access zone-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.251" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#BB00900"><p>I ask Senator Mullen to keep to the section under discussion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.252" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#BB01000"><p>-----then it would be very much caught by this legislation.</p> <p>What the Senator said does not offer reassurance to anybody who thinks it would be wrong to criminalise a person for simply expressing a view to a third party, such as a party who happens to be involved in the provision of services in a hospital across the road from where the conversation is taking place.  This shows that the legislation is extremely draconian.  It is about silencing.  In a country where we have differences of opinion and where particular services are now legally available, I am up for making sure the law prevents anybody from being harassed or intimidated or any of that bad stuff.  As for stopping people from having a conversation in a coffee shop, we all need to call ourselves aside here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.253" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and declared carried.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.254" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Section 4 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.255" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>NEW SECTION</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.256" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#BB01400"><p>I move amendment No. 11:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 5, between lines 27 and 28, to insert the following:<br /><br /><b>&quot;Power of member of Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na to give direction</b><br /><br /><b>5. </b>(1) Where a member of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na finds a person in a public place and suspects, with reasonable cause, that such person&mdash;  	(a) intends to breach any of the provisions of sections 3 or 4 of this Act,<br /><br />(b) is about to breach any of the provisions of sections 3 or 4 of this Act, or<br /><br />(c) is attempting to breach the provisions of sections 3 or 4 of this Act, the member may direct the person to leave immediately that place and the vicinity thereof in a peaceable and orderly manner.<br /><br />(2) It shall be an offence for any person, without reasonable excuse, to fail to comply with a direction given by a member of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na under this section.<br /><br />(3) A person guilty of an offence under this section shall be liable on summary conviction to a fine not exceeding &euro;1,000 or imprisonment for a term not exceeding one month or both.&quot;.  </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.257" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.258" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sections 5 and 6 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.259" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Title agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.260" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Bill reported with amendments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.261" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#BB02000"><p>When is it proposed to take Report Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.262" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#BB02100"><p>Next Tuesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.263" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#BB02200"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.264" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Report Stage ordered for Tuesday, 15 February 2022.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.265" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#BB02400"><p>When is it proposed to sit again?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.266" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1643" speakername="Lorraine Clifford-Lee" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021000002#BB02500"><p>Next Tuesday at 2.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-10a.267" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar athl&oacute; ag 2.58 p.m. go dt&iacute; 2.30 p.m., D&eacute; M&aacute;irt, an 15 Feabhra 2022.</p><p>The Seanad adjourned at 2.58 p.m. until 2.30 p.m. on Tuesday, 15 February 2022.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>