<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.2" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Leas-Chathaoirleach i gceannas ar 14:30</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.4" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.5" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800003#B00100"><p>I have received notice from Senator C&aacute;it Keane that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, she proposes to raise the following matter:<blockquote><br />The need for the Minister for Justice and Equality to discuss the fact there is no legislation or regulations in place to facilitate the orderly transfer of personnel bilaterally between the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and the Police Service of Northern Ireland and the absence of any guarantee, or written provision, that the personnel who do opt to transfer can be assured they can resume their positions and employment with an Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, having completed their service. </blockquote>I have also received notice from Senator Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh of the following matter:<blockquote>Go dtabharfaidh an tAire Oideachas agus Scileanna soil&eacute;iri&uacute; maidir leis na fiosr&uacute;ch&aacute;in at&aacute; ar bun ag a Roinn, faoi na l&iacute;omhaint&iacute; ionsaithe gn&eacute;is at&aacute; d&eacute;anta maidir le h-iar-cheannasa&iacute; ar Chol&aacute;iste Samhraidh agus m&uacute;inteoir, c&eacute; na t&eacute;arma&iacute; tagartha at&aacute; aontaithe, c&eacute;n amsc&aacute;la at&aacute; beartaithe chuige agus c&eacute;n uair at&aacute; s&uacute;il go bhfoilseofar na tuairisc&iacute; go poibl&iacute;. </blockquote>I have also received notice from Senator Lorraine Higgins of the following matter:<blockquote>To ask Minister for Health if he will indicate when Portumna medical centre will reopen for the use and benefit of the people of Portumna and its surrounding hinterland; and if he will intervene to expedite the matter.</blockquote>I have also received notice from Senator Averil Power of the following matter:<blockquote>To ask the Minister for Health to outline what he intends to do to address the chaotic situation in the Dublin North mental health service; and to make a statement on the matter.</blockquote>I have also received notice from Senator Fidelma Healy Eames of the following matter:<blockquote>To ask the Minister for Communications, Marine and Natural Resources to ensure that Galway Bay is on a priority list for an oyster fishing plan for 2013.</blockquote>I have also received notice from Senator Martin Conway of the following matter:<blockquote>The need for the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government to indicate the progress being made on an offer of Leader grant funding to the Tommy White Memorial Community Centre, Moy, Lahinch, County Clare.</blockquote>I have also received notice from Senator Denis Landy of the following matter:<blockquote>To ask the Minister for Arts, Heritage and Gaeltacht Affairs if he can arrange with the National Museum of Ireland to transfer the collection of gold coins that was recently discovered in Carrick-on-Suir back to Carrick-on-Suir for a once-off, one-day event to enable these coins to be exhibited, possibly in the Tudor Manor. </blockquote>I regard the matters raised by Senators Keane, &Oacute; Clochartaigh, Higgins and Power as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment and they will be taken at the conclusion of business.  I regret I have had to rule out of order the matter raised by Senator Landy as the Minister has no official responsibility in the matter.  Senators Healy Eames and Conway may give notice on another day of the matters they wish to raise.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.7" nospeaker="true" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800004#C00050">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.8" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800004#C00100"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, motion regarding the development of Cork Prison, back from committee, to be taken without debate at the conclusion of the Order of Business; No. 2, Housing (Amendment) Bill 2013 - Second Stage, to be taken at the conclusion of No. 1 and conclude not later than 5.45 p.m., with the contributions of group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes and those of all other Senators not to exceed five minutes and the Minister to be called on to reply to the debate not later than 5.35 p.m.; and No. 3, Public Service Management (Recruitment and Appointments) (Amendment) Bill 2013 - Committee Stage, to be taken at 5.45 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800004#C00200"><p>I know the issue of the ongoing crisis and civil war in Syria has been raised in the House.  Could we arrange a debate with the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade?  I state my support for his stance on the issue.  It is a very dangerous situation where certain countries are looking to arm rebel groups, but this will only exacerbate the problem.  The T&aacute;naiste was very strong in his statements on this issue a number of weeks ago.  However, we need to tease out this issue further.  I would not support in any shape or form arming rebel groups in Syria.  The Seanad might provide an opportunity for the T&aacute;naiste to bring us up to date on the progress that has been made at EU level in dealing with the conflict.</p><p>Tomorrow the Government will announce the new code of conduct on mortgage arrears.  We argued vociferously against this on the basis that the Government was also bringing forward the Land and Conveyancing Law Reform Bill which would effectively allow open season on those in mortgage arrears by closing the loophole in respect of home repossessions.  I remind the House that over 145,000 mortgages on principal private residences are in arrears.  The figure is up by over 50,000 in the two years since the Government took office.  In that time we have seen certain initiatives such as the Government advising the banks, including the two pillar banks, that they should be looking at other measures, with which I agree.  However, out of between 145,000 and 150,000 mortgages in arrears, we have only seen 52 split mortgages.  We have also seen the abject failure of the mortgage-to-rent scheme.  I will use the debate this afternoon with the Minister of State with responsibility for housing and planning at the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government, Deputy Jan O'Sullivan, to discover what is being done in that area in which most local authorities will not even operate the scheme.  We are continuing to sleepwalk into a deeper crisis.  After the new code of conduct on mortgage arrears is published tomorrow, I ask the Leader to arrange a debate on it some time next week.  I have called for a broad debate on mortgage resolution measures for which there has been broad agreement, but I would like us to debate in a constructive way the new code of conduct when it is published.</p><p>During a debate on capital investment on 22 November 2011 I raised with the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform the issue of the greater Dublin drainage scheme, on which the Government proposed to spend over &euro;1 billion.  In the light of such massive capital expenditure by the taxpayer, I asked him at the very least to carry out a cost-benefit analysis of the scheme.  He twice gave me an undertaking that he would have the matter investigated, but he has since refused to do so.  He would not take an Adjournment debate on it last week with my colleague Senator Averil Power.  The people of the greater Dublin area but of north Dublin, in particular, deserve much better.  I, therefore, ask the Leader to use his good offices to follow up on the commitment given to me by the Minister on 22 November 2011 that he would ensure the expenditure on this project would be investigated.  A sum of &euro;1 billion or more is not a small amount of money.  I, therefore, ask the Leader to raise the matter with the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="14:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800005#D00100"><p>I join Senator Darragh O'Brien in calling for a debate on the situation in Syria.  It would be timely to invite the T&aacute;naiste to come to the House to discuss the possible approaches that could be taken to this problem.  I share the T&aacute;naiste's view on the danger of arming rebel group in Syria.  In the context of the G8 summit, we would all have hoped some international resolution might have been found.  Many of us might share the view of the Canadian Premier, Mr. Stephen Harper, on the intransigence of the Russian Government's insistence on backing the Assad regime.  There needs to be middle ground between arming the rebels and the unquestioning support Russia and Iran are giving the vicious Assad regime.  It is a pity something stronger has not come from the G8 summit in County Fermanagh.</p><p>I also call for a debate on homophobia in the context of a law proposed by the Lower House of Parliament in Russia which outlaws LGBT activism and criminalises positive depiction of the lives of gay people.  This law has received a great deal of international attention and criticism.  It is described as the gay propaganda law and is already law in some Russian regions, but there is a Bill being debated in Russia to make it a national law.  I am deeply troubled by this development.  I know that many other legislators around the world have expressed their concern about this draconian Bill.  It is also a matter for the Council of Europe, given that it has made it clear that it expects member states to protect their LGBT communities against discrimination.  There have been good recent developments in Ireland in tackling homophobia and homophobic bullying in schools following initiatives taken by the Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy Ruair&iacute; Quinn, and others.  It would be good if the Oireachtas, too, could make a strong statement condemning this law.</p><p>I welcome the announcement that the Greek broadcaster, ERT, will be back on air following the court ruling that required the government to allow broadcasts to continue.  The NUJ in Ireland has been very supportive of the employees of the public broadcaster and condemned the Greek Government's closure of it.  I welcome the European Broadcasting Union's assistance for ERT employees in continuing to broadcast, even when the official signal was closed down.  we all hope to see a resolution of that issue in a way that will protect the journalists working for ERT.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1147" speakername="John Crown" time="14:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800005#D00200"><p>I have an urgent request for the Leader to bring to the attention of the Minister for Health something that has been bubbling under the radar for several weeks, the uneven access to cancer treatments for patients with private health insurance, depending on which company they are with.  This causes spin-off problems for the public health service because patients who require particular treatment and have been paying a premium all their lives to their insurance companies in the expectation that legally approved treatments available in the public system and with other insurance companies would also be available to them are being denied.  Their doctors, after a process of appeal to the company fails, have to discharge them from the private system and bring them to the public system where the treatment is given at taxpayers' expense.</p><p>I will be specific without mentioning any patients' names.  I have one patient who is battling a serious problem with malignant melanoma.  He has been deemed appropriate for the drug Ipilimumab which will be familiar to many in this House as a result of advocacy here and elsewhere and because of a recent high profile patient who bravely went on air and told the story of how he had received substantial benefit from the treatment.  The insurance company in question is GloHealth and it has informed me that it will not cover its members for treatment with Ipilimumab.  I regret to state that at this point the Garda's insurer, St. Paul's Garda Medical Aid Society, which I have found to have a good scheme and which gave its members great coverage has also been difficult in this regard, whereas VHI, Aviva and others have been paying for it.  One could understand if there had been some failure of approval of this drug.  However, it has been approved for routine use.  It is an extraordinarily exciting drug.  It gives huge benefit, albeit to a small number of patients, but they would otherwise inevitably have a fatal outcome.</p> <p>The Minister for Health, Deputy James Reilly, courageously and correctly at a time of mounting financial pressure on him made the compassionate and humane decision that this treatment would be available to public patients, about which I was delighted.  However, I do not know what pressure he can bring to bear in terms of insurance company approvals, but I will gladly say people have choices.  Anybody opting to take out private health insurance should think long and hard before he or she signs up with GloHealth.  This is the thin edge of the wedge.  If this company is adopting a policy of putting itself outside the mainstream of what is considered acceptable practice, potential customers need to know this because it is very good a pointing to potential putative benefits of joining it.</p><p>I would like to make a bigger point on what is a nice sunny day.  The highest rate of malignant melanoma of any group in the world - I am looking at my fair skinned red haired colleague - is among fair skinned red haired Irish people who move to live in sunny countries.  The highest incidence is among Irish people living in Australia.  God did not design us to live in the sunshine.  We were evolutionarily adapted to live under grey misty skies.  As soon as we started to travel, this tragedy occurred.  The incidence of malignant melanoma in this country between 1998 and 2008 doubled from 400 to 800 cases.  Thankfully, with early diagnosis - the disease has a bad reputation - most people will be cured.  However, the incidence of fatal widespread secondary melanoma has also doubled and as these trends are likely to continue, we need to have access to treatments.  </p><p>I would like to put another thought into the Leader's head to be conveyed to the Minister.  The waiting lists to see dermatologists, both public and private, are unacceptably long owing to an unbelievable shortage of dermatologists.  As a result, patients are presenting late and there is a higher chance they will have an incurable disease when they present.  By saving some money in the short term by not having people appropriately employed, we are saving up a big problem, not only a humanitarian and health problem but also a financial one when these patients come back with more aggressive and more advanced disease.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" speakername="Terry Brennan" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800006#E00200"><p>It was no surprise to me when the First Lady of the United States, Mrs. Michelle Obama, when dining last night with her daughters at Matt the Threshers, a well known restaurant in Dublin, requested Carlingford oysters as her starter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.14" nospeaker="true" time="14:45:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800006#E00400"><p>Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" speakername="Terry Brennan" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800006#E00500"><p>Bearing in mind their worldwide reputation as an aphrodisiac-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800006#E00600"><p>Lir Chocolates are an aphrodisiac.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" speakername="Terry Brennan" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800006#E00700"><p>-----the life improving qualities are enhanced if they are actually consumed in my own medieval town of Carlingford where these oysters have been reared by local fishermen for many years.  I take the opportunity to extend an invitation to the Obama family to come to Carlingford to test the veracity of my statement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800006#E00800"><p>I propose an amendment to the Order of Business that the National Asset Management Agency transparency Bill be taken today in the light of the fact that former employees of NAMA are threatening Members of the House.  Mr. Paul Hennigan was employed by NAMA and went to work for an asset fund in London.  Part of his job-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800006#E00900"><p>It is inappropriate to name people who are not here to defend themselves.  B&iacute; c&uacute;ramach.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800006#E01000"><p>As the person I mentioned was threatening Members of this House, he deserves a little recognition for the fact that he seems to want to silence Members of the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800006#E01100"><p>Two wrongs do not make a right.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800006#E01200"><p>It is inappropriate for any member of the public to try to prevent a Member of this House from doing his or her job, whether in raising issues of concern or a loss to the taxpayer.  I fail to understand how NAMA has not included a clause in its employment contracts that employees who leave to work in other areas are not able to work in areas in which they could utilise sensitive information available to them.  I notice that Senator Paul Coghlan is chomping at the bit.  He keeps telling us that NAMA is as white as the driven snow.  He is clear-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800007#F00200"><p>Senator Paul Coghlan will be well able to make his own contribution.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800007#F00500"><p>His coalition colleague, Senator Higgins, has raised the issue and everybody knows the taxpayer is at a loss in the way NAMA is selling its properties because it is not doing it according to the legislation and in an open and transparent manner.  I support my colleague in calling for a debate on mortgages.  The new code of conduct is coming out tomorrow and it will be a charter to terrorise those who are in arrears.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800007#F00600"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800007#F00700"><p>The 145,000 who are in arrears will not be protected by the previous code of conduct whereby they could be contacted only three times a month.  Now they can be contacted three times an hour.  I ask for a debate on this because I understand the code of conduct is illegal.  I ask the Leader for a debate on the question whether this code of conduct has any basis in law.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800007#F00800"><p>As a matter of clarification, which Bill does the Senator wish to prioritise?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800007#F00900"><p>The NAMA transparency Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800007#F01000"><p>Is that on the Order Paper?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800007#F01100"><p>It is.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" speakername="John Kelly" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800007#F01200"><p>Like Senator Crown, I raise the issue of the private health sector.  I am concerned about what the Senator said because I changed my insurance over to GloHealth this year to save myself some money and it is a major concern for people who are changing insurance providers because they do not read the small print.  I did not read the small print and was unaware of the issue Senator Crown raised.</p><p>I wish raise an issue relating to the insurance company I left.  I was listening to Joe Duffy's radio show yesterday and a man announced that after his wife had had an operation in Beaumont Hospital and spent two nights there, he had received a bill for nearly &euro;17,000 for her two nights' accommodation in the hospital.  The bill for the operation and all the other ancillary services provided came to &euro;1,200.  When his daughter came home from America she thought this was incredible, so she phoned the insurance company in question and said she had a similar problem and needed to get it dealt with and that she did not have private health insurance but was prepared to go private.  She asked how much a bed in the hospital would cost for her and they told her it would be between &euro;700 and &euro;900 per night, as distinct from what her mother paid, which was &euro;8,500 per night.  We need the Minister to come to the House and clarify why insurance companies can have deals with private hospitals which mean the taxpayer pays more for private health insurance because we have to fund this excess and waste in the system.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800007#F01300"><p>Ba mhaith liom ceist a chur ar an gCeannaire, ceist a chur m&eacute; cheana, maidir le d&iacute;osp&oacute;ireacht faoi ch&uacute;rsa&iacute; Leader.  I have asked on a number of occasions if it is possible to have the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government, Deputy Hogan, come to the House to discuss the Leader programme.  There is a group from west Cork outside the gates today because they have certain issues with the way Leader is being administered, the plans for the future and the so-called alignment of the local development companies.  Could the Leader indicate when that debate might happen?</p><p>This time last year we were all invited to a presentation in the audio-visual room from the group that was setting up Student Universal Support Ireland, SUSI.  I have a letter from a constituent who has still not received his grant from SUSI.  He is in an appeals process.  His appeal was submitted 83 days ago, although SUSI's policy states it will deal with appeals within 30 days.  He notes there are advertisements for the process for next year, the academic year 2013-2014, in which SUSI is asking people to make applications.  It is clear that SUSI has been a disaster when it comes to administering these third-level grants.  It might be useful if we could have the Minister for Education and Skills in to talk about that sooner rather than later so we can examine that process.</p><p>While the Minister is in he might also discuss the fact that more than 1,000 retired teachers were back for State exam jobs this year.  The State Examinations Commission hired 1,049 retired teachers to ensure exam halls were adequately staffed this year, despite its stated wish to recruit unemployed and under-employed teachers for superintendent roles.  We had a debate here last week on youth unemployment and it is hard to believe this number of retired teachers are being brought back when we have so many unemployed young teachers out there who need this work and should have been given first preference on such jobs.</p> <p>Perhaps the Minister for Education and Skills might address both issues, SUSI and retired teachers, when he comes to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1114" speakername="Deirdre Clune" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800008#G00200"><p>Last Friday the European Council agreed to start talks with the USA on a transatlantic trade and investment partnership.  It is a positive move which represents a great opportunity for indigenous Irish companies across all sectors to export to the huge US market.  There is a great deal of work to be done on common regulatory standards and investment rules and I wish all those taking part in the talks well and look forward to a fruitful outcome.</p><p>  I ask the Leader to provide for a discussion in the House on the annual report of the Pensions Board which was launched by the Minister for Social Protection, Deputy Joan Burton, this week.  Pensions are a serious issue for many following the financial crisis.  Many who invested in property expecting to make a return to provide for their later years now find that that is not going to happen.  People who invested in bank shares and made other provisions for their retirement have been disappointed.  There is a great deal in the report and it is important that it be aired in the House, in particular to discuss defined benefit schemes.  The report states there is actuarial evidence of a &euro;16 billion hole in defined benefit schemes.  In Cork Permanent TSB workers face problems and the European Court of Justice recently issued a decision in respect of the Waterford Crystal workers.  Workers at the <i>Irish Independent</i> also have issues.  Future pensions provision and the serious difficulties faced by many defined benefit schemes are issues the House should discuss with the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1142" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800008#G00300"><p>It was not possible for me to attend the Order of Business last week and I did not have the opportunity to express my deepest sympathy to Mrs. Bridie Fitzgerald and her family on the death of the late Senator Tom Fitzgerald.  Tom was a particularly close friend of mine and a great adviser to me on the first occasion I stood for election to the Seanad.  I was greatly indebted to him for the help he had given to me.  We gave him a great send off in Dingle and I express my deepest sympathy to his wife and family.</p><p>It is nice to have a bit of good news on a Tuesday morning.  I welcome the announcement at the weekend of the new rejuvenation project for Limerick city.  I understand it will be a public private partnership project aimed at restoring Limerick to its rightful place as the retail centre for the mid-west region.  It has the blessing, naturally, of the Minister for Finance and politicians of every hue and I wish it well.  On the same day Foynes Harbour Board announced 150 jobs at a new energy plant on the docks at Foynes.  As a director of the harbour board for 16 years, I note that this is something to which we have longed looked forward and it is wonderful to see it come to pass.</p><p>Approximately six months ago I had a matter on the Adjournment on the other major project awaited on the Shannon Estuary - the Shannon LNG gas terminal.  The Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources, Deputy Pat Rabbitte, attended to discuss the matter and was extremely positive, as has been his Cabinet colleague, Deputy Jimmy Deenihan.  The Minister, Deputy Pat Rabbitte, indicated that there would be significant developments in the coming months.  I suggest it is now timely for him to attend the House to provide a general outline on the issue of energy security and developments in Ireland, particularly in the mid-west.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Maloney" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800008#G00400"><p>I refer to the horrific tragedy at the weekend in County Kerry involving the double murder of a 27 year old woman, Jolanta Lubiene, and her eight year old daughter, Enrika, and express my sincere sympathy to their family.  As a murder investigation is ongoing, I will not comment further.</p><p>The Educational Research Centre has raised fundamental concerns about the teaching of science and maths in school, particularly at primary level.</p> <p>In primary and secondary schools, teachers express concern that not enough time is allocated to the teaching of these subjects.  Primary teachers also express concern that their curricula are outdated and that, in the area of science, only 7% of Irish students reach the advanced benchmark level for scientific achievement.  Irish primary school teachers feel they are not equipped with the right training and equipment.  I refer to the report that reveals that only 12 hours out of three years training was allocated to the teaching of science in Mary Immaculate College in Limerick.  Ireland comes 22nd in the OECD rankings, which is about average.  When the Minister for Education and Skills is in the Chamber, I would like to raise these issues with him and ask him why the concerns of teachers are not being addressed.  We should prioritise those areas.</p><p>Senator &Oacute; Clochartaigh referred to retired teachers.  During the year I raised this issue at the Joint Committee on Education and Social Protection and we received an assurance it would not happen again, that retired teachers would not be utilised for substitute teaching or supervising exams.  Obviously, the assurance did not hold up.  These are areas of concern and should be discussed in a debate.  I would appreciate if the Leader would put these concerns to the Minister for Education and Skills.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800009#H00200"><p>The Chancellor of the Exchequer in the UK said the issue of corporate taxation has moved more in the past 24 hours than in the previous 24 years.  I draw the attention of the House to an OECD report produced in May on base erosion and profit shifting.  A follow-up volume was produced for Enniskillen, entitled A Step Change in Tax Transparency.  It goes forward to the July meeting of the G20.  The area is moving very fast and it has implications for Ireland.  I ask the Minister for Finance to address the issue of the changing corporate tax base and the wish of international public opinion to deal with the problem of base erosion and profit shifting.  It poses a challenge for Ireland to respond to the situation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1124" speakername="Michael Comiskey" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800009#H00300"><p>I welcome the good news that &euro;30,000 has been allocated to Leitrim County Council to have a look at the old railway line that runs from Sligo through Leitrim and Cavan into Northern Ireland, with the prospect of opening up a greenway.  This would be a great boost for jobs in the area in its construction and in tourism enterprise.  The fact that it runs close to the original Rainbow Ballroom of Romance, which I spoke about on a number of occasions, and close to the original cottage of the late Se&aacute;n Mac Diarmada, one of the seven signatories to the 1916 Proclamation, means it would be great to have it all linked.  It would create an amazing tourism industry across Sligo, Leitrim and Cavan and onto Enniskillen.  It is appropriate that the funding comes now that the G8 meeting is taking place in Enniskillen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800009#H00400"><p>As a three times elected Senator, it is my duty to uphold the principles of democracy in our little country.  The slash and burn approach of the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government, Deputy Phil Hogan, to abolishing town councils all over Ireland disempowers Irish citizens and centralises power in the hands of unelected local authority officials.  Town councils, each with a sense of identity, are drivers of economic growth, of enterprise development and of the many festivals and events they organise in towns.  Many of these are based on the local produce of the area, such as the prawn festival in Howth, which is in the electoral area of Councillor Eoghan O'Brien.  These local government cuts not only decrease the political representation of our citizens but also the voice of our citizens at national level.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800009#H00500"><p>Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800009#H00600"><p>I wish to ask the Leader if he will invite the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government, Deputy Phil Hogan to the House.  I would like to have it out with the Minister about this cut to the democratic deficit.</p> <p>How dare he cut the democratic deficit in our little country.  Fianna F&aacute;il is opposed to this attack on local democracy and it is important to remember that the 500 democratically elected town councillors will lose their jobs.  The Minister is putting people out of their jobs.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800010#J00200"><p>I was not present last Thursday because EMC announced the creation of an additional 200 jobs in Cork.  This brings to more than 2,000 the number of employees the company has in Cork.  I pay tribute to the company and to its chief executive officer, Mr. Bob Savage, who is also the chairman of the board of Cork Institute of Technology.  I refer to the changes he has brought about since taking over as chairman and the need for the connection between industry and our educational institutions.  On Sunday, it was reported that there were more than 4,900 vacancies in the IT sector because we do not have sufficient people with the necessary skills in a number of areas, especially in the context of languages.  It is important that the connection between industry and our educational institutions continues to be developed.</p><p>The cost of HSE agency staff was published earlier.  A total of &euro;176 million was spent in 2012.  The cost of agency nurses increased from &euro;105 million to &euro;123 million while the fees paid for nurses on call increased from &euro;27.7 million to &euro;43.1 million in one year.  This emphasises the importance of the Haddington Road Agreement.  If it is adopted by all the unions - and hopefully it will be - there will be an opportunity to employ an additional 1,000 nurses in the health service.  That is important to assist in the reduction of the expenditure on agency staff.  Will the Leader schedule a debate on public sector reforms over the past two years if not during this session, early in the next session, to establish what reforms have taken place to date and what needs to be done in the next two years to make sure issues such as this do not continue to arise?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800010#J00300"><p>I refer to a comment by Senator Paul Bradford regarding the proposed abortion legislation, the Protection of Life During Pregnancy Bill 2013.  He said that he did not think that hiding under a Whip was the correct way for Oireachtas Members to approach such a contentious Bill.  He is quite right and I ask the Leader whether we should have a debate on the operation of the Whip and the possibility of a free vote on an unprecedented life and death issue such as this.  In other jurisdictions, conscience issues of such moment are the subject of a free vote.</p><p>I prefer that the Fine Gael Party keeps its election promise and one could argue against a Whip on the basis that everybody signed up to a particular promise but it is infinitely preferable to breaking that promise and legislating for abortion to allow people at least the freedom of their consciences.  Many Deputies and Senators are deeply troubled by this legislation.  I do not have to remind colleagues either that this House is under scrutiny these days and it is important that we show our distinctiveness and that we take issues perhaps more seriously on occasions than the other House.  More important - and another reason - are the extremely disturbing comments made by the Minister for Health on Sunday when he admitted that the Bill would probably result in more babies being delivered having suffered damage because of their premature delivery.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800010#J00400"><p>The Senator should quote the Minister properly if he going to do so at all.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800010#J00500"><p>That is not what the Minister said.  The Senator should not misquote him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800010#J00600"><p>It is absolutely Orwellian and dystopian.  I am misquoting the news report.  The Minister said he accepted that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800010#J00700"><p>I insist that the Senator does not misquote the Minister, especially on something as profound as this.  I also insist that he puts it in the context of the conversation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800010#J00800"><p>I have never misquoted anybody in this House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800011#K00100"><p>In the context of the conversation-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800011#K00200"><p>Senator Mullen's time is up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800011#K00300"><p>The Minister did accept that this legislation would see this terrible scenario.  He tried to justify it on the grounds that the only alternative would be to force pregnancies to continue but we are not here talking about necessary medical treatments where a physical illness requires an intervention; we are effectively talking about abortion on request.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800011#K00400"><p>We are not.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800011#K00500"><p>There is no medical evidence to back up-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800011#K00600"><p>We are not having the debate today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800011#K00700"><p>That is what it amounts to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800011#K00800"><p>There is a full month ahead for that debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800011#K00900"><p>He is not only misquoting the Minister but he is also justifying the facts that suit himself.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800011#K01000"><p>On a point of order, the Senator insists on misrepresenting both the nature of the legislation and the Minister&rsquo;s comments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800011#K01100"><p>We are not having a debate on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800011#K01200"><p>This is the type of denial we have been getting from-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800011#K01300"><p>The Senator is in denial.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800011#K01400"><p>-----in recent weeks and months.  That is what really has people frightened.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800011#K01500"><p>Senator Mullen&rsquo;s commentary is the type of misrepresentation that we have had to listen to over the past three to five weeks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800011#K01600"><p>The Senator's time is up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800011#K01700"><p>I will happily compare notes with people of goodwill on any side of the House on this issue, but I will not be fooled by the head honchos on the Government side who want to swear that black is white, and to avoid frightening the-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800011#K01800"><p>How does the Senator interpret goodwill?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800011#K01900"><p>Given that there are people deeply troubled on both sides, I believe what has happened here is a clear indication that we ought to have a debate on the possibility of a free vote.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800011#K02000"><p>It is a clear indication of the Senator's misrepresentation of the facts and his own justification to suit his own facts.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800011#K02100"><p>I support Senator Crown on the issue of private health insurance.  I work for many insurance companies in my other job.  Their practice is generally to avoid paying when they can; that is just how they operate.  People should be warned that they should read the small print.  I agree with Senator Kelly in that even those of us who should know better do not always read the small print.  In many instances, people find out about problems with their health insurance cover when they are most unwell and in a very vulnerable state.  This issue should be debated, not least because of the serious rise in the cost of health insurance, irrespective of the company one is with.  We could very usefully debate this in the House in the very near future.</p><p>Let me raise an issue brought to my attention by a councillor in Dungarvan, of which issue I have no doubt the Leader will be aware.  There has been an increase in rates of between 30% and 100% for many of the businesses in the town.  One business saw an increase of 1,100%.  Can one imagine this?  The increases are devastating for the retail sector, especially in a small provincial town.  I am concerned about a precedent being set for other small towns.  We should invite the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government to the House to discuss this in the very near future.  The rates increases are stifling small towns.</p><p>I was surprised but highly irritated when I read the newspapers on Sunday to see that supermarkets are still peddling below-cost beer aggressively.  Incredibly, beer in Tesco was cheaper than water and other soft drinks during promotions that were advertised in many Sunday newspapers last weekend.  I am often slagged for being a killjoy in this area but it should be noted I enjoy a drink as much as the next person.  However, what is occurring is clearly wrong in every sense.  How on earth can beer cost less than water or fruit juice?  What sort of message is this sending out?  Retailers are selling beer for just 65 cent per bottle while bottles of water are retailing at 90 cent.  This highlights the need to stop the below-cost selling of alcohol with immediate effect.  I do not know what is happening with the alcohol strategy but understand issues arise over the advertising aspect.  We have heard much debate in recent surveys that has centred on alcohol sponsorship.  A far simpler, quicker and more effective way of reducing dangerous and excessive consumption of alcohol by young people, and people at home in a less controlled environment, is to end the below-cost selling of alcohol.  The Minister of State at the Department of Health, Deputy Alex White, should be invited to the House to discuss this ever-worsening and very serious problem.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" speakername="Susan O'Keeffe" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800011#K02200"><p>As I am sure others have done, I welcome the First Lady of the United States and her family to Ireland.  I hope they have enjoyed their brief stay.  They have done the country a service by raising its profile and drawing attention to our tourism product.  I thank the US President, Mr. Obama, for having had the foresight to quote William Butler Yeats while he was here and for never missing an opportunity.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800011#K02300"><p>He quoted incorrectly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" speakername="Susan O'Keeffe" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800012#L00100"><p>It was not incorrect. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800012#L00200"><p>It was in the wrong context.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" speakername="Susan O'Keeffe" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800012#L00300"><p>We will forgive him.  Even I will forgive him.  </p><p>Following a very successful Yeats day in Sligo last Thursday, I thank Senators for their good wishes.  In advance of the visit of Prime Minister Abe of Japan to Dublin tomorrow and to cement the links between Ireland and Japan which promise enormous economic, tourism and cultural benefits, I thank Ambassador John Neary who will host a Yeats' day event in Tokyo on Saturday for a wide group of people.  I will have the pleasure of speaking at the symposium with the ambassador.  Cultural and international links are being built.   I ask that at some point we have a discussion on whether we can invite other people to come to Ireland.  We can ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Leo Varadkar, to invite others to come to Ireland to enjoy a variety of activities.  We are very good at inviting journalists from other countries to come to Ireland and write articles in their newspapers.  Perhaps we might short-list four or five interesting people from across the world to come to Ireland to enjoy our company, beautiful sites, culture and so on.  There have been calls for another debate on that issue.  I, again, thank Members for their good wishes.  We had a great day and celebrated Yeats in style.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800012#L00400"><p>I, too, welcome the fact that a very positive image of the island, North and South, has been projected around the world in the past few days.  I hope it will result in many more visitors coming to the country and partaking of the Carlingford oysters to which Senator Terry Brennan referred. </p><p>I hope positive progress is being made at the G8 summit on the conflict in Syria.  I support Senator Darragh O'Brien's call for the T&aacute;naiste to give us an update on progress.  We all want to see a peaceful resolution as a matter of urgency of the appalling conflict in which so many people have lost their lives and millions have been displaced.  I hope the other leaders are able to persuade Prime Minister Putin to change his stance, urge a peaceful resolution and get everybody around a peace conference table as a matter of urgency.  It would be very appropriate for significant progress to be made on the island of Ireland in that regard. </p><p>Reference was made to health insurance costs.  Everybody agrees that the system needs a root and branch review and is highly dysfunctional.  Taxpayers are being fleeced on an annual basis.  We have heard of the possibility of a 30% increase in insurance costs.  The figures mentioned by Senator John Kelly are alarming.  Somebody who paid health insurance was charged &euro;8,500 a night for accommodation, but if he or she had paid cash, the cost would have been between &euro;900 and &euro;1,200.  There is something appallingly wrong with this.  I heard a story yesterday - it may have been the same programme to which Senator John had Kelly listened - where a consultant arrived at a person's bedside to tell her that, unfortunately, he was so busy that he would not be able to see her until the following day.  The woman was charged for two visits to her bedside by the consultant.  There is something wrong with such a system.  Once upon a time if a person went to a garage to have repairs carried out to his or her car, he or she would have been asked whether it was an insurance job or whether he or she was paying cash.  We are now seeing the same in the case of health insurance.  I welcome the comments of the Minister on &quot;The Week in Politics&quot;.  We would welcome an opportunity to have an open and frank debate with him on health insurance costs and how the structure can be reformed to give value to the taxpayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800012#L00500"><p>I refer to Senator Mark Daly's ongoing fatwa against NAMA.  He has not hit the target once.</p> <p>In fact, he has not substantiated a single charge.  In regard to the proposal he has made today, I can only urge the Senator to bring it on.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800013#M00200"><p>As I am loth to referee a Kerry battle, I ask Senator Coghlan to make his point as quickly as possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800013#M00300"><p>Senator Coghlan is well aware that 500 acres were sold in Cork city and nobody in the area was aware it was for sale.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800013#M00400"><p>Senator Coghlan, without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800013#M00500"><p>Senator Daly has never been specific when it was put up to him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800013#M00600"><p>All the information is in the newspapers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800013#M00700"><p>He needs to put up or shut up.  He made a very serious charge today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800013#M00800"><p>It is in the newspapers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800013#M00900"><p>Senator Daly must allow Senator Coghlan to speak.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800013#M01000"><p>One cannot believe everything one reads in the newspapers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800013#M01100"><p>Senator Coghlan's parliamentary colleague has made him aware of the problems with NAMA but he refuses to listen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800013#M01200"><p>I did not interrupt Senator Daly when he was speaking.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800013#M01300"><p>I ask Senator Daly to resume his seat.  It is unfair to interrupt another speaker in this way.  I advise Senator Coghlan that it might be prudent not to draw Senator Daly on any further.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800013#M01400"><p>The Senator made a very serious charge today of illegality.  I am not aware of NAMA doing anything  illegal.  In fact, the recent reports shows how well it has performed thus far on behalf of the taxpayer.  That performance has been commented on favourably by the Minister for Finance and others in authority in this country.  I am interested to see what rabbit the Senator might pull from the hat this time.  I hope he will at least be more specific.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800013#M01500"><p>Senator Coghlan can read about these matters every week in the newspapers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800013#M01600"><p>I am not concerned with what might be written in the newspapers.  Senator Daly has filled a lot of space before, but there was nothing to it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800013#M01700"><p>In regard to the particular matter I have raised, I will supply the Senator with all the information he wants, including on Portman Square in London, which proves that the taxpayer is at a loss.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800013#M01800"><p>Senator Daly cannot interject in this willy nilly fashion on the Order of Business.  To clarify, in regard to the Senator's proposed amendment to the Order of Business, the Bill to which he referred was defeated on Second Stage on 6 June 2012 and, accordingly, is no longer on the Seanad Order Paper.  The Senator cannot, therefore, move an amendment to discuss the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800013#M01900"><p>A new survey by Am&aacute;rach Research shows that more than 80% of Irish people, or eight out of ten, believe that parliamentarians should have the right to a free vote on conscience grounds on the proposed abortion legislation.  It is an issue that is exercising many people at this time.  Young people in particular are shocked that parliamentarians are not entitled to a free vote on this fundamental issue of morality and life.</p><p>  Will the Leader ask the Taoiseach to come to the House for a debate on the right to conscientious objection on moral issues?  This should be par for the course in a democracy and within political parties.  Indeed it is a mark of a mature democracy.  The Whip system is preventing that from happening and is impeding critical thinking on reasoned and informed conscience grounds.  The Whip system is a very dangerous weapon when it is used to whip people's thinking into line on serious conscience issues to do with life and death.  After all, what is a democracy without freedom of conscience?  We are appointed to the Oireachtas, either by direct or indirect elections, yet when it comes to serious moral issues such as this we are told to leave our brains outside the door.  The Irish people do not want us to do so.  They have spoken in this research and eight out of ten of them support the right to conscientious objection.  I ask for a considered debate on this issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800013#M02000"><p>On a point of order, will Senator Healy Eames indicate how many people were surveyed for this research?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800013#M02100"><p>That is not a point of order; it is a point of provocation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800013#M02200"><p>There have been several welcome announcements in regard to healthy living initiatives in Clare in recent days, relating to the construction of walkways, cycleways and greenways.  The coastal walkway connecting Liscannor and Doolin, for example, was officially opened last Friday.  It follows the opening of a beautiful cycle lane between Ennistymon and Lahinch.</p> <p>Today it was finally announced that we will see research, development, planning and design for the old West Clare Railway, which will eventually connect Ennis to Lahinch via Corofin.  Essentially, this will be a greenway that connects Ennis to the Burren through cycleways and coastal walkways.   All of this is very healthy and good for tourism and economic development.  It presents a package that will be very attractive internationally to people who want to come on healthy holidays to Ireland.  There is a huge market for healthy holidays throughout the world and we can capture some of that and capitalise on it.</p><p>I want to bring to the attention of the Leader an unfortunate position with regard to the coastal walk.  Clare County Council had the contract for this walk, but some of the subcontractors have not been paid.  There is great merit in the allocation of public contracts in such a way that the local authorities or public bodies in question can retain a certain percentage of the funds to cover the cost of subcontractors that have not been paid.  The news of the proposed works is positive, but unfortunately some people with families are still waiting for payment for works carried out on behalf of taxpayers.  The taxpayers have paid, but the subcontractors are still waiting to be paid.  This is a regrettable situation.  We need to see an alteration to the e-tender documentation system to ensure we have some sort of protection for poor unfortunate subcontractors who are trying to make a living.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800014#N00200"><p>Senators O'Brien, Bacik and Mullins called for a debate on Syria.  I will ask the T&aacute;naiste to come to the House to update us on the current negotiations and Ireland's stance on that country.  Senator O'Brien also called for a debate on the new code of conduct on mortgage arrears, which will be issued today.  We will have the Central Bank (Supervision and Enforcement) Bill in the House this week and there may be an opportunity to discuss that matter with the Minister during the debate on that Bill.  However, if further debate is required, I will try to arrange for the Minister to come to the House again to discuss the new code of conduct.  With regard to the Senator's question on the greater Dublin drainage scheme, I understand the matter was addressed in an Adjournment matter here last week by the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government, Deputy Hogan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800014#N00300"><p>He washed his hands of it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800014#N00400"><p>I will certainly raise with the Minister the question Senator O'Brien asked about the statement made by Deputy Howlin in this House in 2011.</p><p>Senator Bacik also called for a debate on homophobia, in light of the Bill being taken in the Russian Parliament.  We have had a number of debates in this House on that issue.  The Bill mentioned is very disturbing, but we have had a number of debates on the matter.</p><p>Senator Crown and others raised the issue of uneven access to cancer services and the difficulties with some insurance companies with regard to payments and the prescription of drugs.  This is a cause for concern and the Senator is quite right to point out that some insurance companies are unwilling to cover the drug in question.  I suggest the matter can be discussed when we have a debate this week on the Health (Amendment) Bill with the Minister.  I compliment the Minister on his participation in our excellent debate on hospital services last week.  The Minister spend some considerable time with us discussing the hospital service groupings and a number of other issues raised by Senators during that debate.  I urge Senator Crown to raise the issue with the Minister.</p> <p> I advise Senator Michael Mullins and other Senators who raised the issues of hospital charges and payments, appointments and private health insurance to raise them during the Second Stage debate on the Health (Amendment) Bill 2013 later today.  </p><p>Senator Terry Brennan lauded the benefits of Carlingford oysters.  I have nothing further to add to his comments on the subject.  </p><p>Senator Mark Daly asked when the National Assets Management Agency transparency Bill would be dealt with in the House.  I am surprised that he did not know that Bill was dealt with and voted on last year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800015#O00200"><p>It was voted down.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800015#O00500"><p>It says little for the Senator's research in that regard.  On the matter on which he called for a debate, the Minister for Finance dealt comprehensively with it in the debate on the Adjournment matter tabled by Senator Lorraine Higgins last week or the week before.</p><p>On the matters raised by Senator John Kelly, I refer him to my earlier reply to Senator John Crown, namely, that private health insurance issues should be addressed during the Second Stage debate on the Health (Amendment) Bill 2013.  I hope the Senator and others who have raised the issue will contribute to that debate later today.  I look forward to hearing their contributions.</p><p>Senator Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh referred to SUSI and the appeals system.  I agree that there have been difficulties in this area and that given all student grant applications have now been processed, appeals should at this stage be being dealt with in less than 30 days.  There should be no further delays in that regard.  I also agree with the Senator that unemployed teachers should be given first preference in filling supervisory posts for examinations.  I will ask the Minister for Education and Skills to come to the House to address these issues.</p><p>Senator Deirdre Clune spoke about the agreement to commence the EU-US trade talks, an important issue that is being driven by the Irish Presidency.  One of the aims of the Irish Presidency was to get the talks going.  Senator Sean D. Barrett has referred on a number of occasions in the House to the benefits that will accrue to Ireland and Europe should agreement be reached.  </p><p>Senator Deirdre Clune also referred to the Pensions Board report.  I will raise with the Minister for Social Protection the possibility of her coming to the House for a debate on the subject.</p><p>Senator Ned O'Sullivan lauded job creation at Foynes, which is to be welcomed.  I will make inquiries about the LNG terminal and the prospect of further jobs being created in that regard.  I understand the Minister is addressing a major European conference on oil and gas exploration today.  I will request that he to come to the House to update us on the matter.  Alternatively, the Senator can table the matter for discussion on the Adjournment.</p><p>I join Senator Marie Moloney in expressing the sympathy of the House following the brutal murder of a mother and her daughter in County Kerry on a recent date.  It was a dreadful tragedy.  </p><p>On teacher training and the teaching of science, the Senator hit the nail on the head.  The Minister for Education and Skills will be in the House on Thursday to deal with the Further Education and Training Bill 2013, at which time the Senator can reiterate the points made by her this afternoon.</p><p>Senator Sean D. Barrett spoke about the reports on the issues of tax transparency and base erosion.</p> <p>Again, we will try to get the Minister for Finance into the House to debate this issue.  It is an issue which Senator Barrett has raised before and we have had other Ministers to the House to discuss it.  I am sure the Minister will be quite willing to debate the matter again.</p><p>Senator Comiskey asked about the feasibility study for the opening of the old Leitrim railway line while Senator Conway inquired about the re-opening of the old west Clare railway.  Should these go ahead, they would be of tremendous benefit to tourism in the areas.  We are overdue a debate on tourism in the House.  The Minister has indicated he is willing to come to the House for such a debate, as soon as he has a spot in his diary.</p><p>Senator White raised the abolition of town councils.  This matter will be dealt with when the relevant legislation is brought to the House.</p><p>Senator Burke praised the creation of 200 extra jobs in Cork by EMC and outlined the need for connections between industry and education facilities.  The director of innovation in Enterprise Ireland recently addressed this matter when he raised the question of linkage between Waterford Institute of Technology and local industries with graduates setting up spin-off companies as well.  I concur with Senator Burke that there is a need for a greater connection between industry and educational facilities, particularly institutes of technology.</p><p>Senator Burke also pointed out that &euro;176 million has been spent on agency staff in the health service and the importance of the Haddington Road agreement in that context.</p><p>Regarding Senator Mullen&rsquo;s concerns about the Protection of Life during Pregnancy Bill, I have outlined on several occasions that we will have ample time to debate the Bill in this House.  I understand it will be introduced here in early July.  I am sure we will have a reasonable and dignified debate on this matter at the time.</p><p>Senator Noone raised the importance of reading the small print when it comes to private health insurance.  Again, this matter can be addressed when we are debating the Health (Amendment) Bill 2013.</p><p>Local authority rate valuations caused consternation for small retailers in Waterford city and county when the new rates came out.  It is of paramount importance that retailers have an opportunity to appeal a valuation.  There are quite a number of information meetings going on in Waterford this week on the subject.  It has caused shock to a number of small retailers, in particular.  Second Stage of the Valuation Bill was taken in the House some months ago but Committee Stage will not be taken until after the summer recess.</p><p>I agree with Senator Noone on the below-cost selling of alcohol.  The Minister of State at the Department of Health, Deputy Alex White, has promised to discuss the alcohol strategy in the House after it is launched in the coming weeks.</p><p>Senator O&rsquo;Keeffe welcomed the US First Lady, Ms Obama, and the US President, Mr. Obama, to the country.  Of course, she never misses the opportunity of mentioning former Senator, William Butler Yeats, by raising Yeats Day last week.  I noted her points about its links with Japan.  Cultural tourism is very important for the country also.</p> <p> Senator Mullins joined Senator Darragh O'Brien in calling for a debate on Syria.  I also note the points he made about the difficulties with private insurance.</p><p>I think Senator Paul Coghlan clarified the situation regarding NAMA.  I will not comment further on it as it would be inadvisable for me to get involved in an argument between Senator Coghlan and his colleague from County Kerry.</p><p>I believe the matter of a free vote, which was raised by Senator Healy Eames, will be discussed at her party's parliamentary party meeting tomorrow.  She will have ample time to discuss it at that forum.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800017#Q00150"><p>She is queuing up already.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800017#Q00175"><p>Senator Conway spoke about the development of the old West Clare Railway.  He also mentioned that some subcontractors are not being paid.  I understand the Construction Contracts Bill 2010, which was initiated by Senator Quinn, is currently going through the other House.  It was delayed for quite some time after it was passed by this House.  I assure Senator Conway that it will come back to this House as soon as possible after it has been passed by the D&aacute;il.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.113" nospeaker="true" time="15:55:00" ><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.114" nospeaker="true" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800017#Q00300">New Cork Prison: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800017#Q00400"><p>I move:<blockquote><br />That Seanad &Eacute;ireann:noting:<br />-- that the Minister for Justice and Equality, having considered the need for a new prison in the Cork area, has decided to proceed with the development of a prison on a portion of the site used as Cork Prison, in the townland of Rathmore and city of Cork;<br />-- that the Minister for Justice and Equality has caused the documents specified in section 26(2) of the Prisons Act 2007 (No. 10 of 2007) relating to the development of a prison to be laid before each House of the Oireachtas together with a document containing the observations of that Minister on the environmental impact assessment and the report of the rapporteur;<br />-- that the proposed development relates to the construction of a prison:<blockquote>(<i>a</i>) located on a portion of the site used as Cork Prison, in the townland of Rathmore and city of Cork;<br />(<i>b</i>) for the purpose of accommodating approximately 300 prisoners;<br />(<i>c</i>) which shall consist of buildings of a floor area of approximately 15,000 square metres within a site of approximately 2.64 hectares;<br />(<i>d</i>) the secure facilities within which shall be bounded by a perimeter wall approximately 7.2 metres in height; and<br />(<i>e</i>) which shall consist of buildings with a height of one, two and three storeys;</blockquote>-- that the following alteration having been made by the Minister for Justice and Equality to the development in accordance with section 25 of the Prisons Act 2007 (No. 10 of 2007) in order to mitigate its visual impact:<blockquote>--the reduction of the height of the perimeter wall forming the eastern, western and northern boundaries of the horticultural area at the northern end of the site to approximately 5.2 metres;</blockquote>-- that an environmental impact assessment was prepared with respect to the proposed development;<br />-- that the Minister for Justice and Equality invited submissions or observations relating to the development of the prison from members of the public:<blockquote>(<i>a</i>) by means of advertisements placed:<blockquote>(i) in the following national publication on 8th November, 2012: <i>The Irish Examiner</i>; and<br />(ii) in the following local publication on 8th November, 2012: <i>The Evening Echo</i>;</blockquote>(<i>b</i>) by the erection of site notices at two locations on the perimeter of the site; and<br />(<i>c</i>) by causing an announcement of the proposed development to be published:<blockquote>(i) on the website of the Irish Prison Service; and<br />(ii) on the website of the Department of Justice and Equality;</blockquote></blockquote>-- that the proposed development will not have any significant effect on any European Site, within the meaning of the European Communities (Birds and Natural Habitats) Regulations 2011 (S.I. No. 477 of 2011);<br />-- that the main measures taken to avoid, reduce or offset any possible significant adverse effects of the development on the environment are:<blockquote>(<i>a</i>) the use of visually conditioned concrete with a light-coloured finish on the sections of the perimeter wall most visible to the public;<br />(<i>b</i>) the implementation of a traffic management plan as part of the Construction Environmental Management Plan;<br />(<i>c</i>) the mitigation of light impact by the use of low-level lighting and lighting cowls and the directing of all security lighting, other than the lighting in the area between the perimeter wall and the outer fence, inwards and away from residential property in the area of the prison boundary;<br />(<i>d</i>) the application of Sustainable Urban Drainage Design System principles to the site with the aim of ensuring that the surface water run-off rate shall not exceed existing site greenfield rates;<br />(<i>e</i>) restrictions on the CCTV system to ensure that it is not used in manner that facilitates viewing into neighbouring residential property;<br />(<i>f</i>) the use of obscured glazing in all windows overlooking neighbouring residential property;<br />(<i>g</i>) the mitigation of noise and dust by the construction of the perimeter wall before commencement of the construction of the prison buildings; and<br />(<i>h</i>) appropriate landscaping of the entrance and car park areas;</blockquote>-- that a visual representation of the exterior of the completed development appears at the end of this resolution;<br />-- that the conditions relating to the construction of the new prison to be complied with by the principal building contractor or developer engaged by the Minister are:<blockquote>(<i>a</i>) that the development shall not vary in any material way from that outlined in the environmental impact assessment and the visual representations of the exterior of the completed development as laid before the Houses of the Oireachtas;<br />(<i>b</i>) that the construction schedule shall give priority to the construction of the perimeter wall in order to minimise the impact of construction within that perimeter on persons residing in the local community;<br />(<i>c</i>) that construction shall not commence until a Construction Environmental Management Plan has been drawn up by the principal contractor and approved by the Irish Prison Service and implemented in keeping with best practice and in particular the construction phase mitigation and other measures specified in sections 3.2, 3.4, 3.5, 3.6, 3.7, 3.8 and 3.11 of the environmental impact assessment shall be adhered to by the body or bodies contractually responsible for the construction of the development including any subcontractors;<br />(<i>d</i>) that normal construction and excavation work shall only take place between 08.00 hours and 19.00 hours Monday to Friday and between 08.30 hours and 16.30 hours on Saturdays, with no such work taking place on Sundays or public holidays;<br />(<i>e</i>) that an extensive programme of vermin eradication on the site and its environs shall be undertaken in the weeks immediately before the commencement of the works; and<br />(<i>f</i>) that appropriate noise, vibration and dust monitoring shall be undertaken throughout the construction period;</blockquote>and<br />resolves to approve the development of the said prison in the townland of Rathmore and city of Cork.</blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.116" nospeaker="true" time="15:55:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800017#Q00700"><p>May I take this opportunity to welcome Councillor Donnchadh O'Seaghdha, who has come all the way from Skibbereen, to the Gallery?</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.118" nospeaker="true" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800017#Q00800">Housing (Amendment) Bill 2013: Second Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.119" nospeaker="true" time="15:55:00" ><p>Question proposed: &quot;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&quot;</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1142" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800017#Q00950"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Jan O'Sullivan, to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800017#Q01000"><p>The Housing (Amendment) Bill 2013 makes technical changes to section 31 of the Housing (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act 2009 relating to the charging of local authority rents, which is an important element in the social housing framework.  The Bill is necessary because the Parliamentary Counsel has advised that text in section 31(5) of the 2009 Act precludes the enactment from being commenced in a sequence that ensures a clear statutory basis for housing authorities to charge rents for their dwellings during the transition from the existing rents regime to the new rents system.  To rectify this problem, the Parliamentary Counsel has advised that section 31(5) should be amended so the enactment can be brought into operation in a manner that enables enabling housing authorities to make their new rent schemes under section 31(5) before their rent-charging powers under section 31(3) come into operation.</p><p>I am also taking the opportunity presented by this amending Bill to delete text from section 31(6) that conflicts with a rent system in which charges are determined by reference to household composition and income and, where applicable, the cost of facilities provided to dwellings.  I am fully in favour of local authority rents being linked to household income.  Therefore, I am proposing to delete from the enactment references to specific rent-setting criteria other than income.  Responsibility for setting local authority rents under section 58 of the Housing Act 1966 has been devolved to individual city and county managers since 1986.  While all housing authorities charge rents related to the income of tenant households, similar households in similar accommodation are charged varying amounts of differential rent, depending on which local authority is letting the accommodation.  Individual authorities also differ on issues like the types and amounts of income that are reckonable for differential rent purposes.</p> <p>There is no justification for this disparate approach to rent setting for accommodation that is funded wholly by the Exchequer.  Section 31 of the 2009 Act, therefore, facilitates a significant harmonisation in rents charged, while retaining the principle of rents related to household income and leaving some discretion to individual authorities to determine rent policies in their areas.  The new system will be more equitable and transparent, with regulations providing for rents made up of a base element for each household member and a differential element based on a proportion of net household income in excess of a threshold that varies according to household composition.  The regulations will set out a common method for determining household income across the country for rent purposes and provide for a transitional period so as to allow for a phased introduction of material adjustments to rent levels arising in individual cases under the new system.</p><p>Under section 31 of the 2009 Act, individual housing authorities are also empowered in their rent schemes to include charges in the rent relating to the costs of works and services provided to the dwellings under the Housing Acts, and regulations will set out the manner in which charges will be determined.  Another feature of the new rents system is that, for the first time, council members will have a statutory role in determining local rent policies within the parameters laid down at national level.  This aspect of the new arrangements received widespread support from Deputies during the D&aacute;il debates on the Bill.</p><p>The new rent schemes that housing authorities will make under section 31 of the 2009 Act will apply to beneficiaries under the new housing assistance payment, HAP, scheme to be administered by housing authorities, which will replace rent supplement in the case of households with a long-term housing need.  The household contribution to the rent payable for HAP dwellings will be determined under the new rents system for local authority housing.  An immediate spin-off of this will be the removal of a barrier to employment that currently exists in the rent supplement scheme, whereby a rent supplement recipient who returns to full-time employment loses entitlement to that payment.  Thus, the new HAP scheme, allied to section 31 rent schemes, will go some way towards providing additional security to households in the early stages of returning to employment.</p><p>Proposed legislation for the housing assistance payment scheme will be included in a second housing Bill that I hope to bring forward later this year.  Also included in that Bill will be a new procedure for the repossession of local authority dwellings to replace section 62 of the Housing Act 1966, which the Supreme Court declared in February 2012 is incompatible with the European Convention on Human Rights in certain circumstances.  The proposed Bill will also underpin current requirements in regard to the entitlement of non-Irish nationals to be assessed by local authorities for social housing support.  I am also planning to legislate for a new tenant purchase scheme for existing local authority houses along incremental lines.  I will be working to bring the substantive housing Bill to enactment as quickly as possible in order to maintain the momentum on the programme of social housing reform currently under way.</p><p>To return to the Housing (Amendment) Bill 2013, I look forward to the support of the House for what is a short, technical enactment required to facilitate the effective operation of existing legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Ca&iacute;t Keane" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800018#R00200"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it.  The Bill amends section 31(5) of the Housing (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act 2009 and I will not go through the technical detail of the amendments and deletions it makes as the Minister of State has already done so.  I welcome this legislation, the primary objective of which is to achieve a level of harmonisation of local authority rents at national level in order to prevent huge variations from one area to another.</p><p>It is important to stress this will not preclude the determination or the drawing up of a rental scheme by local authorities in their own areas.  We are always talking about the devolution of functions.  It is very important that functions which are devolved to local authorities are left there and, indeed, we look forward to further devolution of functions to local authorities.  It is critical that any assessment of local authority rent charged to an individual takes account of his or her ability to pay.  This is what differentiates social housing from private housing and that objective is central to the new legislation.  There will be a differential rent scheme to the extent that a person's ability to pay will be the key determinant and the Bill will seek to ensure there will not be a huge variation in rents from county to county.</p><p>It is important that this would happen. Many initiatives have been introduced by the Minister of State's colleague in the Department of Social Protection, particularly with regard to the job activation scheme, which fits job training opportunities and individuals, and focuses on the individual as a recipient of welfare and as an active jobseeker.</p> <p>I am glad the Minister of State mentioned rent supplement and the part that will play.  That must be the philosophy.  Everyone presenting for a rent subsidy should also be assessed individually and, if appropriate accommodation is available within the local authority housing programme, an offer should be made.  Rent supplement should be a secondary response where there is no possibility of the provision of accommodation from the local authority.</p><p>The Minister of State mentioned the housing assistance payment scheme, about which we have not heard enough.  Perhaps she would elaborate further on it.  Ten minutes before I came to the House, I was contacted by somebody who wanted to take up a part-time job, but because she was in receipt of rent supplement it was not worth her while taking up that job because she would lose a certain amount.  This girl was really willing to take up that part-time job.  I welcome the announcement about the housing assistance payment scheme and would welcome more information on it from the Minister of State.</p><p>In addition to the financial side of owning a house, we must consider the need for people to settle down.  It is better for people if they are living in, getting to know and being part of their communities rather than moving from one rental scheme to another.  The Minister of State has said on occasion that having people look upon their communities as their own and work in those communities is part of her philosophy.  In respect of the rent allowance scheme, where children are going to school and established in a social infrastructure, it is unreasonable to uproot them and take them from one town to another just because a local authority house is available in that area.  I know the Minister of State's philosophy on that, and she has spoken on many occasions about social cohesion.</p><p>I commend the RAS as it is a very good case of direct local authority provision.  Integration of the RAS, the housing assistance scheme, the rent supplement scheme and housing policy generally is necessary and the Bill will achieve that aim.  It is reforming legislation.  We must recognise that the rental accommodation market has increased radically.  The number of people renting in Ireland in both the private and local authority sectors has increased by 47% since 2006.  To an extent, we are becoming more like the continental Europeans and house ownership as a first option is fading, maybe out of necessity in many instances.  We have to accommodate this new reality.   Past legislation has given rise to tenants' rights that did not exist in the past and that makes tenants more secure in rented accommodation.  The Government's response in that area is integrated.</p><p>With the RAS and long-term leases, local authority tenants do not have the prospect of purchasing their houses.  This is critical because it means they do not have the responsibility of looking after them and becoming part of the community.  If we want to develop more responsible citizens in communities, home ownership is important in the community building process.  I do not know if the Minister of State has carried out an evaluation of the period when local authorities used to sell properties to tenants to ensure they bedded down in a community rather than moved on and out of the community, or an examination of whether they could be allowed to purchase their homes again.  I accept that financial pressures are significant and nearly every debate in the House is premised on that.  I know the Minister of State with responsibility for the NewERA project, Deputy O'Dowd, said on Second Stage in the other House that in ideal circumstances there would be a notable ongoing programme and that it is intended to ramp up construction as soon as possible.  Could the Minister of State tell us what she envisages in that regard?  </p><p>With regard to housing adaptation grants, there are increasing numbers of people eligible for these grants who are being told more or less that unless they have some critical medical condition, they will not see the adaptation work done in the next couple of years.  It is not fair to build up the hope that there is a scheme in place if it is there in theory but not in practice.  It should be either scrapped or designated for certain people to let people know where they stand.  Again, it is a question of giving people continuity, if they can get their houses repaired because they are dilapidated rather than moving house.</p> <p>The Minister of State has said a lot about the rental accommodation scheme.  I know that many landlords do not take people from the housing list because they have a choice, particularly in the Dublin area.  There are 100,000 families on the housing list.  In my own area, south Dublin, there are 10,500 families on the list.  We must face up to the growing problem in housing provision, especially in Dublin and other major urban areas.  The DAFT website shows that today 2,300 properties are available to rent in Dublin.  There is a problem and I thank the Minister of State for bringing this reforming legislation before the House today.  I welcome it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.126" nospeaker="true" time="16:20:00" ><p>Debate adjourned.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.127" nospeaker="true" time="16:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800020#T00300">Report of Committee of Selection: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="16:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800020#T00400"><p>This is the 12th report of the Committee of Selection.</p><p>The Committee of Selection reports that it has discharged Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen from membership of the Committee on Procedure and Privileges at his own request and has appointed Senator David Norris in substitution for him.</p><p>The Committee of Selection reports that it has discharged Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen from membership of the Seanad Public Consultation Committee at his own request and has appointed Senator David Norris in substitution for him.</p><p>The Committee of Selection reports that it has discharged Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen from membership of the Committee of Selection at his own request and has appointed Senator David Norris in substitution for him.</p><p>The Committee of Selection reports that it has discharged Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen from membership of the Committee on Members' Interests at his own request and has appointed Senator David Norris in substitution for him.</p><p>The Committee of Selection reports that it has discharged Senator Fiach Mac Conghail from membership of the Seanad Public Consultation Committee at his own request and has appointed Senator Marie-Louise O'Donnell in substitution for him.</p><p>The Committee of Selection reports that it has discharged Senator Diarmuid Wilson from membership of the Joint Committee on Education and Social Protection at his own request and has appointed Senator Marie-Louise O'Donnell substitution for him.</p><p>I move: &quot;That the report be laid before the Seanad.&quot;</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.129" nospeaker="true" time="16:20:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.130" nospeaker="true" time="16:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800020#T00500">Housing (Amendment) Bill 2013: Second Stage (Resumed)</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.131" nospeaker="true" time="16:20:00" ><p>Question again proposed &quot;That the Bill be now read a Second Time&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="16:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800020#T00600"><p>I apologise to the Minister of State for my delay in arriving.  I meant no disrespect to the protocol of the House.  I was protesting at the gate with the West Cork Alliance which is protesting against the cuts to rural transport, the fishery cuts and cuts in home care provision.  I also spoke about the abolition of the town councils and said, speaking thorough a megaphone, that this Government has a slash and burn approach to all these cuts.  I do not include the Minister of State personally in that comment because I know what an outstanding politician she is, having sat on the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Health and Children with her.</p><p>Fianna F&aacute;il passed the Housing (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act 2009, which this Bill amends, in order to update and consolidate housing law.  The Housing (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act 2009 amends and extends the Housing Acts 1966 to 2004 to provide local authorities with a framework for a more strategic approach to the delivery and management of housing services.  That framework provides for the adoption of housing services plans, homelessness, action plans and anti-social behaviour strategies, for new more effective methods of assessing need and allocating housing, and for a more effective management and control regime covering tenancies, rents, etc.  Fianna F&aacute;il supports this technical Bill which builds upon legislation introduced by us in 2009.  The topic raised, however, illustrates the failure of the Government to tackle the housing crisis in the country with 100,000 applicants on the local authority housing waiting lists.</p><p>The failure of the Government to use NAMA properties to help address the problem is a damning indictment of the failure of the imagination of the Government to confront the challenges facing it.  Local authority rents also raise the question of the impact of the property tax on council coffers and the approach taken by councils to imposing the charge or absorbing it into their own balance sheets.</p><p>In respect of property tax and rents, housing units are not exempt from the local property tax as they are from the local authority charge and the authorities involved will be charged for the due sum.  The Bill does not refer to the impact of the property tax on local authority tenants.</p> <p>The Bill makes no reference to the impact of the property tax on local authority tenants or to the varying approaches taken by different local authorities, with some adding the charge on to the annual rents and others absorbing it directly on their bank sheets.  The local property tax on local authority housing will be &euro;45 this year and &euro;90 in 2014, with unknown increases due in the coming years as the Government inevitably hikes up the tax.  </p><p>If local authorities pass these costs on to ordinary homeowners, it will be another sharp blow to the already struggling low-income households across the country.  The decision to impose the local property tax on local authority homes will generate real financial difficulties for embattled councils, which have already had funding slashed.  </p><p>I wish the Minister of State success in her political career and as a Minister.  Hers was a well-deserved appointment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="16:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800021#U00200"><p>At some point in the future, the House would appreciate having the Minister of State here for a longer period of time to talk more generally about the future of social housing and other forms of housing delivery because it has come up a number of times on the Order of Business.  Almost every party has raised it.  It is not ideal for us to use a debate on legislation to bend the Minister of State's ear, so I would appreciate it if she came back to the House.</p><p>As the Minister of State said, the Bill makes a technical amendment to section 31 of the Housing (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act 2009.  For me the principal issue with this Bill is the deletion of section 31(6).  Historically, the differential rental scheme has been a very important aspect of Irish social housing.  When it was introduced in the 1960s and enshrined in law in the 1966 Housing Act, it made housing available on the basis of the means of a household and on the basis of that household's composition and need.  It was a needs-based form of social housing delivery and it contrasted quite significantly with what we had in the 1930s and 1940s.  While I do not want to go into a history lesson, it was a very important principle that if one had a housing need, it should be satisfied and any rent should be charged on the basis of one's ability to pay it.  </p><p>Section 31 attempted to give local authorities and differential rent schemes the possibility of charging rents based more on the location of the property and on other factors.  I am very gratified that the Minister of State said that she is fully in favour of local authority rents being linked to household income as an important principle and not on anything else.  I very much welcome that because it is an important principle which goes to the core of what this country is about, namely, the provision of housing according to one's need and one's ability to pay. </p><p>It is no secret that we have as many differential rent schemes in this country as we have shades of green.  It is not acceptable, nor is it the way to do business.  As the Minister of State said, there is no justification whatsoever for this disparate approach.  One will pay a higher rent in one part of the country than in another which bears no relationship whatsoever to the housing unit one is socially renting or to one's family circumstances.  That is ridiculous and should not be allowed.  The principle is an important one and it is based on need and ability to pay. </p><p>There has been a very significant change to the housing system in this country over the past decade with rent supplement, in effect, replacing social housing as the main form of social housing support and with the roll out of RAS.  I congratulate the Minister of State and the Minister for Social Protection, Deputy Burton, on their commitment to rolling out the housing assistance payment system, which is a very significant development for the considerable number of people getting their housing with assistance from the State.</p> <p>There has been a very clear divide up to now between tenants who are paying rent supplement in the private rented sector and those who are lucky enough to be in receipt of social housing.  If one is receipt of social housing, one can pay differential rent, whereas is one is in receipt of rent supplement, one has to stay poor to keep getting that support.  That is keeping people in poverty and I very much support the transfer of the rent supplement scheme to local authorities and the introduction of a differential rent scheme, through the housing assistance payment, HAP, in the rent supplement sector.  It will be a very positive force.  From my experience wearing a different hat, I know that the rental accommodation scheme, RAS, has been very successful in terms of labour market activation and people do return to work when they have an opportunity to do so.  There is very little or no doubt about this.</p><p>I very much welcome the introduction of the housing assistance payment.  I also welcome the Minister of State's statement that she will legislate for a new tenant purchase scheme along the lines of the incremental purchase scheme.  One of the benefits of incremental purchase is that it does not necessarily relate to the dwelling a person is in.  The beauty is that a tenant who is receiving social housing supports, through the housing assistance payment or the rental accommodation scheme, for example, will be eligible for the incremental purchase scheme, whereas before one had to be living in a council house.  This is because tenants in the voluntary housing sector have no eligibility for the tenant purchase scheme.  It will be important in levelling the paying field in order that any tenant who is receiving social housing supports will have eligibility for the tenant purchase scheme.</p><p>I take the opportunity to make one special plea regarding tenants in flats who, as far back as 1986, were promised the opportunity to buy them.  This is a particularly important issue in Dublin and Cork.  Many tenants have tried on numerous occasions to buy the flats in which they have been living and various Governments of different hue have tried to implement a tenant purchase scheme for flats.  It was announced under the Housing (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act 2009 and the Department has put in place pilot projects.  The one difficulty is that it is to be introduced under the incremental purchase scheme, which gives the discount into the future as opposed for years already elapsed.  I do not want to get too technical about this, but one of the difficulties is that many of the occupants have been tenants for 30 or 40 years.  If they are to be given no credit for the years they have already put in, they will not be in a position to purchase their flats.  Given that successive Governments, including this one, gave them that commitment, I would like to see the traditional tenant purchase scheme put in place, specifically, if necessary, for the purchase of flats.  It is a commitment we must fulfil.</p><p>I congratulate the Minister of State on the social housing programme.  We have made much progress.  There is much to be proud of that is ongoing in the Government.  The Minister of State will go down in history as a reforming Minister and I hope we will look back on this period, particularly on the introduction of the housing assistance payment, as being very positive for a significant number of people.  Some 26,000 could expect to benefit under the housing assistance payment when it is introduced.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="16:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800022#V00200"><p>Cuirim c&eacute;ad f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it.  C&eacute; go bhfuil muid ag f&aacute;ilti&uacute; roimh an Bille seo agus go bhfuil muid ag tac&uacute; leis na gn&eacute;ithe a bhaineann leis, caithfear an rud seo a chur i gcomhth&eacute;acs agus a r&aacute; go bhfuil polasa&iacute; an Rialtais i leith tith&iacute;ocht sh&oacute;isialta ina phraiseach i nd&aacute;ir&iacute;re.  The social housing system is in crisis.  Almost 100,000 households are on local authority waiting lists.  Almost the same number are in receipt of rent supplement and emergency social welfare payments for those who are unable to pay their rent in the private sector.  Central and local government spending on social housing building, buying and maintenance has been slashed since 2008.  Never has housing need been so great and never has the cost of housing been so low.  However, the housing policy of the Government, like the last one, has been characterised by inertia and inaction.  It is an indictment of the Government that after two and a half years in office this is the first significant legislation it has brought forward for consideration.  While Sinn F&eacute;in will support the Bill, I am compelled to use this short opportunity to highlight the broader failure of Government housing policy.</p><p>For some years the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government, supported by two Governments, has been abandoning the direct provision of social housing by the State.</p> <p>In its place they have been pushing private sector solutions to the housing crisis.  It is an issue which is particularly difficult in rural areas.  The list of schemes and acronyms grows ever longer.  First, there was the rental accommodation scheme and then the long-term leasing scheme.  To these were added the applicant-sourced housing scheme.  Let us not forget the incremental purchase scheme or the choice-based letting scheme.  As each Administration adds to the number of schemes, the number of households languishing on social housing waiting lists grows ever longer.  There is an urgent need for a new approach to social housing.  Innovative funding approaches are available if central and local government have the policy imagination and political will to develop them.  Whatever happened to the social housing bonds promised in the programme for Government?  Why is the Government failing to develop innovative ways to draw down Housing Finance Agency funding to take advantage of the great value for money in the market?  I am interested in hearing the Minister of State's answers.</p><p>We need as a matter of urgency a new approach to housing.  We must revert to direct provision of social housing by the State and develop new funding models similar to those used elsewhere in the European Union.  Crucially, we must get people off rent supplement, local authority waiting lists and the streets into long-term suitable and sustainable accommodation.  The Bill represents an improvement on the current system.  It is welcome that it provides elected members of local authorities with a greater say in rent setting.  It is a pity the Minister of State did not use the Bill as an opportunity to achieve greater standardisation and harmonisation of rental systems across the State.  </p><p>Senator Mary White raised an important point.  We hear that the property tax will be passed on to tenants in quite a number of cases.  It is hypocritical to bring forward a Bill which takes on board people's ability to pay, while the property tax does not take this into consideration at all.  I hope the Minister of State indicates that she will direct local authorities not to add the property tax to the rent of tenants in the relevant housing.  Harmonisation would have been relatively easy to achieve and would have improved the social housing system significantly.  Having said that, Sinn F&eacute;in is happy to support the Bill, notwithstanding that it proposes only modest changes to the current system.</p><p>T&aacute;imid ag tac&uacute; leis an mBille ach n&iacute;l anseo ach sop in &aacute;it na scuaibe, teasta&iacute;onn gn&iacute;omha&iacute;ocht i bhfad n&iacute;os m&oacute; maidir leis na daoine ar fad at&aacute; ag fanacht ar na liosta&iacute; tith&iacute;ochta.  Housing is the issue raised most often with me by constituents, in particular in relation to the fact that local authorities are not building any housing stock worth talking about.  It is a serious issue on which I await the Minister of State's remarks with interest.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1114" speakername="Deirdre Clune" time="16:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800023#W00200"><p>I welcome the Bill.  It is a small but important body of legislation which will ensure there is a uniform approach to rents nationally.  Everybody will welcome this.  The debate provides Members with an opportunity to make contributions on the general issue of housing and housing supports for individuals who cannot afford to provide their own homes.  It has been mentioned that there are 100,000 people on local authority housing waiting lists.  My experience has been that many of the people concerned are happy with the accommodation they have under the rental accommodation and other rent assistance schemes.  They are not homeless and their accommodation is being provided or supported, which is an important point to make.</p><p>The Minister of State spoke about her hope of again introducing a tenant purchase scheme, which is welcome.  While it is good to encourage individuals to own their homes, there is a danger that the stock of local authority housing can be run down.  This was particularly an issue in Cork following the introduction of the previous tenant purchase scheme.  Tenant purchase is well and good at a time when local authorities or the Government are building housing, but when the stock is not being replenished, issues can arise.  On the whole, I encourage home ownership, where possible.  It is important for individuals as a contribution to their community and in the sense that it allows them to manage their own properties.</p> <p>I welcome and support the rental accommodation scheme.  I speak regularly of this worthwhile scheme.  It has improved the quality of rental accommodation because of the level of supervision by local authorities.  It has also provided certainty to individuals to seek employment and to move on from needing housing support.  It is also of benefit to landlords with properties to offer because there is certainty in the relationship over a number of years.  It is a win-win situation and while it was slow to start it is doing very well now.  Local authorities are responding well to it.</p><p>I wish local authorities would engage more with landlords in sourcing accommodation because my experience is that they leave it to individuals to source accommodation and make a proposal.  If landlords approached the local authorities, it might be better for tenants.  It is a positive scheme, particularly for single people.  I found that, particularly in Cork, apartments can be utilised for individuals in single person households.  In the past, it was very difficult for single people to find accommodation.  I urge the Minister of State to encourage local authorities and work on this and ensure it is developed and progressed.  I welcome the Bill and the fact that it will give councils an opportunity to be involved in the rent setting mechanism, which is important.  Individuals or households will pay rent on the basis of income, which is welcome.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="16:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800024#X00200"><p>Senator Mary White outlined our position on this short Bill, which has been brought forward to amend the 2009 legislation.  This was introduced to tidy up legislation that spanned 1966 to 2004.  In any local authority, there is a housing waiting list but at the moment the lists are getting longer.  We talk about local authority housing in respect of this Bill but there is a wider housing crisis in respect of people with mortgage difficulties, mortgage arrears and associated difficulties, such as banks putting pressure on people to repay moneys due.  For the purposes of the debate, I will zone in on the legislation.</p><p>Fianna F&aacute;il is supporting the legislation.  I refer to the current difficulties local authorities have in dealing with housing waiting lists.  Donegal County Council has many vacant properties but the council does not have the resources to bring them to the required standard so they can be rented out.  Families are waiting on accommodation when the accommodation should be made available faster.  Perhaps the Minister of State can raise this matter with the local authority.</p><p>Some 100,000 families are on the national housing waiting list and the issue needs attention.  On one side of the coin the Department of Social Protection spends over &euro;500 million a year in rent supplement payments.  The money would be better used to build or purchase units, particularly when the price of property has fallen.  A number of years ago, a housing leasing initiative was introduced but it has not been a success.  In my view, in the views of tenants and from talking to local authority officials, the leasing scheme has not been the success everyone envisaged.</p> <p>What are the Minister of State's views on that?</p><p>What is happening with the properties under NAMA's control?  The agency has identified almost 4,000 units that could be made available for social housing.  I understand local authorities have confirmed that 1,500 units would be suitable forthwith while another 800 are being evaluated, bringing the total that may be deemed suitable by them to 2,350.  Are discussions taking place between the Department and the agency to house 2,500 families in those properties.  Why is there a delay in bringing that to fruition?</p><p>I refer to the local property tax.  Local authorities are strapped for cash and they are being asked to collect &euro;2 per week from local authority tenants, which will create difficulties both for the local authorities and the tenants.</p><p>Housing assistance is available through the essential repairs and disabled person's grant schemes.  However, those grants have been greatly diminished.  The percentage available in comparison to the overall cost of any such work is low and this is deterring many individuals with disabilities from upgrading or carrying out essential works to their houses.  There is a need to review the schemes to make sure the percentage allocated is higher than it is currently.  It is wrong that a disabled person cannot carry out essential works to their house because the grant is so low.  Local authority staff who administer these schemes say that they are so restrictive that they cannot go beyond what is laid down in the conditions attaching to them.  This issue needs to be examined.  Little money is being made available under those grant schemes.  We must look after the elderly and people with disabilities in local authority housing and in private housing.  If the elderly cannot upgrade their homes to convert a bedroom, install a shower and so on, they will end up in nursing homes and that will cost the State more money.  A joined-up approach is needed from the Government on the issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1162" speakername="Denis Landy" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800025#Y00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House.  I commend her and the Government on the stimulus package being put in place to provide improvements to local authority housing stock.  Up to &euro;50 million will be made available under this package and this is most welcome.  I respect what the previous speaker said but this money will enable much of the work he mentioned to be carried out on housing stock that is in poor condition and provide for extensions where families have increased in number.  This package will generate work and kick-start local economies with construction workers returning to employment.  It will be a worthwhile and excellent scheme.  I look forward to some of the money coming to south Tipperary and I will speak to the Minister of State about that.</p><p>While I welcome the legislation, I have a number of queries.  It is fair that people pay based on their income.  Properties are being assessed currently but different rates apply in the same local authority area because the property values are different, for example, in a town.  </p> <p>Houses on one housing estate may have a different valuation than on another and, hence, newer estates will attract different rents than older ones under the differential rent scheme.  It is welcome that local councillors are being given discretion in this area.  How much discretion will there be to differentiate between those who move into local authority housing that is five years old as opposed to older houses such as those in my estate which was built in 1939?  Currently, there is a difference between the rents payable on both types of estate.  One person may be living in a fully modern house, while another may be living in a house that is 70 or 80 years old.  Will the Minister of State elaborate on the discretion that applies?</p><p>How will the scheme apply across the country?  In Dublin and other cities the facilities made available to people are better than those in rural areas where there may be isolated cottages and no public transport.  All of these points were factored into the existing differential rent scheme.  The Minister of State mentioned discretion.  Will she expand on what she means by &quot;discretion&quot; that is to be exercised by local elected members?</p><p>How long will the transition period be?  How will it operate?  Harmonisation would probably be good for some and not for others.  With regard to people who are adjusting, how long will the transition period be?  It is not clear from what I read in the legislation or the explanatory memorandum.   I would greatly appreciate it if the Minister of State answered these questions.</p><p>Senator Aideen Hayden has welcomed the fact that the Government intends to introduce a new tenant purchase scheme.  It is very important that people believe they have the opportunity to purchase their own house, put down roots and keep their house for future generations.  In this way, they will not be concerned about the loss of the family history associated with their house on their passing away.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1142" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="16:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800026#Z00200"><p>I welcome the Leas-Cheann Comhairle, Deputy Michael P. Kitt, to the Visitors Gallery.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="16:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800026#Z00300"><p>I thank all of the Senators on all sides of the House who participated in the debate.  I thank them for their support for the Bill.</p><p>A number of issues were raised.  Generally, there was a positive response to a few developments, one being the move towards harmonisation.  Senator Aideen Hayden described the 40 shades of the differential rent scheme across the country.  We are trying to move towards a system under which one will pay in accordance with the family's income.</p><p>On the specific issue raised by Senator Denis Landy, that of transition, there are differences across the country, which are significant in some places.  We envisage that the transition period towards more or less a harmonised rent across the country will probably be three years.  Rent will be set more or less in accordance with the size of the family and their income.</p><p>We will be moving responsibility for the long-term rent supplement scheme to the local authorities and what we propose will facilitate this.  It would be very difficult for the Department of Social Protection to harmonise 40 rent schemes.  I believe there are more than 40 around the country.  We want to see a relatively smooth transition towards what will be more or less a standard payment, again depending on the size of the family.  This also facilitates removing the poverty trap referred to by a number of Senators.  A person is in danger of losing his or her entire rent supplement if he or she finds work.  That clearly is not a phenomenon we want to support in any way.  We want to facilitate a person in being able to take up employment without having to worry about not being able to pay for housing.  Overall, we want to move towards a harmonised, fair system that will work for everybody.</p> <p> A number of other issues were raised.  A number of Senators referred to the supply of housing and waiting lists.  It is a broader issue than the Bill is covering.  There are more than 100,000 people on waiting lists across the country.  I suggest to the Fianna F&aacute;il Senators, in particular, that the list did not start today or yesterday; it was building up right throughout the boom period.  When the country had money we did not build as many houses as we should have.  It is something with which we are trying to deal. </p><p>One of the reasons the leasing scheme was embraced was because it was a way of providing housing fairly quickly for people in need of it.  It carries ongoing costs, therefore it is kept under review.  Ideally, I would love to build local authority houses but unfortunately I do not have the money to do so.  We do not have the capital budget.  Any construction has to be accounted for and is a significant cost.  I will move as soon as I can to have some part of the delivery of social housing under construction.  We currently have limited construction which is largely confined to people with the greatest need, such as those with disabilities, older people, etc.  I would like to move, as soon as I can, to a more significant construction programme.  At the moment, unfortunately, we do not have the money to do as much as we would like. </p><p>Senator Landy referred to the stimulus package.  It comprises &euro;50 million over three years to address 25,000 of the least energy efficient local authority houses around the country.  We are in discussions with local authorities on the houses which need attention.  The programme will start this year and continue into next year and the year after.  It will also help to address fuel poverty for many households around the country which are currently spending a lot of money on heating what are often fairly draughty, cold houses.  It will make a real difference, as well as helping the construction industry to get moving.</p><p>The issue of NAMA houses was referred to by Senators White and &Oacute; Domhnaill, in particular.  We have speeded up the process.  I accept it was slower than it should have been.  It has now set up a special purpose vehicle which is assisting in moving the process forward.  Over 100 houses came over the line in the first few months of this year.  I will be able to give the Senators better figures at the end of the years, but things are moving faster than they were.</p><p>Senators Keane and &Oacute; Domhnaill referred to adaptation grants.  I am reviewing them because we want to make sure the money we have available is put to the best possible use.  There are three different types of grants, namely for disabled, mobility and older persons.  The averages are a lot lower than the upper limits.  We want to see whether we can spread the money around to provide more benefit to more people.  There is a limited amount of money and we are limited in what we can spend on any scheme.  A review is ongoing and we hope as a result we will spread the money as well as we can.  It is a good scheme which allows people to stay in their homes and not have to stay in hospital or nursing homes for longer than is necessary.  We want to make sure we get the best possible value for money.</p><p>Senator Hayden referred to flats and apartments.  A scheme currently operates but not many purchases are made under it.  It merits a review to determine whether it can be more favourable.</p><p>A number of Senators raised the issue of a tenant purchase scheme.  The end of this month is the closing date for completion under the old tenant purchase scheme.  The new incremental purchase scheme will, as Senator Hayden said, allow people who are not currently tenants to buy properties.  To that extent, it will be open to more people than previous schemes have been.  It will be much more related to income than length of time spent in a property.  We feel that is fairer and will allow people to purchase properties.</p> <p>We want people to be in a position to purchase local authority houses where they have the means to do so.</p><p>This is a short, technical Bill, with many of its provisions relating to various aspects of local authority housing provision and to the Bill we will bring forward later in the year which will introduce the housing assistance payment scheme.  It is my intention that the heads of that Bill will be published before the summer break.  We will work on the text over the summer and debate it in the autumn.  I hope I have covered all the points Members raised.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1162" speakername="Denis Landy" time="17:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800028#BB00200"><p>Will the Minister of State comment on the discretion to be afforded to elected local authority members in regard to the HAP scheme?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="17:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800028#BB00300"><p>That type of discretion was heretofore the remit of local authority managers, but elected members will now have a function in this regard.  We have yet to draft the regulations on exactly what their role will be, but they will be able to exercise an element of discretion.  At the same time, however, we intend to retain the concept of harmonisation so that tenants across the country will be able, by and large, to ascertain what level of rent they should expect to pay.  These matters will be dealt with in the regulations under the new schemes and in the upcoming legislation.  As such, I do not have a definitive answer to the Senator's question at this time, but I will keep him informed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1162" speakername="Denis Landy" time="17:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800028#BB00400"><p>Will the Minister of State take into account what I said regarding the variation in property and rental values in different locations?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="17:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800028#BB00500"><p>Certainly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="17:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800028#BB00600"><p>Does the Minister of State have any thoughts on the property tax being transferred to tenants?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="17:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800028#BB00700"><p>The intention is that 80% of income from the property tax will be retained within the local authority to which it is paid, with an equalisation thereafter to ensure smaller councils do not lose out.  In other words, local authorities will be paying most of the moneys raised to themselves.  I do not intend to be prescriptive in terms of how they should pay for the element of it that relates to their own housing stock.  The fact that they will be retaining 80% of what they take in will mean it is a relatively small amount in the overall scheme of things.  We will not be issuing a diktat that these moneys must be taken from tenants.</p><p>  I thank Senators for their contribution to the debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.154" nospeaker="true" time="17:05:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1142" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="17:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800028#BB00900"><p>When is it proposed to take Committee Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Ca&iacute;t Keane" time="17:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800028#BB01000"><p>Next Thursday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.157" nospeaker="true" time="17:05:00" ><p>Committee Stage ordered for Thursday, 27 June 2013.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.158" nospeaker="true" time="17:05:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 4.45 p.m. and resumed at 5.45 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.159" nospeaker="true" time="17:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800029#CC00100">Public Service Management (Recruitment and Appointments) (Amendment) Bill 2013: Committee Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="17:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800029#CC00200"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House.  We are dealing with the Public Service Management (Recruitment and Appointments) (Amendment) Bill 2013, Committee Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.161" nospeaker="true" time="17:10:00" ><p>Section 1 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.162" nospeaker="true" time="17:10:00" ><p>SECTION 2</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="17:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800029#CC00500"><p>Amendments Nos. 1 to 8, inclusive, 8a and 13 to 18, inclusive, are cognate and will be discussed together by agreement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.164" nospeaker="true" time="17:10:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 1:
In page 4, to delete line 8.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1097" speakername="Brendan Howlin" time="17:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800029#CC00700"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach for his welcome.  I am glad to be back.  We made good progress on this matter during the Second Stage debate last week.  It is not a very long or technical Bill.  The Bill is intended to facilitate movement within the public service.  This set of amendments Nos. 1 to 8, and 13 to 18 together, is consequent on the substantial amendment, namely, amendment No. 1.  The purpose of this group of amendments is to remove the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na from the remit of the Bill.  This is to reflect the view of the Minister for Justice and Equality, and the Garda Commissioner, that the authority for deployment and redeployment of members of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, which currently vests in the Garda Commissioner under section 26 of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na Act 2005, should continue to rest with the Commissioner alone.</p> <p>This is to reflect the view of the Minister for Justice and Equality and the Garda Commissioner that the authority for deployment and redeployment of members of the Garda, which is currently vested in the Commissioner under section 26 of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na Act 2005, should continue to rest with the Commissioner alone.  I have reflected on this and agree that is the correct course of action.  We all jealously guard the right of the Commissioner to deploy members of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na operationally as he sees fit.  It would not be appropriate for that to be paralleled by the work of the Public Appointments Service.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="17:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800030#DD00200"><p>That is a sensible alteration.  The Garda should not be part of this and the role of the Commissioner should not be interfered with.  Garda&iacute; are regularly redeployed.</p><p>I disagree fundamentally with the Minister that the Bill is technical.  It is radical and goes way beyond what it is currently set out in the public service agreements.  It should be treated as such.  I am surprised that I have not received representations from any of the public service unions on the Bill.  I wonder if they have their eyes on the ball, notwithstanding the Minister's statement that he has discussed the legislation with them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="17:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800030#DD00300"><p>On amendment No. 1.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="17:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800030#DD00400"><p>I wonder if the unions have explained it to their members and whether those members know what is going through the Oireachtas.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.170" nospeaker="true" time="17:15:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.171" nospeaker="true" time="17:15:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 2:
In page 4, line 9, to delete &quot;(iii) that category&quot; and substitute &quot;(ii) that category&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.172" nospeaker="true" time="17:15:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.173" nospeaker="true" time="17:15:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 3:
In page 4, line 13, to delete &quot;(iv) a local&quot; and substitute &quot;(iii) a local&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.174" nospeaker="true" time="17:15:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.175" nospeaker="true" time="17:15:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 4:
In page 4, line 14, to delete &quot;(v) the Health&quot; and substitute &quot;(iv) the Health&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.176" nospeaker="true" time="17:15:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.177" nospeaker="true" time="17:15:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 5:
In page 4, line 15, to delete &quot;(vi) a vocational&quot; and substitute &quot;(v) a vocational&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.178" nospeaker="true" time="17:15:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.179" nospeaker="true" time="17:15:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 6:
In page 4, line 16, to delete &quot;(vii) any other&quot; and substitute &quot;(vi) any other&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.180" nospeaker="true" time="17:15:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.181" nospeaker="true" time="17:15:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 7:
In page 4, line 37, to delete &quot;(viii) any other&quot; and substitute &quot;(vii) any other&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.182" nospeaker="true" time="17:15:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.183" nospeaker="true" time="17:15:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 8:
In page 4, line 47, to delete &quot;(ix) any subsidiary&quot; and substitute &quot;(viii) any subsidiary&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.184" nospeaker="true" time="17:15:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.185" nospeaker="true" time="17:15:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 8a:
In page 5, lines 1 and 2, to delete &quot;subparagraph (iv), (v) or (vii)&quot; and substitute &quot;subparagraph (iii), (iv) or (vi)&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.186" nospeaker="true" time="17:15:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.187" nospeaker="true" time="17:15:00" ><p>Section 2, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.188" nospeaker="true" time="17:15:00" ><p>Sections 3 to 5, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.189" nospeaker="true" time="17:15:00" ><p>SECTION 6</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.190" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="17:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800030#DD02500"><p>Amendment No. 9, in the name of Senator Thomas Byrne and others, involves a potential charge to the Exchequer and is ruled out of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.191" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="17:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800030#DD02600"><p>I protest that ruling vigorously, as well as the whole operation of the rule about something being a charge on the Exchequer.  A new definition is being introduced in law on basic pay which does not exist anywhere else.  The idea that I cannot propose an amendment to it is crazy.  There is no intention to cost the State money.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.192" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="17:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800030#DD02700"><p>I understand the Senator's position.  Unfortunately, I cannot discuss the ruling here.  That is how the matter is dealt with.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.193" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1097" speakername="Brendan Howlin" time="17:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800030#DD02800"><p>If Senator Byrne raises it in the discussion of the section, I will respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.194" nospeaker="true" time="17:15:00" ><p>Amendment No. 9 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.195" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="17:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800030#DD03000"><p>I move amendment No. 10:<blockquote><br />In page 6, line 48, after &quot;day&quot; to insert the following:&quot;after having first given notice within every relevant public service body and having sought suitable candidates for redeployment and having first considered, in accordance with section 57D, whether to designate any such candidate who seeks redeployment&quot;.</blockquote>We may have to withdraw the amendment and raise the matter on Report Stage instead.  The aim is to have some element of voluntary provision in the legislation.  The idea from Croke Park I to the Haddington Road agreement has been that redeployment will first be sought on a voluntary basis.  That should be established in statute, which is the idea behind the amendment.  I will listen to what the Minister has to say.</p><p>  As drafted, the Bill gives the Public Appointments Service the power to designate an employee of a public service for redeployment.  It does not ask whether the person wants to be redeployed or whether he or she has requested it.  It seems to me that it should be put into the Bill.  It is part of the last two agreements and would be a sensible provision.  One should look for volunteers rather than redeploy by way of the strong hand of the Public Appointments Service.  The Minister is providing the service with a radical power which has not been agreed with the unions.  It would be better for workplace relations if a voluntary element was provided for in statute.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.196" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1097" speakername="Brendan Howlin" time="17:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800030#DD03100"><p>This has worked very well on an <i>ad hoc</i> basis up to now.  Obviously, it is a matter of voluntary movement within the public service.  As I indicated on Second Stage, we have discussed this with the unions and they are fully conversant with all of it.  The legislation has been drafted to give effect to the agreement reached with the trade unions on pay and mobility.</p><p>  I acknowledge Senator Byrne's wish to provide staff with the maximum possible opportunity to volunteer for available posts.  In essence, what is suggested in the amendment is a requirement that, where the skills being sought are available across the public service generally, the Public Appointments Service ask all 300,000 public servants if they wish to volunteer.  That is not practical.  We have had 10,000 voluntary movements in the last few years.  People see the positions that are available, they volunteer and are moved within the architecture of Croke Park I.  That will continue under the agreed architecture of the Haddington Road agreement, hopefully.  Redeployment is obviously a better option than redundancy.  We have had in the past ridiculous situations in which people had literally no work.  In some State agencies, they sat for years on end with no work while drawing a wage.  In the current climate, that is entirely unacceptable and no trade union or other person is arguing for it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="17:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800030#DD03200"><p>Neither are we, in fairness.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.198" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1097" speakername="Brendan Howlin" time="17:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800030#DD03300"><p>I am not suggesting that is the case.  I am setting out the backdrop against which this sort of mobility should be provided for in statute rather than on an <i>ad hoc</i> basis.  It made sense to bring community welfare officers into the Department of Social Protection and to restructure F&Aacute;S as Intreo while redeploying staff.  While the redeployment was agreed without resistance regarding terms and conditions and the timing of movement, there was no statutory basis for doing it.  The provision in the Bill is about putting redeployment on a statutory footing.</p><p>  We must be practical in what we do.  We do not want to provide in statute for requirements that are wholly impractical, such as having to ask all 300,000 public servants if they have the skills required to fill a vacancy in the Department of the Environment, Heritage and Local Government in Wexford.  It is better to operate on a volunteer basis as far as is practical, while not being so prescriptive in the legislation as to make the Bill unworkable for the Public Appointments Service.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.199" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="17:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800030#DD03400"><p>Nobody disputes the need for redeployment or suggests that people who are doing nothing should be left in place.  Nobody is saying that should continue.  We support redeployment.  My amendment seeks merely to provide for what has been agreed in the Haddington Road agreement, which states on page 12 that the Department should identify the number of posts at each relevant grade that are surplus and the location of the surplus.</p> <p>Once a surplus has been established on this basis, the identification of staff to be redeployed will proceed as follows: volunteers will be sought for the redeployment panel and if the number of volunteers falls short of the surplus the process of last in, first out will be applied as appropriate.  It seems perfectly reasonable to have some voluntary element to it.  The Minister is hanging his opposition to my amendment on the basis that I require this of every relevant public service body.  The inclusion of the term "every relevant" was to narrow it down but it is not narrowed down in the Haddington Road agreement.  What is wrong with the Labour Party asking people to volunteer first and putting that in statute?  It was included in the Croke Park Agreement and in Croke Park II.  If the Minister cannot find volunteers, there are compulsory measures.  The strong hand still exists now that the Minister is in power.  There should be a voluntary procedure in statute and I do not see anything wrong with that.  If the Minister thinks there is some technical difficulty with my amendment, which is the basis of his opposition, let that be the reason I withdraw it.  I can resubmit it on Report Stage.  Why not have a voluntary scheme in statute to see if there are volunteers?  It is not to make redeployment voluntary, it is to see if people are looking for it before we force people who do not want to move.  There may well be people who want to move.  We are looking for the Public Appointments Service to look for that before designating people.  The Minister and his officials should think about this.  We are not looking to stall redeployment or to put the kibosh on it, we are simply seeking a requirement that is in the relevant agreements, that volunteers are sought before the compulsory nature is forced on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.201" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1162" speakername="Denis Landy" time="17:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800031#EE00200"><p>I listened with interest to Senator Thomas Byrne, who alluded to the fact that the necessary measures for this matter are proposed in the Haddington Road agreement.  They are already in the Croke Park Agreement and are dealt with in another forum.  The Minister has adequately explained why there is no need to include these measures.  Some 10,000 people have redeployed within the public sector over the past seven to ten years.  All of those were given an opportunity, they all volunteered and there was no problem.  Senator Byrne is trying to create a problem, for the sake of his amendment, when none exists.  The Minister pointed out that, in the current circumstances, people have been given the opportunity to redeploy rather than being made redundant.  They are willing, albeit reluctant, to do so.  Savings must be made.</p><p>When Fianna F&aacute;il was in government and a grand announcement about decentralisation was made, no thought was given to the staff who, theoretically, were going to be sent to the four corners of Ireland.  It never happened because the great man went to Brussels instead.  Members should reflect on this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.202" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1097" speakername="Brendan Howlin" time="17:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800031#EE00300"><p>I am not making a technical point.  If I accepted the amendment, it would fundamentally hamstring the operation of the redeployment process.  My objection is not technical but fundamental.  I cannot accept the amendment for that reason.</p><p>Detailed operational protocols have been negotiated with the trade union movement and set out who should be notified.  The trade union movement understands the practical issue and the protocols are agreed and concern what staff should be circulated with information.  The protocol also provides that certain posts should be confined to organisations closing down within a limited timeframe.  That has been agreed with the trade union movement.  The processes are embedded and well understood.  I ask the Senator to facilitate us enacting the measure to provide for the new Haddington Road agreement so that we can have redeployment, protect employment and have no compulsory redundancies, leading to a more efficient public service.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.203" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" speakername="John Kelly" time="17:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800031#EE00400"><p>I have a question on redeployment.  Apparently, the psychiatric nursing service has no HSE transfer policy even though there is only one organisation.  How does redeployment apply where there is no transfer policy in place?  People are trying to transfer from various parts of the country to other parts of the country.  The policy is not in place so it cannot happen.  If redeployment was in place, would they have the opportunity to get to where they want?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.204" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1097" speakername="Brendan Howlin" time="17:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800031#EE00500"><p>There are two separate issues, transfers and redeployment.  Mutually accepted transfers are a feature of the public service generally but people cannot transfer if there is no job to go to.  I was directly involved with the trade unions and psychiatric nurses in respect of St. Senan's Psychiatric Hospital in Enniscorthy, which is now officially closed.  There was a full five-year programme of redeployment for the staff to migrate into the community settings in which they will work and agreement on who will work where.  There are redeployment strategies in the public service and in the HSE, which deal with the closing down of old institutions that are no longer acceptable and the migration to better, modern community settings such as those provided for psychiatric services in the community.  The new transparent model is something we would like to see more of.</p><p>As far as practicable, I would like to see the role of the Public Appointments Service enhanced to facilitate transfers.  We all get cases where someone would like transfer and, where there is a mutually agreed transfer, it is stopped by an agency because they do not want to lose someone they value in exchange for someone they do not know.  If that was done at arm's length by the Public Appointments Service, it would be a good thing to migrate to.  I am cognisant of the Senator's point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.205" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="17:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800031#EE00600"><p>I will not pursue it any further.  I fully understand there are protocols in respect of redeployment and I fully understand the Croke Park agreement and the Haddington Road agreement.  Although I will not pursue it, I do not understand why the Minister cannot provide a statutory basis for some element of voluntary selection or volunteerism, as is the practice.  Why would the Minister not put the practice into law in a generalised way in order to operate in an efficient way that does not hamstring the redeployment process?  No one is arguing against redeployment but the Bill provides the Public Appointments Service with substantially more power than in the agreement.  I am prepared to withdraw the amendment but I may resubmit it on Report Stage.  I would like the Minister to think about this point, which is reasonable.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.206" nospeaker="true" time="17:25:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.207" nospeaker="true" time="17:25:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 11:
In page 7, line 19, to delete &#8220;basic&#8221;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.208" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1097" speakername="Brendan Howlin" time="17:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800031#EE00900"><p>This is a technical amendment to clarify that when a person is redeployed, the total pay in the new post must not be less than basic pay in the old post.  The provision as published provides that where a person is redeployed, the basic pay in the new post will not be less than the basic pay in the old post.  The text anticipates that, on assignment to the new post, allowances will always be payable but that may not be the position in every case.  The text is being amended to remove any doubt on the issue.  It is something we discussed during the debate on Second State and I want to bring clarity to it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.209" nospeaker="true" time="17:25:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.210" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="17:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800031#EE01100"><p>I move amendment No. 12:<blockquote><br />In page 9, to delete lines 31 to 37 and substitute the following:&#8220;(<i>c</i>) the terms of any collective agreement negotiated with any recognised trade union or staff association concerned, relating to mobility or redeployment of public service employees or if no such collective agreement is applicable, the terms of any policy for the time being of the Minister;&#8221;.</blockquote>If this amendment was accepted, it would deal with most of the issues I have with the Bill.  We do not have issues with the main point of the Bill, which is worthwhile and needs to be passed.  When the Public Appointments Service is making a designation of an employee to be redeployed, it must take into account a number of points.  Section 57D(<i>c</i>) refers to &quot;the terms of any policy for the time being of the Minister, or collective agreement negotiated with any recognised trade union&quot;.  These terms are the wrong way around and the collective agreement term should be placed first, followed by the terms of any policy for the time being of the Minister if no such collective agreement is applicable.  If there is a collective agreement in force, it should have precedence over everything.  In that section, the terms are the wrong way around and the Minister's policy is relevant if there is no collective agreement in place.</p> <p>However, other than that, the collective agreement, presumably, should come first.  Providing for them in this order gives the impression that the Minister's policy is superior or has more meaning for the PAS than any collective agreement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.212" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1097" speakername="Brendan Howlin" time="17:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800032#FF00200"><p>I have thought a deal about the Senator's amendment.  On reflecting on it there is merit in it, but it would put an onus on the PAS to adopt a role in the applicability and interpretation of collective agreements on redeployment and mobility.  On reflection and having consulted my human resources policy division, that role is appropriate to the human resources management, remuneration and industrial relations division of my Department and it would not be appropriate to give it to the PAS.  While I am well aware of the intent of the amendment, the terms I have set out which capture the statutory responsibility given to the Minister under the Ministers and Secretaries Act 2011 should be preserved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.213" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="17:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800032#FF00300"><p>Is the amendment being pressed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.214" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="17:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800032#FF00400"><p>I understand Report Stage is being taken immediately following Committee Stage, which is unacceptable.  If so, I will call divisions.  I am prepared to withdraw the amendment and return to it on Report Stage----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.215" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="17:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800032#FF00500"><p>That is not fully agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.216" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="17:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800032#FF00600"><p>I am hearing rumours that it will happen.  We will be happy if Report Stage is not taken immediately.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.217" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="17:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800032#FF00700"><p>We will deal with that matter when we come to it.  It was not agreed to on the Order of Business and, therefore, will have to be agreed at the conclusion of Committee Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.218" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="17:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800032#FF00800"><p>I do not quite get the Minister's point, but he gets mine and perhaps he might reflect on my amendment and come up with a superior wording, given the superior intelligence that works for him.  Any time the Opposition seeks to bring something forward and the Minister gets the point, there is at least a technical reason it cannot be implemented.  I am willing to reflect on this issue and come back to it on Report Stage because it would be worthwhile to give serious recognition to collective agreements.  While they are recognised, statutes and other matters come ahead of them in the context of redeployment.  I worry about this for the future in terms of collective agreements.  The statute does not set out a framework for redeployment, rather it sets out a framework for compulsory redeployment.  It should be broader than compulsory redeployment and should reflect what is agreed to in practice.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.219" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1097" speakername="Brendan Howlin" time="17:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800032#FF00900"><p>I might be able to give some comfort to the Senator and obviate the need to repeat ourselves on Report Stage.  The amendment looked like a sensible proposal, but given the role and functions conferred on the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform in the reform of public services generally and the allocation of human resources and finances in that context, the broader policy of the Minister on theses issues objectively must be given precedence over collective agreements.  The Senator may be Minister at a future date or have control over public sector pay policy and there might be issues on which he needs to have that statutory right and authority.  We cannot include in statute an impediment to the Government's right to govern.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.220" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="17:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800032#FF01000"><p>It would be worthwhile for the Minister to confirm that there is nothing in the legislation to override the Haddington Road agreement in practice.  Collective agreements are recognised by the Government and despite the fact that a procedure for compulsory redeployment is being provided for, which I accept may be needed, the practice has always been that the first to go leave on a voluntary basis.  A total of 10,000 public servants moved on a voluntary basis and more would have moved had the decentralisation programme gone ahead, particularly to Drogheda.  Loads of people were queuing up to move there, as Senator D'Arcy will be aware.  The Department of Social Protection had a queue a mile long.  I would like the Minister to comment on this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.221" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1097" speakername="Brendan Howlin" time="17:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800032#FF01100"><p>The Minister's statutory right needs to be preserved, with which the Senator will not disagree, but I want to be crystal clear that the Haddington Road agreement will be fully protected by the Government and it is fully protected in this legislation.  However, we are crafting a law that will have duration well beyond 2016, the expiry date of the agreement.  There might be cases in which the Minister might well need to act in preserving the public purse or dealing with other issues and it must be the right of the Minister who has statutory responsibility for the public service and pay to have that authority ultimately.  However, I assure the Senator and the House that the Haddington Road agreement and all other collective agreements will be fully protected by the Government.</p><p>I should not be drawn into discussing the notion of decentralisation which affected my own constituency.  The Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government was supposed to move wholly to Wexford, abandoning the Custom House.  We got a few hundred people and there were many volunteers, but the problem was that they were not all from that Department.  The policy which we terminated as soon we entered government broke the collective memory and wisdom of Departments because new Departments were created.  The Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government was to be formed with anybody who wished to transfer to Wexford, while the Department of Justice and Equality was to be formed by those who wished to move to another location.  That was crazy.  The corporate memory and ability of Departments to carry out their functions would have been hugely damaged by that policy.  However, that debate is over.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.222" nospeaker="true" time="17:35:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.223" nospeaker="true" time="17:35:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 13:
In page 10, between lines 28 and 29, to insert the following:&quot;(k) to the extent not otherwise provided by this subsection, a member of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na;&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.224" nospeaker="true" time="17:35:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.225" nospeaker="true" time="17:35:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 14:
In page 10, line 29, to delete &quot;(k) a position&quot; and substitute &quot;(l) a position&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.226" nospeaker="true" time="17:35:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.227" nospeaker="true" time="17:35:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 15:
In page 10, line 31, to delete &quot;(l) to the&quot; and substitute &quot;(m) to the&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.228" nospeaker="true" time="17:35:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.229" nospeaker="true" time="17:35:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 16:
In page 10, line 45, to delete &quot;(m) staff of&quot; and substitute &quot;(n) staff of&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.230" nospeaker="true" time="17:35:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.231" nospeaker="true" time="17:35:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 17:
In page 10, line 46, to delete &quot;(n) staff of&quot; and substitute &quot;(o) staff of&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.232" nospeaker="true" time="17:35:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.233" nospeaker="true" time="17:35:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 18:
In page 11, line 1, to delete &quot;(o) an Appeal&quot; and substitute &quot;(p) an Appeal&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.234" nospeaker="true" time="17:35:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.235" nospeaker="true" time="17:35:00" ><p>Question proposed: &quot;That section 6, as amended, stand part of the Bill&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.236" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="17:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800032#FF02600"><p>There is no provision for a redeployment appeals process.  Has the Minister considered this issue, given that appeals processes are provided for in collective agreements?  It would be sensible to provide for one.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.237" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1097" speakername="Brendan Howlin" time="17:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800032#FF02700"><p>I am not aware of a difficulty arising in the significant redeployment of staff to date.  I do not want to create a structure that will be so cumbersome that it will become unworkable.  Everybody who has moved, as Senator Denis Landy said, volunteered to do so.  They might not have been enthusiastic about it and might have preferred to stay put, but when agencies are closed or downsized, it is important to have flexibility for people to preserve their jobs and terms and conditions.  All of this is fully vindicated in the process we have set down.  I do not know whether there is a need to have another tier above this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.238" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="17:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800032#FF02800"><p>I did not table an amendment on this issue, but it is worth considering.  The original Croke Park agreement provided for an appeals process and stated, "Where a staff member wishes to appeal a redeployment decision, such an appeal will be managed by an agreed adjudicator who will reach a decision within the terms of the scheme within 21 days".  An appeals process should be a basic provision where there is compulsory redeployment.  It does not have to be administratively burdensome, but it would give staff protection if they are compulsorily designated for redeployment.  This will not arise in the context of the Haddington Road agreement, but we are including in statute something that will give the PAS huge power to move staff around.  While the PAS needs that power, employees need some level of protection.</p> <p>One protection is that redeployment would first be sought or advertised on a voluntary basis.  The 10,000 staff who left did so voluntarily.  There is an element that goes beyond that in the sense that there was no statutory basis.  Perhaps the process was not entirely voluntary but there was an appeals process.  There should be a very simple appeals process set out in the legislation to allow for a second look without turning the matter into an administrative burden or a gold-mining exercise or money-spinner, as occurred with certain appeals processes.  Essentially, the Public Appointments Service could just designate somebody having considered the matters that arise.  Perhaps there needs to be more provision for that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.240" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1097" speakername="Brendan Howlin" time="17:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800033#GG00200"><p>There is a slight misunderstanding of the purpose of the legislation.  I have two points to raise on this matter.  The Deputy quoted provisions in the Croke Park agreement on the appeals mechanism pertaining to redeployment.  There is a mirroring section in the Haddington Road agreement and that will be fully respected, but the Deputy has acknowledged that this will not arise in the context of that agreement between now and 2016.  The fundamental issue is that this Bill is to make statutory provision for redeployment, not to force redeployment; that is the difference.  It is to allow for redeployment to be legally undertaken and to have a proper structure for this to occur through the Public Appointments Service, respecting the agreements made on foot of the Haddington Road agreement for the coming years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.241" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="17:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800033#GG00300"><p>The Minister is playing with words slightly.  Section 57B of the original Act states:<blockquote><br />(1) The Public Appointments Service may designate an employee [&amp;#8230;] for redeployment [&amp;#8230;].<br />(2) Where a person who is designated under subsection (1) holds a position by virtue of a contract that is one for a definite period, he or she shall, on the redeployment day, be redeployed to such position [&amp;#8230;].</blockquote>It is stated designation shall be in writing.  The provision gives the power to designate.  It is not just a provision allowing for redeployment but a provision allowing for compulsory redeployment where it is not necessarily agreed.  I note the civil servants shaking their heads.  They Minister may correct me if what I contend is not the case.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.242" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1097" speakername="Brendan Howlin" time="17:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800033#GG00400"><p>It is not the case.  The Bill permits flexibility to be exercised.  The purpose of this simple and technical Bill is to remove the legal impediments that currently prevent reassignment across organisations other than by way of secondment.  For example, when F&Aacute;S moved into the Department of Social Protection, its employees were technically seconded.  F&Aacute;S was not legally moved.  Temporary secondment is not a proper way of restructuring the public service.  This legislation is an enabler to allow the restructuring to be made permanent, such that the employees of F&Aacute;S, for example, will be <i>de facto</i> employees of the Department of Social Protection.</p><p>  Where redeployment is not an option, there may be circumstances in which voluntary redundancy is an option.  That has happened.  In no circumstances are we looking towards compulsory redundancy.  That is an important point to make.  The legislation is not to force or require people to be redeployed but to enable redeployment to occur on a statutory basis.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.243" nospeaker="true" time="17:45:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.244" nospeaker="true" time="17:45:00" ><p>Sections 7 to 9, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.245" nospeaker="true" time="17:45:00" ><p>Schedule agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.246" nospeaker="true" time="17:45:00" ><p>Title agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.247" nospeaker="true" time="17:45:00" ><p>Bill reported with amendments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.248" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="17:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800033#GG00950"><p>When is it proposed to take Report Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.249" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1163" speakername="Tom Shehan" time="17:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800033#GG00975"><p>Next Tuesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.250" nospeaker="true" time="17:45:00" ><p>Report Stage ordered for Tuesday, 25 June 2013.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.251" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="17:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800033#GG01100"><p>When is it proposed to sit again?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.252" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Ca&iacute;t Keane" time="17:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800033#GG01200"><p>At 10.30 a.m. tomorrow morning.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.253" nospeaker="true" time="17:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800033#GG01300">Adjournment Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.254" nospeaker="true" time="17:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800033#GG01400">Departmental Investigations</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.255" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="17:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800033#GG01500"><p>A number of months ago, we raised an issue regarding a man who used to run a certain summer college.  He was also a teacher working with the VEC and worked with number of Irish language organisations.  There was a difficulty in that there have been allegations of child abuse made against him.  The Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Shatter, intimated approximately two months ago that there were to be three internal investigations, namely, one by the Garda, one in the Department of Education and Skills and the other in the HSE.  I raised this issue last week with the Minister and he told me that the ongoing Garda investigation was under his remit but that the one by the Department of Education and Skills was not.  I am now trying to ascertain the current position with regard to the Department of Education and Skills.  What are the terms of reference of the investigation being carried out by that Department?  How far back is the internal inquiry to go?  Some of the allegations of abuse date from 1955.</p> <p> A trial was initiated in respect of this individual, but it fell on several technical grounds.  That particular case related to victims who were in an educational setting.  As well as working in the Irish language organisation I mentioned, the perpetrator also worked as a teacher for a number of years and was involved in various educational initiatives.  It is important in this context to establish the scope and breadth of the internal investigation being conducted by the Department of Education and Skills.  I am in contact with several of this man's victims who are distraught by what happened to them and feel that because he passed away in recent months, they will never got justice.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.257" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1081" speakername="John Perry" time="17:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800034#HH00200"><p>I thank the Senator for affording me the opportunity, on behalf of my colleague, the Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy Ruair&iacute; Quinn, to clarify the position in respect of the matter raised.  The investigation conducted by the Department of Education and Skills relates to an analysis of files held in that Department.  This was done on foot of recent media reports concerning allegations of child abuse involving a former teacher and head of a summer college.  Under the Education Act 1998, the Department of Education and Skills provides funding and policy directions for schools.  Neither the Minister nor the Department has legal powers to investigate allegations of child abuse, statutory responsibility for which rests with the Health Service Executive and An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.</p><p>The media reports concerning allegations against the person in question are of great concern.  The Department has standard procedures in place for dealing with any allegations of child abuse that are brought to the attention of its staff.  Under these procedures, the Department does not make any judgment on the allegations brought to its attention but instead ensures that the details thereof are immediately passed on to the relevant investigatory authorities, including the school authorities, the HSE and An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  The analysis of records conducted by departmental officials shows one notification of concern regarding the individual in question, which was reported to the Department in 2012.  This was dealt with in accordance with the Department's procedures and reported at that time to the HSE and An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  No other record was found from the analysis of files in the Department.  Departmental officials are, however, in ongoing co-operation with the Garda's investigation into the matter.</p><p>In regard to child protection arrangements for primary and post-primary schools, the most recent update of these procedures was done in September 2011 in order to reflect the updating of the Children First national guidance published in July 2011.  These updated procedures incorporate significant improvements to the previous school guidelines and are intended to ensure consistent and uniform implementation of the Children First guidelines across all schools.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.258" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="17:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800034#HH00300"><p>I welcome the Minister of State's reply on behalf of the Minister for Education and Skills.  He indicated that there is only one confirmed report of a complaint against the individual in question.  I appreciate that this is not within the Minister of State's remit, but he might ask the Minister to confirm the scope of the departmental investigation.  One of the cases that was brought forward related to events in 1955.  Has the Department examined files from that far back to ensure there were no other complaints made against the individual in question?  Whatever information is there must be brought into the open.  Several of the individuals who contacted me are of the view that there might be complaints going back even further.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.259" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1081" speakername="John Perry" time="17:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800034#HH00400"><p>I will raise the Senator's concerns with the Minister and ask him to reply directly.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.260" nospeaker="true" time="17:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800034#HH00500">Primary Care Centres Provision</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.261" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1173" speakername="Lorraine Higgins" time="17:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800034#HH00600"><p>I thank the Minister of State, Deputy John Perry, for coming to the House to address an issue which is of great concern to people in Portumna, County Galway, and surrounding areas.  People in the town have been left without public health services since November 2012 as a consequence of a rat infestation in the health centre building.  This matter was brought to my attention at the time by concerned residents and I asked the Health Service Executive to investigate the claims.  The HSE responded immediately to inform me that steps were being taken to rectify the problem without delay.  I was assured that two surveys had been undertaken by a pest control company with the results showing that there was no rat activity in the health centre itself.  I was told, however, that the surveys did show some evidence of rat activity externally.  I understand the extermination company took all the necessary pest control measures at the time.</p><p>Staff and all services at Portumna were moved to Woodford health centre while the pest control company conducted further investigations into the centre in Portumna.  Clinical services which could not be undertaken at home were temporarily suspended, with an undertaking that they would resume once the health centre reopened.  I understand the staff were asked to return to Portumna in February 2013.  They objected to doing so given that floorboards which were removed from the property in the course of the investigation had revealed a nest of rats.  Nobody could blame them for refusing to work in such conditions, which represent a very significant health and safety issue not only to employees but also to service users.</p><p>The Portumna centre remains closed and residents continue to be deprived of the types of health services that are available in every town and village in Ireland.  There are reports that some public health nurses are working out of their cars.  Baby developmental checks, speech and language therapy and care of the elderly services are all being carried out at other health centre locations such as Woodford and elsewhere in east Galway.  The situation is entirely unsatisfactory.  Such is the depth of feeling on the issue the locals are planning to submit a petition to the HSE.  This issue has been going on for far too long.</p><p>Portumna, a town with a good-sized population and significant numbers living in the hinterland, has suffered greatly in recent times.  The burning down of the Shannon Oaks Hotel, for example, has led to significant job losses, as did the closure of ancillary businesses dependent on the hotel.  In addition, AIB has closed its branch in the town.  I implore the Department of Health to take action.  People in Portumna feel justifiably aggrieved at what essentially amounts to a downgrading of all local health services.  The HSE seems to have forgotten about them, some eight months after the problem of rat infestation at the health centre first emerged.  Action must be taken without delay.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.262" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1081" speakername="John Perry" time="17:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800034#HH00700"><p>I am taking this Adjournment matter on behalf of my colleague, the Minister for Health, Deputy James Reilly.  I welcome the opportunity to address the plans for the provision of primary care services in Portumna, County Galway, and in the wider context.  Portumna health centre is the main centre for the Portumna primary care team, which is situated in south-east Galway.  The team provides services to a population of 6,513 people.  There are several outlying smaller health centres in the area, including Woodford, Gurteen, Derrybrien and Tynagh.  Woodford health centre provides a full-time service, with the other locations providing storage facilities to support clinical services.</p><p>The health centre in Portumna is located on the outskirts of the town, close to the former workhouse and farm land.  The original building was built approximately 50 years ago and has telephone and fax facilities.  It has been closed since the end of 2012 following the discovery of rodent activity outside the centre.  The risk of such infestations are increased because of the location of the centre.  Owing to concerns raised, an extermination company was contracted and all areas treated.  The company has since confirmed in regular checks that the centre is now free from rodents.</p><p>Health Service Executive local management is in discussions with staff regarding the delivery of services from the health centre.  As the risk of rodent activity in the surrounding area continues, the HSE has examined all State assets locally to see whether a more suitable premises is available for utilisation us a health centre.  Unfortunately, no suitable location has been identified.</p> <p>The following services continue to be delivered to people within the Portumna area: public health nursing; physiotherapy, occupational therapy; speech and language therapy; social work; home help; and cardiac specialist services.  For the present, these services are provided from various suitable locations, with the public health nursing service being provided on a similar basis.  Local GPs operate from their own premises in the town.</p><p>The long-term accommodation needs for this area have been identified.  This area was advertised under the national primary care infrastructure programme, a suitable project was identified and a letter of intent was issued in 2009.  This is being reviewed at present, with a view to providing a modern purpose built health centre for the area.  The development of primary care is central to the Government's objective to deliver a high quality, integrated and cost effective health care system.  The HSE recognises that the Government's health reform programme places a new emphasis on developing the role of primary care within a universal health care system and as a consequence, progress in delivering the necessary infrastructure is a priority. </p><p>The development of primary care centres, through a combination of public and private investment will facilitate the delivery of multidisciplinary primary care and represent a tangible refocusing of the health service to deliver care in the most appropriate and lowest cost setting.  The primary care infrastructure model offers a good fit for private sector delivery.  The HSE is progressing the delivery of primary care infrastructure using three mechanisms, namely, HSE direct-build, operational leases, and public private partnerships.  Regardless of the method of delivery, locations cannot be progressed unless there is committed GP engagement.  Between May 2011 and May 2013, some 27 primary care centres opened.  This ongoing development of primary care centres continues to be an extremely important element of the Government's health reform process.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.264" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1173" speakername="Lorraine Higgins" time="18:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800035#JJ00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his response.  However, I am most dissatisfied with it.  There is a pressing need right now to provide health care services within Portumna and its surrounding area.  As the Minister of State mentioned, some 6,500 people want to avail of these services and it is not good enough to think that they are being ignored.  What will the people of Portumna and the surrounding area do until such time as a primary medical care centre is built?  The sense of abandonment of the people of Portumna is quite clear and the Minister and the Department of Health need to do something in the interim until the primary medical care centre is built.  There is no point in looking to the future when 6,500 people are looking for these services on a daily basis.  The issue is far more pressing than the Department realises.  I implore the Minister of State and the Minister to do something now on the issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.265" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1081" speakername="John Perry" time="18:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800035#JJ00300"><p>The good news is that a location for a new primary care facility has been identified.  Obviously, the buy-in to that from local GPs is important.  I reiterate that the HSE has examined all State assets locally.  I suggest the Senator should conduct a due diligence process in Portumna to see if a more suitable premises is available for utilisation as a health centre.  I would be astonished if there was not a suitable location in Portumna that would meet the needs of the HSE.  Therefore, I suggest that the Senator engages actively on the ground to see if she can recommend a suitable location and forward that to the Minister.  The Department is looking for a location, but no suitable location has yet been identified.  That astonishes me.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.266" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1173" speakername="Lorraine Higgins" time="18:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800035#JJ00400"><p>No more than the Minister of State, I am in the business of finding solutions.  Unfortunately, this is a long-term solution to a short-term problem.  Something needs to be done and more urgently than kicking the ball down the road until such time as a primary medical care centre is built or until such time as GPs come on board.</p><p>My door is open at any time to facilitate and help people in Portumna to ensure the project comes to fruition.  However, what are the people going to do in the meantime?  The Department needs to get real on this issue and do something quickly.  This is about exterminating rats and ensuring the facility is good enough to be used by people from the Portumna area.  Therefore, I implore the Minister of State again to pass the message on to the Minister and inform him something needs to be done urgently.</p><p>It is wonderful a primary medical care centre will be made available -----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.267" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="18:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800035#JJ00500"><p>We cannot get into a debate on the matter.  This is a matter on the Adjournment and the Senator has made her contribution.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.268" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1081" speakername="John Perry" time="18:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800035#JJ00600"><p>I suggest again that there is huge community involvement in Portumna and that this is a huge community regeneration project.  The Minister is prepared to facilitate the location of the facility in a suitable property.  With the amount of property that is now vacant in Portumna, I am certain there must be some location the Senator could suggest to the Minister on which agreement could be got from the HSE locally as a suitable location.  The Senator should nominate a suitable location.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.269" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1173" speakername="Lorraine Higgins" time="18:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800035#JJ00700"><p>I am aware the Minister is in talks with a private company in that regard.  However, what I need is a short-term solution for the people of Portumna.  I am not looking at a situation two or three years down the road.  I want to represent the people to the best of my ability.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.270" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="18:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800035#JJ00800"><p>The Minister of State will bring the Senator's message to the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.271" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1081" speakername="John Perry" time="18:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800035#JJ00900"><p>We cannot get something more short-term than that.  The Senator and the people of Portumna should come up with a location and inform the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.272" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1173" speakername="Lorraine Higgins" time="18:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800035#JJ01000"><p>A location has already been identified, but the problem is it is on a long-term basis.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.273" nospeaker="true" time="18:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800035#JJ01100">Mental Health Services Provision</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.274" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1154" speakername="Averil Power" time="18:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800035#JJ01200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House.  I am disappointed the Minister for Health, Deputy Reilly, is not here as this issue relates to his geographical area.  However, I ask the Minister of State to highlight the issues for the Minister on my behalf.</p><p>  The reason I have tabled this matter is the need to discuss the chaotic situation regarding mental health services in the north Dublin area.  This is the result of a major shortage of psychiatric beds, under-staffing and HSE policy regarding psychiatric referral.  Currently, there is a huge shortage of psychiatric beds in north Dublin.  We have the lowest ratio of psychiatric inpatient beds per head of population in the entire country, with just 13.5 per 100,000 people.  The Minister of State may be familiar with the area and be aware there are huge levels of social deprivation in the north Dublin area.  Demand is huge and is increasing daily, as it is in other parts of the country, due to the toll the recession is taking on people and the resulting mental health distress they suffer.</p><p>  As a result of the shortage of beds currently, patients with psychotic disorders have had to wait up to five days in accident and emergency units and medical wards and on trolleys in Beaumont in order to be admitted to hospital and provided with an inpatient bed.  This is both a result of the lack of sufficient inpatient beds and of a HSE policy that ensures the only way people can access the inpatient service is to go through accident and emergency units.  This is a disaster.  Instead of taking referrals straight into the inpatient service, as happened in the past, the policy now is that patients must go through accident and emergency services.</p><p>  As the Minister of State can imagine how distressing the situation is for people in significant mental distress or who may be suicidal to end up in a chaotic emergency department and to be stuck there for three or four days before they can get the proper mental health service they need.  This flies in the face of everything that should be in place.  A calm, supportive environment should be in place for patients with mental health problems the minute they try to access services.  They should not be put through accident and emergency services.  A new centre in Beaumont, the Aisling centre, is due to open later this year, but even when it opens, we will still have the second lowest ratio of inpatient mental health beds in the country.  This is unfair, particularly given the demographic make-up of the area and the extent of the need.</p><p>  I also want to raise another issue I hope the Minister of State will bring to the attention of the Minister, namely the crisis situation that also exists in the community mental health service.  I have here a letter that was returned to a GP who tried to refer one of his patients to the psychiatric service in Beaumont.  The hospital replied and said that the patient's difficulties were more appropriate to the community mental health team so the GP tried to get a referral through the community mental health service.  The response he got was:<blockquote>  I wish to acknowledge receipt of your primary care psychology referral for the following client [gives details] ...  Due to the moratorium on staff recruitment in Dublin North-East, we are regrettably unable to accept the above referral or any further primary care psychology referrals until further notice.</blockquote>The situation now is that the community mental health service in Dublin North is not even accepting referrals into the service, no matter what situation people are in. </p> <p>That is shocking and frightening, given the level of distress and pressure people are under.  I am sure that, like me, the Minister of State, Deputy John Perry, has been visited at his clinics by such persons.  It is frightening that a person with a mental health problem who wishes to access the service cannot do so.  It is regularly stated people must be encouraged to avail of support when they need it.  The people concerned want to avail of the service but cannot access it.  There is a crisis.  </p><p>I hope the Minister of State will indicate that some progress will be made on the issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.276" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1081" speakername="John Perry" time="18:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800036#KK00200"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this topic.  North Dublin mental health services provide a range of adult mental health services within the specialties of general psychiatry and psychiatry of old age and a rehabilitation psychiatry service within the settings of service user homes, acute in-patient facilities, day hospitals, day centres and supported community residences.  The delivery of services is guided by A Vision for Change which provides the strategic direction for the future delivery of mental health services and by the HSE national and Dublin north east service plans 2013 which set out national and regional priorities.  While implementation of A Vision for Change and the reform of mental health services are priorities for the Government, implementation of A Vision for Change has been somewhat slower than originally expected.  It has been delayed by a number of factors, including the changed economic context, constraints in public spending and the moratorium on recruitment.  Nonetheless, a great deal of progress has been made with the accelerated closure of old psychiatric hospitals and their replacement with bespoke new facilities better suited to modern mental health care.</p><p>  In 2012 a special allocation of &euro;35 million was provided for mental health services, primarily to further strengthen community mental health teams in adult and children's mental health services, to advance activities in the area of suicide prevention, to initiate the provision of psychological and counselling services in primary care, specifically for people with mental health problems, and to facilitate the relocation of mental health service users from institutional care to more independent living arrangements in their communities, in line with A Vision for Change<i>.  </i>Some 414 posts were approved to implement the &euro;35 million package of special measures which resulted in an additional 87 WTE posts<b></b>and an additional &euro;6 million was<b></b>provided for Dublin north east mental health services.</p><p>  Budget 2013 provided a further &euro;35 million for the continued development of mental health services and more than 470 additional staff will be recruited to implement these measures.  HSE Dublin North East has been allocated an additional 104.5 WTEs and almost &euro;7.3 million to progress the agreed objectives for the national service plan 2013 investment of &euro;35 million in mental health services.  I acknowledge that the service is operating within a challenging environment and faces a number of critical issues in relation to acute in-patient bed capacity, staffing resources and infrastructure.  However, the opening of the new 44 bed acute psychiatric unit at Beaumont Hospital later this year will assist greatly in alleviating the current capacity issues being experienced by the service.  The service has also recently benefited from the allocation of an additional 13 allied health professional posts as part of the mental health investment initiative to enhance the existing community mental health teams and is awaiting the appointment of 10.5 clinical nurse posts under the national clinical programme.  Also, three nurses are expected to commence on the graduate nursing programme in the next number of weeks.  </p><p>  It is acknowledged that the mental health service in north Dublin faces a number of challenges.  However, management and staff are working proactively to ensure these issues are addressed and an efficient and effective service is provided.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.277" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1154" speakername="Averil Power" time="18:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800036#KK00300"><p>I appreciate that the Minister of State is replying on behalf of the Minister for Health, Deputy James Reilly.  However, I am disappointed with the reply provided for him which does not reflect the reality on the ground.  While reference has been made to the additional posts allocated, they have been in the pipeline for some time and are not yet filled.  The reply does not reflect the urgency of the crisis in terms of the number of people seeking access on a daily basis to the service and who cannot get it.  It is cold comfort to them knowing that posts might eventually be filled.  I ask the Minister of State to bring the attention of the Minister for to the letter from the GP which I read which points out that despite the work in train, the harsh reality is that patients cannot access services and that the community health team is not taking on new referrals.  I ask that something be done about this immediately.  As stated, while it is welcome that additional beds are being provided, the number of beds in the area will still be the second lowest in the country.  Therefore, much more needs to be done.  This matter requires a far greater response than that provided by way of the Minister of State on behalf of the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.278" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1081" speakername="John Perry" time="18:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800036#KK00400"><p>I again thank the Senator for raising this important issue.  The Minister has allocated an additional &euro;35 million to mental health services in 2013 and a further 400 staff will be recruited.  As such, the Senator's concerns are being addressed.  I suggest she send a copy of the letter to which she referred directly to the Minister, with whom I will also raise the matter.  As stated, the Minister is aware of the difficulties in this regard.  The acute bed unit at Beaumont Hospital will greatly assist in addressing the problem.  The Government is aware of the pressure on people at this time.  Mental health and associated services provision is being accelerated by the HSE.  I will bring the Senator's concerns to the Minister's attention.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.279" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1154" speakername="Averil Power" time="18:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800036#KK00500"><p>That would be appreciated.  On the Minister of State's suggestion that I forward the letter to the Minister, I write to him weekly and the longest reply I have ever received is two lines.  As stated by many other Members in the past, everything is referred to the HSE which cannot reply because it is constrained from a policy point of view.  I would appreciate it if the Minister of State could use his good offices to raise the matter with the Minister directly.  A two line reply is as much as I ever receive on serious and important health issues.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.280" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1081" speakername="John Perry" time="18:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800036#KK00600"><p>I assure the Deputy that that will be done.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.281" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="18:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800036#KK00700"><p>I thank the Minister of State for dealing with the first three matters on the Adjournment.  I welcome the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Alan Shatter, to deal with the next matter.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.282" nospeaker="true" time="18:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800036#KK00800">Garda-PSNI Transfers</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.283" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Ca&iacute;t Keane" time="18:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800036#KK00900"><p>I also welcome the Minister.</p><p>  The Independent Commission on Policing for Northern Ireland was set up pursuant to the Good Friday Agreement signed in Belfast in 1998.  We are all familiar with the Patten report published by the commission in 1999 which contained 175 recommendations, nine of which related specifically to transfers between the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and the PSNI, with a further recommendation being that the issue of community balance at more senior ranks of the police service be addressed by lateral entry from other police forces.  The Patten agreement provides for three levels of personnel exchange: a programme of placements to transfer experience and expertise, including in the area of training; a programme for members of each police service to be seconded, with full police powers,<b></b>to the other police service for periods not exceeding three years, and that members of each police service be eligible for certain posts in the other police service.  I acknowledge the current co-operation between the PSNI and the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na on policing matters which was confirmed again yesterday at the British-Irish Parliamentary Assembly, BIPA, meeting on human trafficking which I attended.  </p><p>  I propose to concentrate on the transfer of personnel between the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and the Police Service of Northern Ireland.  While the legislation that underpinned the recommendations made in the Patten report is very positive, a number of practical issues arise which I will outline.  At the level of short-term exchanges, the Patten programme has proved reasonably successful.  This involves 84 garda&iacute; and 75 PSNI officers taking part in what is usually a four week exchange.  Garda officers on exchange to the PSNI remain subject to their own police regulations and have no police powers while in Northern Ireland.  This clearly is a major disadvantage to officers while serving in another jurisdiction.<b></b>The same applies to officers from Northern Ireland on exchange to the Republic.  Other practical issues arise in relation to insurance cover.<b></b> I have been told, by way of first-hand anecdotal evidence, that officers who transfer are effectively there as observers, with a view to increasing their personal-professional contacts and their understanding of issues relating to cross-Border criminal activity.  While this is good, they are effectively civilian observers.  I do not believe this could be classified as anything more than short-term work experience and time out from their own work.<br /><b></b>Longer term secondments of up to three years have proved less popular.<b></b>The PSNI only received one application<b></b>for a secondment in 2009, while An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na received none<b>.  </b>The previous Garda Commissioner, Mr. Fachtna Murphy, expressed his regret that the scheme was not working and indicated that he would assist the PSNI in reviewing the process.  Sir Hugh Orde was, however, sanguine about the absence of long-term secondments at the time.  In 2009 the PSNI decided to review the process rather than go ahead with the secondment.  In March 2010 Superintendent Paul Moran became the first and only officer of any rank from either An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na or the PSNI to take part in a secondment when he was seconded from An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na to the PSNI in Belfast for 18 months.</p> <p>In this secondment he wore the full uniform, had police powers and was permitted to carry a firearm.  He has since returned to An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  </p><p> Lateral entry or transfer between forces has proved somewhat harder to arrange, partly because of significant administrative difficulties.  For example, the difficulty of transferring pension entitlements - both State and occupational - across an international border has proved to be one of the most significant disincentives for individual officers to participate in  long-term movement between the forces.</p><p> The last 50:50 recruitment campaign to the PSNI ended in Northern Ireland in 2011.  From a small number of applicants from An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, one detective garda was accepted as a detective constable in the PSNI in March 2012.  It was necessary for him to resign from An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na to transfer to the PSNI and his pension was non-transferable and, therefore, frozen.  He had to begin paying into the UK police pension scheme.  However, I understand the transfer has been a hugely positive career development and he has been warmly received by colleagues in the PSNI.  However, the fact remains that there is a considerable financial disincentive in such a move by members of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  Any garda who wishes to transfer would also have the added instability of having to reapply for a post in An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na when his or her period of service in the PSNI ended.  The methodology for re-entry needs to be examined.</p><p> Speaking in Seanad &Eacute;ireann ten years ago, former Senator Maurice Hayes said:<blockquote>There is no point in laying down the legislation and making a provision if it is not taken up.  By and large, people will not take up positions unless they see them as being of some advantage to them, in terms of their career, career development and the rest of it.  At the very least, they should not lose money.  It is a sensible and general rule that when somebody is seconded, he or she is offered his or her existing terms and conditions.  There may also be a relocation allowance and an incentive for those separated from their families [This is the case for the PSNI, but it does not apply in the South]. </blockquote>Unfortunately, these points still ring true today as the position for garda&iacute; who wish to transfer to the PSNI for a period has not changed in so far as they are still at a financial disadvantage and also at a disadvantage when they wish to resume service in the Republic because they must reapply to obtain a post they held previously or apply for a new one altogether.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.285" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="18:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800037#LL00200"><p>The Senator should conclude.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.286" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Ca&iacute;t Keane" time="18:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800037#LL00300"><p>I have a few questions for the Minister.  Occasionally members of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na have gone to work with international organisations such as the International Criminal Tribunal for the Former Yugoslavia.  In these cases the members resigned with an option to reapply to An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na when they had completed their work.  Is the position similar for Garda members who choose to transfer between the Garda and the PSNI - that they must resign, their pension is frozen and they must apply to rejoin the force?  Clarification is necessary.  I would like to think the transfer and exchange of personnel between the two forces is something the Government is interested in promoting.  The Minister is only a short time in office, but he has introduced much reforming legislation.  I ask him to consider undertaking work on the transfer-exchange programme.  </p><p>I have another question for the Minister.  Does the Government have plans in the short or longer term to address the pension issue that acts as a disincentive in transfers between the forces?  Will consideration be given to offering incentives to members of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na to transfer to the PSNI for periods of up to three years?  This might be mutually beneficial.  Will the Minister consider allowing members of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na to assist the PSNI in policing events such as the recent G8 summit?  That is what was considered in the Patten agreement, but it is not being implemented.  It would provide garda&iacute; with invaluable training-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.287" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="18:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800037#LL00400"><p>The Senator is way over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.288" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Ca&iacute;t Keane" time="18:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800037#LL00500"><p>I have just one other question.  Former Senator Maurice Hayes raised an important issue ten years ago-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.289" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="18:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800037#LL00600"><p>The Senator has used up more than her time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.290" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Ca&iacute;t Keane" time="18:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800037#LL00700"><p>Just one more minute, please.  I refer to the attractive remuneration package which includes mortgage interest relief, travel costs and moving expenses.  The conditions under which a member may re-enter An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na should be written down.  Are officers who take a proactive approach and move to the PSNI likely to be punished for showing such initiative?  Does the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na promote the gaining of such experience as being desirable and an advantage?  Would a member who takes such an initiative be subject to the current moratorium on recruitment?  It is clear that the process, as envisaged, is not working.  I hope the Minister will encourage those at higher ranks to participate in the transfer programme.  Will we continue in the way we have done for the past 14 years?  It is ten years since former Senator Maurice Hayes raised the matter in the House and I hope the Minister will be able to do something about it in his term of office.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.291" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1025" speakername="Alan Shatter" time="18:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800037#LL00800"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this issue.  On 29 April 2002 the Irish and British Governments signed an agreement on police co-operation providing a framework for the implementation of certain Patten commission recommendations on enhanced police co-operation.  I am pleased to inform the House that all of the necessary administrative and legislative measures are in place to allow for implementation of these recommendations.  The legislative measures were set out in the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na (Police Co-operation) Act 2003 which, in turn, was incorporated into the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na Act 2005.  It is worth recalling that Article 1 of the recommendations deals with lateral entry, that Article 2 deals with secondments with police powers and that Article 5 deals with personnel exchanges without police powers.  Regulations under the Act were required to provide for lateral entry and these are now in place.  Regulations were not required for secondments and personnel exchanges.  The implementation of these articles continues to be a key measure towards improving the level of cross-community confidence in the impartiality of the criminal justice system.</p><p>  It was proposed that personnel provisions of the intergovernmental agreement would take place on an incremental basis, commencing with personnel exchanges without police powers, then secondments with police powers and, finally, lateral entry.  On 21 February 2005 the Garda Commissioner and the Chief Constable of the PSNI signed protocols which provided for the implementation of a programme of personnel exchanges and secondments between An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and the Police Service of Northern Ireland.  These protocols set out a framework for the operation of both personnel exchanges and secondments.  In practice, exchanges take place for periods of between one and two months, without the exercise of police powers in the host jurisdiction.</p><p>  A total of 89 members of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and 76 members of the Police Service of Northern Ireland have taken part in exchange programmes under the auspices of the protocols.  These programmes have been very successful, with exchanges taking place across the whole spectrum of policing areas, including training, human resources, general operational policing and specialist areas.  Outside the ambit of the formal agreement, training and education exchanges have also taken place between the Garda College and the PSNI in a number of areas, including the exchange of teacher-trainers, a senior investigation officers' course, public order training and a firearms instructors' course.  A joint diversity training programme took place involving personnel in the Border division and the PSNI.  Following on from discussions between An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and the Police Service of Northern Ireland, each exchange is now concluded with a comprehensive debriefing session involving representatives of both organisations and each participant in the exchange.</p><p>  The key difference between personnel exchanges and secondments is that members of either force who are seconded to the other force exercise full police powers in the host jurisdiction.  Under section 54 of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na Act 2005, the Commissioner may, on application by a member of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, arrange with the Chief Constable for the member's secondment to the PSNI for a period not exceeding three years.  As the Senator stated, one Garda superintendent was seconded to the PSNI from An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na for a period on 18 months in March 2010.  I understand this was a very successful secondment.  I very much hope there will be further such secondments, although they are, of course, subject to the operational exigencies of the two police services.  That said, it is important that the Patten commission recommendations are fully implemented.  I know that the Garda Commissioner is very committed to building on and enhancing cross-Border co-operation across all aspects of policing.  I must stress at this stage that any member of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na who participates in an exchange programme or takes up a secondment position with the PSNI does so in the full knowledge that his or her employment status within An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na remains completely intact.</p><p>  Turning to the issue of lateral entry, the intergovernmental agreement obliged both Governments to introduce the necessary administrative and legislative measures to enable members of one force to apply for posts at ranks of above inspector level in the other force.  Section 52 of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na Acts 2005 to 2007 provides for the implementation of these provisions for the appointment of members of the PSNI to ranks above inspector level in An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  In 2012 I introduced regulations, namely, the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na Act 2005 (Police Service of Northern Ireland Appointments) Regulations 2012 and the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na Act 2005 (Section 52) Regulations 2012, to give legal effect to the provisions mentioned.  By way of letter, dated 10 September 2012, the Chief Constable of the Police Service of Northern Ireland was notified of the holding of promotion competitions for the ranks of superintendent and chief superintendent in An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  Expressions of interest from members of the Police Service of Northern Ireland were received and subsequently two briefing sessions were held at the Garda College in Templemore in September 2012.  The appointments from this competition have been made and on this occasion did not include any member of the PSNI.</p><p>  Pension transfer is a particularly difficult issue that applies to all public sector workers moving between different jurisdictions.  There is no general provision for a transfer of pension benefit from one state to another.  In the case of lateral entry, where a member of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na resigns his or her position to join the PSNI, or <i>vice versa</i>, that member will retain pension entitlements which, in the case of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, would be due at age 60 and commence new pension payments with the PSNI.  There are certain circumstances where a member of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na who resigns from the force to take up employment with another police force or in the private sector may apply to the Commissioner to be reinstated.  In doing so, that person must be able to show the additional experience and skills set acquired outside the force will be of benefit to the force in the future.</p> <p>I have developed a close working relationship with my ministerial counterpart in Northern Ireland, David Ford, which is of great benefit in addressing matters of mutual concern and enhancing effective police and criminal justice co-operation.  Along with our officials, we will continue to address the operation of these personnel transfer and exchange arrangements to ensure they can be made as beneficial as is possible to the two police services and, indeed, to policing on this island.</p><p>In summarising my response to the points made by Senator Keane, I reiterate that mechanisms are in place for the orderly transfer of members, permanently or temporarily, between the PSNI and the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  I look forward to building on the progress which has been made in this regard.  I would have to say in response to the questions the Senator asked that of course there is no question of anyone being punished for taking an initiative.  It is a lot more simple and straightforward in the area of secondments.  Of course a direct lateral transfer will be much more complicated.  In effect, it involves someone ceasing to be a member of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and becoming a member of the PSNI.  I am determined to encourage the continued exchange of members between the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and the PSNI in the manner that has been successful to date.  The next time I meet Minister Ford, I intend to raise with him the further steps that might be taken to ensure the full intent and objective of what was previously agreed is actually working in practice.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.293" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Ca&iacute;t Keane" time="18:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800038#MM00200"><p>The Minister's final statement, about his intention to raise with his Northern Ireland counterpart the question of whether what was agreed is working in practice, was the best part of his reply.  As I said at the outset, it is not working in practice.  Just one member relocated in each of the years 2009-10 and 2012-13.  Why is this not working in practice?  There is a financial disincentive.  As Maurice Hayes said ten years ago, "People will not take up positions" in such circumstances.  That is one thing.  When the Minister referred to the uncertainty about having one's job guaranteed if one wishes to come back into the force, he said one must be able to show that the experience gained outside the force will be "of benefit to the force in the future".  I suppose there is a degree of uncertainty there.  The Minister also mentioned that when applications were received, no member of the PSNI took up the possibility of transferring down here for the purposes of promotion.  All I will say is that it is not working.  Actions speak louder than words.  The Minister might think it is working, given that one member transferred in each of 2009 and 2012, but I do not think it is.  It is definitely not what was envisaged.  I hope the Minister will encourage it.  I thank him for-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.294" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="18:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800038#MM00300"><p>Thank you, Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.295" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Ca&iacute;t Keane" time="18:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800038#MM00400"><p>I know my time is up, but I am not really satisfied.  If we want this to work, we could do something with pension arrangements.  The PSNI has-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.296" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="18:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800038#MM00500"><p>Senator, do I have to say it again?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.297" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Ca&iacute;t Keane" time="18:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800038#MM00600"><p>No.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.298" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="18:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800038#MM00700"><p>The Senator should not make a speech.  She is supposed to ask a question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.299" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Ca&iacute;t Keane" time="18:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800038#MM00800"><p>I am just asking the Minister about his intention to take this up with the PSNI.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.300" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="18:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800038#MM00900"><p>The Minister gave a very comprehensive reply.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.301" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Ca&iacute;t Keane" time="18:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800038#MM01000"><p>Financial and travel incentives are needed to encourage transfers to take place.  Ordinary, everyday things could be done to make it easier for people to advance North-South co-operation.  Basically, that is all we are looking for.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.302" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1025" speakername="Alan Shatter" time="18:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800038#MM01100"><p>The regulations I mentioned - the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na Act 2005 (Police Service of Northern Ireland Appointments) Regulations and the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na Act 2005 (Section 52) Regulations - were not made until 2012.  They have not been in place for a lengthy period of time.  They allow members of the PSNI to apply for promotions into the Garda.  We will have to wait and see how that works.</p><p>  The issue in this regard is that individual garda&iacute; cannot be compelled to make applications to transfer into the PSNI, and <i>vice versa</i>.  People choose their careers and have career paths.  In the current financial climate, I do not have the funding to provide additional financial incentives for people to transfer from the Garda to the PSNI.  As Minister for Justice and Equality, I have to try to ensure we have as many members in our police force as possible.  I am very happy to encourage the implementation of the intent of what was put in place.  I am happy to discuss it with Minister Ford.  I do not envisage that funding will be available to me to incentivise members of the Garda to apply for posts in the PSNI.</p><p>  The pension issue is not quite as complicated as it sounds.  If someone transfers from one force to the other, he or she retains the benefit of all the pension contributions he or she made in the force of which he or she was a member.  He or she will then start making additional pension contributions in the new force.  Obviously, an entitlement to certain pension payments would accumulate arising from that.  I have no doubt we will return to this issue on another occasion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.303" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Ca&iacute;t Keane" time="18:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800038#MM01200"><p>Will the Minister comment on the applications I mentioned?  The people in question were not qualified because they did not have a certain type of training.  That is why there were no transfers between the PSNI and the Garda at senior ranks.  I refer to the qualifications issue I was reading about.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.304" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1025" speakername="Alan Shatter" time="18:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800038#MM01300"><p>I am not familiar with the issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.305" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="18:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800038#MM01400"><p>If Senator Keane wishes, she can ask the Leader of the House to arrange a full debate on the matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.306" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Ca&iacute;t Keane" time="18:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013061800038#MM01500"><p>I hope we will not leave it ten years again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-06-18a.307" nospeaker="true" time="18:35:00" ><p>The Seanad adjourned at 7.15 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Wednesday, 19 June 2013.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>