<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.4" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#A00100">Teachtaireachtaí ón Dáil - Messages from Dáil</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#A00200"><p>D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann agreed, on 2 March 2022, to the amendments made by Seanad &Eacute;ireann to the Electricity Costs (Domestic Electricity Accounts) Emergency Measures Bill 2022.  D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann passed the Health (Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill 2022 on 2 March 2022, to which the agreement of Seanad &Eacute;ireann is desired.  D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann passed the Redundancy Payments (Amendment) Bill 2022 on 2 March 2022, to which the agreement of Seanad &Eacute;ireann is desired.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.7" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#A00300">Gnó an tSeanaid - Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.8" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#A00400"><p>I have received notice from Senator Sharon Keogan that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, she proposes to raise the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Defence to make a statement on the disposal of land held by the Defence Forces in the Stamullen and Gormanston areas of County Meath. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Barry Ward of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Health to make a statement on the differing rates of benefits available to medical card holders for wigs and hairpieces, depending on where a person lives, and the steps being taken to standardise these rates. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister of State with responsibility for heritage and electoral reform to outline the timeframe for holding a referendum on extending voting rights in presidential elections to Irish citizens outside the State. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Malcolm Byrne of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Further and Higher Education, Research, Innovation and Science to make a statement on Ireland&rsquo;s potential membership of European Council for Nuclear Research. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Maria Byrne of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Justice to make a statement on the barriers facing non-fluent English speakers in reporting sexual and gender-based violence. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Paul Gavan of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Foreign Affairs to make a statement on the war in Yemen. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Martin Conway of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Health to carry out a review of the Shannondoc out-of-hours GP service. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Garret Ahearn of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister of State with responsibility for heritage and electoral reform to amend the Wildlife Act 1976 to extend the period to burn vegetation from 1 March to April. </blockquote> <p>Of the matters raised by the Senators suitable for discussion, I have selected Senators Keogan, Ward, &Oacute; Donnghaile and Malcolm Byrne.  They will be taken now.  The other Senators may give notice of the matters they wish to raise on another day.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.9" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#A00412">Nithe i dtosach suíonna - Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.10" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#A00425">Defence Forces Properties</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#A00462"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Feighan, to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#A00500"><p>The Minister of State is very welcome.  I thank him for coming here to discuss this important matter for the residents of the Stamullen and Gormanston areas.  The Defence Forces currently own land of 261 acres in the Gormanston area, upon which Gormanston Camp is based.  The camp and the disused aerodrome occupy a certain portion of this land and much of the remaining land is leased for agricultural use.  The land to which I refer is filed under folio numbers MH11409N and MH6108N.  It was previously zoned for industrial use some years ago but remains unzoned since 2011.  What future plans does the Minister have for the land surrounding Gormanston Camp?  Will he consider the disposal of a portion of this land, approximately 8 to 9 acres, to the local community in order that it may develop community facilities?</p> <p>This Government has made considerable strides in the past two years to establish bodies and frameworks, such as the Land Development Agency, in order that public land may be used in the most efficient manner to serve the communities where it exists.  In the midst of a housing crisis, this often takes the form of housing.  We all understand, too, that dwellings alone do not make a sustainable environment or community and that facilities and amenities must also receive funding.</p> <p>If this parcel of land were to be placed under the remit of the local authority, it could be used to develop state-of-the-art football pitches for the local club of 360 members.  These children have been using the facilities and pitches at the Franciscan College, Gormanston, but, for reasons outside of their control, will no longer be able to do so from April.  Effectively, they have nowhere to go.  This land could provide them with pitches of their own to enable them to train and play freely and reach their full potential.</p> <p>In addition, the local area has been in need of a graveyard for some time.  A portion of this land could be set aside for this purpose and provide an essential service to the community.  Other plans for the area could incorporate child-friendly and family-friendly amenities, such as playgrounds, obstacle courses and fitness areas.  We know that such community facilities improve quality of life and mental health in our towns.</p> <p>Perhaps the Minister of State knows of some top-secret plans for this land, but cannot divulge them here.  If no such plans exist, will consideration be given to allowing the land to be used and developed for the projects I have in mind?<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Sharon Keogan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=SharonKeogan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=03"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> I would not ask the State for land if I could find land in those areas to serve the people whom I represent in the Gormanston-Stamullen area.  I have gone after every landowner and farm owner in the area asking them to sell some land to the community.  They just do not have any available.  There is no zoned land in Gormanston.  All of it was dezoned as part of the development plan, so there is nothing that can be sold for community use.  I am here today to ask the State whether it would consider disposing of some of the land in question for community use.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1608" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#B00200"><p>On behalf of my colleague, the Minister, Deputy Coveney, I thank the Senator for raising this important issue today.  Unfortunately, I wish to advise the House that there are no plans to dispose of any land held by the Defence Forces in the Stamullen and Gormanston areas to local authorities for </p> <p>The Minister and I fully appreciate the importance of local community groups and the outstanding work that they do across the country.  Indeed, the Defence Forces have a very proud tradition of working with such groups and, where possible, facilitating them.  I understand that there have been previous requests from a local community to access these lands and that officials in the Department set out the difficulties with accessing operational military areas.  The use of this military facility has grown recently for training purposes and this level of usage can be expected to continue in the coming years.  I understand this request was considered at the most senior levels within the Defence Forces and the Department but, regrettably, it was not possible facilitate the requested access for the reasons I have mentioned.</p> <p>While the Defence Forces engage with numerous community organisations across the country and make their premises and facilities available to local groups when possible, military landholdings should not be viewed as a resource to be handed over for civilian use whenever requested.  These are military sites for military activities, and this should always be borne in mind.  Apart from any future requirement, it is vital that the Defence Forces have access to land and facilities at present where they can train and engage in manoeuvres to ensure operational readiness and their ability to carry out tasks assigned to them by the Government.</p> <p>I thank the Senator for raising the specific issue of lands in the Stamullen and Gormanston areas today and, on behalf of the Minister, I assure the House that the Defence Forces will continue the positive community engagements that happen all over the country on a regular basis.</p> <p>The Senator raised an important issue regarding football pitches in her area and the fact that the lands at Franciscan College Gormanston are not available to them for some reason.  She also referred to child- and family-friendly situations and the provision of a graveyard.  She has made a compelling argument and I have no problem with her writing in to express her views.  I will bring them to the attention of the Minister.  The Senator said there were 270 acres and that she was looking for 5 or 6 acres.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#B00300"><p>There are 261 acres.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1608" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#B00400"><p>I will bring that back to the Minister.  This matter has been discussed at the highest level in the Defence Forces.  Unfortunately, I do not have good news for the Senator, but in light of the issues she has raised and the fact that no lands are available under the development plan, perhaps we could ask the Defence Forces to consider this matter again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#B00500"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  I am disappointed by the answer, though.  The State has 261 acres and only 50 acres are being used for military training currently, so losing 5 to 6 acres would not make any difference to it, but it would make a major difference to the community.</p> <p>The Franciscans sold their site for the development of a new school.  This means that the soccer club has to get off the site in April.  The club is paying &euro;20,000 per year to use that facility.  It has the capacity to buy land but there is nothing for sale.  The State has the only land that I can go after.  I would like to meet someone in the Department who could consider whether there is a portion of land that could be given to the community.  I would be happy to sit down with that person and with the local authority to explore the possibilities.  If we cannot do that, then fine, but if we could sit down and explore the matter, we might find a portion of land that could be of use to the community.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1608" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#B00600"><p>I was involved in buying a soccer pitch in my town of Boyle in the late 1980s and I know the use that has been made of it over the past 35 years.  It was money well spent, so I understand the Senator's position.</p> <p>She requested a meeting with the Department.  It is not my Department, but if she writes to the Minister, we can pursue that request.</p> <p>I restate my support for the excellent work being carried out by local community groups throughout the country.  The Defence Forces make time and facilities available to local groups where possible, but they must also consider their operational requirements.  Unfortunately, it is not always possible to accommodate within the role and requirements of the Defence Forces requests from communities to access lands.</p> <p>I ask that the Senator write in and seek a meeting.  I would love to see there being some mechanism whereby the local community could access those lands.  I have seen myself how important such activities can be.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.19" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#B00700">Medical Aids and Appliances</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" speakername="Barry Ward" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#B00800"><p>I thank the Minister of State for attending the Chamber.  This is an issue for many people around the country.  As he will be aware, hair loss is not an uncommon thing in men and women.  It can be caused by a variety of medical conditions, including cancer treatments that result in hair loss, alopecia and so on.  Thankfully, the State has in place measures to help the many people who want to obtain wigs or hairpieces to cover their hair loss, make themselves feel more comfortable or whatever it might be.</p> <p>We had progress in this area recently when the Minister for Social Protection, Deputy Humphreys, put in place a &euro;500 grant for people suffering alopecia to allow them to obtain hairpieces or wigs.  Previously, there was no support for them at all; support was only provided for cancer sufferers.  As the Minister of State will be aware, cancer sufferers usually avail of a medical card service.  Through that, there is a grant to allow them to purchase a hairpiece or wig.</p> <p>This issue has been brought to my attention by Mr. Aidan Fitzgerald, a hair salon owner in Blackrock in my area.  Mr. Fitzgerald is an award-winning salon owner who has been operating for more than 40 years and has an established business.  As part of his work, he specialises in hairpieces and wigs.  He brings them into the country and fits them to people to make sure they fit and suit because hair comes in all shapes and sizes.  These wigs are not made in Ireland, so they have to be imported.  I understand that, generally, they are made in China.  They take different forms, in that there are synthetic wigs and wigs made of real hair that have been donated, and there are different types of wig depending on whether someone is European, Asian, African or whatever.  The wig has to be specific.  Synthetic wigs are slightly cheaper but many people who have been suffering long-term hair loss prefer to have wigs made of natural hair, which have to be imported.  No wigs are made in Ireland, although there are charities in Ireland that deal with hair for the construction of wigs.</p> <p>The difficulty that arises is that, because wigs have to be imported, there is a standard cost.  Many of them come through the UK but, either way, VAT and duties have to be paid on them.  The grants that are available through the medical card scheme are there to assist people.  I understand that the costs range from &euro;650 to &euro;750 for a synthetic wig and from &euro;1,000 to &euro;1,500 for a real wig.  Obviously, various factors affect the cost.  People can also get bespoke wigs, but those cost approximately &euro;3,000.  Generally, such wigs are not chosen by cancer sufferers because their hair will often have grown back by the time the wigs have been made.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Barry Ward:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=BarryWard&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=03"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The medical card scheme, however, puts in place a regime that allows people to claim different sums depending on where they are in the country.  In my area, Dublin, for example, the grant under the medical card ranges from &euro;635 to &euro;700, which does not cover the full cost, very often, although it is a substantial contribution to the cost.  In Carlow or Kilkenny, by contrast, that grant is &euro;440, while in Tipperary, it is &euro;500.  In Cork, it is &euro;450; in Clare, &euro;500; and in the Naas area, for some reason, &euro;767.  There seems to be a terrible discrepancy here.  Aidan told me that yesterday, he fitted a wig for a lady from Wicklow and she got a grant of &euro;650, whereas a lady from Wexford in the same day only got &euro;440.</p><p>There is no good reason for this.  The wigs are not made locally and they cannot be bought locally, so they are bought in.  There seems to be no good reason there cannot be a standardised grant for people who, in this instance, are mostly cancer sufferers, given that alopecia sufferers do not avail of this grant.  Cancer sufferers throughout the country should get the same sum from the medical card scheme.  They should all get the same access to wigs and hairpieces.  It is an important part of their ability to deal with whatever they are going through during treatment and so on, and it is important they be allowed equal access to the grant.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1608" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#C00200"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this important issue and for giving me, on behalf of the Minister for Health, the opportunity to clarify the position on the provision of wigs and hairpieces by the Health Service Executive under community-funded schemes.  The HSE provides many aids and appliances through its community services and it endeavours to meet needs in an equitable way within available resources and given the many demands.  The provision of wigs and hairpieces by the HSE to patients who are being, or have been, treated for cancer or other illnesses is operated by means of a grant or voucher system administered by the community healthcare organisations.  Patients can select their preferred wig or hairpiece and the HSE refunds the service user or the service provider up to the value of the voucher issued.</p> <p>The HSE established a community-funded schemes service improvement programme to standardise the HSE provision of aids, appliances and related items in order that, irrespective of where someone lives, he or she will have access to the same items as people in other parts of the country.  The HSE established an expert group for post-mastectomy products, wigs and hairpieces whose work includes a review of the provision of wigs and hairpieces. The expert group is a sub-group of the aids and appliances work stream of the community-funded schemes service improvement programme. The expert group comprises clinicians and operational staff.  It engaged in consultation with service users, including participation in focus groups.  It noted significant variations in what is currently provided, including in regard to current allowances for wigs and hairpieces.</p> <p>The expert group made initial proposals in 2019 for the development of guidelines by the Health Service Executive to standardise the grants paid.  The work of the expert group was delayed due to the Covid-19 pandemic because clinical staff were redeployed to deal with the demands of the public health crisis.  However, in 2021, the expert group furnished a draft summary of proposed national guidelines for the provision of wigs and hairpieces and of post-mastectomy products.  The finalisation and implementation of these guidelines in 2022 should address the inequity of provision on a geographic basis, which has been a problem for many years.  In addition, the standardised provision that has been recommended should ensure the approval process and the associated administration will be simpler to operate.</p> <p>The HSE recognises that the Covid-19 pandemic has created added difficulty for cancer patients, including through the absence of a facility for wig fittings.  To address this difficulty, the HSE put in place a temporary measure whereby each patient affected by the absence of wig fittings is provided with additional funding of &euro;80 to facilitate the purchase of up to two items of headwear.  I commend the HSE on introducing additional measures to support cancer patients.  It is essential that such patients are not subjected to any additional worry or stress at what is a very difficult time for them.  I wish to see the implementation of the new national guidelines for the provision of wigs and hairpieces as quickly as possible.</p> <p>I again thank the Senator for raising the issue.  It looks as though much work is ongoing and I hope the issue will be dealt with as quickly as possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" speakername="Barry Ward" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#C00300"><p>I appreciate that the Minister of State acknowledged there is inequity of provision on a geographic basis.  To my mind, there should not be.  We have made progress in respect of alopecia sufferers, who previously had no relief, but it is important people who are suffering from hair loss for whatever reason have the option to obtain a hairpiece or wig that will help them deal with the issues they have to deal with.  I appreciate also what the Minister of State said about the need for the implementation of the new national guidelines as quickly as possible.  Those who suffer from hair loss need solutions and we should help them, irrespective of the reason for that hair loss.</p> <p>I applaud what the Minister of State said and I look forward to the implementation of the guidelines in short course.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1608" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#C00400"><p>I again thank the Senator for raising this important issue.  The HSE is working to standardise the grants available for wigs and hairpieces.  Based on the work done to date, an expert group has made a proposal for the development of guidelines by the HSE to standardise the grants paid.  The Senator is absolutely correct that it just does not add up that somebody in Wexford would get &euro;200 less than someone in Dublin.  As I said, while the finalisation of the guidelines was delayed by the Covid-19 pandemic, much significant work has been done and improvements have been introduced in a number of areas.</p> <p>In particular, I welcome the interim measures introduced by the HSE whereby each person affected by the absence of wig fittings is to be provided with additional funding of &euro;80 to facilitate the purchase of up to two items of headwear.  I hope this measure will be of assistance to patients who have experienced additional difficulties caused by the Covid-19 pandemic.  The HSE expects to finalise and implement the new guidelines in mid-2022.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.25" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#C00500">Presidential Elections</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1688" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#C00600"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it.  T&aacute; a fhios agam gur &aacute;bhar &eacute; seo ina bhfuil sp&eacute;is aige.  T&aacute; a fhios aige gur &aacute;bhar &eacute; at&aacute;imse ag ard&uacute; le tr&eacute;imhse mhaith anuas.</p> <p>I welcome the Minister of State.  I am glad he is taking this Commencement matter because I know it will be of great interest to him personally.  He will know and recall from his time in the Seanad that it is an issue I have been raising consistently.  I last raised it as a Commencement matter with the then Minister of State with responsibility for the diaspora in 2020 when, as we all understand, we were in a very different climate.  We were not in a position whereby a referendum could be held, given the health restrictions that were in place.</p> <p>As we head into the St. Patrick's Day celebrations and as Ministers prepare to travel around the world to rightly engage with our diaspora, following the commitment from the Government that no citizens in the North would be left behind, this is a crucial and opportune time for the Government to outline the timeframe for this referendum.  At the time of my previous Commencement matter on the issue, I outlined all the substantial steps going back many years relating to this issue.  I outlined the fact it had been committed to and agreed to at a constitutional convention, the fact the legislation had been published but fell during the previous Oireachtas, and the fact it was then reissued, republished and returned to the Order Paper.</p> <p>All that preparatory work has been done.  We all agree, as parties and groups, that we value our diaspora and that Irish citizens in the North should have full citizenship rights.  One of the most basic rights and entitlements of any citizen is the right to vote.  The President is not the president of a land mass, as he recently articulated very eloquently.  He is President of the Irish people, so it is only right that all Irish people would have the entitlement and the right to vote.</p> <p>I look forward to the Minister of State's response.  We need to hear a timeline and what tangible actions the Government will take to implement this non-contentious commitment which was in the programme for Government.  All we are asking for is to ensure our fellow citizens have a say, whether they are part of our global diaspora family or our fellow citizens just up the road in the Six Counties.</p> <p>Deputy Frankie Feighan: I thank Senator Ward for raising this important issue, and for giving me, on behalf of the Minister for Health, the opportunity to clari$' the position in relation to the provision of wigs and hairpieces by the Health Service Executive (HSE) under the community funded schemes. The HSE provides many aids and appliances through its community services and endeavours to meet needs in an equitable way within available resources and given the many demands. The provision of wigs and hairpieces by the HSE to patients who are being or have been treated for cancer and Other illnesses is operated by means of a grant or voucher system administered by the Community Healthcare Organisations or CHOs. Patients can select their preferred wig or hairpiece and the HSE refunds the service user or the service provider up to the value of the voucher issued. The HSE established a Community Funded Schemes Service Improvement Programme in order to standardise HSE provision of aids, appliances and related items, so that irrespective of where someone lives, they have access to the same items as people in other parts of the country. The HSE established an Expert Group for Post-Mastectomy Products, Wigs and Hairpieces whose work includes a review of the provision of wigs and hairpieces. The Expert Group is a sub-group of the Aids &amp;amp; Appliances work-stream of the Community Funded Schemes Service Improvement Programme. Page 12 The Expert Group comprises clinicians and operational staff. It engaged in consultation with service users, including participation in focus groups. It noted significant variations in what is currently provided, including current allowances for wigs and hairpieces. The Expert Group made initial proposals in 2019 for the development of guidelines by the Health Service Executive to standardise the grants paid. The work of the Expert Group was delayed due to the Covid-19 pandemic, as clinical staff were redeployed to deal with the demands of the public health crisis. However, in 2021, the Expert Group furnished a draft summary of proposed national guidelines for the provision ofwigs and hairpieces and for the provision of post mastectomy products. The finalisation and implementation of these guidelines in 2022 should address the inequity of provision on a geographic basis that has been a real problem for many years now. In addition, the standardised provision recommended ensures that the approval process and the associated administration should be simpler to operate. The HSE recognises that the Covid-19 pandemic has created added difficulty for cancer patients, including the absence of a facility for wig fittings. To address this difficulty the HSE put in place a temporary measure whereby each patient affected by the absence of wig fittings is being provided with additional funding of &euro;80 to facilitate the purchase of up to two pieces of headwear. I wish to commend the HSE for introducing additional measures to support cancer patients. It is essential that such patients are not subjected to any additional worry or stress at what is a very difficult time for them. Finally, I wish to see the implementation of the new national guidelines for the provision of wigs and hairpieces as quickly as possible. ENDS<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2477"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2477&amp;amp;pid=NiallODonnghaile&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=03"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I look forward to the Minister of State's response.  Crucially, I look forward to working with Government colleagues and colleagues right across this House, and the other House, because it will need a positive, collaborative sentiment and work similar to that we have seen come about in recent referendums held in this State.  It will require us to put our shoulder to the wheel to make sure this is won and ensure that we say to citizens who do not currently have a vote in presidential elections that we value them, they are equal and this is a small but important step forward in ensuring they have full rights as citizens.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#D00200"><p>I thank Senator &Oacute; Donnghaile for finishing well within his time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1608" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#D00300"><p>I thank my good friend and colleague, Senator &Oacute; Donnghaile, for raising this important issue.  He raised it on many occasions during my time in the Seanad.</p> <p>In response to the evolving needs of Irish society and its relationship with the wider Irish diaspora, the previous Government agreed in March 2017 to accept in principle the main recommendation in the fifth report of the Convention on the Constitution that Irish citizens resident outside the State, including citizens resident in Northern Ireland, should have the right to vote at presidential elections and that a referendum would be held to seek to amend the Constitution to give effect to this.</p> <p>To inform public discourse on this significant policy change, on 22 March 2017, an options paper was jointly published by the Department of Housing, Local Government and Heritage and the Department of Foreign Affairs.  The options paper set out a broad range of options for the extension of voting rights, international comparisons, the estimated costs involved and related resource issues as well as many of the legal, policy, administrative and logistical challenges associated with extending voting rights to Irish citizens resident outside the State.  The options paper provided a basis for the discussion on voting rights, which took place at the Global Irish Civic Forum in Dublin on 5 May 2017.  It remains available to view or download on the Government's website.</p> <p>The Department of Housing, Local Government and Heritage and the Department of Foreign Affairs have continued to work closely on this issue, and on 16 September 2019, the Thirty-ninth Amendment of the Constitution (Presidential Elections) Bill 2019 was initiated in D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann by the then Minister for Foreign Affairs to facilitate the holding of a referendum on this important issue.  The Bill provides for amendments to Article 12 of the Constitution which, if passed by the people in a referendum, would extend the right to vote for the Office of President to all citizens, irrespective of where they may reside, for elections held on or after 1 January 2025, which would be the beginning of the year in which the next scheduled election for the Office of President would fall due.</p> <p>The Programme for Government: Our Shared Future commits to holding a referendum on extending the franchise at presidential elections to Irish citizens resident outside of the State.  While the Thirty-ninth Amendment of the Constitution (Presidential Elections) Bill 2019 lapsed with the dissolution of the 32nd D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann, in support of the Government commitment, the Bill was restored to the D&aacute;il Order Paper in the summer of 2020.  The restoration of the Bill will also support the commitment in Global Ireland: Ireland's Diaspora Strategy 2020-2025, published by the Department of Foreign Affairs on 19 November 2020, to hold a referendum on this matter.  When the Bill, which is sponsored by the Minister for Foreign Affairs, is passed by both Houses of the Oireachtas, section 10 of the Referendum Act 1994 requires the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage to make an order appointing the day upon which the poll for the proposed referendum will take place.  The Act provides that the polling day shall be not less than 30 days and not more than 90 days after the date of the order.</p> <p>I again thank Senator &Oacute; Donnghaile for raising this issue.  It is one he has championed over the years, and I thank him for that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1688" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#D00400"><p>Gabhaim bu&iacute;ochas leis an Aire St&aacute;it as an fhreagra cuimsitheach.  I thank the Minister of State for outlining some of the technical detail involved.  I note the important fact that the Minister for Foreign Affairs will be sponsoring the legislation going through both Houses.  It is important that we have a key person, an anchor that can be identified and with whom we can work.</p> <p>I appreciate that this is not the Minister of State's brief.  I say this respectfully because the matter does not relate to his Department.  The answer outlined to me today is almost identical to the one I got in November 2020.  What we need to know is, crucially, when the referendum Bill will come before the Houses.  When will the legislation be initiated?  Will it be before the summer recess, for example?  Will the Bill at least begin its journey?  We know that we are dealing with substantial legislation currently, but it is incumbent on the Government to ensure it carves out the necessary time in the D&aacute;il and Seanad.  The Government will find the Seanad very willing to engage with it and to ensure the legislation is passed speedily.  As the Minister of State says, the Bill is succinct.  It is simple in what it is trying to do.  We, collectively, should know we have a date to work towards to ensure the referendum is won.  If the Minister of State is in a position, I ask him to tell us when it is anticipated that the referendum Bill will be initiated and brought through the Houses.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1608" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#D00500"><p>Again, I do not have that detail, but I will bring the Senator's views back to the Minister.  The Department of Housing, Local Government and Heritage and the Department of Foreign Affairs have worked closely on this issue.  They have agreed to facilitate the holding of a referendum on this important issue.  If passed by the people in a referendum, it would extend the right to vote for the Office of President to all citizens, irrespective of where they reside when an election is held on or after 1 January 2025, the year in which the next scheduled election for the Office of President falls due.  I accept that Senator &Oacute; Donnghaile wants to see the Bill before the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1688" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#D00600"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1608" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#D00700"><p>I appreciate the urgency and I will bring the Senator's views to the Minister.  I thank him for raising this issue because we would like to see a situation whereby wherever green is worn, as it were, across the world every Irish citizen would have a franchise to elect the President.  I understand the logistics but the sentiment is shared by us all.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#D00800"><p>I thank the Minister of State and Senator &Oacute; Donnghaile for that interesting Commencement matter.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.35" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#D00900">International Programmes</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1638" speakername="Malcolm Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#D01000"><p>I thank the Minister of State, Deputy Feighan, for taking this matter.  He will be aware that the European Organization for Nuclear Research, CERN, was established in 1954 as an international collaboration to advance human knowledge.  The latest estimate is that more than 16,000 scientists from more than 110 countries have been engaged in CERN's activities.  It is the world's leading particle physics laboratory and is an incredible engineering and IT project.</p> <p>During the entire Covid process we have learned about how international co-operation is crucial for us to be able to tackle some of the global challenges.  It is unfortunate that Ireland is not a member of one of the world's leading scientific laboratories, if not the world's leading one.  Malta and Ireland are the only members of the European Union that are neither members nor associate members.  The Minister of State will be aware that in 2016 there were discussions on starting membership.  In November 2019, the Joint Committee on Enterprise, Trade and Employment stated  there should be immediate plans for us to become members of CERN.  Ireland's foreign policy has always been based on international collaboration.  We pride ourselves on working with other countries to be able to solve some of the world&rsquo;s problems.  This is what CERN has been doing.</p> <p>Many people heard about the Higgs boson in 2012 and read in 2013 how CERN had won the Nobel prize for physics, but CERN is also responsible for things that make big differences in our daily lives.  It was responsible for the Internet, good and bad as it is.  CERN was ultimately responsible for touch screens.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Malcolm Byrne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;MemberID=1111"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1111&amp;amp;pid=MalcolmByrne&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=03"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->As a Minister of State in the Department of Health, Deputy Feighan will be aware that CERN was responsible for medical positron emission tomography, PET, scans, which allow for early detection of cancer, heart disease and brain disorders.  The research that was done in CERN contributed to all of that.</p><p>There have been many reports and calls for Ireland to join CERN and yet it has not happened.  I am asking for a clear timetable on Ireland's membership of CERN.  For those involved in the scientific research community, it is important we send that message.  It also sends a message about Ireland's fundamental belief that we want to contribute to solving global problems.  We believe in science and understand the importance of scientific research.  I hope the Minister of State will deliver at the very least a clear pathway for Ireland's associate membership.  I hope we will enter into full membership of the organisation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1608" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#E00200"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this issue.  Innovation 2020, the national strategy for research and innovation, recognises that for Ireland to become a global innovation leader, our research and innovation system must be open with strong international collaboration links.  Membership of leading international research organisations is an important mechanism for facilitating this engagement.  It is particularly important for Ireland as a small county due to the resource-intensive nature of cutting-edge research.</p> <p>For this reason, the Government gave a specific commitment in Innovation 2020 to initiate discussions with several international research organisations.  Four organisations were identified, namely, CERN, the European Southern Observatory, ELIXIR and LOFAR, and membership of three of these organisations has been completed.  Ireland continues its consideration of CERN membership.  These organisations were identified on the basis of a 2015 study that reviewed the costs and benefits of Ireland's existing and potential independent research organisation memberships.</p> <p>Under the National Development Plan 2018-2027, as part of Project Ireland 2040, the Government outlined its intention to review Ireland's membership of CERN.  In November 2019, the cross-party report by the Joint Committee on Business, Enterprise and Innovation recommended that negotiations start with CERN immediately with a view to Ireland becoming an associate member as soon as possible.  This would generate opportunities not only for Irish enterprise but also for its research community.</p> <p>While the benefits of CERN membership are recognised as significant, the cost is also significant and must be assessed in the context of other departmental and national investment priorities.  Based on indications received from CERN, the eventual cost of Ireland's full membership at 2021 prices would be circa &euro;13.4 million annually.  To become a full member, a country must go through an obligatory associate membership in the pre-stage to membership phase for a minimum of two years and maximum of five years.  In addition to the annual full membership cost there is a special contribution fee calculated as 1.25 times the cost of the full membership fee.  Based on a cost of &euro;13.5 million at 2021 prices, this would mean an amount of &euro;16.8 million would be due on the day a state becomes a full member.  There are, however, options for the payment of this special contribution.  It may be paid over a defined period, possibly ten years, and 20% of this contribution may be paid via in-kind contributions.  An associate membership fee of a minimum of &euro;1.34 million per annum is also possible, based on 10% of full membership cost.  An associate membership at a higher percentage of the full membership cost is also possible.  In the case of associate membership, the return to Ireland would be capped at the same level as the amount invested.</p> <p>I acknowledge there are a lot of numbers in my response.  Following the establishment of the new Department of Further and Higher Education, Research, Innovation and Science, under the Minister, Deputy Harris, CERN membership will be considered in the context of the programme for Government and competing national investment priorities.  Ireland continues its consideration of full and associate CERN membership and the Department of Further and Higher Education, Research, Innovation and Science remains in active regular contact with CERN officials regarding the membership options for Ireland and the associated costs.</p> <p>The Senator wanted a clear timetable.  He believes in science.  I am not involved in the figures I have mentioned but I think, given we have joined the three organisations I mentioned, the Senator has made a compelling argument for consideration of joining CERN.  There are a lot of figures here that raise competing arguments.  I will not go so far as to say those numbers are working against the Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1638" speakername="Malcolm Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#E00300"><p>Listening to the reply that has been prepared for the Minister of State, I am reminded of the Oscar Wilde description of a cynic as somebody who knows the price of everything but the value of nothing.  It is clear the Minister of State's response has been written by an accountant.  It has not been written by somebody who appreciates the value of research.  The Minister of State will appreciate, especially in the context of the battle against Covid-19, the importance of international collaboration in the area of research.  I am not saying the figures the Minister of State has outlined are insignificant but there is considerable potential in terms of what Ireland can gain for its research community and what it can contribute.  Ireland should be to the fore in contributing to the international scientific community.  We have some wonderful researchers here.</p> <p>I respect that there has been progress, but the issue I have is that we have been talking about this for the past decade.  We indicated our intentions clearly in 2016.  An Oireachtas committee recommended membership in 2019.  I ask the Minister of State to please get on with it.  Let us join CERN and allow Ireland's researchers to contribute at an international level to the scientific community.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1608" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#E00400"><p>As the Senator knows, the reply I delivered is not from my Department.  The Senator spoke about knowing the price of everything, but the relevant Department values research and international collaboration.  We saw how important that is during the pandemic.  Ireland, as a progressive country, should be able to take its place at the forefront of what is happening around the world.  As I said, four organisations were identified, namely, CERN, the European Southern Observatory, ELIXIR and LOFAR, and membership of three of these organisations has been completed.  Ireland is continuing its consideration of CERN membership.  I suspect there are some difficulties regarding costs or something like that.  I suspect negotiations are ongoing.  I thank the Senator for raising this important issue.  I think negotiations in terms of costs are ongoing.  I will bear in mind the Senator's comments about Oscar Wilde's definition.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#E00500"><p>I thank the Minister of State for taking all four Commencement matters, only one of which related to the Department of Health.  All Senators appreciate his attendance and replies and the time he has spent with us.  I thank Senators Malcolm Byrne, &Oacute; Donnghaile, Ward and Keogan.  I also thank the administrative staff and ushers for always being helpful during these sessions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.42" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar fionra&iacute; ar 11.18 a.m. agus cuireadh t&uacute;s leis ar&iacute;s ar 12.06 p.m.

Sitting suspended at 11.18 a.m. and resumed at 12.06 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.43" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#K00100">Gnó an tSeanaid - Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#K00200"><p>I thank Senator Sherlock for standing up when I entered the room.  That only happens when I go home and at the start of the day on Commencement matters.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1683" speakername="Marie Sherlock" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#K00300"><p>It is just good manners.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#K00400"><p>I welcome our colleague and friend, the ambassador from Bulgaria to mark their national day.  We were discussing the situation in Ukraine earlier.  As of yesterday, 8,000 citizens from Ukraine were in Bulgaria seeking refuge.  During its war of independence, many Ukrainians helped them.  The wheel does turn.</p><p>Bulgaria's national day is 3 March.  It marks the date of national liberation and restoration of the Bulgarian state after nearly five centuries of Ottoman Empire rule over its territory.  The Irish-Bulgarian connection dates back in history.  More than 100 years ago the death occurred of the most famous Irishman in Bulgaria, James Bourchier from Bruff, County Limerick who was a champion of Bulgarian interests.  He led the delegation from Bulgaria to the negotiations on the Versailles Treaty in 1919.  Like his counterpart, Se&aacute;n T. O'Kelly, a former President, who led Ireland's delegation, he was unsuccessful in his endeavour.  Bulgaria has named a boulevard and metro station in honour of his efforts.  He rests near Rila Monastery, a privilege granted to no other foreign citizen.  Pierce O'Mahony, a philanthropist funded a home for 32 graduate Bulgarian orphans and gave a start in life to them is also honoured in Bulgaria.  Bulgaria and Ireland are both members of the EU, sharing and deciding on a common future, mutually supportive and reinforcing strengths.  The real bond is the connection between people, the dynamic and active Bulgarian community in Ireland, which is almost 8,000 strong in Dublin, Cork, Ennis, Shannon, Tullamore, Monaghan and Waterford, ranging from academics, engineers and IT specialists to medical healthcare professionals and construction workers.  We would like to wish the Bulgarians living in Ireland a happy liberation day.  <i>Chestit praznik</i>.  I thank the ambassador for being with us today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1645" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#K00500"><p>The Cathaoirleach's mastery of language never ceases to amaze.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#K00600"><p>Go raibh maith agat, a chara.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.49" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#K00650">An tOrd Gnó - Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#K00700"><p>Bualadh bos.  The ambassador, Ms Karadjova, is very welcome.  I thank her for visiting.  I wish her, all the citizens of Bulgaria and all the Bulgarian Irish citizens who are part of our community here a very happy national day.</p> <p>The Order of Business is No. 1, motion regarding the earlier signature of the Electricity Costs (Domestic Electricity Accounts) Emergency Measures Bill 2022, to be taken on the conclusion of the Order of Business without debate; No. 2, motion regarding the first meetings of the Joint Committee on Autism and the Joint Committee on International Surrogacy, to be taken on the conclusion of No. 1, without debate; No. 3, motion 96(1) regarding support for Ukraine, to be taken on the conclusion of No. 2 without debate; No. 4, address to Seanad &Eacute;ireann by Ms Linda Ervine to mark Seachtain na Gaeilge, to be taken at 1.30 p.m. in accordance with the arrangements set out in the motion agreed by the House on 24 February; and No. 5, Animal Health and Welfare and Forestry (Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill 2021 - Committee Stage (resumed), to be taken at 2.45 p.m. and to adjourn after 60 minutes, if not previously concluded.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#L00100"><p>Following Senator Craughwell's comments, I must say the Cathaoirleach is a fountain of knowledge.  Ambassador Karadjova is very welcome to the Seanad today.  Our thoughts are very much with her and eastern Europe at the moment.  We are very shocked and horrified by the continuing aggression by Russia towards her neighbours in Ukraine.  We compliment her and her nation on what they are trying to do for their neighbours.  We are doing all we can here for them.  We are totally with the people of eastern Europe on this, and we sympathise with the ambassador on what her country is going through at the moment.</p> <p>I wish to return to roads projects.  At some stage the Leader might ask the Minister for Transport to pay us a visit and deal with a number of road projects.  I do not expect him to come for one road in Roscommon.  We have a very busy route from Athlone to Roscommon, which I am sure the Leader has travelled at some time in her political life.  It is an extremely busy national secondary road.  The sum of &euro;18 million was allocated in the national development plan to do a bypass, the Ballymurray to Knockcroghery bypass.  This is not just a secondary road going from Athlone to Roscommon, it is a road that takes traffic from Donegal right down to Wexford, so it is very important.  Rumours are circulating that it has been taken out of the national development plan.  When we bring in the Minister for Transport, I ask the Leader to put that on the programme for discussion because it is of serious concern to people in County Roscommon, in particular in the mid-south Roscommon area.</p> <p>I extend our good wishes to the Convent of Mercy senior camogie team, which won the all-Ireland championship recently, beating a Cork team from Carrigtwohill.  Any time we beat a Cork team is good.  That is significant for the county.  From your own family connections, a Leas-Chathaoirligh, you know some of the people in the county.  I send congratulations to Ellen Cafferkey and Ali Campbell, the joint captains, and Niamh Fitzgerald who was the player of the match.  We wish them well.  It is another good day for sport in Roscommon.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#L00200"><p>Yes, I suspect I would have family members on the team.  I thank Senator Murphy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" speakername="Barry Ward" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#L00300"><p>I also extend my welcome and good regards to Ambassador Karadjova.  I had the pleasure of visiting Bulgaria and the Rila Monastery about 16 years ago, but I was informed by her of the fact that Mr. Bourchier was buried there.  I was not there with a group of Irish people, so I was not aware of it.  It is a beautiful country.  We are delighted to see the ambassador, although the times are very challenging for any neighbour of Ukraine at the moment.  We wish them well.</p> <p>This morning I want to talk about the resignation of Professor Ben Tonra who has resigned as vice principal for internationalisation and global engagement at the UCD college of social sciences and law.  This must be a siren to academics and to the Government in this country that there is a real danger surrounding funding of third level education.  For some years, in particular since we introduced free fees, mar dhea, and the removal of the ability of universities to fundraise directly through that stream, for example, funding for the third level sector has become increasingly difficult.  We now have a situation where universities are going all out to raise funds through many different streams and students are one of them, but there are also industry partners, international partners and research.  All those aspects have now become independent funding streams for third level.  The danger is that it has left universities open to exploitation.  Where there is money, it will often follow academic activity.  The question is how independent the activity is and how it stands alone from the benefactor or the person who is funding it.</p> <p>China is a part of that.  The funding of the Confucius Institute in UCD started a long time ago as part of the university's Asia strategy at a time when China appeared to be opening up and moving more towards wanting to be a constructive member of the international community.  The reality is that China's funding of the Confucius Institute and other measures comes with baggage and requirements.  I have raised this issue directly with the Minister for Education on the leaving certificate Mandarin syllabus.  We have a situation where Mandarin Chinese teachers are coming to Ireland from China.  They will only teach the simplified characters in respect of Mandarin that are used in mainland China.  We do not explore the possibility, for example, of Cantonese or other Chinese dialects being available to students here and we do not explore the opportunity for them to use the traditional characters that are used in places like Taiwan.  There is a real danger now that the academic integrity of institutions like the Confucius Institute and other institutes in UCD and other universities around the country will be compromised by funding from the likes of China and other international stakeholders.</p> <p>The fact Professor Tonra has now essentially put his job on the line &ndash; he will remain an academic at UCD but he has stepped back as vice principal for internationalisation and global engagement - must be a serious warning for the Government, the Department of Education and the Department of Further and Higher Education, Research, Innovation and Science that they must look at funding for third level institutions.  At this point, they must review how the universities are funded to examine whether we as a State should be putting in place measures to protect them from this kind of exploitation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1645" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#L00400"><p>The ambassador is welcome to the House today.  It is amazing that it took a war in Ukraine to bring us all so close together.  I hope that closeness continues.</p><p>I express my thanks to the Irish Air Corps for going the extra mile and flying to Romania yesterday to bring home parents and their surrogate children.  People have said things about the Air Corps in this place, about it not being regulated and this, that and the other, but when it is required to step up to the plate, it always steps up to the plate.</p><p>Irish neutrality and Irish military non-alignment is now very much in public discourse.  Most people now accept that Ireland is not and never has been a neutral country.  We do not conform to the requirements of the Hague Convention of 1907 as a neutral country, therefore we cannot claim neutrality.  What we can claim is that we are militarily non-aligned.  I heard the words &quot;politically neutral&quot; used the other day.  There is no such concept.  We come out with such nonsense to try to explain ourselves.</p><p>Since 1999, under Chapter 8 of the UN charter, Ireland has deployed with regional organisations.  One might ask what is the difference.  If we deploy with the United Nations, we wear a blue beret.  If we deploy under a regional organisation, which includes the EU and NATO, we wear the beret of our nation.  In the case of the Irish Defence Forces, it is the black beret.</p><p>Ireland and NATO have been in public discourse for some time.  Let us talk about that for a few moments.  The Irish Partnership for Peace has been working with NATO since 1999.  The Defence Forces spent considerable, time, effort and expense getting NATO operational capabilities concept, OCC, phase 1 certification for the Naval Service <i>LE George Bernard Shaw</i>and for the Army Ranger Wing.  Therefore, while we are not aligned with NATO, we are damn close to it.</p><p>Senior officers in the Defence Forces complete the NATO planning process module and are NATO certified on successful completion as part of the senior command and staff course.  All military NATO doctrine is referenced and used in Defence Forces doctrine, so it is definitely aligned with NATO.  Ireland does not use the training doctrine or certification from Russia or China.  Therefore, we are not aligned with them.</p><p>The White Paper on defence in 2015 categorically states we should increase our alignment with regional actors such as NATO and the EU entities.  Ireland is very much aligned militarily with NATO but the real fact is we are incapable of delivering any commitment to NATO, if asked, because of the current state of our Defence Forces.  When the Minister talks about neutrality, military non-alignment and political neutrality, he should probably sit down and study precisely what we are before he makes statements.  Could we please be honest about this and stop being afraid?  NATO is not a bad word.  Being allied to NATO is not a bad thing.  People need to stop muddying the waters on neutrality.  There is nothing wrong with proactive military alignment when it is required.  Ireland is aligned with NATO, but it exercises its right to refrain militarily from NATO activities, save those that are under Chapter 8 of the UN charter.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Gerard P. Craughwell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2402"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2402&amp;amp;pid=GerardPCraughwell&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=03"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> The bottom line is this country needs to have a discussion on neutrality.  Until that discussion happens, however, we are sitting on armaments today that we can send to Ukraine.  I have seen people standing with their shoulders to tanks to try to stop them rolling into their towns.  I have photographs that were given to me this morning by the ambassador from Ukraine and they are horrific.  We cannot sit idly by.  I do not want bloodshed but I want people to be able to defend themselves.  We should send the weapons.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1688" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#M00200"><p>I, too, wish to extend a word of welcome to the ambassador.   She is very welcome to the Seanad.</p> <p>Earlier this week, we held the 61st plenary session of the British-Irish Parliamentary Assembly.  I must say that it was a very worthwhile endeavour, as it usually is.  It is the first in-person plenary we have been able to hold since the start of the pandemic.  While it was a much shorter event this time around, it allowed us a great opportunity to engage between institutions and parliamentarians right across these islands at such a crucial time globally but, indeed, here at home and between these islands as well.  We have in this House a number of very committed members of that body.  The work that it does sometimes gets overlooked.  I propose that going forward, the relevant committees of the British-Irish Parliamentary Assembly, which do some very good scrutiny work and engagement, would perhaps be able to be discussed and platformed in this institution.  I will raise that issue with the Leader and hope to bring it to the Committee on Parliamentary Privileges and Oversight at an appropriate time.  I think that would be a good opportunity.</p> <p>I tabled a Commencement matter this morning on the issue of the referendum to extend presidential voting rights to citizens outside the State.  The Minister of State pretty much informed me of what I have known for some time now, which is that the referendum Bill is on the Order Paper and the Minister for Foreign Affairs will be sponsoring that legislation.  Will the Leader use her good office to encourage the Minister and his Government colleagues to bring that Bill before the Oireachtas?  We are about to head into the St. Patrick's Day celebrations and travel around the world to tell our diaspora just how much we value them and that they have a stake in the life of their home.  We have committed to not leaving citizens in the North behind.  This is a real and tangible way in which we can show citizens that they are valued and have a stake in the life of the nation.  As the President said, he is not the President of a land mass but of the Irish people.  It is only right, therefore, that Irish people wherever they reside, across Ireland or throughout the world, have the opportunity to vote.  We could initiate that referendum Bill in this House.  We have discussed this issue at length in previous Seanaid and there is support right across the House.  This is a short, succinct Bill.  In saying that, however, I am not advocating that we do anything haphazard.  We need to ensure this referendum is won.  We need to bring the same level of positivity, collaboration and inclusion to that referendum as we have seen with others in the past few years.  I look forward to the Leader's response.  Hopefully, it is something on which we can work going forward to ensure that Bill is done as speedily and efficiently as possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1683" speakername="Marie Sherlock" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#M00300"><p>I realise the ambassador has left but I very much want to welcome her to the Chamber.  Veliko Tarnovo in Bulgaria and the people there have a very special place in my heart.  I am delighted to be able to congratulate them on their national day.</p> <p>The issue I wish to raise this morning relates to the National Gallery of Ireland, which is one of a number of extremely important cultural institutions in this State.  In fact, it is the foremost cultural institution in the State and in that role, it has a responsibility to show leadership in who it works with and to whom it contracts work.  Indeed, any public body that is spending State money has that responsibility but in particular, as our primary national cultural institution, the National Gallery of Ireland holds that responsibility.  I support the artists and staff who have expressed concerns about the awarding of the cafe contract to Aramark.  Of course, any State body is perfectly entitled to award a contract to those they deem most appropriate but serious questions must be asked about the procurement policy.  We know that those artists who have withdrawn their works from the Zurich portrait prize exhibition, namely, Brian Teeling, Emma Roche and Emily O'Flynn, have done so at considerable personal and professional risk.  We know that Salvatore of Lucan and Jonathan Mayhew are among the 84 artists who have signed letters expressing their deep-seated concerns about the awarding of the contract.</p> <p>Obviously, it is important that people are entitled to register their concerns about the continuation of direct provision - I think most of us here feel that direct provision needs to come to an end - and, in particular, the standards some companies have maintained within the direct provision centres.  Knockalisheen and Lissywollen are two of many direct provision centres where there have been issues regarding the food provided by Aramark.  I am seeking a debate on procurement policy in the State and the latitude that is allowed.  I have seen the correspondence from the director of the National Gallery of Ireland, which says that the gallery is bound by Irish and EU procurement law.  If that is the case, we need to have an understanding of what it means.  Does that mean that it can only award contracts on the basis of the lowest cost or is there scope to include other factors?  Having looked at procurement law, I believe there is absolutely scope to include other factors but I am not sure that was set out in the tender.  There is a real issue now regarding how the State spends money and the responsibility it has to ensure it is spent well in supporting activities that are worthy of it in this country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1632" speakername="Frances Black" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#M00400"><p>I warmly welcome the ambassador of Bulgaria.  I wish everybody well on this Bulgarian national day.</p> <p>I was at an absolutely harrowing briefing this week on Yemen and what is happening there.  I want to give a little bit of detail of the reality of what is happening.  In the past seven years, 377,000 Yemeni people have died due to direct and indirect causes of war, 10,000 of whom are children.  It is shocking.  That is going on today.  The director of the UN World Food Programme has stated that 400,000 Yemeni children are at risk of dying.  This is absolutely devastating.  There can be huge difficulty in accessing information as there are no foreign journalists on the ground in Yemen.  The war has been extremely under-reported due to the media being prohibited from entering the country.  At the very minimum, there needs to be an insistence by the international community to the Yemeni Government that media should be allowed into the country to report accurately on what is happening on the ground.</p> <p>I learned at the briefing, which was unbelievably powerful, that very little humanitarian assistance has been provided to Yemen and its people due to blockades being imposed in 2016.  The enforcement of the criminal blockade has prevented vital aid reaching 80% of the population who depend on it.  As a result of this lack of assistance, 5 million Yemeni people are now on the brink of famine.  In 2018, the UN warned that Yemen was facing the worst famine in the world for 100 years and predicted that 12 million to 13 million innocent civilians were at risk of dying from lack of food.  I could go on.  I feel that we need to urge the countries supporting such attacks to rethink their contribution to a war that has resulted in bringing this country to its knees.  Some 86% of Saudi Arabia's weapons come from Britain and the US.  We need to take a hard look at ourselves as a country and honestly look at what changes we can put in place to stop being implicated in this war.  It is beyond time for political resolution to end this war.</p> <p>The Government rightly called for sanctions against the brutal Putin regime within five days of the invasion of the Ukraine.  We must ask whether the lives of Europeans are more valued than those of the people of Yemen and, indeed, Palestinians who are living under an apartheid regime.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Frances Black:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2474"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2474&amp;amp;pid=FrancesBlack&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=03"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I ask the Leader for a debate in the coming weeks on the war in Yemen.  It is essential that we investigate this in more detail.  I support the call for this brutal war in Yemen to end now.  There will be a march on 26 March from The Spire at 1 p.m.  As stated by Martin Luther King and referenced in this Chamber the other day, which I will reiterate with regard to Yemen and Palestine, the ultimate tragedy is not the oppression and cruelty by the bad people but the silence in that regard by the good people.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1638" speakername="Malcolm Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#N00200"><p>I had an unusual experience last night.  Last night, the Ukrainian ambassador addressed the Fianna F&aacute;il Parliamentary Party meeting.  While she exhibited the full extent of her diplomacy, she also spoke very personally about the impact of what was happening in the democracy.  As we know, this is about the battle of democracy versus autocracy.  </p> <p>I was also conscious last night that Deputy Alan Kelly had stepped down as leader of the Labour Party.  I extend best wishes to our friends in the Labour Party.  We should appreciate the service that Deputy Kelly has given.  Those of us in politics appreciate the personal sacrifices that everybody makes.  I wish Deputy Kelly well and also the Labour Party in the decision that has to be made.</p> <p>The officer board of &Oacute;gra Fianna F&aacute;il was also in Leinster House last night.  I was struck by their enthusiasm and idealism.  It reminded me of our idealism and why we are in politics.  It brought me back my first day in this Chamber when we were all excited and giddy on becoming Members of the Seanad.  Every time I walk into this House I still feel that sense of the honour and the privilege of coming in here.  Perhaps it is naive but I am very conscious of the opportunity that is presented to all of us.</p> <p>It is a difficult time to be a democrat and a difficult time to be involved in politics but we face the challenges.  We need to use our role to inspire others, to encourage more young people, women and men, into political life, to stand up against those who criticise and give out and to talk about the nobility of political life.  The debate I am calling for does not require any Minister to be brought in.  It is not a big showcase, but about us talking about the value of politics and us being public representatives and the importance of that role.  I would hope the Leader would facilitate that very open discussion.  All of us have got involved for very noble reasons.  We may not always agree, but we got involved for the noble reasons of making our communities, country and planet a better place.  With democracy under challenge, we should have that discussion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#N00300"><p>I join with Senator Malcolm Byrne in sending very good wishes to Deputy Alan Kelly.  I had the privilege of serving on the Council of Europe with him for two years.  He was an extraordinary and effective representative there for Ireland.  I wish him and his family well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1670" speakername="John McGahon" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#N00400"><p>This week, I have focussed all of my comments on Ukraine.  I have talked about how it should be granted immediate accession to the European Union, how we should ensure that if it wishes to join NATO it can do so, how Ireland's policy of neutrality is ridiculous and that we should be sending weapons to defend against the murder of women and children on the streets of the European Continent. </p> <p>Today, I want to focus on another angle that is two-fold.  I commend the Russian people who in their own country are standing up against President Putin.  God knows how dangerous that is, not only for their livelihoods and safety, but their lives.  It has been forgotten in this debate that this horrific war is not being carried out in the name of normal, decent Russian people who abhor this as much as we do.  It takes real courage to protest against President Putin on Russian streets yet people are doing that.  It is important to acknowledge that.</p> <p>I want to focus on the sanctions that we are putting forward.  We have to totally and utterly cripple the Russian economy.  All bets have to be off the table.  We have to cripple it.  In crippling the Russian economy, we cripple President Putin's ability to wage a war of death upon the European Continent.  How do we do that?  We have to ensure that we move SWIFT to include all banks, including banks involved in energy.  There can be no nitpicking among western European countries about what sanctions to impose and not impose because it might hurt our personal interests.  We need total attrition in an economic sense.</p> <p>Mair&eacute;ad McGuinness, in her role as European Commissioner with responsibility for financial stability, is leading the charge for the European Union on this.  She is the woman responsible for introducing these sanctions in Russia.  It would be a very good idea if we wrote to Commissioner McGuinness to ask her to come before the Seanad at some point in the next few weeks - I know she is incredibly busy now - to outline the sanctions that have been imposed, how they can work and what sanctions can act as good deterrents for the future to make sure something like this does not happen again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#N00500"><p>Up to now, I have not spoken on the Ukrainian war but I do so today.  Over the past week, approximately 1 million people have crossed the borders into safe jurisdictions.  These 1 million people will be looking to resettle in Europe.  Yesterday, there was a call by the Taoiseach and the Minister, Deputy Coveney, for volunteers to come forward to see how we could help and house the people that are going to come to our country.  In that regard, figures of 20,000, 25,000, 30,000 or 40,000 have been mentioned.</p> <p>As leaders, we can only do so much.  There are other leaders in our communities, including church and faith leaders.  My call is to them.  We have almost 3,000 parishes in this country.  How lovely would it be for all of those parishes to take on board a family to integrate them into society, get them jobs and housing.  No better vehicle to do that than the churches.  Each church in this country has a responsibility, be that the Muslim, Jewish or any other faith.  My call today is to the church leaders of Ireland to do what they can and for them to step up and show what Christianity and faith is really about.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1695" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#N00600"><p>Today is World Book Day.  It is also the 25th anniversary of World Book Day.  The theme of this year's World Book Day is, You Are a Reader.  It is about encouraging children to dress up in the clothes of their favourite character and to read a book.  It is really important because of the whole educational aspect around it.  Many bookshops have offers on today and reductions in the price of books, in particular children's books.  It is important to get that message out.</p> <p>March is endometriosis awareness month.  Endometriosis is a debilitating illness that affects 167 million women worldwide.  It is endometriosis awareness month worldwide.  For one in every ten women, endometriosis can be very debilitating in that it is very painful.  It is the cause of many people not being able to conceive.  It sometimes takes up to seven and a half years to get a diagnosis, which is too long.  It is important to highlight that this is endometriosis awareness month.  If people feel they have symptoms they should seek an assessment and get checked.  It is really important that we would seek to bring about a reduction in the seven and a half years' timeframe for a diagnosis.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#N00700"><p>As I so often have the pleasure of doing, I support every word said by Senator Black in regard to Yemen.  I attended that meeting on Tuesday as well.  The situation is truly shocking.  The figures which have come from the United Nations are horrific: a minium of 10,000 children have died since 2015, 377,000 Yemenis have died since 2015 and 4 million Yemenis have been displaced.  It is worth bearing in mind as well that the bombs that are dropping on Yemen are dropped with the full support of Britain and the US.  The US has troops in the United Arab Emirates helping to organise those bombs.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paul Gavan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2469"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2469&amp;amp;pid=PaulGavan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=03"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Every one of those troops comes through Shannon Airport; every one of them.  When we have that conversation on neutrality, let us reflect on all of that and our unfortunate role over the past seven years in this awful war.  Thankfully, we are all agreed on Ukraine and the motion we are going to pass later is absolutely necessary and important but I do not understand why we do not have a conversation about sanctions against Saudi Arabia.  In fact, quite the opposite is the case.  A Fianna F&aacute;il Minister went to Saudi Arabia two weeks ago to ask how we can do more business with that country, as it continues to drop bombs on Yemen and as children continue to die in Yemen.  I genuinely do not understand why one set of lives has such value while another set of lives apparently has none.  I would ask everyone to reflect on that.</p><p>I was not planning to speak on that topic but did so because Senator Black spoke so eloquently on it.  I want to raise the fact that at University Hospital Limerick this morning there were 90 people on trolleys.  There was a powerful article in a number of newspapers today on people in the emergency zone.  One patient, an elderly man in his eighties, had a 54-hour wait on a trolley before getting an oncology appointment.  In one zone with a capacity of 22 patients, there were 52 patients with just three nurses allocated.  The Minister visited recently and it was a welcome visit but I stand by everything I said in that regard.  It would be great to have the Minister come to the House so that we can have a conversation on that topic.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1663" speakername="Annie Hoey" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#O00200"><p>Like Senator Maria Byrne, I want to raise World Book Day, an issue that is very close to my heart.  In particular, I want to talk about access to libraries and library services for children.  I loved nothing more than going to the library as a child.  I was a voracious reader and sometimes during the summer holidays when there were late-night openings, my dad would bring us to the library twice in one day.  A love of books is one of the great gifts that my parents gave me and my sisters.  I recognise that it is not always easy for parents to access books and libraries and particularly during Covid, children did not have the same opportunities to browse the aisles of their school library or the local library.  The Labour Party would love to see a scheme introduced to encourage children throughout the country to make a trip to their local library to encourage a lifelong love of books.  A tangible community approach will improve literacy skills in a very targeted way.  Providing each child with a membership card and the offer of a book to keep could stimulate community participation.  In addition, as a late-night reader myself, I believe we should extend library opening hours, particularly at weekends when most people have the time to use and enjoy the library.</p> <p>We need to rethink and reimagine the potential of our libraries, which can be developed as local resource hubs not just for bookworms and students but those seeking training, work and aiming to set up their own businesses.  There are several libraries around the country, including one being planned in Bettystown, County Meath that are really transformative spaces for their communities.  They are not just library spaces but hubs for community activity.  We also need to create a fairer starting point for children to help eradicate illiteracy through early intervention at primary and secondary school.  Even though today is World Book Day, reading is for life and I would love to give every child in Ireland the right to read and to have that rooted in the local library.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#O00300"><p>I support Senator McGahon's proposal to invite EU Commissioner Ms Mairead McGuinness to the House to discuss the sanctions.  I am sure the Commissioner, who is from Ireland, would be very happy to address the Seanad on the mechanisms and methodologies being used to impose sanctions on Russia.  Hopefully, we will see uniformity across Europe and the world in the imposition of these sanctions.  It would be a very interesting discussion to have if the Commissioner was prepared to make herself available.</p> <p>Today is World Book Day, as colleagues have said.  Books are important for people developing their knowledge, even from a later perspective.  The happiness and the opportunities that books give people are wonderful.  However, many people cannot read books, including people who are visually impaired or who have print disabilities.  The Marrakesh Treaty, which was passed a number of years ago, deals with copyright issues for books being transformed into digital formats that can be accessed by people with print disabilities.  The National Council for the Blind of Ireland, NCBI, is the agent in this country tasked with the responsibility of producing books in digital format, not just for blind and visually impaired people, but also people who might suffer from dyslexia and other conditions.  Government funding in this area is important because access to print material is critical.  Let us imagine a library where 90% of the shelves are empty because books are not available.  That is a library one would not be inclined to go into.  Unfortunately, 90% of the books in the world are not available in digital form and cannot be accessed through audio, Braille or other forms of digital transposition.  We have a lot of work to do in this area because 100% of books should be available to everybody.  Nobody should have their choices limited simply because books are not available in the format they would use to read them.  It is a point worth noting and is something of which we should all be aware.  It is so important to make resources available to turn the 10% into 100%.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#O00400"><p>I will begin with a text message I received this morning from a friend who worked in Kyiv and who I had the pleasure of meeting when I was an election monitor.  It reads as follows:</p> <blockquote> 	Talking with all my co-workers, it's like 1939-1941...trying to flee West, jumping on trains, finding cars, leaving wives and kids at the border..the amount of destruction to infrastructure - horrible.   </blockquote> <p>That is from a man who worked with the World Bank in Kyiv until last autumn.  We stand with Ukraine today.  The suggestion of Senator McGahon, endorsed by Senator Conway, that we invite Commissioner McGuinness to the House should be given serious consideration.  </p><p>I ask for a debate on the HSE national service plan, a service plan amounting to &euro;20.7 billion that our good friends in Sinn F&eacute;in never acknowledge.  To be fair to Senators Gavan and Maria Byrne, they come in here and talk about the problems at University Hospital Limerick regularly but there is something fundamentally wrong with our health service when the biggest ever budget of &euro;20.7 billion, plus an additional &euro;350 million for a 2022 waiting list action plan, is not addressing the problems.  There is something fundamentally wrong with the HSE and it needs to be addressed.  All of us want to see waiting lists reduced, hospital bed capacity increased, and home care and social care packages enhanced and increased.  We need an urgent debate, not just about Sl&aacute;intecare or universal healthcare, but about putting the patient, the person who needs care, at the core of what we do in our health service.  I ask that we have that debate as a matter of extreme urgency.  Indeed, we should have a rolling debate on a series of issues related to healthcare and HSE.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" speakername="Mary Seery Kearney" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#O00500"><p>I pay tribute to the Irish people for the extraordinary and overwhelming generosity they have shown towards Ukraine.  The fact that centres all over the country that were set up to collect goods for shipping to Poland have had to stop receiving them because they were overwhelmed is really quite extraordinary.  I note the statement by D&oacute;chas this morning that it would be better for people to give money at this stage.  If people donate money it can be directed to organisations working on the ground in a humanitarian capacity, including Child Fund Ireland, Christian Aid, Concern, Habitat for Humanity, the Irish Red Cross and Goal, among others.  There is a substantial list of organisations on the website<i>www.dochas.ie</i>.</p><p>I also want to pay tribute to the recruitment industry who have reached out to me this morning to say that when people from Ukraine come to Ireland, they will need time to recover and get over the trauma and sheer shock of all they have been through.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Mary Seery Kearney:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=MarySeeryKearney&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=03"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->They are willing at some point appropriately in the future to look at a jobs fair, something to assist and start normalising lives again.  I am very grateful for all that is going on there.  <br/><br/>I want to pay tribute to my home constituency of Dublin South-Central.  In several locations there have been gatherings of goods and of support.  I am overwhelmed by the number of people who are contacting me offering accommodation in their homes for families, saying we have this many bedrooms, or a log cabin at the end of the garden, we are happy to accommodate families.  It comes back to the fact that we have an incredible legacy, we are an incredible people when it comes to reaching out, having a heart for humanity and pulling together at a time of need.  That has been manifest in what is now only a week.  We have had an extraordinary response.  I want to draw that to the attention of the House.  I thank everybody for the support, most of all <i>dochas.ie.  </i>In the future, let us see what we can do when we have given the shelter and the support.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1666" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#P00200"><p>I wish to talk about an issue I have spoken about before, which is, how we use our public amenities.  There is a swimming pool complex in Dunmanway that unfortunately lies idle half the time.  This is a huge issue for our society.  We put &euro;5 million into a complex and have it open between 11 a.m. and 5 p.m. on five days a week.  It is run by the local authority.  I was there last week and one of the big issues is that it is not open at weekends.  Where is the joined-up thinking here?</p> <p>There is an issue about how we provide access to swimming and swimming lessons for the public.  We all have kids, we all have the opportunity to teach them to swim.  In some locations people are waiting two years to get lessons.  If one has a situation where a pool that is owned by the State only runs at half capacity, it is frustrating.  It makes no sense.</p> <p>The big debate is about how we are going to move this issue forward.  Firstly, we have an issue about how a local authority manages its assets.  Secondly, we need to look at providing public pools.  We need to have a programme about providing public pools.  We have seen major work regarding sports capital grants putting money into sports clubs.  We should have a debate in this Chamber with the Minister of State at the Department of Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sport and Media about pools and how he believes the vision needs to be changed on providing those public pools.  The biggest town in west Cork is Bandon.  There is no pool in the town.  If one wants one's kids to have lessons in Bandon tomorrow morning one will be waiting for up to two years.  That is not good enough.  We need to have a vision, a change.  I ask that we invite the Minister of State, Deputy Jack Chambers, in here to ask him what his vision is regarding providing access to water and water safety, and in particular providing public pools for those among the general public who want access.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1669" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#P00300"><p>It is on the Order of Business that we should have no debate on Ukraine and pass a resolution in line with that in D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann.  I have no argument with the terms of the notice of motion that is there.  However, I want to say this.  They are very mild in their terms.  I am thinking of the number of people who have already been killed and such things, and this is very diplomatic language.  It is Iveagh House speak, if I may say so.  Whereas I suggested that we could have a motion passed without debate, I believe we could say more, and we should say more.</p><p>In regard to what Senator Gavan said about Saudi Arabia and Yemen, I fully agree with him.  I have spoken and written as strongly as I can on the subject of Khashoggi, the Yemeni war, the use of cluster munitions on Yemenis and the like, by Saudi Arabia and the United Arab Emirates, and the differential approach that there apparently is to what one condemns and what one does not condemn.  </p><p>I would say that Sinn F&eacute;in should be careful.  Its record speaks for itself.  The party only needs to read the <i>Irish Examiner </i>today to see just how ambivalent and how reticent it was about raising its voice when it mattered, before all this took place.  I want to put that on the record, in a cordial way, but nonetheless let us have some reality here.  What is happening is wrong, it is evil, a crime against humanity and a war crime.  This motion does not talk about sanctions or anything like that.  It should go much further.  I am just putting my views on the record.  It has obtained cross-party support and I do not want to be divisive but I think we have to have a different attitude.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1639" speakername="Miche&aacute;l Carrigy" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#P00400"><p>I wish to raise an issue which is linked to the situation in Ukraine and the knock-on effect that is going to have on our economy over the next 12 months.  I would like the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine to come in to discuss the effects it is going to have on food, fuel and fertiliser.  This is going to have a significant impact on our agriculture sector in particular going forward.  Much of the fertiliser we import comes from Ukraine, as well as grain, barley and wheat.  All of those are grown in that country.  If those crops are not sown shortly, as they need to be, then we are going to have an issue over the next 12 months.  We need to look at that.</p> <p>Do we need to put schemes in place for more tillage to be sown in our own country, to make sure we have a supply for our food industry?  That is very important.  We import the grain, wheat and barley to produce goods to export.  However, if we are not going to be able to access that raw product what effect is that going to have on our agriculture sector?  It is important that the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine should come in, if possible, to discuss this issue and see what we are putting in place for our agricultural and food producing sectors for the next 12 months.  Now is the time to deal with it, not in six months' time.</p> <p>I mentioned fuel.  I got a picture from a family member who is in the bus industry.  It is the first sign I have seen, it was somewhere in north Dublin, of &euro;2 for a litre of plus petrol.  That is the first instance of &euro;2 and that is where we are heading with regard to our fuel.  We are going to have to seriously look at the rebate scheme, extending or expanding that rebate scheme with regard to fuel for transportation, our haulage and bus industries.  The reality is, many companies such as bus companies have contracts for school transport and they are losing money on it because of the costs.  We have to deal with those issues.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#P00500"><p>I thank the Senator and invite the Leader to respond to the issues raised.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#P00600"><p>I thank the Leas-Chathaoirleach and Senator Carrigy.  I will pass on his comments to the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine today because I fear that in order for us to be effective in our sanctions against Putin and Russia it will certainly have an impact on the economies of all the European countries and indeed the western world.  How to plan for that is what the Senator is asking for a debate on, and I will ask for that today.</p> <p>I have no doubt that Senator McDowell would have written a far more strident, strong and probably more effective motion today but at least we have a motion that is a start and that is agreeable and that will be passed hopefully unanimously by the House today.  As agreed on Tuesday this will be a rolling debate.  It is not scheduled for next week but it is rescheduled for the week after.  At that stage maybe we can revisit having a stronger wording.</p> <p>The suggestions made today to invite our Commissioner to address us might be something we could take up with the Committee on Parliamentary Privileges and Oversight because I think it would be worthwhile to hear how and why the sanctions are planned and phased as they are, and why normal people like us do not understand why things are being withheld.  It might be a worthwhile debate.  I thank Senator McDowell for his contribution.</p> <p>Senator Lombard asked for the Minister of State at the Department of Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sport and Media to be brought in with regard to a programme for public pools.  I will organise that.  </p> <p>Senator Seery Kearney talked about the generosity of Irish people.  I do not know whether we are unique but there is always a swell of response and generosity when Irish people are asked to step up and they have indeed done so in spades in the past week and will continue to do so.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Regina Doherty:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2295"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2295&amp;amp;pid=ReginaDoherty&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=03"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I am mindful the Ukrainian ambassador said yesterday that much of what we are collecting is possibly not what is needed.  Ukraine, through the humanitarian agencies, will issue lists of stuff, probably mostly medical supplies, that are actually needed as opposed to what we naturally think we should offer.  I look forward to hearing about that.</p><p>Senator Buttimer asked for an urgent debate, which I will organise, regarding the national service plan and the HSE waiting list action plan.  He is correct that what is required is structural change in our health service and not new plans that come out every year followed by analysis of the plans and why they did not work at the end of the year.  We are all aware that structural changes are needed.</p><p>Senators Hoey and Conway raised World Book Day, as did Senator Maria Byrne.  I wish everybody well on that.  I acknowledge the major input and the joy it is to read a really good book.  When I get one I cannot put down, I love it.  It is a great experience.  I acknowledge that.</p><p>Senators Gavan, Black and McDowell touched on what is an horrific ongoing situation with regard to criminal behaviour.  I did not go to the briefing mentioned by Senator Black as I do not think I was invited to it, but I was not aware that so many people have been murdered in the past seven years.  I will certainly ask for a debate on that and facilitate it as fast as I can. </p><p>Senator Keogan made a very worthwhile plea to all our faith leaders.  Many of us automatically assume we are talking about Catholic Church leaders, but we are also talking about our Protestant and, indeed, Muslim, Buddhist and humanitarian faith leaders.  Senator Keogan made a plea to people to open up their hearts and homes for what will be, according to the Minister for Justice this morning, tens of thousands of refugees we hope to welcome in the next couple of weeks.  Senator McGahon made the suggestion of standing up to the Russian people through the inclusion of all sanctions, which means all banks and not just selected ones that will not impact on us.  He also made the suggestion of asking our European Commissioner to come to the House.</p><p>Senator Malcolm Byrne made a unique but apt suggestion of having a debate on the value of politics and an open discussion of why and how we should cherish our democracy in light of the resignation of our colleague, Deputy Alan Kelly, yesterday evening.  I wish Deputy Kelly, Regina and their children continued success in whatever role, political or otherwise, he chooses in future.</p><p>Senator Black spoke about the war and Senator Sherlock about the awarding of the contract by the National Gallery of Ireland.  I will ask for a debate on procurement policy but, from personal experience, it is determined by European legislation.  It may be something we should start to challenge and ask for those extra conditions to be added to the tender process.</p><p>Senator &Oacute; Donnghaile made a suggestion that post meetings of BIPA we should have a conversation about the committee work it does, which would be very valuable.  I will ask the Oireachtas Committee on Parliamentary Privileges and Oversight to put that on the agenda too.</p><p>Senator Craughwell talked about the repatriation of Irish citizens from Romania by the Irish Air Corps.  He thanked the Air Corps for that and asked for a debate on our neutrality, which was suggested on Tuesday and has gone to the Minister for Foreign Affairs for consideration of a date.</p><p>Senator Ward talked about the resignation of Professor Ben Tonra, his concerns about Chinese influence because of their investment in UCD and a debate on funding for the third level sector.  Senator Murphy spoke about our roads projects and inviting the Minister for Transport to the Chamber, for which there has been an open invitation for the past number of weeks.  We talked about the national development plan, especially the roads projects that have been excluded from it, just before Christmas.  I have not forgotten about it.  I consistently remind the Minister the invitation is open to him to come to speak to us.  Senator Murphy also congratulated the Convent of Mercy senior camogie team, which we join him in doing.  </p><p>It is endometriosis awareness month, which Senator Maria Byrne brought up.  The leader of Fianna F&aacute;il in the Seanad, Senator Chambers, frequently raises the issue because of her personal experiences and interest in it.  It is an enormously quiet disease that women have been made to suffer silently for far too long.  We have talked a lot about women's issues, which is a phrase that annoys me, over the past couple of months.  This is a medical issue that is something we can fix fast.  The other issues are cultural and we may have a more arduous journey to try to change an entire culture, but this is a medical issue that requires medical intervention far quicker than the seven years that is the current average.  We need to wake up and have a proper medical response and programme in Ireland for the one in 10 women who suffer silently from this condition.  I am very happy to add my support to the awareness campaign that is going on this month.  I ask everybody else to do so in a similar way, if they can, for which I would be very grateful.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.78" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.79" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#Q00300">Electricity Costs (Domestic Electricity Accounts) Emergency Measures Bill 2022: Motion for Earlier Signature</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#Q00400"><p>I move:</p> <blockquote> 	That, pursuant to subsection 2&deg; of section 2 of Article 25 of the Constitution, Seanad &Eacute;ireann concurs with the Government in a request to the President to sign the Electricity Costs (Domestic Electricity Accounts) Emergency Measures Bill 2022 on a date which is earlier than the fifth day after the date on which the Bill shall have been presented to him. </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.81" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.82" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#Q00600">First Meetings of Joint Committee on Autism and Joint Committee on International Surrogacy: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#Q00700"><p>I move:</p> <blockquote> 	That&mdash;   	(a) the Joint Committee on Autism, and <br /><br />(b) the Joint Committee on International Surrogacy,  may meet, notwithstanding the fact that in advance of the first meetings of each Committee, the full membership of either has not yet been appointed. </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.84" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.85" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#Q00900">Support for Ukraine: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#Q01000"><p>I move:</p> <blockquote> 	&ldquo;That Seanad &Eacute;ireann:<br /><br />recalls: <br /><br />- that in the first Article of Bunreacht na h&Eacute;ireann the Irish nation affirmed its inalienable, indefeasible, and sovereign right to choose its own form of Government, to determine its relations with other nations, and to develop its life, political, economic and cultural, in accordance with its own genius and traditions;<br /><br />- that Ireland believes in, and is fully committed to the core principles enshrined in the Charter of the United Nations (UN Charter), which include the sovereign equality and territorial integrity of states;<br /><br />- that Ukraine has the same fundamental right as every other sovereign and independent state to choose its own foreign policy and to ensure the security and defence of its own territory; and<br /><br />- the commitments we make as members of the United Nations (UN) are binding on every UN Member State;<br /><br />reaffirms its commitment to the principle of the pacific settlement of disputes and calls on all nations to settle disputes peacefully in accordance with the principles of the UN Charter;<br /><br />condemns in the strongest terms Russia's acts of aggression against Ukraine and reaffirms its unwavering support for the sovereignty and territorial integrity of Ukraine within its internationally recognised borders; <br /><br />notes that our deep concern about the actions of the Russian leadership does not diminish the friendship and respect we have for ordinary Russians, including those who have built a future in Ireland; <br /><br />rejects the decision of the Russian Federation to recognise the so-called &lsquo;independence&rsquo; of certain areas of Donetsk and Luhansk regions as a violation of the territorial integrity and sovereignty of Ukraine and calls upon the Russian Federation to reverse this decision;<br /><br />urges Russia to reverse the recognition, withdraw its military forces, and return to discussions within the Normandy format;<br /><br />calls for the full implementation of the Minsk Agreements as endorsed by the Security Council in UN Security Council Resolution 2202 (2015); <br /><br />welcomes the commitment of &euro;10 million in humanitarian aid to the Ukraine Humanitarian Response Plan as an expression of Irish solidarity with the people of Ukraine; and <br /><br />calls upon the Secretary General of the UN to use his good offices to search for a peaceful settlement.&rdquo; </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.87" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.88" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar fionra&iacute; ar 1.06 p.m. agus cuireadh t&uacute;s leis ar&iacute;s ar 1.35 p.m.

Sitting suspended at 1.06 p.m. and resumed at 1.35 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.89" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#T00100">Address to Seanad Éireann by Ms Linda Ervine to mark Seachtain na Gaeilge</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#T00200"><p>Dia dhaoibh, a chairde.  I welcome our distinguished visitors to the Gallery and welcome back former Senator Labhr&aacute;s &Oacute; Murch&uacute;.  For the benefit of those who are Cultural and Educational Panel, he informs me he will be running in the next election.  Just be warned.</p> <p>I thank colleagues for taking time out of their day to be present for the address to Seanad &Eacute;ireann by Ms Linda Ervine to mark Seachtain na Gaeilge in accordance with the order of Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 24 February.  Proceedings are not to exceed one hour.  I will have opening remarks, Ms Linda Ervine will address us for 15 minutes, contributions by spokesperson will not to exceed four minutes, the Leas-Chathaoirleach will not exceed three minutes and Linda Ervine MBE will conclude.  We will have a "thank you" from the Leader as well.</p> <p>I ask Linda Ervine MBE to come to the Seanad Chamber for her first time.  She may come back in another capacity.  I am sure, with Labhr&aacute;s &Oacute; Murch&uacute;'s assistance, she could end up in the cultural and educational panel yet.  M&aacute;s &eacute; bhur dtoil &eacute;, tabhair bualadh bos do Linda Ervine.</p> <p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh Linda Ervine MBE chuig Seanad &Eacute;ireann.  An bhliain seo caite, bhronn an Bhanr&iacute;on Eil&iacute;s MBE uirthi as an obair a rinne s&iacute; in Oirthear Bh&eacute;al Feirste - I am getting East Belfast and West Belfast mixed up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.91" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Linda Ervine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#T00300"><p>Oirthear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1688" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#T00400"><p>Do not make that mistake, a Chathaoirligh.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#T00500"><p>Nuair a cuireadh an cheist ar Linda c&eacute; a thabharfadh s&iacute; go dinn&eacute;ar d&aacute; mbeadh rogha aici d&uacute;irt s&iacute; go dtabharfadh s&iacute; Nelson Mandela, &Iacute;osa, agus Princess Diana.  Theastaigh uaithi cuireadh a thabhairt do Diana chun a taobh f&eacute;in d&aacute; sc&eacute;al a chloiste&aacute;il.  Linda would invite Princess Diana to listen to her story.  Lorg&oacute;dh s&iacute; Nelson Mandela mar tugann a smaointe ar an maithi&uacute;nas - forgiveness - inspior&aacute;id di.  D&uacute;irt s&iacute; go nd&uacute;irt s&eacute; &quot;if you don&rsquo;t forgive, you are still in prison&quot;.</p><p>Sa l&aacute; at&aacute; inniu she runs the Irish language project Turas in East Belfast.  Cuireann s&iacute; ranganna ar f&aacute;il do gach leibh&eacute;al - &oacute; bhonnleibh&eacute;al go hardleibh&eacute;al.  She has almost single-handedly untapped and awoken a little-talked-about interest among the Protestant community to learn Gaelic.  D&uacute;irt s&iacute;:</p> <blockquote> 	My aim is to connect people from Protestant communities to their own history with the Irish language.  And to make them understand that learning or speaking Irish is certainly no threat to British identity &hellip; Its origins show that it was historically spoken by huge numbers of Protestants across Ulster and in Scotland. </blockquote> <p>Is maith an t-ainm at&aacute; ar an project &quot;Turas&quot;.  T&aacute; s&eacute; r&aacute;ite ag Linda &ldquo;for me it is not only a journey into a language but also a journey of healing and reconciliation&rdquo;.  T&aacute; Seanad &Eacute;ireann bu&iacute;och as an turas iontach saoil at&aacute; d&eacute;anta aici.  Seanad &Eacute;ireann is proud of her journey and life she has led that brought her here.  Cuirimid f&aacute;ilte roimpi go Seanad &Eacute;ireann.  Seanad &Eacute;ireann welcomes her here for Seachtain na Gaeilge.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">An Cathaoirleach:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2246"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2246&amp;amp;pid=MarkDaly&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=03"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I present Linda Ervine MBE.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.95" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Linda Ervine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#U00200"><p>A Chathaoirligh, a Sheanad&oacute;ir&iacute; agus a dhaoine uaisle, go raibh m&iacute;le maith agaibh as an gcuireadh inniu.  Is on&oacute;ir mh&oacute;r dom a bheith anseo inniu.  T&aacute; br&oacute;n orm, ach beidh m&eacute; ag caint i mB&eacute;arla mar t&aacute; nuance i gceist leis an mh&eacute;id at&aacute; le r&aacute; agam.  T&aacute; s&eacute; iontach deacair i dteanga eile.</p> <p>I really want to get my story across.  I will talk about northern Protestants and the Irish language.  My own journey with the language epitomises the situation of many Protestants within Northern Ireland.  I had no knowledge of the language, no connection to the language and no particular interest in it.  It was a non-entity until I had the opportunity to be introduced to it in 2011.  What followed was a roller coaster of new information as I discovered the place names, surnames, the words that we use in our everyday speech and the words that surrounded me my entire life, but I had never had the knowledge of them.  It is not an exaggeration to say that meeting with the language changed the whole direction of my life.  It enhanced it.  I realised that I found this treasure.  I just wanted to share it with other people in my community who, like me, because of the tradition they came from, had never had the opportunity to learn Irish.  </p> <p>When the media decided that my journey was interesting, it ended up in a couple of newspapers because my husband, Brian, was leader of the Progressive Unionist Party at the time.  The reaction to that was twofold.  There were some people from the Protestant community who approached me because they, too, wanted to learn Irish.  There were others who criticised me and said that I was a traitor and a Lundy.  That is the pattern that I have observed over the past ten years, since I set up the Turas Project in oirthear Bh&eacute;al Feirste.</p> <p>Many of you probably think that I am very brave and very courageous because I obviously wear a flak jacket to work everyday and I go through a hail of missiles, which plays havoc with my hair.  On a serious note, I face criticism and attack from some quarters but, overall, apart from a bit of nonsense on social media, the majority of the time I go about my business totally unhindered.  I do not let the negativity that comes from a minority impact on the work that I do.</p> <p>However, the success of my project has presented a threat to those who view Irish as a language of the enemy.  Their only weapon against me is to undermine me by spreading false information.  They say that I am working for Sinn F&eacute;in, that I am only in it for the money and that I am a useful idiot.  I have even read that I am going out with somebody from Sinn F&eacute;in.  My husband, Brian, asked me where I get the time.  Those who make these accusations do it through social media.  They do not use their own names or photographs.  I find that it is difficult to feel threatened by people who do not have the courage to even expose themselves.  They spew out their lies and innuendo from the safety of their own living rooms.  These keyboard warriors are not interested in the wonderful cross-community work that takes place daily within the organisation that I run and the long-term friendships that are created between participants in our programmes.</p> <p>Here is an insight into my world.  These are the comments I hear from Protestants who have no link with the language, no engagement with the language and no knowledge of the language: &ldquo;Why would I want to speak a republican language?&rdquo;, &ldquo;Protestants have no interest in the Irish language&rdquo;, &ldquo;It is a foreign language&rdquo;, &ldquo;It is a dead language&rdquo;, &ldquo;Sure they do not even speak it in the South&rdquo;, although I do not know how true that is, and &ldquo;You would be better off learning French or Spanish, love".</p> <p>I am also told that learning Irish is divisive, which is something that I totally reject.  For me, it is the perfect medium of reconciliation.  It brings together people from our divided community.  It is a bridge that unites our communities and reminds us of our shared history.  It is a bridge between the countries of the British Isles.  It is a language that went from Ireland over to Scotland and to the Isle of Man, and is part of the family of Celtic languages spoken throughout the British Isles at one time.</p> <p>When I started my job as the manager of the Turas Project, I created a presentation called the Hidden History of Protestants in the Irish Language, which I have delivered to thousands of people over the past ten years.  So many times I have watched people arrive and their body language shows that they are hostile.  They have cold, hard stares.  Then I watch as that changes to a look of disbelief, and then an accepting smile, as they discover that the language has links to the Church of Ireland, the Presbyterian church, the Orange Order and even the Red Hand Commando, to name but a few.  What I am trying to say is that people feel differently and react differently when they are given a broad range of information, rather than a narrow slice.</p> <p>Here are some of the comments I have heard over the past ten years from the people who learn Irish with us: &ldquo;I have always wanted to learn Irish&rdquo;, &ldquo;I wish I had the chance to learn it in school&rdquo;, &ldquo;It is beautiful&rdquo;, &ldquo;It is really difficult, but I have loved enjoying learning it&rdquo;, &ldquo;It is so interesting&rdquo;, &ldquo;I love finding out about the place names&rdquo;, &ldquo;I cannot believe it was all around me and I did not know&rdquo;, &ldquo;I have made so many friends&rdquo; and &ldquo;I just love it&rdquo;.</p> <p>I have watched the interest in Irish in east Belfast grow at a phenomenal rate over the past number of years.  What started as a small, fledgling project in 2012 with the support of funding from Foras na Gaeilge is now one of the largest Irish language centres in Belfast, but the majority of learners are from the Protestant, unionist and loyalist, PUL, community.  I would like to express my gratitude, while I am here speaking, to Foras na Gaeilge, because it had the foresight and courage to recognise our potential and it invested in our project.  Without it, we would never have gotten off the ground and the Turas Project would not exist.</p> <p>Ten years ago, many of our learners were frightened of people knowing that they were learning Irish.  They did not want their neighbours, friends or even family members knowing.  They feared criticism or worse &ndash; intimidation.  Today, they are proud to be learning Irish.  They bring their neighbours, friends and family members along to share in this new-found interest.  They are posting about it online.  They are enjoying their first experience of learning the language and they want to challenge those who tell them that Prods do not speak Irish.  They are proving that wrong.</p> <p>However, despite our best efforts, there are still limited opportunities for Protestants to engage with the language in many parts of Northern Ireland.  Much negativity still surrounds the language, with many unionists regarding it as purely political.  We fell foul of this last year when we attempted to open an integrated Irish-medium nursery school in a loyalist housing estate in east Belfast.  Here is how it happened.  I was invited into the estate by the local primary school to teach Irish to every single pupil in the school.  While I was there, I was made aware that there was an old, unused mobile at the back of the school that had been set up for early years education.  It was the perfect venue for the new n&aacute;iscoil that we were planning to start.  We spoke to the board of governors, one of whom was our recently departed DUP MLA, Christopher Stalford, and they gave it the thumbs up.  As almost all of the children were learning Irish already without any issue from the parents, we as a committee believed it would not be a problem to temporarily house 16 three-year-olds.</p> <p>Sadly, we were very wrong.  As soon as the news of the n&aacute;iscoil broke, an online hate campaign began.  This was followed by a petition in the local shop, libellous posters with my face on them around the area, the spreading of misinformation and threats to protest outside the primary school.  Despite pleas from the staff of the school and the parents that we should stay, we decided that it would be better to move.  After much difficulty, we managed to get another venue.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Ms Linda Ervine:</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->However, after a short time it pulled out due to fear of intimidation and attack.  At the last minute another organisation, Christian Fellowship Church in east Belfast stepped in and offered us a temporary home.  Renewed online attempts to stir up trouble and organise protests fell on deaf ears and after what had been a difficult few months we opened on 4 October last year with a reduced number of children but we were still there.  Since then, the na&iacute;scoil has been peacefully doing what it does best, providing high-quality childcare to young children and the na&iacute;scoil's motto: "P&aacute;ist&iacute; sona ag foghlaim le ch&eacute;ile - Happy children learning together" is a reality.  The na&iacute;scoil is almost at capacity and we have 22 registrations for next year.  Our journey or turas continues and the number of Protestant learners continues to grow.  More people are engaging with the language and realising that it belongs to us all on the island of Ireland.</p><p>Where can we say the Irish language is within Protestant communities today?  It is in various places.  It is in the negativity and hostility created by "Tiocfaidh &aacute;r l&aacute;".  It is in the dismissive and condescending attitudes that come from some within unionism.  It is also in the Protestant students who are now studying Irish with us at university.  It is in Na&iacute;scoil na Seolta, where despite the threats of protest and intimidation parents are bringing their children and it is in the classrooms of Turas, where every year hundreds of students take their first faltering steps along their own language journeys.</p><p>I want to end by sharing an experience I had last night.  I got a phone call from a girl I do not know, a Protestant girl called Miranda who lives in a big loyalist estate in Antrim.  She rang me because she has a little bit of Irish having gone to a few classes and she has two children.  The oldest one is old enough to go to nursery school and she wants to send it to an Irish-medium nursery school.  She is worried about what her neighbours would say but her ex-partner is taking her to court because of it and she wanted our support, which we will give her.  Miranda is not the most able girl in the world but she is doing something that makes her able; standing up and making the change.  One day it will not be an issue for Protestant parents in big loyalist estates to send their children to an Irish-medium school but it takes time.  Change is coming.  It does not come easily but it does come.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1688" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#V00200"><p>Maith th&uacute;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#V00400"><p>That was a moving and informative speech on the journey that Ms Ervine and people in her community have undertaken.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1643" speakername="Lorraine Clifford-Lee" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#V00500"><p>Ba mhaith liom f&aacute;ilte &oacute; chro&iacute; a chur roimh Linda.  Is iontach an rud &eacute; go bhfuil s&iacute; linn chun Seachtain na Gaeilge a cheili&uacute;radh agus is iontach an rud &eacute; a sc&eacute;al a chloiste&aacute;il.  T&aacute; a cuid oibre thar na blianta ar son a pobail agus ar son a teanga in oirthear Bh&eacute;al Feirste inspior&aacute;ideach.  Molaim go hard &iacute; as an s&aacute;robair seo.  Briseann an obair sin baic agus crutha&iacute;tear tuiscint agus caoinfhulaingt.  B&iacute;onn Linda ag d&eacute;anamh obair trasphobail agus t&aacute; s&iacute; ag athr&uacute; na meoin at&aacute; ag daoine faoin nGaeilge, rud at&aacute; soil&eacute;ir &oacute;n mh&eacute;id at&aacute; r&aacute;ite aici.  Is rud f&iacute;orchumhachtach &eacute; seo.  Is bean l&aacute;idir stuama &iacute; Linda freisin.  T&aacute; L&aacute; Idirn&aacute;isi&uacute;nta na mBan beagnach linn agus is maith an rud e gur f&eacute;idir linn aird a tharraingt ar bhean cos&uacute;il le Linda ag obair le mn&aacute; eile agus ag tabhairt cabhair d&oacute;ibh.</p> <p>Ba mhaith liom aird a tharraingt ar a cuid oibre agus ar obair a comhghleacaithe freisin.  Go h&aacute;irithe, molaim an m&eacute;id a rinne siad chun Na&iacute;scoil na Seolta a bhun&uacute; le d&eacute;ana&iacute; agus chun an Ghaeilge a bhronnadh ar an gc&eacute;ad gl&uacute;in eile.  Tuigim nach raibh s&eacute; &eacute;asca agus na fadhbanna a bh&iacute; os a gcomhair.  Ba mhaith liom ceannasa&iacute;ocht Linda &oacute; thaobh na cluich&iacute; Gaelacha a mholadh freisin.  T&aacute; s&aacute;robair &aacute; d&eacute;anamh aici leis an gclub Cumainn L&uacute;thchleasa Gael in oirthear Bh&eacute;al Feirste freisin.  T&aacute; borradh ag tarl&uacute; i mB&eacute;al Feirste faoi l&aacute;thair &oacute; thaobh na Gaeilge de agus t&aacute; Linda i gcro&iacute;l&aacute;r an bhorrtha sin.  T&aacute; s&eacute; f&iacute;orth&aacute;bhachtach go n-acht&oacute;far reachta&iacute;ocht do chearta teanga chomh tapa agus is f&eacute;idir chun taca&iacute;ocht a thabhairt don fh&aacute;s sin agus do na daoine at&aacute; ag d&eacute;anamh s&aacute;r-iarracht chun an teanga a fh&aacute;il agus chun ruda&iacute; breise a chur os comhair an phobail.  Gabhaim bu&iacute;ochas le Linda as a bheith linn.  T&aacute;imid anseo chun &eacute;isteacht l&eacute;i.  Lean ort le do s&aacute;robair; change is coming.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#V00700"><p>For some Connemara Irish we have Senator Kyne.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1665" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#V00800"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte chro&iacute;&uacute;il roimh Linda Ervine chuig Teach Laighean agus chuig Seanad &Eacute;ireann.  Is deas an rud &eacute; &iacute; a fheice&aacute;il agus a chloiste&aacute;il agus t&aacute; sc&eacute;al iontach inste aici.  T&aacute; stair fhada sa t&iacute;r seo &oacute; phland&aacute;il Uladh go dt&iacute; Cogadh na Saoirse, na Triobl&oacute;id&iacute; agus toradh reifrinn na Breatimeachta.  T&aacute; an t-oile&aacute;n scartha d&aacute; ch&eacute;ile.  Oile&aacute;n amh&aacute;in at&aacute; ann le: dh&aacute; t&iacute;r; dh&aacute; phr&iacute;omhchreideamh; pr&iacute;omhteanga labhartha, an B&eacute;arla; dara teanga, an Ghaeilge; agus Ultais mar theanga mionlach.  Is &aacute;bhar casta &eacute;.</p> <p>T&aacute; Linda mar ghuth aontaithe don d&aacute; traidisi&uacute;n ar an oile&aacute;n.  N&iacute; r&oacute;l &eacute;asca &eacute; seo agus t&aacute; a fhios agam nach raibh turas &eacute;asca aici.  Tr&eacute;asla&iacute;m l&eacute;i as an obair at&aacute; d&eacute;anta aici chun ranganna Gaeilge a chur ar f&aacute;il in oirthear Bh&eacute;al Feirste do Phrotast&uacute;naigh agus d'aontachtaithe.  Th&aacute;inig logainm phr&iacute;omhchathrach na Tuaiscirt, Belfast, as an nGaeilge, B&eacute;al Feirste, relating to the mouth of the river or the tidal ford across the river mouth.  Th&aacute;inig logainm an dara chathair sa Tuaisceart, Derry, as an nGaeilge Doire, oak wood or grove.  T&aacute; muintir an Tuaiscirt ag &uacute;s&aacute;id na Gaeilge chuile l&aacute;.  B'fh&eacute;idir nach bhfuil a fhios acu &eacute; ach sin an rud at&aacute; Linda ag obair air.  T&aacute; a fhios aici go bhfuil a l&aacute;n ceisteanna maidir leis an nGaeilge sa Tuaisceart faoi l&aacute;thair agus maidir leis an Acht teanga.  Sna tithe seo t&aacute;imid tar &eacute;is Acht n&iacute;os l&aacute;idre a chur tr&iacute;d an Oireachtas.  T&aacute; a fhios agam go bhfuil deacrachta&iacute; le hAcht teanga a thabhairt isteach &oacute; Thuaidh.  C&eacute; go bhfuil s&eacute; scr&iacute;ofa sna doicim&eacute;id idir an d&aacute; Rialtas agus na p&aacute;irtithe go l&eacute;ir, t&aacute; deacrachta&iacute; ann.  T&aacute; an obair at&aacute; &aacute; d&eacute;anamh ag Linda ag cabhr&uacute; leis an bhfeachtas sin chun Acht a chur i bhfeidhm ar mhaitheas na teanga agus ar mhaitheas an traidisi&uacute;in sa Tuaisceart agus ar an oile&aacute;n.</p> <p>Ms Ervine's journey and story are powerful and it was a powerful contribution.  As she said, she has come from having no relationship with the Irish language ten years ago to being inspired to learn and show that journey and relate it to other people.  It is a journey that a lot of Catholics in the Twenty-six Counties can go through as well because a lot of people in the South go through the education system and they leave down the pen after doing paper 2 in Irish in the leaving certificate and that is it.  They do not write another word in Irish although they might say a few words.  It is a reawakening that is needed for so many people across the island.  It is not a Catholic language; it is part of ancestral Ireland.  If all communities can understand and accept that then it can be a language that will unify the island; not physically or governmentally but in a peaceful existence, which is important.  The placenames are a wonderful way of illustrating that.  I mentioned Derry and Belfast and there are hundreds of other examples, from large towns to small villages which have that connection.  There are so many words and it is a wonderful part of our history.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Se&aacute;n Kyne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2343"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2343&amp;amp;pid=SeanKyne&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=03"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Your contribution can only assist in developing relations on this island.</p><p>I wish you well in your continued journey.  I know others are with you, such as Miranda, the lady who contacted you.  I am sure there are many others throughout Northern Ireland.  I wish you well in your endeavours for Irish.  The language is part of the history, tradition and culture of the island.  Irish is included in the Acht teanga but Ulster Scots is also included in recognition of that language.  That has its own place and tradition as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#W00200"><p>An bhfuil cead agam mo chuid ama a roinnt le mo chomhghleaca&iacute;, an Seanad&oacute;ir McDowell?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#W00300"><p>Ceart go leor.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#W00400"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte &oacute; chro&iacute; romhat agus gabhaim bu&iacute;ochas leat, Linda, thar ceann gach duine, as ucht na ceannaireachta cult&uacute;rtha at&aacute; t&uacute; ag tabhairt d&uacute;inn ar fad.  I thank you for the cultural leadership you give that is so important, at this time.  When I think about the Irish language, I think about something that is very fragile in many ways, especially in this generation.  Great steps have been taken, in both jurisdictions, to promote the importance of Irish and the rights of people.  Plenty of ground still has to be covered.</p> <p>However, I think of the recent Acht na dTeangacha Oifigi&uacute;la (Leas&uacute;) 2021 and the steps we are taking politically to ensure in future our Civil Service recruits a minimum percentage of people who are capable of providing services to people through Irish.  That would seem like a basic requirement for the revival, protection and promotion of our national language, but there we are.  Thankfully, good things are happening.</p> <p>However, when I think of Irish, I think of something that is not primarily political, but cultural and of something that has the capacity to be a carrier of beauty and a forger of understanding.  Too often in our history, language and faith have been used as definers of division among people and used as causes when, in fact, lived properly, these are things that unite.</p> <p>I would like to see the day when we do not have association in people's minds between the Irish language and phrases such as tiocfaidh &aacute;r l&aacute;.  I prefer to think of phrases such as duine le Dia, that beautiful, moving Irish phrase to describe a person with disabilities - God's own people.  When you sit down to a meal, you bless &aacute;r gcuid agus &aacute;r gcuideachta; our portion and our company.  I think of our beautiful placenames.</p> <p>I think of the influence of Irish on the English language as we speak it in Ireland.  If you go to London and tell somebody that your brother broke your bike on you, the person might have an idea that he physically took your bicycle and broke it over your head.  Of course, that comes from the Irish, bhris s&eacute; mo rothar orm.  There are so many ways in how we speak English in this country that are influenced by our Irish language heritage.</p> <p>It is so important to keep reminding ourselves that it is not just the heritage of one section of the community.  When one thinks of athbheochan na teanga and the wonderful work that was done with the Celtic revival from the 19th century onwards, so many names associated with the Protestant community were central to the revival and appreciation of the Irish language.  It is true there were nationalist aspirations, but there was something much more significant and uniting going on.</p> <p>With that modest contribution I welcome you.  Treisigh leat.  Keep her lit.  Keep this good work going on all our behalf.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1669" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#W00500"><p>Cuirim f&iacute;orfh&aacute;ilte romhat, Linda.  D&eacute;arfaidh m&eacute; c&uacute;pla focal as B&eacute;arla.  My grandfather, Eoin MacNeill, was, with Douglas Hyde, the co-founder of the Gaelic League.  In 1913, Douglas Hyde was sidelined a little bit from the Gaelic League movement because it was politicised.  My grandfather always regretted that was done to Douglas Hyde.</p> <p>I agree with Senator Kyne.  One of the great tragedies about the considerable amount of time that has been put into the teaching of Irish in this jurisdiction is that when children put down the pen on the leaving certificate, they never speak Irish again and are not in a position to conduct an ordinary conversation in Irish on day-to-day matters.</p> <p>I agree completely with you, Linda, that it is a shared heritage.  The Irish language must not be weaponised.  It must be viewed as a commonly held resource.  I congratulate you on everything you are doing and wish you every success in your efforts in the future.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1667" speakername="Vincent P Martin" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#W00600"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh &aacute;r gcuairteoir speisialta.  Is m&oacute;r an trua &eacute; nach bhfuil Gaeilge l&iacute;ofa agam.  Ba mhaith liom feabhas a chur ar mo chuid Gaeilge.  Tugann daoine cos&uacute;il le Linda inspior&aacute;id dom.  Is ioma&iacute; duine ina ceantar f&eacute;in at&aacute; ag foghlaim Gaeilge don ch&eacute;ad uair.  T&aacute; ardmheas agam ort, a Linda.</p><p>The Irish language will only stay alive for as long as it is spoken.  When a tree no longer bears fruit, it has no future.  However, when new shoots come through the soil, we know that other trees are growing.  All hope is not lost.  There is new growth taking place.  A future is possible.  T&aacute; an Ghaeilge f&oacute;s beo.  T&aacute; daoine cos&uacute;il le Linda ag coime&aacute;d beo &iacute;.  New shoots are in east Belfast which are now firmly rooted.</p><p>Other commentators describe the Irish language as being on its knees, but it is still here.  Linda, you are an example of someone who found it and embraced it.  You made it your own.  It is a language that belongs to everyone.  Is &aacute;r dteanga f&eacute;in &iacute;.  It is a precious jewel.  It belongs to no political party, creed or community.  It is older than all the political parties on this island.  It has been and is still spoken by all traditions and none and must never become entangled in divisive politics.  It should never be marginalised.</p><p>On your wonderful journey, you have remained truly loyal to your background, beliefs and unionism.  Unionism and its culture, which is an important part of our identity on this island, can be in a stronger place with people like you.  It can be in a safer and more confident place.  All of us, North and South, can take a leaf from your book and your leadership.  You are a woman making your own history and history will record that you broke new ground and opened new hearts and minds to the beautiful language of Irish.  Last year, in the Seanad, I congratulated you on your MBE and the incredible work you are doing.</p><p>I also know your brother-in-law is the late David Ervine.  We are honoured to have Brian Ervine, his brother, in the Chamber today.  I greatly admired David.  He looked to the future.  He was born into loyalism but he was authentic and wanted to look to a future and not the past.  He was a huge impetus at the time of the peace agreement in Northern Ireland.</p><p>I remember him, before Ian Paisley had the road to Damascus conversion and became a working friend Martin McGuinness, saying &quot;Big Ian, cop yourself on&quot;.  I thought that was so refreshing.  I remember it like it was yesterday when that peace agreement was struck and David Ervine leaving the building, saying in his lovely vernacular, &quot;I don't know about the rest of you.  I'm dog tired.  I'm going to the pub.&quot;  It is funny what you remember.</p><p>I had the pleasure of meeting David.  He was in the Abbey Theatre at a time when it might not have been politically so easy to come down here.  He attended <i>Observe the Sons of Ulster Marching Towards the Somme</i>, a wonderful play by my former lecturer, Frank McGuinness.  Maybe a challenge for us would be to put on that play as Gaeilge at some stage.</p><p>It is funny what you should say about the lies spun about you that did not put you off course.  At the Green Party Ard-Fheis last year, we had a guest speaker, Professor Monica McWilliams, who played a pivotal role in the peace process.  She said lies were spun about her that she was having affairs.  Anything was done to attack the man or woman and not the ball.</p><p>However, great efforts have been made.  I draw an analogy between the Irish language and the Tricolour, which sometimes can scare people.  I remember a Member of this House, a founder and former member of a political party called the Progressive Democrats giving his presidential address to the Ard-Fheis.  They tried to take back the Tricolour.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Vincent P. Martin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=VincentPMartin&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=03"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I do not know if he remembers this.  He does not do things by half measures.  He plastered the place with Tricolours and they were all over the platform from which he spoke.  There was a definite meaning to what he tried to do, just like when Michael Noonan, who is a very decent man, professed that he was an Irish republican and proud of it when he became leader of Fine Gael.  We have to take back what is ours and only look to ourselves, not to others, to criticise.  Linda will be an inspiration for us all and we are honoured to have her here today.  I congratulate and commend an Cathaoirleach on making what I consider an historic address to this Chamber.  We are so proud that he gave that address here today. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1688" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#X00200"><p>Roimh a chuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh Linda, aithn&iacute;m go bhfuil uachtar&aacute;n nuathofa Chonradh na Gaeilge, Paula Melvin, linn sa Ghaileara&iacute;, chomh maith le hard-sti&uacute;rth&oacute;ir Chomhaltas Ceolt&oacute;ir&iacute; &Eacute;ireann, an iar-Sheanad&oacute;ir Labhr&aacute;s &Oacute; Murch&uacute;.  T&aacute; f&aacute;ilte roimh an bheirt acu agus na ha&iacute;onna speisialta uilig at&aacute; linn inniu.</p> <p>Linda agus Brian, t&aacute; f&aacute;ilte romhaibh.  It is great to see a few more east Belfast people in the Chamber.  They are very welcome.  I have watched with great delight Linda&rsquo;s work, as well as the work of Turas and those who are on the journey with her.  I am sure she would acknowledge that there has been a great team around her.  For all the negativity you have received, you have also had a lot of support, which I know has been of great importance to you as you have led on this journey.</p> <p>You and I are both from east Belfast.  We are both from different backgrounds and traditions and we both have different world views - or so others would tell us.  Does it not say something that what unites us, the commonality we have, is what so many would seek to label as being divisive, that is, the Irish language?  That is what binds us.  That is the tie that binds.  Senator McDowell reflected on the history of the Gaelic League.  The first branch of the Gaelic League in Belfast was established on the Beersbridge Road, in what is now a very staunch and proud unionist and loyalist part of the city.  Part of the work of Turas is sharing that unique history and telling not just the Protestant, unionist and loyalist, PUL, community but everyone, including all of us here today, that that is the history of the language in our city and, indeed, throughout the rest of the country.  My old secondary school, Me&aacute;nscoil Feirste, was established in the early 1990s in a former Presbyterian church on the Falls Road, which is another symbol of our differences and our linkages.  It was set up in Cult&uacute;rlann McAdam &Oacute; Fiaich, which is named after the late Cardinal Tom&aacute;s &Oacute; Fiaich, a great scholar and advocate of the Irish language, and Robert Shipboy McAdam, a Presbyterian who was part of that generation of Presbyterians that did crucial work in preserving the language and keeping that flame alive.</p> <p>As someone who passed through that education sector, I am acutely aware of the history of Protestants preserving the language and handing it down to us, because we were taught about it.  You are the contemporary representation of that, Linda, and what you are doing at Turas is so special.  I do not say that to be clich&eacute;d or to give you any pl&aacute;m&aacute;s.  Not only is Turas and its ethos and work important because it is reawakening an awareness of the Irish language among the PUL community, but because, like so many others across this country and beyond, it is sharing, teaching, learning and speaking the Irish language, l&aacute;n stad.  That is the jewel in this.  That is the real crux and importance of it.  I know you want to get to a point where it does not really matter who you are or where you are coming from but what is important and special is learning, sharing and speaking the language.  I recall when Turas came to visit me at the parlour in City Hall when I was Lord Mayor and when it walked with us in the St. Patrick&rsquo;s Day parade.  You took a wee bit of flack for that at the time, if I recall correctly.  It is a very small group of people and Turas now has some of the biggest, if not the biggest, Irish language classes in the city happening on the lower Newtownards Road.  Who would have thought that possible ten or 15 years ago?</p> <p>The elephant in the room when we come to the Irish language, which Senator Clifford-Lee mentioned, is the need for legislation that protects you and me.  It would protect our community and all of us, and develop and enrich our society.  You are doing fantastic work.  I know you are probably scundered having to sit there and listen to all of this but we are delighted to have you.  It is important that we have more opportunities to hear voices like yours in this institution.  Gu&iacute;m gach rath ort i do chuid oibre agus t&aacute;im ag s&uacute;il go m&oacute;r le bheith ag labhairt leat.  I wish you every success with Na&iacute;scoil na Seolta because that is where this is at.  It is about giving the language to young children and letting them learn it, live it and speak it.  Go n-&eacute;ir&iacute; go geal leat agus go raibh c&eacute;ad m&iacute;le maith agat as a bheith linn. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#X00300"><p>Ba mhaith liom f&aacute;ilte a chur roimh Linda chuig Seanad &Eacute;ireann inniu agus aitheantas a thabhairt don obair th&aacute;bhachtach at&aacute; ar si&uacute;l aici le bun&uacute; Turas agus Na&iacute;scoil na Seolta.  T&aacute; s&eacute; l&eacute;irithe agat gur me&aacute;n &iacute; teanga inar f&eacute;idir pobal a aont&uacute;.  Sin mar is f&eacute;idir dul chun cinn a dh&eacute;anamh agus l&eacute;as a thabhairt isteach tr&iacute; bheith ag foghlaim faoin&aacute;r stair agus faoin&aacute;r gcult&uacute;r comhroinnte.  T&aacute; stair fhairsing ag an Seanad maidir le guthanna mionlaigh agus t&aacute; cuntas ag an Teach seo &oacute; thaobh t&aacute;bhacht na teanga de.  Mar shampla, san Oireachtas roimhe seo, ritheadh Bille an Chathaoirligh, an Seanad&oacute;ir Mark Daly, chun aitheantas a thabhairt do Theanga Chomhartha&iacute;ochta na h&Eacute;ireann.</p> <p>My pronunciation is not great and my language is not great.  Like many, I am trying to improve all the time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1688" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#X00400"><p>Maith th&uacute;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#X00500"><p>The work you have done in recognising what language means, what it can do and how it can be a measure of connection in communities is so important.  That is also important in this House because one of the themes of our centenary is minority voices.  The Seanad has a record in minority voices, both in terms of voices from unionist traditions and minority voices championing the language.  That is something we hold very dear.  In the previous Seanad the Cathaoirleach initiated legislation, which then became law, that recognised Irish Sign Language and gave that legislative recognition to the language.  It is an example of how languages layer onto each other.  Across the island, new migrants are coming in and bringing languages of their own and are learning English and Irish, and in many cases Irish Sign Language as well.  Every time we layer that language, it brings more understanding, more depth and more possibilities.  Senator Kyne put it very well when he said that the Irish language reaches far back into history has a history far longer than the State or our political bodies.  It has a future that goes very far beyond any of the political debates of the day as well.  It has that longer future.  I commend Na&iacute;scoil na Seolta because it recognises the future of the language and the future of learning together.  Its motto is &ldquo;ag foghlaim le ch&eacute;ile&rdquo;, which means "learning together".  You have championed learning together but your work is also about learning what it is to be together.  I commend you on that and thank you again for joining us today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#X00600"><p>Ar dt&uacute;s b&aacute;ire, gabhaim comhghairdeas leis an gCathaoirleach as ucht na h&oacute;c&aacute;ide ionta&iacute; seo a eagr&uacute;.  T&aacute; s&eacute; an-mhaith.  Mo chomhghairdeas duit.  Is c&uacute;is &aacute;thais dom Linda a fh&aacute;ilti&uacute; anseo inniu.  Tr&eacute;asla&iacute;m go m&oacute;r leis an obair iontach at&aacute; ar si&uacute;l agat ar son &aacute;r dteanga agus &aacute;r n-oidhreacht.  T&aacute; s&eacute; an-oiri&uacute;nach go bhfuil t&uacute; linn chun Seachtain na Gaeilge a cheili&uacute;radh.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Joe O'Reilly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=1610"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1610&amp;amp;pid=JoeOReilly&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=03"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Is c&uacute;is &aacute;thais dom chomh maith mo sheanchara, an iar-Sheanad&oacute;ir Labhr&aacute;s &Oacute; Murch&uacute; a fh&aacute;ilti&uacute; inniu, agus in &eacute;ineacht leis, uachtar&aacute;n Chomhaltas Ceolt&oacute;ir&iacute; &Eacute;ireann, CC&Eacute;, &Eacute;amonn &Oacute; hArg&aacute;in, agus baill eile de riarach&aacute;in agus d&rsquo;ardchomhairle CC&Eacute;.  Ar nd&oacute;igh, t&aacute;im an-s&aacute;sta f&aacute;ilti&uacute; roimh uachtar&aacute;n tofa Chonradh na Gaeilge chomh maith.</p><p>Linda, is &iacute; &aacute;r dteanga eochair &aacute;r litr&iacute;ochta agus &aacute;r n-oidhreacht shaibhir agus t&aacute; s&eacute; sin chomh t&aacute;bhachtach.  The language, as you clearly delineated in your remarks, in your life and in all the great work you do with the Turas project etc, is not the possession of any demographic or religion.  In fact, you follow in a great tradition of a wonderful Protestant churchman of the 17th century, Bishop Bedell, who was the Bishop of Kilmore and translated the bible into Gaelic.  You follow in that noble and rich tradition.  Irish language, literature and culture, including musical culture, which is exemplified by our visitors here, are a rich possession of the Protestant community, the Catholic community and, indeed, our new Irish - we want them to enjoy it too.  You are right; it is not about sectarian divisions or walls.  It is about unity and bringing people together.</p><p>I sincerely salute your wonderful work, Linda.  I am proud to be in the same room as you and to have the privilege of welcoming you.  I genuinely admire what you are doing.  We need more people like you.  In fact, people like you are needed all over the world sadly.  Again, I congratulate the Cathaoirleach on this wonderful initiative.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1688" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#Y00200"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#Y00300"><p>It is a very special day for the House.  May we have many such healing and wonderful days in the future.  If only Linda&rsquo;s example could permeate out to the rest of the world.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#Y00400"><p>We will ask Linda to respond to those very kind remarks.  What was the word Senator &Oacute; Donnghaile used?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1688" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#Y00500"><p>Scundered.  I think it might be Ulster Scots.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#Y00600"><p>I am not too sure what it means but I think it is a scarlet or something like that.  Linda, we are delighted to have you here.  Thank you for addressing the Seanad.  The Members were delighted to have you here as well.  I ask you to respond and then the Leader will conclude the business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.120" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Linda Ervine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#Y00700"><p>T&aacute; sibh r&oacute;-chine&aacute;lta.  You are too kind.  T&aacute; m&eacute; overwhelmed.  Is on&oacute;ir mh&oacute;r dom a bheith anseo.  I said to my husband Brian on our way down that I remember him bringing me to Dublin the first time.  It must be about 18 years ago.  To come here today in this respect - as Senator &Oacute; Donnghaile said, we are from a few streets away from each other; I come from a back street in east Belfast and it is such a great honour to be here.</p> <p>Is &Eacute;ireannach m&eacute;.  I have never been anything else but that and I will always be that.  No matter if anyone tries to tell me that I am not.  Is Briotanach m&eacute; fosta ach is &Eacute;ireannach m&eacute; ar dt&uacute;s.  I shared this with someone earlier on.  My grandfather on my father&rsquo;s side was a man from outside London who came here in the 1930s and married my nanny.  The reason we knew we were Irish was not because anybody ever sat us down and told us that but because he was a bloody Englishman.  We knew we were right because we were Irish and he was wrong.  On my mother&rsquo;s side, my grandmother was Kathleen Kelly, a Catholic woman from Clifton Street, who married a Presbyterian man with a very Irish name.  We are not one thing or the other.  We share this island.  This island and the language are part of us.  I am so fortunate to have met the language and to have got the chance to be ag streachailt leis an teanga.  T&aacute; s&eacute; ag &eacute;ir&iacute; n&iacute;os fearr ach t&aacute; s&eacute; iontach fad&aacute;lach.  To the Senators who apologise for their Irish, there is no apology needed.  I do not apologise.  I am just glad that I am learning it.  What started just over ten years ago, I am now in my second year of my degree.  I may never be l&iacute;ofa - I do not know - but the turas, the journey, is wonderful.  Go raibh m&iacute;le maith agaibh. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1688" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#Y00800"><p>Maith th&uacute;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#Y00900"><p>I call on the Leader of the House to respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#Y01000"><p>I am unfortunately in the position of not being able to speak Irish, but I have to say that was one of the most humbling addresses I have ever witnessed in the 11 years I have served in the Oireachtas.  I thank you so much for coming, Linda, for sharing your experience and journey, and for your humbleness to how you approached the conflict and anger you experienced over the past ten years.  You are so good to have given up your time and for sharing your experienced today.  It has enriched my day, my week and my experience.  I wish you continued success in everything you do.  I wish we could clone you and make 50 more of you.  You described the truth and the way forward, in that we are all just what we are but we have to try to get on with and have respect for one another.  That is sadly lacking in many of our political discourse.  Thank you very much for what you are doing from the grassroots up and for sharing that experience with us.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.124" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar fionra&iacute; ar 2.27 p.m. agus cuireadh t&uacute;s leis ar&iacute;s ar 2.47 p.m.

Sitting suspended at 2.27 p.m. and resumed at 2.47 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.125" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#AA00100"> Animal Health and Welfare and Forestry (Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill 2021: Committee Stage (Resumed)</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.126" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>SECTION 4</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.127" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question again proposed: "That section 4 stand part of the Bill."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.128" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.129" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sections 5 and 6 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.130" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>SECTION 7</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#AA00500"><p>Amendments Nos. 4 to 6, inclusive, are out of order as they represent a potential charge on the Revenue.  The amendments in question are Nos. 4, 5 and 6, as tabled by Senators Boylan, Gavan, &Oacute; Donnghaile and Warfield; Nos. 5a, 5c and 5d, as tabled by Senator Higgins; and No. 5b, as tabled by Senators Crowe and Casey.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.132" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That section 7 stand part of the Bill."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#AA00600"><p>I wanted to speak on amendment No. 3 but it was ruled out of order.  I want the opportunity to reintroduce these proposals on Report Stage.  I want to put that on the record in the context of amendment No. 3.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#AA00700"><p>The Senator has just put it on the record but we have already moved on.  We are on section 7 now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#AA00800"><p>Did the Acting Chairperson not call out amendment No. 3?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#AA00900"><p>Amendment No. 3 was dealt with the last day.  It was ruled out of order the last day.  We were dealing with section 4 when we adjourned the debate on that day.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#AA01000"><p>Okay.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#AA01100"><p>If the Senator wants to speak to section 7, she can do so.  She has already mentioned that she might want to bring the amendment back on Report Stage.  We have moved on from section 4, to which amendment No. 3 applied.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#AA01200"><p>The points I hoped to make were made by Senator Gavan during our previous debate on this issue.  When we initially raised concerns around the Control of Dogs Act and the Animal Health and Welfare Act, we were told it was strictly to do with fur farming.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Lynn Boylan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=LynnBoylan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=03"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We were then able to bring in amendments to deal with forestry, so if the scope of the Bill has been expanded, I do not understand why it cannot be expanded further to allow for the introduction of amendments to deal with other areas of animal welfare.  That is fine if it was addressed by Senator Gavan.  I want to put on record that I do not understand why it was ruled out of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#BB00200"><p>The decisions were made by the Cathaoirleach.  I am just-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#BB00300"><p>I know, you are just doing your job, Acting Chairperson, and I am just doing mine.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#BB00400"><p>Could you please speak up, Acting Chairperson?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#BB00500"><p>Certainly.  Does anyone wish to speak on section 7?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#BB00600"><p>Notwithstanding that all of the amendments have been ruled out of order because they impose a charge on the State, very similar amendments were presented to the Minister of State, Senator Hackett, when we last sat.  I cannot speak for everybody, but when we suspended that day, the Minister of State told us that she would come back and provide a response to the spirit of what the Members were trying to relay that day.  We are waiting on that response.  The spirit of what we are trying to say is that the State is closing down these businesses.  We all get why it is and we probably do not dispute that it is closing them down.  What is a real concern to all of us is, first, proper compensation must be provided for the livelihoods of the farmers.  We hear today there have not even been negotiations, discussions or informed consent with the farmers involved.  More importantly, the two weeks' statutory redundancy that was offered some weeks ago for the 35 or so people who earn their living working on these farms does not sit well with any one of us.</p> <p>The State is responsible for making these people lose their jobs.  It needs to stand up and say it knows what it is doing is for the right reasons but it is making sure the measures it puts in place will look after the people's livelihoods.  That goes so far as making sure the Intreo offices look after the people to retrain and reskill them.  Last week, Senator Gavan suggested we should put up a special fund and that was rejected.  As a former Minister for Employment Affairs and Social Protection, I know it is something Intreo offices do as a matter of course.  I would like to know the reason it is not being done here.  There is still an outstanding issue with regard to the compensation package that is being offered to the farmers.  From their communication with us, they do not agree with it, but more egregiously wrong is the way they have been treated in negotiations in recent months.  It is not what we would consider acceptable.  I would like to hear a response from the Minister before we decide if we agree to section 7.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#BB00700"><p>I agree with the Leader.  We had a long protracted debate, and the Minister was not here.  I know he is a reasonable and fair person.  I thank him for the Grant Thornton report that eventually came.  To give the Minister an idea of what went on, it was nearly impossible to get this report.  The farmers could not even get it.  We got it.  We are discussing primary legislation.  We are the Upper House and we had to make a case.  We were told we would have it the next day, but it did not come the next day.  We had to keep asking.  It suggests there is a reluctance to engage with people.</p> <p>As the Minister well knows, I am on the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine, and when I played back the deliberations of that meeting, if there was anyone rigorous and tough in the questioning of the farmers, it was me.  There is a subtle difference between questioning and being rigorous and fair.  I raised a number of issues about the welfare of the animals.  I also wanted there to be a heavy emphasis on the employees of the farmers, because they too are losing out.  I thank the Minister, as the primary Minister in the Department, for coming to engage with us.  As I said to the Minister of State on the previous occasion the Bill was discussed in the House, the reality is this activity is legal today.  By right, those people would be preparing for a breeding programme.  The Oireachtas has made no final decision.  The issue is about compensation for the workers and the farmers.  These farmers represent rural constituencies.  I have spoken to them, and I know of their attempts to have meaningful engagement and dialogue with their public representatives, and it is very disappointing.  I know there are few of them, which does not help their case.  There are three farms in question here.  However, we must be fair.  If the Government were to take a decision tomorrow to close down turkey production, the farmers involved would rightly demand fair play and justice.</p> <p>We talk about a just transition and how the Government would not be found wanting in that regard in rural communities.  We also talk about sustainable communities, rural Ireland and a town centre first approach, and building up the very fabric, economy and community in rural communities.  We hear all sorts of whispers that there will be this or that and these farmers will not get X, Y or Z.  Even at this late stage, I beg the Minister, who is a fair man and represents a rural constituency, to sit down with these farmers.  They are entrepreneurs and I admire entrepreneurs.  They are risk takers and business people - everything the Government talks about supporting.  They must get a decent package of compensation.  It is fundamentally wrong when the Government issues a decree to close down any legitimate, legal business that is operating within the law and complying with the requirements of commercial life, paying income tax and appropriate fees.</p> <p>I do not live in any of the constituencies involved and I do not know any of these individual farmers.  I do not know anyone who knows any of these farmers, but in terms of the section, it is not too late.  Let us be fair to people.  Let us give them a decent package.  All I want is the right sum.  I am not setting myself up to be somebody, but I want to advocate strongly for fairness.  The Minister and his officials should perhaps take this legislation away and take ten or 15 days, fewer if possible, and sit down and get some sort of consensus and be fair to the people involved but, more importantly, to their rural communities, who expect and believe they have the support of the Government for rural communities, agriculture and farming communities.  It is unfair the way they have been treated and I hope it is not too late.  I hope common sense will prevail.  I also hope the Minister will agree to mediate or appoint a mediator to put together a fair package before he comes back to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1666" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#BB00800"><p>I had tabled some amendments that were rejected.  I am not sure for what reason.  I have written to the Cathaoirleach looking for a definition of what he believes is the reason.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#BB00900"><p>They were not on this section.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1666" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#BB01000"><p>No, but they have been rejected.  As a Government party Senator, it takes a lot for me to table amendments to a Bill.  It is a very unusual process.  In fact, this is my first time in the Seanad to have done so.  I have no skin in this game.  The people involved are not from my part of the world at all, but I thought we needed fairness regarding the decision itself.  I spoke at length in the previous debate about trying to get fairness for community, society and for these people who will be out of business because of a Government agreement.  We spoke about a just transition when it comes to other issues and a whole-of-government approach, but it appears we had not joined up the dots on a just transition for the 35 workers involved in the sector.  That is a significant issue.</p> <p>The previous speaker is correct.  These people are working within the law and, for no reason bar a change in the law, they will be unemployed.  The people involved live in remote rural areas.  There is no Internet or Facebook there.  We need to find how we are going to sustain these people going forward so that they have a quality of life and the communities around them can survive.  It is very important we get clarity within the Bill that the process can be protected.  Otherwise, we are failing society itself and I would be deeply concerned about that.</p> <p>Another issue on which I tabled an amendment that was also ruled out of order was about how we can work with the Department and the family farms involved to get a fair package so they can move on to their next enterprise, whatever that will be.  It is not about mink farming.  This is about what happens to the next entity.  This is enabling legislation.  That is the real issue here.  We do not know what will happen in the next decade or so regarding other issues in agriculture.  This is a dramatic sea change in the past year.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Tim Lombard:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2466"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2466&amp;amp;pid=TimLombard&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=03"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I do not know where this is going to stop.  We need to put in place a fair process whereby everyone has the ability to work together.  Realistically, the Department holds all the cards here.  Realistically, the Department has the ability to draft legislation and, on the other side, to negotiate what it wants.  A fairer approach with some kind of mediation process would be much more appropriate.  You cannot draft legislation and mediate at the same time.  It just does not make logical sense.  As I said, it is very rare I would table an amendment, and I have tabled two to this Bill because we need to get clarity on this.  Even though there are small numbers involved here, I am fighting for the principle of the issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1646" speakername="Ollie Crowe" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#CC00200"><p>I welcome the Minister, Deputy McConalogue.  I thank him again for his help on this issue, both now and previously.</p> <p>From my own point of view, this is a controversial topic.  The Government is taking a rather extraordinary step to enforce the end of the sector.  That is fine and probably many people welcome it.  As been outlined by other Senators, however, at the end of the day, we are shutting down the sector.  It is essential this is done in a manner that leaves those who have made this sector their work for all their lives feeling respected and that they were treated with fairness.  That word &ldquo;fairness&rdquo; has been used by all Members in the House today.</p> <p>I have been a Member of this House for nearly two years.  I have never previously tabled an amendment to a Government Bill.  In that regard, I want to highlight in particular that the current approach would see only redundancy being provided for all statutory levels.  Obviously, this is the bare minimum.  We demand and encourage private companies to provide, where possible, additional redundancy that reflects the commitment their staff have given.  This will have a massive impact on 40 members of staff and 40 families.  Therefore, for the Department&rsquo;s proposal to cover only statutory redundancy seems to me to be a mistake.  I ask the Minister to consider this matter.  I have no doubt the Minister, Deputy McConalogue, will.</p> <p>To put this into the context of a human point of view, I, no more than other Senators, met the families last week and spoke to them at length.  That was the first occasion on which I met the people.  I know from my own experience of running a business about what is right and what is wrong.  The point that hit home to me while hearing about the 40 families was that, in one of those cases, I was told people would move from the village in which they currently live.  As a result, there would be one and possibly two fewer pupils going to the national school.  There were tears in those people&rsquo;s eyes while they told me that national schools would lose a teacher as a result.  This is the impact this is having on rural Ireland.  I do not think that should happen.</p> <p>No more than Senator Boyhan and other Senators in the House, when I spoke to the families, I had done a bit of research on the matter.  In terms how the compensation is calculated, I believe the proposal of the five-year term needs to be reviewed.  Certainly, as I said, I know from my own experience in business that there are periods when everything is going well and when business is going well.   There are also periods when that is not the case.  I think a five-year term is too minimal and needs to be broadened.  There is a clear and evident trend that this industry has rises, peaks and falls.  A longer term over ten years would be fairer to all, for those affected and for the Department.  I would provide that it would be a fair reflection and I would welcome the Minister's thoughts on this.</p> <p>I would also like to see more communication with the three farmers affected, regardless of whether an agreement can be reached in all topics.  It would be beneficial to have open lines of communication, as the Leader of the House, Senator Doherty, has said.  There should be close contact so that both the farmers and the Department can have a better understanding of where each side is coming from.  I will leave it at that for now.  I thank the Minister, Deputy McConalogue, again for his time today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#CC00300"><p>The Minister is very welcome.  I acknowledge the fact we have people from the industry here in the Chamber this afternoon.  We have Michael from west Kerry, who has worked in the industry for 37 years.  We have Una from Stradbally as well.  It is important to note they have taken the time to come up here again today.</p> <p>Let me be clear, my concern, as Senator Lombard has said, and he made a very strong point on it on the previous day, is for a just transition for these workers.  That is the issue at heart here.  I am surprised, particularly as the Minister comes from rural Ireland.  Just to be clear, I am from Limerick and I have no direct interest in this apart from justice for these workers.  Industries close all the time.  When I was a trade union official, unfortunately, you would break the bad news to the workers and then you would go into a negotiation and you negotiate a package in the best way you can to enable those people to move on.  I find it shocking and entirely unacceptable that, right now, we are looking at a Bill that will offer these workers statutory redundancy.  I do not know about the Minister but I do not believe I could sleep at night if I were to say to a worker who had given 37 years&rsquo; service and say, &ldquo;You know what, you're just getting statutory redundancy.  That's it.  Good luck.&rdquo;  The Government is sending that message, and I believe everyone in this Chamber - I am not being party political about this - is saying to the Minister that is not right.</p> <p>I am asking the Minister, and this echoes what others have said, to negotiate a package with these people.  It can be done very quickly.  It is done week in, week out in this country because, as we know, sometimes businesses close.  The Government is closing this business.  We need to come up to the mark.  We cannot turn our backs on these people.  Just to be clear, and I mean this respectfully, the Minister has the power and the responsibility to deal with this.  Please engage with these people to ensure they can move on with their lives and to ensure those words &ldquo;just transition&rdquo; have real meaning for these people, their communities and their livelihoods.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#CC00400"><p>As most Members of the House will know, I am a big advocate of fairly massive change in order that we deal with the climate crisis.  I believe we have a few years of very significant change ahead of us.  We will see sectors that will end or change.  How we do it really matters.  That is where it is about finding the commonality that is coming through, the idea of just transition, and what we do to bring that into effect.  Just transition is not simply about certain areas or regions.  It is around certain principles of how we approach the changes.  In some cases, it may be that for sectors that will have to make really huge changes, we will end up with something almost like the workplace subsidy schemes that we have had in the past, where we will have to have sectors supported by the State through a major transition in terms of reimagining what they do.  In other cases, as in this case, we will have areas where a sector will effectively end what it does.  We have to do that right.  There are three companies and 38 workers, as I understand it, but why people are working so hard to try to get it right and why the Minister is hearing this across the Chamber is because we know it sets as well a message for how we do things.</p><p>I tabled four amendments to this section.  I submitted three different approaches to how the issue could be addressed, all of which, unfortunately, were ruled out of order because they are amendments the Minister and the Department need to come forward with.  Looking at the amendments others have put forward and mine, one is in relation to including those redundancy and <i>ex gratia</i>payments that recognise terms of service and where someone puts his or her life, as a worker, into an industry.  We often talk about company owners, but workers put their lives into industries.  They use their best years in working for an industry, and that needs to be recognised, not simply that they are unemployed tomorrow and they have the statutory redundancy, but the fact of what they have invested.  That is where payments that recognise terms of service are so important.</p><p>I tabled another amendment that suggested there should be redundancy payments negotiated between the licensee and the workers, so if a company negotiates fair redundancy with its workers, that would be included in the compensation package set out in this Bill.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Alice-Mary Higgins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2480"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2480&amp;amp;pid=AliceMaryHiggins&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=03"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->In another approach, I gave entire discretion to the Minister to decide such further redundancy payments beyond the statutory minimum as the Minister may deem appropriate.</p><p>We are trying to problem solve.  These are various approaches to try to address the same issue, which is fundamentally that we have to ensure those who have worked in the industry are properly supported as the industry comes to an end and they are not simply left with a minimum and best of luck for the future.  I welcome the amendments tabled by Sinn F&eacute;in on particular employment and reskilling schemes.  These are practical proposals being brought forward from throughout the House.</p><p>My other amendment to the section proposed to address a potential perverse consequence, which would be in line with all of our international obligations and our policies on demolition.  As it stands, the Bill allows for compensation in respect of demolition where repurposing is not possible, but it does not allow for compensation in respect of repurposing.  We know from an embodied energy perspective we want to avoid demolition wherever we can.  The sensible thing is not to say compensation is only for knocking down a building but also that there is compensation if the building is adapted and put to a new purpose.  It is very important we do not create an incentive whereby people feel they have to knock down a building to get money.  This does not serve any of us.</p><p>I want to emphasise this is important as a point of principle, as people have said, in terms of how we move forward on just transition.  It needs to be fast and fair.  It is also important at a practical level.  There are practical solutions.  Given all our amendments have been ruled out of order, I hope the Minister tables Government amendments to address this issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#DD00200"><p>Well said.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1640" speakername="Pat Casey" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#DD00300"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House.  The debate has moved on from mink farming and it is about what happens as a result of the closure of a business.  Senator Higgins alluded to it.  We do not know where we are going.  We do not know what sector might be closed in another 15 or 20 years.  I want to speak about people in family businesses and who have spent the past 30 years building up those business.  If I were in their shoes, how would I feel?  I would have serious concerns about my own viability.  I would be more concerned about the 30 or 40 people I have employed for the past 30 years.  Where will their future lie?  What substitute employment will be put in place for them?  If I had put my life into my business and was told that business would no longer exist, not because of what I had done but because of a change in Government policy, would I be happy with what is on the table today?  Honestly, I probably would not.  This is the most honest answer I can give.</p> <p>I have many reservations about what is in the legislation relating employers.  I also have concerns about future activities.  I say this with regard to planning and trying to get planning permission in a rural area when something is demolished.  Something has to be worked out as to what can substitute for the existing buildings.  As soon as people get funding to demolish the buildings, are they guaranteed planning permission for a substitute business?  No, they are not.  I do not see this anywhere in the Bill.  Anyone from a rural area knows how difficult it is to get planning permission for a one-off house, never mind for an industry.  What will we substitute this industry with?  We do not know.  I hope the Minister will sit down and negotiate these issues, if at all possible.  I am imagining what it would be like if my business was taken from me tomorrow morning, not because of what I did but because of a change in Government policy.  How would I feel?  Hand on heart, I do not believe there has been enough negotiation or consultation.  We need to sit down again.  I hope the Minister can extend such an invitation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#DD00400"><p>I do not know whether it is because spring is in the air but this week in the House we have agreed on many issues, such as offering solidarity to Ukraine and today with Linda Ervine.  The Minister can hear there is a united front on addressing concerns for workers and farmers and the compensation scheme.  He can also hear from everybody who is speaking that we are all desperately trying to put forward credible solutions.  They have all been ruled out of order.  Everybody has engaged in the process and has tried to be constructive and table various measures the Minister could avail of to help these workers and farmers.</p> <p>For example, we tabled a suggestion on the environmental impact assessment.  We fear there is low-balling on the cost of demolition and, as Senator Higgins said, on refurbishment.  The lowest carbon building is the one already in existence.  We tabled concerns about the compensation scheme.  Senator Crowe spoke about this.  There is a five-year calculation rather than what happens in other jurisdictions, which is a ten-year calculation.  We are an outlier with other jurisdictions that have already done this.  The five-year period seems to coincide with a downturn in the industry.  Is this convenient?  I would like to hear why the Minister is choosing a five-year period and not a ten-year period when it is the standard as to how this is done.</p> <p>We have issues with specified assets.  Another amendment we tabled was on the training scheme.  My colleague, Deputy Carthy, and I are very familiar with the EU globalisation funds put in place.  When big multinational corporations moved from one jurisdiction in the EU to others, this funding was put in place to train workers and upskill them.  Why can this not be done on a much smaller scale through SOLAS?  I do not understand why this cannot be accepted as a credible proposal.</p> <p>To get to the crux of it, I am climate activist.  I engage with the Committee on the Environment and Climate Action.  We have fought very hard to get legally binding targets.  I am very concerned that many people in government speak about a just transition but they do not really understand what a just transition is.  If we are to fall now at the first hurdle, which is with a handful of workers, when it comes to the scale of change the State is facing in reaching our carbon emission targets, I am not just concerned for the workers we are speaking about today and for the farmers in the Chamber but also I am very concerned we are going to lose the public on this.  Whatever about Senator Gavan being from Limerick, I am from Tallaght.  We definitely do not have fur farmers there.</p> <p>How can an elected representative go into rural Ireland and say this is how the Government views a just transition but not even talk to the workers?  They will be offered statutory redundancy.  The Government will make sure the compensation comes in at the lowest possible nomination.  I would not like to be the Minister going into any rural community trying to sell a just transition if that is what it means to the Government.  I urge the Minister to listen to people in the House who are genuinely concerned for the workers and farmers here today and about the message it sends out to all of the other communities and sectors that will have to make radical changes if we are to meet our carbon emission targets and our carbon budgets in the very short window we have to do so.  I urge the Minister to sit down with the workers and negotiate a package that is fair and just.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#DD00500"><p>Well said.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#DD00600"><p>It was helpful to listen to the consistency of message and approach throughout the House.  I acknowledge the Minister is in a coalition government with the Green Party and Fine Gael.  I acknowledge the Green Party has set out to close down the mink farming industry.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Victor Boyhan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2463"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2463&amp;amp;pid=VictorBoyhan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=03"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->That is the price to be paid for going into a coalition government.  One party does not get everything the way it wants it and neither does any other party to the coalition.  That is the difficulty.  I also acknowledge that the Minister, Deputy Eamon Ryan, came into this House and talked about just transition.  He was doing the devil and all in terms of just transition, saying they would stay with rural Ireland and with rural farming, farmers and communities, yet the gap is becoming wider and wider.  It is not only three farmers who are affected.</p><p>I acknowledge that Michael from Waterville, County Kerry is here as well as Una from Stradbally, County Laois.  They have linked in with their public representatives and have shared with me, and no doubt with my fellow Senators, the difficulties they are encountering.  Ms Norma Moriarty, a Fianna F&aacute;il councillor from Waterville, County Kerry, said to me on the phone last that all they were looking for, and all she was looking for as a public representative and a member of the Minister's party, was fair play and a just settlement.  Let us have a negotiated settlement with these mink farmers.  That is not unreasonable. </p><p>I am opposed to mink farming in Ireland.  I welcome the fact the end of the mink farming industry for a number of reasons but that is not the issue here.  We have all moved on.  The farmers have moved on from the point of whether they can have a mink farm; they are not arguing to retain their mink farms or their livelihoods.  However, they have a long tradition in this business.  They have given their working lives, they have brought up their families and that is the principal income that has sustained them.  In many ways some of these are generational issues.  They have gone on a long time.  They have a particularly keen eye and skill for the breeding of mink.  They know their industry well and they have survived through difficult times in the past.  Over the past ten years a substantial number of years have been good years.  In the past two years with Covid-19 most people's businesses have suffered a little.  It is about being just, being fair and standing in solidarity with rural communities that the Minister knows well and has served exceptionally well.  With that, I echo Councillor Norma Moriarty's call for a negotiated settlement and a fair deal.  That is not too much to ask for.  I hope in his response he will share with us some of those ideas on those themes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1546" speakername="Charlie McConalogue" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#EE00200"><p>I thank Senators for their contributions.  There is a clear recognition that the State has decided to close down this industry and as a result of that is impacting on three farms and the livelihoods of those farmers as well as their employees.  The objective has always been to be fair and reasonable in recognition of the impact of what we are doing.  There has been ongoing engagement with fur farmers in that regard.  We also commissioned Grant Thornton Ireland to put together an independent assessment of the processes and procedures and reasonable ways to compensate for closing down businesses to inform how we go about it.  We have to have a verifiable process and evidential system for making decisions on what is appropriate compensation for the farmers and what is appropriate expenditure on behalf of the State.  That is important.  It has to be evidential.  It cannot be what a view is or a subjective opinion; we have to have an evidential basis on which to do it.  That is why we commissioned Grant Thornton Ireland to do that.</p> <p>This is a big decision.  It is a very significant one for the fur farmers.  I welcome the two representatives here today.  The third farm, which is not represented here, is based in my own county, in Glenties.  It is very challenging.  This is something that is no fault of theirs.  They have run their businesses entirely in accordance with the law.  They established their businesses in most instances very much with the encouragement and backing of the State, as a new industry back in the 1960s or 1970s when it first kicked off.  It was a much more significant industry over those years.  The number is now down to just three farms but there were many more farms in the past.  This is a Fianna F&aacute;il policy.  It is not happening because of the Green Party.  I put it in my manifesto before the public in the most recent general election.  Fine Gael may have had the same policy, although I am not sure.  The Green party had that policy.  This is agreed among the three Government parties and is a reflection of the fact that this is an industry that has moved on and is now no longer appropriate to the times we live in.  That is no reflection on the farmers at all because they have run their establishments and their farms to the highest standards that were always required and requested of them, and, indeed, provided employment to rural communities as well.  </p> <p>The objective here is to ensure that we are fair in what we do.  We have to have an objective and evidential basis for how we proceed.  I met with the farmers and their representatives three or four weeks ago regarding the outstanding issues.  I asked that there would be further engagement between the farmers and my officials, and agreed that I would meet them further to that as well.  I will do that because the regulations that this legislation will enable us to put the finer detail in place.  That finer detail is not inserted in primary legislation.  It is a matter for regulation and that is what the legislation provides for.  </p> <p>In regard to the amendments, one of the amendments for example talks about repurposing buildings instead of demolishing them, which is eminently sensible.  The focus of the legislation as it stands in this area has been on demolition and clean-up costs for buildings that do not have a further use but repurposing those buildings can provide them with a future use.  This suggestion is being made to my Department, and I am satisfied that it is possible, to use the demolition cost heading for repurposing instead if that is the wish of the businesses concerned and provides for a future use.  I will address this in the regulations.  Costs for repurposing a building that do not exceed the possible costs for demolition will be covered in the regulations.  That is what I will do.  This level of detail is not appropriate for primary legislation so I do not propose to accept the amendment.  It has been ruled out of order but it is entirely sensible.  If a building can be turned into something useful instead of spending money on tearing it, the same money can be used to repurpose it, which makes entire sense.  I will provide for that in the regulations. </p> <p>The other issue I have been reflecting on during our deliberations is support for employees because a number of employees on the three farms will be impacted.  A number of Senators have raised this issue and a number of Deputies raised it in the D&aacute;il as well.  It is a matter which is to be finalised as part of the regulation.  I discussed this with the farmers when I met with them three or four weeks ago and I have reflected further on it.  The legislation provides for statutory redundancy.  That is what the law of the State provides for but there is capacity within the regulations to reflect other costs and the impact on employees.  I will reflect this in the regulations and take it into account.  I will engage further with fur farmers on this but the legislation provides for that to be accommodated under the regulations.  I am very conscious of the issue.  These are employees in rural Ireland who will no longer have the jobs they have worked at.  It is something I will engage further on and provide for additional financial supports for the employees as appropriate in the regulations.  I will engage with the fur farmers directly on that as well.  </p> <p>Where there are other issues that Senators want to bring to my attention and want to have considered, I will consider them.  My core objective is to be fair and reasonable, and to properly reflect what we are doing and the impact it will have on the farmers and on their employees.  We also must be prudent and reasonable in how we spend public money but it has to be fair to the farmers as well.  There will be further engagement between my officials, the farmers and their representatives.  As I said to them when I met them recently, I will meet them again to discuss it further.  I received a letter after the latest meeting from the fur farmers who were not particularly happy with the meeting that we had.  I felt it was a productive meeting.  We did not agree, but the fact we did not agree on issues did not mean that the meeting was not useful.  What I said that day was that there would be further engagement with officials and I would meet with the farmers again.  I made that very clear.  I fully respect the position the farmers are in.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Charlie McConalogue:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2319"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2319&amp;amp;pid=CharlieMcConalogue&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=03"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> I want to ensure the final outcome is fair to them and I want to ensure that is accommodated in the regulation as well.  There will be further engagement on it.  As I have said, it is about balancing what is appropriate, fair and reasonable for the farmers - and we have different views on that with regard to the negotiations so far - with what is prudent from the point of view of the State.  The appropriate way to do that is through finalising the regulations after further engagement between me, as Minister, and the farmers with a view to being fair to them, which is the outcome I have wanted to ensure from the outset.  That is the way in which we are doing the legislation.  It will enable those regulations to be finalised.</p><p>It is appropriate that there be engagement between myself, as Minister and on behalf of the Department and the State as public money is spent, and the farmers themselves.  It is important that we do not do this in a way that puts the Seanad or the D&aacute;il in the middle of those negotiations and where every detail of the ultimate outcome of those negotiations is reflected in legislation.  If that were the case, you would have the Minister negotiating with the Oireachtas and asking whether something is enough and whether other things should be included and the Seanad or D&aacute;il being the forum for negotiation.  While many people would like to be in the middle of negotiations and making those final decisions, the appropriate place for that to happen is in engagements between me and the farmers, with the results to be finalised in regulation.</p><p>With regard to engaging further with Senators and taking on board their views, I am happy to do that.  I will certainly also have further meetings with the farmers.  I very much acknowledge the responsibility I have as Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine to try to get the right and fair outcome on behalf of the State.  A balance has to be struck.  It is an important balance.  It is a big responsibility, particularly with regard to being fair to those who are to be affected and whose livelihoods will no longer be available to them after we pass the legislation and introduce the regulations to make fur farming illegal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#FF00200"><p>I thank the Minister for that very comprehensive response to Senator Higgins.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#FF00300"><p>I thank the Minister for his constructive engagement.  He is right, there are parts of this that it is not appropriate for us to be involved in but there are also parts where our involvement, as legislators, is appropriate.  Given that our job in this House is to provide the Minister with legislation, including legislation that gives him the power to make regulations, it is important that we make sure it is as clear as possible with regard to what we include.  It is useful that, even after Committee Stage, we still have Report Stage to go through.  I am not asking the Minister to come back to us to lay out his proposals and tell us how the negotiations are going but I encourage him to come back to us with amendments that reflect the regulations and the elements we have discussed.</p> <p>I am concerned.  I appreciate the Minister having taken on board the sensible point, which is complementary to Senator Casey's point, with regard to the difference between planning and starting a whole new thing and repurposing something.  I recognise the need for a cost limit and the issue of that being equivalent to the cost of demolition.  That is a sensible provision.  However, I am worried about the existing wording.  I am a stickler for wording.  It currently only refers to "demolition and clean-up costs in respect of the removal of any buildings [...] that cannot reasonably be used for any other purpose".  The regulations do not directly empower the Minister to give compensatory payment in respect of repurposing.  A change in the language is required to do that rather than saying we interpret the provisions in a certain way.  In fact, that is explicitly precluded because demolition compensation may only be paid in respect of buildings that cannot reasonably be used for any other purpose.  We want to allow for compensation in respect of buildings that can reasonably be used for another purpose.  Again, this is aimed at strengthening the Minister's hand as he makes the regulations and at giving him the mandate he needs to deliver the very sensible solution he outlined.  I am concerned that the legislation, as currently drafted, does not include that among the matters he may make regulation in respect of.  In fact, it explicitly precludes that.  I do not want the Minister, or some other Minister, to come up against that as a concern when he has goodwill.  We want to give him the right mandate.</p> <p>Similarly, the matters for which the Minister is being mandated by this legislation to make compensatory payments includes statutory redundancy in light of section 19 of the Redundancy Payments Act 1967.  With regard to my own amendments, although I am sure others were tabled, I did not try to specify what the outcome should be.  I referred to "such further redundancy payments as may be negotiated" and "such further redundancy payments beyond the statutory minimum as the Minister may deem appropriate".  I was not trying to say what the outcome would be but to ensure that, if this legislation passes this House, the Minister will have a mandate and the full list of topics included in the legislation he will need to deliver the kind of positive outcomes he has discussed.</p> <p>The Minister has mentioned engagement with the farmers multiple times.  That is really good and important.  However, it is important that he hear from this House that it is not just about engagement with the farmers but also engagement with the workers.  Even though there has been very good solidarity between the farmers and the workers on this issue, at the end of the day, the farmers are not the representatives of the workers.  It is a limited number, 38, and it would be very useful if the Minister were to engage directly with them so that he has a sense of their needs.  I know there is common purpose in that regard but engagement with farmers is only one piece.  The other big stakeholder is the workers and a little bit of direct engagement may be required.  I thank the Minister for his constructive engagement with us.  He can hear that, as a House, we are very interested in constructive engagement but we might need to strengthen the legislation as well as bringing those matters into the more discretionary space of regulations.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#FF00400"><p>I thank the Minister for his response but I have absolutely no interest in being involved in negotiations and I am sure nobody else here does.  We are certainly not going to do so in this House, in the D&aacute;il or in a committee room.  However, I do acknowledge that there are workers who do not think what is being offered to them is fair.  We also have three farmers who absolutely refute the contention that they have been treated fairly.  I totally understand that the statutory redundancy legislation ties the Minister's hand and limits him to two weeks but, as Senator Higgins has said, we can absolutely make provisions in regulations.  It is only fair for the Minister to let us know what his anticipated plans are so that we can constructively proceed with the legislation to make sure it is passed so that the regulations can be drafted.  However, if we do not know what is going to be in them, it makes it very onerous for us to say whether we agree with sections of the Bill.</p> <p>I completely concur with the Minister regarding the fact that he needs a verifiable process and that the three years was moved to five years.  I know colleagues here have suggested that we go to ten but I understand why the Minister does not want to go to ten and the precedent that it might set.  Senator Boylan is right.  We have a long road ahead of us and other businesses will be forced to close by the State's actions but we need to recognise that there are people here who cannot earn a living anymore.  We have people who have spent millions of their own euros investing in and improving their farms because the State and the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine made them do so over recent years and they are going to get absolutely zero compensation.  Regardless of the language used, I cannot think how anybody could think that is morally responsible or ethical.  It is not.  I understand the Minister wants this legislation passed.  So do we.  However, we absolutely need to know what his anticipated plans are for compensation for the workers and for fair compensation for these farmers, or at least reimbursement of some of the money they have spent on their land over recent years.  What is on offer today is absolutely not fair.  We genuinely need to be fair to the workers and the farmers.  Any understanding of a just transition, regardless of one's party, must include compensating people when we take their ability to earn a living away from them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#FF00500"><p>I will be brief on this.  I waited for the Minister's response and I have taken into account what everybody else has said and it is really important that we get a fair deal for the three farmers involved and for their employees.  As Senator Higgins has said, there is a constructive way forward.  In his reply, the Minister said twice publicly that he will meet the farmers again.  It is really important and positive that we take that step forward.</p> <p>I know some people did not like it but, if you look up our last election manifesto, you will see that it was Fianna F&aacute;il policy to get rid of fur farming.  I know that not everybody agreed with it but that was our policy.  I was a Deputy at the time and, in our discussions on that, we made it quite clear that there would have to be proper compensation for the farmers and their employees.  Everybody is of one mind on that.  How we progress is the important thing.  However, the Minister has made it quite clear today that he is going to meet these people.  I know they were not happy with the last meeting.  The Minister has acknowledged that.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Eugene Murphy:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2444"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2444&amp;amp;pid=EugeneMurphy&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=03"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Maybe with another meeting or two we can make some worthwhile progress to get a proper solution to this, so those people are happy.  As Senator Doherty said, these people have paid their taxes, their employees have paid their taxes and they have contributed to the State.  This is happening because of changes to Government and EU policy.  I agree that we must look after these people when they are suffering because of a change in policy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#GG00200"><p>I thank the Minister for his response.  It would be helpful if the Minister was to give a commitment to sit down with the farmers and the workers next week.  We are back in here to debate again next week and it would just give substance to the debate.  Chatting to colleagues from the industry, I am hearing the concern that there is nothing tangible here at the moment.  The Bill is not adequate on the compensation, and in fairness, the Minister has acknowledged that.  I want to acknowledge that the Minister has acknowledged that.</p> <p>I put it to the Minister that this is not rocket science.  If the Minister could give a commitment that he and his Department will engage constructively in the next week on this issue, and will sit down to meet with the workers and the farmers in the next week, this would build confidence.  We would then be able to see a process on the way to fix the concerns that we have.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1666" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#GG00300"><p>I acknowledge the Minister's contribution, and also those contributions from Members of the Seanad.  I look at this process and I just wonder.  At the moment we are bringing legislation through and then we will have a regulation coming afterwards.  I understand that process, but I believe that the spirit of my amendment, which was to have a mediator, is a pragmatic approach.  It is very hard to bring the legislation through and then on the other side be the person who is going to debate what the compensation package will be, which in effect is what the Department is going to do.  I feel that the Minister and the Department have tied one arm behind the farmers' backs.  They will have no control and no ability.  They will have only a minor negotiation and if they are not happy they are not happy and that will be it.</p> <p>When one considers what it is we are talking about, it is about the principle.  We are closing down an industry, rightly or wrongly, because of Government policy.  That Government policy is a huge step because there could be other changes in Government policy going forward and we could have more industries closed down.  Look at where these areas are and the lack of a just transition fund.  Other Members said that schools might even close.  That would be a significant issue.</p> <p>We need to see, if we possibly could, how a just transition package could be put in place with these three communities that are affected.  There does not seem to be anything in this Bill about that.  We have continually heard the terminology of "a just transition" in other areas, but I believe this is the first time it has come to the Seanad in a piece of legislation that one would say there needs to be an acknowledgement of a just transition.  I do not believe we are seeing this in the Bill.  I am deeply concerned about that.</p> <p>We all know that the changes to come in agriculture are going to be severe.  We all know the changes will have a huge impact on our communities.  If we fail at the first item, which is the first piece of legislation coming forward, then I am very concerned about the entire agricultural industry going forward.  As other Senators have stated, we will see significant changes in agriculture in the next 20 to 30 years.  I cannot tell what those changes will be but they will have an impact on rural Ireland.  We need to get this first step right and we need to get the principles behind it right.  If we can do that, then hopefully we can move forward and the communities affected by these closures can be protected.  It is key.  We need to protect these communities if we possibly can.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#GG00400"><p>I remind Members that we are to adjourn after 60 minutes.  There are three minutes left and three Senators indicating.  I will take Senators Boyhan, Crowe and Casey, in that order, but if Senator Boyhan is still talking in three minutes-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#GG00500"><p>I will exercise my three minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#GG00600"><p>The debate is adjourning in three minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.173" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#GG00700"><p>I thank the Minister for coming to the House, and I really do appreciate his very genuine offer of engagement with the farmers.  It is important.  I also concur with the comments of the Leader of the House, Senator Doherty.  Senator Doherty has previously spoken about leverage.  I do not like using that word in politics, and especially in a constructive Chamber such as this.  We do, however, have some sort of leverage at the moment, which is that we are a House of legislation.  We are trying to perfect this and ensure that the best possible arrangements fall out of this legislation that we are comfortable with and can stand over.  Senator Lombard said that it is important for our rural communities, but it is about a negotiated settlement.   I do not believe this is unfair.  Hopefully, as a result of the Minister's input, we will be in a very much better place next week.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.174" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1646" speakername="Ollie Crowe" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#GG00800"><p>I thank the Minister.  The only request I would make is for face-to-face meetings with the families and the officials.  I welcome the fact that the Minister wants to meet the families on the second occasion.  The Minister has shown leadership across the State, visiting every mart in every county.  The Minister knows the issues on the ground.  My point is that there is a human side to the impact and that the officials would have face-to-face meetings with the families to understand the issues that I have heard about.  That would be very welcome.  I compliment the Minister.  The second meeting is in place and progress has been made.  I thank the Minister for his leadership on the issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1640" speakername="Pat Casey" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#GG00900"><p>I will briefly focus on the verifiable evidence.  I will go back to my own situation.  If the Minister was to come to me and say that he was going to base my compensation on the past five years of my business, but 40% of that time was two years of the worst years experienced in my business, I would not accept it.  If it was five normal years of business I might have a better understanding of it.</p> <p>If the Minister was shutting me down tomorrow morning, and going through what my industry went through the in past two years, which were the two worst years in the history of the hospitality sector, and if the Minister is asking that 40% of the compensation is to be made up based on including two of the worst years in the history of the industry, I would have reservations about this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#GG01000"><p>We are to adjourn shortly and perhaps the Minister's response to this part of the debate can be heard today rather than on another day.  Is that agreed? Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.177" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1546" speakername="Charlie McConalogue" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#GG01100"><p>I thank the Acting Chairman and I thank all of the Senators for their contributions.  Some of the issues included the repurposing.  I have clearly said that this would be dealt with.  I will deal with this as part of the regulation, for which I have the capacity.  My clear advice is that I have the capacity, as it stands, to be able to do that.</p> <p>Likewise, with regard to additional financial assistance for the workers and employees and the impact on them, this is something I will deal with as part of the regulation.  I have given a clear commitment on that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#GG01200"><p>Is it possible to do this in the legislation?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.179" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1546" speakername="Charlie McConalogue" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#GG01300"><p>I was taken aback when coming here today and I realised that we were only in for one hour and were adjourning for the day at 3.45 p.m.  We must work our way through this legislation and finalise it.</p> <p>The breeding season is due to start normally around now.  The onus is on me and the responsibility is on me as the Minister, on behalf of the Government, to engage with the farmers to bring this to a conclusion.  I cannot stand over a situation where I am doing that with the Seanad in the middle of that negotiation where that negotiation must be represented to the very fine detail in the primary legislation, or where we need to know the anticipated plans, or to come back next week with something tangible.</p> <p>The executive role for me as the Minister is to be fair, to work off the principles of the legislation that is there, and to finalise that agreement with the farmers directly on the basis of the legislation that is provided here.  That is the situation we are in.</p> <p>There is an urgency around bringing this to a conclusion.  I will be meeting with the farmers again after the further engagement between the farmers and my officials.  We do, however, need to bring the legislation to a conclusion to enable the implementation of the Government policy.  As I have said very clearly, I absolutely accept the onus is on me as the Minister to ensure that there is a fair conclusion here and a fair outcome that reflects the implications and impact of what it is we are doing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#GG01400"><p>I thank the Minister.  I also thank the Members for agreeing to that.  The Order of Business as agreed this morning was for one hour and to adjourn after 60 minutes.  We have done that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.181" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Progress reported; Committee to sit again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.182" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#GG01700"><p>When is it proposed to sit again?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.183" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022030300002#GG01800"><p>At 2.30 p.m. on Tuesday, 8 March.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-03-03a.184" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar athl&oacute; ar 3.50 p.m. go dt&iacute; 2.30 p.m., D&eacute; M&aacute;irt, an 8 M&aacute;rta 2022.</p><p>The Seanad adjourned at 3.50 p.m. until 2.30 p.m. on Tuesday, 8 March 2022.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>