<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.2" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 14:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.4" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.5" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Ivana Bacik that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, she proposes to raise the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Education and Skills to outline the measures he proposes to take in respect of ongoing issues concerning school admissions and governance at St. Patrick&rsquo;s national school, Greystones, County Wicklow.</blockquote> <p><!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">An Cathaoirleach:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1988"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1988&amp;amp;pid=DenisODonovan&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I have also received notice from Senator Catherine Noone of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to provide an update on the progress of the healthy weight for Ireland action plan. </blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Fintan Warfield of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to address calls for drug testing services at music festivals.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Robbie Gallagher of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine to address the increase in bovine tuberculosis.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator P&aacute;draig Mac Lochlainn of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Education and Skills to make provision for the 30 pupils without a place on buses to secondary schools in Buncrana, County Donegal.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to outline his plans to approve access to the drug Spinraza for children who suffer from spinal muscular atrophy, SMA.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Michelle Mulherin of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government to provide funding for the construction of new rural group water schemes in the areas of Downpatrick, Kilmurray and Furmoyle, County Mayo.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Colm Burke of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Justice and Equality to establish a new system for unidentified human remains which will centralise information and streamline the identification process.  </blockquote><p>The matters raised by the Senators are suitable for discussion.  I have selected the matters raised by Senators Bacik, Noone, Warfield and Gallagher and they will be taken now.  The other Senators may give notice on another day of the matters that they wish to raise.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.8" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#B00200">Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.9" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#B00300">School Admissions</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#B00400"><p>I welcome the Minister for Education and Skills to the House.  I am very grateful to him for coming in to deal with this matter personally.  I raise the matter of the need for the Minister to outline the measures he proposes to take in respect of ongoing issues concerning school admissions and governance at St. Patrick's national school, Greystones, County Wicklow.  These issues concern the linking of school admission policies with church attendance.  Has the Minister engaged directly with the school's patron to ensure these issues are resolved satisfactorily?</p> <p>I raised this issue on the Order of Business last week.  It has also been raised in the media and has been in the public domain.  I understand local Deputies in Wicklow are also engaging with the Minister on it.  Constituents of mine in the Dublin university constituency raised with me their serious concerns around a change in implementation of enrolment policy in the named school, where there has been a linking of attendance at church with school admission.  This change in implementation of policy has resulted in the resignation of the principal, who I am told by all involved is highly experienced and respected, and the resignation of a board member.  My constituents have raised with me that the manner in which the patron, the Church of Ireland, is engaging with these issues and in particular the manner in which it is engaging with parents raise serious concerns.  I am told there was an extraordinary meeting of the parent-teacher association in August at which a strong majority expressed their concern and dissatisfaction with the way the board had handled the matter and expressed their support for the principal.  She has, in fact, resigned and I understand her position has now been advertised.</p> <p>My constituents have asked me to raise with the Minister their concerns about the governance of the school and the change in implementation of the admissions policy and they ask that the Department of Education and Skills intervene.  Will the Minister indicate what, if any, engagement he has had with the patron and whether he proposes to appoint an inspector or some other mechanism to ensure this matter can be resolved?  I should say that a contrary view has also been expressed to me by others involved in this issue who are satisfied with the board of management.  I know there are various issues at stake and do not want to get involved in the detail of the matter.</p> <p>To me, it seems this issue should be dealt with in the more general context.  The Minister has stated his policy, which I absolutely support, of seeking to change the position whereby religious adherence and denomination are the deciding factors in school admissions policy.  This matter raises broader issues about the general context of the need for separation of church and State in education, about which I have spoken many times.  I have sought a more general debate in the Seanad on that.  Some aspects of what the principal has said are in the public domain.  One of the points made was that admission to State-funded education cannot and must not be an adjunct to or a collateral benefit of parochial engagement.  This raises broader issues around schools' entitlement to require that parents demonstrate church attendance or engagement in a particular parish in order to ensure that their children become enrolled in particular schools.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Ivana Bacik:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2248"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2248&amp;amp;pid=IvanaBacik&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->What does the Minister propose to do about this issue and, more broadly, about the issue of linking school admission policies with church or religious attendance and engagement?</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.12" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#C00200">Visit of Egyptian Delegation</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#C00300"><p>Before I ask the Minister to respond, I am sure the Members of the House and the Minister will wish to join in welcoming a parliamentary delegation from Egypt led by His Excellency, Dr. Ali Abdul Aal, Speaker of the Egyptian House of Representatives.  On my behalf and on behalf of all my colleagues in Seanad &Eacute;ireann, I extend a very warm welcome to them and good wishes for a successful visit to Ireland.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.14" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#C00350">Commencement Matters (Resumed)</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.15" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#C00400">School Admissions</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#C00500"><p>I thank Senator Bacik for raising this issue.  To put it in context, it is important to state that, under our education system, patrons' boards of management have an independent role.  It is a right of religious institutions to run their own schools, which is protected in the Constitution, and to have their own characteristic spirit, but they must do so within the laws of the land.</p> <p>The issue of admission to schools is governed by two sets of legislation, the first of which are the Education Acts.  As the Senator will be aware, under our system, parents have a right to choose whatever school they wish their children to attend and schools must have an admission policy which must be available for inspection by parents.  That admissions policy must be non-discriminatory and be applied fairly in respect of all those who apply.  The other element is the Equal Status Act, to which the Deputy referred, which provides protection to schools at present which select on the basis of religion in preference to others.  As the Deputy is aware, I have been a critic of this and have introduced legislation to change that, which was recently passed in Seanad.</p> <p>The position regarding decisions on admission by a board of management or a school are appealable to the Department of Education and Skills.  Therefore, the Department or, in the case of the Equal Status Act, the Workplace Relations Commission will assess whether the school has applied the admission policy fairly and whether it has been done in accordance with the law as set out.  To my knowledge, an appeal regarding unfair admission has not been made at this point to the Department.</p> <p>As the Deputy will be aware, I hope to implement, at the earliest possible date, the new provisions of the Education (Admission to Schools) Bill.  As she will know from discussions in this House, while I have sought to remove religion as a criterion for admission generally, I have provided that a child of a minority religion should be able to apply to a school of that ethos and be given preference in view of the effort we make to ensure that a child or his or her parents gets access to their preferred education.</p> <p>This measure which I have introduced is proportionate.  It does not provide protection to the use of religion in the case of children of a majority religion because they have 18 out of every 20 schools from which to choose, but a child of a minority religion could have only one of every 20 schools from which to choose.  This is a proportionate and fair provision.</p> <p>In assessing that, it is important that consideration is given to what the legislation is providing for.  A primary school may give priority to the admission of a student where the school is satisfied that the student concerned is a member of a minority religion and the school provides a programme of religion instruction or religious education which is of the same religious ethos or a similar religious ethos to the religious ethos of the minority religion of the student concerned.  The school will only be allowed to take account of the statement that the applicant has provided and any evidence that the applicant has provided that he or she is a member of a minority religion.  Schools that admit students of a minority religion in accordance with this provision of the Act will not be permitted to rank those students according to the particular denomination or religion of the child concerned.  I do not believe that linking school admission with church attendance would meet the provisions of the law.</p> <p>It should be said also that these provisions only apply where a school is oversubscribed.  Where a school is not oversubscribed, it is obliged to take all applicants, regardless of religion.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Richard Bruton:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=119"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=119&amp;amp;pid=RichardBruton&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This is a significant step forward in giving fair access for all parents.  I have also amended the provisions of section 29 of the Act, which continues to prevail, so that where a student feels he or she has been unreasonably refused access, he or she has the right to make an appeal.  I will continue to reform in this area.  One of the Bills I hope to shortly present to the House is a parent and student charter Bill, which would ensure that parents are consulted when there is any proposal to change admission policy.  The future direction of reform is to be more embracing of parents and students in the running of schools while respecting the distinctive role of the patron and the board.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#D00200"><p>Is the Senator satisfied with the reply?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#D00300"><p>I will make some very brief follow-up remarks.  I thank the Minister for his very full response to my question.  I am grateful to him for outlining the changes the new legislation will make.  When are they likely to come into effect?  I support the Minister, and we supported the Bill in the Oireachtas.  I am very grateful to him for stating that he does not believe linking school admission with church attendance would meet the provisions of the new Act, once in force.  I agree with him that the Act is a significant step and is very positive.</p> <p>I am also grateful to the Minister for outlining that he will introduce a parent and student charter.  Will that enable parents to have an input if there is any change in admissions policy, even if the change is to the interpretation or application of the policy rather than to its wording?  There is a subtle difference but a very important one in the context of this particular case, and possibly in other cases.  Parents should be informed even where there is a proposal to change the way a policy is being interpreted or applied.</p> <p>There is a broader issue concerning church-State relations in education.  I raised in the Seanad previously the issue of teacher training and a concern about different strands of admission with different CAO points for admission to different religious denominational teacher training courses, at DCU in particular.  I will raise that with the Minister perhaps in a separate context but there is a bigger issue to be addressed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#D00400"><p>We are well over the time limit now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#D00500"><p>We must recognise there is diversity and diversity is a good thing.  That means there needs to be a diversity of teachers capable of maintaining the ethos of a given school.  We have recognised that the right to have distinctive strands of teachers should be protected.</p> <p>The parent and student charter legislation will come before the House for a thorough debate.  It is my intention that schools would involve parents in any significant change that would impact on them.  When we debate the Bill in detail Senator Bacik will have a chance to see whether the phraseology meets her concerns.  I do not have the wording to hand to verify the exact phraseology being used.</p> <p>I am in consultation with the Attorney General's office to ensure that the way I proceed to implement the different sections of the Bill is legally sound and proper.  I hope those consultations will be completed shortly, at which point I will be in a position to make known the schedule of implementation.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.22" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#D00550">Obesity Strategy</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#D00700"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Catherine Byrne, to the House.  Senator Noone has four minutes to outline her case.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#D00800"><p>This Commencement debate is on the topic of obesity and concerns the need for the Minister for Health to provide an update on the healthy weight for Ireland action plan.  The plan is now two years old and there has been no update on its progress despite a pledge to conduct mid-term reviews and report annually.</p> <p>Cancer Research UK launched a campaign this week warning that obesity is set to overtake smoking as a cause of cancer in women.  The low level of public knowledge of the risks and links between obesity and cancer is very serious.  Ireland is facing a silent epidemic of obesity and Irish people are on course to be the heaviest in Europe.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Catherine Noone:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2354"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2354&amp;amp;pid=CatherineNoone&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The action plan A Healthy Weight for Ireland, launched in 2016, contained a pledge to report annually, but its progress has not been reported on.  Tackling the rise of obesity must be made a priority as we are sleepwalking into a nightmare scenario.  It is an issue I have raised numerous times in the House.  By allowing obesity levels to rise unchecked, we are putting a massive additional strain on the health service.  At the same time, the population is ageing, which will put its own strain on the health service.</p><p>I am aware that the Minister of State is doing a good deal of work in this area.  I would be grateful to receive some response on the progress made and any further measure that will be implemented to deal with this very serious issue that places a huge burden on the State.  We talk about the fiscal space, but the fiscal space would be much larger if we dealt with the problem of obesity to prevent cancer and diabetes related illnesses and a myriad others due to lifestyle.  It is very difficult to quantify the cost, but it is estimated to be approximately &euro;2.6 billion annually.  We could do a great deal for citizens with that money if we could adopt a better approach to our lifestyles.  As a nation, we are becoming fatter, with all of the risks that come with it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1307" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#E00200"><p>I thank the Senator for tabling this Commencement matter.  I know how much the issue means to her.  I have heard her speak many times about the issue of obesity and know that she has a real passion to ensure, through A Healthy Weight for Ireland, we will proceed to implement our strategy to tackle obesity.</p><p>I thank the Senator for giving me the opportunity to speak to the House about the important topic of obesity, which is a public health priority.  The House is already aware that the Government's national obesity policy and action plan were launched in September 2016 under the umbrella of the Healthy Ireland agenda.  They recommended that an evaluation framework for progress in implementing the plan be designed.  The Department of Health has initiated this evaluation under step 10 of the plan and will report annually, with the first report expected in 2019.  The House will be aware that the policy prescribed ten steps forward that would be taken to prevent overweight and obesity.  Some early progress on actions under these steps has been achieved.  Of course, as with all of our work under Healthy Ireland, cross-departmental and cross-sectoral co-operation is fundamental to our approach to implementation.  This is reflected in the national obesity policy implementation oversight group which has been established under the chairmanship of the Department of Health and consists of representatives from a range of Departments and agencies.  Sub-groups on reformulation and healthy eating have been established as initial priority areas for action.  The sub-group on reformulation recently held a workshop with key food sector stakeholders.  A sugar sweetened drinks tax commenced on 1 May this year and work is under way with the Department of Finance on an evaluation of this measure.  Engagement is also continuing with other Departments to support the work of stakeholders involved in planning and developing the built environment.  I am pleased to advise the House that it is intended to hold a stakeholder forum in November under this theme.  In addition, a voluntary code of practice for food and beverages promotion, marketing and sponsorship has also been developed involving representatives from the food industry, the advertising sector, statutory agencies and various Departments.  The code was published in February and work is under way to implement it.</p><p>New healthy eating guidelines, a food pyramid and supporting resources have been published and circulated.  Work has also commenced to develop healthy eating guidelines for the one to five years age group.  The House may also wish to know that new nutrition standards for schools, with an initial focus on school meal programmes funded by the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection, have also been developed.  They were developed with the assistance of <i>safe</i>food, the Health Service Executive, the school meals programme in the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection and the Department of Education and Skills.</p><p>Other work taking place includes implementation of a breastfeeding action plan and a new Making Every Contact Count brief intervention framework; the appointment last year of Professor Donal O&rsquo;Shea as first clinical lead for obesity; the introduction in the general practitioner under-sixes contract of health assessments, including weight checks; and a five-year communications campaign called START that supports parents in making healthy choices surrounding food and activity.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Catherine Byrne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2186"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2186&amp;amp;pid=CatherineByrne&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Under the broader Healthy Ireland agenda, a number of other major initiatives support the obesity policy, including a national physical activity plan.  Implementation of the plan is well under way, in collaboration with the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport and a range of other stakeholders.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#F00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  I thought there would be an annual report in advance of 2019.  It does not make much sense to me.  There is an urgency to this issue, and the idea that we would put a plan in place in 2016 and not get any feedback on it for three years does not make sense to me.</p> <p>In addition, I have difficulty with the code of practice to which the Minister of State refers.  By its voluntary nature there is no impetus on television or radio providers to do anything about it.  When one watches the children's movies and so forth on RT&Eacute;, there are rules where it needs to be more than 50% children who are watching it.  The broadcasting agencies have all sorts of statistics about how those movies are mostly watched by adults, but I do not buy that.  I do not think adults are sitting down watching the children's movie on a Saturday.  Some of them may be in the house, but how do the agencies quantify who is actually looking at the television?</p> <p>Advertising is still allowed to be shown at that time, and there needs to be a more mandatory level when it comes to advertising.  There needs to be a watershed whereby after a certain time in the evening these types of sugary and fattening sweet drinks, food and confectionary are not advertised, in order that children do not see these advertisements.  There is a problem with the online space as well, which must also be seriously addressed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1307" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#F00300"><p>I understand the Senator's frustration with the annual report. I had hoped I would have been able to give a little more information on that in my reply this afternoon.  I will proceed, however, to look at it again.</p> <p>On the code of practice and its voluntary nature, one might say that when it was launched it was conservative.  In the meantime, however, there has been much action on the code of practice, and many agencies have come on board.  I know a number of shops, outlets and other areas are also beginning to take it on board.  I was struck in my local supermarket by how it has been rearranged in order that fruit and vegetables are at the front of the shop rather than what had been there in the first place.  It is a voluntary code of practice and we need to continue to work on it.  We might need to emphasise the fact that responsibility comes with having a business and with serving young children, and this is seen on a daily basis.</p> <p>When the sugar tax came in, like many people I was a bit wary of it and where it would go.  As I have continued in my journey in this Department, however, I see the changes as soft drinks manufacturers are starting to take on board many of the things that were raised.  I will take into account the Senator's point about online services and I will ensure the Department reverts to the Senator.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.30" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#F00350">National Drugs Strategy</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#F00400"><p>I call Senator Warfield.  The Minister of State, Deputy Byrne, will also take this matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#F00500"><p>I thank the Chair for facilitating this conversation about harm reduction, and I welcome the Minister of State to the House.  I commend the HSE and the Department of Health for their work in informing drug users about the safe use of drugs.  It is proactive, realistic and life saving.</p> <p>According to a Eurobarometer poll in 2014, the use of psychoactive drugs among 15 to 24 year olds in Ireland is the highest in Europe.  This also extends to music festivals, where MDMA, ecstasy, ketamine and cocaine are all common.  I also commend the specific HSE guidelines on music festival attendees or festival-goers.  It advises that it is always safer not to use ecstasy or MDMA but, if one does, one should test-dose a new batch and begin with a low dose of one quarter of a pill.  Obviously, these illicit drugs do not go through any regulatory testing at all.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Fintan Warfield:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2458"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2458&amp;amp;pid=FintanWarfield&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->There are reports that bad batches have caused havoc among Irish festivalgoers and resulted in the deaths or emergency health reactions of festival attendees.  Not a summer goes by without news here or in Britain of such incidents.  Conversations regarding drug testing at festivals have taken place this summer and Dr. Eamon Keenan of the HSE has called for its introduction.  Having passed a policy through the Sinn F&eacute;in Ard-Fheis, I put out a statement on the matter and the Ana Liffey drug project has also spoken on it.  I commend Ana Liffey, the HSE, Help Not Harm and Electric Picnic, all of which engaged in the provision of harm reduction services at music festivals this summer.  We cannot ignore the inevitability that drugs will be used by a percentage of people attending festivals.  Most importantly, we must recognise that no amount of literature, education or one-to-one advice will ever inform a person about what constitutes a safe dose of an illicit or unknown drug.</p><p>In May this year, two festival goers in Portsmouth died after taking pills which contained three times the typical dose of ecstasy.  It is always safer not to use unknown or illicit drugs at all and they are illegal.  However, we must be conscious, given their prevalence, that putting our heads in the sand or condemning those who partake has failed completely.  We are doing very well in advancing the harm reduction conversation but we can do more.  While I do not wish to pre-empt the work of the national drugs strategy, which is examining the issue, I ask the Minister of State whether the Department will support initiatives similar to The Loop initiative in Britain?  The Loop offers a confidential drug-testing service at festivals in Britain.  A festival goer can provide a sample and will be informed what constitutes it.  The sample is then destroyed in the context of the criminalisation that exists in Britain.  Will the Department consider funding a similar initiative in the absence of decriminalisation?  The British Government has brought various stakeholders together, including police, health professionals, festival organisers and NGOs.  The appetite exists in Ireland and we can achieve this in the absence of decriminalisation.  I would welcome a statement from the Department on the matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1307" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#G00200"><p>I thank Senator Warfield for his interesting and touching contribution on the initiative in respect of drug-taking at festivals.  I also thank him for giving me the opportunity to update the House on harm-reduction measures.</p> <p>Through its strategy, Reducing Harm, Supporting Recovery, the Government is committed to a health-led approach to drug use.  While the advice from the Department of Health and the HSE is that people attending festivals should inform themselves about the dangers of taking drugs and, preferably, should not take drugs at all, reducing the harms caused to individuals, families and communities by substance misuse is at the core of the strategy.  Harm reduction incorporates a spectrum of strategies from safer use to managed use and abstinence.  The HSE has previously undertaken awareness campaigns, including "What's in the Pill", and in July, I launched the HSE's harm reduction campaign in relation to cocaine and crack cocaine.  In addition, the HSE has issued harm reduction information to festivalgoers based on UK reports from similar events.</p> <p>We are all too familiar with the fact that recreational settings such as nightclubs and festivals are associated with use of drugs, including ecstasy, amphetamines and new psychoactive substances.  The risks associated with the use of drugs in these settings may be increased if it is in combination with other drugs, particularly alcohol.  While the provision of drug-testing kits at nightclubs and festivals, for example, might allow people who use drugs to gain feedback regarding the content and potency of what they are consuming, this approach has been criticised as having the potential to inform people who use drugs that what they are consuming is safe when that is not the case.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Catherine Byrne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2186"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2186&amp;amp;pid=CatherineByrne&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I also understand from the evidence review that doubts remain regarding the accuracy and consistency of commonly used testing equipment.</p><p>The HSE's addiction services has had preliminary discussions with emergency health providers who attend music events.  It has examined emerging approaches that provide targeted preventive messages to recreational drug users.  Our strategy, Reducing Harm, Supporting Recovery, looked at evidence related to interventions to tackle the drug problem, including drug testing as a harm reduction measure.  It includes a specific action which aims to strengthen early harm reduction responses to current and emerging trends, as well as patterns of drug use.  This will be delivered by establishing a working group to examine the evidence on early harm reduction responses such as drug testing.  The working group will draw together the relevant stakeholders and examine the available evidence, along with best practice models from other countries to help determine the appropriate response in Ireland.  The Department of Health and the HSE aim to establish this working group in 2019.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#H00200"><p>That was a comprehensive response.  I did not take the chance to commend the Minister of State on launching the cocaine and crack initiative.  There was criticism and pressure about this.  I commend her on showing leadership on the issue.</p> <p>It is welcome that the Department of Health and the HSE will establish a working group to examine such settings as music festivals.  I welcome the fact the Minister of State referred to nightclubs as well.  I did not refer to them earlier.  It is positive the Department is taking nightclubs and festivals together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1307" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#H00300"><p>I thank Senator Warfield.  I know how well he understands these problems.  Like many of us who have come from communities where drugs have had a significant impact on families, friends and young people, the new strategy will take on some of these issues.  As we continue to draw down on the actions and strategy, particularly with the working group on personal drug use, at the end of the year we may have progress in this area, looking at treating in a more health-led way rather than a criminal way those young people who, unfortunately, may find themselves addicted to drugs.  If a young person has made a mistake in life, we need to give him or her the opportunity to recuperate and go back into his or her community.</p> <p>We have established a great working group and, by the end of December, we will have some recommendations from it.  We will then continue the journey in January and onwards in 2019 around looking at what Senator Warfield raised, particularly around drug testing.  Last year, I visited a drug testing service in Wales.  I was struck by the fact that any measures that can reduce harm and death caused by drug use need to be introduced as soon as possible.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.38" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#H00400">Bovine Disease Controls</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#H00500"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it go dt&iacute; an Teach inniu.  I thank the Minister of State for his attendance in the House for this important topic.</p> <p>Recently, many farmers in County Monaghan received correspondence from the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine informing them that the ratio of TB reactor animals in the county is a multiple of the national average.  This is a concerning development when one bears in mind that less than 18 months ago, Monaghan had one of the lowest rates of TB compared with the rest of the country.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Robbie Gallagher:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2471"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2471&amp;amp;pid=RobbieGallagher&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is an awful development in a short period.  It is a serious concern for the farming community with regard to herd genetics and farm incomes.  As I am sure the Minister of State can relate to, it is a worrying and stressful time for farmers, many of whom have spent many years of hard work and sweat in building a herd to find, perhaps overnight, that that herd can be removed from them.  I, for one, coming from a farming background, can relate to the experience of having to undergo a test and for two or three days, one's heart is in one's mouth until one gets the results.  It is deeply worrying.</p><p>I know that the Department is in communication with the farming community in County Monaghan on a number of issues, the most important of which is ascertaining what is causing this sudden upsurge in the incidence of tuberculosis in their herds.  Tuberculosis has been with us for many years and it is frustrating that we do not seem to be able to successfully get a handle on the problem as a country.  Despite vaccinations for many years, the problem still seems to be with us.  As far as the farmer in County Monaghan is concerned, it is probably as bad now as it was at any time in that period.  It is important that the Minister of State outline where exactly his Department is in tackling this problem and identifying the cause and the plans he has in place to eradicate it.  I sincerely hope any plan we have will not be isolated to the Twenty-six Counties but will cover the Thirty-two Counties.  As I am sure the Minister of State can appreciate, Monaghan is bordered by three Northern counties, Armagh, Fermanagh and Tyrone.  We need to consult the Department of Agriculture, Environment and Rural Affairs in Northern Ireland to identify if there are similar problems north of the Border.  I look forward to the Minister of State's comments.  Having spoken to farmers, frustration has been voiced at the fact that, in their opinion, it has taken too long to remove the reactor animals from farms.  I ask the Minister of State to look into that matter.  He might revert to me on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1356" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#J00200"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this important and relevant issue.  As he said, the tuberculosis eradication scheme has been in place in Ireland since the mid-1950s.  This and other measures have led to major improvements in tuberculosis levels in the cattle herd.  Reactor numbers have fallen significantly in recent years from 44,000 a year in 2008 and 2009 to approximately 15,000 to 17,000 reactors in the past two to three years.  In the same period the herd incidence has reduced from 6% to 3.5%, meaning that thousands more farmers are now not affected by the stresses associated with a tuberculosis breakdown.  This is a positive development and we are keen to see this trend continue in support of the farming community.</p> <p>As a member state with bovine tuberculosis, Ireland is required under EU law to have a tuberculosis eradication scheme to facilitate trade.  The tuberculosis eradication programme is consistently the largest animal health programme run by the Department.  This reflects how acutely aware we are both of the financial and mental stress for a farmer associated with a tuberculosis breakdown.  The Department has a range of financial supports available for farmers whose herds experience a tuberculosis breakdown.  The Department works very closely with the farming community in ensuring the risk of spread of bovine tuberculosis is curtailed as much as possible in line with the available scientific evidence.  For example, earlier this year, County Monaghan was identified as an area with elevated levels of tuberculosis.  Through in-depth consultation with stakeholders, a specific tuberculosis control plan for County Monaghan was developed and is being actively implemented.</p> <p>Bovine tuberculosis is a complex disease and it is not possible to attribute the decline in the incidence of the disease to any single factor.  Nevertheless, the main factors involved appear to be the wildlife control policy, improved testing regimes and access to data and technology such as the animal health computer system.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Andrew Doyle:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2170"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2170&amp;amp;pid=AndrewDoyle&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> It is important to acknowledge that the major reduction in disease levels is thanks to the co-operation of all stakeholders, in particular farmers, private veterinary practitioners and Department officials.  We now need to build on the excellent progress that has been made and enhance our efforts further in order to achieve eradication, which we think is an attainable target with all the tools we have at our disposal.  The Minister, Deputy Creed, has set the ambitious target of eradicating TB entirely by 2030 and, in order to help achieve this, he recently received approval from the Government to set up a TB stakeholder forum.  This forum is being independently chaired by Mr. Michael Cronin and held its first meeting in early September of this year.  Encouragingly, it has been broadly welcomed by all members.  It is the intention of the forum to provide the Minister with proposals in early 2019 that can achieve eradication of bovine TB by 2030.  These proposals will be considered very closely with a view to finalising a TB 2030 eradication strategy shortly thereafter.</p><p>I want to reassure the Senator we are firmly committed to eradicating bovine TB.  We want to ensure that many more farmers will be saved from the challenges associated with a TB outbreak over the coming years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#K00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  When he gets the opportunity, there are a couple of issues he might revert to me on.  First, while I welcome his comments on the Department, I would like confirmation in regard to whether we are consulting the authorities north of the Border in regard to the level of disease there.  Are we working jointly on that, given it is essential we do so?  Second, it is important the Department would look into the issue of the time it is taking to remove affected cattle from farms.  Several farmers have contacted me on this issue, including today, so I look forward to the Minister of State's response.  Perhaps he will look into it directly.</p> <p>The Minister of State mentioned compensation levels and it is important compensation is paid out as soon as possible.  As he rightly acknowledged, it can be a very worrying, sad and stressful time for farmers who discover their herds are affected.  We must do all we can to eradicate this disease, which has to be our goal.  However, where the disease does break out, we must look after the farmers as quickly as possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1356" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#K00300"><p>I thank the Senator.  I am working on the assumption Animal Health Ireland is working on an all-island basis in regard to eradication, given the animal health status needs to be all-island based.  There is a slightly different control regime in the UK.  We have started a vaccination programme in the vaccination areas and this is being rolled out on badgers.</p> <p>With regard to the length of time for removal, the valuation process needs to be as streamlined as possible.  It is certainly an issue which has come up and I come from a county which has consistently had higher levels than the national average, although this is improving.  In particular, there is an issue with the speed of paperwork following the identification of a reactor in order to remove the animal and allow the 60-day period to start.  These are all very valid points.</p> <p>The Senator's comments on the compensation process are very relevant.  Blood samples are now taken through the interferon-gamma test, which is more sophisticated and has probably picked up extra reactors.  In reality, that will wash through the system, with an improved herd health status in due course.  From personal experience, I have seen it takes some three years for that to really wash through the system and show benefit at the end of the day.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.45" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 3.20 p.m. and resumed at 3.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.46" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#N00100">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#N00200"><p>Before I call on the Deputy Leader to announce today's Order of Business, I want to refer to an issue that is causing some discomfort for me regarding the way in which Commencement matters are submitted.  Standing Orders technically provide that notice of Commencement matters be given in writing to the Cathaoirleach.  That is not always practical, however, because sometimes when I am down in my home in west Cork, I do not have access to the Internet and so forth.  However, the Seanad Office carries out the administrative work on Commencement matters on my behalf before submitting them to me for selection.  I would be extremely grateful to all Senators if they would submit their matters to the Seanad Office where at least five administrative officers will be able to see them, log the time at which they submitted, etc.  If there is anything of consequence arising, Senators can contact me and I will  try my best to facilitate them but Commencement Matters are best submitted to the Seanad Office.  If the matters are submitted to me alone, they may never get to the Seanad Office or they may be delayed.  It is better to submit matters to the office.  At approximately 12.10 p.m. or 12.15 p.m. each day, a member of the Seanad Office staff brings the eight or nine matters submitted for consideration to my attention and I try to select those for discussion as fairly as possible, giving priority to Senators who have not had a recent opportunity to raise matters on the commencement of the House.</p> <p>That matter of housekeeping dealt with, I call on the Deputy Leader to outline the business of the day.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#N00300"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, motion regarding the Technological Universities Act 2018 (Section 36) (Appointed Day) Order 2018, to be taken on the conclusion of the Order of Business, without debate; No. 2, motion regarding the proposal for a regulation of the European Parliament and European Council establishing the Internal Security Fund, to be taken on the conclusion of No. 1, without debate; No. 3, Criminal Justice (Money Laundering and Terrorist Financing) (Amendment) Bill 2018 - Second Stage, to be taken at 4.45 p.m. and to be adjourned not later than 6.30 p.m., with the contributions of group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes and those of all other Senators not to exceed five minutes; and No. 4, statements on the scoping inquiry into the CervicalCheck screening programme to be taken at 6.30 p.m. and to conclude not later than 7.30 p.m., with the contribution of group spokespersons, who may share time with colleagues, not to exceed eight minutes and the Minister to be given no less than three minutes to reply to the debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#O00100"><p>Could the Deputy Leader clarify No. 3 as I believe we are only to have Second Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#O00200"><p>Yes, I believe it is Second Stage only at this stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#O00300"><p>I raise the issue of sports capital funding and its allocation.  I implore the Minister not to repeat the sins of last year in respect of the distribution of sports capital funding.  The benefit to communities of sporting facilities and sports in general is immeasurable.  In Dublin 8 we have some of highest densities of population and rates of population growth, yet between the Liffey and the canal we do not have a single full-size pitch despite having a population of 50,000.  For example, Kevins GAA club in the inner city, which currently fields 18 teams and has a long tradition of GAA in the inner city, has no place to call home.  Imagine a home club in an area with one of the densest populations in the country being deprived of a pitch.  It would not happen in any other parish in the country.  The Kevins club does not serve only one parish, but eight.  The Minister needs to take heed of this matter and ensure that adequate resources are allocated to children and sports clubs in disadvantaged areas across Dublin city.  It is unfair that children in certain areas have better opportunities when it comes to sporting facilities than their contemporaries in other areas.</p> <p>The second issue I raise is the waiting lists for speech and language therapists and occupational therapists.  There are currently 37,229 people waiting for speech and language therapy.  There are three lists.  Some 15,000 of these people are waiting for a very first assessment.  We know that, if they are able to afford it, many parents are able to skip this list and pay for an assessment privately.  There are 7,894 people waiting for a first treatment and there are 14,361 people waiting for the further therapy they need.  In respect of occupational therapy, there are 31,361 people waiting.  Half of these are children, of whom more than 6,000 have been waiting for more than a year.  We see those who can afford to pay hundreds and thousands of euro get privately diagnosed and skip into the list for first therapy.  This is not acceptable.  It is unequal and cannot continue.  I hope the Minister will look into this matter and ensure these waiting lists become a thing of the past.</p> <p>To end on a high, I congratulate my colleague in Fianna F&aacute;il, Senator Ned O'Sullivan, on his local Tidy Towns committee in Listowel, of which he was the founder, winning the overall Tidy Towns competition yesterday.  I also congratulate other towns across the country and the national Tidy Towns committee on their hard work in ensuring that we have beautiful towns and cities throughout Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#O00400"><p>I join Senator Ardagh in acknowledging the voluntary work done to make Ireland a wonderful place in which to live, particularly by organisations such as Tidy Towns committees.</p> <p>This morning, I received a telephone call informing me that there were seven masts tied up in Haulbowline last night.  That is seven Naval Service ships, of which there are eight.  If one is in service in the Mediterranean and the other seven are tied up in Haulbowline, who is looking after the seas?  Who is carrying out fisheries patrols and dealing with drug trafficking and smuggling?  Who is dealing with the various activities that take place at sea?  I am told that we did not have a crew for a single ship.  If this is true, we are in dire straits.  I am told that senior non-commissioned officers, NCOs, are being asked to board ships and act as able seamen in order that ships can sail.  That is unacceptable and simply not good enough.  Last week, we had 3,500 soldiers and veterans outside the gate with the wives and partners of Defence Forces personnel.  My colleague debated the issue with the Minister to try to secure better terms and conditions for soldiers.  The issue is not pay.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Gerard P. Craughwell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2402"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2402&amp;amp;pid=GerardPCraughwell&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Nobody ever joined the Defence Forces to get rich; rather, they joined to serve.  It is all fine and dandy having a ship in the Mediterranean and getting all of the plaudits and fine words about the work we are doing there, but if we cannot do the job we are supposed to do at home, it is time to bring the ship back to patrol our seas.  We bought a ninth ship but do not have crews to sail eight of them.  The Department of Defence is giving back &euro;27 million to the Exchequer, yet some soldiers are on the poverty line.  Married quarters at the Curragh are boarded up, but they could be refurbished and put back into use such that service personnel would have an affordable rent and 47 or 50 houses would be released into the private rental market.  The current approach must stop.  </p><p>I am blue in the face discussing the treatment of the Defence Forces.  Generally, those in uniform such as nurses and doctors are very badly treated.  In recent days every Senator will have received letters about retention difficulties in the medical profession.  Likewise, we cannot retain people in the Army.   I am sick to the back teeth of hearing about the White Paper on Defence and how it is the blueprint for how the Defence Forces will work.  If one looks at it, one will see that the word "retention" is mentioned once and that there is no strategy.  There is no plan.  It is time to tear up the White Paper and start again from scratch.  We cannot have millions of euro worth of ships tied up in dock because there are no crews available.  We cannot have young sailors coming back after four weeks at sea and having to sleep on board their ship because we have no accommodation for them.  We cannot continue in the way we are going.  I am fully aware that there are crises in every Department.  I feel for the Ministers who are trying to resolve them because I do not know how they will be resolved.  However, the Defence Forces need urgent attention.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#P00200"><p>I, too, congratulate the Tidy Towns organisation and committees on the huge contribution they make to local communities.  I congratulate all those involved in Westport and all of the other towns in County Mayo which won prizes in their categories.  We recognise the very hard work that they do.</p> <p>I wish to mention a four year old girl with a severe neurodisability who is non-verbal and cannot be toilet trained.  She has autism and lives in Castlebar.  The disabilities section in the Department of Education and Skills is refusing to provide home tuition for her.  It is asking this young girl who cannot even respond to her own name to get on a bus and travel 20 km to attend school in Newport.  Will the Deputy Leader ask the Minister of State at the Department of Health, Deputy Finian McGrath, and the Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy Richard Bruton, to come to the House to explain how we are cherishing all of the children of the nation equally when a child aged four years who has autism is refused home tuition and asked to travel 20 km on a bus to school?  It is inhumane and beyond comprehension.  I have gone through all of the processes in trying to get the Department to appreciate the geography of County Mayo and that there is no ASD unit in Castlebar, to recognise that the supports and services needed are not available and that we need some flexibility in our approach.  These are not just numbers but children who deserve far better than this.  I also ask the Minister to clarify the standing of the Autism Spectrum Disorder Bill 2017, to indicate the Stage it is at and when we can expect it to proceed through the House.  There is no point in having conventions to protect the rights of those with disabilities when, in spite of them we have cases such as this.  More and more cases are dropping through the system in this very inhumane way.</p> <p>I commend my colleague, Deputy Eoin &Oacute; Broin, for tabling a motion of no confidence in the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government, Deputy Eoghan Murphy.  Anyone who has any doubt why Sinn F&eacute;in has tabled the motion should look at the short film "Through the Cracks", produced by Ingrid Casey, to hear the personal stories of the children and parents who are homeless in this city, confined to hubs and do not have the security of a home.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Rose Conway-Walsh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2462"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2462&amp;amp;pid=RoseConwayWalsh&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We watched this film earlier today in the audiovisual room in Leinster House to hear how we need to have a right to a home and a human right for housing enshrined in our Constitution.  I would like the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government, Deputy Eoghan Murphy, to come to the Seanad to tell us exactly how he will tackle the housing crisis.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1419" speakername="John Dolan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#Q00200"><p>It is good to be back again.  The budget is coming up in a couple of weeks and I wish to raise two related matters with regard to disability.  This is the first budget to follow Ireland's ratification of the UN Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities.  It is an opportunity of having and a necessity to have a budget that has something for disability across a range of Departments.  There was a wonderful launch this morning of a new programme within the Houses of the Oireachtas called Oireachtas work and learn, OWL.  The first ten people to partake, mainly young people with an intellectual disability, will be here for one year as interns.  Great support is given by the Houses of the Oireachtas services and the staff, which I commend, and the City of Dublin Education and Training Board, CDETB, is underwriting the quality of the training and support.</p> <p>After the year is up, those people need to move on to what I would simply call real jobs.  The Ceann Comhairle said this morning that this is the first parliament in the world to initiate a programme like this.  WALK and KARE are the two organisations supporting the programme, and this morning the director of services from WALK, Catherine Kelly, said that only 1% of the people on the intellectual disability database are in real jobs.  We have a huge job of work to do.  We have pretty much tackled the mainstream unemployment issue in that we are down to almost zero unemployment, so it is high time that we dealt with this other issue.</p> <p>I ask the Deputy Leader if the Seanad can find some way to acknowledge those ten interns practically and welcome them.  Can we find a way where Members can get to meet them one to one? It is the old-fashioned aspect of contacts and support that will help those people into employment.</p> <p>The second related point I wished to raise is that tomorrow is the second iteration of the annual Make Way Day where more than 18 local authorities, a number of disability organisations and people with disabilities are going out to point out - largely through a social media campaign - the infringements on the capacity for people with disabilities to be able to walk unhindered through the street and down the high streets.  There are cars parked on pavements, furniture from businesses is out on the street and there is refuse and so on.  These are all practical things.  I congratulate those who have been involved in this campaign.  Congratulations also to Listowel for the Tidy Towns result.  Ease of access is an important issue in having tidy towns.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#Q00300"><p>I wish to raise an issue that pertains to the operation of small, community pharmacies throughout the State.  It will also resonate with each and every Member in the House who understands how difficult it often is for independent pharmacies to survive in this kind of market.  I understand that new rules have been developed by the Pharmaceutical Society of Ireland that, if they are adopted through a statutory instrument under the 2007 Act, could seriously restrict the role, function and responsibilities of pharmacy assistants in the State.  There are 355 pharmacy assistants, all of whom have particular kinds of qualifications that are recognised.  These courses stopped quite a number of years ago.  The majority of pharmacy assistants are women over the age of 55.  If these proposals manage to migrate into a statutory instrument, which they are likely to over the next short period, these pharmacy assistants could find themselves out of work, with pharmacies throughout the State under severe pressure.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Gerald Nash:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2281"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2281&amp;amp;pid=GeraldNash&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->My call today is for the Minister for Health, who I understand would be obligated to sign the statutory instrument, to review this situation and to understand that if this proceeds, it will cause absolute chaos and mayhem in small pharmacies up and down the country.  There are people in this Chamber who are better qualified than I to speak about it, but I understand the problems it will cause.  We are asking pharmacies to do more work these days.  We are asking them to do more complex work and it is important that they are resourced to do that.  The worst possible thing we could do is take qualified staff from them.  What those staff want is a properly recognised framework for the kind of continuous professional development that they do anyway.  I cannot see an upside to this.  Nobody is advising to the contrary or as to why this is a positive thing.  I ask the Minister to keep a watching brief on this, to be very cautious about how it proceeds and to ensure there is proper engagement to get under the bonnet as to why individual pharmaceutical assistants and the group that represents them are very concerned.</p><p>Members will be aware that new illness benefit forms came onstream in the middle of July without, as I understand, any consultation with the National Association of General Practitioners.  I met with that association last week and understand from it that a mediation process was designed by the Department and then withdrawn.  An eminent industrial relations professional with significant experience was commissioned to assist in the process to develop a framework whereby this issue could be addressed.  The longer it goes on, the more delays we will experience in getting illness benefit applications processed.  I appeal to those Senators who have influence with the Minister for Employment Affairs and Social Protection and, to a lesser extent, the Minister for Health, to try to ensure there is an intervention on this issue.</p><p>I am very pleased that the Minister for Employment Affairs and Social Protection has put on record today at the Joint Committee on Employment Affairs and Social Protection that payment of a Christmas bonus will be made this year to 1.2 million recipients of long-term social welfare payments.  The statement that was issued to the committee yesterday was particularly vague and open to interpretation as to whether there would be a payment made at all this year.  The Minister has put on record that a payment will be made.  However, she has failed to state that the full Christmas bonus will be restored.  I appeal to the Minister and her Fine Gael colleagues to use their good offices to make sure we have 100% restoration of the Christmas bonus to lighten the load for less well-off families as we approach the Christmas period.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" speakername="Gabrielle McFadden" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#R00200"><p>To take up the previous speaker's point about the Minister for Employment Affairs and Social Protection, the Minister never said the bonus would not be paid.  It is disingenuous for anyone to have said that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#R00300"><p>I did not say that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" speakername="Gabrielle McFadden" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#R00400"><p>I am not saying Senator Nash did so.  It had been leaked and that is where the problem lies.  When things are leaked and taken out of context, people are terrorised and frightened.  Old-age pensioners were fearful this morning because of a leaked document.  It was fake news, basically, and I do not think that is right.</p> <p>I would like to speak on housing, as everybody would.  Councillors, Senators and Deputies alike are all frustrated with the housing situation.  I do not think anybody can criticise the Government's commitment to housing.  The Government is very committed to housing and homelessness-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#R00500"><p>It is committed to homelessness, alright.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" speakername="Gabrielle McFadden" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#R00600"><p>-----and to housing those who are homeless.  I feel there are a few things councils could look at doing.  I would like the Minister to come to the House to have a debate with us on the issues.  One of the things I am concerned about is the repair and lease scheme.  It was instigated by the previous housing Minister, Deputy Simon Coveney.  It is a very good scheme but it has not been taken up at all.  I think only 15 people have taken it up in the last years.</p> <p>My suggestion would be that the councils may not be advertising it and pushing it enough.  Perhaps the Minister could put pressure on them to promote it better.  I am also worried about staffing issues and the lack of clerks of works.  The clerk of works in Athlone and the south Westmeath area works on his own and is under pressure.  Perhaps that is another way we could look at it.  If we had the Minister in the House, we could discuss this with him.</p> <p>Sinn F&eacute;in's motion of no confidence in the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government this evening is a stunt.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Gabrielle McFadden:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2399"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2399&amp;amp;pid=GabrielleMcFadden&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It does not have a monopoly on compassion.  We all know everyone should have a home.  I firmly believe that calling for a vote on a motion of no confidence in the Minister will do nothing for the people who are living in hubs or for those who are on the housing waiting lists.  Sinn F&eacute;in would be better served using its time tonight to come up with suggestions and solutions, and trying to help the Government to house people who are looking for housing, instead of calling for votes of no confidence, because, to me, such calls are stunts.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#S00200"><p>Matters that are before the D&aacute;il should not be discussed here.  If a Member wants to table a motion before the House, we can have a discussion on it.  I would prefer that this issue would not be referred to during the course of the Order of Business.  I call Senator Gallagher.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#S00300"><p>I join, as others have done, in congratulating the more than 880 towns and villages that entered this year's Tidy Towns competition.  They all deserve huge credit for their efforts.  I congratulate my colleague, Senator Ned O'Sullivan, on Listowel being successful in winning the overall prize.  I take great pride also today in congratulating Glaslough village in County Monaghan-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#S00400"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#S00500"><p>-----on being awarded the prize of being the tidiest village in the country.  I invite all my colleagues in the House to visit Glaslough if they get an opportunity to do so as it is a beautiful village that has much to offer.  The volunteers who participated in the work in all the more than 880 towns and villages throughout the country deserve great praise.  I compliment them on their hard work and effort.  These things do not happen by accident.  They all deserve great credit.  I encourage others to join them in their efforts because the awards are great both at a personal level and a community level.</p> <p>I would like to spare a thought today for the community of Magheracloone in County Monaghan who yesterday experienced the unprecedented event of having a landslide, which affected the local Magheracloone GAA club and the adjoining community centre.  It was a dramatic event for all concerned.  There is also a question mark over a number of houses within the vicinity.  Many businesses are suffering because of road closures.  I spoke to a representative of Gyproc this morning about the incident and stressed the importance of keeping the community updated on developments as they arise.  I understand some experts from the UK arrived in Magheracloone this morning to undertake investigations to assess the damage and perhaps the reason for it.  Our hearts go out to all those people and we trust that, collectively, they will all work together to ensure that life as normal will return to Magheracloone as soon as possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#S00600"><p>I rise to speak about the National Women's Council of Ireland.  The Deputy Leader will be aware that its representatives had a briefing this morning for Oireachtas Members.  I attended it, engaged with them and commend them on having a very good, meaningful one-to-one engagement with subgroups.  It was very helpful and it was great to have that conversation.</p> <p>A point that came across clearly to me at the engagement was the disconnect that exists sometimes between organisations such as this one and politics and policymakers.  The issues they covered were a women's health action plan, for which it has strongly advocated, and reversing the cuts of crucial payments and services to women.  I was particularly taken by their detailed analysis of the investment in social houses and greater security of tenure.  They also tracked the figure for women and children who are homeless, which is an alarming and a growing issue for that organisation.</p> <p>After having had some engagement with the representatives, it struck me that we need to see more women in local politics.  All those to whom I spoke in one of the groups said the same thing.  We need people of diverse views right across the various spectrums - young, old, straight, gay, bisexual, men, women - and to have a rich sense of diversity.  It is important that all of that is represented in Parliament, be it the Seanad or the D&aacute;il, and in local government.  I posed the question to the people I spoke why there are not more such people.  They cited the issue of childcare costs, of there being a male dominated cabal, as one woman described it, and how confidence was an issue for many women in terms of accessing policy within local authorities and in politics.</p> <p>I would like to see how we, across the political spectrum and across all parties and none, can collaborate and work together in some way now.  Let us not wait for another other five years but rather collaborate on this between now and the local elections in May.  I am talking in terms of the next two to three months.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Victor Boyhan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2463"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2463&amp;amp;pid=VictorBoyhan&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I suggest to the Leader that we collaborate and look at how we might have a public campaign of engagement.  We should have workshops up and down the country encouraging women to be involved in the political movement, whether in political parties or as independents.  I put the idea out there.  Perhaps we would all go away, collectively think about that, and see how we could get a more diverse mix in local politics and especially more women.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#T00200"><p>In deference to your comments, a Chathaoirligh, about the motion in the other House I will say only that I support what my colleague, Senator Gabrielle McFadden, has said.  Sinn F&eacute;in is playing the man and not the ball and would be better advised to come up with policies.</p> <p>I too wish to be associated with the comments about the Tidy Towns competition and the great work that is done by all the communities around the country.  I refer in particular to Skerries and Malahide which both won gold, Swords which won silver, Lusk which won bronze and the Naul which won a prize for endeavour.</p> <p>I will also comment briefly on the fake news story on the Christmas bonus.  I remind Members that it was Fianna F&aacute;il that scrapped the bonus in 2009 and the Fine Gael and Labour Party Government that reinstated it in 2014.  The Government has increased the bonus several times since.  I know the Minister for Finance has no notion of reducing it.</p> <p>The Public Health (Alcohol) Bill has been through this House and is before the other House.  It is important legislation.  A number of Deputies wish to see the provision on cancer warning labels removed from the Bill.  To do so would be inappropriate and ill advised.  We know from our discussions in this House that the World Health Organization, WHO, has determined alcohol to be a class 1 carcinogen.  Approximately 900 Irish people are diagnosed with an alcohol-related cancer every single year.  Alcohol can cause seven types of cancer, namely, cancer of the mouth, pharynx, larynx, oesophagus, breast and liver and colorectal colon cancer.  More than half of the mouth, head and neck cancers diagnosed in Ireland are associated with alcohol.  Alcohol also increases the level of oestrogen in the blood, thereby increasing the risk of breast cancer.</p> <p>What are we afraid of?  Is it allowing the public to know the risk they are subjecting themselves to?  We have no right as legislators to deprive people of that information, in particular young people.  The earlier one starts to drink, the more likely one is to have a problem.  Young people need to know that alcohol is dangerous.  When consumed in moderation it can be a great social lubricant but, sadly, many people in this country drink excessively and our relationship with alcohol has been extremely damaging to society at many different levels.  I know this is the Order of Business but this is something I feel passionate about.  I have always been a strong exponent of protecting young people until they are old enough to make their own decisions and ensuring that adults and children alike are informed of the nature of the product they are consuming.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#T00300"><p>Fianna F&aacute;il and Fine Gael do not appear to have heard about legislation introduced by Sinn F&eacute;in on rent certainty, protection from eviction and security of tenure.  The party introduced Bills in the Oireachtas at least six times.  The Government asked for solutions and it was given solutions but they were knocked back and opposed or Members sat on the fence getting blistered bums.</p> <p>I know I am not meant to speak about the business of the D&aacute;il but what I will speak about is the effect the homelessness and housing crisis is having on children.  Five years ago when I was a councillor I helped a woman who lived in a car with her three children.  I knew at the time something was happening.  I knew there was a tsunami of distraught parents and children beginning to emerge who were left to sleep in cars.  That was the beginning of the housing crisis.  The child whom I met at that time was seven years of age.  The child stopped talking and listening and became incontinent.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator M&aacute;ire Devine:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2468"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2468&amp;amp;pid=MaireDevine&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> My colleague, Senator Rose Conway-Walsh, alluded to the short documentary, "Through the Cracks", which I urge all Members to watch.  It refers repeatedly to the stories of children who are at risk of homelessness or actually homeless.  It is stated all of the children suffer from anxiety and depression.  Where is the therapy for every one of them?  A woman came to see me yesterday in fear.  She has been given notice to quit because the landlord or landlady wants to take back the house.  Her child is in this precarious position.  He is a small six year old boy with mental health issues.  He has become extremely violent because he is picking up on the parents' insecurity, anxiety and depression due to the lack of somewhere to live.  There is a psychologist missing in Cherry Orchard Hospital and a two-year waiting list.  The child has become violent and his mother has been told to ring the police about her six year old.  That is the only solution while she is on a two-year waiting list.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1438" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#U00200"><p>I, too, congratulate the Tidy Towns committees throughout the country on the tremendous work each and every one of us sees week in, week out, which starts at the beginning of the year, to prepare their villages and towns for the task ahead.</p> <p>I, too, ask the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government, Deputy Eoghan Murphy, to come before the House to report positive progress on Rebuilding Ireland.  When one looks at the scheme, he instigated an inter-agency group on homelessness.  There has been a 40% increase in new home completions.  The number of planning permissions is up by 39%, while the number of commencement notices is up 17%.  The overall figure for new builds is up by 40%.  The Minister is also responsible for developing the Land Development Agency.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#U00300"><p>I do not want the Senator to-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1438" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#U00400"><p>I am just highlighting some of the positives-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#U00500"><p>I know that, but-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1438" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#U00600"><p>-----and asking the Minister to come to the House to think about-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#U00700"><p>Please, Senator.  Generally, I do not mind a Member talking about an issue, but referring to a motion in the other House is inappropriate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1438" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#U00800"><p>I have not once referred to the motion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#U00900"><p>Is the Senator referring to it directly?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1438" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#U01000"><p>I have not once referred to it.  I am asking that the Minister come to the House-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#U01100"><p>The Senator might not have mentioned the motion, but unless I am hearing him differently, the Senator is rehashing what is happening in the other House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1438" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#U01200"><p>I am not.  I am just saying it is clear that what Sinn F&eacute;in is doing is a clear tactic-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#U01300"><p>A Chathaoirligh-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#U01400"><p>I have already ruled on the matter.  The Senator must find another way that is-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1438" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#U01500"><p>Sinn F&eacute;in is constantly being accused of bullying.  It will not bully the Minister and it will not bully me either.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#U01600"><p>Please respect the Chair.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1438" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#U01700"><p>Sinn F&eacute;in is not interested in integration but segregation.  It refused-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#U01800"><p>Really; come on.  Kick him out.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1438" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#U01900"><p>It is refusing to allow 900 houses to be developed in south County Dublin.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#U02000"><p>Please respect the Chair.  We are on the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1438" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#U02100"><p>There are 19,000 people homeless in the north of Ireland, the worst figure in the United Kingdom.  Who is in charge there?  Sinn F&eacute;in is in charge.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#U02200"><p>From where did the Senator get those figures?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#U02300"><p>No.  The Senator's friends in the SDLP-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1438" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#U02400"><p>There was a Sinn F&eacute;in councillor on radio the other day commenting on the fact that it was not about money but about his local authority.  As I said - I will not speak for much longer-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#U02500"><p>I think this is out of order.  The Senator has gone on too long.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1438" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#U02600"><p>I ask the Minister to come to the House to report positive progress on Rebuilding Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#U02700"><p>Rebuild Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#U02800"><p>We are taking the votes back.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#U02900"><p>You are not going to get them again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#U03000"><p>I join in the congratulations to the 883 Tidy Towns committees the length and breadth of the country.  It is appropriate that we mention them in the Seanad because they do Trojan work.  Our colleague Senator Ned O'Sullivan was a founder member of the Tidy Towns committee in Listowel, a town which received 339 marks.  That said, my village of Castlecoote received 337, which is very good.  It also received a gold medal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#U03100"><p>Well done.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#U03200"><p>Our premises were also commended, which is rather nice.  I commend the committee.  I will not mention names, but Keadue received 336 marks; Ballintubber, 327; and Clontuskert, 325.  They all performed very well.  Westport again scored very well, while Portrunny received an endeavour award medal.  We should praise the dedication of the people involved.  Roscommon town received 326 marks.  Our colleague Councillor Kathleen Shanagher is chairperson of the committee.  I say, "Well done," to the volunteers the length and breadth of the country for the enormous improvements achieved.  Driving through the towns of Ireland one can see that the ones with active Tidy Towns committees look stunning.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Terry Leyden:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=636"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=636&amp;amp;pid=TerryLeyden&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I also praise a fellow Roscommon man, Mr. J.P. McManus, who has dedicated &euro;3.2 million to the GAA.  That is &euro;100,000 to every GAA county board in Ireland.  It is an unprecedented and incredible gesture, and we should praise him for doing what he is doing in Adare.  People can criticise him all they like but it is one of the most fantastic gestures of a successful Irishman, with whom we should all be delighted to be associated.  I knew his uncle, Owen, who died in 2010, whom Mr. McManus used to visit regularly and bring around the Arignagh village valley in his lovely helicopter.  He used to drop in a bottle of whiskey, and he also brought stone from Arignagh to his place.  I compliment him, his wife Noreen and his family for a lovely gesture to all the GAA people in Ireland.  I say "Well done" to Mr. McManus and may he have continued success.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1415" speakername="Maura Hopkins" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#V00200"><p>I would like to be associated with the congratulations to the Tidy Towns committees across the country.  Yesterday was a great day for recognising the exceptional work that is done by volunteers through the energy, time and commitment they give to ensuring our villages and towns look so well.  As Senator Leyden has rightly said, we have had good success in Roscommon.  Roscommon town, Castlecoote, Kilteeven, Ballintober, Athleague, Portrunny, Keadew, Tarmonbarry and Cloontuskert have all done exceptionally well.  While they may not have received awards, many other towns and villages have also increased their marks, which emphasises that further improvements have been made.</p> <p>Having been involved in many clean-ups and with Tidy Towns over the past number of years, I know it is important that we see further targeted measures to deal with illegal dumping, particularly in rural areas.  I know the Department of Communications, Climate Action and Environment has been proactive in providing funding to assist with major clean-ups where volunteers are unable to access these spots, which is welcome, but we need targeted approaches to deal with prevention rather than clean-ups.  Once again, I compliment all who have been involved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#V00300"><p>It certainly is the case that the Tidy Towns competition brings out the best of Ireland.  Those who are involved at all levels, and volunteers especially, deserve great credit.  I notice Cloontuskert was mentioned twice and I wonder if there are two Cloontuskerts now in the Roscommon-Galway constituency.  Senators Leyden and Hopkins might bring clarity tomorrow as to which one they were referring to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#V00400"><p>I can confirm that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#V00500"><p>There is a fine graveyard in the Galway one, which I know is well kept.</p> <p>A strange controversy erupted last week regarding the Committee of Public Accounts hearing into spending at &Aacute;ras an Uachtar&aacute;in, with members of the Government and the D&aacute;il saying that the hearing would be "unconstitutional".  Several interesting points have emerged from the hearing this morning, however, including details of an annual allowance of &euro;317,000 paid to the President each year which is not subject to audit, and the fact that an audit committee set up in 2014 to monitor spending did not even meet for three years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#V00600"><p>The Committee of Public Accounts is a D&aacute;il committee only, and it is inappropriate while it is in the middle of a debate for us to have a discussion in the Seanad.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#V00700"><p>I will call for a specific debate about freedom of information.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#V00800"><p>The Senator might find another way of doing it.  The Committee of Public Accounts is a specific D&aacute;il committee dealing with this issue.  In my view it is still <i>sub judice</i>, it is hearing evidence and it may go on for some time.  When it is over we might be able to have a debate on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#V00900"><p>I understand, but my point is about the fake political theatre that erupted last week around this issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#V01000"><p>The President should be above this debate, and the Office of the President can be dealt with, but the Senator should find another way.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#W00100"><p>The Constitution states that the President shall not be answerable to either House of the Oireachtas or to any court for the exercise and performance of the powers and functions of his office or for any act done or purporting to be done by him in the exercise or performance of these powers and functions.  It is clear that it does not say that the President is not answerable to the Oireachtas under any circumstances.  It says he or she is not answerable for the exercise and performance of the powers and functions which are specifically mentioned in the relevant article in the Constitution.  My point is that it was nonsense for anyone to say examining spending from the Central Fund by the &Aacute;ras would be unconstitutional.  Why then did the likes of Deputies Miche&aacute;l Martin, Catherine Murphy and Alan Kelly wade in to defend the Government's attempts to prevent this scrutiny on the grounds that it might interfere with the ongoing election?  Surely, that is the point.  Surely, voters have a right to know in advance of an election.  One can imagine what would happen if the Committee of Public Accounts suspended all scrutiny by the Fine Gael-led Government in the run up to the next general election on the grounds that it might impact on the result.  Fianna F&aacute;il and Labour would jump up and down in indignation about such a conspiracy.</p> <p>What we saw last week was political theatre and hypocrisy.  There is almost universal agreement that the Presidency should be made subject to freedom of information legislation.  All parties in the D&aacute;il are on record as supporting that.  If the Government and Opposition leaders consider it unconstitutional for the Committee of Public Accounts to probe spending in the &Aacute;ras, they must consider that any attempt by the Oireachtas to bring the &Aacute;ras within the remit of freedom of information would also be unconstitutional.  Why have they not made that point before now?  The simple reason is that no one really believes this line about unconstitutionality.  It was cooked up at the last minute because of unease regarding details of &Aacute;ras spending in the run up to the election, which the political class has already done its best to stitch up in favour of the incumbent.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#W00200"><p>I told Senator Mullen earlier, but he continued on, that this matter is <i>sub judice</i>before the Committee of Public Accounts.  The Constitution sets out certain parameters and-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#W00300"><p>When &euro;7 million is being spent annually on the President, how can we not have accountability?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#W00400"><p>That is not a matter for us.  It is a matter for the Committee of Public Accounts to make a decision on.  It may be that when the committee has decided, it could be a matter for debate on another day.  The next speaker is Senator Mulherin.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#W00500"><p>I welcome the announcement by the board of An Post that it will enter the Irish retail mortgage market next year and offer customers a 1% reduction in the mortgage interest rates applying where people take out a mortgage for the first time or switch providers.  In due course, An Post will move on to the provision of overdrafts and credit cards.  It is clear that the high street retail banks in this country are fleecing people when one compares the interest rates charged with European averages.  It is good to see An Post move on a commitment it provided in respect of rolling out further services, including financial services.  However, the old chestnut of the closure of post offices remains.</p><p>I am very disappointed to have been notified earlier that Ballindine post office in County Mayo has failed the review and will not be allowed to reopen, including by means of giving someone else the opportunity to run a post office there.  I question the way in which An Post is applying this protocol.  There is no clarity in respect of it.  There are more than 1,500 people in the electoral division comprising Ballindine, Garrymore and Irishtown and my understanding is that An Post's aim is to have a post office in place for every 500 people at least.  There is no explanation regarding the review apart from a standard letter issued to every person who has made a submission.  The letter states that An Post has examined the protocol and is sorry that the post office has not been successful.</p><p>An Post's bona fides in applying the protocol are put into question in another regard.  When An Post is shutting down a post office, it gives ten to 14 days' notice.  If one wants a review, it takes place after the post office is closed.  The post office in Ballindine closed on 10 or 12 August and the results of the review have been provided now.  I do not think An Post is a bit serious about reviewing or reconsidering anything.  I note that three business people in Ballindine made expressions of interest to An Post in August and indicated their interest in discussing the possibility of continuing to provide the services.  These people are not doing it for the good of their health.  If there is a business proposition there, they will run with it.  If there is not, they will not.  An Post has not engaged with them in any shape or form, however, which is a disgrace.  It is using the protocol as a <i>carte blanche</i>to shut down 159 post offices.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Michelle Mulherin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2309"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2309&amp;amp;pid=MichelleMulherin&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I am not suggesting every post office should remain open.  That would be a foolish statement and would detract from the good cases in some communities to retain their post offices.  Will the Deputy Leader take this issue up with the Minister for Communications, Climate Action and Environment, Deputy Denis Naughten?  We have been told that where people want to engage, there will be engagement.  However, the engagement with An Post is not a bit meaningful.  It will have to be taken to task on this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#X00200"><p>I want to acknowledge the Government's remarks at the weekend that it intends to hold the much awaited referendum on extending voting rights in presidential elections in, it is hoped, May next year.  This will be an important debate.  I will not refer to the ongoing presidential election campaign.  The office is representative but not elected by all of Ireland's citizens.  It will be an opportunity for us to initiate a further discussion on the kind of Ireland we want, namely, a fairer and more equal Ireland, as well as one that cherishes, empowers and enfranchises all of our citizens.</p> <p>The Minister is sincere on this matter.  I believe he has worked diligently with officials on preparing the groundwork for this referendum.  This will go some way to creating that more equal and representative society for which we long.  It is a campaign, a referendum and an issue that is not one, however.  To my knowledge, all of the parties represented in this Chamber, as well as those Members who do not belong to any particular party, are supportive of the extension of the voting right to citizens in the North and those who qualify among the diaspora.  There is a longstanding desire for this through the Constitutional Convention, as well as the natural outwork flowing from the peace process and the Good Friday Agreement.</p> <p>There is merit on that basis for the Minister of State, Deputy John Paul Phelan, to update the House on plans for that referendum to ensure we can get a better understanding and insight into the Government's option papers.  I remind all of my colleagues across the House that we will have to go out and win this referendum.  It will afford us an opportunity to have a frank, good, positive and worthwhile discussion and debate about how we want to see Ireland and the Presidency moving forward.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1374" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#X00300"><p>Members have referred to the recent announcement of winners in the Tidy Towns competition.  In Limerick, we are proud five communities won bronze medals, Castleconnell, Limerick city centre, Newcastle West, Galbally and Ardpatrick.  Adare and Garrienderk were also mentioned for county awards.  Birdhill, the winner last year, performed extremely well in the gold medal category.  J.P. McManus runs a Going for Gold/Tidy Towns competition for Limerick which has been very successful.  I commend him on his support of Limerick hurling and his more recent nationwide funding of GAA clubs.</p> <p>I support the call for a debate on housing.  No Member has all the solutions.  This is an integrated problem which needs to be addressed at Department level but also, equally, at local authority level.  Many Members have colleagues on local authorities who deal with housing every day.  As we know, many of the applications for housing go from local authorities to the Department.  Many of them are good applications; some not so good.  We need to avoid grandstanding on the housing issue.  It is a significant issue in Limerick.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Kieran O'Donnell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2207"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2207&amp;amp;pid=KieranODonnell&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We need to find solutions that will work for the people that we represent.  People who are listening in are waiting for houses to be built.  Houses are under construction in Limerick and many have been built but we need to build many more.  We need a mature, considered debate and I ask that the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government, Deputy Eoghan Murphy, come to the House as quickly as possible.  I would be very interested in hearing proposals from all sides of the House once Senators have consulted their colleagues in local authorities on their views.  We need to work collectively on this.  We cannot afford to turn it into a political football.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#Y00200"><p>I place on record my frustration at reports of an internal Government row between the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Shane Ross, and the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government, Deputy Eoghan Murphy, on proposed regulation of Airbnb and who should take the lead on that issue.  This matter has been dealt with.  While Senators talk about working together on solutions, members of the Joint Committee on Housing, Planning and Local Government have been working together on this issue.  The committee recommended that we regulate short-term lets, of which Airbnb is the biggest source.  Airbnb and the Government spent a year developing a memorandum of understanding that the committee said would not work.  The memorandum has been in place for a year and legislation on the matter was introduced by Senator Humphreys.  We must not drag our heels on regulating Airbnb.  According to independent data, 1,000 units in this city would become available and return to rental stock if we regulated short-term lets such as Airbnb.</p> <p>There are solutions.  Dublin City Council suggested there are 4,000 vacant units within the canals of this city, all of which have connections to infrastructure, schools and transport.  It appears, however, that we do not need a vacancy tax and there will not be one in the budget.  Sinn F&eacute;in is offering solutions.  We need a vision and we need to have a conversation about a vision not only now, but about how we future-proof the system - it is not just a market, but a system.  We need to have a conversation about how, in the future, maybe 30% of that system would be comprised of housing provided by approved housing bodies and social and affordable housing, with 70% being private.  That would insulate people from future boom-bust politics.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#Y00300"><p>I agree with my colleague, Senator Kieran O'Donnell, on the need for a debate on housing.  We need to have a genuine debate on the way forward.  There are many challenges for people who are on the housing lists in local authorities.  There are also challenges for people who are caught between not qualifying for the local authority housing list and being unable to buy.  We need to seriously look at that area.</p> <p>There is good news.  Last night, Cork City Council approved the building of 112 new apartments and development work to open a site for the building of more than 600 affordable and social houses in my area.  I welcome the decision by the council to approve 712 units in one night.</p> <p>We have challenges.  This year, we will build 20,000 new houses, which means we are turning out 385 new houses per week.  We need to bring that figure up to around 700 houses per week over the next two or three years.  That process will take time.  With 385 houses currently being delivered each week, I am sure that by this time next year 500 new houses will be completed or brought into use each week and that level of output will continue for the next few years.  We need to assist people, in particular those who are not on local authority housing lists and are unable to borrow to buy a home.  We need to facilitate that group either with affordable housing or by providing for secure long-term letting and a far better rental system than we current have.  We should debate this matter at an early date.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#Z00100"><p>Senator Ardagh raised the issue of sports capital funding.  My understanding is the Minister looks at individual cases and that is the premise of the sports capital funding structure and process.  The Senator also raised the very serious issue of waiting lists for speech and language therapy and occupational therapy.  I suggest this be tabled as a Commencement matter to get some detail as to the state of play when it comes to those serious waiting lists.  Senator Ardagh also congratulated Listowel and, indeed, Senator Ned O'Sullivan, who founded the Tidy Towns committee in Listowel.  As many Senators have acknowledged, it is a brilliant initiative and much work is done by volunteers, which is to be commended.</p><p>Senator Craughwell raised the issue of the Defence Forces.  I do not believe his information is correct when it comes to the reasons the particular ships mentioned may be in port.  Earlier today, as part of its patrol duties, the <i>L&Eacute; Eithne</i>responded to a boat in distress and has taken a recreational vessel under tow to Ballycotton RNLI station.  The rota of ship deployment varies and there are a range of reasons that vessels will be in the port.  The Minister explained in this House last week what is being done to address the issues of recruitment and retention.  Only yesterday, another agreement securing pay increases for members of the Defence Forces was reached for those admitted after 2011.  The issues facing the Defence Forces are being addressed within a framework.  I understand why the Senator raises those issues, which are of concern, and I have spoken to the people involved myself.  It is my understanding, however, that a lot of work is being done to improve those conditions.</p><p>Senator Conway-Walsh raised the issue of a four year old child, which I believe would be better raised as a Commencement matter.  She asked about the autism Bill and I will have to get back to her on that.</p><p>Senator Dolan, as he so often does, raised issues in regard to disability.  His suggestion about interns and how we might be able to facilitate that process in the Seanad is a good one.  It is probably a matter for the Committee on Procedure and Privileges, which might want to take a look at it to see what is possible.  The Senator also acknowledged the work of those involved in the annual Make Way Day.  It is only when people are less able to navigate the streets or public areas that they have an awareness of these issues in that they find it hard to get around.  The Senator raises a very important issue.  Initiatives like the annual Make Way Day are very important for the people he mentions.</p><p>Senator Nash raised the issue of community pharmacies.  I would have thought this is another issue that could be usefully tabled as a Commencement matter.  He also raised the issue of GPs.  To my knowledge, the Irish Medical Organisation, IMO, and the Department are in ongoing negotiations, which are progressing.  We will have to await the outcome of those negotiations.</p><p>Senator McFadden put to bed the issue of the Christmas bonus not being made available.  This is not a real story.  In fact, it is worrying a story like this is put out as it can affect more vulnerable people who are put in fear of not getting that extra bit of help at Christmas time.  The Minister, Deputy Regina Doherty, has no intention of discontinuing the Christmas bonus for any social welfare recipients.  As is always the case, there is no provision for a Christmas bonus in the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection's allocation for 2018.  The decision to pay a Christmas bonus is made at budget time every year.  The Christmas bonus was abolished in 2009 by the Fianna F&aacute;il Government.  As the economy recovered, it was reinstated by Fine Gael in 2014 at the rate of 25%.  This was increased to 75% in 2015 and further increased to 85% in 2016 and 2017.  Those are not the actions of a Government that intends to do away with the Christmas bonus.  I thank Senator McFadden for clarifying that matter.</p><p>Senator McFadden also mentioned issues with regard to housing.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Catherine Noone:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2354"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2354&amp;amp;pid=CatherineNoone&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I will respect the ruling on housing but I will make a few comments.  I do not know how helpful are initiatives such as the motion that will be discussed later are but I do not want to dwell on that.  All I want to point out is that Rebuilding Ireland is based on the same model as the Action Plan for Jobs, which was much maligned.  No one thought it would have an effect, but we are practically at full employment and this has given rise to new concerns about actually getting people to work in various sectors.  We are in the second year of Rebuilding Ireland, which is a five-year plan.  We have turned the corner.  All indicators prove this, and I have no doubt but that the plan will deliver.  In 2017, an additional 7,000 social homes were put into the system that were not there in 2016.  In 2018, 8,000 additional social homes will be put in.  Our target is 12,000 a year and 110,000 by 2027.  There were 3,000 unfinished housing estates when we entered office in 2011; there are now fewer than 150.  Many significant new housing projects have been blocked by those who want to make an issue of this matter later this evening.  They recently blocked the commencement of 900 new homes in south Dublin, including social housing, delayed 78 housing units in Coolock and campaigned against housing in north Dublin.  There is a great deal of politics being played with this issue.  Not one of us sitting here or anywhere else in these Houses or on any council around the country wants to see people without a home.  Our time would be better used in a minority Government situation coming up with solutions that will actually help the situation rather than inflaming it and distracting from the work being done to improve matters.</p><p>Senator Gallagher referred to Tidy Towns, as did many others, and an important issue in Magheracloone, where there was a landslide.  It is a horrific event for the people who have been affected by it, and I hope proper supports will be put in place for the community.</p><p>Senator Boyhan referred to the National Women's Council of Ireland.  I have not had a chance to go over there.  I hope to go over to hear what it has to say.  It is certainly very active, and I agree with the Senator's point regarding more women in politics.  It is quite an unattractive profession for many reasons, not least the adversarial and quite negative nature of the discourse on many occasions, so it is not naturally something in which women want to get involved.  I think it really comes down to that.</p><p>Senator Reilly also referred to Tidy Towns and the various towns in his area that enjoyed good success.  He also raised an issue that is close to my heart, namely, the Public Health (Alcohol) Bill.  I am very disappointed that there would be any rowing back on the warnings on alcohol.  It is clear from what the World Health Organization, WHO, has stated that alcohol is a class 1 carcinogen and it is beyond doubt that we have a broken relationship with alcohol.  The amount of binge-drinking that goes on is hugely problematic.  I find it disappointing that colleagues are trying to dilute the potential effect of this legislation.</p><p>Senator Devine referred to housing and Senator Lawlor addressed a few matters in response to that issue in general.  As already stated, we would all have huge sympathy with anyone who is without a home.  We should all work together to ensure that houses are delivered.  On many councils it is not Fine Gael, Fianna F&aacute;il or Labour that is in a majority.  I think there is a competency issue in many of the councils.  We really need to up our level when it comes to the delivery of housing on that front.  Senator Lawlor also referred to Rebuilding Ireland.  I have addressed that point.</p><p>Senator Leyden raised Tidy Towns and J.P. McManus, whose generosity we would have to acknowledge.  He is a fantastic advocate for the GAA and is certainly very generous to it.  Senator Hopkins also referred to Tidy Towns and the exceptional work done by volunteers in her area.</p><p>Senator Mullen referred to the Presidency, a matter on which I will not comment.</p><p>Senator Mulherin raised a very important point regarding An Post.  I have wondered for years why An Post does not diversify what it does in the sense that people have essentially stopped posting letters to a large degree.  Many deliveries are done by delivery companies and An Post seems to do fewer of them.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Catherine Noone:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2354"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2354&amp;amp;pid=CatherineNoone&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Clearly, the demand for postal services is diminishing.  The idea of An Post getting involved in the retail mortgage market and providing overdraft facilities is a good one.  Ballindine post office is close to my parents' home and I know what the Senator is talking about in that respect.  The Minister appeared before us last week, but it has since become apparent that the procedures being used to review post offices are not clear, so I will seek for the Minister to return and clarify the procedures or to write to all Members clarifying same.</p><p>Senator &Oacute; Donnghaile acknowledged the efforts to extend voting rights.  We would all agree on that issue.  Actually, I should not assume that all of us agree, but I certainly do.  Extending voting rights to the citizens of the North will happen.  It will just take a little time.</p><p>Senator Kieran O'Donnell referred to the Tidy Towns competition and raised the issue of housing, which I have addressed.</p><p>Senator Warfield raised the issue of Airbnb, which has been discussed numerous times in the House.  His point was well made, but regulation needs to be done effectively.  A balance must be struck between housing needs in red zones and the more difficult pressure zones in Dublin, Cork, Galway and Limerick and other areas around the country where Airbnb facilitates the tourism product.  The need to strike a balance might explain any discussion that is under way between Departments.  In referring to the debate between two Departments, though, the Senator mentioned something about which I am unable to comment.</p><p>Senator Colm Burke also discussed housing.  I will not go into his points in detail, but it was positive to see 712 houses being approved in his area of Cork last night.  It is good news.  Such decisions have to be made at local level if we are to make housing stock available to people as soon as possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#BB00200"><p>Regarding Tidy Towns, I agree with the sentiments expressed by many Senators about the tremendous voluntary work that people do all over the country in villages and towns.  Over the past 20 years, the Tidy Towns competition and its categories have been a major success.  I congratulate Listowel, which is a large town, on winning the overall award.  I congratulate my colleague, Senator Ned O'Sullivan, who was one of the founder members of the Listowel Tidy Towns festival.  Be it in their current or past lives, it is good to see Senators doing society and their communities an important service.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.130" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.131" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#BB00400">Technological Universities Act 2018 (Section 36) (Appointed Day) Order 2018: Referral to Joint Committee</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#BB00500"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That the proposal that Seanad &Eacute;ireann approves the following Order in draft:Technological Universities Act 2018 (Section 36) (Appointed Day) Order 2018,a copy of which was laid before Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 13th September, 2018, be referred to the Joint Committee on Education and Skills, in accordance with Standing Order 71(3)(<i>k</i>), which, not later than 9th October, 2018, shall send a message to the Seanad in the manner prescribed in Standing Order 75, and Standing Order 77(2) shall accordingly apply.&quot;</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.133" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.134" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#BB00700">EU Directive on Internal Security Fund: Referral to Joint Committee</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#BB00800"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That the proposal that Seanad &Eacute;ireann approves the exercise by the State of the option or discretion under Protocol No. 21 on the position of the United Kingdom and Ireland in respect of the area of freedom, security and justice annexed to the Treaty on European Union and to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, to take part in the adoption and application of the following proposed measure:Proposal for a Regulation of the European Parliament and of the Council establishing the Internal Security Fund,a copy of which was laid before Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 9 July, 2018, be referred to the Joint Committee on Justice and Equality, in accordance with Standing Order 71(3)(<i>k</i>), which, not later than 27 September, 2018, shall send a message to the Seanad in the manner prescribed in Standing Order 75, and Standing Order 77(2) shall accordingly apply.&quot;</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.136" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.137" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#CC00100">Criminal Justice (Money Laundering and Terrorist Financing) (Amendment) Bill 2018: Second Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.138" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That the Bill be now read a Second Time."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018092500002#CC00300"><p>I am pleased to be back in Seanad &Eacute;ireann for the first time since the summer recess.  I hope everyone is in good form and I look forward to a very interesting, robust and co-operative term in the area of justice.  </p> <p>Money laundering and terrorist financing are cross-border phenomena.  We have a globalised, open economy and criminals will exploit this to move proceeds from one country to another.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Charles Flanagan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=414"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=414&amp;amp;pid=CharlesFlanagan&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->For this reason, the European Union has long had legislation in this area.  Internationally, the recommendations of the Financial Action Task Force, FATF, are applied by 35 member jurisdictions.  The FATF monitors and evaluates compliance by those members.  EU legislation and the FATF recommendations are frequently updated to reflect new trends and to ensure that they are still relevant.  </p><p>It is the fourth directive, 2015/849, that is being transposed by this Bill.  The Bill amends the 2010 Act to bring it in line with the new directive.  Members of this House may be aware that Ireland is late in transposing this directive, the deadline for which was June 2017.  The directive is extremely complex legislation whose subject matter spans a number of Departments and agencies.  An enormous amount of consultation and collaboration was required.  The complexity also led to a lengthy drafting process with the Office of the Attorney General.  Unfortunately this has meant that, despite every effort being made to progress the legislation, we are faced with infringement proceedings.  The difficulty of the task is reflected in the fact that Ireland is one of 20 member states that were unable to transpose this directive by the deadline of June of last year.  In July of this year the European Commission referred Ireland, along with two other member states, to the Court of Justice in respect of the infringement of that deadline.  My officials are continuing to engage with the Commission on this process and have referred the matter to the Office of the Attorney General for further advice.  It is worth noting that any proceedings before the court are likely to be late next year at the earliest, while it is intended that the directive will be fully transposed before the end of this year.</p><p>I emphasise that there are already robust and extensive anti-money laundering laws in Ireland.  The existing 2010 Act runs to 122 sections, with 82 of those sections concerning designated persons and the obligations of such persons.  This legislative framework is supported by a strong operational capability.  There is a range of bodies active in combatting money laundering and terrorist financing including An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, the Criminal Assets Bureau, the Central Bank and my own Department.  The anti-money laundering steering committee brings together relevant Departments and agencies to co-ordinate the national response to risks relating to money laundering and terrorist financing.  In this regard I acknowledge the great success of the Garda in recent times and, indeed, over the past couple of years.  We are oftentimes quick to be critical of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and to point out the need for further resources and the need for a greater level of engagement, but we are not so quick to acknowledge the great work that is being done.  In this regard I want to acknowledge in particular the leadership of Assistant Commissioner John O'Driscoll and his team in light of ongoing operations, some of which are producing very favourable and positive results.</p><p>In its most recent evaluation report for Ireland, the FATF found that Ireland has a generally sound and substantially effective legal and institutional anti-money laundering framework.  This new legislation with which we are dealing this afternoon will update and enhance that framework and will address many of the remaining gaps identified in the evaluation.  </p><p>As well as ensuring that Ireland fulfils its EU and international obligations, this Government is committed to tackling white collar crime in all its forms.  The Bill forms part of the package of measures announced last November that I, together with the Minister for Finance and the Minister for Business, Enterprise and Innovation, am working on in order to combat white collar crime.  The Minister for Finance and his officials share responsibility for the transposition of this directive.  As well as its role in preventing crime, anti-money laundering legislation is aimed at protecting the integrity of our financial system.  The Department of Finance has been working closely with my officials on this Bill and is drawing up its own legislation to transpose provisions of the directive on beneficial ownership of trusts and in respect of bodies corporate.</p><p>Before turning to the individual provisions of the Bill, which is complex and multifaceted, I want to give a general overview of its contents.  The main change brought about by this Bill is a more pronounced switch to a risk-based approach.  This means that, first of all, the businesses concerned, which the legislation calls "designated persons", must assess the risks of money laundering and terrorist financing involved in carrying out their business.  They must have policies and procedures in place to mitigate these risks and must determine the risk attaching to each customer transaction on a case-by-case basis, taking into account relevant factors.  They must also carry out whatever due diligence measures are warranted by that level of risk.  This represents a more targeted, and therefore more effective, application of the measures by the designated person.  The proposed law also recognises the reality that many businesses today operate in group structures across borders.  It makes a number of amendments in this regard.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Charles Flanagan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=414"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=414&amp;amp;pid=CharlesFlanagan&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The Bill expands on the requirements on Irish companies to ensure their subsidiaries overseas apply high anti-money laundering standards.  If a group implements policies and procedures properly, its subsidiaries are not subject to some restrictions that normally apply in respect of high-risk third countries.</p><p>The amendments made by the Bill also extend the scope of existing obligations in other ways.  For example, some measures which only applied to banks will apply to other financial institutions.  There are extra measures that must be applied to the beneficiaries of life assurance policies.  Measures applying to politically exposed persons will now apply to those resident in Ireland as well as those resident abroad.</p><p>Of great importance in the global fight against money laundering and terrorist financing is the role of the financial intelligence unit.  The unit in Ireland is part of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  It is responsible for receiving suspicious transaction reports from designated persons and analysing them so that it can be used to combat crime.  The directive expands the remit of the financial intelligence units and requires them to have access to all of the information they need to carry out their functions.  Taking into account the transnational nature of money laundering, it emphasises co-operation and information sharing between the financial intelligence units of different member states.  All of this is provided for in the Bill.</p><p>I intend to move several amendments to the Bill in this House.  Most of these amendments will be technical in nature but several more substantive items are included.  Of particular note is an amendment to delete section 23 of the Bill and repeal section 43 of the 2010 Act.  These sections require mandatory reporting of all transactions with certain high-risk third countries.  The financial intelligence unit has stated that this provision will unnecessarily increase the number of reports filed and cause problems for banks and non-governmental organisations working in affected areas.  The amendment will be subject to Government approval.</p><p>Also of note is an amendment to introduce a fitness and probity regime for the owners of private members gaming clubs.  This amendment, which transposes a provision of the directive, will require those who hold a directional function and the beneficial owners of such clubs to apply to An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na or the Minister for Justice for a certificate of fitness.  It will be a criminal offence to carry on such activities without that certificate of fitness.</p><p>Turning to the individual provisions of the Bill, sections 1 and 2 contain the usual provisions setting out the Short Title, commencement provisions, and interpretation section.  Sections 3 to 5, inclusive, amend the definitions in the 2010 Act.  For the most part, this is to bring them into alignment with the definitions in the directive.  In many cases, references to financial services legislation are being updated.  An important amendment is that which lowers the threshold for the application of the Act to high-value goods dealers.  Currently, they come within the Act if the value of the goods is in excess of &euro;15,000, and this amendment will bring that down to &euro;10,000.  There is an amendment in section 5 relating to legal professionals to make it clear that the Act only applies to them where they are carrying out certain services.  This amendment was made by the Criminal Justice Act 2013 but was not commenced as a technical change needed to be made.</p><p>Sections 6 to 9, inclusive, amend the definition of "beneficial owner&rdquo; to bring it in line with the new directive.  When carrying out customer due diligence, a designated person must also check the identity of any beneficial owner associated with the customer.  This includes, for example, a major shareholder in a company or the beneficiary of a trust.  The definition of "beneficial owner" will now be broader than under current law and will include, for example, the trustee of a trust.</p><p>Sections 10 to 19, inclusive, are the core provisions of the Bill.  Section 10 inserts two new sections in the 2010 Act concerning risk.  Designated persons will now be explicitly required to carry out an assessment of the risks of money laundering and terrorist financing inherent in carrying out their business.  They are also required to assess the risk of money laundering and terrorist financing in regard to a customer or a transaction, taking into account factors such as the purpose of an account or the regularity of transactions.  They must have regard to guidance and the national risk assessment.</p><p>Sections 11 to 19, inclusive, concern customer due diligence.  Section 33 of the 2010 Act contains the main obligations to identify and verify the identity of customers and beneficial owners.  Some small changes are made to that section.  For example, there are additional requirements relating to the identification of the beneficiaries of life assurance policies.  There is an exception to the rule that designated persons must cease carrying on business with a customer if they cannot carry out customer due diligence.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-09-25a.142" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Additional debate to follow.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>