<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Leas-Chathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.4" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator John O'Mahony that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health, Deputy Simon Harris, to consider the introduction of an alternative scheme to replace the motorised transport grant.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Paul Gavan of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minster for Education and Skills, Deputy Richard Bruton, to make a statement on the failure of a building contractor in receipt of publicly funded Department of Education and Skills projects, to discharge an award made by the Employment Appeals Tribunal, EAT, in favour of an individual, details supplied.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government, Deputy Eoghan Murphy, to outline the cross-Border measures undertaken when implementing emergency co-ordination preparations for, and responses to, adverse weather conditions in Ireland.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Jennifer Murnane O'Connor of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy Richard Bruton, to outline the methodology used in a recent childcare survey in County Carlow.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Martin Conway of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Finance, Deputy Paschal Donohoe, to outline the plans he has, if any, to increase the &euro;37,500 threshold for businesses to register for VAT. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Robbie Gallagher of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Charles Flanagan, to make a statement on the role of the data controller regarding community close circuit television, CCTV, schemes.</blockquote> <p>Of the matters raised by the Senators suitable for discussion, I have selected the matters raised Senators O&rsquo;Mahony and Gavan and they will be taken now.  Senators &Oacute; Donnghaile and Murnane O&rsquo;Connor have withdrawn their Commencement matters, which I had selected.  I regret I had to rule out of order the matter submitted by Senator Gallagher on the ground that it is a repeat of a Commencement matter raised on 17 May 2018.  Senator Conway may give notice on another day of the matter that he wishes to raise.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.7" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#A00300">Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.8" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#A00400">Motorised Transport Grant Eligibility</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#A00500"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Finian McGrath, to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#A00600"><p>I thank the Leas-Chathaoirleach for choosing this matter and the Minister of State for attending.  We know it off by heart at this stage so there is no need for me to go into the details again.  I have had a number of cases on this motorised transport grant, particularly because I come from a rural constituency where there is no public transport and people need to bring their family members to appointments and take them out for therapy, etc.  The withdrawal of this grant in 2013 has caused great stress, trauma and difficulties to these families.  There was a guarantee given that it would be replaced with a new scheme in October 2013.  We are now in July 2018 and nothing has happened since.</p> <p>I have raised it continually during my time in the D&aacute;il and in this House.  I am raising it again now because of an issue I am seriously concerned about.  I refer to a woman whose husband is quite ill.  He is in hospital and she is bringing him to appointments a couple of times a week.  Cars are breaking down on numerous occasions on the way to those appointments.  This woman has saved the State thousands of euro by caring for her husband and she will not allow anyone else to care for him because he has brain damage, epileptic seizures and depression as well as word finding, memory and understanding problems.  It really is a humanitarian issue at this stage.  I am not blaming the Minister of State but I hope he can report some progress and that there is some light at the end of the tunnel.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#A00700"><p>I thank and commend Senator O'Mahony for raising this important issue.  I also commend his determination and perseverance on the motor transport grant proposals.  I am happy to update this House on the progress of the health (transport support) Bill.  The Senator will be familiar with the background to the closure of the mobility allowance and motorised transport grant schemes in February 2013.  Following the closure of the schemes, no further motorised transport grants have been payable.  The Government, however, decided that the detailed preparatory work required for a new transport support scheme, and associated statutory provisions, should be progressed by my colleague, the Minister for Health, Deputy Simon Harris.</p> <p>The Government directed that the Health Service Executive, HSE, should continue to pay an equivalent monthly payment of up to &euro;208.50 to the 4,046 people in receipt of the mobility allowance, on an interim basis, pending the establishment of a new transport support scheme.  I welcome that.  These 4,046 people are getting the &euro;208.50 each month.  The bottom line, though, is that Senator O'Mahony is right.  A Programme for a Partnership Government acknowledges the ongoing drafting of primary legislation for a new transport support scheme to assist those with a disability to meet their mobility costs.  The health (transport support) Bill is on the list of priority legislation for publication in the spring-summer session 2018.</p> <p>There is some light at the end of the tunnel.  I confirm that work on the policy proposals for the new scheme is at an advanced stage.  The proposals seek to ensure there is a firm statutory basis to the scheme's operation, there is transparency and equity in the eligibility criteria attaching to the scheme, resources are targeted at those with the greatest needs and the scheme is capable of being costed and is affordable on its introduction and on an ongoing basis.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Finian McGrath:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1822"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1822&amp;amp;pid=FinianMcGrath&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I recently brought a memorandum to Government for a new transport support payment scheme.  Following consideration of the matter, it was decided to withdraw the memorandum from the Cabinet agenda on 8 May last.  I intend to revert to Government in due course with revised proposals reflective of the discussion at Cabinet.  While not wishing to breach Cabinet confidentiality, the view in government is reflective of Senator O'Mahony's view, namely, that we need to ensure that adequate funding is available for this scheme.  Hence, the debate and the delay.</p><p>It is important to note that the disabled drivers and disabled passengers scheme operated by the Revenue Commissioners remains in place.  Specifically adapted vehicles driven by persons with disabilities are exempt from payment of tolls on national roads and toll bridges.  Transport Infrastructure Ireland has responsibility for this scheme.  Work is ongoing in various Departments, agencies and transport providers on how access to public transport services can be further improved.  Under the national disability inclusion strategy, the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport has responsibility for the continued development of accessibility and availability of public transport for people with a disability.</p><p>Senator O'Mahony has on many occasions raised the issue of inadequate access to public transport, particularly in rural areas.  I am aware of the stress this is causing for families and I hope to be able to report progress soon on the transport support payment scheme.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#B00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his reply.  Can he confirm if he will be bringing a memorandum to Government before the summer recess or the final Cabinet meeting?  If not, this matter will run into the sand.  I do not propose to add to the speculation about an election or the supply and confidence agreement.  This scheme is committed to in the programme for Government and it needs to be delivered.  Can the Minister of State indicate a timescale for when he will bring a memorandum to Cabinet for consideration and approval?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#B00300"><p>In regard to the memorandum, I am considering three options.  I know exactly what I want in terms of this scheme.  I am sure Senator O'Mahony would agree with my proposals.  I was not happy with what was proposed at Cabinet and I undertook to consider other options in terms of funding.  My preferred option is the most expensive.  There is a problem in that as we approach the Estimates process, there are other groups, such as senior citizens with disabled adults seeking residential care, in respect of which I am seeking approximately 400 additional places in 2019.  The assessment of need issue is also on the table and families with young children with disabilities are also demanding funding.  There is competing needs for funding.  As far as I am concerned the Government committed to the introduction of this scheme in the programme for Government.</p> <p>I take the Senator's point about transport issues in rural Ireland, the stress this is causing for families, the amount of work these families do and the savings that accrue to the Exchequer as a result of that work.  In answer to Senator O'Mahony's question, I hope to bring the memorandum to Cabinet before the summer recess, and at the latest, early September.  As I said, I am currently considering three options and I will decide in the next week or two which option I will bring to Cabinet.  I hope I will achieve the objective of bringing it before Cabinet before the summer recess but, if not, I will do so early in September.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#B00400"><p>The Minister of State will not want to hear from me again on this matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#B00500"><p>No.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.17" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#B00600">Schools Building Contractors</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#B00700"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Halligan, to the House to discuss the issue of a migrant worker who has been exploited by an unscrupulous employer.  As there has been a huge amount of correspondence with the Department of Education and Skills on this matter I am sure the Minister of State is familiar with it.  I welcome Mr. Porfireanu and his wife to the Public Gallery.  I know from my background as a trade unionist that this case is not unique but it raises serious issues concerning the award of public contracts.</p> <p>Mr. Porfireanu successfully made complaints to the Rights Commissioner Service under the Payment of Wages Act 1991 and Terms of Employment Information Acts 1994 to 2001 relating to his employment with this contractor.  The contractor appealed those decisions to the Employment Appeals Tribunal, which upheld Mr. Porfireanu's awards on appeal in March of last year.  The value of these awards is &euro;14,246, which is a sizeable sum, the vast majority of which is unpaid wages.  When this exploitation took place, Mr. Porfireanu was employed by P.J. McLoughlin &amp;amp; Sons on publicly-funded projects in Coolock and adjacent to this House at the National Gallery.  Attempts to contact the contractor to ensure he fulfilled his obligations to Mr. Porfireanu were met with frustration.  Despite repeated attempts to discuss the matter throughout last September no reply was forthcoming.  Mr. Porfireanu was forced to engage a solicitor to seek judgment for registration in the Circuit Court and subsequently an execution order to the Sheriff to seek to enforce the court order.  The original award and subsequent judgment remain undischarged.</p> <p>I refer to section 5.3 of the public works contracts which provides that contractors must observe employment law and legally binding determinations of the Labour Court.  The contractor self certifies using standard form MF 1.13. that it is compliant in this regard.  I am sure the Minister of State will agree that this was not respected in this case.  Section 5 of the public works contract reflects the agreements reached on outsourcing in section 20 of the Croke Park agreement and section 3.3.5 of the Lansdowne Road agreement.</p> <p>We should not accept that this contractor can be awarded public contracts and operate on those same contracts while failing to respect or comply with the decision of the state industrial relations processes and subsequent Circuit Court judgments.  This contractor is currently engaged as the main contractor on two Department of Education and Skills projects in Westmeath and Kildare, namely, Curraghmore national school in Mullingar and the Mercy Convent primary school in Naas.  The Minister of State will not disagree that Mr. Porfireanu, who is with his family in the Gallery, has been waiting too long to receive money that he worked hard to earn.  This is an example of a migrant worker, working here legally and being exploited by an unscrupulous employer, one which continues to be rewarded by the Department of Education and Skills.  It is bad enough that this employer refuses to discharge an award of the state industrial relations mechanisms and is in violation of a Circuit Court judgment relating to that award but it is considerably worse that he is able to flout the terms of the capital works contracts.</p> <p>Is the Minister satisfied with the current methods for ensuring that contractors awarded State contracts respect our industrial relations processes and does he have plans to ensure that contractors such as P.J. McLoughlin and Sons do not obtain state contracts while violating the rights of workers like Mr. Porfireanu?  Also, will he help this man who is owed &euro;15,000?  P.J. McLoughlin &amp;amp; Sons continues to be awarded contracts by the Department of Education and Skills despite that it is flagrantly in violation of judgments of the Labour Court.  To be honest, it is but one of many such companies but the Minister of State needs to do something concrete to help this man to restore his confidence in this State.  Mr. Porfireanu has done everything possible to try to get justice but the State has failed him on every occasion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1351" speakername="John Halligan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#B00800"><p>I thank Senator Gavan for raising this matter and I acknowledge his work in respect of workers rights.  I also welcome Mr. Porfireanu and his family to the Gallery.</p> <p>As Senator Gavan will be aware a building project is a complex contractual arrangement between the client, the main contractor, specialist subcontractors, domestic subcontractors, suppliers of materials, suppliers of plant and so on.  In general, all subcontractors employed on education sector building projects are employed directly by the main contractor or indirectly by the main contractor through subcontractors.  As provided for in legislation, it is a matter for all subcontractors to agree terms and conditions and a schedule of payments with the main contractor as their direct employer.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy John Halligan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2315"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2315&amp;amp;pid=JohnHalligan&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->As these contracts involve contractual matters between private companies, my Department has no authority to intervene in these matters.  I have checked this point.  The Department, as funding authority, is not necessarily the employer under the public works contract on schools building projects.  Where the Department does not own the site, the school management authority is normally the employer for the purposes of the public works contract.  Many projects are devolved for delivery to outside agencies, such as education and training boards, the National Development Finance Agency, local authorities etc.  In these cases the devolved agency would normally be the employer for the purposes of the public works contract.  Also, in respect of non-compliance with relevant employment law, enforcement and prosecution falls under the remit of Workplace Relations Commission, WRC.  Where the Department of Education and Skills becomes aware of issues regarding tax compliance or social welfare fraud, such matters are referred to the Revenue Commissioners or the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection or both, as appropriate.</p><p>The Department has taken a number of steps to deal with the use of bogus self-employment contractors on schools building projects.  It has appointed an external consultant, Contractors Administration Service, CAS, to conduct random audits on schools building projects.  Should irregularities be uncovered in terms of non-compliance with relevant employment law, enforcement and prosecution falls under the remit of the WRC and the Department reports any discrepancies found to it.  If the audit uncovers any other matters of concern regarding tax compliance or social welfare fraud, such matters are referred to either the Revenue Commissioners or the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection or both, as appropriate.  My Department does not have the statutory powers to investigate such complaints.  This rests with the WRC, the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection or the Revenue Commissioners, as appropriate.</p><p>It is worth drawing attention also to the advice on the WRC website with regard to enforcement of decisions that "If an Employer/Respondent (Employer) fails to carry out a decision of an Adjudication Officer of the Workplace Relations Commission, or a decision of the Labour Court arising from an appeal of an Adjudication Officer's decision, within the prescribed time, an application may be made to the District Court for an order directing the Employer to carry out the decision."</p><p>I do have sympathy for any subcontractor or worker who is not paid either appropriately or what is due.  I have held detailed discussions with officials of my Department on this issue.  We are bound by legislation and criteria laid down by the Department.  I have no problem with meeting the particular family with the Senator.  I would be delighted to do so because I know the Senator does a lot of work in the area of workplace relations.  I am not afraid to acknowledge that.  I am not too sure what I might be able to do but I would be prepared to meet the family to see if we could go further on this issue.  It does concern me.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#C00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his reply and I acknowledge that he has a record for protecting workers.  I know where he comes from politically and I respect that.  I welcome the offer to meet Mr. Porfireanu.  I will take the Minister of State up on that and make an appointment.  We will make it happen.</p> <p>In respect of the reply he has given me I have two points to make, which I think the Minister of State already sees.  This involves the main contractor, namely, P.J. McLoughlin &amp;amp; Sons.  The Department is awarding contracts to a main contractor which has left this man short of &euro;15,000 in wages and it has disregarded every State body in respect of that.  The Minister of State pointed out the ability to go to the District Court but we have already done that.  The sheriff has said she cannot intervene because several companies are registered at the address so she does not know whose property she is taking.  We have exhausted the procedures.  I have one suggestion which I hope the Department could do as it just means getting it to move slightly and that is to write to the employer asking it to comment on the status of this case.  The Minister of State could write from the Department of Education and Skills saying this has been brought to his attention and he would like to understand why this award has not been carried out.  Something like that could actually help.  I welcome that the Minister of State has offered to work with me on this issue.  Let us set up an appointment and see if we can get justice for this man.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1351" speakername="John Halligan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#C00300"><p>I will meet the man as soon as I possibly can.  As this is a very important issue, I will certainly meet early next week, if that would suit the Senator.  I would be delighted to do that.</p> <p>There are a couple of points I need to make on behalf of the Department.  I am told the Department was not involved in any contractual arrangement in this particular case and the Employment Appeals Tribunal did not bring the matter to the Department's attention at any stage, as the Department was not a party to the proceedings or the contractual matters thereunder.</p> <p>I will take into consideration the proposals the Senator has made and will go back to the Department with them.  There may be something I might be able to do, there may be something I am missing out on that might come to light when I meet the family next week with the Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#C00400"><p>I appreciate that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.24" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 10.56 a.m. and resumed at 11.30 a.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.25" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#G00100">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#G00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, motion regarding special committee on climate action, to be taken on the conclusion of the Order of Business, without debate; No. 2, motion regarding the proposal to re-establish the Seanad Special Committee on the Withdrawal of the United Kingdom from the European Union, to be taken on the conclusion of No. 1, without debate; No. 3, Education (Admission to Schools) Bill 2016 - Report and Final Stages, to be taken at 12.45 p.m.; No. 4, Judicial Appointments Commission Bill 2017 - Committee Stage (Resumed), to be taken on the conclusion of No. 3, and to adjourn at 7 p.m., if not previously concluded, and to be resumed on the conclusion of No. 5 and adjourned at 11 p.m.; No. 5, Private Members' business, Civil Liability (Amendment) (No. 3) Bill 2018 - Order for Second Stage and Second Stage, to be taken at 7 p.m., with the time allocated to this debate not to exceed two hours.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#G00300"><p>I mention an issue that has been raised in this House before, namely, the increase in energy prices that will affect everyone, but in particular 1.2 million households, come September.  These announcement was made by Electric Ireland.  We will see increases of up to 6.2% in the residential sector.  What this means is that householders will be nearly &euro;110 per year less well off.  These are hidden taxes for individuals.  When energy prices increase, we do not necessarily see an increase in income, or an increase in social welfare payments.  The Society of St. Vincent de Paul announced last year that half of the people living in consistent poverty went without heating at some stage last year.  Many of us who canvassed during the winter, going door-to-door, will have met many elderly people who go to bed at 6 p.m. or 7 p.m. to avoid having to put their heating on in the evenings.  This is something we must address.  This is especially important as these price rises are coming in in September, a time when parents are under a lot of pressure to pay out for children who are going back to school.  There is the cost of uniforms and books and the payments to schools to subvent the very low capitation levels.  This is something we need to discuss so I call for a debate on energy prices.</p> <p>The second issue I would like to raise is unemployment levels.  We know unemployment levels are at an all-time low.  The National Economic and Social Council is trying to focus on the reason people find it difficult to transition from social welfare benefits to employment.  It has noted that unemployment levels remain consistently high in many communities around the country, especially in disadvantaged areas.  We need to invite the Minister to the House for a debate, particularly on how people can transition adequately and fairly from being in receipt of State payments to being able to contribute to the workforce.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#G00400"><p>The Leader will know I have some interest in the position of the President.  I understand the Government is going to hold referenda later this year to tidy up the Constitution.  One of the places that it might consider tidying up is the nominations for President.  It is held among the political parties.  This makes it very difficult for any citizen of the State to successfully seek a nomination.  I am not talking, of course, about myself because I will have no problem doing that.  I am talking about future elections.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.29" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#G00475"><p>Be quiet over there in Fianna F&aacute;il.  You are a gutless shower who pulled out of it last week.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.31" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#G00493"><p>Do not give me any of that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#G00500"><p>This is very unpresidential.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#G00600"><p>He has to tie down his Council of State now-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#G00700"><p>Careful now, careful now-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#G00800"><p>I think Senator Craughwell is over-confident.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#G00900"><p>May I continue?  The Senator will not be on the Council of State if he is not quiet.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#G01000"><p>With all due respects, the Senator invited comment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#G01100"><p>I will confine my-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#G01200"><p>By way of clarification, most Senators have an interest in the President but not too many of us want to run for office.  I am happy where I am.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#G01300"><p>What I am talking about is extending the nomination process in order that there is an alternative route outside of the political system.  It is something that we might have a debate on with the relevant Minister after the summer break.  I am sure whoever is sitting in my seat will not mind taking up the issue on my behalf.</p> <p>Last night we had what can only be regarded as a disgusting shambles.  A Bill was brought before the House and we understand from those who oversee these things that there is difficulty with it.  Somebody was shouting about Ireland being independent and all of that.  Is this Bill likely to end up before the European Court of Justice at some stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#G01400"><p>I hope so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#G01500"><p>What happened last night was outrageous.  It is even more outrageous that we are going to try to drive on.  I said it was the Minister's Bill, but it is the Leader's Government that will face the wrath of history for what it is trying to do here.  It really needs to step back and look at what is going on around it.  No support is worth that price, that it would sell its soul.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#G01600"><p>I call Senator Conway-Walsh.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#G01700"><p>I raise the issue again of the Versatis patches.  The Cathaoirleach will know I have raised this issue many times over the past months.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Rose Conway-Walsh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2462"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2462&amp;amp;pid=RoseConwayWalsh&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I recognise that there has been something of a rowing back on this matter and that some adjustments have been made.  While I welcome those adjustments, there are still thousands of people in chronic pain who really need Versatis patches.  I want to give the House an idea of the plight of one of these people.  Her name is Anne-Marie.  She is 49 years of age.  She says she has had rheumatoid arthritis since 1975.  Over the years, her condition has become chronic and she has had almost 40 surgeries, 13 of which involved joint replacements.  She has had both hips, both knees, both shoulders, both elbows and several knuckles replaced.  Most recently, she has had revision surgery on her shoulder.  The other procedures included orthopaedic surgery, gall bladder surgery and so on.  She was only five years of age when she found out she had rheumatoid arthritis.  Given the amount of surgery she has had over the years and all the wear and tear on her joints, she had pain every single hour of every single day.  Given that she had been on opiates long-term, they do not work.  The Versatis patch gave her a great deal of relief when she was on it.  She has severe back and shoulder pain.  In recent days, she has begun to suffer from hip pain again.  She also has problems with her kidneys and eyes.</p><p>For someone like that to be left in chronic pain, though she gets relief from the Versatis patches, cannot be right.  I am appealing for the Minister to give us an update or status report on Versatis patches.  I have asked many times for the decision to withdraw Versatis patches from the medical card scheme to be reviewed.  It is now time to review it.  We are many months into the blunt decision made.  I call on the Minister to come to the House to have a debate on this and to provide a true and accurate update on the situation relating to Versatis patches.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#H00200"><p>I propose an amendment to the Order of Business to defer consideration of the resumed Committee Stage of the Judicial Appointments Commission Bill.  Anyone who was in the Chamber last night or who was observing the debate would have been struck by the extraordinary and somewhat farcical nature of the debate.  Those of us who were engaged in putting amendments in good faith &ndash; I have tabled 20 amendments to the Bill &ndash; asked the Minister whether he had sight of the Group of States against Corruption, GRECO, report.  We know the report expressed significant concerns about the Government proposals in the Bill.  I was able to read into the record of the House certain excerpts from the as-yet-unpublished GRECO report.  At least, they are purported to be excerpts because no one can be sure what it is and we have not seen it yet.  The Minister made the extraordinary statement in the House that he had not seen the report.  It was unclear whether or how many people in his Department had seen it.  He said he had not yet brought it to Government.  He said he would seek Government clearance to publish it at the earliest opportunity.  When we pressed him, the Minister said there would be a Cabinet meeting tomorrow, Thursday.  We understood this to mean that he would be able to seek clearance from Government tomorrow to publish the report.</p> <p>I am proposing an amendment to the Order of Business.  It is reasonable to suggest to colleagues that we should not be asked to legislate in the dark.  We should not debate amendments without knowledge of the full content of the GRECO report or without full knowledge of what the Minister's response will be when he eventually sees the report.  It is a most unsatisfactory state of affairs.  The House will sit late again tonight.  We were here until 11 o'clock last night.  We got to amendment No. 3 because of the issue surrounding the GRECO report.  If we were simply to defer consideration of the resumed Committee Stage from today to enable us to have sight of the report when it is eventually republished, then we would be able to move things on far more swiftly and without the controversy that arose last night.</p> <p>It is extraordinary for the Minister to state that a report is out that he knows of by a reputable Council of Europe body, the Council of Europe Group of States Against Corruption.  The group has expressed or is reported to have expressed significant criticism about the Government proposals.  The excerpt I have is up-to-date as of 31 May this year.  Yet, the Minister has said he has not read it and only intends to seek clearance to publish it at the earliest opportunity, when we are half way through Committee Stage.  We understand that the Minister wishes to have Report Stage next Tuesday, in less than a week.</p> <p>It is utterly unsatisfactory to ask us to debate and draft amendments in this setting.  I appeal to colleagues with any sense of decent and efficient procedure in this House to support the amendment to the Order of Business today.  I am grateful to those who supported it yesterday.  It is a reasonable to request that we would not be asked to continue the debate on Committee Stage without sight of the GRECO report.  It is an important report that appears to be in the hands of many people.  Some of us have excerpts from it, but the Minister does not yet appear to have read it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#H00300"><p>Do I take it that your proposal for the amendment is that the Judicial Appointments Commission Bill, which is on Committee Stage, not be taken today, Senator?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#H00400"><p>Precisely.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#H00500"><p>That is fine.  Senator Conway is next.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#H00600"><p>While we are debating important issues, there are many families, especially in my constituency, who have no water at the moment.  Since last Saturday afternoon, the entire community of Fanore in north Clare has had absolutely no water &ndash; not a drop, not enough water for people to wash their hands.  In the past 24 or 48 hours, the people of Ballyvaughan in County Clare have been in a similar situation whereby they have no water.  They do not even have water to wash their hands either.  I acknowledge and respect the effort that has been made by engineers and other staff of Clare County Council to resolve these problems and make water available.  However, I have no regard for the atrocious behaviour of Irish Water.  People from the villages of Fanore and Ballyvaughan contacted Irish Water in the past 48 hours.  They have been told by the help desk or call centre that Irish Water did not know there was a problem or water shortage in the area.</p> <p>I am a Member of the Oireachtas and I live in north Clare.  Yet, I have had no communication of any kind from anyone in Irish Water to indicate what is going on or to outline the timeline for resolving the problems.  That is totally and utterly unacceptable.  The time has really come for every county to have an office with Irish Water written over the door where people who are paying for water, either through taxes or rates, as is the case with commercial interests, can walk in or ring up and discover the problem with their water pressure or the reason there is no water in their taps and when the supply will be restored.  I am asking the Leader to summon Irish Water to the House today to explain to Members of the Oireachtas exactly what is going on.  The audiovisual room is downstairs.  The officials can come in.  They held clinics here for long enough.  We have not seen sign nor light of Irish Water for the past two weeks since a crisis has developed in water.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#H00700"><p>Is the Senator proposing an amendment to the Order of Business?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#H00800"><p>No, I am asking the Leader, through his good offices, to intervene and try to get some communication for the people of Ballyvaughan and Fanore in County Clare specifically and for the other people of Ireland who are facing water shortages.  It is time Irish Water came out and explained this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1373" speakername="Keith Swanick" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#H00900"><p>We have all been enjoying the unprecedented good weather recently.  I want to mention the unsung heroes who once again keep us safe on a day-to-day basis.  Just as it was during the bad weather we witnessed some months ago, the emergency services have been handling several weather-related crises of late.  The fire services are dealing with unprecedented gorse and grass fires.  The Irish Coast Guard is being called on multiple times each day as those swimming in the sea get into difficulties.  The health services are dealing with people who have suffered bad sunburn and heatstroke.  There are more cyclists and motorcyclists on the roads, which ensures that our first responders are kept busy.</p> <p>Last week, I was contacted by the Irish Water Safety informing me that the lifeguard station at Claycastle Beach in Youghal &ndash; I imagine the Leader is familiar with this &ndash; was broken into and lifesaving equipment was stolen.  The station was vandalised and sprayed with fire extinguishers.  Lifeguards up and down the country are exceptionally busy.  They are under immense pressure with the good weather and now they have to contend with thugs who would seek to destroy this vital equipment that is needed to save lives.  I call on the Leader to convey to the Minister for Justice and Equality the need to look after these people as they look after us.  I would like an update on when the Life Saving Equipment Bill will proceed to Committee Stage.  As we know, there has been great cross-party support for the Bill.  It would be great to see it back before the House soon.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#H01000"><p>I want to raise the issue of hotel workers.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paul Gavan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2469"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2469&amp;amp;pid=PaulGavan&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The Leader might recall that a couple of weeks ago I raised the fact we intended to have a meeting.  We had that meeting yesterday and I thank colleagues who attended.  We had a very good attendance from all parties except one.  Unfortunately, nobody from Fine Gael was able to attend which was a huge disappointment to the SIPTU delegation and the hotel workers who came along.  </p><p>I ask for a debate specifically on the issue of the VAT rebate and the &euro;500 million we subsidise hoteliers with each year.  I want to raise it because the money should be going to health and housing.  If we accept that the money has to keep going to hotels, at the very least the Government should insist that the Irish Hotels Federation, IHF, engages with workers.  Standards in the vast majority of hotels are plummeting.  Only one hotel in Cork - the Imperial Hotel - still deals with workers on a collective bargaining basis.  There is only one such hotel in Limerick, which is the South Court Hotel.  The vast majority of hotels, under direct instruction from the IHF, do not deal with unions nationally or locally and do not attend the Workplace Relations Commission.  As a result, we have standards like this.  We heard from one of the workers yesterday in one of the biggest five-star hotels in the country that on an eight-hour shift she has to clean 30 rooms on her own.  It is the industry "standard" that is being applied.  We have minimum wage jobs.  We got to the bottom of the skills shortages we hear about with regard to chefs.  The average wage of a chef in Ireland is &euro;10 an hour.  Even the Department of Business, Enterprise and Innovation has acknowledged that the problem of the skills shortage arose because the industry will not pay the necessary rates of pay.  </p><p>I am asking for a debate because the Government has another opportunity to do the right thing.  It has consistently failed to do it in previous years despite it being highlighted by me and others.  The right thing to do is to tell the industry that before it is given the subsidy of &euro;500 million it should sit down and engage and work out a sectoral employment order to raise standards and conditions for everyone in the industry.  I ask that we have that debate as soon as possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#J00200"><p>I want to highlight the alarming state of affairs which results in tens of thousands of roadworthy vehicles being prematurely scrapped every year.  It is a growing phenomenon.  The rate at which it is happening this year means there will be a 129% increase on the number of vehicles scrapped last year.  The big concern is it is not driven by a road safety issue per se, because all vehicles on the road have to have a certificate of roadworthiness, but by the fact insurance companies are universally refusing cover or quoting exorbitant premia for vehicles that are ten years old or older.  The consequence is it is not economically viable to insure them and people have to replace their vehicles.  Something stinks in this regard.</p> <p>From an environmental point of view, it takes a lot of energy and carbon emissions to produce a vehicle.  We have an NCT system in place to ensure vehicles are roadworthy.  If we accept a vehicle is roadworthy, we have to be concerned if cars are being put off the road by insurance companies because it does not suit their agenda.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#J00300"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#J00400"><p>There is another issue.  Many people who have older vehicles cannot afford to buy newer vehicles.  In rural Ireland a car is not a luxury, it is a necessity because we do not have public transport.  When many youngsters get their first car, they get an older vehicle.  The issue has to be examined.  The Minister of State, Deputy D'Arcy, has to look into it and he needs to come to the House.  I would like him to investigate if there is collusion between the big insurance companies and the motor manufacturers because this seems to favour the motor manufacturers.</p><p>Another issue, which has been well highlighted, is the number of imports from the UK.  If people are replacing their second-hand vehicles with imports, VRT is not generated by the State.  </p><p>Conor Faughnan comments on motoring matters on behalf of the AA on the radio and in the media all the time.  He represents the AA, which is a big player in the insurance industry.  I would like him to set out that there will be no impediment to people with vehicles that are ten years old or older obtaining insurance from his company at least and to shine some light on what is happening here.  </p><p>I compliment <i>Autobiz</i>, which is the motor trade monthly magazine, on fighting this campaign because it is not good for local economies.  There are serious questions to be answered.  </p><p>A series of insurance issues have been raised in the Chamber in recent weeks.  I would like the Minister of State, Deputy D'Arcy, to come in and deal with them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#J00500"><p>I second Senator Bacik's amendment.  She made the arguments extremely well.  I point out to the Government that the GRECO report will not go away.  It will land with a splat and the criticisms will be out there to be reckoned with.</p><p>I refer to comments the Taoiseach made in New York about the media.  He was perhaps a little ill-advised to align his views with those of President Trump but when he said the media was not interested in the truth but in the story he was 100% right.  I laughed when I heard them all twittering and screaming on RT&Eacute; radio this morning about it.  It was a complete nonsense.  The media get into hysteria at the slightest criticism of them.  From my experience, they lie and lie and lie again.  During the presidential election RT&Eacute;, the national broadcaster, allowed a woman to say on air that I advocated parents having sex with their own children.  <i>The Sun</i>newspaper said I abused the Seanad to get passports for lovers.  Both were absolutely damnable lies and I could give the House 20 or 30 other lies.  They were not interested in the truth; they were interested in the story and they did not give a damn if they lied.  I am one of the few people prepared to stand up and say this.  I know the media will gut me over it but that is the way they behave.  I have to laugh at them getting into a hysterical twitter because the Taoiseach said they are interested in the story and not the truth.  The other thing is he said it at a private lunch.  There is no such thing as a private lunch nowadays because people have their telephones out and they are recording and filming and all the rest of it.  It is all right for somebody like me who does not give a damn what he says because I always try to tell the truth and I do not care whether it goes down well or badly.  </p><p>I will also address the point raised by Senator Craughwell about the presidential election and the nomination process.  He is 100% right.  The political parties have it all sewn up.  It is grotesquely wrong and unfair, and militates against the private individual.  At the Constitutional Convention, I got a motion through broadening it and allowing the ordinary people of Ireland to have a say in the process.  It went through by 98% of the vote, by far the highest of any vote in the Constitutional Convention.  The Government has ignored it.  It is about time we look at the Presidency and revise both the nomination procedures and the financial provisions which also favour the political parties over the private individual.  The citizens of this country are entitled to a fair whack.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#J00600"><p>I will raise the issue of Shannon Airport and its collaboration with ESB on the plan to reduce its carbon emissions.  Climate change is something we are all very concerned with.  Over the next 18 months the airport will bring down its electricity use by over a third, which is welcome.</p><p>There was a report on small breweries in <i>The Irish Times</i>today.  Their drinks have become popular, especially in local pubs.  It is alleged that the bigger breweries are paying publicans not to stock a large supply of drinks from smaller breweries.  I have been contacted by a local brewer in Limerick who is concerned.  The commission investigated the report and said this is not happening.  My local brewer does not agree with the findings.  Local brewers are coming up against a brick wall trying to get some local pubs to stock their goods.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Maria Byrne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2465"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2465&amp;amp;pid=MariaByrne&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is time we bring in the Minister to have a debate and make him see there is an issue here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#K00200"><p>I was appalled at the revelations at the Committee of Public Accounts yesterday that Sammon Contracting received 98% of the payment it was owed under the public private partnership contract but none of the payments were passed on to the subcontractors.  Ever since the umbrella company Carillion collapsed earlier this year, this has been a mess.  Carillion collapsed, Sammon went into examinership and these contractors were never paid.  This is nothing short of disgraceful.  Where is the accountability?  The contractors deserve good pay for good work.  They worked hard for it and they should not lose out.  They have families and employees to support and a future to protect, and we have to do something.</p> <p>I am utterly disappointed with the news that yet again, Carlow has been left at the bottom of the list to have promises delivered.  While contractors are now in place at two Wicklow schools and one Wexford school for work to be completed in September, Carlow was scheduled for December.  I have spoken about our case for a long time and it is frustrating to see Carlow left with a longer timeframe, despite 90% of the school being complete.  A December completion date is better than none but it is unfair on the new secondary school students to have to uproot halfway through their first year in a new school and a new system.  I am not happy with any of this.  I want the Minister for Education and Skills to explain how we can pay someone for a job not done.  This is taxpayers' money and there are subcontractors who have not received a penny.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#K00300"><p>I will follow on from the theme raised by Senator Conway on the issue we have with water restrictions.  We have had an exceptionally dry period over the past four or five weeks and the knock-on effect of the dry period is that wells and water systems throughout Ireland are under pressure.  In my part of the world places such as Nohoval and Robert's Cove are under pressure, as are major towns such as Clonakilty where there were water restrictions last night from 11 p.m. to 7 a.m.  This will be a big issue.  Having water restrictions in place in early July means we will have at least six to eight weeks of real water issues in my part of the world.  Traditionally we are used to having an issue in August if we have had a dry summer.  This is six weeks earlier than ever anticipated.  I am very concerned about what will happen, not alone with regard to our tourism trade and busy towns but also the agricultural community, which depends on water for very obvious reasons as they have to feed their animals.</p> <p>This is a crisis we have to manage over the next eight or nine weeks.  I do not see any major change in the weather going forward and a long-term plan has to be put in place to ensure water systems can survive the next eight or nine weeks.  At present we are sending tankers to many of these places.  Clonakilty and Nohoval have received tankers.  These tankers are augmenting the supply, which is very positive.  We need to put in place a real campaign to start monitoring water and to ensure there are no leakages.  We must also ensure there is no waste of water.  The public needs to be informed on an hourly basis on the water levels required in order that we can actually survive the next five or six weeks.  In the long term, we need real investment in these places to ensure we have a water supply in order that these towns can develop and, more importantly, the water systems required for the future are put in place so that when we have dry weather like this, we will not have the crisis we have at present.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1382" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#K00400"><p>I wish colleagues such as Senator Craughwell who are contemplating a presidential election every success in the coming weeks, including my good colleague from Cavan, an Ulster man, Senator Wilson, who is contemplating a run for the presidential election.  I know he has much deliberation to do.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#K00500"><p>At last.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1382" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#K00600"><p>I am announcing it for him.  At last he is declaring.  I want to wish him well this morning.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#K00700"><p>Are they on the same panel?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1382" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#K00800"><p>On another issue, yesterday I voted to support the Judicial Appointments Commission Bill being debated and I will do the same today.  The reason for it is not that I have been captured or bought by any politician or Government Minister.  I do it because I firmly believe it is the right thing to do.  International comparisons should be used, and all of the international non-legal research that has been carried out by academics who are not linked to the legal profession has shown that having a lay majority for judicial appointments works.  It works in England and Scotland, where the chair is independent.  It is the right course of action to take.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#K00900"><p>The Birmingham Six and the Guildford Four-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1382" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#K01000"><p>Yes there are people with concerns and that is only right, but I think the manner in which we lay out those concerns should be discussed on Committee Stage.</p> <p>Much has been said about the latest GRECO report.  I have not read it but I read the previous GRECO report.  It was overwhelmingly supportive of the current strategy by the Government on this legislation.  It recommends a lay chair to provide balance and independence.  That was the GRECO position in 2014.  I would be very surprised if GRECO has changed its viewpoint so substantially, as has been inferred by other Members.  Some people say Independent Members were bought.  I certainly was not bought.  Nobody approached me to support the Bill.  I am doing it because I believe it is the right thing to do.  I believe the highest office in the land, the Judiciary, which makes laws as well-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#K01100"><p>The President is the highest office in the land.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1382" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#K01200"><p>-----should not be in any way captured by any political party.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#K01300"><p>Hear, hear.  Well said.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#K01400"><p>I wish my colleague from Cavan, Senator Wilson, well in his presidential endeavours.  I have known him down the years and he has a presidential gait.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#K01500"><p>I thought you were backing me.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#K01600"><p>We also wish Senator Craughwell well but we get parochial on these questions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#K01700"><p>I know there is a heatwave and we might be in the silly season.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#K01800"><p>To briefly return to Senator Wilson's situation, he does have a presidential demeanour and gait so it is a good start and I wish him well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#K01900"><p>Thank you.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#K02000"><p>Everyone in the House is thoroughly enjoying the good weather and why would we not?  It is a unique Mediterranean-type weather experience here.  Like everything else it presents its own problems.  There are real issues in the agricultural sector.  There was a very good piece on the RT&Eacute; news last night about the difficulties grain farmers along the south have.  In the area where I live, there is a real issue with water shortages for farmers in Cavan and Monaghan.  There have been challenges in a number of incidences.  There is a challenge with the growth of a new cut of silage and in some instances, there are challenges with crop growth.  There will be a challenge with getting alternative feed for cattle and drawing water in some instances.  I ask the Leader to invite the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine to the House as a matter of urgency to discuss a raft of very specific strategies to be looked at to deal with shortages and the problems confronting agriculture.  We need to know that Teagasc is on board and that the Department is completely on board.  We do not want to anticipate such things, but it may be necessary, unfortunately, in the end to give a form of fodder relief to farmers and that cannot be shirked from if it has to happen.  Will the Leader considering this as a real priority issue?  There are people suffering the downside of what is a wonderful weather spell.  Neighbours of mine throughout Cavan and Monaghan are having bad experiences.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#K02100"><p>I feel somewhat locked out of the conversation about nominating presidential candidates, considering the Irish people's disappointing decision to keep it to those who have reached the age of 35 years.  Senator Ruane would make a wonderful president.</p> <p>I have been meaning to raise the issue of street art for some time.  It adds to the vibrancy of our cities and towns.  My sense is the public art created for the ESB boxes around the city has been popular.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Fintan Warfield :</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I only wish that the artists themselves were rewarded and paid properly for that work.  Recently an order was given by Dublin City Council that a number of very high profile murals be taken down or greyed out, in spite of consent being given by the owners of the property for the artist to paint the gable end.  Places such as Waterford have festivals that champion, encourage and elevate street art and facilitates the work of artists.  This work does not appear out of thin air.  It is the result of many artists toiling together behind the scenes. </p><p>I welcome the formation of a new collective of street artists called Subset, who are asking for more clear rules and regulations in Dublin City Council.  Subset referred to a lack of infrastructure and designated areas for street art, which make the endeavour essentially next to impossible.  I think it is time that we have ministerial guidelines for local authorities regarding street art, murals and busking.  I accept that perhaps a Commencement matter with the Minister might be more appropriate, but I would appreciate a response from the Leader.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#L00200"><p>Having listened to people talk about the water crisis, sometimes I think it is like crocodile tears.  Climate change is a reality and one must take a holistic approach.  Last night the Heritage Bill was voted through the D&aacute;il, which means grubbing and upland burning can take place now.  There is no point in saying that it is terrible to have a water crisis unless one actually addresses climate change in a holistic way.  Unfortunately not everyone is prepared to go down that road.</p> <p>On the Judicial Appointments Commission Bill, I must say that something stank last night.  The Minister who was in the Chamber said he had not read the GRECO report.  Then he was able to turn around to Senators and say there will be no earthquake when one reads it.  After sustained pressure he said that he would bring the report to the Cabinet.  Cabinet papers were circulated several days ago.  Is he bringing it as a matter of urgency?  He had not obviously planned to bring it to the Cabinet at present because at the very least what would be expected of any Minister from any party is that he or she would have read the papers he or she circulates to Cabinet before they are circulated.  </p> <p>GRECO is the Council of Europe's Group of States against Corruption and has issued a report, but we have not seen it.  I believe we were being misled in the Chamber last night.  It is a case of getting this through at all costs.  My party has always acknowledged that there are some good elements in the proposals and we need to debate and discuss them, but we cannot do that in the dark.  At the very least, the full facts should be put in front of us.  I will take the Minister at his word, that he will bring this report to Cabinet tomorrow; that he will seek publication and then it will be circulated.  There is an onus on the Seanad to say that we will not take Committee and Remaining Stages until we have had an opportunity to consider the report, the Government's viewpoints and to ensure that the amendments to the Bill take account of the GRECO report.  I think there is an onus on us to do that.  We have a responsibility to do that.  The courts are one of the pillars of our democracy.  We have seen the Northern Ireland Assembly being taken down as a consequence of "cash for ash".  This is more important than cash for ash.  This is one of the foundations of this State that has served us so well.  We as legislators have a responsibility to ensure any changes in our court services are the best they can be.  I will be supporting the amendment to the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#L00300"><p>Recently I had cause to drive to the west and to the very south point of the country in the same week.  By the time my journey was over, I was really depressed by the decline in the villages and rural areas.  I do not have to go to such far flung places as I can see it in my own county where the villages are passed by and closed down.  The shop fronts remain but the shops are closed.  This has not happened by chance.  In the past 20 years several Governments have orchestrated an oppressive national planning framework and spatial strategies and foisted them on people.  This was supposed to save rural areas but it is killing rural areas, which have been decimated.  In the past ten years some 17% of the houses built in the country have been one-off houses.  Large scale development is non-existent.</p> <p>I call on the Minister to liaise with county managers and ask them to interpret the county development plans to assist and help those applying for permission for a one-off house.  Many county managers stand behind their county development plans to deter planning permission.  This should not be the case nowadays where people cannot start a home.  If one is living in Dublin, Galway or Cork or a metropolitan area one could hope to buy a house but if one is living in Mullingar, Athlone, Ballina or Letterkenny where it is not viable for developers to build a house, houses are not being built.  The only tool that people have is when the county manager loosens up the planning regulations to help people and allow one-off planning permission.  Local authorities should be trying to assist people who apply for planning permission and give them a chance to move on.  This would allow them to start a family and give them hope.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#L00400"><p>Senator Humphreys is correct that the Judiciary and the Courts Service is a pillar of our democracy.  However, it is an elitist area of our democracy and I concur and thank Senator &Oacute; Domhnaill for putting it succinctly this morning.  The noise that is being caused about GRECO as an important report does not take away from the fact that the Bill is for the reform of the elitist Judiciary and it will make the courts and the law available to the ordinary Joe and Josephine Soap in this country.  That is why I will support it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#L00500"><p>Time was when you lot were shooting them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#L00600"><p>I want to raise the disappointment with HIQA.  HIQA has written 15 reports on the different centres for people with disabilities throughout the country.  Unfortunately Cherry Orchard in my area of Dublin South-Central in Ballyfermot has been taken off the register of approved centres for people with disabilities.  It is two separate houses in the Cherry Orchard campus and it has been taken off the register for major non-compliance with standards.  What was very concerning was the procedure in regard to what we term "do not resuscitate", DNR.  This was not discussed with the patients or their families and yet DNR was in their notes and a few of the patients were not resuscitated to the surprise of the family because they had not realised that this decision was made.  The other issue was in regard to the finances of the patients and whether there was proper oversight and record keeping.  They set up a new records system but when HIQA went to look at it, the actual record book was completely blank.  The third area was healthcare infection procedures.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator M&aacute;ire Devine:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2468"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2468&amp;amp;pid=MaireDevine&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The Minister could respond, in particular, to the deregistration of this centre for people with disabilities, which is one of the most vulnerable.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#M00200"><p>We are all aware of how closed-circuit television, CCTV, systems can assist to identify criminals and to deter criminals in the first instance from committing assaults and other crimes in towns and villages.  Over the past three or four years &euro;3 million has been allocated to the installation of CCTV in our towns and villages, but unfortunately only four applications have been approved to date.  The low number is worrying and clearly signifies we have a problem that needs to be looked at.  People are sick and tired of assaults and antisocial behaviour, including littering.  The benefit of CCTV systems particularly in urban areas is immeasurable.  It can assist garda&iacute;, who are short in numbers, in their role.  A light should be flashing over the low uptake level.  Clearly communities want this but unfortunately the application process is too cumbersome and applicants are walking away from it.</p> <p>There is another issue with GDPR.  The County and City Management Association, CCMA, has instructed all councils not to process applications because apparently there is an issue with who holds the data and who the data controller is.  For example, if a camera is mounted in a Garda station an issue arises as to who the controller is in that case.  There has been at an impasse for some time and in the meantime assaults, littering and burglaries are all taking place throughout the country.  The Minister needs to get a hold of the issue.  I ask the Leader to invite the Minister to the House so that we can discuss the scheme in general.  He might be in a position to inform us that he has the GDPR issue resolved to the benefit of everyone.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#M00300"><p>An Seanad&oacute;ir Wilson is the last man standing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#M00400"><p><i>El presidente</i>.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#M00500"><p>Notwithstanding what my good friend and colleague, Senator &Oacute; Domhnaill, has suggested this afternoon, I am quite happy and honoured to be a Member of this House and have no intention of moving out of it for some time to come.  Hopefully my electorate will agree with me on that.</p> <p>I support Senator Bacik's proposed amendment to the Order of Business on the Judicial Appointments Commission Bill which is before the House.  I sat through more than four and a half hours of debate up to 11 o'clock last night where we discussed amendment No. 3, which in essence was the first amendment because amendments Nos. 1 and 2 were ruled out of order.  During that time as the debate progressed, it became increasingly evident that there was something amiss with this legislation.  I alert colleagues who may have concerns but who have given a commitment to support this legislation that there is an international report in the Department of Justice and Equality-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#M00600"><p>Or the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#M00700"><p>----- which the Minister says - I have no reason to doubt him - he did not read.  He only agreed to bring it to Cabinet tomorrow when he was pushed by colleagues on all sides as to when he would do this.  However, he was able to clearly state that nothing in the report would have any negative impact on the legislation before us.  If that is the case, I ask the Leader at this the 11th hour before the legislation comes back before us to contact the Minister's office and suggest to him that it is the opinion of the majority of this House that the Committee Stage of the Bill should not progress until we have clarification on this report.  I repeat that there is an international report on the proposals in this legislation in the Department of Justice and Equality.  We know how that Department deals with reports, emails etc.  I will say no more on that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#M00800"><p>I welcome Senator Wilson's clarification of his intention.  I hope he remains in this House.  To have one Member of the Opposition running against another for the position of President would be unbelievable.  The Senator would make a wonderful President.  I had the honour of studying with him and I know he is a man of high values and morals.  I hope he will one day run for the &Aacute;ras.</p> <p>I thank the 20 Members of the House who contributed on the Order of Business.  I am not sure if it is the hot weather or the impending summer recess, certainly the octane level has reached a new high.</p> <p>I join Senator Ardagh in expressing my disappointment, as I did last week, on the energy price increase.  Of course, we have an independent regulator.  As the Senator will realise, the Government extended the fuel allowance, which can be paid in two lump sums.  It is worth recognising that the price hike is due in part to wholesale energy costs.  Car users will have noticed that the cost of petrol and diesel has also increased.  People who have a legitimate issue paying for fuel should in the first instance talk to the Department about the supplementary welfare allowance scheme which allows them to avail of money for heating.  It is a supplement that can be paid to a person who lives alone.  We should make people aware of it because the points Senator Ardagh raised are valid and should not be dismissed.  Equally we should ask people to engage with the community welfare service.</p> <p>The Senator made a point about the transition from State payment to work, on which we have done a lot of work.  People with an issue have an avenue available to them.  We need to inform and educate people on it.  The transition from being out of work to being back at work can be difficult for people and I concur with the Senator on that.</p> <p>Senators Craughwell, Bacik, Norris, &Oacute; Domhnaill, Humphreys, Devine and Wilson made reference to the debate on the judicial appointments Bill.  The Government's position has not changed.  I have proposed the Order of Business and I do not intend to accept Senator Bacik's amendment.  I understand where she is coming from.  I know Senator Craughwell has left.  The use of language is also important.  We are Members of the Upper House and I will not use derogatory words, like Senator Craughwell.  We are all here to debate an issue.  We can debate its rights and wrongs, its merits and demerits.  The Minister for Justice and Equality has brought a Bill to the House.  He has made amendments to the Bill and if the Bill needs further amending, I am sure he is open to engaging with Members.  Regarding the tenor of what is being said, Senator &Oacute; Domhnaill put it very well.  The Bill is about increasing judicial independence through reforming and transforming how judges are appointed.  It is about transparency.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#M00900"><p>It is just about the person.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#M01000"><p>It is not.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#M01100"><p>It is.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#N00100"><p>It is not.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#N00200"><p>Of course it is.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#N00300"><p>It behoves the father of the House to debate the matter in a manner that befits the Bill, based on the information about the Bill not on a personality.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#N00400"><p>It is limited information because the Government is considerably limited.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#N00500"><p>It should not be on the personality issue.  The Bill has been amended as it has gone along.  If there are other changes to be made, then let us make them but let us not do so in a manner that is about a particular Minister or person.  Let us have the debate about the issues relating to and aspects of the Bill.  We will have that debate, subject to the result of the vote on the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#N00600"><p>A vote will resolve the issue one way or another.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#N00700"><p>That will resolve it.  I am not accepting the amendment.</p> <p>Senator Conway-Walsh raised the issue of the Versatis and Anne-Marie's story, which she told, is disturbing.  The Minister for Health and the HSE have been before the Joint Committee on Health.  Clarity is needed.  It might be best for Senator Conway-Walsh to table a Commencement matter.  The issue she raises is important.</p> <p>Senators Conway, Lombard, O'Reilly and Humphreys raised the issue of water.  I cannot summon Irish Water to the House.  Senator Conway made a very good point, however, in that Irish Water did run a clinic in the previous Oireachtas.  Perhaps it should consider resuming that clinic because it gave Members an opportunity on behalf of their constituents to raise matters around water supply.  As Senator Lombard said, we are having an exceptionally dry spell there are issues regarding water.  We receive updates from Irish Water by email.  It has a Members' help desk which responds quite quickly to queries.  As Senator Reilly said, farmers face challenges in terms of growth and fodder for cattle.  I hope that the water pipe repair work happening in Fanore and Ballyvaughan in County Clare will be completed.  I agree with Senator Humphreys that we need - collectively and collaboratively - to tackle and face up to climate change.  We seeing in our country now four distinct weather periods or seasons that we perhaps did not have before even though we had four seasons.  It is not going to go away and we need to address that matter collectively.</p> <p>I concur with Senator Swanwick about the thuggery taking place in some parts of the country involving damage to property and equipment of the Civil Defence and lifeguards.  These groups make a great contribution to our safety.  No words of mine will describe the thugs that treat people so badly.  I do not have an update on the Life Saving Equipment Bill 2017.  I will not be a barrier to the Senator having it brought back to the House and I hope the Department will engage with him on that.  I have worked with him on other Bills and the one that is coming before the House this week.  He will not find me wanting in respect of this matter.</p> <p>Unfortunately, I was not able to meet Senator Gavan's delegation yesterday.  He is right about the hospitality sector that it is important that people are treated properly in respect of wage and working conditions.  I am an advocate of collective negotiation and bargaining.  I disagree with them, however, on the 9%.  That was a very good decision on the part of the previous Government.  No only does it benefit the hotel industry, it also benefits the service industry.  Are we saying to the hairdressers of Ireland that we will put their prices up and force them to question whether they take people on or let them go and increase the prices to customers?  It affects more than the hotel industry.  I understand the Senator's point but there is a bigger picture and this benefits many different sectors of our economy.  The Irish Hotels Federation should and must engage with workers.  I have never deviated from that view.</p> <p>Senator Mulherin raised the issue of premature scrappage of cars her point about the different ways people use cars is important.  The Council Directive 2000/53/EC on end-of-life vehicles govern this area.  Senator Mulherin's points on this are very pertinent and valid and I would be happy to invite the Minister to the House.</p> <p>Senator Norris referred to the Taoiseach's comments on the media.  I was not present.  The Taoiseach's spokesperson said that his comments were taken out of context and quoted selectively.  We do need to have an independent media.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#N00800"><p>Yes, telling the truth.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#N00900"><p>We need to have a media that will hold people to account.  Senator Norris is correct that with the number of members of the media tweeting and commenting, one would swear they were immune from criticism themselves when that is not the case.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#N01000"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#N01100"><p>We need to have a fair and balanced media.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#N01200"><p>Absolutely.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#N01300"><p>To be fair, we are well served by the majority of our journalists who are people of integrity and of the highest calibre but they are not immune from being to held to account or criticism themselves.  I smiled when I listened to 'Morning Ireland' earlier.  I also smiled when I read about the matter on Twitter.  However, I was not at the Taoiseach's event.  We live in a society where we are all open to being held to account.  That is the way it should be and we do need to have an independent strong media that holds us all to account.  I am all for that.</p> <p>Senator Byrne referred to Shannon Airport.  I commend those in Shannon Airport working with the ESB on the reduction in carbon emissions and reducing electricity usage by one third.  I agree with the Senator that we are benefiting from small craft breweries emerging.  Deputy Alan Kelly has a Bill before the D&aacute;il which will come into the Seanad before the recess.  It is unacceptable that the bigger brewery can have a monopoly.  We need to support our small craft beer industry.</p> <p>Senator Murnane O'Connor raised the very important issue of the Carillion schools and Sammon.  The contract was awarded to the company and it has the obligation and duty to look after the subcontractors but I agree with her that it is unacceptable that many subcontractors, small people employing one or two or even working on their own are being treated the way they have been treated.  I fully concur with her on that.  I have met several subcontractors who have been engaged in work at the schools to which the Senator referred.  One contractor living in Cork has had to let people go.  That is a disastrous consequence of a decision which we all thought was a good one and we have seen what happened.  The examiner is negotiating or engaging with the creditors.  That is of no real benefit or solace to the subcontractor but the Senator is right to raise the point.</p> <p>Senators Craughwell, Warfield, Wilson and Senator Norris, who did so half jocosely, half sincerely raised the matter of the Presidency.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#N01400"><p>I was completely sincere.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#N01500"><p>I know.  I said that.  The nomination process for the presidency is laid out in the Constitution.  Senator Warfield will see it is available for any Member over a certain age to get a nomination by-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#N01600"><p>The Government should listen to the Constitutional Convention.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#N01700"><p>Let us await the decision of An tUachtar&aacute;n on whether he is going to run again or not.  Then we might have a debate on who should run against him or not or who will who might not run.  There are always difficulties in the nomination process, whether internal to a party or an independent grouping.  Democracy involves elections, whether for the presidency, the local authority, the European Council, the D&aacute;il or Seanad.  I would certainly welcome an election contest for the presidency.  We should be afraid of that.  Whether it is right or not is a different matter.  Some members of the media will say Michael D. Higgins should be let run on his own.  Others will say he should be opposed and do we want the cost of an election.  I do not think we can put a cost on democracy.  A price should not be put on democracy.</p> <p>I join Senator Warfield in congratulating those involved in street art, not just in Dublin but also in Cork.  The Reimagine Cork group did a wonderful job transforming the streetscape and public realm in Cork.  I fully welcome the start collective that has been put in place.  It does add vibrancy to the city and I would be happy to work with the Senator to ensure that we recognise the different groups.  Sometimes the decisions of local authorities on the erection of hoardings or murals baffles those of us who are not planners or architects or engineers or urban planners.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Sometimes we should just allow people to be creative.  In White Street in Cork, we have a series of walls where those who engage in graffiti go in and do their work.  It is very creative and artistic.  It might not be to everyone's taste but it is a space where young people in particular can go.  Reimagine Cork has transformed the streetscape and I congratulate the volunteers.</p><p>Turning to Senator Humphreys, the Committee on Procedure and Privileges, CPP, of the Seanad agreed yesterday to the request from the D&aacute;il regarding a climate change committee.  It is important and we will endeavour to take it seriously.  Senator Mulherin has been very strong within our party in terms of promoting measures against climate change.  She been a great advocate in that regard.  I would love to travel around the country with Senator Davitt.  I would love to get into the car with him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#O00200"><p>It would be a great experience for both of us.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#O00300"><p>It would be great.  I could point out to him-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#O00400"><p>A one-way ticket.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1382" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#O00500"><p>Senator Horkan has some self-interest.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#O00600"><p>The Leader had better move on swiftly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#O00700"><p>I will point out two things.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#O00800"><p>Senator Horkan is canvassing already.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#O00900"><p>The first is the failed national spatial strategy of Fianna F&aacute;il, with its hubs, spokes and gateway towns.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#O01000"><p>It was the national development plan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#O01100"><p>The second is the &euro;116 billion from Project Ireland 2040-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#O01200"><p>I did not start talking about the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government, Deputy Eoghan Murphy.  Fair is fair.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#O01300"><p>-----that we will be investing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#O01400"><p>That is over the last 20 years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#O01500"><p>I would also be happy to show the Senator-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#O01600"><p>I said over the last 20 years.  That is a cheap shot.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#O01700"><p>-----proposals-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#O01800"><p>We could show Senator Buttimer all the homeless families.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#O01900"><p>-----that the Government has, such as the living over the shop scheme, enhancing the public realm-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#O02000"><p>How many people have availed of those?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#O02100"><p>I would be happy to do that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#O02200"><p>The temperature is hot enough, I ask the Leader not to raise it any further.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#O02300"><p>I am trying to assist.  Senator Davitt is right that local authorities and local representatives must work to ensure that we protect our towns and villages because they are the lifeblood of rural Ireland.  To be fair to the Minister for Rural and Community Development, Deputy Ring, he has a programme of work and he is engaging with it.  There needs to be a collaborative approach.</p> <p>On Senator Devine's question, I only heard a snippet regarding the report on Cherry Orchard that is emerging from the Health Information and Quality Authority, HIQA.  It is a concern.  The report needs to be implemented.  I refer also to the issues raised in respect of resuscitation, engagement and communication.  It is a source of worry.  Senator Devine works in the area and I am involved myself.  This is one that we need to get right.  It is not just about resources, it is also about a combined effort on resourcing, communications, staffing and engagement.  To be fair, we are very lucky that the vast majority of the facilities and homes that people live in are of an impeccable standard.  However, the points Senator Devine raised need to be worked on.  I would be happy for the Minister to come to the House to discuss the report.</p> <p>Senator Gallagher comes in with the hard question at the end nearly every day.  He raised the issue of CCTV today.  The Government committed &euro;1 million last year and this year to the project.  There have been four CCTV projects commenced, four are awaiting approval and 14 more are going to be approved.  The Senator's point on the issue of data protection is one that is exercising the local authorities because they will be the data controllers.  There must also be engagement with the local joint policing committees and the councils.  We should not be putting bureaucracy in the way of CCTV equipment being erected.  That is the point Senator Gallagher is making and I agree with him.</p> <p>The final point I will make is that while I understand where Senator Bacik is coming from, I will not be accepting her amendment to the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#O02400"><p>Senator Ivana Bacik has moved an amendment to the Order of Business: "That No. 4 not be taken today."  Is the amendment being pressed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#O02500"><p>I am pressing the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.142" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment put.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.143" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>The Seanad divided by electronic means.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#P00200"><p>Under Standing Order 62(3)(<i>b</i>) I request that the division be taken again other than by electronic means.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.145/1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#P00300"><p>Amendment again put: "That No. 4 not be taken today."</p><p>The Seanad divided: T, 22; Nl, 27.</p><br/><br/><p>Tellers: T, Senators Ivana Bacik and David Norris; Nl, Senators Gabrielle McFadden and John O'Mahony.</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.145/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2018-07-04" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#P00300">
            <divisioncount ayes="22" noes="27" abstain="0" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" vote="aye">Catherine Ardagh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" vote="aye">Ivana Bacik</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" vote="aye">Victor Boyhan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" vote="aye">Lorraine Clifford Lee</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" vote="aye">Gerard Craughwell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" vote="aye">Mark Daly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" vote="aye">Aidan Davitt</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1428" vote="aye">Joan Freeman</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" vote="aye">Robbie Gallagher</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" vote="aye">Alice Mary Higgins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" vote="aye">Gerry Horkan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" vote="aye">Kevin Humphreys</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" vote="aye">Terry Leyden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" vote="aye">R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" vote="aye">Jennifer Murnane O'Connor</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" vote="aye">Gerald Nash</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" vote="aye">David Norris</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" vote="aye">Marie Louise O'Donnell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1385" vote="aye">Grace O'Sullivan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" vote="aye">Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1373" vote="aye">Keith Swanick</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" vote="aye">Diarmuid Wilson</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" vote="no">Colm Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1380" vote="no">Paddy Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1423" vote="no">Ray Butler</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" vote="no">Jerry Buttimer</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" vote="no">Maria Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" vote="no">Paul Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" vote="no">Rose Conway Walsh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" vote="no">Martin Conway</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" vote="no">Maire Devine</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1419" vote="no">John Dolan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" vote="no">Frank Feighan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" vote="no">Paul Gavan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1415" vote="no">Maura Hopkins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1438" vote="no">Anthony Lawlor</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" vote="no">Tim Lombard</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" vote="no">P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" vote="no">Gabrielle McFadden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" vote="no">Michelle Mulherin</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" vote="no">Catherine Noone</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1374" vote="no">Kieran O'Donnell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" vote="no">John O'Mahony</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" vote="no">Joe O'Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1382" vote="no">Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" vote="no">Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" vote="no">James Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1399" vote="no">Neale Richmond</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" vote="no">Fintan Warfield</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="abstain">
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.145/3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#P00300"><p>Amendment declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.146" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put: "That the Order of Business be agreed to."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.147" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>The Seanad divided by electronic means.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#Q00300"><p>Under Standing Order 62(3)(<i>b</i>) I request that the division be taken again other than by electronic means.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.149/1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#Q00400"><p>Question again put: "That the Order of Business be agreed to."</p><p>The Seanad divided: T, 28; Nl, 11.</p><br/><br/><p>Tellers: T, Senators Gabrielle McFadden and John O'Mahony; Nl, Senators Ivana Bacik and David Norris.</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.149/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2018-07-04" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#Q00400">
            <divisioncount ayes="28" noes="11" abstain="0" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" vote="aye">Colm Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1380" vote="aye">Paddy Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1423" vote="aye">Ray Butler</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" vote="aye">Jerry Buttimer</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" vote="aye">Maria Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" vote="aye">Paul Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" vote="aye">Rose Conway Walsh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" vote="aye">Martin Conway</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" vote="aye">Maire Devine</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1419" vote="aye">John Dolan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" vote="aye">Frank Feighan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" vote="aye">Paul Gavan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" vote="aye">Alice Mary Higgins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1415" vote="aye">Maura Hopkins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1438" vote="aye">Anthony Lawlor</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" vote="aye">Tim Lombard</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" vote="aye">P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" vote="aye">Gabrielle McFadden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" vote="aye">Michelle Mulherin</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" vote="aye">Catherine Noone</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1374" vote="aye">Kieran O'Donnell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" vote="aye">John O'Mahony</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" vote="aye">Joe O'Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" vote="aye">Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" vote="aye">James Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1399" vote="aye">Neale Richmond</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1404" vote="aye">Lynn Ruane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" vote="aye">Fintan Warfield</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" vote="no">Ivana Bacik</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" vote="no">Victor Boyhan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" vote="no">Gerard Craughwell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" vote="no">Robbie Gallagher</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" vote="no">Gerry Horkan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" vote="no">Kevin Humphreys</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" vote="no">Terry Leyden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" vote="no">Gerald Nash</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" vote="no">David Norris</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" vote="no">Marie Louise O'Donnell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" vote="no">Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="abstain">
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.149/3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#Q00400"><p>Question declared carried.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.150" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#S00100">Education (Admission to Schools) Bill 2016: Report and Final Stages</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#S00200"><p>I would like to remind Senators that a Senator may speak only once at Report Stage, except the proposer of an amendment, who may reply to the discussion on the amendment.</p> <p>Amendment No. 1 arises out of proceedings in Committee Stage.  Amendments Nos. 1 to 10, inclusive, are related.  Amendment No. 2 is consequential on amendment No. 1.  Amendment No. 6 is a logical alternative to amendment No. 5.  Amendments Nos. 7 to 10, inclusive, are consequential on amendment No. 5.  Amendments Nos. 1 to 10, inclusive, will be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.152" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 1:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#S00300"><p>My amendments in this grouping all relate to a new provision that I am inserting in section 29F.  On Committee Stage, Senator Ruane proposed an amendment providing that an applicant could seek a review of a decision of an appeals committee not to hear or determine appeal under section 29.  At the time, I advised the Senator that I accepted the intention of her amendment but wished to have the opportunity to draft the new subsection in conjunction with the Office of the Parliamentary Counsel.  As can be seen by the number of new subsections required to provide for this review, it was important to undertake that drafting work to ensure the new provisions will work effectively.</p> <p>Amendment No. 1 inserts a new subsection (k) to provide for procedures to set out the manner in which and period during which such a review shall be undertaken.  The Bill provides for consultation with the educational partners on new procedures for section 29 appeals, and this amendment will ensure that these procedures and the relevant consultation will also cover the manner in which this review can be undertaken and the timelines for requesting and conducting a new review.  Amendment No. 2 is a consequential numbering amendment as a result of the new subsection (k).</p> <p>Amendment No. 5 provides for the review itself.  It provides that where an applicant receives a copy of a decision from an appeals committee that it is not going to hear or determine an appeal, that applicant can request for the Minister to review that decision.  Where the Minister receives a request for a review, he or she shall appoint a member of an appeals panel to review the decision.  This person shall not have been a member of the appeals committee that made the decision to refuse to hear or determine the appeal.  The person appointed shall review the decision, and following the review shall make a recommendation to the Minister that the decision of the appeals committee is either upheld or set aside.  Where the Minister receives a recommendation that the decision should be set aside, the Minister shall direct the appeals committee to proceed to hear or determine the appeal.</p> <p>I am satisfied that the amendments meet the intention of the Senator in proposing the amendment on Committee Stage.  I agree with the Senator that it is important to allow a parent or guardian to seek a review where an appeals committee has decided not to hear or determine an appeal.  It is an important new provision within section 29, and I am pleased to have been in a position to facilitate the Senator in bringing it forward.  Amendments Nos. 7 to 10, inclusive, are numbering amendments consequential to amendment No. 5.</p> <p>The other amendments in this grouping are amendments Nos. 3, 4 and 6.  I have considered amendment No. 3 and understand the intention to copper-fasten the action of the school must be taken after internal review where an error or failure on the part of the school has had a material effect on the student's application for admission.  Amendment No. 3 will ensure that where a school finds an error or failure in how it applied its admission policy during an internal review by the board and that error or failure had a material effect on a student's application, the school must rectify the matter appropriately.  Where the error or failure related to admission, the school must admit the student, and where it related to a student's ranking on a waiting list, the school must adjust the student's ranking.  On the previous occasion, the Senator rightly pointed out that there was an ambiguity in the way the original provision was phrased.  I am happy to accept her amendment, which will bring greater clarity to the internal review on the admissions conducted by the schools' board of management.</p> <p>Amendment No. 4 provides that at the request of an applicant, a section 29 appeals committee may facilitate "consultation between the applicant and an appropriate member of staff in a neighbouring or otherwise appropriate school, for the purposes of preparing an appeal under this section".  The position with this amendment is somewhat different.  I do not consider it appropriate and, therefore, it would be appropriate to accept it.  Section 29D(2) provides that, "oral hearings shall be conducted with the minimum of formality consistent with giving all parties a fair hearing".<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Richard Bruton:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=119"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=119&amp;amp;pid=RichardBruton&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The Bill provides for procedures on section 29 appeals to be developed after consultation with the education partners, including bodies representative of parents.</p><p>Under the current procedures for hearings and determining section 29 appeals, the parent or guardian can bring up to two additional persons to attend the hearing with him or her.  In addition, with the prior approval of the appeals committee, one of these two additional persons can make the appeal at the hearing on behalf of a parent or student.  It is my intention that the new procedures for hearing and determining section 29 appeals will also provide for a parent or guardian to bring an additional person of his or her choosing to an appeal hearing if he or she desires.</p><p>While I appreciate the good intention behind this proposal, the approach set out is not technically feasible.  It is based on an appeals committee that can be appointed only after an appeal has been made, facilitating this arrangement in advance of any appeal being made.  It also potentially opens up the charge of actual or perceived bias should a committee consider or become involved in the issues under appeal before the appeal is even made.  The Bill already provides for Tusla's education and welfare services to appoint an independent person to take an appeal on behalf of the student.  It also provides for the education welfare services or the National Council for Special Education to support a parent's appeal by the making of submissions to the appeals committee.  I consider this to be the more appropriate approach to providing parents with impartial and independent support in regard to section 29 appeals.</p><p>The amendment is asking the appeals committee, which must hear independently the case being put forward, to become involved in facilitating the presentation of an appeal.  That would not be regarded as a legally sound way to proceed.  By contrast, there is already provision for the expertise of either Tusla or the National Council for Special Education to support a parent, or for the parent to pick his or her own people to attend the hearing and support the presentation of the case.</p><p>As for amendment No. 6, I am providing an alternative version.  While I am not accepting amendment No. 6, I have provided an amendment that meets the intention of Senator Ruane.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1404" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#T00200"><p>I thank the Minister and his officials for giving me time between the last occasion on which we considered this and now to come to some agreements.  I welcome the Minister's acceptance of amendment No. 3.  It gets rid of the lack of clarity over where a child can be placed on a waiting list.  I accept all the related amendments.  I am referring to amendments Nos. 1, 2, 5 and the others in the group.</p> <p>I listened to what the Minister said about amendment No. 4.  Although I had support for it, I believe what the Minister said makes sense.  My wording is such that I bring in the appeals committee before an actual appeal has been submitted.  I am willing to accept the Minister is correct in this regard.  I will not push the amendment.</p> <p>I do not have much to add, other than that the amendments are welcome.  I trust that when it comes to the time for me to remove my amendments, the Minister will have alternative wording.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.156" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.157" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 2:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.158" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1404" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#T00600"><p>I move amendment No. 3:</p><blockquote>In page 9, lines 8 to 11, to delete all words from and including &quot;error&quot; in line 8 down to and including line 11 and substitute the following:&quot;error&mdash;<br /><br />(a) where the failure or error related to the admission of a student to a school or special class, by admitting the student to the school or special class concerned, or<br /><br />(b) where the failure or error related to a student&rsquo;s ranking on the waiting list, by adjusting the ranking of the student on the waiting list.&quot;.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.160" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.161" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment No. 4 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.162" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 5:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.163" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.164" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment No. 6 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.165" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 7:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.166" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.167" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 8:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.168" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.169" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 9:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.170" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.171" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 10:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.172" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.173" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#T02000"><p>Amendments Nos. 11 to 13, inclusive, are related.  Amendment No. 12 is a direct------</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.174" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1404" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#T02100"><p>On a point of order, do the last amendments not need to be seconded on Report Stage to be valid?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#T02200"><p>No.  We are all right.</p> <p>Amendment No. 12 is a direct logical alternative to amendment No. 11.  Amendment No. 13 is consequential on amendment No. 11.  Amendments Nos. 11 to 13, inclusive, may be discussed together, by agreement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.176" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 11:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.177" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#T02400"><p>Amendment No. 11 provides for a review of the new section 37A of the Education Act 1998, which provides the Minister with the power to direct a school to open a special class following a report of the National Council for Special Education.  The amendment requires the Minister to commence the review not later than three years after the new section 37A comes into operation, and that the Minister shall make a report of the findings made on the review to each House of the Oireachtas within 12 months of the expiration of that period.</p> <p>Amendment No. 13 is a consequential numbering amendment arising from the insertion of the provision in amendment No. 11.</p> <p>I thank Senator Kelleher for proposing an amendment on Committee Stage to provide for a review of the operation of the new section 37A.  I was pleased to accept approximately 12 or so of the Senator's amendments on Committee Stage.  While I agreed to the Senator's proposal regarding this review, I advised that I wished to have this particular amendment drafted in conjunction with the Office of the Parliamentary Counsel.</p> <p>Amendment No. 11, which has now been redrafted by the Office of the Parliamentary Counsel in line with the approach set out by Senator Kelleher, inserts a new subsection in section 37A.  Section 37A provides the Minister with the power to direct a school to open a special class following a report by the National Council for Special Education.  The new amendment I am introducing today provides for a review of the operation of the new section.  It requires the Minister to commence that review not later than three years after section 37A comes into operation, as I said.  This effectively means the report must be completed within four years of the section coming into operation given the 12-month period.  I agree with Senator Kelleher that it will be important to review how this important new section of the Bill will operate.</p> <p>The Office of the Parliamentary Counsel has drafted the provision in line with similar review provisions in recent legislation.  This includes, for example, the Data Protection Act 2018, the Gender Recognition Act 2015 and the Protected Disclosures Act 2014.  Amendment No. 13 is a consequential numbering amendment arising from the insertion of the new subsection by amendment No. 11.</p> <p>If this amendment is accepted, we will have a significant new provision such that where the National Council for Special Education identifies a need that is not being met, it can, having reference to a series of procedural requirements, require a school to open a special unit to provide for children with special needs.  In the Lower House, there was considerable concern that although the National Council for Special Education has the power to designate a school to take a child, there can be circumstances in which schools may be resistant to opening special units.  It was felt the power should be available as a reserved power.</p> <p>I pointed out here that, to be fair to schools, the evidence is that there is openness to the creation of these special units.  There were 548 in 2011 and there are now 1,304.  That is a very substantial expansion.  The power in question is an important reserved power that the Minister should have at his disposal to ensure no barrier is raised unnecessarily against a child in a way that would prevent him or her from getting the most appropriate education.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1404" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#U00100"><p>Senator Colette Kelleher could not be here today but she asked me to note that she welcomes the Minister's wording.  Had she been here, she would have withdrawn her amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.179" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.180" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment No. 12 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.181" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#U00400"><p>Amendment No. 13 has already been discussed with amendment No. 11.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.182" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 13:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.183" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.184" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#U00700"><p>Amendments Nos. 14, 20 and 22 to 25, inclusive, are related and may be discussed together by agreement.  Amendment No. 24 is a direct logical alternative to amendment No. 23.  Amendment No. 25 is consequential on amendment No. 23.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.185" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1385" speakername="Grace O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#U00800"><p>I move amendment No. 14:</p><blockquote>In page 23, line 11, after &ldquo;school&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;not aided by the Department of Education and Skills&rdquo;.</blockquote> <p>We addressed this issue in my amendments on Committee Stage.  The Minister indicated that his aim with the Bill was to make incremental progress in secularising Irish education and removing barriers for access to education.  Of course I welcome such efforts and I will be supporting this legislation in the final vote.  However, I appeal to the Minister to again consider why we are taking half measures in this regard.  Is it even fair to take an approach of secularisation when it comes to national schools with a Catholic ethos, yet not with other faith groups?  Do State money and State institutions, be they educational or otherwise, have any role when it comes to promotion of religious faith?</p><p>The Green Party believes that State education should be precisely that: State-funded and run with an exclusive focus on the promotion of education and social development, and not the promotion of religious faith.  Such promotion has its place in churches, community and faith groups as well as in homes and within families, but not within State institutions such as schools.</p><p>We disestablished our church in 1869, yet here we are 150 years later talking about preferential treatment in admissions on the basis of religious faith, a promotion of faith if ever there was one.  I am fully in support of the principle of religious freedom, but as importance is the right to freedom from religion.  That is why I have moved this amendment.</p><p>Amendment No. 20 relates to arrangements for children not taking part in religious classes.  I did not get to speak to this point on Committee Stage.  I intend to press this amendment because it is one that I have personal experience of as a mother of children who did not partake in religious instruction in school.  They sat down the back of the class and were left out and left aside.  It was not a particularly satisfactory arrangement.  I imagine teachers themselves are seldom happy with such arrangements.  Guidance from the Department in this regard would be useful.  The amendment would require the Department to provide guidelines to schools on how they should put in place age-appropriate alternatives for those who do not wish to attend religious instruction during school hours.</p><p>As I have mentioned previously, I believe freedom from religion is an important part of religious freedom, but the current system is not adequate to ensure that students affected do not feel excluded or that their time is poorly used as they merely wait out the class.  The amendment would ensure freedom from discrimination and protection of a child's right to freedom of thought, conscience and religion in school.  As the Government acts to remove the baptism barrier in our national schools, it is only logical for the Department to set guidelines to ensure that all students are treated equally across schools when they opt out of religious classes.</p><p>Earlier this year, the Minister issued a circular to all education and training board schools requiring them to provide alternative subject choices for students who do not wish to partake in religion class in school.  However, this measure only applies to education and training board schools, the logic being that they are multi-denominational.</p><p>I anticipate that the Minister will argue that he does not normally issue guidelines to schools on issues such as this, but that is belied by the fact that the Department has done so for education and training board schools.  My amendment would thus make it compulsory to issue guidelines to deal with this question in all schools.  Apart from giving schools certainty in coping with a shift to a more diverse population and an increasingly non-religious population, it would also ensure the right of students to not partake in these classes.  It would ensure the children affected could spend the time productively and have their wishes respected.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.186" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#U00900"><p>I want to express my support on behalf of Sinn F&eacute;in for these amendments.  As the Minister knows, we welcome the Bill and the level of engagement.  However, I believe the Minister is missing an opportunity with regard to these amendments.</p> <p>It does not make sense for a modern republic to still have the vast majority of schools under a particular faith control.  The most logical step is to separate church and State.  As republicans, we have consistently called for this.  I believe the Minister is missing an opportunity.  This is an opportunity to be bold and embrace the republic that we need to build.  Notwithstanding the fact that this Bill represents progress, the Minister could have gone further.  Perhaps it speaks to the ideological differences between us.  As a party of the left, we fully embrace the separation of church and State.  As a party of the right, regrettably, Fine Gael, does not at this point.</p> <p>I have personal experience currently of the issue amendment No. 20 seeks to address.  Effectively, my children are parked at one side for the best part of half a year in holy communion and confirmation classes.  That is not good enough in a modern republic.  We did not have an opportunity to send our children to a non-Catholic school.  We wanted to ensure our children got an education through Irish.  We had no choice.  The Department can and must do better.  Again, I encourage the Minister to address amendment No. 20.  I accept that amendment No. 14 is probably politically impossible for him given the conservative nature of his party, but surely he should be able to embrace amendment No. 20.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.187" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#U01000"><p>I thank the Senators for this discussion.  Perhaps I come from a different perspective but I certainly favour diversity in education.  I believe that, as the Constitution sets out, parents are the primary educators.  I believe that the State should try to facilitate parents to the best of its ability.  That was the background to the approach.</p> <p>I had a consultation on this matter.  Alternative approaches were being canvassed on how this should be dealt with, such as only allowing religion to be used within the catchment.  Some parties put forward that idea while other ideas included having nearest-the-school rules and so on.  None of these met with consensus.</p> <p>I sought to see how we could facilitate parents to the best of our ability.  I think it is perfectly acceptable that a parent might want to a child brought up in the faith of the parent.  I do not find that to be an objectionable ambition in a republic.  We have many high-quality minority religion schools.  We have many children and their parents, who have a legitimate and recognised desire that their children should have the chance to be brought up in a school reflecting their ethos.  The difficulty is that if we removed religion altogether the concept of a minority religion school would effectively disappear.  We could not have a minority religion school if it was obliged to accept all-comers because effectivity minority religion schools represent one out of every 20 schools.  They would not be able to maintain the ethos.  By contrast, I am not permitting religion to be used in Catholic schools.  People in that situation have 18 of every 20 schools to choose from.  A parent who wants to have a child brought up in a school with a Catholic ethos can achieve that.  Similarly non-denominational schools do not apply religion and I am not in any way interfering with that.  As a result, 19 out of every 20 schools will not be using religion as a criterion.  The one exception to that will be in the case of minority schools.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Richard Bruton:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=119"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=119&amp;amp;pid=RichardBruton&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I am providing that we allow those schools which are a valuable part of our tradition to continue.  I am surprised the Senator is advocating that we should abandon that part of our tradition, given all our political history.</p><p>Senator Grace O'Sullivan has argued that we should have State education institutions but the truth is we do not.  Of our primary schools, 99.5% or more are not State institutions but are private institutions.  That is because of all sorts of historical reasons.  There are denominational schools and Educate Together is another private institution, along with An Foras P&aacute;tr&uacute;nachta.  The only State schools are the education and training board, ETB, schools, and there is a small number of community national schools.  It was 11 at the last count.  The philosophy of those schools is that every religion should be invited in and equally celebrated.  It is a great model and I would love to see many more State schools.  I would like to see the ETB model getting greater traction.  I hope we will see transfers of patronage to that model.</p><p>For all sorts of reasons we did not go down that road.  We have a different model and we must develop and reform the model as best we can.  It is what I am doing here.  It is a significant reform and I can see it in my constituency.  Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in would have the same experience.  Parents feel obliged to have their child baptised simply to get into school or they find they live in an area where a baptised child will get a priority in a local school over their child.  That is not acceptable.  My role is about satisfying parents to the best of my ability rather than imposing uniformity or one model of school.</p><p>Our education system is very much a consensus, with stakeholder engagement and consultation being a very big feature.  One may say this slows progress but Senators may have read the book by the late Fr. John O'Holohan - sadly, he was recently buried - that reflected on education in the past 50 years.  He made a very persuasive case that stakeholder engagement has been a strength of our system.  Although we have much friction and tensions, we have seen much very valuable reform.  We must continue and accelerate that reform.  I am really keen to see far greater diversity.  It is wholly inappropriate that 95% of our schools are denominational when at the last count nationally, slightly more than 50% of parents who get married did so in denominational ceremonies.  Ireland is changing very rapidly and we must facilitate that change.  I hope we can accelerate such change.</p><p>I did not address the provision in the amendments that Senator Grace O'Sullivan seeks to address.  It is the other feature of the equality legislation, which allows protection to review admission where it is essential to maintain ethos.  It is not area where I addressed the change.  It has never been used so it has not been an issue that has exercised public concern.  It is a very high bar to prove it.  I am addressing the real issues of concern.</p><p>Amendment No. 22 seeks to apply the provision I am making at primary level to post-primary level.  When I initiated this consultation it was very clear the problem we were seeking to address was that 95% of schools are denominational and the capacity to use religion as a barrier.  In post-primary education there is far greater diversity, with more than half of schools of non-denominational patronage.  I did not address this in the consultation and it is not anything like as pressing.  In practice, religious denomination is not used to de-bar to any great extent in this sector, or at least there is not the same complexity.  There is much more choice.  Nonetheless, Senator O'Sullivan's proposal would for the same reasons see many small, minority religion, post-primary schools wiped out.  One could not continue to have minority post-primary schools under the Senator's provision, as they provide that children of a minority ethos who want access to those schools get preference.  This may be called ideology but it is catering to a diverse Ireland and the plurality we experience in our community.  Ideology should not totally trounce valuable institutions we have inherited.</p><p>There is the matter of issuing directions and we have made a significant change in this Bill.  Before a child enrols in a school, the school would have to set out the policy it provides with respect to attending religious instruction.  This is an area where there has been a good deal of evolution and we must see more.  One cannot have a one size fits all approach to this and the precise nature of arrangements must be considered by each school, having regard to the particular circumstances.  It would not be appropriate to try to develop a one size fits all approach to this.  I have no doubt we are moving to a position where there must be much more catering for the needs.  I am making provision in the forthcoming parents and learners charter Bill that there must be consultation with parents in how children who do not share the denomination of the school are catered for.  I would prefer to see that develop through a parents and students charter, with a degree of flexibility as to how it would be delivered in the 4,000 schools that we have.  That is instead of having some attempt to say the rules will apply in a small Church of Ireland, Methodist, Catholic or Educate Together school and they must be complied with.  It does not fit with the way in which our school system has evolved and the diversity that exists.  I am not disposed to supporting that.</p><p>Amendment No. 23 arose from amendments tabled by Senators.  It provides that there will be a review of this section within five years of the section coming into operation.  This is an area where custom and practice will evolve and our thinking about such matters will also evolve.  I do not in any way pretend that this is the last word to be said on the matter.  Amendment No. 24 will fall if my amendment No. 23 is accepted.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.189" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1404" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018070400002#V00200"><p>I welcome amendment No. 23 and I thank the Minister for agreeing to review this section of the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-07-04a.190" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Additional debate to follow.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>