<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.2" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Leas-Chathaoirleach i gceannas ar 14:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.4" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.5" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400003#B00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Deirdre Clune that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, she proposes to raise the following matter:<blockquote><br />The need for the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport to allow funds to be redirected for necessary road maintenance programmes in the Cork city area, similar to the recent flexibility in funding he announced for rural areas.</blockquote>I have also received notice from Senator Marc MacSharry of the following matter:<blockquote>The need for the Minister for Education and Skills to outline the unfair and illogical changes to the school catchment area for Ardvarney national school which have determined the loss of a school bus and will cause an unnatural division in an historic local community and unnecessarily undermine the future viability of the school.</blockquote>I have also received notice from Senator Martin Conway of the following matter:<blockquote>The need for the Minister for Education and Skills to outline the process necessary for Mol an &Oacute;ige, Steiner national school, Ennistymon, County Clare, to be granted permanent recognition; the point the school is presently at and the timeframe he envisages the process will be completed; the number of schools that have been granted permanent recognition since September 2008; and the length of time it took to complete the process.</blockquote>I have also received notice from Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill of the following matter:<blockquote>The need for the Minister for Education and Skills to address the urgent need for children with Down's syndrome to be recognised in their entirety and in their own right by his Department.</blockquote>I have also received notice from Senator David Cullinane of the following matter:<blockquote>The need for the Minister for Social Protection to discuss the withdrawal of the community welfare office from Tramore, County Waterford, the impact it will have on the local community and how the community welfare services will now be provided.</blockquote>I regard the matters raised by Senators Clune, MacSharry, Conway and &Oacute; Domhnaill as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment and they will be taken at the conclusion of business.  Senator Cullinane may give notice on another day of the matter he wishes to raise.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.7" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400003#B00300">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.8" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400003#B00400"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, Taxi Regulation Bill 2012 - Report Stage, to be taken at the conclusion of the Order of Business and conclude not later than 8 p.m., if not previously concluded.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400004#C00100"><p>Does the Leader have plans to discuss changes to the health service, in particular, the hospital network?  Buswell's Hotel seems to have been booked by the Department of Health today to launch its policies and plans.  Why the Minister for Health sees fit to book hotels in order to launch his health and hospital strategies needs to be discussed.  He has asked Oireachtas Members to go across the road when there is perfectly adequate accommodation available in this place.  I understand a press conference will take place and officials were in and out of Buswell's Hotel today.  I do not know why this is happening.  Therefore, we need a full debate in this House, this Parliament, this place of sovereignty, where the people are represented to discuss what is happening in hospitals.  We are aware of all the promises made before the general election, particularly with regard to the small hospitals dotted all around the country.  We already have broken promises, most notably in Navan and also in Roscommon.  I am sure my colleague beside me will wish to contribute to any debate on the matter.  There is much happening and much is being dressed up today.  I want to know the cost of what is happening such as the cost of the use of the hotel.  I also want to know why the Department's own offices cannot be used for these events and why Oireachtas Members have to leave a perfectly good place which is available at no extra cost to the taxpayer and cross the road to a hotel to be told about changes to hospital services.  More fundamentally, we need a debate in this House tomorrow with the Minister for Health on the subject of hospital services.  I look forward to the Leader's response.</p><p>Another important issue was raised last week in the other House by Deputy Mattie McGrath - the plea made by the families of the bereaved at Omagh, led by Mr. Michael Gallagher who lost his 21 year old son, Aidan, in the bombing in 1998.  They want the truth to be disclosed about what happened.  In 2012 they provided a comprehensive report for the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Alan Shatter, which asked for a full public inquiry, but they have not yet received a real response from the Government.  The Taoiseach, when in opposition, promised to meet the families of the Omagh bereaved, but such a meeting has not taken place, nor has he given any commitment to arrange such a meeting.  There has been no response in a proper or meaningful way from the Minister, Deputy Alan Shatter.  Nobody seems to know what is happening and why it is taking so long for the Government to consider this comprehensive report provided by the families who should not be fobbed off any longer by the Government.  I ask it to meet them for a full and comprehensive response to be given, by the Minister in particular.  I call on the Taoiseach to meet them, as he promised to do.  It might be worthwhile having a short debate in this House on the matter.  This was a significant and hugely tragic event in the history of this country.  It was a desperate event and everyone remembers the details.  A debate in the House might result in some action being taken by the Government in order to find out the truth of what happened and give the families some closure.  When I met Mr. Gallagher last week, I was struck by his genuineness, sincerity, grief and desire for answers.  The Seanad could play a role in helping to move the matter forward.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400004#C00200"><p>I pay tribute to Donal Walsh, the young teenager who tragically died from cancer earlier this week.  I extend our sympathy to his parents, sister and family.  He was a young man who in a short lifetime achieved a great deal, not only in raising awareness of suicide and doing important work on suicide prevention but also in his immense fund-raising efforts for Crumlin children's hospital.  Much of his involvement was so commendable and his family must be very proud of him.  In my time in this House we have had numerous debates on the subject of suicide prevention, yet the short video on suicide prevention which he filmed spoke volumes.  It will have a much greater impact and has done so already than a great deal of other suicide prevention work.</p><p>I ask the Leader to arrange a debate on the inspection of centres for children and adults with disabilities.</p> <p>I am delighted HIQA has announced it will begin inspections of these centres later this year.  That is hugely important and is something for which many people have been looking for a long time.  It has set out 60 standards which will underpin the inspections.  However, it would be good for this House to debate the sort of inspections of centres for children and adults with disabilities carried out in other jurisdictions and the sort of standards which should be adhered to in those centres.</p><p>I welcome the progress being made on the Bus &Eacute;ireann strike at the Labour Relations Commission, being conscious that so many people were affected by yesterday's strike.  I very much hope there will be a successful conclusion to the negotiations at the Labour Relations Commission.  It is very welcome from the point of view of all sides that the strike has been called off to allow those negotiations to take place and tribute should be paid to the Labour Relations Commission and all those involved in the negotiations.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" speakername="Eamonn Coghlan" time="14:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400005#D00200"><p>I, too, pay my respects to the parents of young Donal Walsh who passed away - his mum, Elma, and his dad, Fionnbar.  As somebody who has worked for many years with Our Lady's Hospital for Sick Children in Crumlin in the area of fundraising, I have seen many young children who have passed through the hospital pass away.  Young Donal was diagnosed with cancer at 12 years of age and he had the courage and the wisdom to refuse to give up on what was termed "a death sentence" when he was diagnosed.  According to Donal, every day he went to the hospital was like a trip to hell.  When one thinks of what is happening in the world today, whether strikes, economic crises and the various issues which come up in the Seanad and in the D&aacute;il, the death of this young man puts life and the meaning of life into perspective.</p><p>He became an advocate for suicide prevention in a television appearance and in the press articles written about him.  He viewed suicide as a permanent solution to a temporary problem.  Given that suicide is one of the leading causes of death among young people in Ireland, perhaps Donal's death should not be in vain and that is time for the Government to put extra resources into mental health, in particular for young people.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="14:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400005#D00300"><p>T&aacute; &aacute;thas orm gur ardaigh mo bheirt chomhghleacaithe b&aacute;s Donal Breathnach.  I share in the tributes rightly being paid to the late Donal Walsh.  He was a teenager who many of us have followed in recent months, since his appearance on RTE television.  In those short few months, he achieved what many people fail to do in a lifetime, which is, he found his voice and a way to turn his sickness, his suffering and his impending death into a way to help others.  Many people do not find that meaning and purpose in their lives and it is a tragedy for them but it is all the more awesome that Donal did and that he spoke with such clarity.  As many people find difficult to do in his situation, he had a very clear idea of what was happening and he was not afraid to face up to that.</p><p>He challenged us all - young and old - to be grateful for our lives and to take the opportunity each day presents.  His particular message about suicide might have been difficult for some people to hear, in particular other young people, but he had the credibility and ability to say something which was vitally important for them to hear.  It was more than just youthful idealism; there was a determined maturity in what he was about.  As has been said, he taught us a lot in that short time.  He taught us a lot about suffering, happiness and ultimate meaning.  May he rest in peace and may his family be consoled by the fine and courageous example he set to all.</p><p>On that tragic subject of suicide, it is noteworthy - others have spoken about it - that in recent weeks, a coroner in south Kerry and a coroner in north Donegal have spoken out about the problem of suicide.  One asked if we were losing sight of humanity while the other feared we were not taking it sufficiently seriously in terms of the amount of money spent on suicide prevention compared to road safety.  For example, &euro;30 million was spent on road safety in 2011 while just &euro;3 million was spent on suicide prevention.</p> <p>I understand that tens of millions of pounds sterling have been spent in Northern Ireland.</p><p>As I have said before, I do not know what the exact answer is for suicide prevention.  I do not know if it should be about one single organisation, as in other jurisdictions, focusing on the problem.  A lot of it is about attitudes.  It is about recognising that the law and the wider culture are educators.  Each of us looks to the culture in this situation, and in other areas, to see what is the appropriate way to respond in a time of crisis.  Our message must be much clearer as a society.  While we console those who have been bereaved and pay a just tribute to those who have died, we must convey a loud and clear message that what has happened is the wrong thing.  As has been said, suicide is a permanent solution to a temporary problem.  The debate must continue but in a way that helps rather than hinders. </p><p>Finally, I welcome the announcement by the HSE of the membership of a review group to examine the emergency response to the incident of a tragic death of a toddler in Cork last week.  He had to be driven to hospital by a local sporting hero because there was no question of an ambulance arriving on time.  The availability of emergency services to people is a human rights issue.  No matter what difficulties we face as an economy we cannot lose sight of that.  I hope that the review group will conduct its work speedily.  We must also pay tribute to the great work being done by ambulance drivers, first aid personnel and so on.  We have a serious problem if we cannot guarantee a basic minimum response of emergency support and care to people as arose in the very tragic case involving a young boy, Vakaris Martinaitis. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400006#E00200"><p>Like others, I wish to express my sympathies to the family of Donal Walsh, a very brave young man.  I learned of his death on Sunday night from my younger daughter who, like a lot of young people, got the information on YouTube and Facebook.  On Sunday night I sat down and watched his YouTube video on his life and I also read his account of his experience with cancer.  He has motivated practically every second level student in the country to raise money for the children's hospitals.  In his long writings he stated that when he relapsed the second time with cancer and had to return to Crumlin children's hospital that as he re-entered the ward it struck him that nothing had changed since his first stay.  He discovered that the conditions in the ward, in terms of the facilities available, were just as they were when he developed cancer and sought treatment the first time.  If his death does nothing else it proves to me that our decision to prioritise the building of a new national children's hospital was not just necessary but long overdue.  Much as I appreciate the efforts of young people to raise money for our hospitals, such fundraising should not be necessary in a developed country.</p><p>Yesterday, I was very proud to attend the opening of an Access housing unit in Cork with the Minister of State at the Department of Health, Deputy Kathleen Lynch.  It is an innovative new service that will house homeless people by moving them out of long-term homeless accommodation into homes, principally in the rental sector.  It was established in response to the unfortunate growing demand for emergency accommodation and a growing incidence of homelessness.  The prioritising of homelessness makes sound economic sense for the State because its prevention saves it a significant amount of money.  We spend &euro;23,000 on every single person in emergency homeless accommodation.  It is in that context that I again ask the Leader to arrange a debate on homelessness, particularly the shortage of housing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400006#E00300"><p>I want to be associated with the expressions of condolence and the sentiments already expressed by Senators in respect of the passing of Donal Walsh.  I too offer my condolences to his family.</p><p>I want to again register my party's protest at the very light Order of Business for the next number of days and for this week.  Only one piece of legislation will be debated this week, namely, Report Stage of the Taxi Regulation Bill.  Sin &eacute; for the week.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400007#F00200"><p>What about the Private Members' Bill?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400007#F00300"><p>We have a Private Members' Bill but that is a Bill being introduced by members of the Opposition.  I am talking about legislation coming forward from the Government.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400007#F00400"><p>It is a Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400007#F00500"><p>We have one item of legislation.  On Thursday we will have the Order of Business followed by statements with an MEP.  There is no reason that could not be taken on Wednesday.  It is beyond me why we will sit on Thursday.  It seems we are trying to pad out days here and not doing what we should be doing, which is introducing legislation.  My concerns about that are genuine and I will express them again.  I wish to move an amendment to the Order of Business, to be helpful to the Leader, that we take No. 26 on the Order Paper, which is the Corporate Manslaughter Bill 2013 tabled by Sinn F&eacute;in.  If the Government is not prepared to bring forward legislation we should debate the legislation the Opposition wants to bring forward.</p><p>I ask the Leader that we would be given ample time and opportunity to discuss the detail of the Higgins report, which will be published shortly.  I state my objection to the way that report is being launched.  It is being launched first to the press at an event in Croke Park following which Deputies and Senators will be briefed.  That is not the best way for Oireachtas Members to be briefed on legislation.  It should be done in both Houses of the Oireachtas and not initially at press conferences.  I register my protest about the way that is being done.  That aside, there is no doubt that the Higgins report will have profound implications, both positive and negative, for acute hospital services across the State for generations to come.  It is that important, and given that, it is vital that this House has the opportunity to properly tease out people's concerns while welcoming the positive aspects but also to tease out the genuine concerns of patients across the State and also in the Leader's constituency, the south east.  I ask the Leader to provide sufficient time for that to happen because we need to have proper debate on the full implications of what will be contained in the Higgins report.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400007#F00600"><p>As a former member of Dublin City Council - I was on the council when it came into being - I welcome the news that it has been agreed to treble the number of bicycles available under the Dublinbikes scheme from 500 to 1,500.  Since it was introduced four years ago the Dublinbikes scheme has proven a template for cities across Europe and the world and has shown how a properly implemented and efficiently run urban bike scheme can be successful.  In a time when we are experiencing cutbacks on all levels it is good to see something being extended.  At the end of April last year, Dublinbikes passed 3.5 million journeys and when we consider this was achieved with only 500 bicycles it is all the more impressive.  It is envisaged that by 2015 we will be on course to increase the fleet to 5,000 bicycles and it is anticipated that it will extend as far north as Dublin City University.  Members will agree that the Dublinbikes initiative has changed attitudes and behaviours, freed up our roads, encouraged many more people to engage in a form of public transport, and is very cheap.  Ultimately, it is great for tourists, workers, students and businesses, and it is great for Dublin.  I commend Dublin City Council councillors on voting last night to treble the number of bicycles and look forward to further successes from this initiative in the coming years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" speakername="Mary Moran" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400007#F00700"><p>I, too, would like to add my-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400007#F00800"><p>What about us?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400007#F00900"><p>Go mo leithsceal.  Senator MacSharry is the next speaker.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400007#F01000"><p>I see that our plan to phase ourselves out is almost complete.</p><p>I would like to be associated with the tributes to Donal Walsh, a most inspirational young man.  I do not want to pour negativity on the positive messages people are giving but, yet again, we in this House are the champions of rhetoric on suicide.  Somebody who was dying spoke up and used their impending demise to promote an issue and we stand up, one after another, to say we should put in more resources and talk more about the issue - good old Donal; was it not fantastic the way he did something and we did not.  Actions speak louder than words.  I have in my hand a policy that was welcomed by everybody.  It is comprehensive.  It will cost &euro;100 million a year and will reduce suicide by 30% yet we have not even debated it in this House.  We could have any amount of the time available this week to debate it.</p> <p>Actions speak louder than words except when it comes to suicide or unless there is a suicide or some child dies promoting suicide prevention.  When are we going to start doing something about it?  As Senator Eamonn Coghlan rightly said, let not this man's death been in vain, let it have meant something, finally.  Actions speak louder than words.  Let us debate it this week.</p><p> On an important issue regarding the procedures of the House, there are quotations in an article in today's <i>Irish Examiner</i>from correspondence of Members of the Houses with the Standards in Public Office Commission.  I ask the Leader to contact the head of the Commission to request the identity of the person who provides briefings to members of the media in place of copy to provide colour articles to make fun of Members of the Oireachtas who go on foreign trips to research and inform themselves of very important issues to the people of the State, such as abortion.  Irrespective of whether the trip to the United States of America, on which Members of both Houses went, ought to have been paid for directly by them or was correctly paid for by their hosts, the highest watchdog of the integrity of the Houses of the Oireachtas should not be engaged in gutter-sniping in the press in the interests of feeding copy to lazy journalists.  I ask most respectfully that in the interests of the integrity of the House and the professionalism of the Standards in Public Office Commission, we have an answer to the question by tomorrow.  It is unacceptable that an article in today's <i>Irish Examiner</i>authoritatively quotes the private correspondence Members from all sides sent to the Commission for its consideration.</p><p> It is appropriate that someone should raise this matter in the House.  Perhaps it is most appropriate that it should be me as I have never been on a foreign trip in 11 years in the House.  I am the first to acknowledge, however, the importance of such trips in informing the business of both Houses.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400008#G00200"><p>It is only fitting that we all acknowledge the sad passing of Donal Walsh and convey our deep sympathy to his family.  As a mother of teenagers, I was particularly struck by the extent to which he was a role model at 16 years of age as well as by the unique message he conveyed.  I ask the Leader to schedule yet another debate on suicide and reflect on how best to mark Donal's young life and to continue his positive message.  He touched young people in a way that few others have managed.</p><p>I support the call for a debate as soon as possible on the report by Professor Higgins on hospital reorganisation.  While it looks positive, it is worth teasing out given the broad-ranging ramifications it will have.</p><p>I welcome HIQA's stated intention today to inspect and register residential centres for children and adults with disabilities.  There are 900 people with disabilities living in 1,200 residential centres nationally.  They can be our forgotten people.  They can be voiceless unless we advocate for them and ensure their services are of the high standard of other people's services.  This is what HIQA is achieving.  We complain about a great deal in the House, but HIQA is doing fine work.  It has done great work in older people's centres and is now moving on to residential centres for people with disabilities.  I welcome that and would like to see others do the same.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400008#G00300"><p>Senator Moran is next.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400008#G00400"><p>Sorry-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400008#G00500"><p>The next speaker is Independent.  This list is on the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400008#G00600"><p>Senator Moran is a Labour Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400008#G00700"><p>She has not spoken.  I will conduct the business, with respect.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400008#G00800"><p>The Leas-Chathaoirleach is doing a very good job, but the procedure is that the order of speakers alternates from one side to the other.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400008#G00900"><p>The procedure as laid out for the last two years is exactly as I am following it.  Senator Leyden is delaying matters.  Senator Moran, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400008#G01000"><p>Thank you very much.  It is not the one I follow when I am in the Chair.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" speakername="Mary Moran" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400009#H00100"><p>I thank the Leas-Chathaoirleach and can assure Senator Terry Leyden that it is worth waiting for.  </p><p>I extend my sincere condolences to the family of Donal Walsh.  He made a lasting impression and was an inspiration for young and old.  I have no doubt that his memory will live on as a powerful advocate on suicide.  I, too, would welcome another debate on the issue.  It is a discussion that needs to be held continually.  Last night in my home town a positive mental health forum that I had set up in January had that conversation on suicide, dispelling the myths about it.  It was well attended.  It is only by coming forward and speaking out that we can offer help to one another.</p><p>I welcome the launch by the Minister of State, Deputy Kathleen Lynch, of the national standards for residential services for children and adults with disabilities, which was long overdue.  I am delighted that the systems standards of HIQA will be in place to ensure vulnerable people and those with disabilities will have the safeguards they need in order that they will be protected and their quality of life will be enhanced in every way.  However, I have grave concerns about the number of people with disabilities who need access to residential care services.  There is a difficulty for those trying to access such care.  While improving standards, I hope HIQA will ensure the number of beds and services available for people with disabilities will not decrease.</p><p>One item of great concern concerns care in the home for the elderly.  I refer specifically to the case, brought to my attention in recent days, of a 90 year old woman in my locality who fell three weeks ago.  She has not been able to lie down since because of a broken arm, diabetes and a heart complaint.  She has been forced to sleep on a chair at night because no orthopaedic bed is available.  We spoke earlier about human dignity and people's rights.  It is appalling that in a developed country an orthopaedic bed cannot be provided.  I do not mind what cutbacks or cuts to services are made, but we owe this to elderly people and all other citizens.  A 90 year old woman is struggling when the problem could be rectified so simply.  Such persons need the services provided, including continual home help.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400009#H00200"><p>The reason for the lack of business in this House is perfectly clear and it is not the responsibility of this House to deal with the matter.  The Taoiseach and the cabal that runs Fine Gael have decided that they will take over the role previously held by Fianna F&aacute;il as the slightly constitutional party.  They have decided to destroy the Seanad by refusing to refer legislation to it.  Members should watch this space.  There will be some changes made in the coming weeks, which I think we can guarantee.  We will be looking for the co-operation of everyone in the House in that regard.</p><p>I ask the Leader for a debate on the welfare of children in the State.  A number of Members have referred to the tragic question of an infant in Cork.  The infant might not have survived, but an emergency ambulance should have been available for him.  There is also the worrying situation where the welfare of children in counties Carlow and Kilkenny is not protected in terms of protection from abuse.  We have the question of Bethany Home where children are being abused.  I have been raising the matter for many years and the Church of Ireland Archbishop of Dublin begged the Government to include in the rescue scheme.  If it had been the Roman Catholic Archbishop of Dublin, could we imagine such a call being ignored?</p> <p>However, it was ignored and a programme broadcast last night demonstrated quite clearly there is an utter divergence between the way in which Roman Catholic agencies and Protestant agencies are treated.  The Bethany Home should come in.  The Sisters of Charity home in Cabra and the Brothers of Charity home in Galway both had fewer criteria than were met by the Bethany Home and yet the latter was excluded, partly as a result of an utterly disgraceful deal done by the former Minister, Michael Woods, which let the clergy off the hook.</p><p>Finally, there is an irony about the protest made by Senator MacSharry.  I have read the article in question and note a number of Members, including some Members of this House, were apparently mentioned, albeit in not very damaging ways.  I, of course, deplore leaks and bad journalism - I am unsure whether this was bad journalism - but these were the very people who, in this Chamber, applauded openly the stings that were perpetrated by the so-called pro-lifers, who I would call anti-choice people, for example, when they went posing as people with crisis pregnancies to the family planning clinics.  More recently, people from such groups invaded the clinics of fellow politicians from the other House from the Labour Party, told lies and pretended to have a particular position but secretly recorded the conversations and then fed them to the newspapers.  Let us have some integrity in this regard, as well as some consistency.  If practices are bad on one side, they are bad on both sides.  Let us not have any waffle about the subject.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1124" speakername="Michael Comiskey" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400010#J00200"><p>I wish to raise once again the fodder crisis.  While I acknowledge a good debate was held in the Chamber last Thursday, the position has worsened since then on foot of very bad weather.  First, I welcome the Minister's decision to double the transport subsidy.  This has been a highly positive move since the issue was discussed in the Seanad last Thursday.  I now seek the speeding up of the delivery of the fodder that is coming from France but also wish to call on any State agency that owns land banks or has them in its care.  NAMA is in possession of quite an amount of land nationwide, which it could make available to the farming community, as did Shannon Airport in the past.  I believe Dublin Airport has done something similar.  Land banks owned by the State or by NAMA should be considered in this regard, as it would alleviate the problem somewhat for those farmers who now are in severe difficulty.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400010#J00300"><p>I wish to be associated with the tributes to the late Donal Walsh.  He was an inspirational young man and the point made by Senator MacSharry is very important, in that the very good policy document he prepared should be debated in this House.  Moreover, there is plenty of time available in this House and it would be recognition of what Donal Walsh has done.  He has been most inspirational and his parents should be proud of him, as should his sister and the whole community in County Kerry, because he has led a campaign that was more effective than all the advertisements issued by any Department or adult because as a teenager, he advocated living one's life and stated that suicide was no solution to any problem a young person might have.  I believe this affords Members a great opportunity to express their sincere sympathy to the family.  I acknowledge there are rules in this regard but this is an exceptional situation.  He raised money for Crumlin children's hospital and certainly used each minute of his 16 years effectively.  He will be remembered when many are forgotten in this world but I do not believe the name of Donal Walsh ever will be forgotten because of what he already has contributed.</p><p>I also supports Senator Comiskey's call with regard to the fodder crisis.  It is not over and 143,000 cattle have died since the beginning of the year.  A farmer contacted Connacht Gold's operation in Athleague yesterday and found there is a waiting list for fodder at present.  Farmers are in dire straits and there has been enormous psychological pressure on farmers in this regard.  I reiterate a comment I made previously that the Minister, Deputy Simon Coveney, has let down the farming community.  He has neglected his role as Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine and frankly, compared with previous Ministers-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400010#J00400"><p>That is nonsense.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400010#J00500"><p>-----he has not responded in a positive way.</p> <p>He is good on PR and was good for photo opportunities down in Cork when some fodder came in but he was not in Athleague yesterday to meet the farmers who were waiting for fodder there.  I agree with Senator Comiskey that this matter is not finished.  The Minister should continue to provide the subsidy for the transportation of fodder into the co-operatives and marts.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" speakername="Terry Brennan" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400011#K00200"><p>I welcome the offer of mediation by the Labour Relations Commission in the Bus &Eacute;ireann dispute.  That both parties entered further discussion is to be welcomed.  All sides need to work together to secure the future of services and jobs at Bus &Eacute;ireann and to ensure the company's financial circumstances are brought under control.  This is not easy for any side, including workers, management and unions.  Great credit is due to the Labour Relations Commission for facilitating the talks between all parties.  The industrial dispute has already cost the company &euro;500,000, at a time when it is already losing &euro;500,000 per month.  Time is of the essence in bringing this dispute to a successful conclusion for the benefit of all concerned, including management, staff and customers.</p><p>Let me say a few words on the Croke Park II negotiations.  I commend the progress made to date by Mr. Kieran Mulvey of the Labour Relations Commission and the various unions involved.  Significant progress has been made with a number of unions.  As the Government has consistently said, there is no room for manoeuvre on the fiscal arithmetic as the urgent need to achieve a saving of &euro;300 million in 2013 remains.  Mr. Kieran Mulvey, chief executive officer of the Labour Relations Commission, and all the unions involved in the Croke Park II negotiations are to be commended.  I wish them continued success in their deliberations.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" speakername="Feargal Quinn" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400011#K00300"><p>The costs of living and of doing business in Ireland have always been among the highest in Europe.  An announcement last week by the European Commission in Brussels on the payment services directive gives us an answer and the opportunity to do something about it.  The Commission has stated the objective of the directive is to encourage more use of electronic payments that will cost the public nothing or very little.  We have been very slow to develop electronic payment in Ireland.  We have one of the lowest rates of usage of electronic payment systems in Europe.  Electronic payment could reduce our costs of living and business by a very considerable amount.  There are steps we can take and we can do something about this; it is in our hands.  In the past, the European Union has passed regulations and opened the door.  Other countries have availed of opportunities afforded to them in this area but we have been reluctant or very slow.  Now is the time to do something about this matter.  It is worthwhile having a discussion on this in the near future in the House because there are steps that we can take that will encourage far more use of electronic payments.</p><p>Some years ago, making a telephone call was outrageously expensive but the cost has decreased dramatically because of technology.  The same applies to electronic payments, the cost of which has reduced dramatically.  However, we still have a system in which the banks are able to control the costs, almost with a monopoly and certainly with a system that does not afford us the ability to do as we desire.  Ireland is still one of the biggest users of coins and money in Europe.  The effort now being made by the Central Bank or the Minister, an experiment to do away with one-cent and two-cent coins makes a great deal of sense.  In Finland, the one-cent and two-cent coins were never introduced at the very beginning.  Prices were rounded up or down by five cent.  It did not cost anything but saved a considerable amount of money.  A very large number of people do not use the one-cent and two-cent coins anymore.  We can take steps to do as I propose but the main aim is to avail of the opportunity afforded by the payment services directive that the European Commission launched last week.  Let us make sure we do not leave it for another couple of years before we do something about this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1155" speakername="Kathryn Reilly" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400012#L00100"><p>Two very important reports were released today.  The Economic and Social Research Institute, ESRI, released a study on the impact of the economic crisis on younger and older people, while the National Economic and Social Council, NESC, released a detailed report on the social dimension of the economic crisis.  The details of these reports make for depressing reading.  The NESC report confirmed that 22% of all households are now without any work and a quarter of all children are living in jobless households.  The ESRI report states that the impact of the crisis on people under the age of 45 years has been dramatic, particularly when compared with the impact on people over 45 years of age.  Given the importance of these two reports and the issues they explore, would it be possible to invite the authors of the reports to present the key findings to the House, perhaps through the Seanad Public Consultation Committee?  A debate with these experts on the reports would feed into our workplan and the work we do.  The Seanad Public Consultation Committee would probably be the appropriate forum.  Will the Leader consider that suggestion?</p><p>I also second the amendment to the Order of Business proposed by Senator Cullinane.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400012#L00200"><p>Ba mhaith liom moladh a thabhairt don tseirbh&iacute;s leabharlainne agus taighde at&aacute; againn anseo.  D&eacute;anann siad obair na gcapall agus tugann siad an-taca&iacute;ocht do Sheanad&oacute;ir&iacute;.  I commend the support work that is done by the Oireachtas Library and Research Service to help us in our role as Senators and parliamentarians.</p><p>I echo the thoughts of my Sinn F&eacute;in colleagues that the schedule in the House over the past number of weeks has been lighter than it could have been.  To be positive and make constructive recommendations, we often speak about how much European legislation that is laid before the Houses is not debated, so I took an example from the documents laid before the Houses last week.  It is quite pertinent to my area of interest as it relates to rural development funding.  The document is the Regulation of the European Parliament and of the European Council laying down certain transitional provisions on support for rural development by the European Agricultural Fund for Rural Development and amending certain regulations regarding interim payment procedures for rural development funding for 2014.  It goes into some detail about the agreements relating to the Common Agricultural Policy, CAP, and the legal basis for the reformed CAP.  It states that transitional rules are needed to define technical arrangements which would permit a smooth adaptation to the new conditions while at the same time ensuring continuity of the different forms of support under the CAP.  There will be a great deal of detail in that about payments made to farmers, payments made under the Leader programme and so forth, so it would be beneficial if such matters were discussed here.</p><p>There has been much confusion over the last few years about the position with Leader programme funding.  Certainly, some local area groups are still confused as to how much funding they will have for the rest of the year.  People with projects are asking me to find out when the moneys will be released to them, when they will find out what will be available to them and whether they can make applications under the Leader programme before the end of the year.  If there are to be transitional arrangements in place for 2014, it would be useful to debate them with the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government, Deputy Phil Hogan, and to ascertain what implications they will have for people in rural areas.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400012#L00300"><p>The Acting Leader of the Opposition, Senator Byrne, called for a debate on the hospital groupings.  I will certainly arrange a debate on that in the short term.  With regard to the Omagh bombings, the Taoiseach has stated that he is willing to meet with the bereaved families in Omagh.  I am sure that will be arranged in the short term also.</p><p>The fact that the vast majority of Senators mentioned the sad passing of young Donal Walsh is indicative of the life he led and the example he gave to everybody.  He certainly was an inspiration to all who listened to him.  While we of course extend our deepest sympathy to his heartbroken family, we should certainly celebrate a life that has given inspiration to so many people and which highlighted the issue of suicide prevention.</p> <p>A number of Senators, in expressing sympathy, have also raised the question of debates on suicide.  We have had four or five debates to date on suicide and its prevention.  People have also been critical of funding for mental health services.  This Government committed to a &euro;35 million special allocation for mental health services in 2012 and 2013 for adult and child mental health services.  The special allocation included the creation of 414 mental health posts of which the majority, 410, are now in place.  That is significant progress in that area.</p><p>I am happy to inform the House that the budget for 2013 allocated a further &euro;35 million which will include an additional 470 posts that will be advertised shortly.  We have seen action in that regard and the Government is committed to the area.  The Minister of State, Deputy Lynch, has received assurances from the HSE that the recruitment process for the 2013 posts is in progress.  Advertising for them has commenced.  An example of the spending involved in the &euro;35 million special allocation on suicide strategy is as follows.  The Minister of State has taken the lead and is committed to implementing the recommendations of Reach Out, the national strategy for action on suicide prevention 2005-14.  I am happy to be able to inform the House that the national office for suicide prevention has implemented most of the recommendations in the strategy, delivering a general population approach to mental health promotion and suicide prevention, using targeted programmes for people at high risk of suicide, delivering services to individuals who have engaged in deliberate self harm and providing support to families and communities bereaved by suicide.  I am not prepared to accept suggestions from the House that the Government is doing little or nothing regarding mental health and suicide prevention.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400013#M00200"><p>It is not just this Government.  All Governments------</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400013#M00300"><p>Allow the Leader to respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400013#M00400"><p>It is not about politicising the issue; it is about debate-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.53" nospeaker="true" time="15:25:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400013#M00600"><p>The figures speak for themselves.  We are losing the battle on suicide.  How many people have to die?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400013#M00700"><p>I ask Senator MacSharry to respect the Chair.  Allow the Leader to respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400013#M00900"><p>On a point of order, the Leader is coming out with figures which do not stand up to the facts.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400013#M01000"><p>That is not a point of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.58" nospeaker="true" time="15:25:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400013#M01200"><p>The information the Leader is giving is factual.  Obviously if people do not want to listen to it, that is their prerogative.  I know it may hurt in some instances.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400013#M01300"><p>The figures speak for themselves.  We are losing the battle on suicide and the empty rhetoric will not save any lives.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400013#M01400"><p>Senator MacSharry, please respect the Chair.  I call on the Leader to respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400013#M01500"><p>Senators Bacik, Healy Eames and Moran also welcomed the fact that HIQA inspections will now take place in facilities for children and adults with disabilities, which is to be welcomed by the House.  </p><p>Senator Mullen and others raised the question of suicide prevention.  Senator Hayden outlined that the national children's hospital is of paramount importance.  It will commence in due course.</p> <p>The Senator also spoke about new measures to combat homelessness.  I will ask the relevant Minister to come to the House to address that issue.</p><p>Senator David Cullinane raised concerns regarding the business of the House.  Similar concerns were voiced by his colleague, Senator Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh, last week when he asked why we were not sitting until noon on Wednesday.  I had assumed Sinn F&eacute;in Members would know we were commemorating the dead of 1916, but apparently they were not.  As I have previously stated, any legislation that is ready to be brought to the House is presented as soon as possible.  Since coming to power in 2011 this Government has introduced a considerable amount of long overdue reforming legislation-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400014#N00200"><p>How can the Leader make such a claim?  One need only look at the cl&aacute;r for this week.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400014#N00300"><p>-----along with the legislation that has been necessary to bring into effect the agreement with the troika.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400014#N00400"><p>Will the Leader name one reforming Bill the Government has introduced?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400014#N00500"><p>Members must allow the Leader to speak without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400014#N00600"><p>This has placed great pressure on the Attorney General's office in recent years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400014#N00700"><p>Name one piece of reforming legislation?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400014#N00800"><p>Naturally there has been a knock-on effect in the drafting of legislation.  If there is no Bill ready, I cannot bring it before the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400014#N00900"><p>There is no shortage of Opposition legislation to debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400014#N01000"><p>Senators opposite are constantly interrupting and are not prepared to listen when I answer their questions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400014#N01100"><p>The Leader is not answering our questions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400014#N01200"><p>I am trying to answer the questions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400014#N01300"><p>No, the Leader is defending the indefensible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400014#N01400"><p>The Leader, without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400014#N01500"><p>I also remind Members of the considerable volume of legislation that has been initiated in this House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400014#N01600"><p>By the Opposition.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400014#N01700"><p>This has given the Seanad a real opportunity to influence debate and legislative provisions, which is more than can be said for previous Governments.  I have had every Minister and Minister of State here on numerous occasions to discuss matters which Members have highlighted as being of considerable national importance.  Yet, on the majority of those occasions, only a small number of Members have been present in the Chamber to discuss the issues.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400014#N01800"><p>On the Government side of the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400014#N01900"><p>My advice to Members opposite is that people in glasshouses should not throw stones.  I will be doing them a favour if I do not expand on that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400014#N02000"><p>We have introduced three Private Members' Bills.  How many have Government Members introduced?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400014#N02100"><p>Senators opposite could not even summon a quorum during one of the debates last week.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400014#N02200"><p>The Government is selling a pig in a poke to the public.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400014#N02300"><p>Senator Marc MacSharry must refrain from interrupting the Leader.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400014#N02400"><p>The drama festival in Athlone is over; Senator MacSharry should give somebody else a chance to perform.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400014#N02500"><p>The Leader should get real.  He is playing senior hurling now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400014#N02600"><p>Senator Catherine Noone complimented Dublin City Council on the success of the Dublin bicycle scheme and its proposed expansion.</p><p>Senator Marc MacSharry referred to the leaking of information by the Standards in Public Office Commission to newspapers.  I will certainly raise that matter with the commission and if I receive a response will relay it to the Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400014#N02700"><p>With respect, will the Leader undertake to request a response?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400014#N02800"><p>A Leas-Chathaoirleach, I am constantly being interrupted by Senator MacSharry.  He is giving me no opportunity to answer the points raised.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400014#N02900"><p>Senator MacSharry, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400014#N03000"><p>Senators Fidelma Healy Eames and David Cullinane referred to the Higgins report.  I will ask the Minister to come to the House for a debate on the contents of that report.  Senator Cullinane observed that it will include both positive and negative news.  I am pleased to tell him that in the case of Waterford Regional Hospital the news is very good indeed, with a recommendation that services not only be retained but enhanced.</p><p>Senator Mary Moran asked about additional residential places for persons with disabilities.  I will ask the Minister to address the House on that issue.  Senator David Norris raised concerns regarding the welfare of children and referred once again to the status of former residents of Bethany Home.  Again, I will ask the Minister to respond to those points.</p><p>Senators Michael Comiskey and Terry Leyden referred to the fodder crisis.</p> <p>I thank the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine for coming into the House last week after he had been requested to do so.  He outlined in detail the measures taken.  His decision to extend the scheme is to be welcomed by all.  We realise farmers still have problems, about which there is no question, and the Minister is doing everything possible to address them.</p><p>Senator Terry Brennan welcomed the role played by the Labour Relations Commission in bringing the management and staff of Bus &Eacute;ireann together.  He also welcomed the ongoing Croke Park II talks.  I am sure we all wish the Labour Relations Commission every success in the talks.</p><p>I could not agree more with what Senator Feargal Quinn said about the payment services directive, the objective of which is to encourage people to use more electronic payments.</p><p>Senator Kathryn Reilly called for a debate on the social consequences of the recession.  She suggested a recent report on the matter could be referred to the Seanad Public Consultation Committee.  I am sure the committee can consider it.</p><p>Senator Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh spoke about EU rural development funding.  I am sure the matter will be raised at the Joint Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine and, if necessary, referred for scrutiny at the Joint Committee on European Union Affairs which was the subject of a motion in the House last week.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400015#O00200"><p>Senator David Cullinane has proposed an amendment to the Order of Business, "That No. 26, Corporate Manslaughter Bill 2013, be taken today".  Is the amendment being pressed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400015#O00300"><p>It is.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.96/1" nospeaker="true" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400016#P00050"><p>Amendment put:</p><p>The Seanad divided: T, 12; Nl, 27.</p><p>Tellers: T, Senators David Cullinane and Kathryn Reilly; Nl, Senators Aideen Hayden and Michael Mullins.</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.96/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2013-05-14" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400016#P00050">
            <divisioncount ayes="12" noes="27" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" vote="aye">Sean Barrett</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" vote="aye">Thomas Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" vote="aye">David Cullinane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" vote="aye">Terry Leyden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" vote="aye">Marc MacSharry</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" vote="aye">Paschal Mooney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" vote="aye">R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" vote="aye">Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" vote="aye">Feargal Quinn</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1155" vote="aye">Kathryn Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" vote="aye">Jim Walsh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" vote="aye">Diarmuid Wilson</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" vote="no">Ivana Bacik</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1121" vote="no">Paul Bradford</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" vote="no">Terry Brennan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1114" vote="no">Deirdre Clune</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" vote="no">Eamonn Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1124" vote="no">Michael Comiskey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" vote="no">Martin Conway</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" vote="no">Maurice Cummins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" vote="no">Jim D'Arcy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1160" vote="no">Michael D'Arcy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" vote="no">John Gilroy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1144" vote="no">Jimmy Harte</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" vote="no">Aideen Hayden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" vote="no">Fidelma Healy Eames</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1173" vote="no">Lorraine Higgins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" vote="no">Ca&iacute;t Keane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" vote="no">John Kelly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1162" vote="no">Denis Landy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" vote="no">Mary Moran</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" vote="no">Michael Mullins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" vote="no">Catherine Noone</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" vote="no">Marie Louise O'Donnell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" vote="no">Susan O'Keeffe</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" vote="no">Pat O'Neill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1163" vote="no">Tom Shehan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" vote="no">Jillian van Turnhout</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1176" vote="no">Katherine Zappone</mpname>
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.96/3" nospeaker="true" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400016#P00050"><p>Amendment declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.97" nospeaker="true" time="15:45:00" ><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.98" nospeaker="true" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400017#R00100">Message from Dil</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400017#R00200"><p>D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann has passed the Defence Forces (Second World War Amnesty and Immunity) Bill 2012 on 7 May 2013, without amendment.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.100" nospeaker="true" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400017#R00300">Taxi Regulation Bill 2012: Report Stage (Resumed) and Final Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.101" nospeaker="true" time="15:50:00" ><p>Debate resumed on Government amendment No. 23:
In page 15, to delete lines 14 to 47 and in page 16, to delete lines 1 to 42 and substitute the following:11.--(1) Where a person who makes an application for a licence to drive a small public service vehicle is engaged in another occupation which involves driving a vehicle, the person when making the application shall--(a) inform the licensing authority of this fact, and
(b) show to the satisfaction of the licensing authority, that he or she has informed in writing any employer of his or hers connected with that occupation, of his or her intention to make an application for that licence.(2) Where the holder of a licence to drive a small public service vehicle becomes engaged in another occupation which involves driving a vehicle, the person shall--(a) inform in writing the licensing authority of this fact, and
(b) show to the satisfaction of the licensing authority, that he or she has informed in writing any employer of his or hers connected with that other
occupation, that he or she is the holder of a licence to drive a small public service vehicle and carries on the business of driving a small public
service vehicle for hire or reward. (3) This section does not apply to a vehicle used in connection with agricultural activities on a farm.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1163" speakername="Tom Shehan" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400017#R00500"><p>I remind Senators that a Senator may speak only once on Report Stage except the proposer of an amendment who may reply to the discussion on the amendment.  On Report Stage each amendment must be seconded.</p><p>Amendments Nos. 24 to 26, inclusive, are alternatives to amendment No. 23.  Amendments Nos. 23 to 26, inclusive, may be discussed together, by agreement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400017#R00600"><p>Further consideration has been given to this matter by the Office of the Attorney General.  On foot of advice from that office I am withdrawing the amendment to section 11, as tabled, and I intend to make the necessary amendment to the section at the next available opportunity on Committee Stage in the D&aacute;il.  Obviously Senators will have a chance to come back to the issue again.  I will take on board all the comments made previously by Senators in respect of the section.</p><p>In regard to amendments Nos. 24 to 26, inclusive, having considered the matter in light of Senator Barrett's previous comments on Committee Stage, I have proposed an appropriate amendment to section 11.  Therefore, I cannot accept the amendments, as proposed by the Senators.  As I have said previously, this is an issue we will return to on Committee Stage in the D&aacute;il.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400017#R00700"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House and thank him for his thoughts on the amendments.  I was concerned at a possible breach of the European Convention on Human Rights and privacy but I am delighted to hear the Minister of State is thinking along those lines.  I hope it augurs well for the rest of the afternoon.  I thank the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.105" nospeaker="true" time="15:50:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.106" nospeaker="true" time="15:50:00" ><p>Amendments Nos. 24 to 26, inclusive, not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.107" nospeaker="true" time="15:55:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 27:
In page 19, line 31, to delete &#8220;subsection (1)&#8221; and substitute &#8220;this section&#8221;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400018#S00300"><p>This is a minor drafting amendment relating to the cross-reference in section 14 of the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.109" nospeaker="true" time="15:55:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1163" speakername="Tom Shehan" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400018#S00500"><p>Amendment No. 28 arises out of committee proceedings.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400018#S00600"><p>I move amendment No. 28:<blockquote><br /><br />  In page 19, to delete lines 40 to 45.</blockquote>My concern is that the section may be unconstitutional.  We have created a property right and the Constitution forbids us to place restraints on the transfer of that property.  My view is that the licence should have no value.  It was worth a lot more, at over &euro;100,000, at one stage when the licences were scarce.  They are currently selling for about &euro;3,000, as advertised in the<i> Evening Herald </i>most evenings.  The licences are property and we would be interfering with the right of people to transfer a licence which has constitutional protection.  My wish is that licences were not treated as property and that they had no value other than as pieces of paper.  If too few of them are issued, they then acquire this value and they then become the same as any other kind of property.  I would be concerned about the constitutional implications of restricting the right of people to transfer that property.  I wish they were worth zero but they are worth something.  This section may interfere with the right to dispose of property under the property rights provisions in the Constitution.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400018#S00700"><p>The introduction of a prohibition of transfer of the SPSV licence is a recommendation under action 14 of the taxi regulation review report 2011.  The underlying principle for this proposal is that a licence should determine a person's suitability to carry out the function and should have no monetary value or be traded in the open market.  The Senator and I are in agreement on that point.  I dealt comprehensively with this issue on Committee Stage.  I will not be accepting the Senators' amendment as it asks me to go against the unanimous views of the taxi review group which recommended this action on the transfer of SPSV licences and to ensure it did not happen.  A licence should be personal to the licence-holder.  They should be awarded on the grounds of suitability and not on the basis of having bought out an incumbent operator.  The taxi review group insisted on this provision and we dealt with it in great detail.  In my view it is the way to create an industry that operates with consistency and regulation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400018#S00800"><p>Article 43.1.2&deg; of the Constitution states:<blockquote><br />The State accordingly guarantees to pass no law attempting to abolish the right of private ownership or the general right to transfer, bequeath, and inherit property.</blockquote>I accept that the Minister of State has been given advice but I, too, have received advice.  I wish to alert the House to the danger.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400018#S00900"><p>I am cognisant of the High Court ruling concerning the constitutionality of imposing controls on entry to the taxi market.  Therefore, I have had the matter examined by a senior counsel at the Office of the Attorney General.  I conclude from that advice that the underlying policy principle for this decision is sound.  Furthermore, as there has been a gradual move towards full prohibition of SPSV licence transfer over a number of years, the measure could not be challenged successfully on grounds of it being an unforeseen or unduly severe regulatory change or imposition on the industry.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400018#S01000"><p>I should have added that the fear among the lawyers with whom I discussed this measure is that there will now be ingenious transactions.  The licence will not have a value but it will come in a box which will be worth something.</p> <p>It is not beyond the ability of the legal profession to design such mechanisms.  However, we have had the discussion and I thank the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.117" nospeaker="true" time="16:00:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.118" nospeaker="true" time="16:00:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 29:
In page 21, line 7, before &quot;the&quot; where it firstly occurs to insert &quot;if the holder is an individual,&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400019#T00400"><p>This is a minor drafting amendment to provide more precise text in section 17.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.120" nospeaker="true" time="16:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.121" nospeaker="true" time="16:00:00" ><p>Government No. 30:
In page 21, between lines 35 and 36, to insert the following:&quot;(m) details of any revocation of the licence;&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400019#T00700"><p>This amendment provides that the register of licences maintained by the National Transport Authority under section 17 includes details of the revocation of a licence also.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.123" nospeaker="true" time="16:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400019#T00900"><p>I move amendment No. 31:<blockquote><br />In page 23, between lines 6 and 7, to insert the following:&quot;(<i>j</i>) to encourage investment by new market entrants in vehicles and services and to issue new licences to ensure that investment is not diverted into the purchase of licences from incumbents.&quot;.</blockquote>Advertently or inadvertently, the danger in what we are doing is that we will create a scarcity value for the licences the Minister of State mentioned in the last section.  If one takes accounts of the estimates of Paul Gorecki of the ESRI, the way we have restricted entry since SI 250 of 2010 will create a scarcity value for licences.  That means the investment is diverted to buying licences from incumbents.  I share the Minister of State's view that the licences should have no value, but they will have a value because they will be scarce.  </p><p>  Taking account of the 2013 estimates from the National Transport Authority, there are 5,000 fewer people involved in the industry since its peak in 2008.  We want to have an industry which has newcomers, not just incumbents who are always defending the <i>status quo</i>.  In this branch of economics the incumbents are evil, while the new entrants are the heroes who keep an industry dynamic.  There is far too much emphasis in the Bill on protecting the interests of the incumbents and keeping out new entrants.  Today's finding from the ESRI that the burden of the recession has been overwhelmingly borne by young people is topical.  Keeping new entrants out of a sector is very nice for the incumbents, as they do well out of it, but it puts the burden of the recession which everyone in the House is trying to correct on people who are outsiders in this insider-outsider labour market.  </p><p>  In many previous amendments we tried to move the Minister of State away from a system of quantity licensing, which is rigidly enforced.  Paul Gorecki's estimate is that at the current pace it will be approximately 30 years before we have open entry again.  That is preventing the growth of an industry which in the period after deregulation, as the Goodbody report showed, generated a substantial number of jobs.  We seek some commitment from the Minister of State that he is not in favour of old-fashioned quantity licensing, as applied between 1978 and 2000 and which was overturned by decisions of the High Court, and that we will stop inventing new ways to keep out new entrants, which is what we have been doing on a macro scale in this country.  It is something we will have to address across all Departments.</p><p>  We have tabled an amendment to seek to have the Minister of State use the same formula suggested by the troika in regard to young doctors who wanted to take over patients in the general medical service, but he has rejected it.  It is wrong if the person in charge of a sector controls right of entry in the interests of incumbents.  We have had that situation since 2008 and it looks like it will continue for a very long time in the absence of a commitment from the Minister of State that he will take a more lenient view of new entrants, which means the burden of the adjustment will be borne by those outside the current licensing system.   </p><p>  Having new entrants is absolutely vital.  In the past new entrants had to buy an existing licence at a time when a licence cost as much as six vehicles.  We want transport to be provided; we do not want people to buy pieces of paper.  The ingenuity of licence holders to devise ways to keep out new entrants and make a lot of money in selling licences under whatever guise their legal advisers tell them is a major obstacle.</p> <p>We need to facilitate new entrants particularly if, as we all hope, the economy starts to grow again.</p><p>As the Minister of State will know, I am in favour of the outright revocation of SI 250 of 2010.  I would be grateful if he would give some assurance that the Government has not shut down the sector for new entrants.  That would be good news for younger people who have borne the brunt of the recession, as the ESRI said today.  The incumbents are powerful and organised and have occupied buildings, including the regulator's office, and blockaded the airport.  Parliament should not give in to that type of conduct but should recognise that every sector needs new entrants.  They got a pretty raw deal under SI 250 of 2010 and, mostly, they got a pretty raw deal in the Bill and that is why I tabled my amendment.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1163" speakername="Tom Shehan" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400020#U00200"><p>I allowed the Senator a lot of latitude even though his amendment has already been discussed with amendment No. 17.  I call on the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400020#U00300"><p>As the Acting Chairman has said, the amendment was discussed earlier so I shall not go over old ground.  We have had a comprehensive debate.</p><p>I know where Senator Barrett is coming from because he has relayed his comments on numerous occasions.  As he is well aware, the Bill proposes to create a regulatory framework.  There is a capacity for new entrants.  It was unfair of him to say that there is none because structures have been put in place.  It has been consistently stated in the Bill that we are creating a framework to improve the industry.  The Senator has also made consistent arguments on economic theories and the current state of the industry but I have opposed them on many occasions here.  His arguments stem from the right reasons but the industry needs to completely change its regulatory framework.  There is access to the market but we must ensure that those who operate in it and will operate in it do so in an acceptable fashion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400020#U00400"><p>The barrier that the Minister has created costs a new entrant 91% more for the vehicle and 27% more to run it.  If his officials do not understand its impact by now then it is a poor look out for new entrants to any sector that the Government seeks to regulate.  The provision has acted as a massive barrier because no general category taxi licence has been issued since 2010.  One cannot enter the business because the incumbents have control of the Department and the National Transport Authority and have succeeded in keeping new entrants out.  That is why licences have a scarcity value again.  Therefore, I shall press my amendment because new entrants are vital to any industry.  The absence of any undertaking by the Minister of State to respond to our repeated tabling of amendments seeking to allow new entrants is unsatisfactory.  The effects were stated in the paper produced by Professor Paul Gorecki of the ESRI.  I do not think that any economist in Ireland could support the suggestion to keep new entrants out of any sector in the Irish economy, particularly as the burden of the recession has been borne by young people.  The incumbents have been so successful at keeping new entrants out and there is no doubt that is where the policy originated.  There is very little economics involved as I shall demonstrate with later amendments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1163" speakername="Tom Shehan" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400020#U00500"><p>Does the Minister of State wish to reply?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400020#U00600"><p>No.  The amendment was discussed with amendment No. 17.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1163" speakername="Tom Shehan" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400020#U00700"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400020#U00800"><p>Usually an amendment is pressed rather than discussed again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.133" nospeaker="true" time="16:05:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.134" nospeaker="true" time="16:05:00" ><p>Amendments Nos. 32 and 33 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.135" nospeaker="true" time="16:10:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 34:
In page 25, to delete lines 24 and 25 and substitute the following:
&#8220;(g) the regulation of the rental or leasing of a small public service vehicle or equipment associated with it;&#8221;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1163" speakername="Tom Shehan" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400021#V00200"><p>Is the amendment agreed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400021#V00400"><p>Could I respond on amendment No. 34?  Rental of vehicles is a financial transaction normally regulated by the Central Bank of Ireland and the financial services authority.  Why are we regulating the rental of vehicles?  What is the rationale for that?  I refer to the Minister's amendment No. 34 which refers to the regulation of the rental or leasing of vehicles.  Those are normal commercial transactions usually regulated by the Financial Regulator.  Why does the Minister's Department want to regulate the rental and leasing of vehicles?  It is a normal commercial transaction and I do not understand the reason it is in the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1163" speakername="Tom Shehan" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400021#V00500"><p>With all due respect to the Senator, amendment No. 34 was discussed with amendment No. 8 and has been agreed.  Unless the Minister wants to respond-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400021#V00600"><p>We have been down this road.  The rental market needs to be completely changed.  A certain television programme highlighted that not long ago.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.140" nospeaker="true" time="16:10:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1163" speakername="Tom Shehan" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400021#V00800"><p>Amendment No. 35 cannot be moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400021#V00900"><p>Can I reply?  The television programme has obsessed the Minister of State.  The reports of the Goodbody committee-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400021#V01000"><p>It has not obsessed the Minister at all.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400021#V01100"><p>-----and of Paul Gorecki tell the real facts.  I would not base economic policy on one television programme.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400021#V01200"><p>What the Senator has said is ridiculous and inappropriate.  For the general public it exemplified the <i>laissez-faire</i> approach to the rental market, which was unacceptable and needed to be regulated.  The Senator does not believe in proper regulation.  I believe in proper regulation.  I believe the taxi industry as currently constituted needed to be completely changed, hence the changes made here.  Anybody who knows anything about the industry knows that the rental market has been all over the place, so to speak, and that the way one got the different components to be able to drive a taxi was unacceptable.  That is why it needed to be changed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.146" nospeaker="true" time="16:10:00" ><p>Amendment No. 35 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1163" speakername="Tom Shehan" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400021#V01300"><p>Amendment No. 36 was discussed with amendment No. 12.  How stands the amendment?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400021#V01400"><p>It is not being pressed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.149" nospeaker="true" time="16:10:00" ><p>Amendment No. 36 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1163" speakername="Tom Shehan" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400021#V01600"><p>Amendment No. 36<i>a</i> is a Government amendment.  Amendments Nos. 37 and 38 are alternatives to No. 36a.  Amendments Nos. 52a and 56a are related.  Amendments Nos. 36<i>a</i>, 37, 38, 52<i>a</i> and 56<i>a</i> may be discussed together by agreement.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.151" nospeaker="true" time="16:10:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 36a:
In page 27, to delete lines 37 to 47 and in page 28, to delete lines 1 to 15 and substitute the following:
21.--(1) A person shall not drive or use a mechanically propelled vehicle in a public place for the carriage of persons for hire or reward unless--(a) the vehicle is--(i) a small public service vehicle licensed under licensing regulations, 
and
(ii) licensed to be operated or driven in that place, and(b) the person holds a licence to drive a small public service vehicle of the category that he or she is driving or using.
(2) A person shall not ply or stand for hire with a mechanically propelled vehicle which he or she is driving or in charge of in a public place unless--(a) the vehicle is a taxi in respect of which there is a licence in force for those purposes, and
(b) the person holds a licence to drive a taxi and to ply or stand for hire with the taxi in a public place.(3) A person who contravenes subsection (1) or (2) commits an offence and, if that person is not the owner of the vehicle, such owner commits an offence, and is liable on summary conviction to a class A fine.
(4) Where a person is required under licensing regulations to hold a licence to act as a dispatch operator or provide booking services, a person shall not act as a dispatch operator or provide booking services, as the case may be, unless the person holds a licence in that regard.&#8221;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400021#V01800"><p>Regarding amendment No. 36<i>a</i>, the amendments to section 21 of the Bill are drafting amendments which provide greater clarity on the prohibition on providing SPSV services without the required licence.  The principle of the provision is unaltered.</p><p>  Regarding amendments Nos. 52<i>a</i> and 56<i>a</i>, the amendments to sections 32 and 33 are consequential as a result of the drafting changes to section 21 to correct the referencing of the demerit offences associated with the offences of contravention of the prohibition on operating without a licence under section 21, as amended.</p><p>  I cannot agree to amendments Nos. 37 and 38.  Subsections 21(1) and (2) are specific offences for providing SPSV services without a small public service vehicle licence and an SPSV driver licence.  This is clarified in subsection (9), which specifies that these provisions do not apply to bus services.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400021#V01900"><p>I was hopeful that would be of assistance because it states that "A person shall not drive or use a mechanically propelled vehicle in a public place for the carriage of persons for reward unless the person holds a licence to drive a small public service vehicle ...".  There are two kinds, as the Minister of State said, but as it is worded it states that one cannot drive a bus unless one has a licence to drive a taxi.  That is all I was trying to get across.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400021#V02000"><p>I understand the Senator's motives.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400021#V02100"><p>Go raibh maith agat.  I will not press those amendments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.156" nospeaker="true" time="16:10:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.157" nospeaker="true" time="16:10:00" ><p>Amendments Nos. 37 and 38 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1163" speakername="Tom Shehan" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400021#V02500"><p>Amendment No. 39 is out of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.159" nospeaker="true" time="16:10:00" ><p>Amendment No. 39 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.160" nospeaker="true" time="16:20:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 40:
In page 30, lines 12 and 13, to delete all words from and including &quot;and&quot; in line 12 down to and including &quot;paragraph (a)&quot; in line 13.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="16:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400022#W00200"><p>Amendment No. 40 removes local authorities from the list of bodies set out in paragraph (<i>c</i>) the observations of which are to be considered by the NTA when consulting on maximum fares under section 23.  The purpose of the amendment is to align paragraph (<i>c</i>) of the section with paragraph (<i>a</i>) which does not include local authorities.  It is for the sake of consistency.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.162" nospeaker="true" time="16:20:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1163" speakername="Tom Shehan" time="16:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400022#W00400"><p>Amendments Nos. 41, 43 to 47, inclusive, 53 and 57 are related and may be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.164" nospeaker="true" time="16:20:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 41:
In page 31, to delete lines 23 and 24 and substitute the following:&quot;(4) The driver of a taxi shall not stand or attempt to stand for hire with the taxi --&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="16:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400022#W00600"><p>The amendments will have the effect that the offence under section 24(10) on the failure by a person to comply with a request to move on by a member of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na - previously an "authorised person" - will now only apply under section 24(7), that is, to a driver or a person in charge of a vehicle which is not a taxi standing or parking at an appointed stand.  Previously, the offence under section 24(10) involved a failure by a taxi driver to comply with such a request to move on in the circumstances set out in section 24(3) to (6), inclusive, including standing for hire at a stand in an area the driver is not licensed for; standing at a rank that is full; standing on part of a public road adjoining or in proximity to a stand that is full, and standing at a taxi rank when the vehicle is not available for hire.  The offence under section 24(9) will continue to cover contraventions of subsections (3) to (7), inclusive, by a taxi driver or other person in charge of a vehicle which may give rise to the imposition of a class D fine.  However, under the amendments under discussion, there will not be a further offence connected with a failure to comply with a request to move on in the case of subsections (3) to (6), inclusive.</p><p>With due regard to the underlying policy concern over the availability of taxi ranks, about which I have taken much comment from drivers on board, there is justification for some leniency in the system of penalties for the regulation of driver behaviour at ranks without diminishing the core offences.  The amendments which waive the extension of the offence for contravention of a request to move on will go some way towards minimising any risk of conflict and public order issues arising at ranks between enforcement officers and taxi drivers who may feel justified in competing for limited taxi rank space, particularly in the greater Dublin area.  All Senators will know stories about such incidents.  For the same reason, amendments Nos. 45 and 46 - on the reduction in fine levels on conviction for the offences listed under section 24(9) and (10) - aim to reflect the more lenient approach to this specific suite of offences.  In proposing the amendments I am taking account of representations made to me by taxi interests.</p><p>Amendments Nos. 52 and 53 are intended to ensure demerits will not apply under Part 5 of the Bill to offences under section 24 concerning plying for hire or standing at taxi ranks.  The taxi advisory committee has made representations to me to raise concerns about the attachment of demerits to offences relating to appointed stands.  The committee said it was too harsh a penalty, leading to the suspension of a licence, given the lack of availability of taxi spaces relative to the number of taxis.  On foot of these concerns, I have excluded the imposition of demerits for such offences.  I have also taken on board comments made in the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.166" nospeaker="true" time="16:20:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.167" nospeaker="true" time="16:20:00" ><p>Amendment No. 42 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.168" nospeaker="true" time="16:20:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 43:
In page 31, to delete lines 36 and 37 and substitute the following:&quot;(7) The driver, or person in charge of, a vehicle which is not a taxi shall not stand with the vehicle, or park it, at an appointed stand.&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.169" nospeaker="true" time="16:20:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.170" nospeaker="true" time="16:20:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 44:
In page 31, to delete lines 38 to 44 and in page 32, to delete line 1 and substitute the following:&quot;(8) Where, in the opinion of a member of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, the driver or person in charge, of a vehicle is contravening subsection (6) or (7), the member may require the person to move the vehicle from the appointed stand concerned.&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.171" nospeaker="true" time="16:20:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.172" nospeaker="true" time="16:20:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 45:
In page 32, lines 3 and 4, to delete &#8220;class C fine&#8221; and substitute &quot;class D fine&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.173" nospeaker="true" time="16:20:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.174" nospeaker="true" time="16:20:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 46:
In page 32, lines 5 and 6, to delete &quot;an authorised person&quot; and substitute &quot;a member of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.175" nospeaker="true" time="16:20:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.176" nospeaker="true" time="16:20:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 47:
In page 32, line 7, to delete &quot;class B fine&quot; and substitute &quot;class C fine&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.177" nospeaker="true" time="16:20:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1163" speakername="Tom Shehan" time="16:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400022#W01900"><p>Amendments Nos. 48 to 51, inclusive, are related and may be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.179" nospeaker="true" time="16:20:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 48:
In page 35, line 13, to delete &quot;the Schedule&quot; and substitute the following:&quot;subsection (3) or the Schedule, as the case may be&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="16:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400022#W02100"><p>Amendments Nos. 48 to 51, inclusive, aim to rectify an omission in the Bill concerning the application of mandatory disqualification in the case of a person with a conviction for offences which correspond to the road traffic offences specified in section 28(3).  For example, a person with a corresponding road traffic conviction from Northern Ireland who has an application for or holds a PSV licence in the State will be subject to mandatory disqualification under section 28.  This corrects an anomaly and provides a basis for fair treatment of nationals and non-nationals.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.181" nospeaker="true" time="16:20:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.182" nospeaker="true" time="16:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 49:
In page 35, to delete lines 27 to 30 and substitute the following:&#8220;(c) a corresponding offence to an offence specified in the Schedule (other than an offence mentioned in paragraph 20 of Part 2 of the Schedule).&#8221;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.183" nospeaker="true" time="16:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.184" nospeaker="true" time="16:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 50: 
In page 36, line 27, to delete &#8220;or&#8221;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.185" nospeaker="true" time="16:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.186" nospeaker="true" time="16:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 51:
In page 36, line 29, to delete &#8220;2010,&#8221; and substitute the following:&#8220;2010, or(f) a corresponding offence to an offence mentioned in any of the preceding paragraphs,&#8221;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.187" nospeaker="true" time="16:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1163" speakername="Tom Shehan" time="16:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400023#X00700"><p>Amendments Nos. 52 and 56 are related and may be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.189" nospeaker="true" time="16:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 52: 
In page 40, line 30, to delete &#8220;19(4)&#8221; and substitute &#8220;19(4)(a)&#8221;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.190" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="16:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400023#X00900"><p>These amendments provide that demerits, under Part V of the Bill, will only apply to substantial breaches of the SPSV regulations under section 19.  Representatives of the taxi industry indicated their concern about attaching demerits to minor breaches of SPSV regulations.  Their view is that it could potentially, very quickly, lead to suspension of SPSV licences for what are minor matters and that it was too harsh.  I have reviewed the offences and sought to provide a degree of proportionality to the application of penalties for breaches of the SPSV regulations under section 19.  The amendment allows the NTA, in regulations, to specify what it considers substantial breaches of the SPSV regulations.  With regard to breaches of the SPSV regulations that warrant demerits, demerits will only be applied on conviction.  Such substantial breaches will give rise to a prosecution before the courts.  The imposition of a fixed fine is inappropriate to such breaches.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.191" nospeaker="true" time="16:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.192" nospeaker="true" time="16:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 52a: 
In page 40, line 30, to delete &#8220;21(5) or (6)&#8221; and substitute &#8220;21(3) or (8)&#8221;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.193" nospeaker="true" time="16:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.194" nospeaker="true" time="16:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 53:
In page 40, line 31, to delete &#8220;24(9) or (10),&#8221;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.195" nospeaker="true" time="16:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.196" nospeaker="true" time="16:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 54:
In page 40, line 38, to delete &#8220;section 47&#8221; and substitute &#8220;section 46&#8221;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="16:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400023#X01600"><p>Amendment No. 54 is a technical amendment and does not change the intended meaning of the provisions.  It seeks to correct a typographical error in the cross-reference in section 33(1) to section 46, rather than section 47.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.198" nospeaker="true" time="16:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.199" nospeaker="true" time="16:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 55: 
In page 40, line 40, after &#8220;offence,&#8221; to insert the following:&#8220;(other than an offence specified in column (2) of the Table to this section at reference number 6 or 8)&#8221;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.200" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="16:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400023#X01900"><p>This amendment is very technical in nature and provides for precision in the table on page 42 in section 33.  It follows from the fact that offences under section 19(4)(<i>a</i>), for substantial breaches, and section 21 (5) or 21(6) of the Bill are not fixed payment offences and will therefore only incur demerits upon conviction before the courts.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.201" nospeaker="true" time="16:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.202" nospeaker="true" time="16:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 56. 
In page 42, to delete line 41.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.203" nospeaker="true" time="16:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.204" nospeaker="true" time="16:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 56a: 
In page 42, line 42, to delete &#8220;21(5) or (6)&#8221;and substitute &#8220;21(3) or (8)&#8221;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.205" nospeaker="true" time="16:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.206" nospeaker="true" time="16:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 57. 
In page 42, to delete lines 45 and 46.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.207" nospeaker="true" time="16:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.208" nospeaker="true" time="16:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No 57a:
In page 46, line 8, after &#8220;premises&#8221; to insert &#8220;or place&#8221;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.209" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="16:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400023#X02800"><p>This is a drafting amendment to clarify and improve the wording of section 38.  In paragraph 3(<i>a</i>), the word &quot;premises&quot; is changed to &quot;place&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.210" nospeaker="true" time="16:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.211" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1163" speakername="Tom Shehan" time="16:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400023#X03000"><p>Amendments Nos. 57<i>b </i>and 57<i>c</i> are related and will be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.212" nospeaker="true" time="16:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 57b: 
In page 46, line 45, after &#8220;licences&#8221; to insert &#8220;, records&#8221;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.213" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="16:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400023#X03200"><p>These are drafting amendments to clarify and improve the wording in section 38.  In paragraphs 38(3)(<i>g</i>) and 38(3)(<i>h</i>), the amendment provides for the inclusion of records among the list of items that can be inspected or removed by item by authorised persons in the course of their enforcement duties.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.214" nospeaker="true" time="16:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.215" nospeaker="true" time="16:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No 57c: 
In page 46, line 48, after &#8220;licences&#8221; to insert &#8220;, records&#8221;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.216" nospeaker="true" time="16:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.217" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1163" speakername="Tom Shehan" time="16:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400023#X03600"><p>Amendments Nos. 58, 59 and 60 are related and will be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.218" nospeaker="true" time="16:35:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 58:
In page 50, line 9, to delete &#8220;or directions&#8221;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.219" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400024#Y00200"><p>Again, these are drafting amendments to provide for more precise text in section 43 by deleting the text, "or direction", in all instances where it occurs in the section.  There is no provision in the Bill, as drafted, in respect of the issue of directions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.220" nospeaker="true" time="16:35:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.221" nospeaker="true" time="16:35:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 59:
In page 50, line 23, to delete &#8220;or direction&#8221;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.222" nospeaker="true" time="16:35:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.223" nospeaker="true" time="16:35:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 60:
In page 50, line 31, to delete &#8220;or direction&#8221;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.224" nospeaker="true" time="16:35:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.225" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1163" speakername="Tom Shehan" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400024#Y00800"><p>Amendments Nos. 61 and 62 are related and may be discussed together, by agreement.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.226" nospeaker="true" time="16:35:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 61:
In page 52, line 5, after &#8220;prescribe&#8221; to insert &#8220;, in accordance with subsection (5),&#8221;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.227" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400024#Y01000"><p>These amendments will provide for an upper limit on the amount the National Transport Authority can prescribe as a fixed payment for any of the offences specified as such under section 46.  In the case of fixed payment offences, under road traffic legislation the Minister prescribes the fixed payment amount which, in principle, should be a fraction of the fine on conviction for the offence, with due regard to the economic circumstances of the person concerned and, of course, his or her ability to pay.  Therefore, the amendments will provide parameters within which the National Transport Authority will have the power to make regulations specifying the fixed payment amounts for each fixed payment offence which will be no more than 10% of the fine applicable on conviction.  This also will provide reassurance for the industry with regard to the ability of individuals to pay the fees involved and has taken on board some comments I, as Minister of State, have received.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.228" nospeaker="true" time="16:35:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.229" nospeaker="true" time="16:35:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 62:
In page 52, between lines 11 and 12, to insert the following:&#8220;(5) Where the Authority prescribes the amount of a fixed payment, the amount shall not exceed, where the fine to which a person would be liable on summary conviction of the alleged offence is--(a) a class A fine, &euro;500,
(b) a class B fine, &euro;400,
(c) a class C fine, &euro;250,
(d) a class D fine, &euro;100, or
(e) a class E fine, &euro;50.&#8221;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.230" nospeaker="true" time="16:35:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.231" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1163" speakername="Tom Shehan" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400024#Y01400"><p>Amendments Nos. 63 to 65, inclusive, are related and may be discussed together, by agreement.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.232" nospeaker="true" time="16:35:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 63:
In page 53, line 11, to delete &#8220;person&#8221; and substitute &#8220;holder of the agreement&#8221;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.233" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400024#Y01600"><p>Again, these are drafting amendments to provide more precise text in section 48.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.234" nospeaker="true" time="16:35:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.235" nospeaker="true" time="16:35:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 64:
In page 53, line 14, to delete &#8220;person&#8221; and substitute &#8220;holder&#8221;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.236" nospeaker="true" time="16:35:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.237" nospeaker="true" time="16:35:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 65:
In page 53, line 18, after &#8220;guidelines&#8221; to insert &#8220;by notice to the holder of the agreement&#8221;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.238" nospeaker="true" time="16:35:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.239" nospeaker="true" time="16:35:00" ><p>Amendment No. 66 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.240" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1163" speakername="Tom Shehan" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400024#Y02300"><p>Amendments Nos. 67 to 69, inclusive, are related and may be discussed together, by agreement.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.241" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400024#Y02400"><p>I cannot accept these amendments.  Amendments Nos. 67 and 68 are unnecessary and, therefore, not appropriate inclusions in the text of the Bill.  Section 58 provides for balanced representation on the advisory committee, including representation of consumers, business and tourism.  The Competition Authority is, in fact, represented on the committee.  It is also a function of the authority, under section 18, to promote competition in the industry.  Furthermore, it is an express requirement under section 18(3) that the authority be independent.  The subsection states: "Subject to any policy direction under section 26 of the Act of 2008, the Authority shall be independent in the exercise of its functions under this Act".  This embraces the regulatory capture issue raised by Senator Barrett.  </p><p>As for amendment No. 69, as I stated previously on Committee Stage, an express objective of the National Transport Authority as regulator in carrying out its functions in the licensing and regulation of the small public service vehicle, SPSV, sector is to encourage and promote competition in services offered by SPSVs.  The taxi regulation review report, in recommending the future approach to taxi regulation, supports qualitative improvements in industry standards, as well as enforcement of the regulations.  These matters are the focus of the Bill.  The courts have already dealt with the issue of quantitative restrictions and there is no proposal in the Bill for the imposition of such restrictions.  I acknowledge that we have been up and down this road a number of times.  It is an express function of the authority, under section 18, to pursue the continued development of a qualitative licensing system.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.242" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1163" speakername="Tom Shehan" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400024#Y02500"><p>First, I apologise to Senator Sean D. Barrett.  I should have called him first.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.243" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400024#Y02600"><p>The Senator just gave me the nod.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.244" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1163" speakername="Tom Shehan" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400024#Y02700"><p>For the information of Members, it should be noted that amendment No. 66 was ruled out of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.245" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400024#Y02800"><p>Having heard my answer, the Senator can give me the question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.246" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400024#Y02900"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  On amendment No. 66, my intention was to praise the Minister of State.  I was at the meetings of the Joint Committee on Transport and Communications attended by the new chairman of Shannon Airport and the new chairman of the Port of Cork.  It is a suggestion this appears to work and if the Minister of State thinks it is a good idea, it might also apply in this case.</p> <p>I will leave that to him to address.</p><p> With regard to amendments Nos. 67, 68 and 69, my concerns remain.  They are expressed most strongly in Mr. Paul Gorecki's recent paper on this subject, published by the ESRI.  The use of SI No. 250 of 2010 to overturn four High Court decisions was inappropriate.  I refer to one's ability to enter the industry if one has the necessary skills and training.  We risk the same fate as was evident in the Supreme Court last Thursday regarding the control of electricians.  The incumbents were judged by the Supreme Court to have far too much say.  We checked the records today.  SI No. 250, which reimposes quantity licensing, was never discussed by the Oireachtas.  It is part of the judgment that the Supreme Court gave against similar arrangements with regard to electricians.  It is stated the function of legislation cannot be delegated by the Oireachtas to any other body.  What occurred was a deliberate attempt to overturn the High Court decision on open entry to the sector.  It has not been discussed in the House.  The ban has been maintained with the 91% capital cost disadvantage and the 27% running disadvantage.  There is a four-year delay in getting cases to the Supreme Court.  My legal advice is that it was wrong that a statutory instrument was used to overturn a court decision.  The Minister should have appealed the High Court decision to the Supreme Court and allowed the legal issues to be worked out there.</p><p> Sufficient regard has not been had to competition law.  It illustrates regulatory capture.  One could count the number of times the Minister of State said the taxi industry told him to do this or that, but he never made any reference in any of his speeches to the fact that the independent evaluation showed &euro;780 million in benefits from opening up the taxi industry.  As frequently happens in Ireland, the sector is frequently dominated by the producers, and the consumers are excluded and not being heard.</p><p> The Minister of State referred to a<i>laissez-faire</i>regime applying.  That has very obviously not been the case before this Bill.  If one takes the previous regulator's speech in Lisbon on 13 July 2010, one will note she listed item after item of regulatory developments.  Page 6 of her speech referred to ten quality improvements made under her term in office.  Page seven lists another five, page 8 contains another 15, and page nine contains another five.  What the regulator did and what the Goodbody report stated have received pretty short shrift in these proceedings.  Let me describe what the Minister of State considers a<i>laissez-faire</i>regime.  The previous regulator's document states:<blockquote>- national taximeter area introduced<br />- national maximum taxi fare [&amp;#8230;]<br />- national vehicle licensing system  - one vehicle, one licence<br />- colour coded tamper proof discs<br />- requirement to issue receipts<br />- requirement to carry guide dogs<br />- requirement not to unreasonably refuse fares of 30 km or under<br />- roof sign requirements clarified<br />- vehicle standard requirements- National and secure driver identification cards introduced <br />- National register of vehicle, driver and dispatch operator licences established and maintained<br />- Dispatch operator licensing system introduced.  <br />- Wheelchair accessible vehicle register established<br />- Joint administration of the driver licensing process with An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  [&amp;#8230;]</blockquote> With regard to compliance, the document states:<blockquote>- Dedicated enforcement team <br />- Fixed charge penalty system<br />- National prosecutions function<br />- Joint operations with other enforcement agencies<br />- Consumer complaints investigated <br />- Collect and disseminate statistical data relating to compliance levels in the SPSV industry in Ireland. </blockquote> On quality standards, reference is made to vehicle standards having been introduced for new entrants since 2009 and to a skills development programme having been introduced in May 2009.  On examining the list, one will realise it was not a<i>laissez-faire</i>industry; it was being regulated.  The difference recently has been the reintroduction of quantity licensing.  The industry is captured by the producers, who dominate the committee and Department.  The Department has spent a lifetime preventing competition - in the bus sector, for example.</p><p> The justification given by the Minister of State and his supporters for its position was that the industry was associated with social welfare fraud and crime.</p> <p>Let us look at what the previous regulator said about that.  Between 2008 and 2010 the number of consumer complaints reduced from 601 to 175.  That is for 77 million journeys.  The number of fixed charge penalties was reduced from 258 in 2008 to 129 in 2010.  The number of prosecutions reduced from 106 to 32, while the number of offences reduced from 117 to 32.  The danger in this legislation is that the part the Minister of State is retaining and has refused to change, despite all the amendments that have been tabled, is rigid quantity licensing.  It will take 30 years before he secures the quota for wheelchair accessible vehicles and before it becomes open entry.  We know from jurisdictions throughout the world that this means the taxi licences acquire scarcity value, those with them are in a monopoly and the standard of service declines.  To overturn a decision that benefited the Irish public through the creation of approximately 20,000 extra jobs and generated time savings worth &euro;780 million, as calculated by the Goodbody report, and to never even refer to the Goodbody report but to work from a document prepared by incumbents who do not like new entrants is wrong.  It is the wrong way to carry out economic policy in this country.</p><p> I will regret it if this Bill goes forward in its current form.  It is not the way to proceed.  When we sometimes get economic policy right, it is good to persist with it.  We have enough economic policies that need reform and this is not one of them.  The evidence from what Kathleen Doyle and the previous regulator said in 2010 shows it was not an area of tax evasion and social welfare fraud.  One forged driving licence is what the Minister for Social Protection found in a thorough investigation to clamp down on social welfare fraud.  Ditto the views of the sector against part-time people, given that in a business that is so heavily concentrated between Thursday and Saturday part-timers are a normal economic response.  However, the producers have dominated this, as they dominated the sector between 1978 and 2000 until the courts overturned it.  What we have been doing here is unpicking a decision of the courts.  I am sure this will return to the courts at some stage.</p><p> Incidentally, it is not just me saying this.  It is what the previous regulator said.  Scant regard has been paid to her role in this.  It was not a <i>laissez faire</i>industry.  She was regulating but, as part of the programme for Government, her functions were moved to the National Transport Authority.  It has assumed it took over a sector which was some type of wild west show, but it was not.  I was anxious to put those numbers on the record.  The sector was not<i>laissez faire</i>but was performing a viable function.  That function is not furthered at all by what we are doing here.  We still cannot get the clarity that we can move this Bill away from quantity licensing to quality licensing only.  That is the reason for tabling the amendments.  I am disappointed but not surprised that they have all been rejected.  That is the way the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport operated with regard to air transport and still operates with regard to bus transport.  If it sees competition, it tries to stop it.  This sector was a success.  I presume the main fault as far as the Department is concerned is that the success was not due to the Department but to the four learned judges who opened up the sector.</p><p> I wish the Department had a better view of open markets and competition, as would almost everybody in economics.  This is the wrong way.  It allows sheltered sectors to get regulatory capture over the Government and to get protection at all stages.  It is about time we introduced legislation in the interests of the wider public, not just producers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.249" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1163" speakername="Tom Shehan" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400026#AA00200"><p>Is there a seconder for the amendment?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.250" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400026#AA00300"><p>I will not move the amendments.  I just wish to put it on the record that if this Bill is passed, it is a sad day for Irish economic policy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.251" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1163" speakername="Tom Shehan" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400026#AA00400"><p>The Minister wishes to respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.252" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400026#AA00500"><p>I genuinely do not doubt the Senator's sincerity, but I believe he is in a minority of one with regard to some of his views on this.  I take on board everybody's views.</p> <p>To be fair with regard to the points the Senator has made during my four or five visits to this House, I have taken on board some of his comments and we have made a number of changes based on all of the comments made in the Seanad, which is the way it should be.  At the end of the day, however, I have a job to do, and that applies to taking on board everyone's views.  It would be inappropriate if I did not also take on board the views of those who are acting in the industry.  If anything, I get criticised in most cases for not taking them on more than I do.</p><p>I also have to take on the views of consumers, whose views are quite clear.  After the Senator's soliloquy, I want to make the point that it is quite clear the consumers of this country did not feel the industry was in the position it should have been in during recent years.  Anyone who walks down any of the main streets in Dublin on a Saturday night will see an industry that is not fit for purpose and is not at the level it should be at, yet in many parts of the country there is market failure on top of that, with no taxis available.</p><p>I inherited an industry that was not at the level it should be at.  That is why I set up the committee, why I chaired it myself and why I made all of the recommendations that I made.  When I came into the position, the enforcement of regulations was not in place, there was no joined-up thinking in regard to enforcement, the standards were not at the level required and the issues of people with disabilities and wheelchair accessibility had not reached the standard they should have.  To be honest, I was not very happy with the standard of knowledge for those who had acquired certain licences, and I have had direct experience of this myself, so it was something we had to deal with.  There are concerns in regard to consumer safety and taxi driver safety, and there are also concerns in regard to criminality and fraud, which is why parts of this Bill deal with those issues.  That is the simple fact of the matter.  These are genuine concerns.  The Senator can shrug his shoulders all he wants but that is what people are saying, and it must be accepted.</p><p>We have to accept we need an industry which is fair and which can allow a person to make a living.  That is an appropriate consideration.  There are people working in the industry and they have to be able to make a living in a fair and acceptable manner.  I do not necessarily believe that is what existed heretofore.</p><p>The Senator referred to the rental market, which is an issue that concerned me.  I accept there is a need for the rental market and that will always be the case.  Unfortunately, however, the standards and regulations in this regard were simply not acceptable.  When I took over as Minister of State, some of what I heard in regard to the rental market was completely unacceptable, which is why the Bill focuses on that space in particular.  I believe that by having the proper regulations and following up with the proper enforcement afterwards, and by changing that side of the industry in particular, we will be able to deal with a large majority of the issues we have faced in recent years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.254" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1163" speakername="Tom Shehan" time="16:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400027#BB00200"><p>Did Senator Barrett say he was not moving amendments Nos. 67 to 69, inclusive?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.255" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="16:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400027#BB00300"><p>That is correct.  Some 96% of the people cited in the Goodbody report said they found deregulation had benefited them.  On incomes, it was found that incomes were lower than the average industrial wage but higher than the minimum wage.  On safety, there was no dimension because that is regulated by the insurance industry and the per kilometre charge for driving a taxi is the same as for any other vehicle for insurance purposes.</p><p>So many of the things that have been said would not stand up if people had read the Goodbody report or had read Professor Paul Gorecki.  I have to say to the House that a picture has been invented which is not confirmed by the Goodbody report, which thoroughly investigated the sector.  People in the other House or people in the courts, when this goes to the courts, will have to decide on that, but much evidence was not called upon in the preparation of this Bill.  The neglect of the Goodbody report is particularly serious because all of those points were dealt with, although they were ignored in the way the Bill has been put through the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.256" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1163" speakername="Tom Shehan" time="16:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400027#BB00400"><p>Amendments Nos. 67 to 69, inclusive, are not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.257" nospeaker="true" time="16:55:00" ><p>Amendments Nos. 67 to 69, inclusive, not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.258" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1163" speakername="Tom Shehan" time="17:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400028#CC00100"><p>Amendment No. 70 is out of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.259" nospeaker="true" time="17:05:00" ><p>Amendment No. 70 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.260" nospeaker="true" time="17:05:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 71:
In page 60, between lines 13 and 14, to insert the following:
60.--Section 3 of the Act of 2010 is amended in the definition of &quot;specified person&quot; (inserted by section 9 of the Road Traffic (No. 2) Act 2011) by substituting for paragraph (d) the following:&quot;(d) is the holder of a licence to drive a small public service vehicle granted under section 9 of the Taxi Regulation Act 2013, while driving, attempting to drive or being in charge of a small public service vehicle when the vehicle is being used in the course of carrying on business,
(da) not being the holder of a licence to drive a small public service vehicle, purports to be or acts as such holder, while driving, attempting to drive or being in charge of a vehicle for the carriage of persons for reward, or&quot;.&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.261" nospeaker="true" time="17:05:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.262" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="17:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400028#CC00500"><p>Before concluding Report Stage, I ask the Acting Chairman to direct the Clerk of the Seanad, in accordance with Standing Orders, to make a correction to the Bill in order to rectify a technical printing error that occurred in the reprinting of the Bill as amended in committee.  The correction is that section 15 should appear before section 14 in the order in which the sections are arranged.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.263" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1163" speakername="Tom Shehan" time="17:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400028#CC00600"><p>The correction is noted.  Thank you, Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.264" nospeaker="true" time="17:05:00" ><p>Bill, as amended, received for final consideration.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.265/1" nospeaker="true" time="17:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400029#DD00100"><p>Question put: "That the Bill do now pass."</p><p>The Seanad divided: T, 26; Nl, 12.</p><p>Tellers: T, Senators Aideen Hayden and Michael Mullins; Nl, Senators David Cullinane and Kathryn Reilly.</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.265/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2013-05-14" time="17:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400029#DD00100">
            <divisioncount ayes="26" noes="12" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" vote="aye">Ivana Bacik</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1121" vote="aye">Paul Bradford</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" vote="aye">Terry Brennan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1114" vote="aye">Deirdre Clune</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" vote="aye">Eamonn Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1124" vote="aye">Michael Comiskey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" vote="aye">Martin Conway</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" vote="aye">Maurice Cummins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" vote="aye">Jim D'Arcy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" vote="aye">John Gilroy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1144" vote="aye">Jimmy Harte</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" vote="aye">Aideen Hayden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" vote="aye">Fidelma Healy Eames</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1173" vote="aye">Lorraine Higgins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" vote="aye">Ca&iacute;t Keane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" vote="aye">John Kelly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1162" vote="aye">Denis Landy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1167" vote="aye">Fiach MacConghail</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" vote="aye">Mary Moran</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" vote="aye">Michael Mullins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" vote="aye">Catherine Noone</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" vote="aye">Marie Louise O'Donnell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" vote="aye">Susan O'Keeffe</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" vote="aye">Pat O'Neill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1163" vote="aye">Tom Shehan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" vote="aye">Jillian van Turnhout</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" vote="no">Sean Barrett</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" vote="no">David Cullinane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" vote="no">Terry Leyden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" vote="no">Marc MacSharry</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" vote="no">Paschal Mooney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" vote="no">R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1142" vote="no">Ned O'Sullivan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" vote="no">Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" vote="no">Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" vote="no">Feargal Quinn</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1155" vote="no">Kathryn Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" vote="no">Jim Walsh</mpname>
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.265/3" nospeaker="true" time="17:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400029#DD00100"><p>Question declared carried.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.266" nospeaker="true" time="17:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400030#FF00100">Adjournment Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.267" nospeaker="true" time="17:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400030#FF00200">Road Maintenance</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.268" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1114" speakername="Deirdre Clune" time="17:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400030#FF00300"><p>I am grateful for the opportunity to raise this issue on the need to address the serious condition of road surfaces in cities, particularly in my native Cork city.  Recently, the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Varadkar, announced the provision of emergency funding for local and regional roads, although not in city areas.  He wrote to 29 local authorities stating that &euro;42 million from the restoration improvement grant could be diverted for emergency repair works on local and regional roads.  I support that decision.  All the roads in the country are in a bad state.  A litany of weather incidents has taken its toll and road surfaces need to be repaired.</p><p>I accept there is little money available and the Minister has always been clear in stating that.  We are aware of the situation.  I am aware from my engagement with local councillors and the city manager in Cork city that funding is not available to address the problems, so the initiative whereby funding can be reallocated from other areas is important and welcome.  My point is that there should be something similar for city areas.  While I accept that cities do not have roads of the same length, those roads carry high intensity traffic which is taking a toll.  It is dangerous for both motorists and cyclists and must be addressed.  The situation cannot continue.  This issue is constantly being raised with me by members of the public and by Cork city councillors who are concerned about it.  Would it be possible to divert a portion of the funding that is currently allocated for worthwhile cycle ways, footpaths, mobility improvement and green routes?  There has been much investment in these facilities in our cities.  This infrastructure is important in urban areas to encourage pedestrians and cyclists and to improve mobility, while taking the emphasis off car transport.</p><p>However, in many cases we have what could be described as white elephants in wonderful developments yet the roads on which people and cyclists are travelling are in very bad repair.  There are large potholes.  The Minister is very well aware of this issue as the photographs go to his Department.  I am anxious to make a strong case for the Cork city area.  I am not asking the Minister to provide new funding but that the local authority be allowed to redirect funding it is spending on new projects to improving the serious condition of road surfaces.  If we do not invest now, we will create further problems for the future.  Unless we address it, what is a substantial pothole filling problem today could require major restoration work in the years to come.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.269" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1074" speakername="Michael Ring" time="17:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400030#FF00400"><p>I am replying on behalf of my colleague, the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Leo Varadkar.  The Minister has responsibility for overall policy and funding relating to the national roads programme.  The planning, design and implementation of individual road projects is a matter for the National Roads Authority, NRA, under the Roads Acts 1993 to 2007 in conjunction with the local authorities concerned.</p><p>Within its capital budget, the assessment and prioritisation of individual projects is a matter in the first instance for the NRA in accordance with section 19 of the Roads Act.  The NRA has a budget of &euro;318 million for improvement and maintenance works on the national roads network in 2013.  The improvement and maintenance of regional and local roads is the statutory responsibility of each local authority, in accordance with the provisions of section 13 of the Roads Act 1993.  Works on those roads are funded from local authorities' own resources supplemented by State road grants paid by the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport.  The initial selection and prioritisation of works to be funded is also a matter for the local authority.</p><p>The Minister, Deputy Varadkar, announced the 2013 regional and local road grant allocations on 25 January last.  A total of &euro;350 million is being provided under the regional and local roads investment programme this year.  From that allocation, Cork County Council is being provided with an allocation of over &euro;40 million and Cork City Council is being provided with over &euro;4.4 million.</p><p>The level of grants allocated to individual local authorities is determined having regard to a number of factors.  These factors include: the total funds available in a particular year; eligibility criteria for the different road grant schemes; road pavement conditions; length of road network; the need to prioritise projects; and competing demands from other local authorities.</p><p>In determining the annual grant allocations, the overall objective remains to supplement the resources provided by each local authority in a fair and appropriate manner.  Ireland has a uniquely extensive road network.  There are approximately 98,000 km of road in the network, which represents two and a half times the EU average in terms of kilometres per head of population.  The maintenance and improvement of this extensive network of roads places a substantial financial burden on local authorities and on the Exchequer.</p><p>With the vast network of roads serving very disparate needs from small farmers to large multinationals, a one-size-fits-all based regional and local roads maintenance regime would not be appropriate.  Decisions should be made locally by local public representatives.  Given the current financial position, the main focus has to be on the maintenance and repair of roads and this will remain the position in the coming years.  There have been very large reductions in roads expenditure over the past number of years and there will be further reductions in the future.  In 2007, there were grants of &euro;2.375 billion available towards national, regional and local roads.  These grants have fallen to &euro;665 million in 2013 and will fall further to &euro;629 million in 2014.  The grants programme is structured to allow councils reasonable flexibility in using grants while also ensuring that there are clear outputs for the moneys allocated in terms of length of road maintained or rehabilitated.</p><p>County councils were provided with additional flexibility this year, enabling them to transfer funding from their restoration improvement grant to their discretionary grant.  In Cork County Council's case, its restoration improvement grant is over &euro;18 million while its discretionary grant is just over &euro;7 million, or 17.9% of it total allocation.  When one compares this to Cork City Council, whose discretionary block grant of &euro;2.8 million accounts for 63% of its total allocation, one can see that the city council already has a greater degree of flexibility in deciding where to spend this grant funding.  It is also important to reiterate that the role of Exchequer grants for regional and local roads is to supplement councils such as Cork county and city councils in their spending in this area.  The reality is that the available funds do not match the amount of work required.  My Department and local authorities are working closely to develop new, more efficient ways of delivering the best outputs possible with the funding available to them.  Given the likely continued squeeze on Exchequer funding this concentration on efficiency is essential to achieve the best outturns for the limited money available.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.270" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1114" speakername="Deirdre Clune" time="17:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400031#GG00100"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his reply.  I agree that the main focus must be on the maintenance and repair of roads.  I urge him to ensure local authorities enforce this priority because, unfortunately, from what I am hearing from members of the public, it is not yet happening.  A failure to invest now in maintenance and repairs will mean greater costs in the future.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.271" nospeaker="true" time="17:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400031#GG00200">School Transport Provision</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.272" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="17:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400031#GG00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State, Deputy Ciar&aacute;n Cannon, for coming to the Chamber to deal with this matter.  </p><p>Ardvarney national school in north Leitrim has 41 pupils, 28 of whom avail of school transport.  Of these 28, 14 are deemed by the Department of Education and Skills and Bus &Eacute;ireann to be eligible for free school transport, with the remainder availing of the concessionary scheme.  I was recently made aware that, from September, the school was at risk of losing one of the two school buses which served these pupils.  The school made this discovery by chance and it was even suggested the news was not to be broken until the summer holiday, when it would be more difficult to harness community assistance to lobby for a reversal of the decision.</p><p>The 2013-14 enrolment for Ardvarney national school is up to 43, with the numbers projected to avail of the school transport service expected to remain more or less the same.  Several of the pupils availing of the concessionary arrangement were deemed ineligible by Bus &Eacute;ireann for the free scheme because of their proximity to another school which was not only outside the parish but also the diocese.  The fact remains that these students are living within the traditional and ongoing catchment area for Ardvarney national school.  While some of them do live closer to another school, they have chosen to attend Ardvarney national school because it is their parish school, which is perfectly understandable.</p><p>The changes proposed in 2011 in terms of eligibility, requiring a minimum of ten eligible students instead of seven, have led to a situation where one of the two school buses serving the school will be withdrawn in September.  The Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy Ruair&iacute; Quinn, is constantly referring to the viability of smaller schools.  Ardvarney national school, with 41 children, has doubled its enrolment in the past five years.  In fact, enrolment projections based on an assessment of families living in the area suggest the number of children eligible for the free scheme will increase to 16 in the next few years, which means that a single 14 seater bus would no longer be sufficient.  There is also a suggestion Bus &Eacute;ireann has adjusted the catchment area for the school such that children living in the Killavoggy end of the parish will not be deemed eligible, yet without being advised of anything to the contrary, children from that townland have enrolled in the school in recent years and been deemed eligible under the transport scheme.  That does not seem to make sense.</p><p>While we all accept the need to have criteria in place to determine eligibility for school transport, there is surely nothing in the spirit of these provisions which seeks to threaten the very viability of a school that has doubled its enrolment in recent years.  The proposed curtailment of the service to pupils of Ardvarney national school will unnecessarily divide and decimate a community which has many generations of history.  There are not too many rural schools that have doubled their enrolment in such a short timeframe.  Will the Minister of State undertake to intervene personally in the matter?  I am aware that he is inundated with requests of this nature during Adjournment debates in both Houses, but I contend none is more worthy than this.  The proposal would immediately impact on 30% of the enrolment of the school.  One of the most frustrating issues for those of us seeking a solution to the matter is that Bus &Eacute;ireann is directing us to the Department, while the Department is telling us it is a matter for Bus &Eacute;ireann.  In the meantime, the future of a viable school is threatened.  The Minister of State has the power to ensure the spirit of the Department's criteria is fulfilled in this case rather than eliminating a school that is not only viable but also central to its community.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.273" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1042" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Cannon" time="17:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400031#GG00400"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this matter.  I will begin by offering Members an outline of the extent of the school transport service.  School transport is a very significant operation managed by Bus &Eacute;ireann on my Department's behalf and covering more than 82 million km annually.  In the region of 115,000 children, including more than 8,000 with special needs, are transported in approximately 4,000 vehicles on a daily basis to primary and post-primary schools throughout the country.  Catchment areas are no longer a feature of the primary school transport scheme.  At primary level, children are eligible for transport to a particular school where they reside not less than 3.2 km from it and where it is determined to be their nearest national school, having regard to ethos and language.  Bus &Eacute;ireann is responsible for the planning and scheduling of school transport routes and services.  The company endeavours, within available resources, to ensure each eligible child has a reasonable level of school transport service in the context of the scheme nationally.</p><p>In regard to the case raised by the Senator, Bus &Eacute;ireann has advised that two services are operating to Ardvarney national school for the 2012-13 school year.  These services accommodate a total of 13 children who are eligible for school transport, the remaining seats being allocated to children who are not eligible but are availing of the service on a concessionary basis.  The closing date for receipt of school transport applications for the 2013-14 school year was 26 April.  The Senator will appreciate that decisions regarding the retention or establishment of transport services for the next school year will be made by Bus &Eacute;ireann only after all applications have been received and assessed.  The retention or establishment of services is determined, in the first instance, by the number and location of children who meet the eligibility criteria.  The terms of the schemes are applied equitably on a national basis.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.274" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="17:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400031#GG00500"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his response, but it is entirely unsatisfactory.  It is an abdication of responsibility to claim this is a matter for Bus &Eacute;ireann.  The fact is that the spirit of the legislation and the Department's own criteria are not being followed in this case.  Going around the country engaging in a literal interpretation of every rule will mean rural communities are unnecessarily decimated.  Surely common sense and scheduling can achieve the required savings, while also ensuring rural communities are not further damaged because of a shortage of school transport, as they have been by the closure of Garda stations and countless other cutbacks in recent years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.275" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="17:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400031#GG00600"><p>I am sure the Minister of State has taken the Senator's point on board.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.276" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1042" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Cannon" time="17:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400031#GG00700"><p>I am far from abdicating my responsibility in this area.  On the contrary, I am honouring my responsibility to ensure scarce national resources are used in the most efficient way possible.  I remind the Senator that these decisions emanated from a value for money report initiated by a former colleague of his who rightly sought a forensic assessment of the costs associated with school transport.  Several of the conclusions emanating from that analysis were put into place in 2011, including the requirement that children should be eligible for transportation to their nearest school only.  That is a fair, logical and economically sound principle which is being adhered to equitably on a national basis.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.277" nospeaker="true" time="17:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400031#GG00800">Schools Recognition</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.278" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="17:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400031#GG00900"><p>This is the second time in the past 12 months that I have raised this issue on the Adjournment.  I am frequently approached by teachers and parents frustrated by the failure of the Department to grant permanent recognition to Mol an &Oacute;ige national school in Ennistymon, County Clare.</p> <p>The school has been in existence for a number of years and its population is well in excess of 100.  According to the latest figures, some 126 children are enrolled in the school, which probably makes it one of the biggest schools of this type in the country.  The teaching quality at the school is of a very high standard.  Teaching quality throughout County Clare is of a very high standard.</p><p>Many parents are choosing to bring their children to Mol an &Oacute;ige national school which has received temporary recognition and I have no reason to believe it will not continue to receive such recognition.  However, the parents want permanent recognition for a number of reasons, the overriding reason being that they want to send their children to a school that is recognised by the State.  Temporary recognition is far from permanent recognition and I would like the Minister of State to outline the criteria used in seeking and granting permanent recognition.  At what stage of the process is Mol an &Oacute;ige national school at?  Is it on the radar?  Within what timeframe can the parents of the children attending the school realistically expect permanent recognition to be granted?  Is there a reason such recognition is not being granted?  Perhaps some personnel within the Department are in favour of an ethos that differs from the teaching principles used in the school.  These principles are mainstream, in effect.  It is unfair that some children have almost gone through the entire primary school cycle - I have mentioned that the school has been in existence for a number of years - while the school has continued to operate on the basis of temporary recognition.  Given that it has gone through the process mentioned and that the parents and teachers have put a serious effort into meeting all the criteria required for permanent recognition, perhaps it is time for the Department to meet them more than halfway.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.280" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1042" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Cannon" time="17:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400032#HH00200"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this matter and giving me an opportunity to outline the current position on the recognition status of Mol an &Oacute;ige national school in Ennistymon, County Clare.  The school in question which implements the Steiner approach to education was initially awarded provisional recognition in 2008.  This was extended each year until October 2012 when a three year extension was granted.  The current position is that the school has provisional recognition until 31 August 2015.  This extension is designed to give the school a sufficient opportunity to satisfactorily meet the criteria for recognition agreed in 2008.  The extension will not prevent the school from receiving permanent recognition in the interim if the criteria for recognition are met.  As the Senator is aware, all recognised schools, regardless of their philosophy or ethos, are required to comply with the Education Act 1998 and the rules for national schools.  Specific criteria relating to patronage, the board of management, implementation of the curriculum, admissions policy and procedures for the appointment of teaching staff must also be satisfied by schools seeking permanent recognition.  Such recognition is contingent on schools demonstrating they meet these requirements satisfactorily.</p><p>A process is under way with regard to the request for permanent recognition from the school.  This process is based on its progress in fulfilling ten undertakings committed to by its patron in 2008.  These undertakings were based on requirements outlined in the Education Act 1998, the rules for national schools which all recognised schools must meet and the aforementioned criteria which all schools applying for permanent recognition must satisfy.  One of the undertakings is that the school will follow the primary school curriculum.  It is important to note that the decision on full recognition depends on the satisfactory implementation of all the undertakings.  Officials from the Department met the school authorities last October to discuss the current position on the undertakings and the school's application for permanent recognition.  I understand substantial progress has been made.  However, significant issues remain to be resolved, particularly in respect of curricular provision for pupils in infant classes.  I understand the Department and the school have committed to ongoing engagement with the objective of enabling the school to meet the permanent recognition criteria as soon as possible.</p><p>If a school is to be considered for permanent recognition, it must make an application stating it has met the criteria for recognition of new primary schools, which include the requirements to follow the 1999 primary school curriculum, comply with the rules for national schools and demonstrate that enrolments are sufficient for the long-term viability of the school.  The enrolment requirement is usually but not always confined to a period of three years.  The Department has granted permanent recognition to 45 schools since 2008, the majority of which are in developing school areas.  The recognition process for each of the schools was undertaken on a case by case basis and varied in duration for that reason.  All of the 45 schools granted permanent recognition met all of the criteria satisfactorily.  A number of schools granted provisional recognition prior to 2008 are still awaiting permanent recognition, as they do not meet all of the criteria required to be met.  </p><p>I again thank the Senator for giving me an opportunity to outline the position on the application for permanent recognition from Mol an &Oacute;ige national school.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.281" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="17:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400032#HH00300"><p>The board of management and, in particular, the parents who participate actively in the running and development of the school have convinced me that they have met all of the criteria.  They are concerned that permanent recognition continues to be an issue.  I ask the Minister of State to check the matter again because I understand the delay is being caused by a specific issue.  While I do not expect him to do that today, perhaps he might do so when he returns to the Department of Education and Skills tomorrow.  My understanding is that it is a question of a specific mannerism associated with the teaching methodology being used to teach a particular element of one subject.  This issue should be resolved well in advance of the end of the current three year period for the sake of everyone involved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.282" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1042" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Cannon" time="17:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400032#HH00400"><p>The Department has been very proactive in trying to address the question of the permanent recognition of the school and its door is always open.  It is willing to collaborate with the school to achieve that recognition.  As the Senator has mentioned and I pointed out in my initial response, there are certain issues relating to the delivery of the curriculum in the school's junior classes.  If the school and the Department were to collectively focus on how these challenges can be overcome, we could move towards a point where recognition could be achieved soon.  If these issues can be addressed, recognition can be achieved in the very near future.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.283" nospeaker="true" time="17:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400032#HH00500">Special Educational Needs</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.284" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="17:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400032#HH00600"><p>The issue I am raising on the Adjournment relates to an anomaly in the allocation of educational resource hours to children with Down's syndrome who attend mainstream primary schools.  Down's syndrome is a chromosomal anomaly which causes a global development delay.  Approximately 80 children with this syndrome are enrolled in mainstream primary schools each year and the syndrome is not currently listed by the Department of Education and Skills as a complex low-incidence disorder.  This means that some children with Down's syndrome are not entitled to resource hours.  It is estimated that approximately 40% of children in the State who have Down's syndrome do not receive an allocation of resource hours.  Some 82 children in County Donegal with Down's syndrome do not receive resource hours in mainstream primary schools, which is wholly inappropriate, as it is creating an inequality in the education system.  It discriminates against children with Down's syndrome.</p><p>As I understand it, the Department's special education circular, 02/05, provides that a child with Down's syndrome must have a second disability in order to access vital resource hours.  I have a copy of the circular with me in the Chamber.  I am calling for Down's syndrome to be recognised in its own right by the Department.  Children with Down's syndrome cannot and should not be categorised as having mild or moderate learning disabilities.  Such a categorisation does not reflect all of the aspects of the syndrome generically.</p> <p> Education policy in Ireland places children with Down's syndrome at a disadvantage or in an unfair position by not supporting their full educational development to the degree that other people with disabilities are supported in the system.  The children concerned deserve every opportunity to reach their full potential.  They deserve to be treated in a manner which encompasses the word "equality" and allows them to be cherished equally within the education system.  They deserve to be allowed to advance their educational opportunities.  This is obviously an issue that needs to be addressed.  We are talking about a small number of pupils within the State and we are doing them a great disservice by not allowing Down's syndrome to be regarded as a full-scale disability and not allowing the children concerned to develop to their full potential.  I hope the Minister of State will take this on board.  I know Down Syndrome Ireland has been lobbying to have this anomaly corrected and hope the Minister of State and the Minister will be in a position to deal with this issue and put matters right as quickly as possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.286" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1042" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Cannon" time="17:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400033#JJ00200"><p>I am pleased to be given the opportunity by the Senator to clarify the position on the provision of teaching support tor children with Down's syndrome.  The position is that pupils with Down's syndrome who are attending mainstream primary schools may receive additional teaching support in primary schools, either under the terms of the general allocation model of teaching supports, if the pupil's educational psychological assessment places the pupil in the mild general learning disability or high incidence disability category, or through an allocation of individual additional resource teaching hours which are allocated to schools by the National Council for Special Education, NCSE, if the child is assessed as being within the low incidence category of special need, as defined by my Department's circular, Special Education 02/05.  Pupils with Down's syndrome who are assessed as being within the category of mild general learning disability but who also have an additional assessment of another low incidence disability such as hearing impairment will also be supported by an additional allocation made by the NCSE.  Resource teaching provision is, therefore, made for children with Down's syndrome in the same manner as for other children with assessed syndromes and in accordance with the policy of my Department set out in Circular 02/05.  It should be noted that, whether resource teaching hours are allocated to schools under the general allocation model or through an allocation made by the NCSE based on individual low incidence special needs, it is ultimately a matter for schools to utilise and manage these resources to best provide for the teaching needs of qualifying children.  Each school will use its professional judgement to decide how the provision of additional resource teaching time and hours is made for the qualifying pupils in the school to ensure all of their individual needs are met.  Additional teaching time may be provided for pupils on an individual basis or in pairs or small groups.  It may also be provided in the classroom through team teaching or withdrawal to a resource teaching room.  Guidance for schools on the management of their resource teaching allocations is provided in the circular, Special Education 02/05.</p><p>I advise the Senator that the NCSE which has a formal role under section 20 of the Education for Persons with Special Educational Needs Act 2004 to advise the Minister for Education and Skills on any matter relating to the education of children and others with disabilities has been asked to provide policy advice on the issue of whether Down's syndrome should be reclassified as a low incidence disability in all instances, regardless of assessed cognitive ability.  This advice will be included in the NCSE's policy advice on how the education system can best support children with special educational needs which will be presented to the Minister shortly.  As I am not in a position to pre-empt this expert policy advice, we must await the advice received from the body with the greatest expertise in this area.  I can assure the Senator, however, that the Government is very conscious that meeting students' educational needs in an equitable manner is the paramount consideration which must be kept at the centre of proposals and recommendations.  The position of all children with assessed syndromes and special educational needs must be considered in any review of policy.  The Minister will give full consideration to this matter once the policy advice has been received.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.287" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="17:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400033#JJ00300"><p>I appreciate the Minister of State's response.  He has noted that the matter is being looked at and I agree with him that we cannot pre-empt that consideration.  However, taking on board the campaign being launched by Down Syndrome Ireland and given that I am not sure whether the Minister, Deputy Quinn, or the Minister of State has met Down Syndrome Ireland, I urge that its views be taken into consideration before a decision is taken and that a meeting be scheduled with its CEO to discuss the outcome of the NCSE's policy report.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.288" nospeaker="true" time="17:45:00" ><p>The Seanad adjourned at 5.35 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Wednesday, 15 May 2013.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.289" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="17:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400034#JJ00100"><p>  Education policy in Ireland places children with Down's syndrome at a disadvantage or in an unfair position by not supporting their full educational development to the degree that other people with disabilities are supported in the system.  The children concerned deserve every opportunity to reach their full potential.  They deserve to be treated in a manner which encompasses the word "equality" and allows them to be cherished equally within the education system.  They deserve to be allowed to advance their educational opportunities.  This is obviously an issue that needs to be addressed.  We are talking about a small number of pupils within the State and we are doing them a great disservice by not allowing Down's syndrome to be regarded as a full-scale disability and not allowing the children concerned to develop to their full potential.  I hope the Minister of State will take this on board.  I know Down Syndrome Ireland has been lobbying to have this anomaly corrected and hope the Minister of State and the Minister will be in a position to deal with this issue and put matters right as quickly as possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.290" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1042" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Cannon" time="17:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400034#JJ00200"><p>I am pleased to be given the opportunity by the Senator to clarify the position on the provision of teaching support tor children with Down's syndrome.  The position is that pupils with Down's syndrome who are attending mainstream primary schools may receive additional teaching support in primary schools, either under the terms of the general allocation model of teaching supports, if the pupil's educational psychological assessment places the pupil in the mild general learning disability or high incidence disability category, or through an allocation of individual additional resource teaching hours which are allocated to schools by the National Council for Special Education, NCSE, if the child is assessed as being within the low incidence category of special need, as defined by my Department's circular, Special Education 02/05.  Pupils with Down's syndrome who are assessed as being within the category of mild general learning disability but who also have an additional assessment of another low incidence disability such as hearing impairment will also be supported by an additional allocation made by the NCSE.  Resource teaching provision is, therefore, made for children with Down's syndrome in the same manner as for other children with assessed syndromes and in accordance with the policy of my Department set out in Circular 02/05.  It should be noted that, whether resource teaching hours are allocated to schools under the general allocation model or through an allocation made by the NCSE based on individual low incidence special needs, it is ultimately a matter for schools to utilise and manage these resources to best provide for the teaching needs of qualifying children.  Each school will use its professional judgement to decide how the provision of additional resource teaching time and hours is made for the qualifying pupils in the school to ensure all of their individual needs are met.  Additional teaching time may be provided for pupils on an individual basis or in pairs or small groups.  It may also be provided in the classroom through team teaching or withdrawal to a resource teaching room.  Guidance for schools on the management of their resource teaching allocations is provided in the circular, Special Education 02/05.</p><p>I advise the Senator that the NCSE which has a formal role under section 20 of the Education for Persons with Special Educational Needs Act 2004 to advise the Minister for Education and Skills on any matter relating to the education of children and others with disabilities has been asked to provide policy advice on the issue of whether Down's syndrome should be reclassified as a low incidence disability in all instances, regardless of assessed cognitive ability.  This advice will be included in the NCSE's policy advice on how the education system can best support children with special educational needs which will be presented to the Minister shortly.  As I am not in a position to pre-empt this expert policy advice, we must await the advice received from the body with the greatest expertise in this area.  I can assure the Senator, however, that the Government is very conscious that meeting students' educational needs in an equitable manner is the paramount consideration which must be kept at the centre of proposals and recommendations.  The position of all children with assessed syndromes and special educational needs must be considered in any review of policy.  The Minister will give full consideration to this matter once the policy advice has been received.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.291" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="17:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013051400034#JJ00300"><p>I appreciate the Minister of State's response.  He has noted that the matter is being looked at and I agree with him that we cannot pre-empt that consideration.  However, taking on board the campaign being launched by Down Syndrome Ireland and given that I am not sure whether the Minister, Deputy Quinn, or the Minister of State has met Down Syndrome Ireland, I urge that its views be taken into consideration before a decision is taken and that a meeting be scheduled with its CEO to discuss the outcome of the NCSE's policy report.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-05-14a.292" nospeaker="true" time="17:55:00" ><p>The Seanad adjourned at 5.35 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Wednesday, 15 May 2013.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>