<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.4" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to address the issue of lengthy waiting times for methadone maintenance programmes and the number cap that is imposed on certain clinics that is restricting their capacity to service the needs of their patients.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Tim Lombard of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Housing, Planning, Community and Local Government to create specific national guidelines pertaining to solar farms to help local authorities deal consistently with applications.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Gerard P. Craughwell of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport to outline his plans for the regulation of scrambler bikes, which currently are being driven by underage, uninsured drivers on roads, footpaths and green areas, posing a real risk to lives and constituting serious anti-social behaviour.</blockquote> <p>I regard the matters raised by the Senators as suitable for discussion.  I have selected the matters raised by Senators &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in and Craughwell and they will be taken now.  Senator Lombard has withdrawn his Commencement matter which I had selected.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.7" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#A00300">Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.8" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#A00400">Drug Treatment Programmes Availability</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#A00500"><p>I welcome the Minister of State.  As part of my responsibilities when I was Minister of State with responsibility for the national drugs strategy, I took the opportunity to visit as many clinics and speak to as many service operators and service users as I could.  Last year, I visited a clinic on Granby Row off Dorset Street where I met a wonderful woman who was travelling from the midlands to Dublin every day to access her methadone.  She was a young mother getting her life back together.  She took a bus from Portlaoise to the national drug treatment centre in Trinity Court and back every day because she was told she would have had to wait six months for treatment where she lived.  Three weeks ago, she died of an overdose.  I am told that those who have come to a stage in their lives with their addictions when they realise they cannot go on and ask for help are told they have to wait between six months and two years to get on a methadone maintenance programme.  There is a cap on the number of clients certain clinics can help.</p> <p>I appreciate the efforts of the Minister of State, Deputy Catherine Byrne in this regard.  I have observed her work at first hand and listened to a number of her speeches.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2301"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2301&amp;amp;pid=AodhanORiordan&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I was at an event a few mornings ago at which she gave an incredibly impassioned speech about our responsibility to treat those who are vulnerable due to their addictions with the most compassion possible.  I believe she is doing a sound job and I support her in everything she is doing.  However, what is the Department's and the Government's response on how to shorten the waiting time to access this essential treatment programme?  Also, what can we do to ensure that clinics such as the one on Granby Row have the capacity to deal with all those who require their services?  Obviously, we must address the long waiting times, but having caps on the numbers of patients clinics can deal with does not stand up to scrutiny.</p><p>This is a life or death issue.  I am advocating for people who are often not well thought of or well regarded in our society.  I was incredibly struck when I heard the news last week that the beautiful person I had met, who was getting her life together and doing her best to overcome her addiction by travelling from Portlaoise to Dublin every day to make her and her child's life better, had succumbed to her addiction three weeks ago and died on the street of an overdose.  We could save lives by changing or re-evaluating how we are doing things.  The people on the front line simply wish to be given the tools to do their work better.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1277" speakername="David Stanton" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#B00200"><p>On behalf of the Minister of State at the Department of Health, Deputy Catherine Byrne, I am pleased to address the Seanad on the subject of methadone maintenance treatment.  I acknowledge the work Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in did when he was Minister of State and his continued genuine and passionate interest in this area.  I also acknowledge his support for the Minister of State, Deputy Byrne.  She regrets that she cannot be present as she is attending a meeting of the Joint Committee on Health.  I will convey the Senator's comments to her.</p> <p>Government policy on the drugs issue is set out in the National Drugs Strategy 2009-2016.  The overall objective of the strategy is to tackle the harm caused to individuals and society by the misuse of drugs.  The strategy emphasises the need to provide opportunities for people to move on from illicit drug use to a drug-free life where that is achievable.  Methadone maintenance treatment is a critical stabilising treatment that enables the people concerned to counter their problem drug use and to rebuild their lives.  In conjunction with other services and supports, such as counselling, after-care and training, methadone maintenance treatment provides a pathway to recovery for the individual affected by problem substance use.  However, different people in various circumstances may require different approaches to treatment and support.</p> <p>There are currently over 10,000 people availing of methadone treatment.  The Health Service Executive, HSE, has advised that the number of individuals awaiting treatment has significantly reduced in recent years.  At the end of March 2016, a total of 163 people were waiting on opioid substitution treatment.  This compares with 445 in July 2010, a reduction of over 63%.  This is against a background of increasing numbers in methadone treatment.</p> <p>Historically, the development of the addiction service was made possible through consultation and partnership with local communities.  This has meant that services were established within particular geographical areas, with the agreement of the local community, that would provide a service specifically to people from that area.  The effect of this type of agreement is that it has enabled the HSE to develop methadone services in some areas which may not have had such services previously.  However, they were restricted in some instances to providing a service solely to residents from within that area.  This approach has made it difficult to develop services that respond to individuals with particular needs, such as people who are homeless, since they do not belong to a specific geographical location.</p> <p>As the Senator will be aware, the Department of Health is currently developing a new strategy, which the Minister of State hopes will be completed in early 2017.  One of the key issues being examined as part of the process is how to improve access to treatment for people affected by problem substance use.  A number of issues have been raised in the course of this process, including the difficulty of attracting general practitioners, GPs, to participate in the methadone programme.  The slow rate of transfer of patients from the clinics to the primary care setting and from level-two GPs to level-one GPs is also an issue affecting progression rates.  The Minister of State is hopeful that solutions will emerge to these issues in the context of the new strategic action plan to tackle the drugs problem.</p> <p>I am sorry to hear the person the Senator was acquainted with has passed away in those circumstances.  I extend our condolences.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#B00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State, Deputy Stanton.  I appreciate that the Minister of State, Deputy Byrne, is obliged to attend a meeting of the health committee.  Perhaps the Minister of State would convey to her the seriousness of the situation.  I accept that she is aware of it, but perhaps a meeting with the senior team in Granby Row would be of benefit simply to have a first-hand conversation on the pressures the team is under and the solutions it is offering.</p> <p>I met with the Minister of State, Deputy Byrne, after she was appointed and I suggested a number of places that she should visit.  She has done that.  I am particularly impressed by the compassion she has brought to this brief.  Statistics on a page are one thing but the problem with this issue is that those who are afflicted with addiction, particularly heroin addiction, are constantly undermined in the public perception because of their portrayal in the media.  When one meets somebody who is getting her life together and who symbolises in one's mind how the system can work and then one hears less than a year later that the person has succumbed to her addiction and one tries to square that with the reality of her life travelling from Portlaoise to Dublin every day, one must only come to the conclusion that the reason this continues is that, at some level, public policy demands that this person be ashamed of the reasons they are ill.  There is an element of victim blaming in that regard.  I realise the Minister is trying to change this and that she feels passionately about it, but perhaps the Minister of State, Deputy Stanton, would convey to her an invitation to meet with the senior team in Granby Row.  It would be an attempt to understand better the realities that people are dealing with on the front line.</p> <p>The issue of the cap was not mentioned in the Minister's response.  The statistics that were outlined would suggest that things are getting better.  Regardless of whether that is true, people are being told it could take two years to get onto a methadone maintenance programme.  I believe that is being said to give people the impression that this will not happen overnight, but two years is an awfully long time.  Six months is also a long time.  For some people the prospect of waiting six months is too long.  We are losing people in that gap.  I ask the Minister to convey to the Minister of State, Deputy Byrne, the invitation to meet the senior management team in the clinic.  Perhaps we can then move to a situation where fewer lives are being lost unnecessarily.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1277" speakername="David Stanton" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#B00400"><p>I certainly will convey the Senator's comments to the Minister.  As the Senator said, she is deeply committed to, and passionate about, this area.  She wants to make a difference and is working hard on that, following the work the Senator did in a similar capacity in the last Government.  I also note his point with respect to the public perception and the fact that addiction is an illness and should be treated as such, rather than as a crime.  That is something which, in other work we have done together previously, we have acknowledged and recognised.</p> <p>I thank the Senator for bringing this important and serious matter to our attention today.  Some questions were unanswered, unfortunately, but I will bring them to the Minister's attention.  In addition, if other issues require further clarification, I will ask that it be provided.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.14" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#B00450">Road Safety</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#B00500"><p>I thank the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport for coming to the House this morning.  The issue I wish to discuss covers two parts of the Minister's portfolio, sport and transport.  The Minister is not the type of man who would wish to have any form of nanny state to over-regulate the sporting side of our lives.  Both of us would agree that all sports should be allowed to take place, provided they do so in a correct and safe environment.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Gerard P. Craughwell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2402"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2402&amp;amp;pid=GerardPCraughwell&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The problem that has been brought to my attention relates to the use or misuse of scrambler motorcycles and quad bikes.  I was quite shocked to learn that children as young as eight years of age are being given motorcycles of 50 cc and upwards which are essentially designed for use as off-road vehicles.  Children are using these bikes and quads on main public highways and around housing estates.  When I researched this matter, I learned that the Enniskerry Woods area and some of the public pathways in Enniskerry are being recommended as places where children can learn to use quad bikes as long as they are aware of the presence of pedestrians.  It is clear that this is not a safe environment for kids to be using these vehicles.  I have also found that these bikes are being used on main roads in places like Tallaght and Finglas.</p><p>As these bikes have no registration, no tax and no insurance, a garda who sees one of them on the road has no way of identifying the owner.  If one of these vehicles runs into a bus or a car, the likelihood is that the person driving the vehicle will be killed and, more importantly, will cause risk to the life and limb of others.  One can imagine what would happen if a Garda car or motorcycle pursued an eight year old kid driving one of these vehicles through an estate.  If the child was injured, the Garda would come under immediate scrutiny from the general public, which would want to know why the child was chased.  Although this is not a huge problem, it is a serious one.  These things are typically allowed to run.  I accept that this did not start on the Minister's watch.  It has been going on for a long time.  I have been asked by local authority members to call on the Minister to introduce some form of regulation to control how these bikes are being used and to provide for some form of recognition of who owns them and where they belong.  Some form of identification mark would allow us to track down the users of these vehicles.  We need to provide for some means of ensuring they are not used on the road.  If they are used on the road, the full rigours of the law should apply.  I thank the Minister for coming to the Seanad to listen to what I have to say on this issue.  I look forward to his response.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#C00200"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this matter with me.  He is not the only person who has done so.  Many local county councillors have also raised it.  The chair of South Dublin County Council's joint policing committee, Councillor Deirdre O'Donovan, was in touch with me about this issue yesterday.  I know the Senator will be familiar with Councillor O'Donovan.  This is a matter of great concern for many local authority members.  I understand and sympathise with those who are concerned about this issue.  It might be helpful if I begin by clarifying the current legal position on the regulation of scrambler bikes under road traffic legislation.  Then I will deal with the specific issues raised by Senator Craughwell.  As a scrambler is a mechanically propelled vehicle, which is defined as "a vehicle intended or adapted for propulsion by mechanical means", road traffic legislation provides that regardless of engine capacity, the user of a scrambler motorbike in a public place is legally bound to have insurance, road tax and a driving licence and to wear a helmet.  If he or she does not comply with these requirements, the road traffic laws provide for severe penalties including fixed charge notices, penalty points, fines and the possible seizure of the vehicle.  Notwithstanding what I have just said, I am aware that many people using scrambler bikes do not comply with the regulations, as the Senator has said.</p> <p>For the purposes of the Road Traffic Acts, a "public place" means "any street, road or other place to which the public have access with vehicles whether as of right or by permission and whether subject to or free of charge".  Road traffic law does not extend to the use of mechanically propelled vehicles on private property.  Certain places, such as parks under the control of local authorities, can be subject to by-laws prohibiting the use of these vehicles.  Local authorities have the power to introduce such by-laws.  Some scrambler motorbikes do not comply with the requirements of the Road Traffic (Construction, Equipment and Use of Vehicles) Regulations 1963 to 2002 and the Road Traffic (Lighting of Vehicles) Regulations 1963 to 1996.  These regulations prescribe standards in relation to essential matters such as brakes, steering, mirrors, safety glass, wipers, headlamps, rear lighting, indicators and reflectors.  Such vehicles are not, therefore, considered suitable for use in a public place.  The Road Traffic Act 2004 makes it an offence to supply a mechanically propelled vehicle to a person under 16 years of age.  With effect from 24 January 2005, a person convicted of supplying a vehicle to a minor faces a fine of up to &euro;5,000 or a term of imprisonment of up to six months, or both.  Mini-motorised scooters, micro-motorcydes and quadricycles also come within the definition of a mechanically propelled vehicle for road traffic law purposes.  The supply of such vehicles includes giving a gift or loan.  As a result, it is illegal to supply such a vehicle to a person under 16 years of age.</p> <p>The enforcement of road traffic laws is a matter for An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, which is satisfied that it has the necessary powers under the Road Traffic Acts to deal with cases of the use of scrambler motorbikes and similar vehicles in public places.  It should be noted that the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na does not have any legislative powers to deal with scrambler bikes being driven on private lands.  Local authorities have the power to introduce by-laws to prohibit the use of vehicles in areas under their control, such as parks.  The Minister for Arts, Heritage, Regional, Rural and Gaeltacht Affairs has similar powers to control off-road vehicles in certain areas.  For example, the unauthorised use of off-road vehicles is prohibited in certain national parks.  Section 41 of the Road Traffic Act 1994 and the Road Traffic Act (Section 41) Regulations 1995 provide for three grounds for the detention of a vehicle by An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na in a public place.  A vehicle may be detained if the person driving the vehicle refuses or fails to produce there and then a driving licence then having effect and licensing him or her to drive the vehicle and the Garda is of the opinion that the person by reason of his or her age is ineligible to drive the vehicle; if the vehicle is registered in the State and the Garda reasonably believes a policy of insurance is not in place for the vehicle; or if the vehicle is registered in the State and motor tax has not been paid in respect of a continuous period of three months or more immediately prior to use.  An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na can also use section 20 of the Road Traffic Act 1961 to perform an examination of roadworthiness of any vehicle being used in a public place.  An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na has indicated to me that it is satisfied with the powers it has to deal with the use of scrambler motorbikes by under age and uninsured drivers in public areas.  Following the representations from Senator Craughwell and others, I will discuss this matter with my colleague, the Minister for Justice and Equality, to see whether any legislative amendments are needed to deal with the specific issues they have raised.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#C00300"><p>I thank the Minister for the comprehensive answer.  Perhaps his Department will consider notifying the retailers of these bikes that they are required to advise a customer who is purchasing one of them for someone under the age of 16 that he or she is breaking the law.  I will conclude by asking the Minister a question.  I do not expect him to answer it today.  Will he ask his officials to consider the introduction of some form of registration identity mark on off-road bikes that do not need to comply with on-road legislation so that the owner of such a bike can be recognised and tracked down?  I ask the Minister to consider such a measure, as it would allow garda&iacute; to investigate the misuse of a bike by taking the registration number and subsequently contacting the owner and bringing charges if necessary, rather than having to physically chase after the user of the bike.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#C00400"><p>The answer to the Senator's question is "Yes".</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.20" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 11 a.m. and resumed at 11.30 a.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.21" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#G00100">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#G00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, motion re the visit of the First Minister of Scotland to Seanad &Eacute;ireann, to be taken on conclusion of the Order of Business, without debate; No. 2, National Tourism Development Authority (Amendment) Bill 2015 - all Stages to be taken at 12.45 p.m. and to conclude no later than 2.15 p.m., with the contributions of group spokespersons on the debate on Second Stage not to exceed six minutes, those of all other Senators not to exceed four minutes and the Minister to be given four minutes to reply, and Committee and Remaining Stages to be taken immediately thereafter; and No. 3, Competition (Amendment) Bill 2016 - Report and Final Stages, to be taken at 2.15 p.m. and to conclude no later than 3.30 p.m., if not previously concluded.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#G00300"><p>On behalf of my party, I wish to ask about the serious inequality with respect to the ordinary five-eights in Ireland, middle Ireland, the coping classes, the squeezed middle.  This caring Government which claims to have prioritised social reform has done anything but that - it has bared its teeth on middle class Ireland.  No longer can a garda or a teacher marry a bank clerk or a Dunnes Stores' worker and hope to settle down and raise a family.  The moral fabric and generational right of the middle class is being unspun by a Government that cares only for big business, large enterprise and banking fat cats.  The Government will quip about what it inherited two elections ago but with some will and a little vision middle Ireland, which it has sucked dry and left lifeless, could have hope.  Get the councils off their backsides to service the sites they have in land banks and sell them on to first-time buyers at cost price.  Middle Ireland will do the rest.  They will beg, borrow and help each other to build and get our country moving again.  Where there is only despair, let there be hope.   Come on, Taoiseach, give the coping classes a break.  Help them to help themselves.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1428" speakername="Joan Freeman" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#G00400"><p>I would like to move a motion calling on the Acting Leader to invite the Minister for Health to come into the Seanad to enable us ask him two important questions.  The first is why is there such dishonesty and lack of transparency over what moneys have been allocated to mental health services?  We were told &euro;35 million would be allocated but only &euro;15 million will be allocated for 2017.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#G00500"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1428" speakername="Joan Freeman" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#G00600"><p>Why is there such dishonesty about that?  Second, why is it that a month after the budget was announced we still do not know how and into what areas this money will be allocated?  Why is it that only the mental health services receive this treatment?  It makes me wonder whether it is because having this lack of transparency means the Government can move the money around when it suits it to whatever Department suits it instead of it being honest about where this money should be going.  I call on the Acting Leader to invite the Minister for Health to attend here at his earliest convenience.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#G00700"><p>Did I just hear right?  Was Fianna F&aacute;il giving out about banking fat cats?  Seriously.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#G00800"><p>The Senator heard it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#G00900"><p>That is a strange one.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#G01000"><p>Eight years ago when we were in power-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#G01100"><p>One speaker only, and I ask the Senator Gavan to address his comments through the Chair.  It is not allowed for Senators to interact with each other like that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#G01200"><p>I just want to confirm that is what we heard.  That was all.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#G01300"><p>-----there was no shortage houses.  Nobody was living on the streets, not like here in Dublin where people are lying and dying on the streets.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#G01400"><p>Senator Gavan to continue without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#G01500"><p>In light of the Labour Court proposals on Garda pay, the ongoing and welcome negotiations between the Association of Secondary Teachers Ireland, ASTI, and the Department of Education and Skills and the serious threat of industrial action that remains there, the impending action by our nurses and midwives, the anger of our public health workers, in particular, and Jack O'Connor's comments on radio the other day - I am a member of SIPTU, one of the architects of the Lansdowne Road agreement - when he said that agreement is dead, let us be clear, all of us in this Chamber know that this is the case.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paul Gavan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2469"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2469&amp;amp;pid=PaulGavan&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We know the situation has moved on.  We also know the Government is sleepwalking its way into further industrial relations chaos unless the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform does what he needs to do, as Mr. O'Connor spelt out, which is to confirm that the successor to the Lansdowne Road agreement needs to be negotiated and to give a firm and clear start date for those negotiations.  The negotiations should start immediately after Christmas.  Fine Gael is just not very good at industrial relations.  Consistently, the party leaves things until the last moment or beyond and yet again, we have a silence from the Minister on this issue.  What is worse is that he is saying the Lansdowne Road agreement is fine when all of us know it is not fine, times have moved on and the just grievances of public sector workers need to be addressed.</p><p>We are calling clearly for a successor agreement with negotiations to begin as soon as possible.  Key principles should come into play in the negotiations such as equal pay for equal work.  It is shocking that the Government will not commit to that simple principle, which all of us know is correct.  It is not right that new entrants to the Garda and the teaching profession are paid less than their colleagues, yet the Government will not come out clearly and say that and, more important, outline a timeline in respect of when those changes will happen.  The FEMPI legislation needs to be unwound and there must be pay equalisation for post-2011 entrants.  The public sector must become a living wage employer.  It would not cost much to make that change and it would send a powerful statement in terms of a principled stance by our Government.  Again, we have heard nothing to date.  Pay increases are needed for low to middle income workers because simply unwinding FEMPI on a blanket basis will reward those at the top more than they deserve without giving decent pay increases to those at the bottom.</p><p>The principles we espouse are pay justice, equality, restoration and recognition for the Garda and the Defence Forces.  I call on the Acting Leader to bring the Minister to the House to debate these issues.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1408" speakername="Frances Black" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#H00200"><p>Yesterday, in the AV room, I viewed an informative and disturbing film by Riste&aacute;rd &Oacute; Domhnaill called &quot;The Atlantic&quot;.  The film is a reminder of the mismanagement of Irish natural resources.  It highlights the devastation of our coastal communities by the fishing quotas imposed by Brussels and the exploitation of our waters by super trawlers, which are permitted to operate without adequate scrutiny off our coast.  A worrying feature was the contrast between the Norwegian Government's stance on maintaining control of its resources and doing deals for the benefit of its people and our natural resources being surrendered to big business.  Gerry Kane, a fisherman who featured in the documentary, said Irish fishermen feel unrepresented by politicians and see super trawlers devastate fish stocks while they are tied up in port because of quotas.  In one instance, 4,000 tonnes of fresh herring was dumped in the sea from a Dutch factory ship because they were not of the required size for processing.  This is a criminal waste of perfectly good food and will lead to the devastation of our fish stocks.  This can be contrasted with the arrest of Jerry Early from Arranmore Island, County Donegal, for having a net with the potential to catch salmon.  The scrutiny of super trawlers is needed and this should be done by insisting each boat has an inspector on board to ensure they adhere to the rules.  In Newfoundland and Norway, &Oacute; Domhnaill filmed politicians who were different compared to their Irish counterparts.  They were strong on natural resources and had stood up against big, powerful interests to fight for their local communities.  He said:</p><blockquote>I don't know if it's a historical thing or a cultural thing in Ireland but we seem to turn our backs on the ocean and undervalue our coastal communities.  I recommend that every single politician here in Leinster House makes it their business to see this film and see the devastation of our coastal communities and the loss of our fishing heritage.</blockquote> <p>This proud fishing tradition handed down through the generations is now in danger of being lost because of greed.  Why was there not one representative of the Government parties at yesterday's presentation?  Jerry Early was there and his father, an 84 year old fisherman, was also there.  They talked about their culture and heritage and how in the old days the fishing tradition was passed down to the next generation.  Jerry's 17 year old son is not a fisherman.  It is a disgrace and this issue needs to be highlighted and addressed.  More needs to be done for our fisherman.  It is one of our top traditions and it is vital that we look after fishermen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#H00300"><p>Edmund Burke once said that the only way evil can prosper is for good men to do nothing.  America has just elected a fascist and the best thing that good people in Ireland can do is to ring him up and ask him if it is okay to still bring the shamrock on St. Patrick's Day.  I am embarrassed by the reaction of the Government to what has happened in America.  I cannot believe the reaction from An Taoiseach and the Government.  I do not use the word &quot;fascist&quot; lightly.  What else would one call somebody who threatens to imprison his political opponents?  What else would one call somebody who threatens not to allow people of a certain religious faith into his country?  How would one describe somebody who was threatening to deport 10 million people?  What would one say about somebody who says that the media, the judiciary, and the political system is rigged?  He then wins an election and the best we can come up with is a phone call asking if it still okay to bring the shamrock.  I am appalled that a female Member of this House went on social media to congratulate this man.</p><p>I refer the Cathaoirleach and the Leader to the statement from Angela Merkel:</p><blockquote>Germany and America are connected by values of democracy, freedom, and respect for the law and the dignity of man, independent of origin, skin colour, religion, gender, sexual orientation, or political views.  I offer the next President of the United States close co-operation on the basis of these values.</blockquote> <p>Can the Government not understand what is happening?  We are at an ugly international crossroads.  What is happening in Britain and across Europe is appalling.  It has echoes of the 1930s.  America, the most powerful country in the world, has just elected a fascist and the best a Government spokesperson can come out with is, &quot;We have to talk about foreign direct investment and we have to be conscious of American investments in Ireland&quot;.  There are 50,000 undocumented Irish in America who I am sure are fearful for their futures.  When will we have the moral courage to speak in terms other than economic all the time and to realise what is happening?  If the Taoiseach of this country cannot stand as an Irishman at the crossroads of the ugly venture that the international political system is facing into and call it for what it is, then we are doing nothing.  I am absolutely frightened by what is happening to our world and what is happening in respect of our inability to stand up against it.</p><p>I congratulate Colm Eastwood of the SDLP who said he will not participate in the charade on St. Patrick's Day.  It is a clear challenge to other political leaders in the country who may be more interested in their fund-raising capacity in America so as not to insult potential American donors and the dollars that could come into their political coffers here in Ireland.  Will the Acting Leader invite the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade to the House to ask him how we are supposed to deal with this monster who has just been elected President of America because none of us in years to come should look back on this period and say we did not do everything in our power to call this out for what it is?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#H00400"><p>Will the Acting Leader ask the Minister of State with responsibility for sport when there will be an announcement about a further round of sports capital funding?  It has over the years enabled many sports clubs and organisations around the country to upgrade their facilities and provide opportunities for people of all ages, whether it be at leisure or competitive level, to participate in sport.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator John O'Mahony:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2202"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2202&amp;amp;pid=JohnOMahony&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Over the years, it has enabled many sports clubs and organisations around the country to upgrade their facilities and provide opportunities for people of all ages to participate at whatever level, whether leisure or competitive level.  We have seen particularly over the past week and months evidence of how sports can lift a nation at every level.  It looks now as if there will not be any funding in 2016, but an announcement was imminent at one stage.  I would like clarity in that regard because many clubs and organisations are contacting us about this.  Many clubs have benefitted from this, as I said, but others, since it could not all be done at once, are waiting in the queue and need some clarification.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#J00200"><p>I echo the sentiments expressed by Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in.  I was not here yesterday, but we woke up to a very worrying world with the election of Donald Trump as President of the greatest democracy in the world.  When I went to school I studied Greek.  The word &quot;democracy&quot; comes from the Greek words <i>demos</i>and <i>kratos</i>, meaning the voice of the people, and the concept originated in Athens.  I always had the ultimate faith in democracy as the only system, with all its flaws, but I am not so sure this morning.</p><p>It is extraordinary that a nation that could give us Jefferson, Lincoln, Roosevelt and Kennedy has finally given us someone like Trump.  I sympathise with the womanhood of the world particularly.  As a feminist, I think it is a gross insult to the female gender that that man should be elected President.  I think &Eacute;amon de Valera famously - or infamously - said that the majority have no right to do wrong.  He did not get an overall majority, but one would have to worry about democracy.  I hope the people who will be handling Mr. Trump, if he can be handled, will be able to bring to bear on him the huge responsibility he has and that he must be careful about what he says and does and the way in which he refers to people like the handicapped, foreign nationals and so on.  It is a bit depressing.  I wanted to express my views on it as well.</p><p>I rise today to ask that we have a debate with the Minister for Social Protection about the contributory old age pension.  Many people in the State will seek a contributory old age pension in their old age.  Unlike the case for most other pension schemes, there is much disinformation and non-information out there about people's rights.  Most people, such as us in the Oireachtas, can ring their pension providers and ask for a pension forecast, and they will get it.  They will be told what they can expect to receive in terms of a lump sum or a pension if they are to retire next week, next year or whenever.  That applies to most private pension schemes as well in so far as they can be predicted.</p><p>However, the Department does not give pension forecasts.  It makes it clear that it will not do so.  What it does is refer people to a website where there is a plethora of information.  One would need an actuarial qualification to go through all that detail to see one's average payments, the minimum payments one requires and so on.  How many times I have met constituents who have just reached retirement age only to find out that had they done A, B or C in their working life, they would have qualified for a full contributory old age pension, which is in the order of &euro;200 a week.  However, because they were not aware of their rights or the fact that they could get credits or make voluntary contributions, they let matters fall and have no pension or a reduced pension.  It is not unreasonable in this day and age to ask that our Government be able to advise people as they come close to retirement age how they stand and what options they may have to enhance or secure a pension.  I look forward to the Leader's response.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#J00300"><p>I second the request by my colleague, Senator Freeman, for the Minister for Health to be brought here at his earliest convenience to discuss the cuts to the budgeted figure for mental health.  Mental health problems are a plague in this country, and we must do something about them.</p> <p>I had other things to say but I am afraid I cannot let the statements made by Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in and my colleague, Senator Ned O'Sullivan, go unchallenged.  We are standing in the heart and soul of democracy in this room.  I congratulated Donald Trump yesterday and qualified it by saying we are now in the middle of a perfect storm.  Donald Trump was elected by the people of the United States.  A total of 4% of the black women, 26% of the Latino women and 52% of the white women of America voted for Donald Trump.  What right has anybody in this room to criticise the democratic choice of another country?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#J00400"><p>Hitler was elected democratically as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#J00500"><p>I do not like anything about Donald Trump, I do not like anything about what he has said and I do not like anything he stands for, but he is the elected leader, soon to take office, of the United States, where there are tens of thousands of Irish people.  By standing up and criticising him now, our Government puts those people who are at risk over there in much greater jeopardy than they are in already.  We have a job to do, and that job is to be done by the mainstream political system.  It has failed the people.  Right across the world, mainstream politics has failed the people because it has not countered the populism of the Trumps of this world with empirical fact, which shoots their stories down into the gutter where they belong.</p> <p>Mainstream politics has lost the people; the people have not lost mainstream politics.  Donald Trump has been elected and, God help us, we must live with him for the next four years.  Let us therefore not create a rocky road that we will regret.  There will be weeping and gnashing of teeth if that man decides to turn his anger on our citizens in the United States.  There will be weeping and gnashing of teeth in this country if he decides to offer a 5% corporate tax rate and brings all his companies home or to put them under pressure to pull out of this country.  The House should look around Ireland and consider the number of United States companies working in this country.  Yes, Hitler was brought to power by a similar system.  God help us, that is what democracy is about.  We have four years of this man.  Let us learn to live with him and work with him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#J00600"><p>I wish to raise an issue happening in my part of the world, and probably the Cathaoirleach's part of the world.  I refer to Digital Week in Skibbereen, which is one of the most unique ventures that happened last year and which is now happening again this year.  Last year, 80 world-class speakers came to Skibbereen, a rural town in west Cork.  It was an unbelievable experience.  This year, another 80 speakers are coming to Skibbereen.  Last year, the three-day event generated nearly 12 million tweets and brought many people into Skibbereen.  It was launched today and will take place today, tomorrow and Saturday.  It is a great event for west Cork, and the Ludgate Hub in Skibbereen is one of the driving forces behind it.  This is what we want to see.  We want to see digital communication and the digital industry located in the heart of rural Ireland.  It is a very worthy event, so I wish it well.  We need to promote such events more.  I look forward to going to the event over the week to see exactly how wonderful it is.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#J00700"><p>I am sure the Senator has the full imprimatur of Deputy Daly to raise that issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#J00800"><p>I want to raise a number of issues today, the first of which is the Irish Coast Guard service.  There is significant concern among the members of the Coast Guard about a threat to their future and helicopters being moved away from their bases.  They call for legislation to put the Coast Guard on a statutory footing.  As the House knows, there are four primary response agencies in the State: the fire service, the ambulance service, the Garda and the Irish Coast Guard.  The latter is the Cinderella in this arrangement, and we need to put it on a statutory footing and resource it adequately.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator P&aacute;draig Mac Lochlainn:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2321"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2321&amp;amp;pid=PadraigMacLochlainn&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->They are being asked to save lives around our coast every year and they are not getting the support they need.  Will the Acting Leader bring this to the attention of the Minister?  What is interestingly is that the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Shane Ross, who is responsible, is in this Chamber next week.  When he makes his statement to the Chamber, I ask that he would address the issue of the Coast Guard service to reassure us on that.</p><p>I support the comments of Senator Frances Black.  I also viewed the documentary "The Atlantic" last night.  There is also huge food for thought in regard to the map presented recently to the Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine by BIM.  The map showed British waters in the context of the post-Brexit scenario and it can be seen that Irish waters will be squeezed further.  It is potentially a calamity for our fishing community who are extremely angry at how they have been squeezed over the years.  Will the Acting Leader bring that matter to the attention of the Minister, Deputy Michael Creed, who I hope has watched the documentary, in particular the issue of Ireland's territorial waters and how our fishing community will be affected by Brexit.</p><p>To those who are devastated by the election of Donald Trump, I would say they have to ask themselves why working class communities in their droves backed Boris Johnson on Brexit in England and why they have backed Donald Trump in their droves in the United States.  It is because of the failure of mainstream politics to address the concerns of those communities, which have been raised repeatedly.  Rather than all of us making statements such as have been made today, given we all feel deeply concerned about what is evolving due to the two votes on Brexit and the US presidential election, the challenge for all of us is to reassure working class communities, communities who have been left behind and minority communities as to what we are going to do to help them and how we are going to put in place policies.  Rather than looking at Donald Trump, we need to look at ourselves collectively and see how we change the direction we are heading in.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#K00200"><p>Following on from that, we have to look at the relevance of the budget that has recently been passed.  It was said that Brexit was future proofed but a mushroom farmer or a worker in the mushroom industry has not been future proofed.  A person working in the agriculture sector whose main export market is the UK has not been future proofed.  A person working in the retail sector will only need to look at the roads to Newry and Belfast to see the effect on the retail sector, so that person is not future proofed.</p> <p>We need to engage very quickly with our EU partners in regard to a derogation for investment and the protection of rural Ireland.  In many ways there is a balance in that Dublin may possibly gain investment due to Brexit but rural Ireland will certainly lose out because its main export market is the UK.  We need to engage urgently with our EU partners about a derogation or we will see a huge loss in the workforce.</p> <p>While we talk about future-proofing for Brexit, we have not future-proofed for Trump, although his election will have a major impact on global growth.  It would be timely to schedule the Minister for Finance, the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform and the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine to come to the House.  These are the three main areas that will have most influence on how we deal with what I believe will be a global crisis.  President-elect Trump spoke about a trade war with Canada, Mexico and China, and we would be caught very badly by that.  We are the piggy in the middle.  We are squeezed between the EU and the United States.  With regard to dealing with this as mainstream parties, we see that what is happening socially in the UK and the US is enormous.  However, if we ignore what could possibly be an economic crisis that puts this country back into recession, and we do not have a debate with the relevant Ministers, we have no right to be here.  Will the Acting Leader schedule a meeting with the Ministers or, if they are scheduled, will she notify us when they will come to the House?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1373" speakername="Keith Swanick" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#K00300"><p>In July and August my office sent out more than 940 confidential mental health questionnaires to all local authority members throughout the country, from all parties and none.  This was the first comprehensive anonymous mental health questionnaire to be circulated to councillors.  To tell the truth, the findings, which I presented at an AILG conference in Gorey recently, were stark and startling.  Some 79% of councillors said their role as a public representative impinges on their personal life, 82% said their responsibilities had increased in recent years, 47% experienced low mood and, worryingly, 5% expressed thoughts of self-harm.  This is a very serious and real issue.  We forwarded the results to the Minister for Health, Deputy Harris, and the Minister for Housing, Planning, Community and Local Government, Deputy Coveney.  Mental health is a big issue.  We lost one of our councillor colleagues earlier in the year.  It is important that we have the Minister to the House to discuss and debate this further.  I ask the Acting Leader to invite him in as soon as possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1423" speakername="Ray Butler" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#K00400"><p>I spoke two weeks ago about planning in my local town of Trim where planning permission has been granted for 400 houses.  As the economy changes, planning permission will be sought for developments.  Just two days ago, a water mains burst in the middle of Trim resulting in something akin to a lake in the middle of the town.  The issue ended up as a story on the front page of the <i>Meath Chronicle</i>.  Some &euro;1.3 million was supposed to be spent on the 35 year old water plant and on water issues in the area, but that money is gone since the debacle of Irish Water.</p><p>We need a debate in this House on the way forward for planning, facilities, services and even schools.  I believe local authorities are not looking at the issues when they give planning permission.  Two years ago the school in my area was 60 places short yet, although we do not have enough schools, we are now talking about the development of 400 houses in the Trim area.  We need a debate in the House on planning and the development of facilities.  We had this during the Celtic tiger, when we built continually without putting any facilities whatsoever in place.  That left people in a terrible state.  The debate on planning should include Irish Water and how we view the role of either the local authorities or Irish Water, if it still exists as we move forward.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#K00500"><p>Given the passion and emotion that Trump caused and the shock we all felt in the pit of our stomach yesterday morning, I echo Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in's view.  However, a knee-jerk reaction is not positive.  I think he is a bit naive, as is the SDLP leader, in saying we will not cross any threshold there.  We need to be involved and we need to make sure we can do the best for this country.</p> <p>I raise the issue of the bizarre HSE memo sent to acute hospitals encouraging nurses to use force to remove patients from beds.  It was rightly labelled by the unions and the Minister, Deputy Harris, as utterly offensive and unacceptable.  This memo was issued on 11 October and came to nurses' attention earlier this week.  It stated that nurses should use minimum force to remove trespassers, that is, patients, who are incapable or unwilling to give up beds.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator M&aacute;ire Devine:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2468"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2468&amp;amp;pid=MaireDevine&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This is incredible and repugnant.  Nurses' first professional obligation is to their patients and adherence to the code of professional conduct and ethics of An Bord Altranais.  Nurses are gobsmacked by the coldness and callousness of this memorandum.  It confirms the loss of compassion and respect for the public that the HSE is supposed to serve.  I demand a written formal apology from those responsible.  People in senior managerial positions must carry out a root cause analysis and hold those responsible to account.  There are numerous reasons for some patients being unable to vacate beds.  For example, a young, wheelchair-bound 18 year old man from Crumlin cannot leave the acute bed because it will take a year for the adaptations in the house to be carried out.  He must use the back garden as his toilet.</p><p>I urge the Acting Leader to follow up on this and demand an apology.  We have gone from trolleys to chairs to forcible ousting.  Perhaps the next instruction to nurses will be to taser these trespassers, our patients.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#L00300"><p>Senators raised a variety of issues on the Order of Business.  Senator Davitt made a number of comments about the squeezed middle, with which I agree.  Certainly, when canvassing during the general election campaign, I met a huge number of people who are feeling very squeezed by cuts that have been made over recent years.  However, ours is a recovering economy and a job is the best way to deal with the inequality the Senator mentioned.  Unemployment has decreased from 15% to 8% under this Government.  There is still work to be done and I accept the Senator's comments, but since the previous Government took office huge strides have been made.</p> <p>Senator Freeman raised-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#L00400"><p>It is the housing.  People who are working cannot get a house.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#L00500"><p>Allow the Acting Leader to respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#L00600"><p>Another Senator also raised the issue of housing.  I will be happy to invite the Minister, Deputy Coveney, to the House to discuss it.  As I said, I share Senator Davitt's concerns about that.</p><p>Senators Freeman, Craughwell and Swanick raised the issue of mental health.  I would welcome if the Minister, Deputy Harris, or the Minister of State, Deputy McEntee, could come to the House to discuss it.  I doubt that either of them would have a problem doing that to clarify the position.  A total of &euro;35 million in new services will be initiated in 2017, to add to the &euro;35 million provided in 2016.  It remains in the base funding of mental health services.  I will invite the Minister as requested.</p><p>Senator Gavan spoke about the Lansdowne Road agreement and strike action.  In light of recent developments, we are all concerned about the various strikes that have been threatened.  I will be happy to suggest that we invite the Minister to the House to discuss these matters, which are of great concern to most citizens.</p><p>Senator Black raised fishing quotas, natural resources and super-trawlers.  It is a matter that has not been discussed in the House during this term and I am sure the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine will be happy to come to the House to discuss it.  Senator Mac Lochlainn raised that issue too.  I will invite the Minister to the House.</p><p>Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in spoke about Mr. Trump.  I believe it is the only issue people in the country have been talking about since yesterday.  We are trying to come to terms with what has happened.  I share the concerns about Mr. Trump.  I would have preferred to be speaking about a President Clinton but I agree with comments that Ireland and the US, regardless of the president in office, will have to work to ensure they have a relationship.  We have citizens in the United States who need our protection.  People can make whatever comments they wish about St. Patrick's Day but it is a useful time for us to be in the US and to promote Ireland.  Bernie Sanders said a few hours ago:</p><blockquote>To the degree that Mr. Trump is serious about pursuing policies that improve the lives of working families in the country, I and other progressives are prepared to work with him.  To the degree that he pursues racist, sexist, xenophobic and anti-environment policies, we will vigorously oppose him.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#L00700"><p>It would be wonderful if the Taoiseach had said that.  Will it happen?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#L00800"><p>The Taoiseach said very little, in fairness.  He said that he will go to the United States for St. Patrick's Day.  There would be more criticism if we did not continue that relationship.  That is all he has said.  I agree with Angela Merkel's comments and I agree with the Senator raising the matter.  I found yesterday very depressing.  Many people did.  Senator Ned O'Sullivan used the word "depressing".  I believe it was depressing, but that is as much as I am willing to say today.</p> <p>Senator O'Mahony asked about sports capital funding.  It is very important for clubs and organisations in rural and urban communities.  I will seek clarification from the Minister of State, Deputy O'Donovan, on when the funding is likely to be disbursed again.</p> <p>As I said, Senator Ned O'Sullivan spoke about Mr. Trump.  He also raised the contributory old age pension and made a very relevant point.  The Minister for Social Protection, Deputy Varadkar, has not been to the House previously to discuss the old age pension so I will be happy to invite him to do so.</p> <p>Senator Craughwell also spoke about Mr. Trump and I agree, for once, with some of his comments.</p> <p>Senator Lombard mentioned Digital Week in Skibbereen.  I commend him on highlighting it.  It is a very positive week for Skibbereen and west Cork.</p> <p>Senator Mac Lochlainn spoke on the natural resources issue which had been raised earlier by Senator Black.  He also commented on Mr. Trump.  The Senator raised the Coast Guard service.  The Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport will be in the House next week and that will be a good opportunity for him to raise that issue.</p> <p>Senator Humphreys questioned the relevance of the budget in the context of Brexit and the US election.  It would be a good idea to have a series of debates in the House with each of the Ministers in charge of the potential developments with Brexit and our relationship with the US.  I would be happy to suggest that we invite the three Ministers concerned, the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine, Deputy Creed, the Minister for Finance, Deputy Noonan, and the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, Deputy Donohoe, to the House, not just to discuss it and raise issues but in order that we can come up with some ideas as to how we can maximise our ongoing relationships with these countries.</p> <p>Senator Swanick raised the important issue of mental health for our councillors.  I have already suggested that we invite the Minister of State, Deputy McEntee, to the House.  I am sure she will be happy to address the Senator's concerns about local representatives.</p> <p>Senator Butler spoke about planning, particularly in Trim.  A debate on planning, Irish Water and housing would be very useful.  It is to be hoped we can arrange it before Christmas.</p> <p>I agree with Senator Devine's comments on Mr. Trump.  I was appalled when I read about that statement on using minimum force to remove patients from beds.  The Minister was as well.  I commend the Senator on raising issues pertaining to nurses.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#L00900"><p>Will we get an apology?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#L01000"><p>Nurses' jobs are difficult enough without being given such directives from the powers that be.  I wholeheartedly agree with the Senator, as would the Minister.  An apology would be called for.  As I said, the Minister agrees and has criticised it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#L01100"><p>Call for an apology.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#L01200"><p>I will certainly ask the Minister and mention the Senator's comments to him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#L01300"><p>I rarely comment on issues from the Chair.  Much of the Irish public and many Members are animated by the result in America, but that is outside our control.  America has its own democratic system.  We may or may not like it but we must accept what happens there.</p> <p>To make another brief comment, as somebody whose father, grandfather and great-grandfather were fishermen, I have raised the plight of fishermen in this House for more than 20 years.  I wish the Members who are raising it more success than I had.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.65" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.66" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#L01500">Address to Seanad ireann by Ms Nicola Sturgeon: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#L01600"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That Seanad &Eacute;ireann agrees with the recommendation of the Committee on Procedure and Privileges that, in accordance with the provisions for the address to Seanad &Eacute;ireann by Distinguished Persons, Ms Nicola Sturgeon MSP, First Minister of Scotland, be invited to address Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 29th November, 2016, and, notwithstanding anything in Standing Orders, the following arrangements shall apply:(i) the Seanad shall meet at 11.30 a.m. on Tuesday, 29th November, 2016;<br /><br />(ii) Standing Orders 29 and 30 shall stand suspended; <br /><br />(iii) the proceedings in respect of the address by the First Minister of Scotland shall commence immediately after the reading of the Prayer, shall conclude no later than 1.15 p.m. and shall consist of - <blockquote>(a) a speech of welcome by the Cathaoirleach, <br /><br />(b) an address by the First Minister,<br /><br />(c) a contribution not exceeding five minutes by a spokesperson for each Group,<br /><br />(d) questions from Senators in accordance with the sequence set out in the Schedule to this resolution, which shall not exceed one minute in each case and to which the First Minister may reply,<br /><br />(e) not later than 1 p.m. a response by the First Minister;<br /><br />(f) a speech of thanks by the Leader of the House; </blockquote>(iv) on the conclusion of the proceedings in respect of the address by the First Minister the sitting shall stand suspended until 2.30 p.m; <br /><br />(v) the Order of Business shall be proposed at 2.30 p.m. <div>Schedule </div>Fine Gael Group <br /><br />Fianna F&aacute;il Group <br /><br />Independent Group <br /><br />Sinn F&eacute;in Group <br /><br />Civil Engagement Group <br /><br />Labour Group.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.68" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.69" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 12.20 p.m. and resumed at 12.45 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.70" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#O00100">National Tourism Development Authority (Amendment) Bill 2015 (Certified Money Bill): Second Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.71" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That the Bill be now read a Second Time."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#O00300"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy O'Donovan, to the House.  I remind the House that this is a certified money Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1267" speakername="Patrick O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#O00400"><p>The National Tourism Development Authority (Amendment) Bill 2015 provides for an increase in the upper limit that applies to the overall capital funding that can be voted to the National Tourism Development Authority, which is known to us all as F&aacute;ilte Ireland, for the purposes of supporting the development of the tourism product.  As this Bill has been certified as a money Bill, tight constitutional deadlines apply to the return of Seanad recommendations to the D&aacute;il.  I thank Senators for allowing all Stages to be taken today in Seanad &Eacute;ireann, thereby facilitating the swift passage of this short but important Bill.</p> <p>The National Tourism Development Authority Act 2003 provided for the dissolution of Bord F&aacute;ilte &Eacute;ireann and CERT Limited and the establishment of the National Tourism Development Authority, F&aacute;ilte Ireland.  Section 24(1) of the 2003 Act gives the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, with the consent of the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, the power to "advance to the Authority out of moneys provided by the Oireachtas such sums as the Minister may determine".  Section 24(2) of the Act limits the total amount of money that can be advanced to F&aacute;ilte Ireland by the Minister over a series of years for "capital expenditure on projects or enterprises".  It is important to note that this limit refers only to the total cumulative cap on capital funding that may be advanced by the Minister to F&aacute;ilte Ireland in support of the development of the tourism product.  It is an enabling provision rather than an allocation.  It is important to note that it is not an allocation.</p> <p>Specific Exchequer allocations to F&aacute;ilte Ireland continue to be made in the normal way through the annual Estimates and budgetary process.  The limit on total capital funding was originally set at &euro;65 million but was later increased to &euro;150 million under the National Tourism Development Authority (Amendment) Act 2011.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Patrick O'Donovan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2316"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2316&amp;amp;pid=PatrickODonovan&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->As things stand, total capital investment in tourism by F&aacute;ilte Ireland from the Exchequer allocation has almost reached that limit.  Once the spending limit has been reached, no further voted capital moneys can be advanced to F&aacute;ilte Ireland for tourism capital investment projects.  Accordingly, it is necessary now to legislate to increase the limit.</p><p>The Bill takes into account the allocations under the Government's capital plan, Building on Recovery: Infrastructure and Capital Investment 2016-2021.  The Bill proposes raising the limit to &euro;300 million to cover anticipated allocations over the lifetime of the plan.  To reflect changes in ministerial roles and responsibilities since the legislation was last amended, the Bill also clarifies that it is now with the consent of the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, rather than the Minister for Finance, that the Minister may advance moneys to F&aacute;ilte Ireland.</p><p>Tourism is a growing industry and a key contributor to our overall economy.  It creates jobs and generates earnings in communities throughout Ireland, especially in rural areas.  The year 2015 was the fifth successive year of growth for Irish tourism.  Central Statistics Office figures for overseas travel show a new record high of over 8.6 million visits to Ireland during the year.  Expenditure in 2015 by overseas visitors, excluding carrier receipts, amounted to over &euro;4.2 billion, an increase of over 18% on 2014.  When combined with spending by domestic tourists, total tourism expenditure was worth over &euro;5.7 billion to the Irish economy.  The tourism and hospitality sectors now employ an estimated 220,000 people and provide a wide range of opportunities to access the labour market.  Things are certainly moving in the right direction but this is no time to rest on our laurels.  We need to capitalise on this positive momentum to drive further growth and maximise returns.</p><p>Continued capital investment in our tourism product is essential to maintain our competitive position.  We must provide for continued investment in the further development of our tourism offering in line with visitor expectations to stand out in a crowded international marketplace.  With this in mind, F&aacute;ilte Ireland is continuing to develop the signature experience brands, including the Wild Atlantic Way, Ireland's Ancient East and Dublin: A Breath of Fresh Air.  They have the necessary scale and impact to stand out internationally and give Ireland a strong base for promotion overseas.  F&aacute;ilte Ireland is also considering how best to develop and progress a new proposition for the lakelands.</p><p>Capital allocations for tourism product development will provide for continued investment in these experienced brands through the development of attractions and other tourism infrastructure.  In parallel, current expenditure on tourism will further enhance, animate and promote these key experienced brands by funding businesses, supports, training, festivals and other related programmes.  The Government's capital programme sets out the framework for capital investment in the coming years.  This will allow Departments and agencies to plan investment over the medium term and longer term.  The programme provides for approximately &euro;125 million for expenditure on tourism product development up to 2022, with investment rising significantly as time progresses.</p><p>The existing spending cap set out in legislation is insufficient to provide for the anticipated annual allocations over the life of the capital programme.  Without this revised proposed legislation no further voted Exchequer moneys can be advanced to F&aacute;ilte Ireland for tourism and capital investment projects once the existing limit has been reached.  Accordingly, I am bringing forward the Bill to make the necessary legislative changes.  I commend the Bill to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#P00200"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it.  I commend the Minister of State on his work in the Department, which he is undertaking with a great degree of success, in fairness.</p> <p>We support the Bill.  As the Minister of State has said, it is an enabling provision.  We have to make provision for additional funding if and when it becomes necessary.  We have no problem with that.</p> <p>I do not have a great deal to say today.  Tourism is one of our big success stories and we have to mind it, nourish it and try to keep it going in the right direction.  The figures are good.  All sectors seem to be up.  We had a useful exchange yesterday at our committee meeting with the leaders of the tourism industry.  Whereas we are all cautious and concerned about certain developments, there is a belief that Irish tourism is in a strong position.  We should be able to withstand the threats and dangers that are coming, especially Brexit, if we all work together.</p> <p>We have many things going for us in tourism, not least, our natural environment, scenery, culture, history, dance and music.  More important, as we often say, the greatest single tourist attraction in Ireland is the people.  The people are friendly and welcoming.  We want to see people coming to our shores.  Local people have a great and abiding interest in promoting their areas and niche tourism.  That is not something anyone can buy.</p> <p>The Minister of State will be aware of a product in his constituency at Foynes.  He will be aware of the Foynes Flying Board and Maritime Museum, which operates under the leadership of Margaret O'Shaughnessy and her team.  I am simply highlighting this venture because it is one with which the Minister of State and I are familiar.  It has grown from a small idea.  Every few years the operation expands and those involved come up with a new element.  If that could be replicated throughout the country, then I have no fears for the tourism industry.</p> <p>Recently, we launched the Kerry tourism strategy in Listowel.  There was a great attendance at the launch.  It was great to see all the players and involved parties, including hoteliers, restaurateurs and those in tourism transport.  The document was brought out under the aegis of the Kerry County Council chief executive, Moira Murrell, and her team.  It would make a good template for local authority tourism input throughout the country.  I am not suggesting Kerry is better than anywhere else but at the same time we have a big stake in tourism and it is important for us.  I believe there are counties in the north, south, east and west that have beautiful amenities but they have not been properly marketed.  Anyone who has done a tour of Ireland - as we all did during the Seanad elections - will know that there is extraordinary beauty in most parts of Ireland.  However, according to the figures, the north west amounts to only 5% of the entire tourism take.  This area includes beautiful counties like Donegal and Leitrim.  It is surprising that we cannot do better here.  Corresponding figures include 12% from the west, 17% from the south west and over 40% from our great capital city of Dublin, naturally.  There is plenty of room for improvement as, I am sure, the Minister of State will agree.</p> <p>There is no doubt that the biggest threat we are facing around the corner is Brexit.  Yesterday, the head of F&aacute;ilte Ireland indicated that it is already impacting negatively on our tourism base.  Given the devaluation in sterling, it is going to be rather expensive for United Kingdom and Northern Ireland tourists to spend as much in Ireland as they have done heretofore.  Almost 40% of our total tourism business comes from the UK and the North, a sizeable segment.  The English are good tourists.  They come all year round, not only in high season.  They come for fishing and shooting.  They come off the main shoulder season.  They are good spenders.  This is something on which we will have to work hard.</p> <p>I will highlight one of my great bugbears, although I know it is not particularly relevant to what we are talking about.  Anyway, it relates to the overpricing of hotel accommodation in our capital city.  This is becoming a crisis.  Any time a big rock star comes or a big event is scheduled - Rod Stewart is coming next weekend - people find that they have to stay in hotels in Portlaoise and Wicklow.  They cannot get accommodation in the city.  We are lucky to have Airbnb to take up the slack.  We also have to be aware that capital investment in tourism is slipping.  We are down 17% on the grants for F&aacute;ilte Ireland and Tourism Ireland since 2012.</p> <p>I will make a final comment on the Asian market.  I imagine the Minister of State and those in his Department are well aware that this is a major growth area and presents a great opportunity for us.  We are going to have to study this market.  The head of the restaurant association said lately that we know more about the 6.5 million cows in Ireland than we do about the 6.5 million tourists who come here.  That is pretty true.  As far as the Asian market is concerned, there is great potential.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Ned O'Sullivan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2233"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2233&amp;amp;pid=NedOSullivan&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Tourists from Asia stay for longer periods, spend more and travel more.  We welcome that and will have to work on it.</p><p>I have referred to skills shortages in a number of debates here before.  We have a difficulty training chefs especially.  I will ask the Minister of State another time to take a serious look at how we will train our chefs and kitchen staff generally and how we will reinvigorate CERT and many other such ideas.  However, today is the day to give the Minister of State the freedom to draw down more money if it is needed, and I am happy to support that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#Q00200"><p>Gabhaim mo bhu&iacute;ochas leis an Aire St&aacute;it as a bheith anseo linn inniu.  The Minister of State made a very compelling case in his contribution as to why he wants this Bill to pass and why we would want to invest further in our tourism offer.  As Senator Ned O'Sullivan outlined very eloquently, Ireland overall has a fantastic, world-class tourism offer, the economic benefits of which can be, should be and need to be tangibly felt.  When we approach this issue, particularly around capital investment and the offer we spread across the country, we need to think strategically and think how best we can make our offer go beyond Kerry, with the greatest respect to that county, and be felt beyond the city of Dublin.  We need to think how the merits and investment which, justifiably and necessarily, Government makes in our tourism offer reap some rewards for communities, small business-owners, small restaurateurs, hoteliers, and publicans, etc.  I am inclined to support anything that seeks to do that.</p> <p>I sat previously on the board of Visit Belfast, the tourism body responsible for tourism in Ireland's second city, and I understand the significant need to support tourism initiatives.  Ireland has pioneered very well the kinds of initiatives about which Deputy Ned O'Sullivan talked.  In my city there is a huge interest in political tourism, for example.  It is probably one of the biggest and fastest-growing sectors in the city of Belfast.  When I visited Derry city recently, Visit Derry, the relevant organisation there, was very keen and anxious to work with colleagues in Donegal to promote the broader north-west region referred to as well.  I approach this in the context of being truly national when we come to these strategies and seeking to bolster organisations such as Tourism Ireland, which has responsibility for promoting, highlighting and working on behalf of the capital investment we make on a global stage.  Anything we can do to bolster that offer or benefit the tourism infrastructure, whether hotel beds or greater connectivity within and greater links to the island of Ireland, is to be welcomed and encouraged.  That is why I have no doubt that the Minister of State will have our support in the Seanad in seeking to make that additional investment.</p> <p>I will make a number of quick points before I finish.  Senator Ned O'Sullivan is right to touch on Brexit.  It has implications both North and South because the North relies on visitors from the South in order to support its economy as well.  As an island, we have a responsibility, because of the implications of Brexit, to ensure that this momentum North and South and between both islands, whether day trips or short weekend breaks, continues and is bolstered, thought about and considered in the time ahead.  This is another indication of how the decision of the United Kingdom to leave the European Union impacts right across every facet of our lives.  It is not just reserved to the expected or more commonly spoken about issues.  Brexit has major implications for the tourism offer right across the island.  It would be good to hear, whether from the Minister of State, his colleagues or Tourism Ireland, specifically how best they wish to and practically can work to offset some of the negative implications of Brexit and what they will do in the immediate time ahead.</p> <p>I touched very briefly on the need for infrastructure.  Belfast City Council, for example, which has a memorandum of understanding with Dublin City Council on issues such as tourism, recently passed a motion seeking to develop the high-speed rail link between both cities.  That would be mutually beneficial to communities right across the country.  When we come to these issues, given the very eloquent case the Minister of State made and the very understandable case for investment in our tourism offer, I reiterate that it is fantastic when one walks the streets of this city to see the place absolutely overrun with tourists.  That is very good and encouraging, particularly given the global economic climate in which we have found ourselves.  However, I stress the point, with which I am sure the Minister of State will agree, that any investment, as I said at the beginning of my contribution, must be matched by the political will and every other kind of will to see that communities across the length and breadth of this island benefit.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#Q00300"><p>I welcome the Minister of State and welcome this Bill, which aims to increase the cumulative total of funding for spending and capital tourism projects.  As the Minister of State rightly pointed out, it is not an allocation but it will allow allocations down the line.  It is important to continue to support tourism projects and investments.  As has been pointed out already, we saw the updated figures for 2016 at a meeting of the Committee on Transport, Tourism and Sport yesterday.  Brexit is a threat and a worry, but it is great to see that it has not affected the numbers travelling from the United Kingdom.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#Q00400"><p>Not yet.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#Q00500"><p>While we need to take account of Brexit and be aware of it, we do not need to talk ourselves into a crisis about it.  Senator &Oacute; Donnghaile said that it has not yet affected the figures.  People are making decisions now about where they will go in 2017, and we need to be on the ball in that regard.</p> <p>The great thing about tourism is that every region has benefited from it in terms of jobs and spending in the economy.  Spending by tourists in regional Ireland is even more beneficial because the regions lack spending in other areas.  That must be concentrated on as well.  Reference was made as well to the fact that funding to support tourism suffered in the financial crisis like everything else.  It is good that we are discussing the lifting of a cap rather than the imposition of a cut, but it is important to note that tourism has been the success story of the recession and the financial crisis in Ireland.  It shows what happens when all bodies can get together, whether the agencies, the industry itself, the Irish Hotels Federation, the Restaurants Association of Ireland and so on, along with the Government.  While funding was cut, incentives and supports were put in place by way of the 9% VAT rate, the elimination of the travel tax and so on.</p> <p>It was pointed out to us yesterday that there are challenges ahead, and everyone sees them.  Sterling has dropped by 20% in the last number of months, and we saw a wobble on the markets with the election in the United States.  It is important that such matters be met and whatever supports necessary can be put in place.  Maybe the one small weakness concerns Dublin, the capital city.  If we go abroad, we think of capital cities, and that is fine, but there are some wonderful resources in tourism.  The biggest resources in tourism are in the regions, whether scenery, activities, holidays or whatever.  The Minister of State wears his sporting cap here as well.  Activity holidays and so on are important.  There is a lack of hotel beds.  While the solution to that in Dublin is the building and opening of new hotels, it is important that there be another solution, that is, that we get people directly into the regions.  I know Shannon Airport and the surrounding area is close to the Minister of State's heart.  Knock Airport is close to mine.  There are also airports in Cork and Belfast.  Tourism marketing has been wonderful in the past five years.  I refer to the Wild Atlantic Way and Ireland's Ancient East.  However, we should educate tourists that there is brilliant value for money in the rural and regional areas, despite hotel rooms in Dublin sometimes being massively overpriced in many respects, with the Rod Stewart concert and sporting events and so on.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator John O'Mahony:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2202"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2202&amp;amp;pid=JohnOMahony&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->If there is one positive outcome from the challenges, it is that there are considerable opportunities arising from them.  For the investment that has been made in tourism, there are multiples of it that come back into the economy.  I very much welcome this Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1385" speakername="Grace O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#R00200"><p>I welcome the increase in funding for tourism.  It is good that all of my colleagues here in the Seanad today are welcoming this Bill.  The Minister of State says tourism is a growing sector and a key contributor to the overall economy, both of which it is.  It creates jobs and generates earnings in communities throughout Ireland, particularly in rural areas.</p> <p>I am from the south-east region, from Tramore, County Waterford, and unfortunately we are not seeing the growth or recovery in jobs in the south-east region like we are seeing in other areas of Ireland.  Particularly in terms of tourism, it would be fitting for the Government to look at where recovery has not been felt on the ground in some rural areas and when distributing capital funding, that it specifically target the weak economic areas, such as Waterford and the rest of the south-east region, and bolster these areas.</p> <p>The Wild Atlantic Way is a magnificent offering.  I believe Ireland, as a tourism product, is next to none.  I have travelled the length and breadth of the globe through 30 years and Ireland has the beautiful green rural regions that are excellent for tourism but it would be wonderful if capital investment went to areas, such as the south east, that really need an input, particularly with regard to Ireland's Ancient East.  The Wild Atlantic Way has received a significant contribution over the past years and we are seeing the success.  I would like to see such capital funding coming into areas that really need this support at present.</p> <p>In Waterford, we have the Waterford Greenway.  It is a cycling and walking route through areas of Waterford, looking at the beautiful Comeragh Mountains and looking out at the Atlantic and the Celtic Sea region.  I would like to see sustainable ecotourism developed more in the south east because we have the surfing beaches and areas that without doubt need the capital funding that will bring more jobs into the region.</p> <p>It is a great day for Ireland that there is more funding coming into tourism.  I ask that the Minister of State have regard to the south east and that a good proportion of the funding would go to rural areas that really need it, such as the Waterford area that has not seen the recovery in job creation that other areas have seen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#R00300"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House and compliment him for his grasp of the brief that he has achieved in the past few months.  When one looks at the sport and tourism brief, Deputy Patrick O'Donovan really has a good grasp of it, and it is a credit to him.</p> <p>This legislation will be important because it lifts the cap on spending.  It is probably the first step in ensuring that we can sustain what is a good tourism sector at present.  It is about building on the successes of the Wild Atlantic Way and Ireland's Ancient East, which have been one of our major success stories in the past few years.  That is basically down to the Government commitment.  It is basically down to the 9% VAT rate.  It is about how we sold the product itself - some Senators mentioned that the product is the people - and we have managed to do that quite effectively.  It is about building on that.</p> <p>The figure the Minister of State mentioned of 8.6 million visitors in the past year is phenomenal, and that is a credit to the policies.  Hopefully, the investment that is being proposed here today will strengthen the case so that we can deal with the Brexit issue and deal with the issues around our neighbours and where they are going.  That is probably one of the biggest issues out there.  The confidence factor in the market, with Brexit and with UK tourists, is an issue that will haunt us for the next few months, if not years.</p> <p>One of the key issues of the tourism strategy has to be tourist offices.  We have a unique network of 32 tourist offices the length and breadth of this country.  When we are looking at investing in the infrastructure on the ground, the tourist offices need to be supported.  There have been unfortunate cuts in this regard.  For instance, Kinsale has only 1.5 whole-time equivalent staff and it would be the sixth busiest tourist office in Ireland.  It is open only six days a week.  When one considers what tourism is to a town like Kinsale, an investment in staff members in that infrastructure is key because, as some Senators stated earlier, the people are what we are selling.  When tourists meet the person at the coalface, he or she has the ability to engage and tell them where to go and ensure that their experience in Ireland is as good as it can be.</p> <p>This is an important investment.  The Minister of State has done a courageous job in the past few months.  I commend what he has done and I hope in the investment in the future that he might be able to tie in the tourist offices and the staffing levels there because we need to sell our people who work at the coalface if we possibly can.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1267" speakername="Patrick O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#R00400"><p>I will try to respond to each of the Senators who have shown up and, in fairness, put a bit of thought into their contributions, and I thank them for it.</p> <p>Starting off with my near neighbour, I agree entirely with Senator Ned O'Sullivan regarding the initiatives that have been taken in Kerry.  I was due to launch the Kerry tourism strategy but, unfortunately, on the same day the late Anthony Foley was being laid to rest and, as Minister for sport, I had to attend the funeral.</p> <p>A number of Senators have raised the issue regarding local authorities in their local areas.  I am meeting the County and City Management Association later on.  From the day that I was appointed as Minister of State, I have felt strongly about this.  The last speaker, Senator Lombard, alluded to it as well in relation to tourist offices.  Local authorities have a much greater role and I will be expecting a much greater role from them.  I will be communicating to them today that I expect over the next number of months that every local authority in the country will develop a tourism strategy.  In that regard, I need city and county managers, the CEOs, to be proactive rather than reactive.  It is a requirement under the Local Government Reform Act 2014 that tourism is no longer to be viewed as something that a local authority might do.  Tourism is now viewed as something that one must do as a local authority.</p> <p>I am delighted that the Kerry CEO is as proactive as she is - I have met her and many other CEOs - but there are some who are not proactive.  The way I will view it will be very simple.  CEOs of local authorities and local authority members have to rise to the mark in their contribution from tourism.  Over the next number of months I will be bringing all the CEOs together.  We will launch every one of the local authority tourism strategies.  These strategies will not be dust-gatherers because I will expect my officials from the Department who are here today from Killarney to assess the implementation of these strategies and seek updates from local authorities on a regular basis.</p> <p>Senator Lombard mentioned an issue that is close to my own heart to do with tourist offices.  There is a local authority office at almost every crossroads in the country now.  Every large or medium-sized town has a local authority office.  There is nothing stopping local authorities grasping the Local Government Reform Act 2014 and saying they will fill the vacuum here, and some local authorities are doing that.  Our local authority offices need to be more than merely a place where people who require local authority services go.  They are the front of house in terms of Ireland's image for the visitor coming into a provincial or small town.  Local authorities will have to start looking at their network of offices to see what facilities and services they can make available in them.</p> <p>Senators Ned O'Sullivan and O'Mahony mentioned the need for hotel rooms in Dublin, and I agree entirely.  I met the Irish Hotels Federation.  We had all of the financial institutions in at a meeting recently.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Patrick O'Donovan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2316"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2316&amp;amp;pid=PatrickODonovan&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We are due to meet Dublin City Council and we will also meet in the coming weeks with the Department of Housing, Planning, Community and Local Government with a view to seeing whether there are specific issues that are blocking the pipeline in terms of the delivery of badly needed hotel rooms.  It is an issue I am very conscious of.  I come from a rural location and I see at first hand the issues that exist.</p><p>Several Senators mentioned the skills shortage.  When I was appointed as Minister of State, education and training boards were given the freedom and the initiative to look at the skills deficit in their own area.  I have to compliment the Limerick and Clare Education and Training Board, which has established an initiative to look at deficits in training in its own area, specifically the skills shortage in the tourism and hospitality industry.  I would view this as best practice.  What I have decided to do, with my Department, is to ask that other education and training boards be brought before the Tourism Leadership Group, which I chair, and that we would share information as best practice.  We do not need to go off establishing another quango or reinventing the wheel.  If chefs and tourism and hospitality staff can be trained in the ETB in Roxborough in Limerick, it can be done everywhere and we should be able to meet the skills deficit.  There is a requirement under the legislation that ETBs would do that and I will be seeking to make sure under the Action Plan for Jobs and the Regional Action Plan for Jobs that this is done.</p><p>Senator &Oacute; Donnghaile mentioned the all-island aspect of this issue.  I could not agree more.  I was in attendance at the World Travel Market in London with Tourism Ireland during the week.  To me, selling Ballymena is every bit as important as selling Bandon and I do not differentiate between them.  Ten million people visited the island of Ireland last year.  What we want to do is make sure we contribute to employment growth.  Some 8.6 million visited south of the Border and, in fairness, the Northern Ireland Tourist Board and F&aacute;ilte Ireland do a very good job within their remit under the umbrella body, Tourism Ireland.  I had a very good meeting with the chair of Tourism Ireland, Brian Ambrose, yesterday in Belfast when I was there for the launch of the women's rugby world cup.  As Senator O'Mahony said, sports tourism is part of my brief, and that is why I am anxious and hopeful we get the rugby world cup in 2023.  Every time somebody comes up from Mayo or Kerry to an all-Ireland final, or from Limerick, the odd time they are here, that is domestic tourism.  Those sporting occasions, such as on Saturday, when Ireland play Canada - we hope they have a victory like they had in Chicago - are domestic tourism.  Again, the two things go hand in hand.</p><p>The Senator also mentioned Brexit.  I view the three greatest threats to the Irish tourism industry as being Brexit, political instability and uncompetitiveness.  Unfortunately, we do not have a role in terms of putting a floor under the value of sterling as that is governed by forces outside our control.  The offering in the Lake District in England, in Wales and in Scotland is going to be far more inviting to the British tourist than it was heretofore.  We have a challenge, which is competitiveness.  As we can do nothing to influence the value of sterling, we need to make sure we have competitive prices, that people are well looked after and that we send them home looking forward to coming back again and, more important, telling their friends and family we want them back again.</p><p>We need a stable political environment in which to do that.  For example, some in this House opposed the 9% VAT rate in a recent budget proposal which would have decimated rural and provincial hotels, restaurants and tourism attractions.  I could not stand such over a situation.  Dublin is in a very strong position but Donegal, where I was on holidays, and Waterford, which I also visited during the summer, are not.  I agree with Senator Grace O'Sullivan that Waterford has a great offering.  In addition, there is nothing stopping Cork County Council, in regard to the coast from Kinsale to the county border close to Youghal, agreeing with Waterford County Council, in regard to the coast from there to Dunmore East, and then with Wexford County Council, to do something like what is being done on the Shannon Estuary between Limerick and Clare.</p><p>To go back to my original point, we need our local authorities to be far more imaginative.  There is a fantastic asset between Dungarvan and Waterford city, the greenway, which is being funded by my Department.  I want to see more of that.  However, I have pulled up the handbrake in regard to greenways recently because I want to see a national strategy developed whereby we would have a national map of Ireland and greenways would not start in the middle of nowhere and end in the middle of nowhere.  Greenways should start in a location where people can get off a bus and take a bike for a cycle, then get back on a bus or train.  With regard to Senator Ned O'Sullivan's home place, we are very anxious to have the great southern trail cross what is almost the Rio Grande into north Kerry and then take it on to Listowel.  I hope that can happen, but in order for it to happen, we need local authorities to do the Part 8 work, undertake the consultations, talk to landowners and agree a platform on the way forward.  I hope to do that over the next number of months.  We will launch a public consultation shortly in regard to the development of greenways.  It is one of the issues I feel very strongly about.</p><p>Senator O'Mahony referred to Knock Airport, which is rightly close to his heart.  Shannon Airport and Kerry Airport are close to my heart and Cork Airport has a very important role, as do the seaports of Rosslare Harbour and Cork.  We want to maximise the number of people who come into Ireland at provincial locations.  One of the ways we can do that is by encouraging the tour operators, particularly coach and bus operators, to start looking at locations other than Dublin.  We cannot force them not to come to Dublin but, if they want to come to the capital city, as Senator O'Mahony rightly said, we at least need to try to get them out into the regions as quickly as possible.  To do that, however, a visitor attraction is needed.  That is why we have brought forward this Bill and we have lifted the cap on spending up to &euro;300 million.</p><p>We have been criticised for not doing enough but there is currently a grant scheme available of &euro;125 million and we are particularly encouraging local authorities and State agencies to apply.  Frankly, when a local authority sends in an application for a grant to do something in their local area and it does not include a feasibility study, it is very difficult to give grant-aid due to the spending rules that have to be adhered to.  Leader companies will also have a role and they have to rise to the mark.  The Department and F&aacute;ilte Ireland cannot do everything.  What we are doing is putting in place a structure that will empower people at local level to look at the success of the Wild Atlantic Way and the success that Ireland's Ancient East will be, and ask how their community can grab onto that.  This is why, in my own area, we have developed a driving route that will start in Loop Head and finish in Foynes, as Senator Ned O'Sullivan said.</p><p>This is enabling legislation.  At some stage in the future, I would like to come back to the House for a general discussion with Senators on how we can develop this product.  While there are constraints, who would have thought, when this country was banjaxed in 2008, that the two industries we would have turned to in order to drag us out of the mire, agriculture and tourism, would have delivered the return they have?  Tourism has come up to the plate.  I want to take this opportunity to thank the people working in the tourism and hospitality sector, my Department officials in Killarney and Dublin, the staff of F&aacute;ilte Ireland and Tourism Ireland.  They do a great job and we work collectively but there is a responsibility that I will now shove over on top of local authorities.  They are going to have to do more and I would expect they will do more.  I ask the Members of Seanad &Eacute;ireann to support me in that.  I know how close they are to the councillors around the country.  I would encourage Senator Ned O'Sullivan in the discussions he has on his grand tour of Ireland, although I hope he does not have to embark on it soon.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#S00200"><p>I am in no hurry.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1267" speakername="Patrick O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#S00300"><p>In all seriousness, when Members come in contact with their councillors, I ask that they put this item on the agenda in their local authorities.  It has the potential to deliver jobs in every part of the country, as Senator Grace O'Sullivan said.  We have an obligation to try to do that.  There is a challenge in doing that but we are up for that challenge, as is the Department.  I welcome the contribution of the Senators.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.88" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#S00600"><p>When is it proposed to take Committee Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#S00700"><p>Now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.91" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.92" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#S00900">National Tourism Development Authority (Amendment) Bill 2015 (Certified Money Bill): Committee and Remaining Stages</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.93" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Bill put through Committee, reported without recommendation and received for final consideration.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.94" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That the Bill be returned to the D&aacute;il."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#S01200"><p>Will I have a chance to speak?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#T00100"><p>I will allow Senator Kevin Humphreys to speak.  He missed his slot.  The Minister of State was responding to Second Stage.  If the Senator has a brief comment to make on the Bill, I will allow him some discretion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#T00200"><p>I will not exploit the discretion the Acting Chairman has given me.  I very much welcome the Bill.  Investment in the tourism industry has brought real dividends.  We must be slightly concerned about the VAT rate.  The Minister of State referred to the 9% VAT rate which I support, although it needs to be a little more targeted.  The Minister of State is right about the Dublin region.  We must question whether we continue the 9% VAT rate.  I accept that it would be very difficult to apply different VAT rates across the country.  The Department should engage with the hospitality sector and inform it that the State, taxpayer and citizen need to see a return.  The hospitality sector in the Dublin region, especially the hotel sector, is operating at capacity.  If they are receiving a preferential VAT rate, there is an onus on employers to consider the long-term unemployed.  They have a social and moral responsibility, especially given that they are receiving a tax break from Central Government.  This tax break comes from the taxpayers and citizens and it is well over &euro;300 million.</p> <p>I have travelled quite a bit within Ireland on holidays, and restaurant prices have increased within and outside the Dublin region.  Much of this relates to demand.  The Minister of State mentioned Killarney.  I was there recently and I also saw a substantial increase in bedroom rates and in the hotel sector.  If we are not going to kill the goose that laid the golden egg, we must ensure we keep our costs under control.  Those costs are not labour costs but exploitation costs.  The Minister of State mentioned that when there is a rugby match on a Sunday or an all-Ireland final, there is often exploitation of people who have to visit the city for those major championships.  If we want them to return and use Dublin as a gateway, they must see value for money.</p> <p>I ask the Minister of State to try to engage with the hospitality sector.  When I was Minister of State at the Department of Social Protection, I engaged with the sector regarding employment opportunities.  A loud and clear message must be sent to the sector that if it wants to keep the benefit of the 9% rate, it must consider our unemployed people and youths for jobs.  We can train them, but if the hospitality sector is not giving them the breaks but is constantly seeking visas for people to come in and work in those areas, it is unacceptable.  We need to clearly tell the hospitality sector that if it does not play ball with us, we will put the 9% rate under the magnifying glass.  Unless the sector considers employing people from the long-term unemployed group, they will lose the 9% VAT rate.  They have got a very good deal and they have a social responsibility to step up to the plate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1267" speakername="Patrick O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#T00300"><p>I thank the Senator and other Senators for making the point.  I agree with Senator Humphreys and that is why one of the first things I did when I was appointed Minister of State was to call in the Irish Hotels Federation and make very clear the Government&rsquo;s dissatisfaction about what is happening in Dublin and certain aspects of the Dublin hotel base.  Unfortunately, we need many more hotel rooms in Dublin.  We cannot magic them up.  If there are planning bottlenecks, we need to ensure they are widened and we can address it.  I view the importance of ensuring we have adequate hotel space in the same way as we view other key pieces of infrastructure that are needed to drive the economy.  In the recent past we have had the advent of a hotel which I was honoured to open, the Holiday Inn Express on O&rsquo;Connell Street.</p> <p>Local authorities can do much more in their areas.  Hoteliers and people in the hospitality industry will say there are many areas in which they would love a face lift regarding street furniture, footpaths and public lighting and the basic infrastructure required to ensure a place is attractive for people to come in and make the massive investment of constructing a hotel.  Senator Humphreys knows exactly where I am talking about.  There are many places in the city that are in dire need of a face lift.  I said so in the D&aacute;il in a debate on 1916.  O&rsquo;Connell Street is one of the key pieces of historic infrastructure in the country.  Although it is of great national significance, it has been let fall over a number of years and by a number of successive councils.  Dublin City Council has neglected North King Street and other areas around this very important area from Heuston Station down to the Customs House, on both sides of the River Liffey.  It has nothing to do with the Government or the Seanad.  Dublin City Council needs to take its responsibility much more seriously.  If we are asking people to come and make massive investments in hotels and accommodation, the very least they should have is a decent level of public lighting and street furniture.</p> <p>The Senator mentioned exploitation and employment opportunities.  In my response to Senator Ned O&rsquo;Sullivan, I mentioned the Limerick and Clare Education and Training Board.  It has a fantastic record of getting employment for people from disadvantaged areas in Limerick in the local Limerick hospitality area.  This is not about work visas but about our ETBs which are empowered under legislation to do the job they are required to do to meet a skills deficit.  If they can do it in Limerick, they should be able to do it in Dublin.  There is no reason the ETBs in this city cannot replicate exactly what is being done in the Limerick and Clare area and give opportunities to young people from disadvantaged areas to get a start in life on the first rung of the ladder.</p> <p>The hotels in the mid-west region, including Clare, Limerick and north Tipperary, will say the initiative being taken in the old Krups factory, now Limerick Enterprise Development Partnership, LEDP, in Roxborough, is key to ensuring there are young people who are interested.  I have met them.  They are up for it and are full of enthusiasm.  They are the front window of Irish tourism and are the ambassadors of the country from the first point people check into a hotel, have a pint pulled, have their dinner put down in front of them or listen to the narrative on a tour bus.  The Senator is correct that we must sort out this element.  There is a blueprint.  I am not in favour of a new quango being established to do something that local ETBs should be doing.  In my role on the leadership group of the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport, I am anxious to push this initiative.</p> <p>I thank the Senators and the Cathaoirleach for allowing the swift passage of this important Bill.  F&aacute;ilte Ireland will hit the funding ceiling very quickly.  We do not want a piece of legislation to block F&aacute;ilte Ireland from making the investment to which all the Senators and Deputies referred.  This gives us the opportunity to ensure the &euro;125 million we have set aside to spend over the coming years is not kept until 2022.  I hope we can get to a situation where I am, or my successor is, back in the House in the near future seeking to have the ceiling raised again.  The only way we will get it raised is if local authorities, local people and local groups make applications to F&aacute;ilte Ireland for money for tourism-related infrastructural projects.  I hope the Seanad supports me when I drive CEOs of local authorities to do the job they were empowered to do under an Act that was passed by the House to ensure tourism is delivered to every crossroads in Ireland.  There is not a parish in the country that does not have something to offer.  I hope, in my time in the Department, I make some sort of difference.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.99" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.100" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 1.40 p.m. and resumed at 2.20 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.101" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#Y00100">Competition (Amendment) Bill 2016: Report and Final Stages</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#Y00200"><p>I welcome the Minister, Deputy Mitchell O'Connor.  I remind the House that a Senator may speak only once on Report Stage, except the proposer of an amendment who may reply to the discussion on the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.103" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 1:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1247" speakername="Mary Mitchell O'Connor" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#Y00400"><p>On the advice of the Attorney General, I am proposing a new Long Title to the Bill because some other Government amendments seek to amend the Competition Act 2002 by inserting a new Part and a new Schedule into that Act regarding the application of section 4 to collective bargaining and agreements in respect of certain categories of workers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#Y00500"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House.  I also welcome the many people who are in the Gallery to represent the various unions that have been campaigning on this matter for some time.  SIPTU, the National Union of Journalists, Equity, the Musicians Union of Ireland and many other unions have a long-standing commitment to reform in this area.  The Bill we are considering on Report Stage today represents the culmination of their long campaign.  I welcome amendment No. 1, which involves the insertion of a new Long Title, as the Minister has said.  My view, which is shared by Senator Nash and our colleagues in the Labour Party group, is that the new Long Title probably more accurately describes the purpose of the Bill, which is to amend the Competition Act 2002 to provide that section 4 of that Act will not "apply to collective bargaining and agreements in respect of certain categories of workers".</p> <p>I remind the House that we are seeking to ensure the Competition Act is amended in this way to make a real change in respect of what occurred in 2004.  As the people in the Gallery and many Members of this House will recall, the Competition Authority ruled in 2004 that a collective agreement between Irish Equity and the Institute of Advertising Practitioners in Ireland in respect of voice-overs provided by freelance workers was in breach of section 4 of the Competition Act 2002 on the basis that each actor was a separate self-employed contractor - a separate undertaking, in effect - and therefore it was unlawful for any group of them to collectively fix prices for voice-over services.  As the people in the Gallery are well aware and have told many of us, this has had a very detrimental effect on the livelihoods of many people involved in voice-over work.  I refer not just to actors working on voice-overs because it is clear that it also had an impact on many other trades, particularly in areas like journalism, performance and the arts.  It has had a chilling effect on photographers, writers, musicians, models and many other self-employed people on whose behalf unions have traditionally collectively negotiated.</p> <p>I should declare a professional interest because as a barrister at the time, I advised the unions on the need to try to resolve this matter by gaining some sort of exemption to the Competition Act 2002.  The view taken by the unions, and now also by the Minister and the Government, was that competition law should not be applied in such a rigid way to these groups of vulnerable self-employed workers and that an exemption could and should be sought in respect of them.  The Bill before the House relies heavily on the original Competition (Trade Union Membership) Bill 2006, which was proposed ten years ago by President Michael D. Higgins, who was a Deputy at the time, in order to permit an exemption of this kind.  Without going into the history in any great detail, a commitment to deal with the matter was then included in the Towards 2016 partnership agreement that was negotiated at national level.  The Bill we are discussing this afternoon, which was introduced in this House by the Labour Party group as a Private Members' Bill in January of this year, seeks to resolve this long-standing matter.  It was not dealt with in Towards 2016 because of the bailout and the troika requirements.  We are glad to see that the matter is being resolved now.  I know the unions will be glad to see it resolved.  We are happy to accept the Minister's amendments as a way of making the Bill a workable solution to deal with vulnerable groups of self-employed workers in respect of whom competition law should not have been so rigidly applied.  This is a proud day for the Seanad because this will be the first Private Members' Bill to pass all Stages in either House of the Oireachtas since the new Government came into office.  I think it is a positive sign of new politics.  I thank the Minister and, in particular, her officials, with whom we have engaged extensively since the Bill was passed on Committee Stage on 6 July last.  I thank the officials for engaging so constructively with us on the text of these amendments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.106" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.107" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 2:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1247" speakername="Mary Mitchell O'Connor" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#Y00800"><p>I am proposing the deletion of section 1.  As my amendments seek to amend the Competition Act 2002 by inserting a new Part and a new Schedule into that Act, it is necessary to define that the "Principal Act" referred to in my amendments to later sections means the 2002 Act.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#Y00900"><p>As the proposer of this Bill, the Labour Party group supports this amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.110" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#Y01100"><p>As amendments Nos. 3, 4 and 6 are related, they may be discussed together by agreement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.112" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 3:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1247" speakername="Mary Mitchell O'Connor" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#Y01300"><p>The need to protect vulnerable self-employed workers was often cited during previous debates on this Bill.  As Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, I have a duty to ensure all workers, regardless of their situations, are protected by robust and transparent law.  The Bill, as initiated, proposes to exempt people other than vulnerable self-employed workers from certain provisions of competition law.  If it were enacted without amendment, it would result in higher costs for those to whom services are supplied by such workers, including consumers, businesses and the State.</p> <p>The amendments I am proposing address the policy objectives of the Bill in a more targeted way, thereby minimising the potential negative costs on the Exchequer.  They allow a trade union to apply to the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation to exempt a particular class of self-employed workers from the provisions of section 4 of the Competition Act 2002.  The trade unions must provide evidence that their members are "false self-employed" or "fully dependent self-employed".  Those categories are defined in the amendments.  In addition, they must provide evidence that there would be no economic effect, or a minimal economic effect, on the market or on costs to the State and that the exemption, if granted, would be consistent with Irish and EU competition law.  In defining a "false self-employed worker" or a "fully dependent self-employed worker", due consideration has been given to the European Court of Justice ruling in the Dutch musicians case and other International Labour Organization deliberations on this topic.</p> <p>The Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation may consult relevant Ministers or other people or bodies about any proposal to make an order to prescribe categories of self-employed workers for whom trade unions have applied for exemptions.  The amendments allow the Minister to refuse an application or revoke an order if market conditions change, but not without due consultation with key stakeholders and full consideration of all the facts.  As it is not appropriate for any ministerial order to be made time bound, the proposed amendment does not do so.  I will endeavour to ensure all applications are considered in the shortest possible timeframe.</p> <p>I am proposing the deletion of section 3 of the Bill, as initiated, which would allow the representative body of any profession to represent its self-employed members who are paid by the State, such as doctors providing health care for the State.  This would, in effect, allow such professionals to set prices.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Mary Mitchell O'Connor:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2284"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2284&amp;amp;pid=MaryMitchellOConnor&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Thus, the Bill as currently drafted would result in a big increase in the cost of services provided to the State by professionals, with obvious negative effects on the Exchequer.<br/><br/>Amendments Nos. 4 and 6 insert a new Schedule 4 into the Competition Act 2002, thus giving effect to a previous Government commitment under the social partnership agreement entitled Towards 2016 Review and Transitional Agreement 2008-2009 - Amendment of the Competition Act 2002.<i></i>The new Schedule exempts those three activities outlined in the Towards 2016 commitment, namely, actors engaged as voice-over actors, musicians engaged as session musicians and journalists engaged as freelance journalists from section 4 of the Competition Act 2002.  The exemption will come into effect when the Bill enters into force and an application for exemption will not be required for the three activities which I have listed in the Schedule.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#Z00200"><p>I join with my colleague, Senator Bacik, in welcoming all the people in the Gallery.  They are my colleagues from Equity, the Musicians Union of Ireland, the National Union of Journalist and SIPTU.  This is a very significant day and I hope all of us will welcome it.  This legislation is long overdue and it is probably worth repeating what Esther Lynch had to say when the Competition Act came into effect.  She stated the authority's decision effectively turned the clock back almost 200 years to the era of the combination laws, which made it unlawful for workers to join together to press their employer for shorter hours and more pay.  As we all know, the consequences over the past decade or more have been particularly harsh on people who make a major contribution to our society, the arts and so many other professions.</p> <p>I must pay tribute to Senators Bacik and Nash in particular as they deserve full credit today.  I chatted yesterday to Senator Bacik and I know there is a long history for her on the issue.  Given what has happened in the past couple of days, it is important to recognise that the best antidote to some of the depressing politics happening worldwide is when all of us can come together and make a constructive difference.  The Minister and Senator Reilly would be more used to me giving out and complaining about this Government - as I do, and I make no apologies for that - but equally I must give credit today.  We have looked at this Bill in detail and the contribution from the Department has been very good.  We must acknowledge that today in particular.</p> <p>I am very happy with all the amendments, and they are significant in particular with regard to definitions, including those for collective bargaining for a self-employed worker.  There has been a reference to the Dutch musician case and to the fully dependent self-employed worker, which relates to the International Labour Organization, ILO, deliberations.  These are significant and the right choices to make.  While it is long overdue, we welcome this.  I hope the legislation will pass smoothly today and I urge the Minister to make great haste, if possible, as these people have waited more than long enough.  It is fair to give everybody credit for what has happened today.  It is a significant day and is it not great to see a Private Members' Bill pass through the Chamber this session?  There should be congratulations across the board.  I should be clear that this Bill has the full support of our party.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#Z00300"><p>I thank Senator Gavan for his words and all colleagues across the floor and on both sides of the House for their support of this Bill.  It took support from all sides to ensure it would reach Report Stage in Government time.  It is historic because not many Private Members&rsquo; Bills have traditionally become law so we very much look forward to this becoming law and welcome the support of all colleagues.  I should say that this, of course, stems from a long-standing Labour Party commitment.  When we introduced it on Second Stage, my colleague, Senator Nash, as a junior Minister had a large part to play in its acceptance on Second Stage by the Government.  I thank the Minister for continuing support for it and bringing it through Report Stage in Government time.</p> <p>We support the amendments proposed by the Minister, which will provide for a new process for two groups of vulnerable self-employed workers to achieve exemption through application by their trade union to the Minister.  The first category is the false self-employed work; this is somebody who is described as self-employed but who is in all but name an employee.  This is the category of worker in respect of whom the European Court of Justice had previously ruled in the FNV Kunsten Informatie en Media case, relating to session musicians in a Dutch orchestra.  In that case, very helpfully, the court set out a list of criteria by which somebody who is described as self-employed may be considered to be falsely self-employed, or in reality an employee.  These are the criteria set out in the Minister's proposed amendment.  We very much support that.</p> <p>There is a second category of worker in respect of whom trades union will be able to apply for exemption to the Minister.  These are people who are not necessarily captured by the false self-employed category and we were very conscious that many of the people who came to us, such as freelance journalists, would not come under the Kunsten case but would rather be better regarded as fully dependent self-employed workers.  We are grateful to the Minister and her officials for working hard on this and the drafting of that was perhaps more difficult because there was not a clear set of criteria set out in a court judgment.  It is helpful to know it derives from ILO sources and we can see other countries, like Germany, where there is a similar sort of provision in place for somebody who might be described as self-employed but is fully dependent on perhaps one or two person for the vast bulk of their income.  As the Minister's amendment indicates, their main income in respect of the performance of their services under contract is derived from not more than two persons.  That will capture a large number of people who have been really disadvantaged by the Competition Authority ruling.</p> <p>Finally, the Bill will also provide a welcome automatic exemption for a third category of self-employed worker, the three groups who were previously specifically mentioned the Partnership 2016 programme and who will now be listed in the Schedule to the Competition Act as automatically exempt.  Those are voice-over actors, session musicians and freelance journalists.  We very much welcome that automatic exemption.</p> <p>I will finish with three points on the amendments.  I am grateful to the Minister for outlining her intention to ensure applications are dealt with speedily.  I raised with the officials the issue of a set timeframe for decision making.  We and the unions would anticipate that although the timeframe is not specified, the Minister would always act expeditiously and speedily in coming to a decision and applying the criteria.  I know the Bill anticipates that the Minister will allow for the application to be made.  For example, there may be guidance as to timing set out in that, which would be very helpful for unions in making applications to the Minister for an exemption.</p> <p>The second point is I understand there is no prohibition on reapplication by a trade union in respect of a class of a relevant category of self-employed worker where, for example, some conditions have changed or a new group of individuals have come into membership of a union and so on.  I am sure the Minister will confirm there is nothing in the Bill to prevent a union from reapplying.  The third point is the timeframe for the Bill's passage into law, and I am very glad to see it will be dealt with in amendment No. 5, with the Act coming into operation no later than three months after the date of its passing.  That is a comfort to the unions and all those who have been engaged in this campaign for so long.  We hope it will speed through the D&aacute;il and I am glad to see a commitment that it will be brought into operation no later than three months after the date of its passing.  We have no difficulty with the deletion of section 3 from our original Bill, as I made clear on Committee Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#Z00400"><p>I will be quick, as the proposer of the Bill has already spoken.  I support the Bill and commend Senator Bacik in her long work in following through on these issues.  It is a very positive step forward.  The Civil Engagement group is very happy to support this.  I commend the Minister and her Department for engaging very constructively in this area.  I echo the points welcoming the definitions, as they will have a valuable contribution and give much clarity to many workers.  I acknowledge the particular exceptions made in respect of artists and those working in the arts.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Alice-Mary Higgins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2480"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2480&amp;amp;pid=AliceMaryHiggins&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The arts sector is in the process of real transformation as it seeks to place itself on a more secure footing and ensure that all can participate, work, make progress and live fully in the sector.  </p><p>I accept and support the legislation.  The amendments have been constructive and I give the endorsement of my group to the Bill.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.119" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to. 



Government amendment No. 4:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.120" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.121" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 5:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1247" speakername="Mary Mitchell O'Connor" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#AA00500"><p>Amendment No. 5 is a standard provision for the Short Title and collective citation.</p> <p>In respect of the commencement of the Act, I may appoint different days for different purposes but in any event all parts shall be in operation three months after its enactment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#AA00600"><p>I have reserved my comment on this matter until we reached amendment No. 5.  I reiterate that I am glad that there is a provision for the coming into force of the Act.  I ask the Minister to confirm, in respect of the earlier amendments, that there is nothing in the Bill to prevent reapplication.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1247" speakername="Mary Mitchell O'Connor" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#AA00700"><p>I confirm that there is nothing in the amendments to stop unions reapplying.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#AA00800"><p>I thank the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#AA00900"><p>I welcome the Bill.  It rights a wrong that existed for quite some time.  It should have been addressed previously and it has now been addressed.  l congratulate Senator Bacik on the legislation.  It is not the first Private Members' Bill that she has put through this Chamber.  It is great that the legislation has come through the Seanad.  I appeal to the Minister and other Ministers to use the Seanad to initiate Bill because I found it useful myself, when I was a Minister, to put Bills through here where we had a reasoned discussion and then the legislation went through the D&aacute;il with very little problem. </p> <p>I welcome the Minister's provision for trade unionists to apply and for confirming that they can reapply.  I very much welcome the fact that there is room for a review where an application is not granted that people feel should have been granted.  It is always good to have a review  process when a decision is made that people feel strongly might not be correct. </p> <p>I congratulate the Minister on all the work she has done on this legislation.  A lot of consultation has taken place, which is only proper and right.  It has allowed for cross-party agreement on an important Bill.  That is important to the many people seated in the Gallery, whom I welcome, and to the many people who cannot be here today.  </p> <p>I have always believed that trade unions are hugely important and exist to protect workers.  They are also very important to Government because one can deal with a group who can seal a deal and have their members partake in a deal.  Rather than having to deal with 25 different disparate groups, one can deal with one group.  Over the years the fact trade unions have been able to make agreements with the Government and employers has been very beneficial to the wellbeing of many people in this country and also the economy. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#AA01000"><p>On behalf of Fianna F&aacute;il I welcome all of the contributors here today.  They are the people on whom this legislation will have a direct effect.</p> <p>It is a red letter day for Senators Bacik and Nash.  They have been here before and I commend them on all of the work that they have done on the legislation.  It is a level headed piece of legislation.  </p> <p>I commend the Minister.  As a Senator, I have found her to be one of the hardest working Ministers around.  She has made herself available to discuss anything about a business matter for anyone who cares to engage with her.  This is the first legislation that has been passed since the formation of the new D&aacute;il and Seanad but that does not happen by chance.  Only for the Minister, her Department and the two Senators who worked hard to push the legislation through, it would not be here.  To follow on from what Senator Reilly said, this legislation is an example of the great work that takes place in the Seanad.  Legislation can be initiated in the Seanad and moved on.  I am curious to know why the Taoiseach is hell bent on cutting the Seanad to pieces.  Reform is the word but I am curious to know what he is trying to achieve.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.128" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.129" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 6:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.130" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#AA01400"><p>The Minister has asked to make a few concluding remarks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1247" speakername="Mary Mitchell O'Connor" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#AA01500"><p>I, too, commend Senators Bacik and Nash on all of the work they have done.  I am delighted to be here today and thank Senators for their nice comments.  It has been a pleasure to put through this legislation because we have all worked together.  I thank my departmental officials for their hard work.  They worked with Senators to make sure that we got the exact sense of what needed to be done.  I am glad for all of the people in the Gallery because they have waited a long time.  I am delighted to be able to do this work.</p> <p>As I have previously noted in this House, while understanding the principle behind the original Bill, the Government had concerns that the legislation, as drafted, went far beyond that objective and would have had a serious impact on the Exchequer.  Along with other Senators, I am delighted that Senator Bacik and the Labour Party's legislation has been passed in Seanad &Eacute;ireann.  I believe President Higgins tried to do this many years ago. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#AA01600"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1247" speakername="Mary Mitchell O'Connor" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#AA01700"><p>It is great that this legislation has been passed.  We have worked hard in a collaborative manner with the Government to ensure a more targeted measure has been agreed and that the focus in the Bill is on vulnerable self-employed workers.</p> <p>I thank my officials for doing this work in a good, efficient and effective manner.  I look forward to similar collaboration in the Oireachtas in the future.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#AA01800"><p>I was going to say a few words of thanks to the Minister for her comments and to thank others.  Perhaps I will  wait until the Bill has been passed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#AA01900"><p>Yes, I will allow the Senator speak at that point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#AA02000"><p>I know others wish to speak at that time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#AA02100"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.139" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Bill, as amended, received for final consideration.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.140" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That the Bill do now pass."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#AA02500"><p>Senator Bacik can make her comment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#AA02600"><p>I am delighted that the Bill has been passed.  I sincerely thank the Minister for her kind comments.  It has been a pleasure to work with her and her officials.  Her constructive approach has been welcome and positive.  I thank her for closely engaging with us on this legislation from the start.  I echo Senator Davitt's words about her capacity for hard work and, in particular, her constructive approach to all of these things.</p> <p>I thank her officials.  In particular, I thank Mr. Kieran Grace, Ms Breda Power and Ms Colette Reilly because they have been so good dealing with us all through the process.  I thank all of those in the trade union movement who have worked so hard for so long on this legislation.  There are too many names to mention but I single out Mr. S&eacute;amus Dooley of the NUJ, who cannot be here but who has worked really hard on this legislation.  Ms Ethel Buckley, Ms Karan O'Loughlin, Mr. P&aacute;draig Murray and many others have also worked extremely hard.  I know other people in ICTU have also actively worked on this Bill.  </p> <p>This is a time of fairly bleak political developments overseas.  This week, we have seen bloated progressive politics internationally, and some of us have already acknowledged the situation in this House.  This Bill is a positive example of constructive legislative work by the Seanad and between the Government and the Legislature.  I hope it is a good example of more to come.  Senator Reilly recalled, as a previous Minister, accepting my Private Members' Bill on the prohibition of female genital mutilation.  It was another example of the Senators working together to pass a Bill and there have been many more, including work done by former Senator Feargal Quinn.</p> <p>Today's Bill is a positive example of constructive work done in a collaborative fashion by an active Legislature.  This is also a good example of the collective rights of workers being asserted against a neoliberal ideology that was applied over rigidly by an authority working within EU law.  We have shown through our work on this Bill, the Government's acceptance of this Bill and through working together on it that other interpretations are possible within EU law.  We have also shown that collective rights can and should be asserted, where necessary, to protect vulnerable groups of workers who would otherwise face a huge amount of disadvantage as a result of particularly rigid approaches.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Ivana Bacik:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2248"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2248&amp;amp;pid=IvanaBacik&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I am grateful to colleagues for their support for the Bill and, in particular Senator Gerald Nash, who had an important role in making sure this Bill came through.  It is a proud day for the Seanad and a historic day for all of us.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#BB00200"><p>I was delighted to have had the opportunity to enable this Bill at an early stage to pass through the Cabinet approval process during the previous Government's term.  Senator James Reilly was a member of that Government too.  Success has many fathers and, indeed, mothers.  Many people in this Chamber have played a role in bringing this legislation to this point today.  I thank the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, Deputy Mary Mitchell O'Connor, for the fact her door was always open and that she took little convincing about the necessity of this legislation passing.  I also thank her departmental officials for their consistent engagement with Senator Ivana Bacik to ensure we have legislation that is workable, practical and constitutionally robust.</p> <p>I recall other colleagues involved in the development of legislation of this nature in recent years.  Our former colleague, Emmet Stagg, attempted in 2012 to get similar legislation passed but, unfortunately, it did not make it through the process.  As Senators Ivana Bacik and Paul Gavan said this is an important day for new politics and progressive politics.  This Chamber has shown its better self in working together to achieve a positive objective for working people.  Ultimately, we are here to represent the interests of citizens of this country.  For several years, we have all been concerned about the rigid determination made by the then Competition Authority in the application of European Union competition law in this regard.  I said in this Chamber previously that EU directives and regulations in this respect have been overly, literally and rigidly applied to many of those sitting in the Gallery today.  I do not believe when these regulations were being drafted by the European Commission that it had Irish session musicians, freelance journalists and others in mind.  It was dealing with regulating major utility and telecom companies and others.</p> <p>Accordingly, it is important we can express ourselves in this Chamber, address deficiencies in the interpretations of our laws and see them amended.  What we are about is trying to improve living standards for our people.  Ultimately, this legislation, collectively viewed with other legislation which will be passed over the next couple of years by the Minister, will see improvements to people's living standards, their opportunities to provide for themselves and their families, as well as to participate fully in our society as active citizens in the economic sectors in which they are involved and work.</p> <p>It is important to point out this is constitutionally robust legislation.  Some legislation in the employment rights field was struck down as unconstitutional in recent years, such as joint labour committee and registered employment agreement legislation.  We have reformed and reconstituted this legislation in recent years to make it constitutionally robust.  I can see a thread and a pattern in this Bill where those lessons have been learned.  Some of the consequent formulae have been applied to this legislation regarding the importance of ministerial orders and laying matters before the House.  It is important the Houses of the Oireachtas have a role in terms of legislation like this.  Those deficiencies have been addressed and the repairs we have provided are reflected in this legislation.</p> <p>Having scrutinised this Bill and the Minister's amendments, it can be argued this is future-proofed.  The world of work is changing rapidly.  Industrial sectors that we have not yet imagined will be born soon.  We need to be nimble and be able to react to them.  There is sufficient flexibility in this legislation to ensure new categories of workers which might emerge in the future are catered for in the context of the protections and supports they need.  Most important, this Bill will ensure the right to be collectively represented and the right to collective bargaining in one's workplace in one's interest to improve one's living standards and opportunities, as well as, ultimately, delivering fairness and decency in every workplace.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.145" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#BB00400"><p>When is it proposed to sit again?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111000002#BB00500"><p>At 2.30 p.m. on Tuesday, 15 November 2016.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-10a.148" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>The Seanad adjourned at 2.55 p.m. until 2.30 p.m. on Tuesday, 15 November 2016.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>