<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.2" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Leas-Chathaoirleach i gceannas ar 14:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.4" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.5" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Paschal Mooney that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport to outline his Department's proposals for the development of the greenway from Sligo to Enniskillen, via Manorhamilton, and to indicate if he will provide the necessary funding for its development.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator John Kelly of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform to abolish the pension levy for retained firefighters, as it does not entitle them to a pension.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Sean D. Barrett of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to review the planned sale of Baggot Street Hospital in the context of the need for more hospital beds in general and the large increase in the population and employment in inner city Dublin and to consider whether the sale should be cancelled.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Paul Bradford of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government to estimate the number of local authority houses which are unoccupied and the number of privately owned properties in the State which are unoccupied and to state his plans to make these properties available for letting. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Gerard P. Craughwell of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Arts, Heritage and the Gaeltacht to outline what steps are being taken to preserve and excavate the Bronze Age track at Mayne Bog, Coole, County Westmeath.</blockquote> <p>I regard the matters raised by the Senators as suitable for discussion.  I have selected the matters raised by Senators Mooney, Kelly, Barrett and Bradford and they will be taken now.  Senator Craughwell may give notice on another day of the matter he wishes to raise.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.7" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#B00100">Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.8" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#B00200">Greenways Funding</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#B00300"><p>I welcome the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Paschal Donohoe to the House.  He is always welcome to this Chamber, seeing he was a by-product of this great Seanad.</p> <p>Senator Mooney has four minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#B00400"><p>I too welcome the Minister.  This is the first time that two people with the name Paschal have been involved in a debate on different sides of the motion.  That is a little bit of history.</p> <p>In November 2013, Leitrim County Council submitted an application to the National Cycle Network, NCN local authority funding scheme 2014-16.  I understand from Leitrim County Council that five projects were funded nationally but the Leitrim project was number six on the list and just lost out.  The matter is a constant source of debate and dialogue in that part of the county.  That application was a single application for the development of the greenway from Drumduff, County Leitrim on the Leitrim-Sligo border to Blacklion in County Cavan, a distance of 40 km, the application contained two clear options for funding one of two distinct phases.  The first option was for a bound surface from Drumduff to Manorhamilton, a distance of 18 km at a then cost of &euro;2.3 million and-or for a bound surface from Mahorhamilton to Blacklion, a distance of 22 km at a cost of &euro;4.3 million.  Leitrim County Council considered that its application had the potential to deliver considerable social, recreational and economic benefit and looked forward to the feedback from the Department on it.  As I have said, the application was unsuccessful on that occasion.  </p> <p>I have raised this issue because the Government has indicated in recent weeks that it will provide extra funding for the development of greenways.  The Taoiseach, as the Minister knows, was present in Moate for the official opening of a greenway in that part of the world.  It was interesting that the chairman of Westmeath County Council, Councillor Paul Daly, referred to that piece of railway track being used in the movie "The First Great Train Robbery" starring Sean Connery.  I remember seeing that film which I would recommend to Members.  This is now part of a greenway that will stretch from Dublin to Galway.</p> <p>The Minister will be very aware of how important tourism is to County Leitrim, which has a very low industrial manufacturing base, in particular the area around Manorhamilton to the Sligo border.  The development of tourism attractions is crucial to the future economic wellbeing of the area.  This can only happen with State aid, as there are insufficient resources within the county council and the local communities to develop the greenway - much and all as they have the will and the desire to develop it.  Everybody is in favour of developing this disused railway track dating from the middle of the last century.  This is not a new issue and I am sure it has been on the Minister's desk, from before the time he took over.  I hope he will have some positive news for me.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1007" speakername="Paschal Donohoe" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#B00500"><p>I thank Senator Mooney for raising this issue.  This is the first time we have dealt with each other on a matter like this.  It is the first time we have had a Commencement matter to address.  What we now need is for Paschal Sheehy to cover this item and then it will be a historic coming together of different Paschals across the country.</p> <p>I agree with Senator Mooney that greenways are making a significant contribution to tourism development across the country and also to sustainable transport.  I am reliably informed that the greenway the Taoiseach opened on Sunday was being actively used by local residents long before it was officially opened, such was the recognition of its use and value.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Paschal Donohoe:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=2244"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2244&amp;amp;pid=PaschalDonohoe&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We are all familiar with various greenways in place across the country that have the kind of economic effect described by the Senator.  We have only to look at the work under way in Waterford and what it is doing in regard to greenway development.  We are all familiar with the success of the greenway in Mayo and the effect it has had on many of the communities located along side it.  The challenge we face in terms of greenways is twofold.  The first is funding, an issue on which I have to respond as Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, but the second - I am not saying it applies to this proposal - is that as we look at expanding the number of greenways in the future, we will have to work to ensure they are all of the quality required and that they are located in and traverse through areas that reflect the best practice of tourism.  F&aacute;ilte Ireland has done much research on the development of greenways across Ireland and Europe.  It is clear they need to be constructed in a certain way and traverse through communities and amenities in a particular way in order to generate the demand that will make these good investments by central Government and local authorities.</p><p>In regard to the particular greenway the Senator has raised, my Department is aware of the proposal.  I acknowledge the quality of the work under way.  In relation to how funding might be imminently drawn down for this project, I confirm it is my understanding that the local authority is putting together a very good proposal on how the greenway could access EU INTERREG funding.  Given the way the greenway is being constructed, I believe it may well meet many of the criteria laid down for this funding stream.  I recommend that this be considered at the first opportunity for two reasons - first, the call for applications for the funding programme will open on 4 December and, therefore, there is a window of opportunity for the greenway to access funding and second, this programme and the way it is constructed makes available a very high percentage of the total amount of the cost of the project.  This particular funding stream has the ability to deliver up to 85% of the total cost which would be a massive contribution to the construction of this greenway were it to be successful.  My Department and I will certainly be available to help in any way we can to support the application and ensure it is as effective and as comprehensive as possible.  As this funding opportunity will be open soon and as it can offer a significant amount of funding, it offers the best opportunity for this project to get funding to allow it to move to construction in the future.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#C00200"><p>I have been made aware of what the Minister has outlined in regard to INTERREG V.  The council is very much on top of this and as the Minister indicated, it is in the process of putting together an application.  However, it begs the question that the Minister is dealing with a local authority with limited resources.  There is a 15% shortfall in funding.  In raising the issue, I did not want to muddy the waters by referring to the INTERREG issue as I wanted to get an indication of the Department's and the Minister's thinking on it, which is supported by Cavan County Council and Sligo County Council.  Sligo County Council is making a separate application for its end of the project.  This project was specifically about Leitrim but there is also the cross-Border element.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paschal Mooney:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=1990"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1990&amp;amp;pid=PaschalMooney&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> I am unsure whether the Minister can give an indication at this point but in the event of Leitrim County Council getting funding and were it to require financial support to fulfil the other 15%, because I do not know from where that would come, would it be a matter for the Department to consider an application from Leitrim County Council?  I thank the Minister for taking this matter and for outlining the importance he attaches to greenways in general and to this one in particular.  I reiterate the Minister can appreciate the reason there is such universal support in County Leitrim for this proposal because it could prove to be a catalyst for the development of further incoming tourist numbers other than residents.  This applies in particular in a region that as a former chairman of F&aacute;ilte Ireland north west, I am aware has the lowest level of visitors of all regions in Ireland because of its peripheral nature and other reasons.  The Minister can understand why I perceive issues like this as being of great importance in the development of a quality tourism product.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#D00200"><p>That is the $6 million question for the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1007" speakername="Paschal Donohoe" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#D00300"><p>Indeed.  I am confident that were the local authority to go ahead with the project and were it to be successful in its application for INTERREG funding, it would be able to find from within its own resources the final 15%, if that was what was required.  In advance of that, however, it might be more sensible for me to state I support the application the council intends to make for INTERREG funding and as Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, I very much recognise the value of this project.  The Senator has already touched on its cross-Border element and I also point to the degree to which I understand it would mirror the Shannon-Erne Waterway for some parts of it at least.  The local authority is doing good work at present in preparing an application and for the time being, it would be wise for everyone to concentrate their efforts on how to best support that application and to cross all those bridges in the future as to how other funding could be found, were that need to materialise.</p> <p>I thank the Senator for raising this matter and agree wholeheartedly it is the kind of project that would make a great difference to allow more people to experience the beauty of County Leitrim.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#D00400"><p>I thank the Minister.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.18" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#D00500">Pensions Levy</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" speakername="John Kelly" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#D00600"><p>I thank the Minister of State for taking this matter.  Many anomalies arise in respect of the infamous pension levy.  My understanding is somebody who works in the private sector and is a retained firefighter does not pay any pension levy by virtue of the amount they earn as a retained firefighter.  A person who is self-employed and is a retained firefighter will pay 4.5% in a pension levy.  However, if one is employed by a local authority as a semi-skilled worker, one pays 10% in a pension levy on one's wages and one pays 10% as a retained firefighter, which is a huge chunk to take from a working family's wages.  Many such individuals are now struggling with both the pension levy and the universal social charge, USC.  I note the welcome changes to the USC announced in the budget and the Minister is to be complimented on that.  Crucially, however, in all these cases of retained firefighters paying a pension levy, they still do not qualify for a pension.  I note members of the Garda took and lost a court challenge on the subject of the pension levy.  They lost it on the grounds they actually were paying into a pension fund, which is why they continue to pay the pension levy.  However, the retained firefighters are not paying into a pension fund but are paying a pension levy.  Therefore, I call for the abolition of the pension levy in this instance and I believe it is in the gift of the Minister, Deputy Howlin, to so do.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1106" speakername="Simon Harris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#D00700"><p>I thank Senator Kelly, on behalf of my colleague, the Minister, Deputy Howlin, for raising this important matter.  The public service pension-related deduction, sometimes referred to as the pension levy, applies to the pay of pensionable public servants.  However, it is not a pension contribution.  The measure was introduced as an emergency measure in 2009 to effect a reduction in the remuneration paid to public servants, including retained firefighters, as a contribution to the necessary reduction in public service expenditure brought about by the financial crisis at the time.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Simon Harris:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=2338"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2338&amp;amp;pid=SimonHarris&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The measure is progressive in that the reduction applied is directly related to the amount of remuneration paid, with those earning more being subject to the greater reduction.  The first &euro;15,000 of remuneration paid is currently exempt from reduction.</p><p>The specific law underpinning the PRD is the Financial Emergency Measures in the Public Interest Act 2009, as amended.  That Act provides that PRD is to apply to the pay, including any non-pensionable pay elements, of public servants who are pensionable.  In this connection, the term "pensionable" is defined in terms that give it a broad reach.  It includes not just membership of a public service pension scheme but also any payment in lieu of such membership.  I understand from the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government that retained fire-fighters have historically qualified on retirement for a one-off, non-recurring gratuity calculated at one eighth of their annual retainer payment multiplied by the number of years of actual service up to a maximum of four times the annual retainer.  To qualify for the gratuity, a retained fire-fighter must have a minimum of two years service.  The maximum gratuity payable is four times that of the annual retainer and retained fire-fighters do not pay any contribution to that gratuity.</p><p>Retained fire-fighters in place in 2008 and those hired thereafter until the end of 2012 were given the option of joining the local government superannuation scheme and receiving a pension and retirement lump sum based on their pensionable remuneration and length of service.  All retained fire-fighters appointed after 1 January 2013 must join the single public service pension scheme.  Section 2(1)(b) of the Financial Emergency Measures in the Public Interest Act 2009 provides that any public servant who is a member of a public service pension scheme or who is entitled to benefit under such a scheme or receives a payment in lieu of membership of such a scheme is subject to the deduction.  The payment of the one-off gratuity at retirement to retained fire-fighters who are not members of the superannuation scheme constitutes a payment in lieu of membership of the pension scheme and, as such, all retained fire-fighters, regardless of whether they are members of the public service pension scheme, are subject to the deduction.</p><p>I will address the recently announced plans by the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform for the reduction of the pension levy as it applies to all public servants, including retained fire-fighters - which, I am sure, will be good news and welcomed by the retained fire-fighters - when the Senator has had a chance to respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#E00200"><p>The Senator may ask a brief supplementary.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" speakername="John Kelly" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#E00300"><p>In the first sentence of his response, the Minister of State said "the public service pension-related deduction, sometimes referred to as the pension levy, applies to the pay of pensionable public service."  As stated earlier, they do not pay into a pension fund.  I appreciate that they receive a gratuity.  It is a one-off payment and is not a pension.  I think there is a difference.  They were still entitled to that gratuity prior to the introduction of the pension levy, as an emergency measure, in 2009.  As matters are improving, consideration should be given in these cases to exempting retained fire-fighters.  I would appreciate it if the Minister of State could bring this matter to the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform and ask him to re-examine it.  Garda&iacute; took a case and they lost it purely because they were paying the pension levy.  Being assured of a gratuity is different.  If a case was taken to the courts in this instance, what would be the outcome?  I would appreciate whatever the Minister of State can do to improve the lot of these retained fire-fighters.  When a guy is working with a local authority, pays 10% on his wages - which are &euro;28,000 or &euro;29,000 - then gets another &euro;16,000 as a fire-fighter and has to pay 10% on that, it is a heavy burden on families.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1106" speakername="Simon Harris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#E00400"><p>I agree fully with the Senator that it is a heavy burden on families.  The Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform and the Government are very eager to reduce that burden.  I concur with the Senator.  He quoted the first sentence of my response.  I reiterate that, in legislation, the term "pensionable" is defined as not just membership of the pension scheme but also any payment in lieu of such membership.  Without being technical about it, that is the legal basis as to why the position is as it stands.</p> <p>As the economy grows, the absolute priority of the Minister and the Government is to reduce that burden on public servants.  We all know the very positive impact that retained fire-fighters have in all our communities throughout this country.  The agreed proposals brought forward by the Minister - these are in line with the Lansdowne Road Agreement and will be subject to the enactment of the recently published Financial Emergency Measures in the Public Interest Bill 2015 - will provide a significant reduction of the PRD burden on all public servants, including retained fire-fighters.  This follows on from a more modest reduction in the rates applicable, which were agreed under the terms of the Haddington Road agreement.  The latter was implemented in January 2014.  The new Bill, which we will debate shortly in this House and the Lower House and which we will, hopefully, pass into law, provides that the threshold in annual earnings below which the pension-related deduction is not applied will increase from its current level of &euro;15,000 per year to &euro;26,083 per year on 1 January 2016 and will increase to &euro;28,750 per year on 1 January 2017.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Simon Harris:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=2338"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2338&amp;amp;pid=SimonHarris&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This substantial relaxation of the PRD, as proposed in the new FEMPI Bill, will mean significant income gains for all affected public servants and, more particularly, ensure  a significant proportion of public servants will be fully exempt from the PRD by 2017.  Many retained firefighters would be expected to be among those exempt entirely from the PRD in this way, assuming their only public service remuneration consists of their retained firefighter earnings and that they are not simultaneously working in other public service jobs.  </p><p>The message from the Minister and the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform and the Government is that as the economy has continued to improve, we are now in a position to reduce the burden.  If the legislation is passed, the threshold will be increased this January from &euro;15,000 to over &euro;26,000 and from January 2017 to &euro;28,000, which will remove many public servants, including many retired firefighters, from the PRD net, which I am sure will be welcomed by all.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.26" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#F00200">Hospital Services</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#F00300"><p>I welcome the Minister for Health, Deputy Leo Varadkar.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#F00400"><p>I, too, welcome the Minister.  The last time I met him in person was at the funeral in Dundalk last Thursday.  I was with him this morning via the use of technology during his interview on &quot;Morning Ireland&quot; on the care of people in hospitals outside the jurisdiction.</p><p>I tabled this issue for discussion in the Commencement debate having read in a newspaper article that Baggot Street Hospital was to be sold for &euro;14 million.  According to Department of Health archives, there were 193 beds in the hospital, which equated to a capital cost of approximately &euro;73,000 per bed.  In terms of their replacement, according to data from the HSE capital spending programme, the cost of the provision of 50 beds at Tralee General Hospital is &euro;9.4 million, while the cost of the provision of 100 beds in Ballincollig hospital is &euro;19.47 million, which equates to approximately &euro;190,000 per bed.  I am concerned about the bad value being obtained by the Department of Health in the sale of Baggot Street Hospital, particularly in the context of the Minister's remarks this morning on having to send people abroad, the widespread recognition - there is no one more avid in recognising it than the Minister - of lengthening hospital waiting lists and future shortage of capacity in hospitals.  <i>Prima facie,</i>it does not appear to be a good deal to sell the 193 bed spaces at Baggot Street Hospital for &euro;14 million.  Is it worth investigating whether it would be more useful to retain them in the system, in which, as the Minister will agree, they are badly needed?</p><p>Having read the data, I estimate that approximately 674,000 bed days have been lost in the city centre of Dublin following the closure of the Adelaide Hospital, Sir Patrick Dun's Hospital, Dr. Steeven's Hospital, Mercers Hospital, the Meath Hospital, St. Vincent's Hospital on St. Stephen's Green, the National Children's Hospital, Jervis Street Hospital and the Richmond-St. Lawrence's Hospital.  Following the sale of Baggot Street Hospital, a further 62,000 possible bed days will be lost.  It is also proposed to remove beds from Holles Street Hospital and the Rotunda Hospital.  Based on an analysis of the last population census in Dublin, prepared by Mr. Jamie Cudden of Dublin City Council, Mr. Brian Hughes of the Dublin Institute of Technology and Mr. Declan Redmond and Mr. Brendan Williams of the School of Geography in UCD, we are moving hospitals away from the direction in which the people are moving.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Sean D. Barrett:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2370"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2370&amp;amp;pid=SeanDBarrett&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->They found a 62% increase in Dublin city centre between the 1991 census and the 2011 census.  They stated that the increase reflects the high level of apartment building in the inner city from the late 1980s onwards.<br/><br/>They point out that the rest of the Dublin City Council area had a decrease of 1.2% in the population between 1991 and 2011.  We all want hospitals near where people live, which is increasing in the city centre, and where people work, which happily is increasing in the city centre.  Is this deal justifiable given the need to have hospitals near where the people are and an area of rapidly increasing population?  I was surprised to read what the three scholars found about the increase in the population in the centre of Dublin.  <i>Prima facie</i>, it does not look like good value for money to do so, given the cost of replacing those beds elsewhere.<br/><br/>In his interview with Cian McCormack this morning, the Minister welcomed anything that throws up cost comparisons.  I had tabled the motion before I heard the Minister speak, but it is in that spirit.  I agree with him; if it turns out that what we have before us today does not make financial sense, at least we will have discussed the hypothesis.  He said that anything like that strengthens his case for spending.  He mentioned keeping taxpayers' money in Ireland when he has debates with his colleagues.  It could also shorten waiting lists and strengthen his case for more funding.<br/><br/>In that spirit that we are all on the one side on this particular issue, does the closure make sense given the location of the patients?  Does it make sense given the cost of beds in our health service?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/948" speakername="Leo Varadkar" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#G00200"><p>I thank Senator Barrett for raising this matter and for giving me the opportunity to advise the House on the proposed sale of the old Baggot Street Hospital complex.  This facility, like much of our health-care infrastructure, dates from around the mid-1800s.  As a consequence it is of limited use as suitable accommodation for the delivery of modern health services.  The complex also contains a number of protected structures.</p> <p>Therefore, given the age of the complex and its protected status, the cost of upgrading the buildings to meet modern standards for health-care accommodation would be prohibitive.  If it were still in use as an inpatient hospital, we would be planning to rebuild it on a new site, as we are with other hospitals of a similar vintage, like the Rotunda, Holles Street and Temple Street, for example, all of which will be replaced by new modern hospitals in the next ten years.</p> <p>The inability of older facilities like Baggot Street Hospital to respond to changing health-care needs and medical technologies impedes the efficient delivery of modern health care and the development of clear care pathways.  Old facilities also have much higher recurring costs.  The costs of meeting sustainability targets on energy alone would be prohibitive.  The national energy efficiency action plan sets a public sector energy efficient target of reducing energy usage by 33% per annum which is to be achieved by 2020.</p> <p>In addition, the HSE must comply with the Government's green procurement guidelines.  These require public bodies to ensure that a minimum building energy rating of B3 is achieved in all new build and leased buildings from January 2012.  From January 2015 the minimum rating is A3.  We have to reduce the number of environments where inadequate infrastructure is determining how resources are spent.</p> <p>In an improving property market, the HSE sees an opportunity to leverage the sale of Baggot Street Hospital.  The proceeds of the sale will deliver accommodation for primary care and community services in central Dublin.  The balance of the proceeds will fund modern accommodation for mental health services.  The new primary-care and community-care facilities and the redevelopment of the old hospital complex will revitalise the surrounding area.</p> <p>It is Government policy to enable people to easily access a broad spectrum of services in the community through their local primary care team.  Therefore, the development of primary-care health services is central to the Government's objective to deliver a high-quality, integrated and cost-effective health-care system.  This ensures health care is delivered in the most appropriate and economic setting.  Our key objective is to ensure that the right facilities are provided to support best practice models of care, and that they are suitably located, efficiently designed and appropriately procured to serve the health needs of communities.  In addition to providing the most appropriate health care to the local resident population, those employed in the surrounding area may also access these services.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#G00300"><p>I thank the Minister as always.  I am concerned that the big increase in the city centre population is not being factored into much of our planning for the future of the city centre.  In addition, those who work in the city centre need access to hospitals.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Sean D. Barrett:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2370"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2370&amp;amp;pid=SeanDBarrett&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->As a person who lived in the city centre for a long time, I am aware that hospitals such as the Adelaide had a significant place in the local community.  Such hospitals were really valued as institutions.  Hospital beds have moved out of the city centre at such a rate, even though the population is moving back in.  Reference was made to energy costs.  The cost of replacing 193 beds is substantially in excess of what we will get for selling the 193 bed places.  I am concerned that sometimes there is too much emphasis on the age of buildings in terms of Irish hospitals when the waiting lists reflect people wanting more staff, which I know the Minister has addressed and on which he has reported to this House.  Is there an edifice complex?  Is the HSE determined to rebuild the entire hospital stock when people would like more doctors and nurses?  Is the capital budget put under full appraisal?  Reference was made by the Minister to energy costs but the wage costs, the medical costs and the cost of people being on waiting lists are greater.</p><p>I do not know how far the sale has progressed but perhaps in the light of what the Minister said this morning and the high cost of sending people abroad, if they avail of their entitlements under the European laws to which he referred, we might adopt a revised attitude to dispensing with old hospitals, in particular in areas where so many of them have been shut down and turned into office blocks and given over to other uses.  One could ask whether some of those decisions were short-sighted.</p><p>When the Minister was responsible for transport, I discussed with him the re-opening of the railway line between Connolly Station and Heuston Station.  Instead of Dr. Steevens' hospital becoming the headquarters of the HSE, and an office block, it would have been an ideal location for a hospital because people from all parts of the country, from Dundalk to Tralee, could go to the station across the way.  I would welcome more planning in terms of those issues.  I am sure I will discuss this matter with the Minister from time to time but there are factors that must be taken into account.  I thank the Minister, as always, for his reply and I wish him well in his post and in his endeavours.  Perhaps this particular sale does not support the goals which we jointly share.  Go raibh maith agat, a Chathaoirligh.  I thank the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/948" speakername="Leo Varadkar" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#H00200"><p>I have not had a chance to visit Baggot Street yet but I am due to visit it in the next couple of weeks and to take a look at the place for myself.  To the best of my knowledge, it is not used as an inpatient hospital any more, it is used for other services.  Perhaps some short-stay services are provided but it is not used as an acute hospital, so to do what Senator Barrett proposes would mean turning it back into an acute hospital.  That would have a very high cost associated with it, which the HSE Estates believes is greater than to build something from scratch.</p> <p>There are big problems with the old hospital buildings.  Very often one has 20 to 30 beds to one toilet and because the buildings are old, it is very difficult to put in additional toilets.  While that sort of thing might have been acceptable in the past, that is no longer the case.  Increasingly, our building standards for hospitals require people to be either in private rooms or to at least have 3 m on either side of their bed for infection control, which cannot be achieved in an old building.  Such buildings also have very high running costs.  There are enormous difficulties getting medical gases in because one has to pipe through stone walls sometimes.  In addition, much of the new equipment, including the big X-ray machines, cannot fit through the doors and into the rooms in old hospitals where the only equipment they might have had in the old days was an X-ray machine.</p> <p>The point the Senator made about the city centre and the fact the population is moving back there is worthy of consideration.  Most of the old city centre hospitals, in effect, moved out to the suburbs.  If I remember correctly, Jervis Street was one of the ones that went out to Beaumont and the Adelaide and the Meath hospitals went out to what is now Tallaght hospital.  That reflected the fact that at the time, the suburbs were burgeoning and the city centre was emptying out.  As the Senator rightly pointed out, good planning, good transport and common sense suggest that we should move people back into the city centre in the years to come.  That process is already under way.  If we were to increase the bed stock in the city centre area, it would make more sense to put new wings and new blocks into the likes of the Mater, St. Vincent's and St. James's hospitals.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Leo Varadkar:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=2192"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2192&amp;amp;pid=LeoVaradkar&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->There are already three major hospitals not far from Dublin city centre.  Accordingly, putting in a fourth one, with all the costs associated, would have to be considered.  An opportunity does potentially arise over the next five to ten years because several existing city centre hospitals will become vacant.  These include Crumlin, Holles Street, the Rotunda and Temple Street.  Consideration will have to be given as to how they could be used for alternative health care purposes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#J00200"><p>I thank the Minister for giving his experience as a hospital doctor which is better than that of any economists.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.36" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#J00250">Housing Provision</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1205" speakername="Paul Bradford" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#J00300"><p>I thank the Leas-Chathaoirleach for allowing me to raise the matter concerning the vacancies in public housing stock across the country, as well as the many vacancies in the private housing sector.  I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Ann Phelan, to the House.</p> <p>The Government seems transfixed with rent certainty as it seems to be a cause of ongoing internal debate around the Cabinet table.  However, the certainty we require concerns the supply of local authority housing and the allocation of vacant properties.  Figures presented in the other House several weeks ago indicated almost 3,000 vacant local authority houses are available for repair and, hopefully, allocation.  In County Cork alone, between the city and the county, there are approximately 700 such houses.  It is very difficult for the tens of thousands of people on housing waiting lists to see these statistics and how 3,000 local authority houses have not yet been allocated.</p> <p>Obviously, some of these houses require some degree of refurbishment.  All of us as individual public representatives, however, have come across cases where houses which have become vacant are in excellent condition, almost turn key, but there is still a lengthy delay in their allocation.  Recently, I inquired about a house in the Cork area which, to the very best of my knowledge, was in a condition that would make it available for letting immediately.  When I asked in September whether it would be made available in October or November, I was told it would probably be next February or March.  That is unacceptable.  We must ensure that once a house is vacant and is in a fit condition for letting, it should be let in the immediate future.  At a time when tens of thousands of people are on housing waiting lists, it is unforgivable that such vacancies occur.  Will the Minister of State let me know what the Government is doing to ensure these 3,000 vacant houses will be made available to people on social housing lists as soon as possible?</p> <p>There are also tens of thousands of vacant private dwellings across the country.  Many of these were previously not available for letting.  At a time of an acknowledged housing crisis and when rural, as well as small town and village, depopulation is a critical social problem, we have to examine all solutions.  Does the Minister of State have statistics from her Department or the CSO on the number of vacant private dwellings?  We have to devise some scheme to encourage the letting of these properties.  While I am not a major fan of tax breaks or incentives, mainly because they have left a long disastrous legacy, we may have to look at putting schemes in place to encourage the repair and refurbishment of some of these properties for letting.  There have been schemes, such as rural resettlement, which have been tremendously successful.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paul Bradford:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=73"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=73&amp;amp;pid=PaulBradford&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->One size does not fit all and that must be at the core of our thinking with respect to our housing problems.  The Cabinet might be having internal debates about rent certainty but there is the issue of vacant local authority houses and the issue of there being probably thousands upon thousands of vacant private houses across the country.  Our towns and villages are dying off.  A significant number of people - although, admittedly, not the majority - on housing lists in our larger cities would be willing to take up the offer of a tenancy of a good house in a rural area if the proper procedures were put in place.  We must be more joined up in our thinking in regard to the housing crisis.  Tens upon tens of thousands of people are looking for houses, there are tens upon tens of thousands of vacant houses across the country and it is not good enough that we cannot marry those two statistics into a solution.  </p><p>I ask the Minister of State for an update on the number of local authority and private houses that are not occupied and to indicate the Government's intentions and plans in that respect.  The Government's debate on housing must stretch far beyond rent certainty and into the territory of making those houses available and getting them filled as soon as possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/964" speakername="Ann Phelan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#K00200"><p>I thank Senator Bradford for raising this very important issue.  I know that the issue of vacant local authority housing, or voids as they are called, has been a topical one, given the need to address the waiting lists and to make best use of the existing stock, while the extensive programme of new build that the Minister, Deputy Kelly, has put in place with the local authorities is advanced.  The issue of voids and the reletting of them has always been an issue with elected public representatives on local authorities.  The time it takes to redo a house and relet it has always been a bone of contention.</p> <p>An important point to make is that there is no fixed number of vacant local authority houses.  The numbers change constantly across all the 31 authorities, as tenants move in and out of social housing.  General statistics on local authority housing stock, including vacant units, are published annually by the Local Government Management Agency as part of its service indicators for local authorities and are available on its website.</p> <p>Recognising that there had been a build-up of vacant social houses for a number of years, in 2014 my Department introduced a new programme to support local authorities in returning voids to productive use.  More than 2,333 units were remediated under that programme, which is targeted at lettable units and making them energy efficient.</p> <p>For 2015, given the continuing need to make social housing available as early as possible, we are supporting local authorities to tackle another 2,500 vacant units.  In addition, I should point out that local authorities also do their own work on the more routine relettings, where a lower level of expenditure is involved.</p> <p>The key focus of the Minister is on ensuring that Exchequer support is made available where it is needed to complement the work that local authorities do under their own resources.  The allocation of targets for a further 2,500 units this year is in response to the number of vacant, lettable units that local authorities have identified to my Department.  Exchequer funding to the authorities is on condition that the accommodation will be occupied immediately following the works, with priority given to homeless families to the greatest extent possible.</p> <p>In regard to privately-owned properties, there are currently in excess of 323,000 tenancies registered with the Private Residential Tenancies Board.  The private rented sector has more than doubled in size in recent years with one in five households now accommodated there.  My Department does not have the power to direct private property owners to let their properties.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Ann Phelan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=2293"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2293&amp;amp;pid=AnnPhelan&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->However, under the Department's housing assistance payment, HAP, scheme, eligible households can source their own accommodation in the private rented sector and rental payments are then made electronically, directly to the landlord, on behalf of the tenant.  More than 4,300 households are being supported by HAP across the pilot local authority areas operating the scheme, with more than 2,000 unique HAP landlords involved in those tenancies.</p><p>In summary, therefore, the Government is responding comprehensively to the social housing challenge through the Social Housing Strategy 2020 and in respect of vacant social houses, the necessary support is being given to the local authorities to get units back into use for those on the waiting list.  As for private rented accommodation, the roll-out of the HAP scheme, which is now progressing well, provides an important vehicle for ensuring that this type of accommodation can also be brought into play to assist in meeting social housing needs.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1205" speakername="Paul Bradford" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#L00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for her response.  I acknowledge she is concerned; the Government is concerned as is everybody else. However, we require action rather than concern.  Will the Minister of State simply reflect on the fact that it is unacceptable that houses should be vacant for so long?  This might require a change in the law.  Certain housing applicants would be willing to move into a house and carry out minor repairs.  However, houses are not being let because a lock or a pane of glass is broken or there is a minor internal difficulty.  I ask the Minister of State to reflect on that.</p> <p>Will her officials also examine the current housing application form?  Many people apply for a council house, as they are entitled to do, to qualify for the HAP scheme but the council housing application form is detailed.  It is 20 pages long and one would need a PhD.  The fact that people who have lived outside the country for one month or six months or 12 months have to obtain certification from authorities abroad that they do not have properties in those countries adds greatly to delays.  These blockages could be waived.  The Minister of State will be aware from her time on the council that every applicant for a council house has his or her application checked by a housing officer who physically calls to him or her.  I cannot understand why a 20-page form is required.  When the Leas-Chathaoirleach and I were members of Cork County Council, a one-page form did the job every bit as well and it was a much quicker process.  There is a great deal of daft bureaucratic red tape which should be waived and written out of the script.  If we want to make progress in filling vacant houses, we have to use a little cop-on and common sense.  I ask the Minister of State to examine these minor issues.  A housing applicant almost requires a PhD in form filling before he or she can even submit a form to the local authority, which is unnecessary.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/964" speakername="Ann Phelan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#L00300"><p>I take the Senator's points.  We have had discussions about using common sense and joined-up thinking.  We are also considering a rural repopulation programme within rural economic development, RED, zones but that would not be on a statutory footing.  It would be a voluntary repopulation programme.  We are in the process of developing that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.43" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 3.25 p.m. and resumed at 3.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.44" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#O00100">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#O00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, motion regarding the proceeds of the sale of Aer Lingus, back from committee, to be taken on the conclusion of the Order of Business, without debate; and No. 2, the Marriage Bill 2015 - Second Stage, to be taken at 5 p.m., with the time to be allocated to group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes and that for all other Senators not to exceed five minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#O00300"><p>I see the Leader intends to take No. 1, which deals with the disbursement of the proceeds of the sale of the State's share in Aer Lingus.  Those proceeds amount to &euro;335,272,562.50.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Darragh O'Brien:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2178"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2178&amp;amp;pid=DarraghOBrien&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I raised this matter before it was referred to the committee and asked that a commitment be given that when it was referred back from it, a debate would be held on it because the very reason the State had this money was that it had robbed Aer Lingus, Dublin Airport and former SR Technics pensioners and pension fund members, 15,000 of whom effectively and arbitrarily had had their pension entitlements cut.  Many Members will know, particularly colleagues in the Labour Party who had given them promises that they would deal with this issue and reneged on these promises-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#P00200"><p>On a point of order, is it correct to say somebody - a Government or anybody else - robbed something?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#P00300"><p>As long as a person is not named.  Perhaps the Leader of the Opposition might be a little more selective.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#P00400"><p>Let me put it this way.  If I was to get &euro;100 at the end of next week, as promised by my employer and underwritten by the State in legislation, and the State then passed a law to take back &euro;40 of that &euro;100 from me, without my consent, I would call it robbery.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#P00500"><p>So would I.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#P00600"><p>That is what it is.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#P00700"><p>I would call it pilferage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#P00800"><p>Will Senator Darragh O'Brien, please, make his point in order that we can move on?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#P00900"><p>More than 5,000 retired members, people in their 70s, 80s and 90s, who worked for Aer Lingus, the Dublin Airport Authority and SR Technics, or Team Aer Lingus, as it was, have had six weeks pay taken from them.  There are also deferred members of long-standing.  A man I met last night who is due to retire and draw his pension later this year after 42 years service has had a 48% cut to his pension entitlement.  The T&aacute;naiste gave indications last year that she would, in some way, shape or form, move towards reducing these cuts and a number of Labour Party members at the Labour Party conference actually signed a motion to look for fairness in this regard, but they have reneged on this completely and utterly.  I do not think anyone in the House can say, in any way, shape or form, that what has happened to airport pension scheme members, IASS members, is fair or equitable.  The reason the Government did it was simply to write off the debt in the pension scheme before it sold Aer Lingus.  Therefore, the reason the State has &euro;335 million-plus is it robbed the airport pension scheme members; it is as simple as that.</p> <p>I asked last week, when the Government referred the matter to the committee, that when it was referred back, that we debate it in order that I would be able to debate it with the Minister, Deputyj Paschal Donohoe, to see if there was any way the Government would look at reducing the level of cuts, which have been absolutely scandalous, for this group of workers and retired members.  It had never happened before in the history of the State that a profitable company was allowed to run down its pension scheme.  Complicit in this was the legislation brought forward by the Government to enable it to happen.  I am, therefore, proposing an amendment to the Order of Business that No. 1 be taken with debate.  What does the Minister have to hide?  Let him come here and tell us what he is going to do.  He has an extra &euro;335 million that he wants to put into a connectivity fund, whatever the hell that is, but it is not acceptable to take the matter without debate.  I will be pushing the amendment to a vote.</p> <p>On another very serious matter, the report issued today on the assessment of paramilitary activity, with a particular focus on the role of the Provisional IRA, as currently constituted in the Sinn F&eacute;in movement, I ask the Leader to ensure we are given time to read the report and debate in the Seanad, given the implications for democracy, both in the Republic and the North of Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#P01000"><p>I know colleagues across the floor would again wish to join me in offering our sincere condolences to the families of those who died so tragically in the fire in Carrickmines.  The first of the funerals are being held today and it is appropriate that we remember them today, particularly so soon after the funeral of Garda Tony Golden which took place last Thursday.</p> <p>On a happier note, I welcome the appointment of Professor Philip Lane to replace Professor Patrick Honohan as Governor of the Central Bank.  Of course, Professor Lane is known to us as the holder of the chair of political economy at Trinity College Dublin.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Ivana Bacik:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2248"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2248&amp;amp;pid=IvanaBacik&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I congratulate Professor Lane on his new appointment.</p><p>Senator O'Brien referred to the independent report on paramilitary activity in Northern Ireland that was issued today by the British Secretary of State, Ms Theresa Villiers.  It would be useful to have a debate on that report in due course, once we also see the report by the Garda Commissioner on paramilitary activity which, as I understand, is due to be published later today.  I had a brief look at the report published by the British Government which has found that the structures of the Provisional IRA remain in existence, albeit in reduced form.  One line in the report is quite chilling when one considers the context and reality on the ground in Northern Ireland.  That line is: "Our firm assessment is that, to different degrees, the leaderships of the main paramilitary groups are committed to peaceful means to achieve their political objectives."  It is very welcome to see an assessment made that there is a commitment to peaceful means, but the phrase "to different degrees" must worry any reader.  It would be helpful to explore and debate in this House the nuances in that report and in the Garda Commissioner's report that we will see later today.</p><p>I commend Graham and Helen Linehan on their work with Amnesty Ireland in producing a video that was launched in Belfast last night and the screening of which I was privileged to attend this morning.  The video, which is called "Chains", is narrated by Liam Neeson and concerns the experience of a pregnancy involving fatal foetal abnormality.  It calls for repeal of the eighth amendment, the campaign for which is being spearheaded by Amnesty under the heading of "She is Not a Criminal".  The campaign seeks to change the criminalisation of women-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#Q00200"><p>Disgraceful.  They should stick to what they know best, which is looking after prisoners of conscience.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#Q00300"><p>-----and challenge-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#Q00400"><p>The couple in question would know better than the Senator about this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#Q00500"><p>Amnesty should be looking after prisoners of conscience.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#Q00600"><p>Senator Bacik, without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#Q00700"><p>I ask colleagues to do me the respect of not heckling on this important point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#Q00800"><p>It is the same song every day.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#Q00900"><p>I ask colleagues to look at this powerful, two- or three-minute video, "Chains", the message of which is about the need to repeal the eighth amendment to safeguard the health of Irish women.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#Q01000"><p>That is a fallacy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#Q01100"><p>All colleagues, particularly male colleagues across the House-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#Q01200"><p>It is a fallacy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#Q01300"><p>-----would benefit from watching it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#Q01400"><p>On a point of order, it should be put on the record that Ireland has an exemplary record on protecting rights-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#Q01500"><p>That is not a point of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#Q01600"><p>It is the point Senator Bacik is attempting to undermine.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#Q01700"><p>It is not a point of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#Q01800"><p>Try telling that to the women-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#Q01900"><p>The Senator is attempting to undermine medical services in this country to pursue her own agenda.  That is what she is doing and it is a disgrace.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.76" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#Q02100"><p>Senator Mooney can make that point when it is his turn to speak.  I have called Senator Barrett.  If Senators keep interrupting each other, I will adjourn for 15 minutes.  I do not mind.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#Q02200"><p>That is fine.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#Q02300"><p>I echo what Senator Bacik said about Professor Philip Lane and the tributes paid to him by the Minister for Finance, Deputy Michael Noonan, as he assumes the office of Governor of the Central Bank of Ireland.  It is a quarter of a century ago that he came to my scholarship class before going on to Harvard and Columbia.  I am sure he will bring many talents to his new post.</p><p>In the presence of Senator Eamon Coghlan, who knows much more about international athletics than I do, I express my regret that we are losing our national boxing manager, Mr. Billy Walsh.</p><p>I compliment Mr. Justin Trudeau, who was elected as Prime Minister of Canada this morning.  The Canadian crest includes the <i>fleur-de-lis</i>, rose, thistle and shamrock, the latter in recognition of Ireland's role as one of the founding nations of Canada.  We should be very proud of all that Irish people in Canada have accomplished, including such persons as Thomas D'Arcy McGee who drew up the constitution of the Canadian Confederation in 1867.  Mr. Trudeau is returning to the house where he lived as a boy when his father was Prime Minister.  I take this opportunity to thank the outgoing Canadian Government, which was always a great friend to Ireland.</p><p>I share Senator O'Brien's misgivings regarding No. 1 on the Order of Business today.  The Secretary General of the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport refused to appear at a meeting of the transport committee to discuss this matter on the basis that to do so would infringe Stock Exchange takeover rules.  I have always regarded a democratic parliament as being far superior to such rules-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#Q02400"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#Q02500"><p>-----particularly when one considers the &euro;64 billion that was secured for the banks on 29 September 2008.  The Minister of State at the Department of Finance, Deputy Simon Harris, heard that debate and could confirm that nobody supported what was done.  Whether or not one likes privatisation is not really the issue.  I did not like this particular one and have opposed it in this House.  I thank colleagues for their indulgence in the matter.  In the budget this year, Ervia is putting &euro;250 million into the Exchequer, which is to be allocated to housing.  The priority should not be to give the Aer Lingus money back to the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Sean D. Barrett:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2370"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2370&amp;amp;pid=SeanDBarrett&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Consideration should be given to spending it on social priorities such as housing, education and the health service.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#R00200"><p>And pensions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#R00300"><p>Yes.  As my colleagues, Senators Norris and Darragh O'Brien, both indicated, it should be spent on the pensions.  The Government has rewarded the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport for the way it treated the Joint Committee on Transport and Communications by giving it another &euro;350 million of pocket money to spend on electric trains and whatever else it wants.  Connectivity is facilitated by aircraft.  However, the Department sold the aircraft - wrongly, in my view - so why give it this money?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1187" speakername="Hildegarde Naughton" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#R00400"><p>I wish to refer to the reports relating to the commission of burglaries in the Knocknacarra area of Galway by drug-fuelled individuals, a matter which has received attention in the press today.  It has been alleged that the perpetrators of the many burglaries being committed in the area to which I refer are out on bail.  While I stress that these are only allegations, I wish to highlight the fact that this morning the Garda seized &euro;250,000 worth of drugs in Galway.  This shows that the force is constantly monitoring the situation relating to drugs in the region.  I remind Senators that the Minister for Justice and Equality has commenced the passage of the Criminal Justice (Burglary of Dwellings) Bill 2015.  The Bill is targeted at those repeat offenders who have previous convictions and who are charged with multiple offences relating to residential burglaries.  It strengthens the provisions for the refusal of bail and provides for tougher sentencing for repeat home burglaries.  It was also announced this morning that the Garda will receive a large fleet of high-powered vehicles that will allow officers to conduct high-speed pursuits, particularly on major roads.</p> <p>In the light of the allegations relating to the commission of burglaries in the Galway area and elsewhere, I have asked the Minister for Justice and Equality to meet me to discuss the matter.  I ask the Leader to invite her to come before the House to debate the issue of crime.  If resources are needed to tackle this issue, then they must be provided.  We cannot have a situation where people do not feel safe in their homes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#R00500"><p>I ask the Leader to convey the sentiment of the House, which I like to think I reflect, on the resignation of Billy Walsh who, up until yesterday, was employed as head coach of the Irish boxing team by the now discredited Irish Amateur Boxing Association, IABA.  Perhaps the Leader will convey our compliments to the Minister of State at the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Michael Ring, the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport and the Taoiseach who have come out strongly in support of Mr. Walsh.  His resignation is both a national scandal and a disgrace, particularly when one considers the proud record of Irish boxers under the leadership of Billy Walsh and his team.  We have now lost his expertise.  As a small country, we can ill afford to lose his expertise to the United States, one of the largest countries in the world.  It will be dreadful to see Billy Walsh wearing the stars and stripes of America - and facing up to the green, white and gold of Ireland - at the boxing championships at next year's Olympics in Rio.  I ask the Leader, when conveying the shock and dissatisfaction that all of us feel about the manner in which the IABA has handled this matter, to raise questions regarding the funding given to that organisation.  I am not suggesting that this funding should be withdrawn because such a move would affect boxers throughout the country, both those at elite level and individuals who box in local gyms.  I refer, in particular, to youngsters who are starting out in their chosen sporting career.  This matter should afford the Government an opportunity to raise questions about the way in which the IABA has gone about its business in respect of this matter.  Even the Irish Sport Council, through its CEO, John Treacy, has expressed its exasperation with the failure of negotiations.</p><p>I am a member of the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Transport and Communications, which deals with sport and which is due to meet tomorrow morning.  This issue will almost certainly be raised at that meeting and I shall use the opportunity to call for the IABA or whomever has responsibility in this regard to be brought to account.  We cannot afford to lose such expertise in any area of Irish life, particularly in view of the small size of our country.  It is just not acceptable that we should lose this level of expertise in a sport which was under-represented for many years but which has proven to be one of our most successful areas of endeavour in recent times.  The latter is the result of the structures that were put in place.  Mr. Walsh has admitted that the structures predate him but he continued with them.  Now we are faced with a massive gulf in expertise due to the loss of somebody who provided expertise, guidance and support to Irish boxers.  The IABA should feel ashamed about the situation.  It should clarify matters and explain how this situation arose because we are in dark regarding what has occurred.  With the exception of issuing a statement expressing hypocritical regret last evening, the IABA has remained silent.  I commend to the House an article by Vincent Hogan, published in today's issue of the <i>Irish Independent</i>, which provides the background to how all of this happened.</p><p>Finally, I commiserate with my colleague, Senator Comiskey, who did not make it on to the nomination list last week.  I am genuinely sorry that he was unsuccessful but wish him well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#S00100"><p>I call Senator Hayden.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#S00200"><p>I appreciate that it does afford an opportunity to put on the record that, irrespective of the media comments at the weekend about the political directions, Fianna F&aacute;il will be seeking a mandate from the Irish people for Deputy Miche&aacute;l Martin, as Taoiseach, after the next election.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#S00300"><p>The Senator has exceeded his time.  In fairness, the leaders have each got three minutes and I hate to see the second speakers taking four minutes.  I call Senator Hayden.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#S00400"><p>I wish to make a brief reference to a recent European Central Bank report which stated that between 2009 and 2013 Irish people lost more of their personal wealth than any other eurozone country.  Many of those who lost their personal wealth, lost the bulk of their savings and the values of their pensions.</p> <p>It has come to my attention recently that an approach was made, as I understand it, to the Minister for Finance by a particular company which acquired assets at the bottom of the market in this country.  These are assets that Irish people have bought and paid for and which they and their children will be paying for over the next number of decades.  It is unacceptable that companies that have acquired assets at below market rates are influencing Government policy when it comes to housing.  At the end of the day, what is important are the people of Ireland, the roofs over their heads and the homes in which they live.</p> <p>I ask the Leader to arrange for a broader debate on the whole issue of Irish housing, who has acquired it, what has happened with NAMA, what has happened with all the vulture funds that have acquired Irish assets cheaply and, in my opinion, below market values, because, as I said, it is the Irish people who will pay for this for the next number of decades.  This Parliament and other former Governments looking across the way here will have to answer to the Irish people on how we managed the value of Irish assets during the decades of the financial crisis.</p> <p>One other debate I seek relates to the under 26s who, as I said on the night of the budget, did not receive, as other groups did, some of the restoration of their rights, particularly when it comes to payments.  I call for a broader discussion on the issue of youth policy in relation to payments to young people, the system of support for third level education grants and the wider issues that affect young people in society. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#S00500"><p>With regard to No. 1, I completely disagree with the Leader that it should be taken without debate.  This is a debating Chamber.  The people in Aer Lingus have been swindled out of their pensions.  It is devastating that people have their pensions cut in half at a time of economic difficulty.  If one compares this with what happened in Waterford Glass where the Government found the money to pay off the pensions, it is outrageous that this House should pass a measure allowing the Government to transfer almost &euro;350 million without paying the pensioners from the company that is being dissolved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#S00600"><p>Hear, hear.  It is outrageous.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#S00700"><p>It is an absolute disgrace and a reproach to this House that we should take it without debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#S00800"><p>Daylight robbery.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#S00900"><p>I wish to raise the issue of the eighth amendment.  My church was completely against the eighth amendment.  I was against the eighth amendment.  It is a disgrace that third parties outside a relationship should dictate to people such as Graham Linehan and his wife who have a non-functioning pregnancy where there is literally no real child, that they should continue for nine months being asked, "Are you hoping for a boy or a girl", and "Have you got an extra room".  It is a disgusting human situation.  I thought we had matured beyond this stage.  The Irish people have gone beyond this but Irish politicians lack the guts to tackle this issue.  I welcome what Mr. Linehan has said.</p> <p>Like Senator Hayden, I also heard the announcement on the wireless today that Ireland lost the most during the economic crisis.  Who won?  The winners of the Second World War, of course, Germany.  We lost &euro;18,000 per individual in this country, the Germans made &euro;33,000 per individual in the country because we stupidly picked up the gambling debts of the German banks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" speakername="Jim D'Arcy" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#T00100"><p>Last Thursday in my local village of Blackrock, County Louth, I attended the funeral of my near neighbour, Garda Tony Golden.  The Taoiseach was present, as was the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Frances Fitzgerald; Deputy Miche&aacute;l Martin; the Garda Commissioner, my colleague, Senator Terry Brennan; and many other politicians and public figures.  The funeral also was attended by many thousands of garda&iacute; and a sombre local community who feel so much for Garda Golden's widow, Nicola; his three beautiful children; his mother-in-law and father-in-law who live in the village; and his own mother, father and family from Ballina, together with the extended family.  It was a dastardly deed and words cannot express its horror or the legacy it has left for the family.</p> <p>I welcome the forthcoming provision of additional resources for the Garda to deal with criminal activity engaged in by so-called republicans in the Border area.  Today Mr. Mark Durkan has called for a special task force to be set up.  I echo that call which echoes the report produced by Members' esteemed colleague, Senator Paul Coghlan, and his team on this criminality.  I also note that the IRA's ruling body, the Army Council, has today been declared to still exist in a report by Secretary of State Villiers.  She states it has a wholly political focus, but anyone who knows anything about republicanism and its ideology knows that the IRA Army Council was always a political body and, in fact, considers itself to be the legitimate government of this country.  I ask that both the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade, Deputy Charles Flanagan, and the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Fances Fitzgerald, come to this House to outline the implications of that statement, particularly as it goes on to indicate that Provisional IRA members believe-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#T00200"><p>T&aacute; an t-am istigh.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" speakername="Jim D'Arcy" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#T00300"><p>I apologise.  They believe the Army Council oversees both the IRA and Sinn F&eacute;in with an overarching strategy.  I wish to hear what the implications of this are and ask the aforementioned two Ministers to come to the House because this is an all-Ireland issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#T00400"><p>The Senator has made his point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#T00500"><p>T&aacute;imid ag smaoineamh ach go h&aacute;irithe inniu ar an dream den Lucht Si&uacute;il at&aacute; &aacute; gcur inniu tar &eacute;is gur cailleadh iad sa tine uaf&aacute;sach sin i gCarraig Mhaigin an tseachtain seo caite.  Ba mhaith liom comhbhr&oacute;n a dh&eacute;anamh lena muintir agus lena dteaghlach ar fad.  T&aacute; s&eacute; thar a bheith br&oacute;nach mar l&aacute; d&oacute;ibh si&uacute;d.</p> <p>I was happy to attend a presentation this morning by Women's Aid in which it called for a number of issues to be addressed.  Members of the Seanad, in particular, have had a good record in this regard and it would be timely for them to have another debate on some of the issues raised by Women's Aid.  The presentation highlighted the issue of resources, in that all systems supporting and assisting women and children experiencing domestic violence or leaving abusive relationships should be fully resourced.  Women's Aid has also highlighted a number of pieces of legislation that should be brought up to date and into line with the Istanbul Convention and the EU victims directive.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2363"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2363&amp;amp;pid=TrevorOClochartaigh&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It has also highlighted the issue around relevant staff of all statutory systems that provide assistance to victims being trained, resourced and informed about domestic violence and the need to ensure accurate data and statistics on domestic violence for the planning, delivering and evaluating responses to women and children experiencing abuse.  It is, unfortunately, an issue that is on the increase.  Based on my experience on the joint policing committee in Galway, the figures are increasing.  I have listened to groups, such as Domestic Violence Response in Oughterard, Riverside House and others, and they tell me that their resources are being cut back and that they are finding it very hard to deal with the increase in the numbers of people calling on their services.  Even though we raised issues here a number of years ago in regard to Dolphin House and its facilities, the situation is getting worse, so it is important for us to have a debate about the issues highlighted by this group and other groups to see what policy changes can be made and what proposals are in place concerning resourcing.  Now that we are being told that we have turned the corner, certainly in the context of the budget, we need to see where the extra resources will be made available and how the extra moneys to organisations like Tusla will be employed, particularly in the area of domestic violence.  Ba mhaith liom iarraidh ar an gCeannaire smaoineamh ar d&iacute;osp&oacute;ireacht d&aacute; leith&eacute;id sin a reacht&aacute;il.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" speakername="Eamonn Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#U00200"><p>I would like to add to Senator Mooney's comments because my phone has been ringing off the hook over the past number of days with regard to the resignation, if I may call it that, of the great Billy Walsh.  My response to people has been that there is nothing I can do.  They have said, "Well you're a Senator, you should be able to raise the issue and do something about it."  Last week, we referred to the amateur boxers who were competing in the world championships and wished them well.  I congratulate the Irish Amateur Boxing Association, not because we won gold, silver and bronze but on the "shamamateurism" of the organisation.  There is public outcry as a result of Billy Walsh's resignation.  I can understand the support he is getting from the public because he has proven to be one of the most successful coaches in the history of Irish sport.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1196" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#U00300"><p>Like all things, we destroy them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" speakername="Eamonn Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#U00400"><p>His biggest problem was that he became too successful.  I certainly know that one is never regarded as a prophet in one's own land.  I got to know Billy Walsh at the Olympic Games in Seoul in 1988.  Over the years since, I have found him to be a very humble, proud and brilliant leader in our sports community.  He is the ultimate professional.  He leaves no stone unturned in his preparation.  His high-performance structures in Ireland are the envy of the rest of the world.  He has gained trust among the boxers and that is very hard to do.  He has gained the trust of the Irish Sports Council over the years and, in particular, the trust of the fans.  He does not have an ego.  He allows his results to dictate.  The biggest problem is that he hurt the ego of the green blazers.  He became too big in their eyes and they had to take him down and wear him out.</p> <p>We, as taxpayers, have funded the IABA to the tune of many millions of euro over the past eight, nine or ten years.  Why did we do this?  While the money was well spent, it was because we produced world, Olympic and European champions.  It was also because we had a high-performance coach in Billy Walsh who was not even given the opportunity to be called the high-performance director - something he wanted.  He wanted to bring his team around but those in the IABA would do it.  Like Senator Mooney, I question the systems that exist in the IABA.  It does not want to give Billy Walsh the power.  It does not want to give the Irish Sports Council the opportunity to dictate terms to it, so it is time to review and to question funding and the IABA's ability.  There is an old motto, "If it ain't broke, don't fix it."  The IABA's motto is, "If it ain't broken, let's break it."   Yesterday was a sad day.  It was the biggest fight Billy Walsh had to go into and, sadly, it was against his own organisation.  I wish him well because the IABA drained him and forced him to throw in the towel.  I know that when he goes to the US, he will be welcomed with open arms, revered and respected but I know that at the Olympic Games in Rio de Janeiro next year, if there is an American fighting against an Irish person, his heart and soul will be with that Irishman and Irishwoman.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#V00100"><p>I second Senator Darragh O'Brien's amendment to the Order of Business.  I also take this opportunity to welcome to the Public Gallery Dr. Keith Swanick who will contest the forthcoming Seanad by-election on behalf of the Fianna F&aacute;il Party.  Dr. Swanick is from Castlerea.  I wish him well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#V00200"><p>That is not relevant to the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#V00300"><p>I think it is appropriate that I would-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#V00400"><p>I have ruled on the matter.  The Senator should not abuse-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#V00500"><p>Dr. Swanick comes from County Roscommon and practises in Belmullet.  He is a very successful young man who will make be a major addition to this House.</p> <p>I also ask the Leader to arrange for the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, Deputy Bruton, to come to this House to review the Personal Injuries Assessment Board which was established more than ten years ago by the then Minister, Mary Harney.  The board processed more than 31,576 claims last year and made 12,420 awards totalling &euro;281 million.  </p> <p>The cost of car insurance is spiralling out of control.  In many cases, premiums have increased by 25%.  The reason for this is the quick settlement of claims, some of which are allegedly fraudulent, to avoid having to go before the courts to fight them.  I recently came across a case involving an accident that occurred last Christmas and involved only a scratch to a car but in respect of which six months later a claim was made in respect of whiplash.  How a person could experience whiplash six months after an accident is beyond me.  Companies such as Liberty Insurance and others are settling such claims rather than fighting them in court but the people who are paying for these claims are the people paying for insurance.  We must fight fraud.  If I do not get results in this particular regard then, using parliamentary privilege, I will act on behalf of the public to name and shame companies in this House, as I did in relation to price increases.  In one particular case, because of an uncontested claim, a young man now has to pay &euro;5,000 per annum to insure his car which he needs to get him to a job he has been offered in County Kildare.  </p> <p>My request is a reasonable one.  The Leader is very responsive to requests and I ask that he ensure the Minister, Deputy Bruton, comes to this House to discuss the issue of insurance and how we can rid ourselves of fraud and fraudulent claims.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#V00600"><p>An article in today's edition of <i>The Irish Times</i>regarding drink driving convictions states that in some parts of the country the conviction rate is below 20% and in others the average conviction rate is higher than 68%.  This raises very serious questions about how summonses are prosecuted, including whether there is a defect in the manner in which they are presented by the Garda, whether there is a defect in how they are being dealt with by the courts or whether we have an extremely efficient and hardworking legal profession in some parts of the country and not in others.  There are serious questions that need to be asked about this matter.  It is appropriate that the matter be debated in this House.  I acknowledge that there are some changes proposed in this area but there are questions around this issue that need to be answered quickly.</p><p>I have defended cases successfully in the District Court because that is my job.  However, it must be borne in mind that in many road traffic accidents a person may have lost a mother, father, son or daughter because the driver of one car was over the legal alcohol limit.  We must address this matter in the fastest possible way to ensure appropriate penalties are imposed on persons caught driving while over the legal alcohol limit.  As we approach Christmas, the current message is that the risk is worth taking.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Colm Burke:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2353"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2353&amp;amp;pid=ColmBurke&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->That is the one concern I currently have.  We are now approaching that time of the year when people need to be more careful and should not be taking risks.  While I have no objection to people having a drink, I have a problem with people drinking and driving.  It is something we need to be conscious of.  We should have a debate and the Minister for Justice and Equality should give some explanation for the wide variation in convictions across the country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" speakername="Feargal Quinn" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#W00200"><p>I was very impressed to read yesterday of the Taoiseach's enthusiasm for cycling and for cycle runs, particularly the one in the midlands.  Our attention has been drawn to the opportunities for Ireland in the area.  Apparently some 20 million people in Europe cycle and Germany alone has 70,000 km of cycle runs, but we have practically none.  We have the opportunity to do something about that and increase our tourism facilities to give those tourists opportunities to do that cycle run.  I think particularly of the western rail link that goes from Collooney in County Sligo to Athenry in County Galway.  It is available and would take very little to put it into operation.  All it needs is determination and enthusiasm.  If we can do that we will be able to benefit tourism to a very large extent.</p> <p>On this week every year for about 22 years I have stood up here and pointed to something else we could do.  Next Sunday let us take the first steps towards joining Central European Time so that we get that extra hour of daylight every evening.  It is quite bright now at 4.20 p.m., but it will not be next week.  Next week it will be like that at 3.20 p.m.  Let us ensure we can do something about that.  We do not want to do it on our own; I know an effort has been made to do so.  A large number of British Members of Parliament are also enthusiastic about taking that extra hour every evening and doing it for the entire year.  The way for us to do that is to join Central European Time.  I believe we can do it.  We should not do it on our own because I do not want to see a barrier between Dundalk and Newry or between Belfast and Dublin.  There are a sufficient number of people in Britain and Northern Ireland who would say, "That's a step we can take."  It will help our tourism and it will help reduce energy and other costs.  More than anything else it will make us all feel better every evening of the year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" speakername="Terry Brennan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#W00300"><p>I welcome the announcement by the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Fitzgerald, that &euro;5.3 million is to be spent on 260 new Garda vehicles between now and the end of this year.  These vehicles will be used to assist the Garda in pursuit of mobile gangs using high-powered vehicles.  These 260 vehicles will be added to the 370 vehicles that have already come into operation so far this year.  They will be used to tackle the scourge of highly mobile criminal gangs committing crimes throughout County Louth and across the country.  The Minister, Deputy Fitzgerald, has allocated &euro;5.3 million to provide the Garda with additional high-powered vehicles, marked and unmarked patrol cars, cars for surveillance, motorcycles for high-visibility policing and vehicles for public-order policing.</p> <p>This investment will support the Garda in carrying out more visible and responsive patrols on our motorways and in rural communities.  The extra vehicles will give it the resources to increase surveillance of criminal gangs and to enhance night-time public-order policing.  The Government will have invested more than &euro;34 million in new Garda vehicles since 2012.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#W00400"><p>And no one is driving.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" speakername="Terry Brennan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#W00500"><p>This is a massive increase on the &euro;4.8 million - one eighth - provided by the previous Government between 2009 and 2011.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#W00600"><p>Outrageous.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" speakername="Terry Brennan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#W00700"><p>In July the Minister, Deputy Fitzgerald, published the general scheme of a new bail Bill to strengthen the law and get tougher on serious and repeat offenders who are out on bail.  This new law will result in a clampdown on repeat burglars and will support garda&iacute; who work extremely hard to catch these repeat offenders.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Terry Brennan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2360"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2360&amp;amp;pid=TerryBrennan&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->If you could bear with me, a Chathaoirligh, I wish to welcome-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#X00200"><p>Senator Brennan is well over the limit.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" speakername="Terry Brennan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#X00300"><p>-----and acknowledge the announcement of the deployment of 27 additional garda&iacute; to Dundalk Garda station.  I hope the decision will make a difference to policing along the Border in north Louth and south Armagh.  I commend Commissioner O'Sullivan on taking this initiative soon after the murder of Garda Tony Golden in Omeath just ten days ago and the death of Detective Garda Adrian Donohoe in January 2013.  I am deeply concerned at the dastardly crimes that have been committed, as is my colleague, Senator Jim D'Arcy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#X00400"><p>I find it very sad that Amnesty International, which has done so much good work over the years, has tainted its human rights credentials, not only by promoting legalised prostitution and the cause of pimps and users of persons in prostitution, but also in its virulent campaign for legalised abortion.  It is disturbing to see promoters of legalised abortion using the tragic cases of those whose child has been diagnosed with a severe foetal abnormality as the wedge issue on which to destroy the eight amendment in this country when the reality is that those campaigners want to see abortion legalised in far wider circumstances, starting with but not confined to people with disability generally.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1119" speakername="James Heffernan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#X00500"><p>Ah, give over, R&oacute;n&aacute;n.  Jesus.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#X00600"><p>In their world, if one is not what they call "wanted", one is not worthy of life.  It is wrong and dishonest to invoke the fact that there are criminal sanctions for women in terms of abortion.  There are criminal sanctions for women in every abortion regime as well.  I challenge Senator Bacik and others in the sense that I would support removing all criminal sanctions for women in the case of abortion if they would support the retention of criminal sanctions for abortionist doctors and others involved in this process, which is tragically destructive.  Those who propose abortion have a tragically destructive world view that is exclusive of other human beings.</p> <p>Ba bhre&aacute; liom d&aacute; bhf&eacute;adfaidh an tAire Talmha&iacute;ochta, Bia agus Mara teacht isteach anseo chun labhairt faoin gcl&aacute;r g&eacute;an&oacute;ma&iacute;ochta agus sonra&iacute; mairteola.  T&aacute; f&eacute;idearthachta&iacute; m&oacute;ra ag baint leis an sc&eacute;im seo, mar a bhaineann s&eacute; le r&eacute;imse na mairteola ach go h&aacute;irid, ach mura gcuirtear ina lu&iacute; ar fheirmeoir&iacute; na t&iacute;re seo go bhfuil tairbhe nach beag sa sc&eacute;im seo d&oacute;ibh, n&iacute; bheidh aon rath uirthi.  Ba ch&oacute;ir don Aire teacht os comhair an T&iacute; chun cuntas a thabhairt d&uacute;inn ar fhorbairt na sc&eacute;ime seo.  Caithfear rannph&aacute;irt&iacute;ocht na bhfeirmeoir&iacute; sa sc&eacute;im seo a chinnti&uacute; agus go pr&aacute;inneach.  M&aacute; theipeann ar an Roinn &eacute; seo a dh&eacute;anamh, t&aacute; inmharthanacht chuid mh&oacute;r de theaghlaigh na t&iacute;re seo i mbaol d&aacute;ir&iacute;re.</p> <p>I would like if the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine could come to this House-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#X00700"><p>T&aacute; an t-am istigh.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#X00800"><p>-----to explain the beef data and genomics scheme from which many farmers have withdrawn in recent times.  This is very important for the quality of beef output in the country.  Many fine farmers feel the scheme is not worth the trouble or they do not buy into it because they have not found themselves in agreement that this is important in terms of improving the quality of beef outputs.  Many farmers look at finishing traits but they do not necessarily take into account the traits of the mother and other factors in cattle breeding.  That is most important if we are to have a long-term development in the quality of beef output.  It took many years to achieve that in the dairy sector and perhaps the Department is trying to achieve it in a very short period in the beef industry.  It would be good if the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine were to come to the House to discuss this important programme and we wish to hear how it is progressing, why the Government believes farmers have been pulling out of it, and what the Government intends to do about that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#X00900"><p>I join with the calls of colleagues for a debate with the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Fitzgerald, on crime and the resources being made available.  I very much welcome the Government's increased commitment to properly resourcing the Garda and adding 600 new recruits this year as a major attempt to come to terms with the very mobile and dangerous criminals roaming the countryside and terrorising people in their homes.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Michael Mullins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2368"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2368&amp;amp;pid=MichaelMullins&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I want to see further investment in technology to help apprehend the people concerned and keep a trace on them after they have committed a certain number of offences.  We need to look at the issue of the tagging of dangerous criminals.  Civil liberties groups will be unhappy with a statement such, but the civil liberties of people living in rural areas and cities who are being terrorised in their homes and having their lives changed forever are being seriously infringed.  We should do everything possible to ensure repeat offenders are put out of business once and for all.</p><p>I welcome the support of Deirdre Clune, MEP, a former Member of this House, for a motion in the European Parliament calling for the global abolition of the death penalty.  I saw some staggering figures in this regard.  It is hard to believe 2,466 people in 55 countries were put to death in 2014, a 23% increase since 2013.  They included several women who were stoned to death for committing adultery in Pakistan, Nigeria, Iran and Saudi Arabia.  Eight states - Mauritania, Sudan, Iran, Saudi Arabia, Yemen, Pakistan, Afghanistan and Qatar - still have the death penalty for homosexuality, while 33 other states apply it for drug-related offences.  This is a serious human rights issue.  Will the Leader organise a debate with the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade on how Ireland could spearhead a campaign in the European Union to get agreement and put pressure on other countries to get rid of this barbaric sentence?  It is not acceptable in 2015 that 2,500 people will be executed.  I am always concerned about a miscarriage of justice in such cases.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1119" speakername="James Heffernan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#Y00200"><p>At this time of year there is the ancient Celtic festival of Samhain, a time when we think of loved ones who have passed.  Those of the Catholic tradition will visit the graves of dead family members and friends in the next couple of weeks.  I spoke to one such mother this morning.  It is with her permission that I refer to the murder of her son, Paul Quinn, on this day in 2007.  He was lured to a farmhouse in Tullycoora, County Monaghan, on the pretence that he would move cattle with three friends.  When he got there, he saw that his friends were being held hostage.  In the following our up to ten armed and masked men proceeded to pulverise him with cudgels with nails.  They finished him off with iron bars.  When his mother, Breege, saw him lying in a hospital bed in Drogheda, she was told by the doctors that there was nothing left to fix.  With her husband, Stephen, and all those who live in the communities of south Armagh and north Monaghan, she has known for a long time that the IRA still exists.  I have been saying it, too, in this Chamber for some time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#Y00300"><p>Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1119" speakername="James Heffernan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#Y00400"><p>It exists in those communities which it rules through the utmost fear and intimidation.  Not one of those called in over the death of Paul Quinn spoke one word to the authorities.  They sat in stony silence.  To the IRA killers of Paul Quinn I hope the doors of the other world will be opened and that they will be haunted by his murder.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator James Heffernan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2362"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2362&amp;amp;pid=JamesHeffernan&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->If they are men they will come forward and hand themselves over to the authorities.  I appeal to people in that area who have information and who may be sheltering those murderers to come forward also with that information.  We have heard today that, contrary to what Sinn F&eacute;in has been telling us, the IRA has not left the stage and that it is still directing the production.  We need to know who is the tail and who is the dog and who is in control of what.  We need an urgent debate following on from the statement today by the Secretary of State for Northern Ireland, Theresa Villiers, about the state of play of paramilitarism across Northern Ireland and across our State as well.  We need that to happen as a matter of urgency.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1196" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#Z00200"><p>I rise to request that sufficient speaking time be granted to allow all Members to make their contributions to the debate on the Marriage Bill later today.  I have raised the matter of speaking time for Independent Members on a number of occasions since I was democratically elected to this House last year.  I am long enough around to know that every organisation must have its standing orders under which to operate but it is high time that the Standing Orders of this House were examined and reformed as the institution itself needs reform.</p> <p>Having won, by way of election, the privilege to serve my country as a Member of this House, I am committed to fully debating legislation and other issues as they come before the House.  I know also that Members present here today and every day are equally committed.  However, there are those, a small few, who are Members of this House who appear so infrequently in the Chamber that it beggars belief that they would accept a salary of &euro;65,000 a year for the job.  Clearly, their external occupations are more important than the important work of the national Parliament.  What is worse is that some of these people have speaking time available to them with a higher priority than me despite attending the Seanad and the Joint Committee on Education and Social Protection----- </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#Z00300"><p>With respect, the Senator is jumping the gun slightly.  As I understand it, and the Leader will clarify this, the debate that will take place later on the Bill to which the Senator referred, is open-ended.  In other words, it does not have to be concluded this evening.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#Z00400"><p>If Senator Craughwell was listening during the Order of Business, he would know that there is no time limit on that debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1196" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#Z00500"><p>I accept that but there are issues with respect to this matter and if I would be allowed to conclude what I stood up to say, it might clarify them.  This House and its Members have long been accused of being a useless drain on public moneys.  It is hard to defend this view when some who have been given the privilege to serve do not bother to turn up to debate some of the most important, humane and, perhaps, bravest legislation introduced by any Oireachtas in the history of this State.  Worse still, if one of those habitual absentees turned up when there was just enough time remaining in a debate for one speaker, they would have priority over me-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#Z00600"><p>With all due respect, this is not an appropriate matter for the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1196" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#Z00700"><p>-----notwithstanding my attendance record.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#Z00800"><p>Members may be absent for different reasons.  It is wrong to cast aspirations by making general statements.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1196" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#Z00900"><p>If the Leas-Chathaoirleach allows me to finish he will understand from where I am coming on this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#Z01000"><p>I clearly understand that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1196" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#Z01100"><p>I fully understand that Members of this House are away on business frequently and I respect that.  I further respect the elected Members of this House in the way they participate and their dedication to this House.</p> <p>I have sometimes sat here for a number of hours waiting to make my contribution, only to depend on the generosity of the Chair or another Member to share speaking time.  Sometimes I have been told there is no time left as happened, for example, during the debate on the budget last week.  I will be writing to the Committee on Procedure and Privileges today to request an urgent review of how speaking time is allocated in this Chamber.  I will be asking how a group, the Independent group in this case, can refuse membership to one who attends the Chamber while granting membership to absentees, some of whom are rarely seen in this Chamber.  I will be writing to An Taoiseach, as the leader of the Government, to ask him what briefing-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#Z01200"><p>The Senator's time is up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1196" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#Z01300"><p>-----he gave to his nominees when he appointed them as I expect elected Members of the Seanad can speak for themselves.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#Z01400"><p>The Senator was allocated two minutes and he has already used four minutes.  I am trying to be fair to him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1196" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#Z01500"><p>I have 30 seconds left.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#Z01600"><p>No.  The Senator does not have 30 seconds left.  He was allocated two minutes and he has used four minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1196" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#Z01700"><p>I request that I be given a further 30 seconds.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#Z01800"><p>I ask the Senator to conclude but much of what he has put on the record would be more appropriate to put to the Committee on Procedure and Privileges.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1196" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#Z01900"><p>Sometimes, things have to be put into the public domain.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#AA00200"><p>Not necessarily on the Order of Business.  There are other ways of raising them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1196" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#AA00300"><p>Sometimes it has to be done this way.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#AA00400"><p>I will allow the Senator ten seconds to conclude.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1196" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#AA00500"><p>Like the Leader and many other Senators who are here because they want to be here, I respect the privilege of serving in this House.  I want nothing more than to be allowed to do the job I was elected to do.  I want in future to ensure there is time for every Member to add to whatever legislation comes before the House.  I thank the Leas-Chathaoirleach for his indulgence.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#AA00600"><p>The Senator's point prohibits me from letting Senator Healy Eames speak as we are over the time.  He referred to Members coming in late looking for speaking rights.  He exceeded his time and we are over the time allocated.  I am not trying to personalise this but we are five minutes over the allocated time.  I call the Leader to respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#AA00700"><p>Senator O'Brien made the case in respect of Aer Lingus but this has been debated at length in the committee and, therefore, I do not propose to amend the Order of Business.</p> <p>The report on paramilitary groups in Northern Ireland was raised by a number of Senators, including Senator Bacik.  I hope when we have the full details of that and the report of the Garda Commissioner that we can have a debate on this important issue.</p> <p>Senator Bacik and others reminded us of the families of the bereaved in Carrickmines.  I am sure all our hearts go out to the families involved.</p> <p>Senators Bacik and Barrett welcome the appointment of Professor Philip Lane as Governor of the Central Bank.  Senator Barrett also congratulated the new Prime Minister of Canada.  I noted his points in respect of transport issues and Aer Lingus, in particular.</p> <p>Senator Naughton raised the issue of burglaries in Knocknacarra, County Galway.  The Criminal Justice (Burglary of Dwellings) Bill 2015 is before the Lower House and it will be in this House soon.  I understand the bail Bill is also in the other House and we will also have it within a few weeks.  We will, therefore, deal with those matters and there will be ample time and opportunity for Members to make a contribution on those Bills.  The Senator and Senator Brennan welcomed the announcement of the provision of 260 additional high powered vehicles for the Garda by the end of the year and the allocation of &euro;5.3 million by the Minister for Justice and Equality for their purchase.</p> <p>Senators Mooney, Coghlan and others raised the issue of Billy Walsh's resignation.  There is no doubt he has been an excellent ambassador not alone for his sport but for the country since he took over.  If my memory serves me correctly, his predecessor, Gary Keegan, was also forced out of that high performance post.  Questions need to be asked of, and answered by, the IABA.  I am sure the question of the funding of same will be considered as regards the governance of that body.  It is a sad day that a person who has given so much of himself to the sport has been forced out in such a way.  I wish him well in his new position if he takes it up, but I am sure he has no option to do so at this time.</p> <p>Senator Hayden referred to the report on Irish people's loss of personal wealth over the past number of years in comparison to other countries.  She called for a debate on housing and the acquisition of assets.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Maurice Cummins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2003"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2003&amp;amp;pid=MauriceCummins&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We will try to arrange that with the Minister for Finance.  The Senator also called for a debate on youth policy and education grants.  We have not had a debate on that issue since the youth guarantee so I will endeavour to hold one.<br/><br/>I note Senator Norris's points in regard to the eighth amendment.  I suggest to him that Irish people hate to be dictated to by any source on any issue, certainly on this issue.<br/><br/>Senator Jim D'Arcy spoke about the death of Garda Tony Golden, who was a close neighbour of his.  I attended in Dundalk last week and I offered my sympathy in the Garda station in particular.  I am delighted the extra 27 garda&iacute; have been put in place by the Garda Commissioner.  As Senator D'Arcy said, the British-Irish Parliamentary Assembly only last year called for a task force to be put in place in the Border area.  I would hope that will now take place, both from the Irish and the British side.  There is a need to deal with the criminality - the diesel laundering, the smuggling, the beatings and so on.  I know Senator Heffernan has referred to Paul Quinn's murder, which was a barbaric act.  People would ask who sanctioned that murder and those beatings.  A mafia-style <i>omerta</i>exists in that area of our country and there is undoubtedly a fear within the community.  We will certainly debate the report of the Secretary of State, Theresa Villiers MP.  One point that stands out is that the Provisional army council oversees both the Provisional IRA and Sinn F&eacute;in with an over-reaching strategy.  That is one of the things many people have been stating all along and there is a need for clarification and debate on that issue.<br/><br/>Senator &Oacute; Clochartaigh called for a debate on domestic violence.  We will certainly try to arrange that.  A number of Members welcomed the Government's and the Taoiseach's stance that the ratification of the Istanbul convention will be done by the Government in early course.<br/><br/>Senator Leyden called for a review of the personal injuries board and also for a debate on fraud in the insurance sector.  I share his concerns on that matter and will try to arrange same with the Minister, Deputy Bruton.<br/><br/>Senator Colm Burke raised the issue of drink driving offences and the low number of convictions being recorded in many areas of the country.  If so many people avoid conviction, there is a clear need for more watertight legislation to be put in place.  I believe the Minister is considering this in early course and, hopefully, we will have legislation before Christmas, if possible, to deal with these loopholes.  People are appalled at the low percentage of convictions in these cases.<br/><br/>Senator Quinn spoke on the question of green-ways and cycle-ways, and the need to increase our tourism opportunities.  We are succeeding in that area but there is a need for further improvement.The Senator also raised an issue he has raised every year, the whole question of Central European Time.  As he states, it must be done in conjunction with our UK neighbours because otherwise, it cannot come in.  The justice committee and Members of the British Parliament are very favourably disposed.  We must jump together on this issue if it is to be introduced.  I would certainly agree with Senator Quinn's sentiments in this regard, as I have over many years.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Maurice Cummins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2003"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2003&amp;amp;pid=MauriceCummins&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> Senator Brennan welcomed the provision of 260 new high-powered Garda vehicles, in addition to the 370 vehicles which already have been put in place this year.  He also welcomed the 600 extra garda&iacute; who will be trained in Templemore.</p><p>Senator Mullen questioned Amnesty International's stance on abortion.  He also called for the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine to come to the House for a debate on the beef genomics scheme.  The Minister has attended the Chamber on that matter.  As I recall, it was raised on the Commencement debate and may also have been debated on other occasions.  It certainly has been debated comprehensively at the Joint Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine.  There is no point in having repetition in various areas.</p><p>Senator Mullins welcomed the 600 Garda recruits and emphasised the need for new technology in order to combat burglaries and all types of criminality.  He mentioned, too, the need for electronic tagging.  It is easy to say we should have such a facility, but its success is dependent on a number of factors.  Those factors will be examined by the Joint Committee on Justice, Defence and Equality in early course.  Senator Mullins also highlighted the need for the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade to lead a campaign for the global abolition of the death penalty and highlighting human rights issues.</p><p>Senator Heffernan spoke about the death of Paul Quinn, to which I have already referred.</p><p>To clarify for Senator Craughwell, as I mentioned on the Order of Business, the Marriage Bill 2015 will be taken at 5 p.m., with the time allocated to group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes and that for all other Senators not to exceed five minutes in each case.  The debate will conclude when everybody is finished.  The Senator may certainly take up the other matters he raised with the Committee on Procedure and Privileges.  When I hear him talking about the disagreements between the Independent groups and who should or should not be affiliated, I question how stable a government would be if it were made up of Independent Members.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1196" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#CC00200"><p>There should be no groups in here at all, as the Leader knows.  We should all be members of vocational panels, not groups.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#CC00300"><p>Senator O'Brien has proposed an amendment to the Order of Business, "That No. 1 be taken with debate."  Is the amendment being pressed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#CC00400"><p>It certainly is.  I am gravely disappointed that the Leader has not consented to a debate on this matter, particularly in view of his indication last week that we would have such a debate.  Therefore, I am pressing the proposal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.161/1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#CC00500"><p>Amendment put:</p><p>The Seanad divided: T, 17; Nl, 24.</p><br/><br/><p>Tellers: T, Senators Paschal Mooney and Diarmuid Wilson; Nl, Senators Aideen Hayden and Michael Mullins.</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.161/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2015-10-20" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#CC00500">
            <divisioncount ayes="17" noes="24" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" vote="aye">Sean Barrett</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1205" vote="aye">Paul Bradford</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" vote="aye">Thomas Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1196" vote="aye">Gerard Craughwell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1147" vote="aye">John Crown</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" vote="aye">Fidelma Healy Eames</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1119" vote="aye">James Heffernan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" vote="aye">Terry Leyden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" vote="aye">Marc MacSharry</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" vote="aye">Paschal Mooney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" vote="aye">R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" vote="aye">David Norris</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1115" vote="aye">Labhr&aacute;s &Oacute; Murch&uacute;</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" vote="aye">Darragh O'Brien</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1200" vote="aye">Averil Power</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" vote="aye">Feargal Quinn</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" vote="aye">Diarmuid Wilson</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" vote="no">Ivana Bacik</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" vote="no">Terry Brennan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" vote="no">Colm Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" vote="no">Eamonn Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1124" vote="no">Michael Comiskey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" vote="no">Martin Conway</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" vote="no">Maurice Cummins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" vote="no">Jim D'Arcy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" vote="no">John Gilroy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" vote="no">Aideen Hayden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1152" vote="no">Imelda Henry</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" vote="no">John Kelly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" vote="no">Mary Moran</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" vote="no">Michael Mullins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1187" vote="no">Hildegarde Naughton</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" vote="no">Catherine Noone</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1169" vote="no">Mary Ann O'Brien</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" vote="no">Marie Louise O'Donnell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" vote="no">Susan O'Keeffe</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" vote="no">Pat O'Neill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1163" vote="no">Tom Shehan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" vote="no">Jillian van Turnhout</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1143" vote="no">John Whelan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1176" vote="no">Katherine Zappone</mpname>
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.161/3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015102000002#CC00500"><p>Amendment declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-10-20a.162" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question, "That the Order of Business be agreed to", put and declared carried.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>