<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Leas-Chathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.4" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Paul Daly that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Employment Affairs and Social Protection to consider automatically extending free travel to all individuals who travel significant distances for hospital treatment for cancer, dialysis and other illnesses.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government to provide an update on preparations for a referendum on voting rights in presidential elections for Irish citizens outside the State.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Anthony Lawlor of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to introduce a free contraceptive scheme.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Catherine Noone of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to consider introducing fibroscans to improve diagnosis of non-alcoholic fatty liver disease, NAFLD. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Kevin Humphreys of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government to make a statement on the issue of the lack of affordable housing in urban areas and if he will provide an update on the proposals for affordable housing in Poolbeg west.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Martin Conway of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Education and Skills to provide pre-service and in-service education in the areas of movement therapy for learning readiness.</blockquote> <p>Of the matters raised by the Senators that are suitable for discussion, I have selected those raised by Senators Daly, &Oacute; Donnghaile, Lawlor and Noone and they will be taken now.  I regret I had to rule out of order the matter submitted by Senator Humphreys on the ground that it is a repeat of a Commencement matter raised on 18 April 2018.  Senator Conway may give notice on another day of the matter he wishes to raise.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.7" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#A00300">Free Travel Scheme Eligibility</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.8" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1383" speakername="Paul Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#A00400"><p>I was recently contacted by a lady who is receiving treatment for cancer.  She applied for disability allowance in April this year but was told she is not likely to receive a decision on her application until mid-July.</p> <p>In the interim, she has been travelling to and from Dublin every day from Westmeath to receive treatment.  She does not have her own transport and there is no alternative for her to get to Dublin from where she lives but to take public transport.  Every day, she and a companion, who travels with her to support her, take the bus to Dublin and back in order that she can receive radium treatment.  The cost of this travel is almost &euro;40 per day.  A cancer diagnosis does not mean everything else suddenly stops.  Bills still need to be paid and food put on the table.  Life has to go on, but for already stretched families an extra travel bill of &euro;40 per day is often too much to bear.</p> <p>If this lady's application for disability allowance is approved, and we expect it will be given her circumstances, she would be eligible for free travel and would not have to incur these costs.  However, as I understand it, it is not possible to claim back travel costs already incurred once disability allowance is finally granted.  This means people who are extremely ill and would ordinarily be entitled to this benefit are incurring very high costs for transport due to the long processing delays in the Department.</p> <p>On a separate issue related to delays, I have also been contacted by a lady who has applied for carer's allowance but must wait 18 weeks before her application will be reviewed.  These long waiting times are simply inexcusable and unacceptable and something must be done to address them.  </p> <p>Specifically in the case of those who have been diagnosed with life-threatening illnesses, such as cancer, and who are receiving regular treatment that requires travel over long distances, it would be appropriate to automatically grant them free travel from day one.  This would relieve the extraordinary financial stress that some find themselves under at a time when they are already extremely vulnerable and need all of the support they can get.  Lest we forget, these people are fighting illness and we should do all we can to help them.  </p> <p>I understand that disability allowance, or any other benefit, cannot simply be handed out without a proper assessment as to entitlement, but where we know that somebody has a serious and potentially terminal illness and has to travel for treatment, free public transport should be offered from the outset and without any further review.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paul Daly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2464"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2464&amp;amp;pid=PaulDaly&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=28"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is likely that a large number of people will make their own transport arrangements and not need to take public transport.  This measure should make a huge difference to those who need public transport and its introduction would be reasonable and justifiable.  Most importantly, it would be the caring and compassionate thing to do for those affected.  Therefore, I ask the Minister to consider amending the system to make this benefit available in circumstances such as those I have outlined.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1307" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#B00200"><p>I thank the Senator for tabling this Commencement matter, to which I am responding on behalf of the Minister for Employment Affairs and Social Protection, Deputy Regina Doherty, who apologises for being unable to come to the Chamber.  </p> <p>The Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection provides a free travel scheme as a secondary benefit for older people and certain people with disabilities who are customers of the Department.  The scheme provides free travel on the main public and private transport services for people who are eligible under it.  There are approximately 914,000 customers in receipt of free travel.  A person who regularly travels significant distances for hospital treatment for the illnesses described by the Senator will already have this entitlement if he or she is in receipt of invalidity pension or disability allowance.  Therefore, any extension would have to involve others who have no such entitlement.</p> <p>The objective of the free travel scheme is to ensure older people and people with disabilities remain active within their communities.  Any extension of eligibility under the scheme to include people who are not customers of the Department would change this objective and radically alter the nature of the scheme.  Any such scheme would require a more significant operation than that which administers the Department&rsquo;s free travel scheme because, potentially, it would have to grant and withdraw a significant number of passes each year from people who are not customers of the Department.  It would have to do this using information which would ultimately be provided by doctors or hospitals.  All free travel passes issued by the Department entitle the holder to unlimited free travel on the main public and private transport services.  The Department would have no way of limiting the use of the pass to ensure it was being used for travelling to and from hospitals for treatment only.</p> <p>Any increase in eligibility under the scheme would require a substantial increase in the level of funding provided, which currently stands at &euro;90 million per annum.  The social welfare payments that allow people under the age of 66 years to receive free travel passes include disability allowance, invalidity pension, carer's allowance and partial capacity benefit.  Disability allowance and invalidity pension are long-term illness payments, for which people who are receiving hospital treatment may qualify.  Therefore, persons in receipt of such payments are already eligible for free travel.  </p> <p>Under the supplementary welfare allowance scheme, the Department may award a travel supplement if it is warranted by the circumstances of a case.  The supplement is intended to assist with ongoing or recurring travel costs that cannot be met from the client's own resources and are deemed to be necessary.  Individuals who must travel significant distances to and from hospital for treatment may apply for a travel supplement.  Each decision is based on consideration of the circumstances of the case, taking account of the nature and extent of the needs and resources of the person concerned.  Therefore, the Minister is not in a position to extend the free travel scheme in the manner proposed by the Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1383" speakername="Paul Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#B00300"><p>I note the response given by Minister of State who is representing the Minister, Deputy Regina Doherty, but I am not overly impressed by or happy with it.  Applications are in the process of being dealt with in many cases, including the case I have highlighted.  That is the point I am trying to make.  If it was not taking such an inordinately long time to deal with the applications, I would not be here and the lady I have mentioned would not have the problems she has.  I am talking about what should happen in the interim when a live application is in process, especially where medical evidence demonstrates that the applicant needs treatment in a location to which he or she must make a long journey.  The Minister of State overlooked that aspect of the matter in her response.  Although the people to whom I refer are not existing customers of the Department, it is most likely that they will become customers.  As I said, the expenses they incur while waiting cannot be reimbursed.  I think the Minister of State missed that angle of my presentation.  It is likely that the people to whom I refer, whose live applications are in the process of being dealt with, will eventually become customers.  In the meantime, they are spending money they do not have.  Perhaps that money might be refunded to them when the Department gets around to processing their applications.  They should be reimbursed for the money they have spent, or their applications for free travel should be fast-tracked.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1307" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#B00400"><p>I have taken note of the Senator's concerns and will bring them back to the Minister of State, Deputy Jim Daly.  I remind the Senator that I mentioned in my initial response that a supplementary travel benefit can be made available to people who find themselves under considerable stress because of the circumstances of their illness.  Perhaps it might be possible for the Senator to look into that matter on behalf of the lady in question who may be able to avail of the supplementary travel allowance while she is waiting to hear back on her application for disability allowance.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.13" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#B00500">Diaspora Issues</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#B00600"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy John Paul Phelan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#B00700"><p>Cuirim fearadh na f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it.  Gabhaim bu&iacute;ochas leis as ucht a chuid ama a thabhairt don cheist th&aacute;bhachtach seo.  The Minister of State is very welcome.  </p> <p>This straightforward Commencement matter does exactly what it says on the tin.  I am looking for an update on the Government's plans for the proposed referendum to extend the franchise in presidential elections to citizens living outside the State, including the North.  We hope a referendum on presidential voting rights will take place in 2019.  It is important to note the work of Senator Billy Lawless on behalf of the diaspora community.  There is growing consensus on the issue among people across a broad shade of political and civic nationalism in the Six Counties.  I know that they have raised it directly during their engagements with the Taoiseach and his Government colleagues.  The issue which is important in its own right has been highlighted particularly in the context of the jeopardy that hangs over us as citizens in the context of Brexit.  I hope the Minister of State will be able to provide us with an update and appreciate his time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1265" speakername="John Paul Phelan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#B00800"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this issue which has been part of many discussions I have had in the Department in the past 12 months.  It has been and will be more prominent in the next 12 months.  Like a number of Members of both Houses, the Senator has been a strong advocate for extending the franchise in presidential elections to citizens resident outside the State.  The Government decided on 7 March 2017 to accept in principle the main recommendation in the fifth report of the Constitutional Convention that citizens resident outside the State, including Northern Ireland, should have the right to vote in presidential elections and that a referendum should be held to amend the Constitution to give effect to that decision.  When it was announced by the former Taoiseach in Philadelphia on 12 March 2017, it received a generally positive response from Irish citizens at home and abroad.</p> <p>Following the announcement, an options paper which had been jointly prepared by the Departments of Housing, Planning and Local Government and Foreign Affairs and Trade, was published on 22 March 2017 to inform public debate on this significant policy change.  The paper provided a focus for discussions at a dedicated session on voting rights held at the second Global Irish Civic Forum on 5 May 2017.  The forum was attended by a wide range of representatives of Irish organisations abroad, including groups that had been campaigning actively on the issue for a number of years.  Senator Billy Lawless has been mentioned in that context.  The participants in the forum welcomed the opportunity to have their say and emphasised the positive role the Irish abroad would play in achieving progress on the issue.  I understand those present at the forum seemed to have a broad understanding of the importance of due consideration and preparation being given to the option to be chosen and the wording of any amendment to the Constitution to be put to the people in a referendum.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy John Paul Phelan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2004"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2004&amp;amp;pid=JohnPaulPhelan&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=28"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->There was also a broad acceptance that the legislative and administrative change involved means it will not be possible to have voting from outside the State in place before a presidential election later this year even if a referendum was immediately held and passed .</p><p>There was also broad acceptance that the legislative and administrative change involved means that it will not be possible to have voting from outside the State in place before any presidential election later this year even if a referendum is held immediately and passed.</p><p>At the forum, the almost unanimous view of participants in regard to which citizens should have the right to vote at presidential elections was that the franchise should be extended to all citizens resident outside the State.  There was also broad agreement that the extension of the franchise should not be limited to those who have left Ireland in recent years or within a certain time limit.  There was a recognition among those in attendance that introducing a requirement to hold a valid Irish passport would be a reasonable criterion for eligibility.  In light of the views expressed at the forum, my Department and the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade are working methodically and carefully through some of the details that could arise in respect of the various options with a view to bringing a report to Government that will assist in identifying a preferred option to be put to the people in a referendum.  Preliminary work has also commenced within the Department on the modernisation of the voter registration process, which will facilitate those eligible to vote to exercise their franchise from outside the State should a referendum be passed by the people in due course.</p><p>As the Senator may recall, the Government announced on 26 September 2017 that it has agreed indicative dates for the holding of referendums in 2018 and 2019, subject to the timely passage of constitutional amendment Bills by each House of the Oireachtas.  It is intended to hold the proposed referendum on extending the franchise at presidential elections to Irish citizens resident outside the State on the date of the local and European elections in late May 2019.  Against that background, my Department will, in consultation with the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade, bring forward an appropriate constitutional amendment Bill on extending the franchise at presidential elections to Irish citizens resident outside the State in good time for the holding of the proposed referendum next year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#C00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  He will not be surprised to hear that I believe his final two paragraphs are key-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1265" speakername="John Paul Phelan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#C00300"><p>They usually are.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#C00400"><p>Indeed they are.  The detail therein is very important.  The Minister of State is correct to acknowledge Senator Lawless and his work with various organisations on the matter.  I also have majored on this issue since I was elected to the Seanad.  Our experience and that of the Minister of State is that there is a willingness to work collaboratively and try to ensure this is done speedily and correctly.  Many contributions on the matter have referenced the work being done by officials and I wish them well in those endeavours because we need to get this right.  As we come to the stage where we hope to bring the legislation to the Houses, it is important to have a last round of engagement with the civic and representative organisations in regard to people in the North and the diaspora.  I hope that Senator Lawless and I will have the opportunity to discuss the matter with the Minister of State and his officials over the summer recess or shortly thereafter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1265" speakername="John Paul Phelan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#C00500"><p>I have no problem taking the Senator up on that offer.  This issue has rumbled on for several years and there have been many meetings on it.  I met the Minister of State, Deputy Cannon, last week on the matter.  This Commencement Matter is very timely and there is a general acceptance of the need for change.  In the considerations prior to and at the forum, the possibility of a time limit such that citizens would have the right to vote if they had lived in the State within the previous five years or similar was raised but it was decided that that was too messy and that it would be difficult to agree upon a timeframe.  Irish citizens with an Irish passport should be allowed to vote.  There are other complicating factors.  I have met with several groups, in particular in London and elsewhere in the United Kingdom, over the past few years.  There is also the issue of where voting centres will be held.  In many countries, they are held in consulates or embassies but postal voting is also a possibility.  Much work has yet to be completed.  The Minister of State, Deputy Cannon, and I will meet with any Member of this House, including Senator &Oacute; Donnghaile, on this issue because the Government intends for the matter to go to a referendum of the people next year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1438" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#C00600"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach for allowing me to bring forward this Commencement Matter.  I thank the Minister of State for her attendance.  I know the Minister, Deputy Harris, is also quite interested in this subject.  I raise the national roll-out of a free contraceptive scheme.  Ready access to effective contraceptive care is a key part of good reproductive and sexual health for many citizens.  Known barriers to effective access to contraceptive care currently contribute to the levels of unplanned and crisis pregnancies.  These barriers include cost, particularly for women who are just above the threshold for primary care reimbursement service, PCRS, eligibility, younger women and adolescents.  The latter group includes adolescents who may be eligible for services under the medical card scheme but who, for reasons of cost of attendance, confidentiality, particularly when they are on a family medical card, or ignorance - they may be unaware that they are eligible under a medical card scheme or can discuss the matter with their GP, practice nurse or pharmacist - are currently apprehensive about attending a general practitioner, GP, or family planning clinic.  There is strong evidence that young people positively view GPs as reliable sources of health-related information but there are also deterrents to their accessing necessary advice and essential services.</p> <p>The Government should cost and closely consider an improved and integrated primary care contraceptive scheme to provide better access to this key service which is highly relevant in reducing rates of abortion, the risk of unplanned pregnancies, the transmission of STIs and related anxiety among many women and some men of reproductive age in many Irish communities.  There should be funding for an integrated primary care contraceptive scheme to increase the capacity of the primary care sector to deliver this essential service.  An educational component to ensure that those who would benefit from an improvement in these services are aware and knowledgeable about when and how to access the services is also required.  Such scheme would bring us into line with many European Union countries where such such services are largely free at the point of delivery to most EU citizens. It would also be consistent with long-standing Government policy on extending many free primary care services to many of our citizens.  Reducing the number of abortions by means of an enhanced and expanded contraceptive scheme is particularly attractive at a time when medical abortions will become available through a process of constitutional change.</p> <p>Schemes in regard to medical contraception and education should be considered.  There are several problems relating to the knowledge and understanding of the population in terms of how and when to access and use these services.  As part of the maternity scheme, participating GPs should be required to confirm that they have consulted with expectant mothers in regard to post-partum contraception.  Adolescents should be advised that they are eligible to consult with their local pharmacist, practice nurse or GP for relevant services.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Anthony Lawlor:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=2283"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2283&amp;amp;pid=AnthonyLawlor&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=28"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> As part of an integrated primary care contraceptive scheme, we should provide a related message service for secondary schools, as well as public health messages.  The latter should include information on how to access relevant services, as well as clear messages that highlight high risk sexual behaviour, similar to the effective campaigns run by the Road Safety Authority.  This aspect of the initiative would build on experience already gained, but it would be more powerful and sustained than previous campaigns on the topic.</p><p>At a community level, pharmacists, practice nurses and GPs who are interested should be enabled, encouraged and modestly supported to engage with local secondary schools.  I also suggest school boards of management periodically invite interested practitioners to outline the services available and answer questions and inquiries made by students and school staff on relevant aspects of sexual health.  Healthcare professionals who are assisting on this aspect of an integrated primary care contraceptive scheme could be engaged, supported and have their activities co-ordinated through high level agreements with their postgraduate training bodies and representative organisations.</p><p>Overall, an integrated primary care contraceptive scheme would be very welcome.  As I said, we should take on board what the people demonstrated in passing the referendum.  Of course, there will be crisis and unplanned pregnancies.  We should provide support and consider introducing a scheme that will assist all of the people.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1307" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#D00200"><p>On behalf of the Minister for Health, Deputy Simon Harris, I thank the Senator for raising this matter in the Seanad.  The Minister is unavoidably absent as he in the D&aacute;il Chamber dealing with Priority Questions and asked me to come in his place.</p> <p>The cost of contraception has often been cited as a factor in unintended pregnancies.  The Oireachtas Joint Committee on the Eighth Amendment of the Constitution recommended the following: "the introduction of a scheme for the provision of the most effective method of contraception, free of charge and having regard to personal circumstances, to all people who wish to avail of them within the State".  There are insufficient data for the significance of the cost of the use of contraception.  We know from the Irish contraception and crisis pregnancy study 2010 that other important issues, besides cost, influence access and decisions on contraception.  Almost half of the women surveyed for the study said contraception had been used at the time of their most recent crisis pregnancy.  Aggregate population data for contraceptive use in Ireland are not available.  However, the health Ireland survey 2016 indicated that 46% of respondents used no contraception.  Usage was highest among the group of people aged between 17 and 24 years and declined with each age group, with significant numbers in each group using no contraception.  Clearly, there are other important issues besides cost in whether people choose to use contraception when pregnancy is not desired.  Work in the United Kingdom suggests access to reliable contraception is only one of the measures needed to achieve a reduction in the number of unintended pregnancies.  They include relationships and sexuality education, timely access to contraception and information and engagement with appropriate health services.</p> <p>Contraception is widely and easily accessible in Ireland.  A comprehensive range of prescription hormonal contraception is available through the community drugs schemes, including long acting reversible contraceptives.  Condoms are not reimbursed but are widely available in retail outlets.  Additionally, post-coital contraception is available over the counter in pharmacies and free for medical card holders.</p> <p>The main cost of obtaining contraception relates to medical care such as consultations, follow-up visits and the fitting and removal of devices.  However, 44% of the population have free GP services, either through the medical card or the GP visit card.  </p> <p>I will come back to some of the other issues raised by the Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#D00300"><p>Does Senator Anthony Lawlor wish to ask a brief supplementary question?  I remind him that I allowed him latitude when he made his initial statement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1438" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#D00400"><p>I thank the Acting Chairman.  I probably spoke a little longer because this is my first Commencement matter.</p> <p>The Minister of State spoke mostly about the cost of contraception.  It is easy to discover how much it costs because many people a medical card.  Therefore, one can easily analyse the cost per head by analysing how many avail of existing services.  </p> <p>I am disappointed that the Minister of State did not mention sexual health education.  There are medical practitioners who are willing, if asked, to go into schools to provide such education.  I suggest the Departments of Health and Education and Skills become involved in providing such education.  The latter Department could issue directives to various school boards of management to encourage them to invite medical practitioners to their schools.  Such education is really important, particularly as the referendum has been passed.  It is known that free contraceptive care and increased knowledge reduce the number of crisis and unplanned pregnancies.  I urge the Government to introduce an integrated scheme to provide free contraceptive care and the necessary education for all citizens.  Let us be mindful of the fact that sexual health is an issue for both males and females.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1307" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#D00500"><p>I shall return to the recommendation made by the Oireachtas Joint Committee on the Eighth Amendment of the Constitution.  On numerous occasions the Minister for Health has said he fully supports the recommendation made by the joint committee and its call for contraception to be made available free of charge.  Work on the legislation is ongoing, particularly since the passing of the referendum.  I do not have information from the Department of Health with me, but I assure the Senator that the Department is introducing a new health and well-being programme into all primary and secondary schools.  Two new booklets, one of which is entitled, Tom's Flower Power: A gentle explanation of how babies are born, were launched a few weeks ago.  Such education is provided for young people in primary school.  I also assure the Senator that the Department of Education and Skills is doing a lot of work at primary, second and third levels, although I do not have a comprehensive reply for him from it.  I promise, however, that I will ask the Minister to convey to him what the Department is doing.  I shall reiterate what the Minister for Health has said.  He has clearly said he will follow the recommendations made by the joint committee.  However, it will take some time to put in place some of the measures recommended, some of which are legislative.  We are at the beginning of the process which will continue for the next couple of months.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.28" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#D00600">Disease Management</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#D00700"><p>I thank the Minister of State at the Department of Health for taking this matter on behalf of the Minister for Health, on whom I call to consider introducing fibroscans to improve the diagnosis of non-alcoholic fatty liver disease, NAFLD.  Ireland is facing an epidemic of liver disease.  NAFLD is driven by obesity and diets that are high in fat, sugar and salt.  Sadly, many are unaware of the risk such diets pose to their health.  NAFLD can be managed and prevented from developing, once detected.  In the vast majority of instances it is currently not detectable by a routine liver test - generally a blood test.  Fibroscans can accurately diagnose the condition in a timely manner.  A fibroscan is quick, simple, pain free and non-invasive.  If fibroscans were introduced, they would help to address the under-diagnosis of NAFLD.  Non-alcoholic steato-hepatitis, NASH, is the more aggressive form that emerges if NAFLD is left untreated.  It is a silent epidemic and as many as 80% of people with NAFLD are not diagnosed routinely.  Fibroscans are relatively inexpensive and can be performed by GPs.  It would make great sense to introduce them, given the incidence of obesity in the country.  </p> <p>Professor Suzanne Norris is a specialist in the area.  She has said: "In my lifetime there will be a tsunami of liver disease in Ireland."  It is only in recent times that it has been realised liver disease is caused by a diet high in fat, sugar and salt, rather than alcohol.  Up until now it was predominantly suffered by males an alcohol-related but now it is presenting in a large volume of younger people and many females.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Catherine Noone:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2354"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2354&amp;amp;pid=CatherineNoone&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=28"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I will be very interested in the Minister of State's response because this makes a lot of sense.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1307" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#E00200"><p>I hope the Senator is interested in the response which is wide-ranging, but I will have some notes to add at the end.  </p> <p>Chronic diseases are largely preventable diseases linked with a set of four common risk factors - tobacco use, harmful use of alcohol, unhealthy diet and physical inactivity - and which can remain preventable until late in life.  As described in the recent Sl&aacute;intecare report, they present a major challenge in future health service planning.  The demographic profile has changed, life expectancy has risen and the diseases we encounter have changed.  Chronic diseases such as cancer and cardiovascular disease now account for over 60% of all deaths in Ireland.  The health system needs to reflect these changes and adapt to meet the needs of the current and future populations.  Chronic diseases and multi-morbidity require a different type of care that is preventive, ongoing and managed close to home.</p> <p>Services to treat most chronic conditions are mainly provided in acute hospitals, although significant advances have been made in some areas, particularly diabetes care.  The development in 2008 of the national policy framework for the prevention and management of chronic diseases addressed the management of chronic diseases through a reorientation towards primary care and the provision of integrated health services focused on prevention and returning individuals to health and a better quality of life.  The Sl&aacute;intecare report builds on the work that commenced in 2008 under the national policy framework for the prevention and management of chronic diseases.  The model of care envisaged in Sl&aacute;intecare is chronic disease management by multi-disciplinary teams, incorporating evidence-based approaches, care plans, self-management and shared care protocols, which will be community-based.  This model of care will offer a comprehensive package of services, from prevention to diagnostic services, disease management and rehabilitation.  Referral to an acute hospital will only be for episodes which require specific specialist care, with discharge back to community care, as required.  </p> <p>lt is important to recognise that a significant proportion of the ill health associated with chronic diseases is preventable.  Significant progress has been made in the early implementation of Healthy Ireland which provides a solid platform for tackling lifestyle risk factors, social determinants of health and factors which contribute to health inequalities.  It also provides the framework within which individuals, communities and sectors can be supported in playing a proactive role in improving the nation's health and well-being and throughout the course of life.  In the next decade the focus will increasingly shift to driving monitoring and evaluating implementation.  This will be supported by the evolving Healthy Ireland infrastructure.  Under the Healthy Ireland agenda, our aim is to prevent much of the chronic disease through action on risk factors and by creating an environment which will support people in making the healthier choices which will reduce their risks of ill health during their lifetime.</p> <p>Implementation of a range of initiatives is under way, including implementation of the obesity policy and action plan which was approved by the Government in 2016 and which aims to reduce levels of excess weight among the population.  Our mission is to get the message of Healthy Ireland into every home and community in order that we can better help and support people in making the healthy changes they want to make but which everyday struggles can make harder to do.  It is important that we all work together to deliver clear, simple and consistent messages to encourage people to take those first steps and understand everything they do will count towards a healthier future for their families.  No step is too small and the most important thing is to start.  </p> <p>I have held the health promotion and Healthy Ireland brief for almost a year and had the privilege of meeting many people and organisations that are working with us on the Healthy Ireland agenda.  I am always struck by how passionate and committed they are about promoting health and well-being in communities.  I look forward to continuing our work over the summer and beyond in order that we can support more people in eating, thinking and being well.  I will come back to the specific question asked and answer it with a comment I have received in the past few minutes.  I know that was a very broad response.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#E00300"><p>That is appreciated.  I know of the good work the Minister of State is doing and could not agree more with the general idea that if we are and keep well, we will prevent disease.  This is a tangible and specific way to prevent this disease at low cost.  The answer is great, but the prevalence of the disease is worthy of a more specific measure.  I would appreciate hearing any further comment the Minister of State has to make.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1307" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#E00400"><p>I know that the Senator is passionate about this subject, as we all are.  Obesity is becoming very prevalent, particularly among young children.  I do not have a specific answer to the Commencement matter, about which I am disappointed.  I was handed this note before I walked into the Chamber and will read it.  The Minister and the Department of Health do not have a role in decisions on the diagnostic tests to be provided for specific patient groups.  It is an executive responsibility of the Health Service Executive.  The investment decisions should be informed by expert clinical opinion, an assessment of patient need, evidence of effectiveness and budget impact.  The roll-out of major new technology should be the subject of a formal health technology assessment.  I know that will not satisfy the Senator, but I have not been able to speak to the Minister because he has been in the D&aacute;il Chamber.  I will come back to the Senator because her Commencement matter is specifically about fibroscans and I do not believe the answer was adequate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#E00500"><p>The issue has been highlighted.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.35" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 11.05 a.m. and resumed at 11.30 a.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.36" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#G00100">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#G00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, Private Members' business, Civil Law (Missing Persons) Bill 2016 - Report and Final Stages, to be taken at 12.45 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#G00300"><p>Despite what one might call, pardon the pun, the healthy economic indicators that are with us now, our hospital waiting lists have never been as long.  There are 711,000 people on inpatient and outpatient waiting lists, which is a staggering percentage of the population.  We also have acute shortages in consultants and nurses in hospitals, leaving our most vulnerable citizens without access and, probably more important, timely access to necessary services.  According to the Irish Medical Organisation, in excess of 400 consultant positions remain unfilled.  Overcrowding costs lives and must stop.  We need to improve and increase capacity, recruit the necessary staff and increase resources for the National Treatment Purchase Fund in the short and long term.  I ask that the Minister for Health come to the House at some point to outline how he intends to reduce waiting lists and tackle the issues I raise.  I am sure lots of work is being done but it is important that we find out exactly what is being done to tackle waiting lists specifically and the many vacancies in the health service.</p> <p>Yesterday, Electric Ireland announced an increase in its residential electricity prices by 6.2% and residential gas prices by 8%.  It is estimated that these price hikes will add an extra &euro;56 to the average annual electricity bill and &euro;55 to the average annual gas bill.  According to the Society of St. Vincent de Paul, during the past 12 months, 29% of households were unable to afford to keep their homes warm.  While the issue of people trying to keep people warm is probably not one to raise on a day like today - the opposite is probably the case - the proposed increases in electricity and fuel charges will affect many people.  The Government must make sure there are safeguards in place, particularly for the most vulnerable.  </p> <p>Litter, particularly in Dublin and Dublin city centre, is another factor associated with the current weather conditions.  Dublin City Council provides a good service but it needs to ramp it up during this period, particularly around canals and beaches.  The capacity that is normally required falls far short of what is needed for these kinds of days.  In many cases, people trying to deposit rubbish they find that bins are full.  Extra staff are needed in Dublin City Council and other councils.  The chief executive of Dublin City Council, Owen Keegan, was the county manager in D&uacute;n Laoghaire-Rathdown County Council when I sat on the council.  I know he has staff but extra capacity is needed, not only for tourists, although that is also important, but for citizens visiting or living in Dublin.  Senators are fond of referring to seagulls but I saw a seagull pecking at a bag, opening it and getting all the rubbish out.  We need adequate capacity and extra bins for this time of the year.  </p> <p>The so-called McLibel case in the European Court of Human Rights concerned the right of all citizens to paid legal representation.  There are people who are unable to access free legal aid in cases involving the repossession of family farms and residential properties by banks and various vulture funds.  Promises were made to provide free legal aid.  Will the Leader find out when the Government will provide free legal aid for people who are facing this difficulty?  My understanding is that it is a European right and that Ireland is in breach of a ruling of the European Court of Human Rights because it does not provide this right for citizens.  I ask the Leader for a response?  Yvonne Walsh has been in jail for 55 days arising from a case involving the attempted repossession of her house.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1439" speakername="Ian Marshall" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#H00100"><p>The House will be aware that yesterday, Mr. Chris Patten, a former junior Minister in Northern Ireland and former chairman of the Policing Commission, was in Dublin and raised serious concerns about Brexit.  He referred to a nationalist rage getting the UK into a terrible mess in an effort to control trade policy and take back control from the EU, and said that ultimately the UK will end up taking the rules that determine commerce from other places, such as China or even the United States.  He said there is no doubt that ideology is overruling common sense and rational thinking.  He went on to say: "It is strange that as Ireland has become more pluralist, more extrovert, more committed to individual liberty and human rights as a constructive member of the European Union, Britain has become less comfortable and has felt less at home as a member of the Union to which it has belonged pretty much on its own terms."</p> <p>As the sand rapidly runs through the hourglass we are getting more concerned that no deal due to intransigence could be a reality.  It is a horrendous situation for Ireland, North and South.  I have no doubt that Northern Ireland will be collateral damage in any such scenario.  The other collateral damage will be to the rural economy in Ireland.  Yesterday in Dublin Castle, at the national economic dialogue event, a number of stakeholders made representations and raised concerns about economic uncertainty.  Figures shared with me by the Irish Farmers Association, IFA, indicate that the agrifood industry is Ireland's largest indigenous industry.  It supports 300,000 jobs, creating &euro;26 billion in turnover, and currently is in one of the areas of the Border conundrum that has proved too difficult a nut to crack.  If the figures are correct, and I have no doubt they are, a proposed cut in Common Agricultural Policy, CAP, support of 5%, with a 2% proxy rate of inflation applied, actually amounts to a potential 17% loss in real terms.  Translated into finances is a further &euro;3,004 reduction in the average income.  That is unacceptable.  Coupled with a potential distortion in trade, tariff implications, production costs and added uncertainty, it leaves the rural economy in a very precarious situation.  Mr. Chris Patten said yesterday that the UK needs to work closely with its neighbours in order to look after its own interests, but that this argument had not been heard very often at Westminster.</p> <p>Yesterday, the summer economic statement was discussed in the House.  It referred to growth in the economy and an ambition to ensure steady and sustainable growth.  However, the challenge to this will be to mitigate these risks and ensure that due to extremely high levels of rainfall we have enough in the coffers to address calling on any rainy day fund.  It is concerning that for us the first priority is a resolution to the Brexit discussion whereas at today&rsquo;s EU Council meeting it is far from the top of the agenda.  Summer time and a heatwave must not distract from the importance and significance of negotiating and getting agreement on what the potential position post Brexit could look like and what it will deliver for Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1404" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#H00200"><p>Can the Leader schedule a debate in the House on the implementation of the national drugs strategy?  A debate on that is being held in the D&aacute;il and it should also occur here given that the consultation process on decriminalisation is taking place.  Perhaps that could be arranged for before the summer recess.  On a related issue, I invite Senators to a briefing I am holding next Tuesday.  It will involve a group of service users who have been in and out of drugs services for many years, including methadone clinics.  They have joined with the Irish Human Rights and Equality Commission to produce an in-depth report on what they see as human rights abuses for them as service users.  They are coming here to launch the report for the Oireachtas.  It will be a good opportunity to talk face-to-face with them, a human rights commissioner and a doctor.  The report, entitled "Our Life, Our Voice, Our Say", makes 28 recommendations.  One of them refers to supervised urine tests and how degrading and inhumane it is to have to do this constantly with doctors and in clinics.  I urge Members to come along at 11.30 a.m. on 3 July to support them and hear what they have to say.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#H00300"><p>I wish to propose an amendment to the Order of Business, that non-Government motion No. 11 on the Order Paper be taken without debate before No. 1.</p> <p>I also wish to raise the sex offenders register.  Yesterday, I heard the case of a young woman, and it is covered further today, who made her identity public recently.  She was raped at 11 years of age and last year found out by chance, as she lives in a small town, that the rapist was appealing to be removed from the sex offenders register.  She waived her right to anonymity as she is seeking that victims be notified when their attackers seek to be removed from the register.  There is no formal process by law for victims to be notified.  This is a flaw in the system.  Can the Leader ask the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Flanagan, to address this in the House?  He has said that there are proposals for a new sex offenders amendment Bill, which I believe is in the drafting stage, to ensure victims are notified of the intention to remove an attacker or rapist from the register.  This would keep victims safe and informed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#H00400"><p>You raised the good weather, a Chathaoirligh, and it is great to see so many people in the capital city enjoying themselves at concerts and outdoor events.  However, there has been a downside to that due to the excessive use of alcohol and public order offences.  With an increasing number of outdoor events it is necessary to have a set of standards nationwide to ensure the safety of young people, and not so young people in the case of Billy Joel, attending concerts and open air events with regard to policing, access to alcohol and the general inconvenience for neighbouring properties in respect of noise.  Certainly, things went badly wrong in the case of the open air events in the RDS and we were very lucky not to end up with any fatalities.  The Killers concert on Sunday night was an example of what can go wrong in the vicinity of an open air event when there are no proper safeguards for the public attending it.  There is a need for guidelines.  This is not just a Dublin issue.  Open air events take place throughout the country.</p> <p>Turning to an equally serious matter, I wish to raise the Judicial Appointments Commission Bill 2017 which is currently before the House and is due to be debated today.  Grave concerns have been raised about it not only by our senior judges, who have said clearly that there has been no indepth consultation on the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Ross's Bill, which is being taken through the House by the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Flanagan, but also by the European watchdog, which has poured scorn on the Bill.  The Council of Europe's Group of States against Corruption, GRECO, is due to issue a report shortly.  I am gravely concerned about giving consideration to the Bill before that report has been published and the Government comments on it.  We are putting ourselves in the same position as Poland and other eastern European countries.  While the Bill is considered very important by the Minister, Deputy Ross, and certainly he has a level of vanity about it, we must take account of the greater interest regarding how our judges are appointed and how we safeguard the Judiciary and its independence.</p> <p>With that in mind I am proposing the following amendment to the Order of Business, that Committee Stage of the Judicial Appointments Commission Bill 2017 not be taken before September to enable the Seanad to receive and consider the as yet unpublished report touching on the issue from the Council of Europe Group of States against Corruption and to consider the Government response, if any, to that report.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#J00100"><p>I welcome the fact that there will be 37 extra special needs assistants, SNAs, in Limerick in both primary and secondary schools in the coming academic year.  It is a 42% increase on 2011 and will bring the number of SNAs in Limerick to a total of 606.  Education is vital for the future of primary and secondary school students and this is very welcome news.</p> <p>This week, the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Shane Ross, announced there would be a third terminal at Dublin Airport.  I hope this will not be done at the expense of Shannon and Cork airports.  Project Ireland 2040 places great emphasis on providing a counterbalance to Dublin on the western seaboard.  Development is needed outside Dublin because the capital is oversubscribed, so to speak.  The announcement of a third terminal and runway for Dublin Airport raises the question of whether this will be at the expense of airports in the west.  I understand a report on the development of State owned airports up to 2050 is to be released shortly by the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport.  I ask the Leader to invite the Minister to the House when the report is published to debate the development of airports.  We must ensure the western seaboard is not forgotten, especially Shannon Airport.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#J00200"><p>I request that the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government, Deputy Eoghan Murphy, come into the House to intervene in a dispute between Roscommon County Council management and the F&oacute;rsa trade union.  There are now two days of strike action taking place every Tuesday and Thursday in Roscommon which is very disruptive.  The matter has been before the Workplace Relations Commission seven times and has been the subject of two Labour Court hearings and three clarifications.  I am told by F&oacute;rsa that Roscommon County Council is the only local authority in which flexible leave is banned.  This concession applied to F&oacute;rsa members in Roscommon for 17 years, as it did in all other local authorities.  According to the trade union, the business cases for granting flexibility leave cannot have disappeared overnight.</p> <p>It is not our responsibility, as Members of the Oireachtas, to get involved in industrial disputes.  I suggest that the Leader communicate with the Minister responsible, with a view to asking Mr. Kieran Mulvey, who was involved in labour relations for 25 years until his retirement in 2016, to arbitrate in this dispute as a last resort.  Mr. Mulvey was the head of the Labour Relations Commission, now the Workplace Relations Commission.  He is also from Roscommon and he and I were both brought up in Roscommon Town.  There has been a breakdown in communications between the trade union in question and management and an independent outside expert should be brought in to resolve the matter as it is causing major disruption to the people in County Roscommon who are affected by the withdrawal of labour on Tuesdays and Thursdays.  It is also difficult for the staff who are protesting and on strike today.  These matters should be resolved.  Over the years, there have been many good negotiations, resulting in the Haddington Road and other agreements.  I hope an intervention will be made sooner rather than later.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#J00300"><p>I second the amendment to the Order of Business proposed by Senator Devine.</p> <p>I wish everyone a safe, happy and healthy Dublin Pride and encourage people to join the protest on Saturday at 2 p.m. from St. Stephen's Green south.  The We are Family theme chosen for Pride this year is not a coincidence given that the World Meeting of Families will take place in Dublin this year.  I commend the LGBT community on leading the way in building a new Ireland and, as global community, on leading the way in building a different world.  The persecution of our brothers and sisters around the globe impacts members of the LGBT community wherever we are and causes us great stress.  It also adds to fear and becomes internalised.  Knowing that people are persecuted for having the same characteristics as I and others have leads to social withdrawal and causes us to identify with that persecution on a small level, although obviously not on a fatal scale.  LGBT people around the world who experience violence, hate and discrimination are counting on us in Ireland to implement laws that protect individuals in being who they are.  This will provide international examples of law that are effective and work.  We will highlight and address these issues in this country because we can do so.  I call for international solidarity.  I also look forward to the launch of the LGBTI national youth strategy tomorrow by the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs, Deputy Katherine Zappone.  I am hopeful that the strategy will include actions to ban conversion therapy.  I am also in contact with the Minister of State, Deputy Catherine Byrne, on the issue.  I ask the Leader to encourage the Government to ensure this process is completed as quickly as possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#J00400"><p>I join Senator Warfield in wishing everyone a happy Pride in the week that is in it and commend him on his work on conversion therapy.</p> <p>I second the motion put forward by my colleague, Senator Humphreys, seeking to adjourn Committee Stage of the Judicial Appointments Commission Bill and providing that the Seanad will not take Committee Stage until we have received and considered the unpublished report from the Council of Europe's Group of States against Corruption, GRECO.  We need time to allow us to consider the Government's response, if any, to the report.  As Senator Humphreys stated, it is essential that we see the text of the GRECO report and the Government's response to it in advance of our debate on the amendments to this important legislation.</p> <p>I raised this matter in the House on Tuesday, as did Senator Boyhan and others who expressed concern.  We are effectively being asked to legislate in the dark without sight of the Government's amendments or what it proposes to do in response to serious criticisms.  GRECO has expressed significant concerns about the composition of the judicial appointment's commission, as proposed in the Bill.  It also considers that the proposals represent a move that is not in line with European standards.  This is a very serious critique of the proposals that are being driven through government like a speedy chariot by the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport.  This is not a good way to legislate.  We should be able to see the report and the Government's response.  We should also be able to see what the Government proposes to do by way of amendments.  We were in the dark during Second Stage when we did not have sight of any of this.  On behalf of the Labour group, I have submitted 20 amendments to the Bill without prejudice. I am hopeful we will have time to be able to consider the GRECO criticisms before we debate them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#J00500"><p>I am afraid the proposal by Senators Humphreys and Bacik to amend the Order of Business is in this instance both presumptive and anticipatory because the purpose of the Order of Business is to make arrangements for the taking of the business of the day.  It is not proposed to take the Bill in question today.  Therefore, however meritorious the Senators' cause, I suggest they find another way to pursue it.  If the legislation was on the schedule for today, they would be entitled to oppose the Order of Business.  Under the rules and regulations governing business, it cannot be anticipated that it will be scheduled next week.  If it is scheduled next week, the Senators should oppose the Order of Business on the relevant day.  I regret that I must rule the amendment out of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#J00600"><p>Committee Stage of the Bill was originally proposed for today, as indicated in the schedule, as originally published.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#J00700"><p>The Order of Business, as outlined by the Leader on behalf of the Government, is for today's business.  I cannot deal with the business of next week or the week after.  The Senators' amendment anticipates certain business being taken.  However meritorious or valid their objections, this is not an appropriate time to deal with them.  Consequently, I an ruling the amendment out of order with regret.  The schedule is not a proposal to the House.  I call the Leader to respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#K00100"><p>I thank the nine Members who contributed to the Order of Business.  They caught me on the hop.  I was not really ready.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#K00200"><p>Perhaps Senator Buttimer was off anticipating something.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#K00300"><p>I was actually.  Senator Horkan raised the issue of hospital waiting lists.  They are a source of concern and Government has committed to a further allocation of funding to tackle the trolley crisis and reduce inpatient and outpatient waiting lists.  We have some seen some action in terms of numbers.  It is important to recognise that reducing waiting times is a priority for Government.  We saw a &euro;50 million increase in funding for the National Treatment Purchase Fund.  Under the action plan drawn by the Minister of Health, the number of patients waiting longer than nine months has fallen.  It looks like the overall number of people waiting for hospital appointments and procedures will be reduced by a further 70,000.  The point made by the Senator is a valid one.</p> <p>He also raised the increase in electricity and gas prices by Electric Ireland.  We have an independent regulator, as the House is aware.  The points made by Senator Horkan are very pertinent.  This is about fuel poverty and the people who are most vulnerable and who need access to heating and light - thankfully, not today because of the weather - but in the winter months.  The Senator's points need to be monitored.  I hope the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection with the rest of Government and the industry can look at how we can ensure that prices do not go berserk.    </p> <p>I concur with Senator Horkan regarding the issue of litter.  Collective responsibility is needed on the part of all of us and not just because of tourists.  I welcome the fact that overseas visits to Ireland have increased by 7.6%.  A total of 273,300 more people have come to visit our country.  It is important that the c&eacute;ad m&iacute;le f&aacute;ilte they receive also includes an impeccable public realm.  All of us recognise that there are black spots that need to tackled.  I concur with Senator Horkan in terms of the role city and county councils can play.  I hope we would have an action plan for litter because it is a blight on our country.  If one looked at the edition of "Prime Time" on the waste industry and if one looks at the individual, never mind the collective, attitude to litter, one can see that we need to do something about it because we are actually slipping as a country in terms of our attitude to litter.  Senator Horkan also raised the case of Yvonne Walsh.  I do not have the answer but I would be happy for the relevant Minister to come to the House.  Alternatively, the Senator could table a Commencement Matter.  </p> <p>Senator Marshall raised the very important issue of Brexit.  Again, he made a wonderful contribution to the Order of Business and showed the importance of having his voice in this House.  I reiterate what the Senator and Chris Patten said.  It is important that the UK works with all of us to ensure we have a solution to Brexit.  The Taoiseach is right as well in that it is not our duty to come up with a response to the UK, which voted to leave.  However, it is important because as the Senator said, there is economic uncertainty.  The worrying part of Brexit is the economic uncertainty for us and in the UK if we look at the potential number of jobs that could be lost in the UK and the potential loss to us in terms of agriculture and our economy.  The point made by the Senator is very relevant.  Unfortunately, I did not get to attend Chris Patten's lecture in Iveagh House last night.  Today is a very important summit in the EU and I wish the Taoiseach and the Minister of State with responsibility for European Affairs, Deputy McEntee, well.  Obviously, we are heading towards an October timeframe.  The points made by Senator Marshall are important.  I hope that we will have an update from the European Council meeting before the summer recess.  </p> <p>In response to Senator Ruane, it is also my intention to have a debate if we can on the implementation of the national drugs strategy.  The Senator is right.  There has been a huge consultation process.  I commend her on what she has been doing and I would encourage as many Members as possible to go to her briefing next Tuesday.  </p> <p>If I am correct, what Senator Devine is asking for in her amendment concerns No. 11, the National Asset Management Agency (Amendment) Bill 2017.  Is that the one?  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#K00400"><p>It is the motion regarding Lloyds Pharmacy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#K00500"><p>Is the Senator asking for that to be taken today?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#K00600"><p>Yes, to be taken without debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#K00700"><p>Which one is it?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#K00800"><p>It is No. 62, motion No. 11.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#K00900"><p>I am slow to take it today on the basis that I had no foreknowledge of the motion coming before the House.  I do not want to divide the House on a very important issue, which I know was raised by Senator Gavan previously, but could Senator Devine wait until next Tuesday because it is important that we get proper notification of a motion?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#K01000"><p>Is there a possibility that the Leader would accept Senator Devine's proposal next Tuesday?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#K01100"><p>Yes, there is a possibility.  I do not want to divide the House.  I have not read the motion, to be honest.  I do not want to fly blind on this.  I am not against the motion.  If the Senator could wait until next Tuesday, I would be happy to take it then.  Could the Senator submit it again on Tuesday?</p> <p>Senator Devine also raised the issue of the proposed sex offenders amendment Bill.  This is being drafted with an update-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#K01200"><p>Senator Devine has until the end of the Order of Business to reflect on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#K01300"><p>My brain is ticking over just thinking about it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#K01400"><p>I must put it formally to Senator Devine and we might see what we can do with it at that stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#K01500"><p>The sex offenders (amendment) Bill is being drafted to update the Sex Offenders Act.  We hope to publish it in the autumn.  Senator Humphreys raised the issue of the good weather in the context of public order, health and safety and alcohol misuse.  I went out to D&uacute;n Laoghaire pier on Tuesday night and got caught in traffic coming back in from the concert.  The Senator makes the point that we need a set of standards which we should expect and live up to in terms of holding events in or around residential areas but also in terms of behaviour and what we can and should not allow.  The Senator made a good point.  I commend An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na on the work I saw last Tuesday night.  Garda&iacute; were very courteous and vigilant.  Their rationale was the safety of people travelling from the concert and people stuck in traffic.  I was one of them.  It took 45 minutes to get back to where I was going when it would normally take me two minutes.  Is it not great that we have concerts in venues like the RDS, the Aviva Stadium, Croke Park and P&aacute;irc U&iacute; Chaoimh?  The Cathaoirleach has ruled on Senator Humphrey's amendment.  I know the Senator will be disappointed with the ruling.  He can take it up with the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport at a different time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#K01600"><p>Minister Ross or Minister Flanagan?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#K01700"><p>Minister Flanagan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#K01800"><p>The Senator has a thing about the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#K01900"><p>I think it is just us.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#K02000"><p>The Leader should be careful about what kind of thing Senator Bacik has for the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport so b&iacute; c&uacute;ramach.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#K02100"><p>I do not know what the Cathaoirleach means.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#K02200"><p>I think we will head for the end line.  Senator Byrne rightly welcomed the extra special needs assistants, SNAs, for Limerick.  I commend her on her advocacy on behalf of Limerick.  She is a very strong voice.  It is good that more SNAs are being employed, particularly in the Limerick area.  I join with Senator Byrne in calling on the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport and the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport with regard to airports.  We must understand the importance of Shannon and Cork in our aviation policy.  We should not just put the emphasis on Dublin even though it is important and a hub.  The points made by Senator Byrne are very pertinent and valid in terms of the overarching policy of aviation in our country.</p> <p>Senator Leyden made reference to Roscommon.  I am not familiar with the details of the case about which he spoke but it is important that arbitration continues and that talking takes place.  I know he made the point about Kieran Mulvey, an esteemed public servant who has done a huge amount of work in the country.  His suggestion is one that could be taken up.  </p> <p>I join with Senators Warfield and Bacik in wishing everybody a happy Dublin Pride this weekend.  It is an important visible sign of our diverse, inclusive and welcoming nation and capital city.  I hope all those who participate in it enjoy themselves, do so safely and, again, hang out their brightest colours.  It is certainly an event I hope will happen with good weather.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=28"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I join with Senator Warfield in welcoming the publication tomorrow of the national youth strategy and commend the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs, Deputy Zappone.  I commend also Ms Una Mulally on the work she has done on the drafting of the report and in the consultative process which ends tomorrow with the publication of the report.  It is important work involving a wide range of stakeholders and people.  I agree with the Senator on conversion therapy and I commend him on the work he is doing in regard to that.  I hope the report will be positive in that regard.  It is the first LGBT strategy to be published and it is important and welcome.  It is being launched in association with Dublin Pride which will hopefully send the right message.</p><p>Senators Bacik and Humphreys raised the Judicial Appointments Commission Bill and Dublin Pride.</p><p>If Senator Devine is happy to wait until next Tuesday, I would be happy to take her motion then.  She can move it then.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#L00200"><p>I know this is highly irregular but while Senator Devine is gathering her thoughts, could I ask the Leader when the Heritage Bill will be before the House?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#L00300"><p>I do not have the schedule in front of me but, from memory, it will be the week of 10 July, but I am open to clarification on that.  I will consult with the Senator after the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#L00400"><p>Senator Devine has moved an amendment to the Order of Business: "That No. 62, motion 11, to be taken without debate before No. 1."  Is the amendment being pressed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#L00500"><p>The amendment is being pressed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#L00600"><p>I will accept the amendment.  I will not divide the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#L00900"><p>Go raibh maith agat.  I thank the Leader.  The strike is tomorrow.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#L01000"><p>  Order of Business, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.80" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 12.12 p.m and resumed at 12.45 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.81" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#O00100">Industrial Dispute: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#O00200"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That Sean &Eacute;ireann acknowledges that it is the failure of Lloyds Pharmacy management to adhere to a Labour Court recommendation that has precipitated the current dispute between Lloyds Pharmacy management and the workers of Lloyds Pharmacy; <br /><br />- condemns Lloyds Pharmacy management for failing to accept and implement the recommendations of the Labour Court in February 2017; and <br /><br />- calls on the management of Lloyds Pharmacy to respect the rights of Lloyds Pharmacy workers, to engage meaningfully with the workers through their representative union Mandate, and to introduce the recommendations of the Labour Court.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1383" speakername="Paul Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#O00300"><p>I second the motion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.84" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.85" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#O00500">Civil Law (Missing Persons) Bill 2016: Report and Final Stages</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.86" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Bill recommitted in respect of amendments Nos. 1 to 50, inclusive.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#O00700"><p>Amendments Nos. 1 to 4, inclusive, 7, 9, 13, 30 to 32, inclusive, 35, 36, 38, 41, 43 and 44 are related and may be discussed by agreement.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.88" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 1:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#O00900"><p>I thank the Seanad for taking this important legislation today.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Charles Flanagan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=414"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=414&amp;amp;pid=CharlesFlanagan&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=28"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I acknowledge the work of Senators Colm Burke, Lynn Ruane and Marie-Louise O'Donnell on this Private Members' Bill.  I am very pleased that we have been able to progress matters to the current Stage.  The Bill, as presented, provides for the effects in civil law of persons who are missing, including arrangements for the interim management of the property of the missing person.  At its core, however, is the making of provision for the civil status of missing persons where the circumstances of their absence are such that their death is virtually certain or highly probable.</p><p>I propose these amendments with a view towards focusing the Bill on status issues.  It is my view that the management of the property of a missing person requires a more rigorous framework than set out originally in the Bill.  I am proposing the deletion of all references to "interim management of property", including from the Long Title.  I am proposing a new Short Title to reflect the revised focus of the Bill on the presumption of death.  Section 3, which provides for the interim management of the property of a missing person, is proposed for deletion in its entirety.</p><p>The final substantive amendment I am proposing in this area is to amend the definition of "missing person".  I am of the view that the definition of a "missing person" is too broad in that it encompasses all missing persons, including those who step out of their lives for whatever reason but who subsequently return to that life.  Given that I am proposing that the Bill should not address the interim management of property, a revised definition of "missing person" is appropriate.  The definition I am proposing focuses on a narrower target group of persons whose death is either virtually certain or highly probable.  I would ask Senators to accept this for the purposes of clarity.</p><p>I acknowledge again, as I did before the arrival of Senator Marie-Louise O'Donnell, the importance of this legislation.  Having regard to the fact that it is some time - almost two years - since the Bill was originally published, I hope we can move matters towards a successful conclusion, perhaps by this evening.  I am not sure of the Senators' disposition in that regard; I can sit late if they wish.  I ask Senators to accept my amendments in the spirit in which they are proposed, namely, to ensure a level of clarity and acknowledging the fact that the Bill is a Private Members' Bill which the Government has accepted.  On the matter of the definition of "missing person", which is the most important issue here, the narrower definition I am proposing is in line with best practice for my Department, having engaged in consultations, and also draws on the considerable body of work undertaken by the Council of Europe in this area.</p><p>I again acknowledge the work of the Seanad&oacute;ir&iacute; in drafting and tabling this important legislation which will go some way towards meeting what was a difficult engagement for many families and persons who have gone through a very difficult process in terms of social and emotional engagement and of the legal consequences.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#P00200"><p>I thank the Minister and his officials for the work they have done in bringing forward the amendments.  I have gone through them in detail and am quite satisfied in an overall context.  They have streamlined what was an initial draft.  I have highlighted issues that could cause complications at a later stage.  There are one or two issues to which I will refer as we go through the amendments.  I do think it is important that we deal with this issue.  The most recent matter to which this is of great relevance is the incident off the Mayo coast in which four people tragically died.  The remains of two people have been recovered but the remains of the other two people have not.  It is in those kinds of circumstances that there is a legal vacuum.  If this Bill is passed it will deal with that issue.</p> <p>In the time of the Minister's predecessor, Deputy Frances Fitzgerald, as a result of the debate here in the Seanad a family contacted me whose daughter had gone missing.  All the evidence was that she had died although no body was recovered.  The only avenue open to me was to ask the Minister to get the coroner to hold an inquest.  In fairness, the Minister did follow up and, as a result, an inquest was held.  All of the procedures that could be carried out were completed for that family.  Although the number of families affected in this way in any one year is quite low, the legislation will also be important for those families.  Similar provisions have been up and running in Scotland for over 40 years and are in place in other jurisdictions as well.  We need to have these provisions in place to deal with very tragic circumstances where all the indications are that the person has died.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1383" speakername="Paul Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#P00300"><p>Fianna F&aacute;il is supporting the Bill and recognises the importance of legislation in this area.  We welcome the Bill and hope it can be progressed as quickly as possible.  I was a little taken aback to see there were no amendments submitted on Committee Stage.  To have a tranche of amendments on this Stage is a little unusual.  Having said that, I am encouraged by and will take guidance from the fact that my colleague, Senator Colm Burke, is supporting the amendments.  I am aware of the amount of work he has put into the Bill with the Department.  Given that he is supporting the amendments, we will also support them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1404" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#P00400"><p>I thank Senator Colm Burke for asking me to co-sign the Bill.  Senator Marie-Louise O'Donnell and I did not have to do much; Senator Colm Burke has been working for a long time on getting the legislation through.  I was delighted to support him.</p> <p>I have one question for the Minister which is more for my own understanding.  Perhaps I need to go away and do research and the answer might be there for me to find.  When Senator Burke talks about events off the coast of Mayo and other more certain circumstances, I wonder how, when the definition is narrowed - I have no issue with it being narrowed -  "virtually certain" and "highly probable" are to be determined.  Does there need to be a long investigation by the Garda and for the Garda to say it is highly probable?  What exactly is in place to make that determination in situations that are a little less clear cut?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#P00500"><p>I was privileged to be part of the Bill.  Senator Colm Burke led the way legally, parliamentarily and in every other way, language-wise, with the Bill.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Marie-Louise O'Donnell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2390"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2390&amp;amp;pid=MarieLouiseODonnell&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=28"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I learned a significant amount.  The Minister is correct that Senator Burke, among others, has been waiting for two years for the Bill to be progressed.  In the meantime, I wrote a big report for the Government on dying, death and bereavement and it was interesting that people's fears about their loved ones being lost and being in a legal limbo arose in that regard.  I congratulate Senator Burke and am happy to support the amendments if he is happy with them from a legal point of view.  I thank the Minister for seeing the Bill through to this Stage.  I will go along with what Senator Burke has to say about the amendments.  I look forward to the Minister's answer to Senator Ruane's question on the need for the Garda to say a death is highly probable.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#Q00200"><p>On the point raised by Senator Paul Daly, I do not wish to interfere with or intervene in the Standing Orders or procedure of the Seanad but there may be another opportunity to table amendments now that the Bill has been recommitted,.   I very much regret if Senator Daly believes he has been taken short by the debate this afternoon.  As always, I am very keen to accommodate Senators in every way possible, but the fact that we are now technically in committee-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#Q00300"><p>We are on Report Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#Q00400"><p>-----may give rise to a further Report Stage.  If not, my understanding is that the Bill will go to the D&aacute;il, which would give the Senator and his colleagues an opportunity to table amendments.  I hope to be as accommodating as possible of Senators, as I always try to be.</p> <p>On Senator Ruane's question, it will be a matter for the courts, having regard to all the circumstances surrounding the events, to define what is highly probable on a case-by-case basis.  That may be the best way of dealing with the matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#Q00500"><p>Does Senator Devine wish to contribute on amendment No. 1?  The Senators and the Minister seem to be in agreement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#Q00600"><p>I think we are in agreement and will not require a vote on the amendment.  I welcome that there is movement on the Bill and that it is progressing through the Seanad and hope that it will quickly progress through the D&aacute;il.  I wish to put on the record my acknowledgement of the good work done by Senators Colm O'Rourke, Marie Louise O'Donnell and Lynn Ruane in highlighting and championing the need for reform in this area.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#Q00700"><p>I think the Senator meant to refer to Senator Colm Burke rather than Colm O'Rourke.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#Q00800"><p>Senator Colm Burke.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#Q00900"><p>Yes, of course.  I thought that was what the Senator said.  Forgive me.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1383" speakername="Paul Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#Q01000"><p>Senator Devine said "O'Rourke".</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#Q01100"><p>Did I say O'Rourke?  I apologise to Senator Colm Burke and the Leas-Chathaoirleach.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.106" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.107" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 2:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.108" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.109" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 3:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.110" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.111" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 4:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#Q01800"><p>On amendment No. 4, the-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#Q01900"><p>The amendment has already been discussed with amendment No. 1.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#Q02000"><p>I wish to raise a technical issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#Q02100"><p>All right.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#Q02200"><p>The amendment inserts Part 1, which states "This Act may be cited as the Civil Law (Presumption of Death) Act 2018."  Amendment No. 50-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#Q02300"><p>This is a Government amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#Q02400"><p>We are on amendment No. 4.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#Q02500"><p>I know that.  This is a technicality.  Amendment No. 50 states &quot;&lsquo;<i>Act of 2018</i>&rsquo; means the <i>Civil Law (Missing Persons) Act 2018</i>&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#Q02600"><p>The Senator is pointing that out for clarification.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#Q02700"><p>We can refer back to that change at a later time.  It will be dealt with.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.122" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.123" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 5:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#Q03000"><p>Amendments Nos. 5, 6, 27, 29, 46 and 49 are related and may be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#Q03100"><p>A presumption of death order should be conclusive insofar as the end of a marriage or civil partnership is concerned.  These amendments deal with the issue of marriage.  Following discussions with the Office of the Attorney General, I am proposing in amendment No. 46 that either party can apply to the High Court for a rather novel form of declaration which, if granted, would have the effect of treating the marriage or partnership with a formerly missing person as one where a decree of divorce or a decree of dissolution had been granted.  This would not have the effect of reviving the marriage or partnership nor would it impact upon the status of any new marriage or partnership where relevant.  However, the provision would allow the parties to plug into existing family law arrangements such as maintenance or access.  I am advised that a provision of this nature would make a constitutional challenge less likely than the absolutist approach of simply bringing the marriage or partnership to an end.  I ask Senators to accept that amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#Q03200"><p>I agree with amendment No. 46.  It is important because we must be very careful of constitutional issues.  The amendment has been very carefully drafted and takes that issue into account and I very much welcome it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.127" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.128" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 6:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.129" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.130" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 7:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.131" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.132" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 8:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#Q03900"><p>To address any doubt in regard to the previous amendment, it creates a situation broadly similar to that in the United Kingdom.  Amendment No. 8 deals with expenses and is a standard provision which Senator Colm Burke and the other proposers of the Bill will concede was not addressed in the original Bill.  Senators will also agree that this is standard practice and a standard provision.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#Q04000"><p>On a technicality, the amendment now becomes section 2.  I presume that section 2 of the original Bill will become section 3.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#Q04100"><p>As a consequence, yes, and that will be reflected in the Bill as passed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.136" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.137" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 9:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#R00100"><p>Is the amendment agreed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#R00200"><p>No.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#R00300"><p>The Senator is not agreeing to it?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#R00400"><p>I would be against the amendment but will not be pushing for a vote on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#R00500"><p>The Senator is against amendment No. 9?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#R00600"><p>Amendment No. 9, yes.  Is that okay?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#R00700"><p>Okay.  Does the Senator want to say anything about it?  It was already discussed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#R00800"><p>Not really, I just think that many of the amendments that Sinn F&eacute;in will not be supporting are technical and unnecessary.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#R00900"><p>I take the Senator's point.  I think the question is carried.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.147" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.148" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 10:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#R01200"><p>Amendments Nos. 10 to 12, inclusive, are related, and may be discussed together by agreement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#R01300"><p>This relates to the matter of applicants in section 2.  Senators will see that section 2 of the Bill specifies the persons who may apply for an order under the provisions of the Bill or the Act, as it will be.  Amendment No. 10 inserts a specific provision for a half-brother or half-sister to be an applicant.  This is in line with the provision in legislation in Northern Ireland relating to applicants who are close relatives, in the context of the Disappeared, for example.  It makes common sense.  None of the legislation in comparable jurisdictions, including England, Wales, Northern Ireland and New Zealand, has an explicit reference to a creditor as an applicant as is currently contained in section 2(<i>f</i>).  I have formed the view that such a reference could, in certain circumstances, be misinterpreted.  Accordingly, amendment No. 12 proposes to delete &quot;creditor&quot;.  Amendment No. 11 is a technical amendment relating to the deletion of &quot;creditor&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#R01400"><p>I welcome amendment No. 10.  It was obviously left out and I welcome the addition of half-brother and half-sister.  It is a technicality and an important addition.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1404" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#R01500"><p>This might seem like a strange question.  I look at this and see "half-brother" and "half-sister".  Are those official terms used for family?  Where are they laid out?  Where does that come from?  Is that something that has been used as a description but is not actually a legal term to describe a family?  Is it something that we have applied to siblings ourselves?  What do we recognise half-siblings as?  My two daughters have the same mother but would not consider themselves half-sisters, but sisters.  Is it different if they grow up in the same household or are children of the same father?  I am sorry to confuse the issue.  I wonder what it applies to.  My daughter would have other siblings belonging to her father.  If there were half-siblings belonging to the father who never had a relationship with each other and never grew up in the same household, they would say they were half-brothers and half-sisters because their father happened to have a load of kids in various different parents of Dublin and they are technically seen as half-siblings.  Is there a definition of half-brother and half-sister?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#R01600"><p>These definitions have been accepted in law for a long time and would indeed be a consequence of the Succession Act with regard to entitlements under succession and establishing relations, whether by blood or accepted practice, and other aspects of legislation which were overlooked or omitted in this Bill but, in the circumstances, would reflect what is in essence an important interested party.  The interest relates to familial contact.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.154" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.155" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 11:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.156" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.157" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 12:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.158" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.159" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 13:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.160" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.161" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 14:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#R02500"><p>Amendment No. 14 relates to evidence in section 4 of the Bill and the presumption of a death order in respect of the missing person.  The amendment is "In page 5, lines 15 to 17, to delete &ldquo;fruitless&rdquo; in line 15 down to and including line 17 and substitute &ldquo;fruitless;&rdquo;."  I say this because the manner in which evidence should be provided to the courts is a matter best left to rules of court, so I propose the deletion of the requirement in respect of an affidavit, etc.  I propose to delete the provision for reliance on the international Convention Abolishing the Requirement of Legalisation for Foreign Public Documents.  I have already proposed the deletion of the associated definitions in section 1.  These definitions are part of our general law and obligations which flow from them, and will apply in any event whether or not there is specific reference to them in the Bill.  Is Senator Burke satisfied with this?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#R02600"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.164" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.165" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 15:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#R02900"><p>Amendments Nos. 15, 16, 24, 25 and 50 are related and may be discussed together, by agreement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#R03000"><p>These amendments introduce a measure of clarity and ensure strict coherence with existing arrangements which apply in respect of the registration of life cycle events in accordance with the Civil Registration Act 2004.  These amendments have been developed following consultation and in close co-operation with colleagues in the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection.  Amendments Nos. 15 and 16 will facilitate registration of a presumed death in the new register of presumed deaths which is to be established under Part 3 of the Bill.  The process envisages an applicant providing the details necessary to register a presumed death as part of an application for a presumption of death order, which will be available from the court.  It will be less onerous on the applicant since all the details required for an application for a court order and the registration of presumed death will be captured in a single application or process.</p><p>Amendment No. 24 places an obligation on the court to include in the presumption of death order the particulars available to it, which are necessary for the registration of a presumed death in the new register.  By virtue of amendment No. 50, those particulars would be set out in the new Part 5B of the First Schedule to the Civil Registration Act 2004.  This will have the effect of ensuring that the process is streamlined and that it will ease the burden on those applying for a presumption of death order from the court and, subsequently, presumably in a very short time thereafter, registering that death in the new register of presumed deaths.</p><p>Amendment No. 25 deletes the current provisions of the Bill which concern the registration of a presumed death.  However, it maintains the idea that a presumption of death order made by a court has the same effect as the registration of a death under section 13(1)(<i>d</i>) of the 2004 Act.  This amendment acknowledges that an appeal may be brought against the making of a presumption of death order, thus it introduces a stay on the effect of the presumption of death order until such time as the normal period allowed for an appeal has expired which, in the circumstances, is not only understandable but important.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Charles Flanagan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=414"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=414&amp;amp;pid=CharlesFlanagan&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=28"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Such a provision is also covered in the equivalent legislation in other jurisdictions.  It seems to act as a precaution to avoid inappropriate or presumed entries in the register of presumed deaths.</p><p>Amendment No. 50 is the most important in the group.  It provides for the establishment of a new register of presumed deaths through a number of amendments to the Civil Registration Act 2004, as amended.  The new register will be part of the suite of civil registers maintained by the Registrar General.  Specifically, amendment No. 50 inserts a new Part 5B into the Civil Registration Act 2004, as amended, which sets out the registration process and a new set of required particulars in Part 5B of the Schedule to the Act.  It is important to note that the amendments introduce a new register to record those cases where a presumption of death order has been issued by the courts.  The existing register of deaths will continue to operate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#S00200"><p>I welcome the amendments.  It is extremely important to create the register in order to have a clear record.  The proposed new Part 5B of the Civil Registration Act 2004 sets out all of the information clearly, including the date and place of presumed death and the place of birth of the missing person.  It is welcome that all of the relevant information will be added to the register and that a clear and accurate record will be kept as a result.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#S00300"><p>The registration process for which we are providing will place the onus on a court, once a presumption of death order has been made, to provide for the civil registration service the appropriate details to facilitate the registration of a presumed death.  The appropriate registrar of the civil registration service will then formally register the presumed death.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.171" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.172" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 16:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.173" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.174" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#S00700"><p>As amendments Nos. 17, 20, 22, 23, 26 and 28 are related, they may be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.175" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 17:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#S00900"><p>I am proposing these six amendments on behalf of the Government in acknowledgment of the fact that the Bill will give both coroners and the courts a role in the matters in hand.  Presumption of death orders should only be made by a court.  Other associated matters should also be dealt with by a court.  I do not envisage a role for coroners in matters addressed in the Bill.  The amendments propose to delete all references to the Coroners Act 1962 or coroners.  I think they will find favour with the proposers of the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.177" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#S01000"><p>I agree with the amendments.  We included the coroner issue in the original Bill because we were talking about two procedures.  I can see why the Department and the Minister have chosen to add clarity by providing for these issues to be dealt with by one stream.  In the circumstances, it is appropriate that they be dealt with by the courts only.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.178" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.179" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#S01200"><p>As amendments Nos. 18, 40 and 48 are related, they may be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.180" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 18:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.181" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#S01400"><p>As I said when introducing the amendments we have just considered, my view is that presumption of death orders should be made by a court only.  Other associated matters should also be dealt with by a court.  I am proposing revised jurisdiction provisions in amendments Nos. 40 and 48 because, as amendment No. 40 makes clear, my view is that applications for variation orders under section 7 should be made to the High Court only.  The reason for this is that such cases are likely to be extremely rare and, if they do occur, they may well give rise to difficult and often untested legal issues.  The High Court will also have jurisdiction where the Attorney General or a person acting on behalf of the State is the applicant, again because of the likely rarity and, in many cases, complexity of such issues.  Amendment No. 40 proposes to expand the category of persons who may apply for variation orders.  The Bill provides that a formerly missing person shall be the only person who can make such an application.  I am taking the opportunity to propose that an applicant may apply for a variation order.  Amendment No. 48 takes account of the fact that, where land is concerned, the jurisdiction of the Circuit Court is determined by market value rather than the rateable valuation.  The monetary threshold of the market value is currently set at &euro;3 million.  Amendment No. 48 also allows for jurisdiction based on the applicant's residence, a position which is consistent with that taken in other jurisdictions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.182" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.183" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#S01600"><p>As amendments Nos. 19 and 21 are related, they may be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.184" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 19:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.185" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#S01800"><p>As Senators will be aware, these amendments follow directly from the revised definition of "missing person" as someone whose existence has become uncertain because he or she has disappeared without trace and there are no signs that he or she is alive.  The distinction between a death which is virtually certain and one which is highly probable allows for a differentiation in the time period after which an application can be made for a presumption of death order and gives the courts a degree of certainty that the person in question is dead.  Given the profound and complex legal consequences of such an order, I consider such a distinction to be appropriate and necessary in these circumstances.  </p> <p>Amendment No. 21 addresses some concerns I have about section 4.  It does not specify a waiting period for an application for a presumption of death order.  In that context, it would be appropriate to draw a distinction between deaths which are virtually certain and deaths which are highly probable.  The amendment reflects the recommendation of the Council of Europe that there not be a minimum waiting period where the missing person&rsquo;s death can be taken as certain but where the body cannot be recovered.  For those whose death is likely, the Council of Europe has recommended that a minimum waiting period of a year be accepted.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.186" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.187" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 20:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.188" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.189" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 21:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.190" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.191" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 22:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.192" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.193" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 23:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.194" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.195" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 24:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.196" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.197" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 25:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.198" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.199" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 26:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.200" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.201" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 27:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.202" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.203" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 28:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.204" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.205" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 29:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.206" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.207" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 30:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.208" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.209" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 31:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.210" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.211" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 32:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.212" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.213" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#S04600"><p>As amendments Nos. 33, 42 and 45 are related, they may be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.214" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 33:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.215" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#S04800"><p>These are technical amendments.  I am not sure of the extent to which they require debate.  I ask Senators to accept them as being self-explanatory.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.216" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.217" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#T00200"><p>Amendment No. 34 is a Government amendment.  Amendments Nos. 34 and 39 are related and may be discussed together by agreement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.218" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 34:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.219" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#T00400"><p>This is merely an amendment to what was an incorrect cross reference.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.220" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.221" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 35:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.222" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.223" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 36:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.224" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.225" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 37:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.226" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#T01100"><p>In amendment No. 37, I am proposing to delete the words "being administered by the person who applied under section 5".  This is because section 6 requires the applicant to effect a policy of insurance in respect of any claim which might arise from a variation order.  It further provides that the insurance premium should be a charge on the estate of the missing person.  The amendment proposes the deletion of text which presumes that the applicant for a presumption of death order would always be the person charged with administering the estate, as such a presumption would not always be correct.  For example, a will might make specific reference to a named person to act as executor and that would not necessarily be the applicant in all cases.  I expect that Senators Colm Burke, Marie-Louise O'Donnell and Lynn Ruane, as the proposers, would accept what I am saying and allow for these circumstances should they pertain.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.227" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#T01200"><p>I welcome the amendment.  The issue of insurance will arise but it is important that there is some safety mechanism in place.  It is important that a person who takes the decision to apply for such a court order will be able to effect the necessary protection from his or her point of view.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.228" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.229" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 38:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.230" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.231" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 39:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.232" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.233" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 40:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.234" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.235" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 41:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.236" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.237" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 42:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.238" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.239" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 43:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.240" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.241" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 44:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.242" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.243" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 45:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.244" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.245" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 46:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.246" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.247" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 47:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.248" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#T03300"><p>This is to insert a new section after section 7.  The purpose of the new section 8 is to ensure that all affected parties are put on notice as to the making of applications for presumption of death orders or variation orders under section 4 or section 7 to avoid any injustice that might ensue if an application were to be made and an order granted in the absence of the parties.</p> <p>Section 4(5) in its current form puts the obligation, which is expressed in permissive terms, on the court to serve notice on an affected party.  This may not seem to be appropriate.  The obligation should be on the applicant with the court's duty being to ensure that the applicant's obligation has been complied with.</p> <p>There is no equivalent of section 4(5) in section 7 and this is a lacuna which the new section also seeks to address.  I ask the Senators to accept that this would be an obligation on the part of the applicant rather than something that is put on the court.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.249" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#T03400"><p>I welcome the amendment and I understand where the Minister is coming from on it.  There has to be an obligation on the applicant and providing for it in the legislation provides clarity.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.250" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.251" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 48:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.252" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.253" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 49:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.254" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.255" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 50:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.256" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#T04200"><p>May I make a point regarding Part 3, amendment No. 12 of the Act of 2004, which I raised earlier?  It states that the Act of 2018 means the Civil Law (Missing Persons) Act 2018, whereas at the start of the Bill we were changing the wording to the Civil Law (Presumption of Death) Act.  Could we get clarification on that issue?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.257" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#T04300"><p>That will follow to be sure that the references are in line with amendments we have already made to the Title.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.258" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#T04400"><p>I thank the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.259" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.260" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Bill reported with amendments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.261" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Bill, as amended, received for final consideration.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.262" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#T04700"><p>When is it proposed to take the next Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.263" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#T04800"><p>I propose that we take the next Stage now but I am conscious of what Senator Paul Daly said earlier.  I very much regret if he did not have an opportunity to-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.264" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#T04900"><p>If Senator Daly is happy-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.265" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1383" speakername="Paul Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#T05000"><p>I have received all the clarification needed.  I am happy to proceed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.266" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That the Bill do now pass."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.267" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#T05300"><p>I want to acknowledge the importance of this legislation.  It is a Private Members' Bill.  It is not often that we have an opportunity in either House to complete all Stages of a Private Members' Bill from start to finish.  I was very pleased, on behalf of the Government, to assist Senators Marie-Louise O'Donnell, Colm Burke and Lynn Ruane on this legislation.  I am aware that all the Senators, particularly Senator Burke, were keen to ensure this issue was never far from the priority list in terms of the ordering of business here in the Seanad.  I am pleased we were able to come forward with amendments before the end of this session, which will mean the Bill will be ready for transmission to the D&aacute;il.  Given that there is only a short period of time left, I do not suppose I can promise that the Bill will be taken in the D&aacute;il in the next couple of weeks but we are ready to proceed in early autumn.</p> <p>On behalf of the Government, I acknowledge the importance of collaboration in this regard.  The debate we have had in the past hour or more shows that, working together, we can bring about improvements.  We have a short but important Bill containing 11 sections.  The fact that we had 50 amendments indicates the approach of the Government in that regard.  I thank my officials, in particular, Ms Regina Terry.</p> <p>It was the preferred choice of the Government that we would accept the Bill in the names of the Senators and amend it rather than take the easier option of casting it aside and coming back at some stage with a Government proposal.  I am very pleased that the hallmark of this legislation, as it is enacted on the Statute Book, will bear the names of Senators Lynn Ruane, Marie-Louise O'Donnell and Colm Burke.  That is testament to their important contribution as legislators.  I am aware of the impact of this Bill and that these provisions will have an important and positive consequence, fortunately on a very small number of people.  Once enacted, the Bill will bring a degree of certainty, comfort and normality into the lives of those who continue to mourn a loved one who has gone missing.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Charles Flanagan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=414"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=414&amp;amp;pid=CharlesFlanagan&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=28"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Of all the engagements I have had in my diary over the past 12 months, National Missing Persons Day in Farmleigh was perhaps the most poignant I have experienced.  I want to acknowledge the work of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na missing persons bureau and the continued engagement of members of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na up and down the country on these most sensitive issues involving human tragedy.  I do not in any way presume to suggest that the Bill will assuage the grief of individuals and families in any way, but I have no doubt it will make a contribution in terms of taking a vital step which will enable people to move in a positive direction with their lives, even where there is a large measure of distress attended on that movement.</p><p>I thank Senators for introducing the Bill and my officials for ensuring that the Bill is now in a position where it can be regarded as legally robust and sound.  I am pleased that we all worked together and I hope we can move matters on to the Lower House for the autumn session.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.269" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#U00200"><p>I want to congratulate Senator Colm Burke because it is his Bill and we were privileged to be part of it.  I thank him for including me.  There were some marvellous speeches made on Second Stage, which ignited the Bill and encouraged the Government to prioritise it, which I was glad to see.  I thank the Department and the Minister most sincerely because the amendments tabled were excellent and enhanced and protected the Bill.  It is Senator Burke's day and he has worked very hard for it.  He saw the Bill through and stayed with it.  He was right.  As I said in my report, it came up in a thousand different ways which we forget about.  I agree with the Minister that it will not take away grief and pain, but will give some kind of conduit or ending for it, in terms of the awful vacuum for those left living when a person goes missing for years without any sense of returning.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.270" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1383" speakername="Paul Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#U00300"><p>I would like to be associated with those remarks.  I thank the Minister for his clarity in his explanation of the amendments.  I wish to compliment Senators Colm Burke, Marie-Louise O'Donnell and Ruane who brought the Bill forward.  From my short period of time here I know how hard it is to get a Private Members' Bill across the line.  I congratulate them.  It is a very worthy cause.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.271" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1404" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#U00400"><p>I join with my colleagues in congratulating Senator Colm Burke.  The Bill highlights other areas where we can work on legislation in a cross-party manner.  Sometimes we are too protective of legislation, but we can take a leaf out of Senator Burke's book and see where we can and cannot agree in order to work on important legislation.  This issue only affects a small minority but has a significant impact.  The House could work on many small Bills like this together and we should follow Senator Burke in working on such proposed legislation and move it forward together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.272" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#U00500"><p>I again congratulate Senators Colm Burke, Marie-Louise O'Donnell and Ruane.  There is compassion and empathy for those who have experienced the worst possible thing, namely, someone going missing.  To bring the Bill through the House is a great thing and I am delighted to support it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.273" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#U00600"><p>I thank the Minister for coming forward with amendments and giving a very detailed explanation of each one.  I thank his officials, in particular Ms Regina Terry, for their work, and all of those in the Department and the Office of the Attorney General who provided legal back-up support in bringing forward the amendments.  It is a very technical Bill and it is important that we get it right.  It is also important that I acknowledge the Law Reform Commission's extensive 2013 report which set out all of the issues which needed to be addressed.  It was great to be able to work from that background document and bring forward the Bill.</p> <p>I thank my colleagues, Senators Marie-Louise O'Donnell and Ruane, for their work.  Cross-party support on this matter was important.  The current law creates a significant vacuum for families.  Sometimes there is clear evidence that a person has died, something which was brought home to me after a debate here in 2016 when a family contacted me about a young girl who disappeared.  Her car was found on a beach and her clothes were found.  A note had been left and it was clear she had died, yet the family was left in limbo and was unable to finalise anything about her estate.  The Bill deals with such cases and it is to be hoped it will be passed by the D&aacute;il in the not too distant future.</p> <p>I thank my colleagues for their comments and contribution to this debate.  I look forward to seeing the Bill passed into law and being commenced.  In the amendments brought forward the Department approached areas in the Bill which were not covered by the Law Reform Commission even though it examined the issue.  That is not a criticism of it, rather it shows how technical the Department got in dealing with this matter and making sure all angles were covered.  I thank it for its expertise and willingness to deal with me, as well as its assistance to me in bringing the Bill to a conclusion in the House.  I thank the Department, the Minister and my colleagues.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.274" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.275" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#U00800"><p>When is it proposed to sit again?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.276" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1404" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#U00900"><p>We are sitting early next Tuesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.277" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#U01000"><p>At 12.30 p.m. next Tuesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.278" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018062800002#U01100"><p>I have an important meeting at 12 noon on Tuesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-06-28a.279" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>The Seanad adjourned at 1.40 p.m. until 12.30 p.m. on Tuesday, 3 July 2018.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>