<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.2" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Leas-Chathaoirleach i gceannas ar 14:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.4" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.5" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#A00050">Gnó an tSeanaid - Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#A00100"><p>I have received notice from the following Senators that they propose to raise the following matters:</p> <p>Senator Se&aacute;n Kyne - The need for the Minister for Health to make a statement on the need for an annual meningitis awareness campaign, and the funding of organisations that support bereaved families.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">An Leas-Chathaoirleach:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=1610"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1610&amp;amp;pid=JoeOReilly&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Senator John McGahon - The need for the Minister for the Environment, Climate and Communications to consider direct air capture technology as a means of reaching 2030 and 2050 climate targets.</p><p>Senator Garret Ahearn - The need for the Minister for Further and Higher Education, Research, Innovation and Science to provide an update on the proposed development of Kickham Barracks, Clonmel, as a dual campus of education between Tipperary Education and Training Board and the Technological University of the Shannon.</p><p>Senator Martin Conway - The need for the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine to make a statement on the changes to the Burren programme for farmers which will result in a potential loss of income and decrease in incentives for conservation measures. </p><p>Of the matters raised by the Senators suitable for discussion, I have selected Senators Aisling Dolan and Eugene Murphy, who are sharing their time, Se&aacute;n Kyne, Robbie Gallagher and Malcolm Byrne and they will be taken now.  I regret that I had to rule out of order the matter raised by Senator Boyhan on the ground that the Minister has no official responsibility in the matter.  The other Senators may give notice on another day of the matters they wish to raise.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.8" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#B00200">Nithe i dtosach suíonna - Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.9" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#B00250">Covid-19 Pandemic Supports</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#B00300"><p>It is my pleasure to welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Butler, to the House.  She is a very popular visitor.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#B00400"><p>I welcome the Minister of State at the Department of Health, Deputy Mary Butler.  I am sharing this Commencement matter with Senator Eugene Murphy.  We met with Annette, Cathy, Martina and Nora.  These are all people who work in Portiuncula University Hospital in Ballinasloe.  These are people who were on the front line all during the pandemic.  They were our hospital warriors in the face of Covid-19.  They were our warriors that went out every single day and left their families at home when we were asked to stay at home.  When we were asked to keep people safe, they were asked to keep people safe by going to work.  They put themselves on the line.  These are contract cleaners and caterers.  They work with Noonan's and Aramark, particularly in the Saolta University Hospital Group.  They worked 12- or 14-hour shifts and they did what was asked of them, as many of us did.  We came together as a country to fight this battle.</p> <p>The pandemic recognition payment is a recognition by the Irish Government on behalf of the Irish people to staff who worked on the front line.  We have an estimated 125,000 people, HSE and section 38 staff, who have now received this payment.  Let me say again, it is a payment totally in recognition of the work that was done.  However, a number of other categories remain.  Our question here is what are the categories that are left?  What about the clarification of contract cleaners and caterers for the pandemic health care payment?  Are cleaners and caterers part of this?  Do we have an estimate of the remaining payments and timelines now that we have a new provider?  What is that going to be?  I really appreciate the Minister of State's time on this.  We really need to have fair and equal treatment for people who have worked so hard to keep everyone safe and to save lives.  Members of my own family worked in cleaning.  I have worked in cleaning.  All through college I was involved in this kind of work.  These people were on the front line for us.  Go raibh maith agat.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#B00450"><p>I thank Senator Dolan for her timing.  I want to ensure that Senator Murphy gets two minutes or else he might think I was acting in a partisan fashion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#B00500"><p>You are always very fair and of course your Roscommon connection makes sure you are always so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#B00550"><p>I have to be.  Otherwise I would be in trouble.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#B00600"><p>Our health is our wealth.  It is really fantastic to see the Minister of State back here in good form and I thank her for letting me know the good news two weeks ago.  I am delighted for her because at the end of the day good health is what we all wish for.  Many people get challenges with their health every day of the week.  I am just going to endorse what Senator Dolan has said.  I think she has given the story as it is.  We met with those people.  Cathy and the others met us with their SIPTU representative in Gullane's hotel in Ballinasloe last week.  These people are struggling with the cost-of-living crisis to rear their families.  They are doing a very good job and they are coming up with what I would call an embarrassing situation for the Oireachtas.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Eugene Murphy:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2444"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2444&amp;amp;pid=EugeneMurphy&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I accept the Minister met these workers somewhere in Galway city in recent weeks, possibly at the university hospital, and that he was sympathetic.  I acknowledge he is trying and that the Minister of State is quite annoyed about the situation.  We are told this work is being out sourced to a company.  The reality is we should get on with whatever has to be done and try to get that money paid to those people for Christmas.  It is simply not right and it is embarrassing for us that it is happening and we need to get it out of the way.  I have no more to say about that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#C00200"><p>I thank Senators Dolan and Murphy.  They are setting a very good standard of working for a common objective in the constituency.  I invite the Minister of State at the Department of Health, Deputy Butler, to respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1614" speakername="Mary Butler" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#C00300"><p>I thank both Senator Dolan and Murphy for raising this really important issue.  In January of this year, to recognise their unique role and extraordinary efforts, the Government announced a pandemic recognition payment for front-line public sector healthcare workers.  The pandemic recognition payment was introduced to express the appreciation of Government for those working in front-line environments exposed to Covid-19.  Significant efforts have been made to progress the payments under this measure and it has been extremely frustrating.  As the Minister of State with responsibility for mental health and older people, I have found it particularly frustrating.</p> <p>These payments are the result of extensive efforts by Department of Health officials and the HSE.  To date, more than 124,000 eligible front-line HSE and section 38 healthcare workers have been paid.  This means the vast majority of these eligible front-line workers have now received the pandemic recognition payment.  A wide variety of front-line workers within the HSE and section 38 organisations are eligible for this payment.  Support staff such as cleaning and catering staff, among other groups, are included once they meet the eligibility criteria set out.  There are also certain non-HSE and non-section 38 healthcare workers who are encompassed by the Government decision.  Included in these groups are eligible staff in private sector nursing homes and hospices; section 39 long-term residential facilities for people with disabilities; agency roles working in the HSE; healthcare support assistants contracted to the HSE, who went into houses day after day during the pandemic; members of the Defence Forces redeployed to work in front-line Covid-19 exposed environments in the HSE and did Trojan work in supporting nursing homes and the roll out of the vaccine; and paramedics employed by Dublin Fire Brigade to deliver services on behalf of the HSE.</p> <p>The Department of Health has been working with the Department of Defence and the Local Government Management Agency to expedite and ensure the payment of eligible members of the Defence Forces seconded to Covid-19 exposed environments in the HSE as well as Dublin Fire Brigade paramedics.  The Department of Health has now transferred funds to Dublin City Council and the Department of Defence to allow for these payments to be completed as soon as possible.  Payments to these eligible workers will be arranged by their employers.  Anyone who was contracted directly by the HSE received their payments in a timely manner, but we have seen many areas where that did not happen.  I am glad to see the issue of payments to members of the Defence Forces and the Dublin Fire Brigade paramedics has been expedited.</p> <p>In August 2022, the HSE published an invitation to tender for a third-party contractor to assist with the payment process for eligible non-public sector workers.  The Minister of Health, Deputy Donnelly, has instructed the HSE to use a simplified process to expedite payments to non-HSE organisations and the HSE and KOSI Corporation have now finalised a process to ensure the payment of these workers.  I have spoken several times to the Minister regarding this and he is extremely frustrated by the slow pace of the delivery to the non-HSE workers and in rolling out the payments.  Last week, information packs began issuing to relevant organisations.  Packs have now issued to more than 750 organisations, including nursing homes, disability facilities, agency organisations and home care organisations.  Organisations which make prompt returns can expect to receive funds in the coming weeks and I know everybody will welcome that.</p> <p>Government is mindful of other workers who played their part in sustaining services during the Covid-19 pandemic.  Officials considered the matter carefully and listened to the views of stakeholders before reaching their decision.  It was difficult to draw a line on this matter, but the Government based its decision on the risks eligible front-line healthcare workers faced.  I take on board the point made by both Senators in relation to the contract cleaners and caterers but I refer again to the line that states there are also certain non-HSE and non-section 38 healthcare workers who are encompassed by the Government decision.  Support staff such as cleaning and catering staff among other groups are included once they meet the eligibility criteria set out.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Mary Butler:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2445"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2445&amp;amp;pid=MaryButler&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Support staff such as cleaning and catering staff, among other groups, are included once they meet the eligibility criteria set out.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#D00200"><p>I take it from the Minister of State's explanation that contract cleaners and caterers are included in this.  Is that correct?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#D00300"><p>The Minister of State will respond at the end.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#D00400"><p>The Minister of State's written response notes that packs have now been issued to 750 relevant organisations, including agency organisations.  The agencies I am concerned with, particularly around the sale to the university hospital healthcare group, which includes Portiuncula and other hospitals, are Aramark catering and Noonan cleaning services.  That would include the security porters.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#D00500"><p>I thank the Minister of State for her response.  I remember a number of weeks after the announcement being contacted by some of those people in Ballinasloe, family members of the contract cleaners.  I sought clarification.  The clear answer I got at that time was that staff of any company the HSE contracted to do work on the hospitals were eligible.  I think they will come under that.  I hope, given what the Minister of State said, things will start to move and these people will get the payments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1614" speakername="Mary Butler" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#D00600"><p>The pandemic recognition payment is in the final stages of its roll-out and should begin reaching organisations very soon so that eligible staff can receive the payment as soon as possible.  The nub of the issue is that there is a wide variety of front-line workers in the HSE and section 38 organisations eligible for the payment.  Support staff such as cleaning and catering staff, among other groups, are included once they meet the eligibility criteria set out.  These also include private sector nursing homes and hospices, section 39 long-term residential facilities for people with disability, agency roles in the HSE, healthcare support assistants, members of the Defence Forces and paramedics employed by Dublin Fire Brigade.  I hope that clarifies it.  My understanding is they need only meet the eligibility criteria that is there for all, meaning those who work for a certain amount of time on the front line.  Hopefully that payment will issue very soon.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.25" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#D00700">Infectious Diseases</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1665" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#D00800"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach's office for picking this Commencement matter.  I welcome the Minister of State.  It is great to see her back.  Hopefully she will be back to flying form in the coming weeks and months.</p> <p>I raise the issue of meningitis, meningitis awareness campaigns and supports for meningitis.  Invasive meningococcal disease is the most common form of bacterial meningitis in Ireland, causing up to 90% of cases.  The disease may present as meningitis, septicaemia or both.  Meningitis is inflammation of the meninges, which is the covering layer of the brain and spinal cord.  Septicaemia is a form of blood poisoning cased by the same organism that causes meningitis.  Early symptoms can include fever, headache, vomiting, diarrhoea, muscle pains, stomach cramps and cold hands and feet.  The HSE advises not to wait for a rash if someone is ill and getting worse, but to get medical help immediately.  One in ten people may carry the bacteria.  Carriage of the bacteria increases with age.  It is typically followed by development of immunity.  Peak carriage may occur in the 15-and-19-years age group, of whom 25% are carriers, but it is also highly prevalent in small babies and young children.  </p> <p>The impact meningitis can have on a family is tremendous.  It impacts small children, babies and young adults typically at the start of their college years or whatever.  It can be a sudden loss for those involved.  It is important that there be national awareness campaigns at local level, at schools and universities and across society so people are aware of the disease, who is most impacted and the symptoms.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Se&aacute;n Kyne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2343"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2343&amp;amp;pid=SeanKyne&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Act for Meningitis is a national charity based in Galway.  It aims to raise awareness and educate society about the signs and symptoms of meningitis, while offering free support services for those affected by the disease.  These support services are tailored to the needs of the individual or the family to find the most appropriate and beneficial service for them.  Act for Meningitis is a national charity, although it is based in Galway.  It has been turned down for the scheme to support national organisations on nine occasions.  It has applied to the HSE under different types of funding.  It is so reliant on donations and events that impacted families might engage in.  The support services it provides are hugely important for bereaved and impacted families.  It needs a reliable source of funding to ensure its services continue.  The organisation is 11 years in existence since last July.  It has no sustainable income.  Pre Covid, 68% of its income came from private fundraising and it is now down to 22%.  It is looking for sustainable funding to ensure its valuable work in raising awareness nationally about this disease can continue, to keep the show on the road and provide supports for impacted families.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1614" speakername="Mary Butler" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#E00200"><p>I thank Senator Kyne for giving me the opportunity to speak to the issues around meningitis awareness and the supports provided.  I am acutely conscious of some families that were recently bereaved, including the family of a beautiful young girl in my constituency.  As I speak here today, I am very conscious of the families left behind.</p> <p>The HSE has recently investigated a number of cases of meningococcal meningitis and septicaemia.  Meningitis is a serious illness involving inflammation of the membranes covering the brain and spinal cord.  It can be caused by a variety of different germs, mainly bacterial infections and viruses.  Bacterial meningitis, identified in recent cases, is less common but usually more serious than viral meningitis and requires urgent treatment with antibiotics.  Bacterial meningitis may be also be accompanied by septicaemia or blood poisoning.  These bacteria live naturally in the nose and throat of normal healthy persons without causing illness.  The illness occurs most frequently in young children and adolescents, usually as isolated cases.  Bacterial meningitis or septicaemia requires urgent antibiotic treatment.</p> <p>In Ireland, most meningococcal infections occur in winter and early spring.  Meningococcal disease may occur at any age but sporadic infection is most common in infancy and early childhood, with a second smaller peak of incidence in adolescents and young adults.  The HSE advises that if people have any concerns, they should contact their GP in the first instance but ensure that medical expertise is sought quickly.</p> <p>Vaccination plays a central role in disease prevention.  The meningococcal B vaccine and the meningococcal C vaccine are offered to children in Ireland as part of the primary childhood immunisation programme.  Protection against meningococcal C disease reduces over time so a booster dose is recommended for children in first year of secondary school, and age equivalent special school and home-schooled students, to provide additional protection against meningococcal C disease.  It is vital that parents check that their children are up to date regarding the recommended vaccinations.</p> <p>The HSE raises awareness around the signs and symptoms of meningococcal disease and the importance of children receiving the available recommended meningococcal vaccines to protect them from the most common meningococcal disease in Ireland.  World Meningitis Day takes place annually to help raise awareness around the disease.  This year's event took place on 5 October.</p> <p>I take on board the Senator's point about Act for Meningitis.  We are all in agreement.  I know it is a decision everyone makes for themselves but vaccination is so important.  As children grow older, we have to be aware of the symptoms that can present.  I have heard of Act for Meningitis.  I will look into the reasons the organisation has been unsuccessful on so many occasions with regard to funding.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Mary Butler:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2445"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2445&amp;amp;pid=MaryButler&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is very hard to raise funds.  Many organisations were very good at raising funds prior to Covid-19 but it has really challenged them recently.  Sections 38 and 39 of the Health Act 2004 provide for the HSE to provide funding for agencies to deliver services on its behalf.  There is, therefore, a funding stream in place.  That includes funding across a range of care areas including a number of organisations that provide bereavement support services to families.  All these details are available on the HSE website.  I take on board the Senator's point, however.  These recent cases frightened many people; they are worried.  People want a dedicated source of information at which they can look.  I will certainly raise the issue with regard to Act for Meningitis.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1665" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#F00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for that response.  We all unfortunately know of people who have suffered bereavements.  As I said, it is heartbreaking for families because it happens so suddenly, particularly in young adults.  The awareness is not just in that person but in his or her cohort.  Their friends might say there is something wrong and it is serious and this person needs help.  It can happen, and hours can be critical in diseases like this.  I would certainly welcome if the Minister of State could take the issue of Act for Meningitis up with the relevant section in her Department.  As I said, it has an office in the Ballybane area in Galway city.  I would appreciate if she could get back to me regarding a sustainable source of funding if that is possible.  The organisation does valuable work across the country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1614" speakername="Mary Butler" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#F00300"><p>Further work on raising awareness is carried out by the National Immunisation Office and the Health Protection Surveillance Centre through the sharing of content on social media platforms and web pages.  As we know, meningitis is also covered during the promotion of European Immunization Week in April every year.  If the Senator does not mind, he might drop me a quick email with regard to this and I will certainly have it looked at through the Department.  Volunteer organisations do a huge amount of work.  It is very important that we try to support them as best we can.  I will certainly have it looked at for the Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#F00400"><p>I thank the Minister of State very much.  I also thank Senator Kyne for bringing up this very appropriate matter during today's Commencement debate.  We are all aware of what meningitis has done to families so suddenly in different parts of the country.</p> <p>We always like to see visitors in the Gallery, some of whom I know, such as Cormac, and some of whom I do not.  They are all very welcome; c&eacute;ad m&iacute;le f&aacute;ilte.  I hope they enjoy their afternoon.  We are now taking Commencement matters, which is an opportunity for any Senator to raise an issue, which could be local or national in nature.  The Minister of State with responsibility for trade promotion, digital and company regulation, Deputy Calleary, is now entering the Chamber.  He will take an issue from Senator Robbie Gallagher from County Monaghan.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.33" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#F00500">Foreign Direct Investment</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1658" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#F00600"><p>I, too, welcome our guests.  I am glad to have the Minister of State with us as well.  I would like to take this opportunity, which is the first I have had, to congratulate him on his new appointment.  As they say, no better man for this job than his good self.</p> <p>I would like to talk to the Minister of State about a new IDA advance technology building that has been completed in County Monaghan.  The new 1,400 sq. m building was built at the IDA Business and Technology Park just outside Monaghan town at Knockaconny.  It has ancillary office space over two floors.  Advanced technology buildings, which are referred to as ATBs, are designed to facilitate a change of function to advance office buildings, if required.  They also have 100% expansion capability, which is a very good feature.</p> <p>The IDA said these ATBs offer ready for occupation, high-specification flexible and sustainable property solutions suitable for high-value manufacturing and global business services to support the winning of investment from foreign direct investment clients.  The Monaghan development is part of IDA Ireland's wider regional property programme, the objective of which is to develop property solutions in regional locations across the country in places such as Monaghan.  The initiative is vital in supporting the Border region in particular because in the past, the region has been left behind.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Robbie Gallagher:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2471"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2471&amp;amp;pid=RobbieGallagher&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This new facility must now help to attract more investment to a county and region that has previously had to fend for itself.  I am aware that advertisements to potential investors began when the building was completed towards the end of last year and that is an ongoing process.  I am also informed that the IDA is actively promoting this facility across 24 offices across the globe.  I hope that the IDA can find an investor with long-term potential and one that has the potential to grow even further. </p><p>County Monaghan and the Border regions have for far too long exported their children to the capital city and further afield.  It is interesting to note recent statistics, which state that Monaghan has in more recent years had one of the highest levels of young people going to third-level institutions of any county in the State.  However, unfortunately, many of our young people who graduate have no work in their native county to return to.  That is something that we need to address.  That is why a county like Monaghan is long overdue some foreign direct investment.  I believe that this facility has the potential to kickstart that development.  I appreciate that the Minister of State may be curtailed in what he can say to us this afternoon, but I am hoping that he might be able to outline what progress has been made to date by the IDA in trying to find a tenant.  How many site visits have there been?  Hopefully, as a result of those site visits, we might have some positive news for the county shortly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#G00200"><p>Go raibh maith agat.  Anois, an Aire, f&aacute;ilte go dt&iacute; an Teach inniu.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1602" speakername="Dara Calleary" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#G00300"><p>I, too, welcome the guests in the Gallery and I thank Senator Gallagher for his contribution, for his ongoing interest in this issue and for his good wishes.</p> <p>Senators will recall that 2021 was a record-breaking year for foreign direct investment employment.  Total employment in IDA client companies now stands at 275,384, which was up over 29,000 on the 2020 figure.  Growth in the regions was particularly buoyant, with 53%, or 133 projects of the 249 investments won by IDA, going to regional locations.  Employment growth was recorded in every region of the country in 2021 and our agencies are currently finalising the 2022 employment survey with a view to publishing it before the end of this year.</p> <p>Monaghan is marketed by the IDA as part of the wider Border region made up of the counties of Donegal, Cavan, Sligo, Leitrim, as well as Monaghan.  There are currently eight IDA-supported companies in Monaghan employing 430 people.  The FDI performance in the Border region has been strong over the past five years with employment among IDA clients increasing by 18% as traditional strengths in sectors such as engineering, industrial technologies and medical technologies were complemented by new investments from the technology, international financial services and life science sectors.</p> <p>Key to that success is strategic collaboration with national and local stakeholders on the enhancement of the regional value proposition.  The existing FDI-based companies in Monaghan enjoy strong collaborative links with several third-level colleges including Dundalk Institute of Technology, the Technological University of the Shannon and the Atlantic Technology University.  IDA Ireland is committed to ensuring a good supply of suitable property solutions to be available for FDI in regional locations and as such the agency has a network of business and technology parks across every region to support both IDA and Enterprise Ireland client companies. </p> <p>As the Senator said, IDA&rsquo;s business and technology park is located on the outskirts of Monaghan town, which is an 80-minute drive from Belfast City Airport and from Dublin Airport.  The park comprises 17 ha and is fully landscaped.  The development of the advance building solution in Monaghan was part of IDA Ireland&rsquo;s wider regional property programme.  The programme is funded by the Government with an extra &euro;20 million this year.  Completed in 2021, this building is located in the IDA park and offers additional IDA lands adjoining the site offering opportunities for expansion subject to planning.  The building includes a technology or manufacturing space and two-storey accommodation. </p> <p>I am advised that the IDA has regular engagement with client companies and stakeholders in the county and this will continue both towards the end of 2022 and throughout 2023.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Dara Calleary:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2201"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2201&amp;amp;pid=DaraCalleary&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->IDA Ireland will continue to market Monaghan and the wider Border region through its overseas offices, as referred to by the Senator, to target mobile FDI and will arrange corresponding site visits as required.  I will continue to keep pressure on IDA Ireland to ensure we fill the unit as soon as possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1658" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#H00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his comprehensive response.  I have no doubt he and his office will leave no stone unturned to ensure we find a suitable client for this state-of-the-art facility.  Monaghan has shown, through indigenous industries, whether in engineering with Combilift or in food with Monaghan Mushrooms, that we can be world leaders in whatever field we choose.  To date, unfortunately, foreign direct investment has been a stranger to our shores, so we hope that with this facility, and with the Minister of State at the helm, we will push all we can to ensure we get a suitable tenant here in order that our young people and graduates, who heretofore have been forced to travel, will have the option to come home to work in their chosen occupation, in line with their qualifications, in a facility located in their own county.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1602" speakername="Dara Calleary" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#H00300"><p>I assure the Senator I will certainly look forward to working him and other Oireachtas colleagues towards promoting this advanced building solution.  Its construction is a major win for Monaghan.  Having a site that is ready for go for any potential investor will put it well ahead of other locations.  As the Senator noted, there is a proud tradition of enterprise in Monaghan, and the collaboration I mentioned with the third and fourth level institutions and the easy access to transport hubs, for both air and sea travel, make it a high-value proposition for inward investment.  I will continue to work with the Senator on promoting that and I have asked IDA Ireland to keep me updated on its efforts to fill the building.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.41" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#H00400">Tax Reliefs</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#H00500"><p>I welcome the Minister of State at the Department of Finance, Deputy Fleming.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1638" speakername="Malcolm Byrne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#H00600"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it.  As he will be aware, we are seeing a global explosion in content production, in film, television, animation and the new digital sector, and Ireland has been very much to the fore in ensuring we get a slice of that international pie.  We have an excellent film, television and animation sector in Ireland, and one reason that has been the case relates to the section 481 tax relief, which helps in financing these productions.</p> <p>It was welcome in the budget that section 481 was extended to 2028 but there was no clarity in the budget concerning the regional uplift, which allows for projects to be produced outside the Dublin-Wicklow region.  This additional relief is available to allow film and television crews to travel, but the broader idea behind it was to ensure we could build up in the regions a sustainable film and television production sector and have people within the regions who would be able to support the development of the sector.  The Minister of State will be aware that all those who are involved within the industry, such as Screen Producers Ireland, Screen Guilds of Ireland, Animation Ireland and Ard&aacute;n, which represents the studios, as well as IBEC, the audiovisual sector and SIPTU, as the main trade union, were all supportive of this because we could see the development starting to happen.  Indeed, he will be aware of film and television production that was starting to happen in his county, Laois.</p> <p>This relief is crucial, not least as we are looking at seeing a significant number of new film and television studio spaces developing throughout the country, including in Westmeath and my county, Wexford.  To ensure we have something that is sustainable until 2028 and in order that we can guarantee to the regions that there will be support, we should have, as was originally introduced in 2019, a 5% regional uplift until 2028.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Malcolm Byrne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;MemberID=1111"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1111&amp;amp;pid=MalcolmByrne&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This would mean that it would be more attractive to look at filming and creating new content outside the Dublin-Wicklow hub.  It would make it attractive for domestic production and also particularly in terms of us being able to attract international productions to Ireland.</p><p>We also know the tourism and cultural dividends that come from investment in film and television production when people from outside this country see the scenery on offer here as a result of what they see on their screens, it makes it more attractive.  There have been numerous reports to verify this.  I hope, while it is welcome that section 481 has been extended, that the Government will commit further to regional film and television production and to animation production by ensuring the extension of the regional uplift.  When it was originally introduced, Covid-19 was not anticipated, which interrupted the process.  Now, we need a period to allow that to bed in and allow for regional film and television production and animation to grow in a way that will support jobs in all of our regions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1590" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#J00300"><p>Section 481 of the Taxes Consolidation Act 1997, also known as the film tax relief, is intended to act as a stimulus to the creation of an indigenous film industry in the State creating quality employment opportunities and supporting expressions of culture.  I thank the Senator for his opening remarks.  He has shown a depth and knowledge of the industry that very few Members have and he has gone through the various groups involved in the sector that participate and are involved in it.  They earn a good livelihood and income from it, with the benefit of the tax consolation relief I mentioned.  The scheme provides relief in the form of a corporation tax credit related to the cost of production of certain films.  The credit is granted at a rate of 32% and is available on qualifying expenditure of up to &euro;70 million for any project or film.</p> <p>The Finance Act 2018 introduced a short-term, tapered regional uplift for productions being made in areas designated under the state aid regional guidelines.  The purpose of the regional uplift is to support the development of new, local pools of talent in areas outside the current main production hubs of Dublin, Cork and Wicklow to support the geographic spread of the audiovisual sector.  The uplift originally provided for an increase of the credit for four years, with 5% available in years 1 and 2, 2019 and 2020.  That 5% uplift is on top of the 32% available everywhere in the country.  That was followed by 3% available in year 3, 2021, and 2% available in year 4, 2022.</p> <p>However, in recognition of the detrimental impact the Covid-19 crisis had on the audiovisual sector, the Finance Act 2020 amended the original uplift scheme to provide for an additional 5% in 2021.  Instead of being available for two years, it was available for three.  I asked about the matter that surely during Covid-19, this may not have cost the Exchequer that much, but the film sector did reasonably well during the Covid-19 period as lots of their productions were in different areas throughout the country and the sector was more resilient during Covid-19 than many others.  That may not have been anticipated at the time.  In effect, this was to replace the incentive year lost.  As I said, an extra year was given.  The tapered withdrawal of the uplift then restarted this year, with a reduction to 3% in 2022.  It will reduce 2% in 2023.  No uplift will remain thereafter.</p> <p>The uplift is an approved state aid.  The premise upon which it was notified to the European Commission was that it would be temporary in nature and would be withdrawn on a tapered basis.  If the uplift was deemed to be permanent, it might not have been approved in the first instance.  If the uplift were to be changed or retained for a further period, we would then have to go back to the European Commission and start negotiations again.</p> <p>I am aware of how the uplift was received upon its introduction.  However, there are currently no plans to increase the regional uplift rate or to introduce alternative proposals for regional-specific changes in the context of section 481.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Sean Fleming:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=418"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=418&amp;amp;pid=SeanFleming&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The main film tax credit will remain available to qualifying productions in all areas of the country following the winding down of the uplift in those regions.  That costs about &euro;70 million per annum.  The Senator is aware that the Government is committed to the continued growth of the audiovisual sector.  The Finance Bill 2022 provides for the extension of section 481 from the current end date of 31 December 2024 to 31 December 2028.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1638" speakername="Malcolm Byrne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#K00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  I appreciate that he is only reading the figures given to him by the Department of Finance.  It is clear that the Department is not committed to the development of a regional film and television industry on the basis of this response.  That is quite disappointing.  It is also clear that the Department does not understand the importance of section 481 and the regional uplift.  The fact that everyone in the sector saw new productions coming into the regions that would not have happened if it were not for the uplift.  It was well-intentioned and was interrupted by Covid.  The scheme was only getting going and then it disappeared.  The Minister of State made the point that it was temporary, as agreed with the European Commission.  Did any further negotiation with the European Commission take place?  I do not believe so.  Given the fact there was an interruption, if we were to consider temporarily extending the scheme to allow it to continue until 2028 in line with the current section 481 arrangements, that would allow us to develop a strong regional film and television sector.  We must give it a chance.</p> <p>I ask the Minister of State to ask the Minister for Finance to reconsider this matter.  The scheme is important for the development of the sector in the regions.  The Department does not fully understand how important the uplift is.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1590" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#K00300"><p>I acknowledge what Senator Malcolm Byrne said.  The fact the Department is, in the context of the Finance Bill, extending the main relief available under the scheme for all counties for another four years is an indication that it fully supports the general scheme.  It is a nationwide scheme.</p> <p>On assisting particular regions, the Senator will be aware the Department of Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sport and Media recently announced funding of &euro;2 million for the establishment of five new national talent academies in Wicklow, Limerick, Galway and Dublin for film, television, drama, animation and production crew.  Various local authorities are active in this area through their arts offices in facilitating local projects.  IDA Ireland is working in this area to increase facilities in different regions.  In the context of the Finance Bill, which is currently going through the Oireachtas, there are no plans to extend the uplift.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#K00400"><p>I thank the Ministers of State, Deputies Fleming, Butler and Calleary, the Senators who tabled Commencement matters and the staff, including the ushers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.50" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar fionra&iacute; ar 3.18 p.m. agus cuireadh t&uacute;s leis ar&iacute;s ar 3.30 p.m.<br /><br />Sitting suspended at 3.18 p.m. and resumed at 3.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.51" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#N00100">An tOrd Gnó - Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1665" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#N00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, statements on Housing for All, to be taken at 5 p.m. and to conclude after two hours, if not previously concluded, with the time allocated to the opening remarks of the Minister not to exceed ten minutes, group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes, all other Senators not to exceed five minutes, time can be shared and the Minister to be given no less than eight minutes to reply to the debate; and No. 2, Private Members' business, Protection of the Native Irish Honey Bee Bill 2021 - Committee Stage, to be taken at 7 p.m. and to adjourn after two hours, if not previously concluded.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#N00300"><p>I will today deal with something that is very topical.  Because of his Roscommon connections, the Deputy Leader will know what I am going to talk about, which is Lough Funshinagh and the serious flooding in south Roscommon.  The callows area along the River Shannon has flooded for years and years.  Part of Senator Kyne's county in south Galway also floods very badly.  I posted a video on social media last week in which I travelled to Clonown in south Roscommon where literally thousands of acres of land are now flooded.  The farmers have moved their stock off it.  Roscommon County Council had carried out considerable work on the roadways in the area in recent months, raising them in the hope that floods would not interfere with them.</p> <p>However, I was brought on a bit of a tour by some of the farmers up there and it was extraordinary to see the water cutting off some roads.  In light of the forecast that the incessant rain of recent weeks is going to continue, I fear for local communities.  Farmers move their cattle off the land in time because everybody understands most of that land is going to flood.  The problem we are now going to have is that households and people may be cut off.  This creates very significant problems.  We had this problem in 2016 and in 2009 so it looks like it is coming every six or seven years.  Nobody can say that such flooding is a once in 100 years event anymore.</p> <p>Perhaps the Deputy Leader could talk to the Minister of State with responsibility for the Office of Public Works, OPW, Deputy O'Donovan, who is very aware of the situation, with a view to ensuring that all of the agencies including the OPW, the ESB and everybody else involved with the Shannon can keep the water flowing.  When I say that, I do not mean that people downstream in Clare or Limerick should be flooded.  However, we sometimes find that gates are not opened in Meelick.  Senator Gavan will not want me to flood Limerick but we should ensure that as much water as possible is let go to avoid people in our region being very badly affected again.</p> <p>With regard to Lough Funshinagh, the Minister of State, Deputy O'Donovan, will be meeting with a local group and Oireachtas people next Thursday here in Dublin to see if a way out can be found.  All in all, it is just a question of the weather and the incessant rainfall and of the hardship and misfortune being brought to many people, particularly in the Roscommon and Galway region.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#N00400"><p>I concur with the Senator.  As he will be aware, I have a lot of family in that catchment area.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">An Leas-Chathaoirleach:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=1610"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1610&amp;amp;pid=JoeOReilly&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This is a tragic situation where people are out of their homes etc. but the Senator has put the case very well so there is no reason for the Chair to make a further intervention on it.  I now call Senator Conway to speak on behalf of the Fine Gael grouping.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#O00200"><p>The Minister, Deputy Eamon Ryan, visited Clare last week and as always, the Minister is always very welcome there.  He turned a sod officially on the new Killaloe bridge project, which is badly needed in south-east Clare because there has been traffic congestion there for years.  I sincerely hope that we will see the Blake&rsquo;s Corner project in Ennistimon moving swiftly forward, now that it has overcome the An Bord Plean&aacute;la hurdle.</p> <p>The point about which I was most disappointed with the Minister's visit to Clare was his absolute insistence that the northern distributor road to connect south-east Clare to Limerick has no prospect whatsoever of getting funding in the short, medium, or long term.  This is most disappointing because that particular stretch of road is essential for road transport connectivity between south-east Clare, Clare, Limerick and beyond.  Some &euro;19 million has already been spent on this project and we already have the first phase of that road between Coonagh Cross to Knockalisheen open.  To have this project completely dismissed out of hand is not acceptable.  I am looking for a debate here in the House in order that we can tease out this particular issue and find out exactly why the Minister believes that this project will not happen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#O00250"><p>Well said.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#O00275"><p>Senator Gavan knows as well as I do how important this particular issue is.</p> <p>This is a project which was committed to by previous governments and my understanding of the programme for Government is very clear, in that any project that has been committed to would proceed.  Where has the change happened in the programme for Government?  We need clarity on that fairly urgently.</p> <p>The other issue I wish to raise with the acting Leader is the plight of the farmers on the Burren in County Clare, who essentially are the custodians of the Burren and who have done great work in protecting the environment and in ensuring the flora, the fauna and the unique character of the Burren thrive.  That has happened through State support with a particular scheme that has been developed, promoted, designed, and has been ultimately successful in European awards.  Dr. Brendan Dunford and other people have worked tirelessly to create a scheme that benefits and promotes farming in the Burren but also conserves that area and ensures that its unique international character is retained.  There is the winterage scheme and even the Burren Winterage Weekend festival, which took place two weeks ago and was a phenomenal success.</p> <p>Now, the farmers are being encouraged to take part in an agri-climate rural environment scheme, ACRES, which is operating in part of Galway and other areas.  This is welcome in its own right but the problem is that it will certainly create a situation where farmers in the Burren will be short-changed.  Yes, it will benefit some but it should benefit all.  While ACRES is welcome in its own right, why should farmers in the Burren suffer as a result of it?  What was wrong with the scheme that this Government and previous governments nominated for and which won international awards?  What was wrong with that scheme running in parallel with ACRES?</p> <p>My call is to have a debate with the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine on ACRES in this House in order that we can tease out why he intends to financially disadvantage farmers in the Burren.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#O00287"><p>I thank Senator Conway.  The proposition is clear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1645" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#O00300"><p>On 12 July, in the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs and Defence, I asked the Minister, Deputy Coveney, if the constitutionality of overflights by the RAF had ever been considered by the Cabinet.  The Minister, Deputy Coveney, replied that &ldquo;We do not have overflight arrangements with the RAF, to be clear.&rdquo;<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Gerard P. Craughwell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2402"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2402&amp;amp;pid=GerardPCraughwell&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Yesterday afternoon in the House of Commons, following a question from Mr. Ian Paisley Jr., the DUP MP for North Antrim, on the issue of overflights by the RAF in Irish airspace, the relevant Minister stated:</p><blockquote>	The hon. Gentleman will know, however, that RAF jets have deployed into Irish airspace on occasion.  It is for the Irish Government to set out their policy on why, when and how. </blockquote><p>Today, the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Defence issued a statement.  The statement read:</p><blockquote>	We do not comment on issues concerning arrangements of national security.  The Government's engagement in international security cooperation is aimed at ensuring public safety and is conducted with full respect for Irish sovereign decision-making authority and for Ireland's long-standing policy of military neutrality. </blockquote><p>We cannot claim military neutrality if we are depending upon a third country to defend our airspace.  The issue of Irish neutrality has long been a question in this House.  Many Ministers down through the years have declared how Ireland is neutral.  We are militarily aligned with the UK, which is a member of NATO.  As a result, our airspace is being protected by NATO aircraft.<br/><br/>Article 15 of our Constitution - of which we are the guardians - states that it is the Houses of the Oireachtas that has the authority to raise armed forces.  The question of the RAF overflying our airspace has never come before the Houses of Oireachtas.  The matter has not been debated in the Houses.  Question about this matter arise today as a result of the statement made in the House of Commons yesterday.  This Oireachtas is faced with a dilemma.  Has the Minister knowingly misled the joint committee or is he not aware of the agreement that is in place to allow armed RAF aircraft to fly though our airspace?  This is a question for the Oireachtas to resolve.<br/><br/>On whether an agreement should have been entered into, the question for the Oireachtas is does our Constitution require that such a decision would come before the Houses and be agreed by them?  We cannot claim neutrality while we depend on another country to defend our airspace.  We cannot declare neutrality while we are in a military alliance with another country.  I respectfully request that the Minister for Defence come before the House to explain to us the dichotomy with which we are faced.  Is there an agreement in place?  If there is, who put it in place, when was it put in place and why was it put in place?  Why was the General Officer Commanding the Air Corps and the director of military aviation informed at the time the agreement was put in place?<br/><br/>This is the most serious constitutional issue that has come before the House in my time, and for as long as I can remember before that.  People talk all the time about it taking 800 years to get the Brits out of Ireland.  They are not out of Ireland.  They are protecting our skies.  I understand they are building a ship to protect the cables beneath our waters.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#P00200"><p>I wish to draw the House's attention to the fact that Members are not allowed to suggest that a Minister might have misled the House or an Oireachtas committee.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1645" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#P00300"><p>With all due respect, it is fairly clear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#P00400"><p>We will move on.  I call Senator Gavan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#P00500"><p>Today I want to raise the issue of the cost-of-living crisis and ask for an urgent debate on the matter.  Some of the Members may have seen the survey published by Barnardo's at the end of last week that showed that there were times in the past 12 months when one quarter of families across this State could not feed their children.  The same survey also showed that some 41% of households have been consciously cutting back on food spending.  A spokesperson for Barnardo's stated:</p> <blockquote> 	According to our research the cost-of-living is forcing families to choose between food and other essentials, such as energy costs.  Barnardo's has seen a marked increase in demand for its services and is concerned about the toll that soaring bills are having on families' mental health. </blockquote> <p><!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paul Gavan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2469"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2469&amp;amp;pid=PaulGavan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I want to highlight how the cost-of-living crisis is hitting our nurses and healthcare workers in particular.  Some of them have started to share their stories on social media and I shall quote a couple of them.  One says:</p><blockquote>	I am a nurse.  I am awake all night worried.  I have three children and work full-time.  I don't even have the petrol money to get to work next week.  My ESB bill will be out on Monday.  I don't even know how I will feed my children.  What has this country come to?  At this stage I feel like walking away from it all. </blockquote><p>A second nurse simply says, &quot;I can't cope with the mounting bills&quot;.  The Irish Nurses and Midwives Organisation, INMO, has repeatedly raised concerns about the safety of staff, particularly at University Hospital Limerick, which continuously has the highest trolley numbers in the country and serious overcrowding issues.  The staff are burned out and overwhelmed.  Then they go home after a long day or night's work and worry endlessly that they will have no food on the table for their family or money to pay the bills.  This is the reality of life for too many front-line workers and nurses in Ireland in 2022.<br/><br/>A cost-of-living crisis rally will take place at City Hall in Limerick on Saturday at 2 p.m.  The protest is being organised by the national Cost of Living Coalition, with local involvement from several political and community groups, including Sinn F&eacute;in, People Before Profit, the Social Democrats, the Socialist Party, the Postgraduates Students' Union, the Community Action Tenants Union and Limerick Suicide Watch.  The Government has not done enough to tackle the cost-of-living crisis.  It has even opposed taxing the windfall profits on energy companies, which is an absolutely shameful decision.  There are solutions.  Germany is the latest country to introduce a temporary price cap on electricity and gas.  Sinn F&eacute;in has called for less than that and just a temporary cap of five months on electricity to reduce the cost of electricity over the winter period.  Childcare, rents and mortgage interest costs here do not have to be the most expensive in Europe.  There are solutions.  What we need is a much firmer response from the Government.  I call on the people of Limerick to join us at 2 p.m. this Saturday for the cost-of-living crisis rally.  Show solidarity, stand up and call very clearly on this Government to do more.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#Q00200"><p>I welcome our guests from Monksland, which is an area near Athlone, to the Gallery.  It is good to have them visiting Leinster House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1663" speakername="Annie Hoey" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#Q00300"><p>I ask Senators to please forgive me because I must leave this session a little early.  I apologise to the Leas-Cathaoirleach and the Deputy Leader.</p><p>I am sure that we all saw the chaos generated by the Twitter layoffs at the weekend.  Twitter laid off people, potentially unlawfully.  The situation is still somewhat unclear, with employees in the Dublin office being let know of their redundancies via email.  Some employees, a number of whom I know personally, tweeted that they had no access to their work emails and feared that they had been laid off.  There was a really terrible lack of communication regarding the whole matter.  I do not need to go into numbers, but we know that 50% of Twitter's employees have been laid off and that offices have been temporarily closed to prevent staff returning.  In Ireland, staff are entitled to a 30-day consultation process even if there is no trade union.  There is still legal uncertainty about the layoffs.  An employee who lost their job at Twitter in Dublin noticed that their password had been changed overnight.  In Ireland, it is a requirement that staff are given a formal written letter of redundancy, which Twitter failed to do.  There have been conversations on the matter involving the T&aacute;naiste.  I would like to know what exactly the Government or the T&aacute;naiste intend to do about this matter.  It is no good offering platitudes in the media in respect of this matter.  What is needed is firm action.</p><p>The second topic I want to discuss is the forthcoming World Cup in Qatar.  Amnesty International has stated that significant human rights violations have occurred in Qatar in preparation for the World Cup and has called for workers to be compensated.  It is stated that these workers have been housed in poverty-laden communities, often without access to basic amenities like running water, working sewerage infrastructure or electricity.  These workers were expected to work for up to 18 hours a day with no day off during the week.  It has been reported in <i>The Guardian</i>that up to 6,500 migrant workers may have died in the country in the decade after it won the right to host the event.  That is a serious number of deaths.  Amnesty International and other organisations have said that there has been insufficient research into the thousands of deaths of those who worked in construction in the country over the past decade and the contribution that the extreme heat played in this.  I need not even go into the perilous situation faced by the LGBT community in Qatar.  Under the Qatari regime a cursory Google search will reveal the horrors that members of my community have been subjected to.  I shall quote some words by a Nepalese worker who said:</p> <blockquote> 	You see, some families are in rented accommodation back home.  Now for eight months if we don&rsquo;t send any money, how would they live there?  Their landlord is going to throw them out of their houses now.  Right now they are somehow trying to make ends meet...  That&rsquo;s why we are asking the company, &lsquo;it is ok if you don&rsquo;t give us money, but please send us home&rsquo;.  We asked them to just return our passport and send us back. </blockquote> <p><!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Annie Hoey:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=AnnieHoey&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is an extremely serious situation over there.  It is important to put on the record while we are gearing up for a global sporting event.  It behoves us to be aware of the brutal regime that lies behind this event.  Sport should be for all.  Alas, it seems that this World Cup event cares little for the thousands of migrant workers who potentially died in its preparation or indeed the LGBTQIA people who are going to be hunted and tormented as happy football revellers descend upon Qatar.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1633" speakername="Niall Blaney" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#R00200"><p>I wish to call for a debate on safety in our sporting stadia, particularly in light of events in Markets Field in Limerick last Friday night.  Galway was taking on Waterford in a League of Ireland decider match.  The match was held up during the first half because of structural issues.  Thankfully garda&iacute; intervened quickly and got all the Waterford supporters out.</p> <p>In this day and age we should not be having such issues in our stadia.  Thankfully there were no injuries in this case.  I commend the garda&iacute; and personnel on the ground.  This is quite worrying.  I have since spoken to supporters of other League of Ireland clubs and they have concerns about other facilities across the country.  It is timely that we have a debate in the House on the safety code and standards within our stadia.  It would be timely for the relevant committee on tourism, culture, arts, sports and media to have an update from the FAI on all the stadia within its brief and stadia of clubs within the League of Ireland.  I do not think this is good enough.  It is important that we act.</p> <p>It is timely that we would have a review of clubs in all sporting disciplines.  We have had enough tragedies over the years with sporting facilities and other structural facilities.  We do not need more.  This is a call to act.  I ask the Acting Leader and the committee to act.  It is timely that we have a review from all sporting facilities and organisations as to the status and safety code of all their facilities.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#R00300"><p>I ask that the Minister for Enterprise, Trade and Employment come to the House and that we have a debate on the world of work, in particular on employment law and the situation regarding our tech industry in light of the appalling behaviour by Twitter over the weekend and especially Mr. Musk and the way he has trampled on the rights of workers.  Like Senator Hoey, I wish to express my abhorrence at what has happened to the workers.  There was no notification other than by an email.  They were locked out of their accounts and out of the place where they work.  There was no due process in terms of the 30 days' notice that we have in this country.  The rights of the workers were trampled on.</p> <p>Thankfully, we have robust employment laws which must be adhered to and followed.  It is important that we have a debate in the House on the nature of work now and on the tech industry around jobs and job security.  I very much welcome that the Minister, Deputy Varadkar, and Ministers of State, Deputies Calleary and English, met yesterday with IDA Ireland and Enterprise Ireland regarding the situation.  It is important that we as a House stand in solidarity with the workers.  While recognising that Twitter is a global corporation, we do have to recognise that we have robust employment laws in this country.</p> <p>I also concur with Senator Hoey regarding the World Cup and the awarding of the contract to Qatar, especially given its denial of and complete lack of regard for the rights of people who are of our LGBT community.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->As we move towards the World Cup I will be calling for a further debate on how sporting events are awarded.  It is important that we send a message from the floor of the Seanad to the workers in Twitter in particular.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#S00200"><p>On 24 July 2020, I said in this Chamber that the decision to postpone bowel and breast cancer screening over the course of that spring and summer until September was a mistake.  Even at that early stage, when social media was awash with videos of people dropping dead on the streets of China, falsely attributed to Covid-19, and fear and panic around the unknown severity and mortality rate of the virus gripped the country, the cancelling of essential cancer screening seemed to many to be an ill-judged decision.  As time went on and we learned that our worst fears could never be realised, the full reopening of these services should have been swift and decisive but such was not the case.  Repeated Government-ordered lockdowns caused further disruption to appointments and check-ups and even when these were available the chilling effect of Government and media fearmongering led to so many people ignoring early warning signs.  They were terrified to step outside of their homes to go and receive medical care.</p> <p>It is important to distinguish that Covid did not cancel cancer appointments but the Government and the HSE did.  In his comments as reported last week, the Taoiseach seemed to once again portray the mindset that lockdowns were a thing that just happened as a result of Covid, rather than them being decided on by the Government and enforced by organs of this State, which it leads.  The issue was raised directly with the Taoiseach in the Lower House on 31 March 2021 by Deputy T&oacute;ib&iacute;n.  The Taoiseach told him in an exchange that should not quickly be forgotten to "get real".  It would seem that the reality has finally caught up with us just in time for winter when our healthcare system, the most expensive in Europe by some metrics, struggles and falters every year, even pre-Covid.  In the months to come people across the country will receive news that they have cancer and that it could have been treated if it had been caught sooner but it was not.  I am not asking that the Taoiseach provide a miracle for those people but perhaps an apology would be appropriate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1638" speakername="Malcolm Byrne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#S00300"><p>I want to take up the last comment.  I have enormous respect for Senator Keogan but we went through two difficult years with Covid and the vaccine scepticism of herself and Deputy T&oacute;ib&iacute;n is not acceptable.  The vaccines were what got us out of the difficulties we face and there was no effort on the part of the Government to prevent people from going for their necessary treatments.  The Senator needs to stop spreading these anti-science and anti-vax messages.  It is not acceptable.  Our health service responded in the best way it possibly could and vaccines were what saw us through the Covid period.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#S00400"><p>Cancer screening was-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#S00500"><p>There will be interruptions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1638" speakername="Malcolm Byrne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#S00600"><p>I want to return to recent weather events.  In Wexford we saw a number of events in the past week which were quite serious.  In my hometown of Gorey we saw extensive flooding, including the motorway being closed.  I saw the impact of what was a mini tornado in Foulksmills and Clongeen.  Parts of buildings were demolished, roofs were taken off and damage was done to concrete in a number of houses.  Unfortunately we will see more of these extreme weather events and it is important that the exceptional weather payments would be open to those homes and businesses that are impacted.  Rather than it being done on an <i>ad hoc</i>basis we will need a clear programme on how to respond to the rising number of these climate-caused weather events.</p><p>One of the other implications has been that those who live in Wexford town are under a boil water notice.  Some 25,000 people are under a boil water notice in Wexford town due to problems with the water infrastructure in and around the town.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Malcolm Byrne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;MemberID=1111"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1111&amp;amp;pid=MalcolmByrne&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I ask again that we have a debate around Irish Water and the necessity to upgrade the water infrastructure around the country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#T00200"><p>An ch&eacute;ad Seanad&oacute;ir eile le labhairt linn n&aacute; an Seanad&oacute;ir Lombard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1666" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#T00300"><p>I ask the Acting Leader to organise a debate around the significant announcement made by the Government last week regarding the forestry programme of &euro;1.3 billion.  It is a very positive step forward.  We need a debate in any of the Chambers but since the Minister with responsibility for that actual issue is a Member of this Chamber, it should work very swiftly to ensure we have the appropriate time put in place to have a decent debate about the issues of forestry.</p> <p>The forestry programme has been long-debated and in particular the afforestation programme and the targets which need to be improved.  Our targets for the last decade have been appalling to say the least.  This programme has been talked about for the last three or four years and is something that is very much welcomed but a debate in the House is required and we need to also put a timeline on a review.</p> <p>Meeting with people around west Cork over the last two days in particular, it is clear there are issues pertaining to this proposed programme.  There are huge issues regarding commercial forestry and whether it is going to be affected or whether it will be adequately promoted.  There is a significant grant of nearly &euro;11,000 per hectare over a 20-year period for broadleaf planting while spruce planting is given less than &euro;4,000 over the same period.  It is about making sure we get enough commercial forestry into the system itself.  A timed review of this is important.  There is no point putting a programme in place that will remain there for the next five years and not have a significant uptake in actual afforestation rates.  We need to have a timeline so if we do not have that increase in afforestation rates, we can come back and review the programme.  I am not saying the programme is wrong but a timed review will give an understanding that it will be amended if it is not working.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#T00400"><p>I add my endorsement to the comments around the awarding of the World Cup to Qatar and to offer solidarity to the LGBT community as that country should never have gotten the World Cup.</p> <p>I also raise an issue around another country that is well-known for its human rights violations, namely, Egypt.  As somebody who has gone to Egypt, has been in an Egyptian prison, and has spoken to members of families of the thousands of political prisoners who are there, it is unfortunate to see world leaders descend on Sharm el-Sheikh this week in the hope of a good outcome in the Conference of the Parties, COP27, negotiations. We all hope for good outcomes but this is clearly a practice of whitewashing the human rights abuses going on in that country.</p> <p>Instead of easing the crackdown on civil society, President El-Sisi's dictatorship has actually ramped them up.  Ahead of COP27, they have security agents and surveillance, the restricted green zone which was previously always open to the public and to civil society to engage in, has been locked down, and people's phones are being seized and their social media accounts monitored.</p> <p>I have particular concerns for the Egyptian-British activist Alaa Abdel El-Fattah who is on hunger strike.  He has been imprisoned since 2011 and there are huge concerns around his welfare as he embarked on a hunger strike and then a water strike in the past number of days.  His family do not know or cannot get confirmation of whether he is even still alive at this point.</p> <p>It is deeply disappointing that COP27 is being hosted by a country that has such a poor track record in terms of human rights violations and has thousands of political prisoners who are held in the most barbaric conditions.  I was inside the prison and met the families.  I also had my car followed by the security surveillance.  I want to offer solidarity to all of the Egyptian civil society who are not able to make their voices heard during this COP protest.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1695" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#T00500"><p>I raise one of my favourite subjects which is University Hospital Limerick. Some 15,600 people have been waiting on trolleys so far this year.  This is the highest number in the country followed by Cork University Hospital which has over 10,000 people on trolleys.  I encourage the Minister for Health to come to the Chamber to have a debate on this issue.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Maria Byrne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2465"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2465&amp;amp;pid=MariaByrne&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I want the Minister for Health to come in here for a debate because we are heading into the winter.  We need to look at reality and at ways to resolve this issue.  </p><p>The National Transport Authority currently has a public consultation on proposed cycle routes in 22 counties, but not many people seem to know about it.  On the website there are very few submissions because it has not publicly advertised the fact that these routes are there.  </p><p>In my city of Limerick, I think there are about ten proposed routes.  I was looking for something else recently and discovered there was a proposed cycle lane on a street not far from my house.  I have had elderly people calling me on the phone.  One man whose wife is in a wheelchair asked that if they completely remove his parking, as they propose to do, how he will put his wife in the car.  There are many people concerned.  It has caused huge upset to some older people.</p><p>I am not against cycling.  It is a very proactive thing but people did not know these routes were being proposed so no submissions were going in.  I think the transport authority and CycleConnects wanted very few submissions so they could go to the local authorities and say they had advertised it and nobody commented.  It is inappropriate that they have not run public awareness campaigns in the different areas to highlight this.  These should be redrawn and re-advertised to let people know.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1694" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#U00200"><p>Members may know I come from the town of Listowel and am proud to say that.  The town has been making headlines recently for all the wrong reasons.  A visiting priest - not a regular priest of the parish - made a number of homilies over the weekend in which he stated straightforwardly that people who are homosexual and in same-sex relationships or other things like that were living in sin.  I have no problem with him believing that.  He is entitled to his opinion.  I do not know if it is church dogma.  I am not qualified to say that.  It is a matter, as far as I am concerned, for the church.</p> <p>Certain slants in the media would give an opposite impression but he was not speaking for me, people I know or the people of Listowel.  Listowel has always been a very open and liberal community.  In results of recent referendums on the eighth amendment and equality in marriage, there was a majority in Listowel for those motions.  I say to the LGBT community to have no fears of our community in north Kerry.  We are with you and we support you.  </p> <p>I spoke in this Chamber a couple of years ago about another incident in the same church, St. Mary's in Listowel.  It had to do with the tragic story of a young girl called Peggy McCarthy, who died in labour because she was not admitted to the local health services, basically because she was having a child out of wedlock.  It is unbelievable that that happened as recently as 1946.  To compound it, the parish priest of the day refused to allow her remains to repose in the church before burial.  He locked the gate and put bars and chains on it.  That did not stop the local community standing up for their neighbour, breaking down those chains, opening the church and making sure the body was received as was right and proper.  My town is a proud and open town.  We welcome everybody and condemn nobody.  The age of Peggy McCarthy is long over and it is time that other people woke up and realised that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" speakername="Barry Ward" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#U00300"><p>I raise the issue of accessibility.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Barry Ward:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=BarryWard&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We have heard quite a lot about it recently and there has rightly been a focus on accessibility, particularly on public transport.  I live in an area where we thankfully have the DART.  Iarnr&oacute;d &Eacute;ireann invested a lot of money in putting in new DART bridges that have lifts and make both platforms accessible.  However, as often as not, they seem not to work.  It is unreasonable that just because someone is a wheelchair user, whether he or she can use the DART is at the whim of whether somebody has fixed that lift.  If using Bus &Eacute;ireann, it is worse.  People have to give 24 hours' notice before they get the bus.  It is not an acceptable way to proceed.</p><p>I recently saw a story posted by an Irish paralympian who travelled for her sport.  She is a wheelchair user.  She flew with an airline and when she got to her destination - I think it was London - her wheelchair was not to be found.  Losing a wheelchair on an aircraft is not like losing a set of golf clubs or a suitcase, however inconvenient or unfortunate that might be for the person who owns them.  A wheelchair is part and parcel of the mobility and accessibility of an individual who needs it.  They are not cheap either.  They cost thousands of euro.</p><p>We have to look at this, particularly in a situation where persons have to surrender their means of transport when they get on a plane.  We should put in place a mechanism showing that this is not acceptable from airlines, handlers or whoever is responsible.  There seems to be a dispute about who is actually responsible.  There should be a very clear penalty for companies that do not take seriously the responsibility they have as custodians not just of the passenger but of the passenger's means to leave the airport afterwards.  When a person arrives at a destination in an airplane and the wheelchair is not available when he or she gets off the plane, there must be a serious penalty to make a serious public policy statement about how seriously we take that.  If there was a proper monetary measure involved, airlines would not be cavalier about this kind of thing.  A wheelchair should be the last thing to go on a plane so it is available first thing when the plane lands.  We need to take this seriously.  We should have a debate about this.  We as a House should be putting down a very clear marker that we take mobility and accessibility seriously and that we are willing to put that on the record.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#V00200"><p>One of the most fundamental freedoms we enjoy as citizens of a democracy is freedom of expression.  That is one of the things that marks us out from countries like China and many others that disregard human rights constantly.  People are free in our society to express their thoughts freely, subject to the minimum of restrictions.  The real test of our tolerance as people is our willingness to accept and take on board that people will express different points of view.  It is not the people who trenchantly express points of view that we agree with.  That is not where the test of our tolerance and liberalism is.  It is when we passionately disagree with those people.</p> <p>It is in that context that I note the publication of the Criminal Justice (Incitement to Violence or Hatred and Hate Offences) Bill 2022, discussion of which is soon to commence in the D&aacute;il.  This is very important legislation.  It is important that we scrutinise it carefully.  Following recommendations I made directly to the Department of Justice, I am glad to see the inclusion of reasonable contributions not just on literary and scientific matters but also religious discourse.  That is very important.</p> <p>I also note that section 11 provides for a direct recognition of freedom of expression around discussion or criticism of matters related to a protected characteristic, where a contribution to debate or material or behaviour is solely that.  Therefore, mere discussion or criticism of matters related to protected characteristics cannot be caught by the legislation.  This is important because in striking the balance between freedom of expression and prevention of incitement to hatred in our society, the balance can be got wrong.  The UN Assistant Secretary-General for human rights, Ilze Brands Kehris, has pointed to the danger of disinformation being used as a pretext to intimidate and harass critical voices.  States sometimes get it wrong when they clone other countries' legislation in this area, where governments respond to public pressure by rushing in with simple solutions for complex problems. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#V00300"><p>Go raibh maith agat.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#V00400"><p>I just wanted to put that on the record.  It is important that we scrutinise this legislation carefully in the coming weeks-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#V00500"><p>The Senator has done that very well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#V00600"><p>-----to see if it does indeed get the balance right.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2250"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2250&amp;amp;pid=RonanMullen&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The scrutiny is only beginning.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#W00200"><p>I wish to draw the attention of the public, Chamber and Leader to the fact that Ulster Bank today announced it is going to start freezing accounts.  As the Leas-Chathaoirleach will appreciate, Ulster Bank has been a very large and important financial institution in the history of this State, really since the foundation of the State.  It is a major thing for a large bank like Ulster Bank to leave.  It has been doing so in an organised, measured and slow way but the day is coming where it will freeze accounts.  Indeed, on 6 January, it will close 12 branches and another 13 branches on 13 January.  Those 25 branches will transfer to Permanent TSB into the future but all the records, files and details relating to those accounts will go back to Ulster Bank headquarters or wherever.</p> <p>I would like the Leader to schedule a debate, or suggest that we have a discussion, not just about the future of banking in Ireland but in particular, the need to draw attention for all those people who perhaps are not using their Ulster Bank accounts.  They may have had one in the past and have moved their account.  They may have opened multiple accounts when they were students or attending college at a previous time.  Ulster Bank said it will close the accounts and send the details to the last known address.  Many people may not have been using those accounts, however, and may have moved addresses since those accounts were in place.  Much more focus and attention needs to be brought to the fact that Ulster Bank is finally now freezing and, ultimately, closing many accounts, many of which are inactive.  There will still be balances on them, however, and those people are entitled to their money.  Therefore, perhaps the Leader could schedule a debate with regard to KBC Bank Ireland but also pertinently, related to Ulster Bank.  The time is now coming and it is incumbent on all of us to alert people to be aware that Ulster Bank is leaving the market.  They probably know about it but that day is coming soon.  It is important that we draw attention to this to allow people to get their money back from this institution before it is gone and, therefore, much harder to retrieve.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#W00300"><p>I thank Senator Horkan very much.  I know he speaks with professional experience as well as in his public representational role.  Senator Davitt is next.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1652" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#W00400"><p>I wish to raise today a matter that was recently brought to my attention regarding a little accident.  Most of us grew up or have been around rural settings and farmyards.  We would have learned our trade driving different machines and started off in tractors and all that sort of stuff.  There have been great campaigns on safety with regard to machinery in recent years but there is something that deserves a debate and that we should thrash out.</p> <p>The licensing system for younger people to drive tractors does not differentiate the type of tractor he or she drives and that is a big issue.  We see high-powered tractors now of more than 200 horsepower carrying heavy machinery and heavy loads.  Trying to stop some of these machines on the road is nigh on impossible over a short distance.  I certainly would not have a problem with a 16-year-old with little experience driving something in a field in a rural or agricultural setting where it would be appropriate.  The on-road use of heavy machinery by people who probably have very limited experience deserves consideration, however.  In particular, there should be some link to the horsepower of a tractor or machine that somebody with very little experience is able to drive.  I would have no problem with that.  Heretofore, a person would be driving little Massey Ferguson tractors and whatever else around and it would not pull the socks off them but nowadays, some of these machines are going at 40 km/h, 50 km/h and 60 km/h on the road while carrying behind them some heavy machinery and trailers.  It really is something we must tease out.  We want to encourage young people into farming.  I am certainly not a killjoy in that regard.  It would be worthwhile to debate the issue here to see where that might go.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#W00500"><p>I thank Senator Davitt very much indeed for raising that important matter.  We move now to Senator McGahon.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1670" speakername="John McGahon" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#X00100"><p>Before the outbreak of the war in Ukraine, 46 Irish citizens were studying in university in Ukraine, all of them studying medicine.  Naturally, when the war broke out, they all came back to Ireland.  One of the provisions introduced by the Minister for Further and Higher Education, Research, Innovation and Science, Deputy Harris, quite rightly, was that, because there simply was not space for these 46 people to go straight into medical courses in this country at that time, they were told they could continue their studies online through university in Ukraine but they would be allowed to take part in the practical lessons in a university in Dublin.  That way, they were getting the best parts of their education.</p> <p>Of the 46 students, 43 are now being accommodated with practical lessons in a university in Dublin, and that is great, but there are three students who are not, and they are dentistry students.  The other 43 students are all studying medicine and they are able to carry out the practical lessons.  However, the university has told three students, two of whom are from County Louth, that it has no space for them at a practical level.  That is despite the Minister, Deputy Harris, saying all 46 students or any students in Ukraine would be facilitated.  That was the message from the Department, yet the university is going against that message and it is saying it does not have space.  There are three dentistry students who are continuing their online studies via their Ukrainian university but who cannot complete their modules.  They cannot do the necessary work unless they can carry out practical work as part of their course, which the other 43 students, who are Irish citizens in Ukraine, are able to do.  I would greatly appreciate if we could have a wider debate about it or if we could write to the Minister to ask him to use his ministerial powers to ensure all universities are playing ball and are making sure all students are able to take part in the practical lessons, as was designated by the Minister himself.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1665" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#X00300"><p>I thank all Senators for their contributions.  There was a wide variety of topics.  Senator Murphy spoke about the flooding at Lough Funshinagh.  I have great sympathy for all those who have been impacted by the floodwaters there.  The Minister of State, Deputy O'Donovan, who is responsible for the Office of Public Works, OPW, has been passionate about his concerns about the planning process as well as about objections to projects, including in Lough Funshinagh.  The CEO of Roscommon County Council did much work to try to provide a solution and to get works moving.  I welcome the fact the Minister of State is to meet with a local group next week.  He is always amenable to engaging with people on the issues.</p> <p>Senator Conway welcomed the Minister, Deputy Ryan's attendance at the opening of the sod turning at Killaloe Bridge.  The Senator spoke about the northern distributor road and asked for debate.  I will ask for the Minister to attend or perhaps the Minister of State with responsibility for roads, Deputy Naughton, might attend in his place regarding that project and other road projects.</p> <p>Senator Conway also spoke about the concern about the agri-climate rural environment scheme, ACRES.  The Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine, Deputy McConalogue, held a briefing for Members the week before last, so I am sure the Minister would be happy to engage in a Commencement debate, if the Senator were to table one regarding the specific details of the Burren LIFE programme and ACRES.</p> <p>Senator Craughwell raised issues regarding the constitutionality of RAF flights over this country and whether this has been approved by the Cabinet.  I am not privy to that information, but I am sure he can have that raised with the Attorney General or with the Taoiseach.  He has also asked for the Minister to come into the House.  I suggest this is first a matter for the Oireachtas committee at which he spoke initially.  He can liaise with the committee in that regard.</p> <p>Senator Gavan has spoken about the cost of living and the rally on Saturday.  It is important and welcome in this country that we have the ability to protest and to march.  Senator Gavan did not, of course, mention any of the range of measures put in place by the Government in the budget last month, some of which are coming through now, including the doubling of child benefit, the autumn double payment, the &euro;500 disability support grant, the &euro;500 lump sum for the working family payment, the &euro;200 lump sum to people living alone, the &euro;500 carer&rsquo;s grant, the Christmas bonus double payment, as well as the energy payments.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Se&aacute;n Kyne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2343"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2343&amp;amp;pid=SeanKyne&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We acknowledge that all of this is absolutely necessary because families are under tremendous pressure this year.  We encounter people every day of the week who are experiencing difficulties.  Thankfully, the Government has been able to respond, and everything we have done has been done because it was necessary.  We have been able to do it because we had the financial firepower, from a well-run economy, to be able to put in place these supports for people who are deserving of them.</p><p>Senators Hoey and Buttimer referred to the layoffs at Twitter, and Senator Buttimer asked for a debate on the matter.  I will certainly ask the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Enterprise, Trade and Employment to come to the House to talk about the state of the tech sector.  A number of concerns have been expressed in respect of announcements made in respect of not just Twitter but also Stripe and other companies.  The treatment of Twitter employees was not right and was not what we would expect from a world-renowned multinational company.  I accept there have been a number of changes in the company management over the past while and, unfortunately, we saw the brunt of that in the form of the layoffs that took place.</p><p>Senators also referred to the World Cup in Qatar, an event that is tarnished and should never have been planned for.  There has been much talk about the fact the country has had to build many new stadiums, with questions as to whether they will ever be used again, and there is the ongoing question of whether it is right to bring such an event to that part of the world, why it was chosen in the first instance and what impact it will have through lives lost and people injured.  As far as I am concerned, it is a tarnished event.</p><p>Senator Blaney talked about the events last week at Markets Field in Limerick during the match between Galway United and Waterford Football Club.  Thankfully, nobody was seriously injured or worse.  I will ask the Minister of State with responsibility for sport to engage with stakeholders in respect of sports infrastructure throughout the country and to come to the House to talk about that.</p><p>Senator Keogan argued that Covid did not cancel cancer screenings but rather it was the Government and the HSE that did so.  I appreciate there were differing points of view but the Government, through majorities of these Houses, initiated legislation to impose severe restrictions - we accept that - in what we believed to be the national interest.  We have to balance the fact that thousands of lives have been saved by virtue of what was done, including among healthcare staff, and that was the reasoning.  We had full debates and democratic votes in these Houses in respect of the lockdowns as they happened while we were awaiting the development of vaccines.  Unfortunately, judging by reports I have read, it is an international expectation that there will be delayed cancer diagnoses, which is deeply regrettable for all families who have been impacted.  I reiterate we had democratic votes in these Houses on the policies of lockdown and vaccines and we were protecting front-line healthcare staff, who were under tremendous pressure throughout the country, from Covid.</p><p>Senator Malcolm Byrne talked about the impact of the flooding in Gorey and called for a clear programme of supports.  The Red Cross, along with the Department of Social Protection, has initiated measures to support businesses that have been impacted in any of these floods and it has not been found wanting.</p><p>Senator Lombard raised the announcement of the &euro;1.3 billion forestry programme, which was welcome news.  I will invite the Minister of State with responsibility for forestry, Senator Hackett, to address the House in respect of this exciting programme of supports for the sector.  We have historically low levels of planting in this country, and while we have seen some difficulties over recent years with regard to licensing, this will give a new impetus to planting.</p><p>Senator Boylan also referred to upcoming events in Qatar and to human rights issues in Egypt.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Se&aacute;n Kyne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2343"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2343&amp;amp;pid=SeanKyne&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I think there were a number of areas, whether Iran, Egypt or Qatar, on which we could invite the Minister for Foreign Affairs to discuss issues of human rights.  I will do that.</p><p>Senator Maria Byrne spoke about University Hospital Limerick and the unfortunate ongoing issues regarding patients on trolleys.  I know that management were before the Joint Committee on Health where she, Senators Conway and Gavan and others would have questioned them on issues and the management in the hospital that were impacting on people and the quality of care.  Senator Maria Byrne also raised proposed cycle lanes.  We have come across this in other areas as well.  Everyone says they support cycling infrastructure which is the right thing to do but it has an impact on narrow streets in terms of removing parking and through traffic.  Reducing roads down to one lane is something that one has to bring people with one on.  One must iron out the difficulties that arise and it is not easy.  We have come across that in Salthill in Galway in the past.  Senators talked about Limerick and I am sure it has arisen and will arise in other areas as well.</p><p>Senator O'Sullivan gave a very passionate defence of the town of Listowel and the happenings last week regarding the visiting priest.  The Senator spoke of the fact that people in Listowel have indicated their support for the repeal of the eighth amendment and marriage equality.  He raised the case of Peggy McCarthy which I read about over the weekend.  One would have thought it was something of the past.  It was a shameful episode.  I am always a great believer, as the Bible says, to do unto others as you would like them to do unto you.  It is from Luke 6:31 and Matthew 7:12.  So in everything, do to others what you would have them do to you.  Leviticus 19:18 says love your neighbour as yourself.</p><p>Senator Ward talked about accessibility issues.  The concerns about lifts might be something to raise directly with Bus &Eacute;ireann and Iarnr&oacute;d &Eacute;ireann.  The majority of us who do not need to use a wheelchair in our daily lives probably will never know the challenges that people face.  For those who have to use a wheelchair every day who find these obstacles to daily travel, it is not good enough.  I agree there needs to be a debate on that issue and I will ask for that debate.</p><p>Senator Mullen spoke about the Criminal Justice (Incitement to Violence or Hatred and Hate Offences) Bill 2022.  He has already been involved in initiating some changes to that legislation.  I look forward to the debate on that Bill when it comes to the House.</p><p>Senator Horkan mentioned Ulster Bank and the freezing of accounts from today and he called for a debate on the future of banking.  It is a challenge now because there are a number of account holders who have not closed their accounts.  Ulster Bank indicated a long time ago that it was leaving the country.  There should be a debate on the future of banking and I hope that people are given the time and space to ensure that they have alternative arrangements for their accounts.  Senator Horkan raised valid points about people's last address, which they might not have updated, and that they do not want a cheque from a closed account arriving at an address at which they are no longer living.  That is important.</p><p>Senator Davitt spoke about machinery and the driving age for tractors.  It is something that I have thought about regarding very high horsepower tractors on our roads.  I might ask the Minister of State, Deputy Heydon, to come in and talk about farm safety.  </p><p>Senator McGahon talked about a specific issue involving three students of dentistry who have been told there is no space for practical work.  He might raise that as a Commencement matter with the Minister, Deputy Harris, or directly.  I will engage with him or write to him.  He would have more accurate details of the issue.  I will send a copy of the transcript to the Minister and ask him to investigate this as a matter of urgency.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022110800002#Z00200"><p>I thank the Acting Leader, Senator Kyne, for his comprehensive responses and, indeed, for displaying an in-depth knowledge of scripture as well.  It is another facet of his knowledge that we were unaware of previously.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.102" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-11-08a.103" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar fionra&iacute; ar 4.35 p.m. agus cuireadh t&uacute;s leis ar&iacute;s ar 5 p.m.<br /><br />Sitting suspended at 4.35 p.m. and resumed at 5 p.m.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>