<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.2" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Leas-Chathaoirleach i gceannas ar 14:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.4" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.5" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#A00100">Gnó an tSeanaid - Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#B00100"><p>I have received notice from Senator Pauline O'Reilly that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, she proposes to raise the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Rural and Community Development to provide multi-annual funding streams to community environmental organisations, including Green Sod Ireland. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Garret Ahearn of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Health to outline his plans to bring forward new legislation on organ donation becoming an opt-out system. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Aidan Davitt of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Further and Higher Education, Research, Innovation and Science to make a statement on the delays in apprentices entering phases 2, 4 and 6 of their training programmes. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Foreign Affairs to make a statement on the findings of the Operation Greenwich report published by the Police Ombudsman for Northern Ireland in January. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Malcolm Byrne of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Enterprise, Trade and Employment to make a statement on supports for the development of Irish economic activity in, as well as regulation of, the metaverse. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Mary Seery Kearney of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister of State with responsibility for public health, well-being and the national drugs strategy to make a statement on the need to add nitrous oxide to the statutory list of controlled substances. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Erin McGreehan of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for the Environment, Climate Action and Communications to make a statement on the deposit return scheme. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Fiona O'Loughlin of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Defence to make a statement on the future of Cathal Brugha Barracks. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Joe O'Reilly of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine to make a statement on the current income crisis in the pig industry.  </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Robbie Gallagher of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Foreign Affairs to make a statement on the waiting times for first-time passport applicants. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Maria Byrne of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Health to make a statement on the waiting lists for children with complex needs for permanent residential beds in the mid-west healthcare area. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Tim Lombard of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Education to make a statement on plans to build a second post-primary school in Kinsale, County Cork. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Victor Boyhan of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage to make a statement on the commencement date of the Planning and Development (Amendment) (Large-scale Residential Development) Act 2021. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator R&oacute;is&iacute;n Garvey of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage to make a statement on increased supports for upstairs living in shops in towns and villages. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Emer Currie of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Foreign Affairs to provide an update on legacy structures following the publication of the British Government's command paper Addressing the Legacy of Northern Ireland's Past in July 2021. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Barry Ward of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Transport to permit category B licence-holders to drive category AM vehicles. </blockquote> <p>Of the matters raised by the Senators suitable for discussion, I have selected those raised by Senators Pauline O'Reilly, Ahearn, Davitt and &Oacute; Donnghaile and they will be taken now.  The Cathaoirleach regrets that he had to rule out of order the matter raised by Senator Robbie Gallagher on the ground that it anticipates the debate on the Fine Gael Private Members' motion regarding the Passport Service which is scheduled to take place in the Seanad on Wednesday, 2 February 2022.  The other Senators may give notice on another day of the matters they wish to raise.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.7" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#C00200">Nithe i dtosach suíonna - Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.8" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#C00300">Departmental Funding</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#C00400"><p>I welcome the Minister of State at the Department of Health, Deputy Butler.  I invite Senator Pauline O'Reilly to address her Commencement matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1693" speakername="Pauline O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#C00500"><p>I understand the Minister of State is taking this matter on behalf of the Minister for Rural and Community Development, Deputy Humphreys.  If there are outstanding matters, I ask that the Minister, Deputy Humphreys, refer back to me.  I understand she is not available today.</p> <p>I wish to speak about an organisation called Green Sod Ireland.  It is an amazing organisation which does its work voluntarily.  Like many environmental organisations, it is scraping around in search of funding to keep itself going.  One of the key issues this organisation and many others have is multi-annual core funding.  Green Sod Ireland is disappointed that it has not been successful when it has applied previously to the scheme to support national organisations.  I am told it has not been successful because of the criteria, which are addressing poverty and social exclusion and promoting equality.  I believe much of the work the organisation does could qualify under these criteria.  Apart from that, however, it is quite disappointing to see environmental organisations, which put so much into their local communities, being turned down for this type of funding.  I ask that the Minister consider broadening the criteria if she does not feel they match.</p> <p>I will give an outline of the organisation's work.  It has over 100 acres at present.  It has had to turn down donations of more acres.  Its members are stewards and custodians of that land, ensuring that it is rewilded and that habitats are brought back to their natural state.  It varies from place to place.  The organisation has tracts of land in Ballinrobe in Mayo, in Connemara, Galway, Cavan and Donegal.  It has areas all over the country and part of its function is to provide support for ecologists to do a report and then to maintain the land.  Its members also visit schools and promote biodiversity.  They work with communities to bring these tracts of land back to life.</p> <p>As the Minister of State can understand, it is very much about equality of access to our wild spaces and equality in the broadest sense of equality for all species.  I look forward to hearing the Minister of State and to hearing about what other schemes the Minister, Deputy Humphreys, could provide in this respect.  While I am aware that there are other schemes, I believe the organisation also has not received funding from the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine, which was a great disappointment.  Doors are being closed to it all the time.  However, this scheme applies more generally and I am sure I am not alone in having organisations coming to me to seek multi-annual funding.  It is time we stepped up because applying for a grant only gives funding for a small project, which means the organisation cannot retain a member of staff or plan for the long term.  It is also a major burden to make grant applications year after year, and perhaps several in one year, to sustain the organisation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1614" speakername="Mary Butler" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#C00600"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this issue with regard to environmental organisations working in the community, including Green Sod Ireland.  The Senator explained in detail the work it does and where it is located throughout the country.</p> <p>With the publication of Climate Action Plan 2021, the Government recognises that there is an opportunity to create a cleaner, greener economy and society that can cut emissions, create jobs and protect both the planet and people.  In keeping with Green Sod Ireland&rsquo;s purpose to protect and conserve Irish land in perpetuity, for the sake of its indigenous inhabitants, cleaner air, warmer homes, less traffic congestion, a healthier population and greater biodiversity are among the many benefits Ireland will enjoy as a result of taking action.  The Climate Action Plan 2021 sets out a pathway to reducing carbon emissions by 51% by 2030 and becoming a net zero and climate neutral economy by no later than 2050.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Mary Butler:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2445"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2445&amp;amp;pid=MaryButler&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=01"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Although the targets are challenging and require fundamental changes in many parts of Irish life, standing still is not an option.  The benefits to rural communities are many, including: new opportunities in sustainable industries; improved water and air quality; improved quality of land; increased biodiversity; and a climate-resilient, robust and profitable agrifood sector.</p><p>Climate Action Plan 2021 places specific emphasis on citizen engagement.  To this end, Pobal and the Minister launched strand 2 of the community climate action programme, which focuses on climate education, capacity building and learning by doing.  An overall budget for strand 2 is set at &euro;5 million.  Its aim is to build capacity and know-how of communities, enabling and empowering them to become low-carbon in an inclusive and collaborative manner.  It is envisaged the strand will fund a mix of different types of projects that focus on providing climate education rather than awareness, and this will lead to tangible climate action within communities.  The funding will facilitate eligible organisations to develop supports, tools, approaches and know-how with local communities to tackle climate change.  The key point to note in that regard is that it will facilitate eligible organisations.</p><p>In keeping with the citizen engagement theme in Climate Action Plan 2021, the Department of Rural and Community Development has committed to complete a public participation networks, PPNs, structural review, with a focus on ensuring PPNs are fit for purpose for climate action as per the Programme for Government: Our Shared Future.  In addition, the Department will facilitate consultation with communities on climate policy through the public participation networks in collaboration with the Department of the Environment, Climate and Communications.  Under the Climate Action Plan 2021, the Department of Rural and Community Development is also working with the Department of Housing, Local Government and Heritage to develop and include a module on climate change in the guidelines for the development of new local economic and community plans.</p><p>The mission of the Department of Rural and Community Development is to promote rural and community development and support vibrant, inclusive and sustainable communities.  Funding is available under the rural regeneration and development fund to support job creation in rural areas, address depopulation of rural communities and support improvements in towns and villages with a population of fewer than 10,000 persons, as well as outlying areas.  Initial funding of &euro;315 million has been allocated to the fund on a phased basis for the period 2019-22.  Category 1 applications for the fund are now open for submissions.  Funding will support large-scale regeneration projects that are ready to commence.</p><p>All measures under outdoor recreation and infrastructure schemes are supported by the Department of Rural and Community Development in partnership with F&aacute;ilte Ireland.  The aim is to promote the development of a sustainable outdoor recreation sector that leverages our natural environment for the benefit of local communities and Ireland&rsquo;s tourism offering.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1693" speakername="Pauline O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#D00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  The type of language she is using is very welcome.  It is a change from where we were a couple of years ago and that is very welcome, as is the amount of funding.  However, I go back to my point on multi-annual funding, which is what these organisations are seeking.  The Department has a key role in this regard.  It is not just for other Departments.  I ask the Minister of State to request that the Minister review that to ensure all organisations providing community engagement and community-based projects have equal access.  Every part of the planet, including humans and all the different species, is inextricably linked, so we must consider them equally and place them all on an equal footing.  I would like to hear the Minister of State commit to going back to the Minister, Deputy Humphreys, and making the argument that these groups need multi-annual funding.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1614" speakername="Mary Butler" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#D00300"><p>To conclude, in November 2021, &euro;15.5 million in funding was announced for 84 outdoor adventure projects.  The projects chosen for investment include walking and cycling trails, cliffways, beaches, lakes, rivers, bogs, greenways, blueways and bridleways.  This investment, which is a key part of Our Rural Future, will support rural economies and I know all present welcome this investment throughout the country.</p> <p>I take on board the point the Senator is making in respect of multi-annual funding.  We have discussed at length in the Department of Health how important multi-annual funding is in terms of facilitating planning.  We saw this first hand last year in the context of the Department of Housing, Local Government and Heritage.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Mary Butler:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2445"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2445&amp;amp;pid=MaryButler&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=01"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->For the first time, we had multi-annual funding, a commitment of &euro;30 billion.  We also saw such multi-annual funding for Irish Water.  It means one can plan ahead.  I know how important it is.  I will relay the matter to the Minister's Department and let it know exactly how the Senator is feeling.  I thank her for her interest.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.16" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#E00200">Organ Donation</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1629" speakername="Garret Ahearn" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#E00300"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the Chamber and thank her for coming here to speak on this matter.  I am aware the issue is important to her, her colleagues and the Department.  However, it is also an issue that is important to the Government, because it commits in the programme for Government to addressing this in its lifetime.</p> <p>Instead of having our current system for people who wish to donate their organs when they pass away, whereby they must sign a donor card that allows for donation if something happens to them, I recommend what is done in Spain, where one has to opt out of donation.  This is important for several reasons.  One reason our current system fails is that the organs of those with organ donor cards may not be donated after their death if they have not had a conversation about donation with their next of kin.  It happens quite often that the next of kin are uncomfortable with organ donation.  Even when someone with an organ donor card tragically passes away, the next of kin still have to be asked if they are okay with donating his or her organs.  Often this happens in very tragic circumstances.  There are many things the next of kin have to worry about in addition to organ donation.  Obviously, the decision has to be made extremely quickly.  The next of kin may not be comfortable with donation and, most important, the conversation between a potential donor and his or her partner or next of kin may not have happened.  If we introduce an opt-out system, it will be the choice of the next of kin not to have the organs of the deceased donated if they have a strong view on it.  In Spain, about 14% of the population over 18 have opted out of donation.</p> <p>It is obvious what an opt-out system does: it gives more opportunities to those who need an organ donation.  In Ireland, about 650 people need an organ donation.  I believe 270 organ donors died last year, affording an opportunity to donate, but only 190 transplants actually happened as a consequence.  Of these, 123 were kidney transplants, 37 were liver transplants and 16 were lung transplants.  Nine patients received a heart transplant.  Some 650 people need an organ transplant but we have 190 transplants per year.  That means 450 people are still waiting and going through very traumatic times, be it on dialysis or otherwise.  Many of these are young kids.  We do not want people waiting longer than necessary to receive a donation, be it of a kidney, lung or heart. </p> <p>From my experience, many are willing to be organ donors but have not applied.  They all have busy lives and may not have had the conversation.  If there were an opt-out system, they would be happy with it.  There would be no need to do anything.  This is about caring for and protecting people and making it as easy as possible for those in very difficult circumstances and who need a donation to receive one as quickly as possible.  I look forward to the Minister of State's response.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1614" speakername="Mary Butler" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#F00100"><p>I wish everyone a happy St. Brigid's Day, L&aacute; Fh&eacute;ile Br&iacute;de.  The Cathaoirleach is a very strong advocate for St. Brigid, and I commend him on his mask; it is lovely.  From next year on we will celebrate a bank holiday on L&aacute; Fh&eacute;ile Br&iacute;de.  We can all look forward to that.</p> <p>I thank the Senator for raising this issue and for the opportunity to speak on it on behalf of my colleague, the Minister for Health, Deputy Donnelly.  I am very glad to get the opportunity to speak on this subject because I am a very strong advocate for organ donation.  I remember as a teenager signing up to that particular card.  The reason I did it was we lost a young girl in Portlaw many years ago and it was the first time I had heard of organ donation.  At the time, when we heard her organs were being donated, it struck me how important it was.  One person dying is a tragedy, but the gift of life could be given to so many other families.  By coincidence, the girl's brother has been a Member of this House.</p> <p>It is such an important thing and it is the most selfless act that we can bestow on each other.  The improvement in the quality of life for organ recipients and their families cannot be overstated.  We have a duty to do everything we can to ensure that as many people as possible benefit from organ donation.  In that context, the Government allocated an additional &euro;1 million in funding in 2022 to continue to improve organ donation and transplantation services in the State.  This funding will support the ongoing development of transplant services, enhance our ability to access organ donors from abroad, and improve organ donation staffing and infrastructure.  This funding will also ensure that our organ donation and transplantation services are equipped to meet the additional demands arising following the enactment of the human tissue Bill.</p> <p>The programme for Government includes a commitment to "Enact the Human Tissue Bill, providing the legal basis for an opt-out system of organ donation and deliver a public information campaign."  Reference was made to Spain, and I was struck by the fact that 14% of people in Spain have opted out.  This means that 86% of people are included, which is a phenomenal figure.  The aim with the Bill is to make organ donation the norm in Ireland in situations where the opportunity arises.</p> <p>Under the soft opt-out system, consent for organ donation will be deemed unless the person has, while alive, registered their wish not to become an organ donor after death.  It is proposed, however, that even though consent is deemed, the next-of-kin will always be consulted prior to removing any organ.  If the next-of-kin objects to the organ donation, the donation will not proceed.  The best way for a person to ensure that their wish to become an organ donor is realised is to have that conversation with their family, discuss their intention around organ donation and make their wishes clearly known to family members.</p> <p>The proposed opt-out register for organ donation will create a clear and easily communicable choice to individuals to either opt-out of deceased organ donation entirely, or to allow deemed consent to apply.  Signing up to the opt-out register will be a definitive expression of the person&rsquo;s wish to not become an organ donor after death.  An opt-out register will make organ donation the clear default option, and signal to citizens the move towards organ donation being the norm.</p> <p>The enactment of the human tissue Bill is a priority for the Government.  The Department of Health continues to engage closely with the Office of the Parliamentary Counsel to progress the drafting of the Bill with the objective of bringing a memorandum to Government to secure approval to publish the Bill as soon as possible in the 2022 spring legislative session.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1629" speakername="Garret Ahearn" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#F00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for her response and her support.  The most important line in her response is "Signing up to the opt-out register will be a definitive expression of the person&rsquo;s wish to not become an organ donor after death."  This means that the current confusion will be gone.  One organ donor can save eight lines.  It is phenomenal.</p> <p>She give an example of the case in her own county.  Members may also have seen video footage of other families who have met the individuals who received organs donated from their loved ones.  Each donation has saved the life of an individual.  There is a sense of pride and amazement among the family when they hear the heartbeat of their loved one in the other person's body, or when they understand that a young child may be alive and living a normal life because of the contribution made by their loved one.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Garrett Ahearn:</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->As the Minister of State said, 86% of people in Spain are in favour of it.  I think the people of Ireland would be the same once we introduced it.  The quicker we do it, the more lives we save and the more people who will be proud of the things they have done when they are deceased.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1614" speakername="Mary Butler" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#G00200"><p>I welcome Senator Ahearn's support for our efforts to increase the rate of deceased organ donation.  I do not want to pre-empt any Bill but I am confident that when the Bill comes before both Houses, it will get a lot of cross-party support.</p> <p>The Senator nailed it on the head when he said the proposal is to introduce a soft opt-out system of consent.  Nobody will be forced and everyone will have the opportunity to opt out.  It is important that message goes out there.  The Department continues to work with the HSE's organ donation transplant Ireland, the intensive care units and the transplant hospitals, namely, Beaumont, Mater and St. Vincent's, in building a better future for organ donation in Ireland as we continue to recover from the pandemic.</p> <p>The Bill will be accompanied by a campaign which will aim to ensure individuals understand the opt-out system and encourage individuals to have the conversation and make their wishes in relation to organ donation known to their next of kin and other family members.  We look forward to the Bill coming before the Houses soon.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.22" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#G00300">Apprenticeship Programmes</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#G00400"><p>I welcome the Minister of State at the Department of Further and Higher Education, Research, Innovation and Science, Deputy Niall Collins, to the Seanad to take this Commencement matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1652" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#G00500"><p>I am delighted to welcome the Minister of State.  He is a hard-working Minister and well known to this House.  I have discussed this with the Minister of State already and am delighted he agreed to come to the House to flesh out the figures and the details.  There has been a concern that there are not enough places in some of the courses at present, or qualified staff to teach these apprenticeship courses.  It seems to be an issue.  They are the two big concerns I am hearing.</p> <p>I am well aware of how the apprenticeship scheme works.  We have had several apprentices through our hands over the years.  It has always been a great system, particularly in the auctioneering sector.  Nearly anyone who got through the system went on to achieve good things in their line of business.  It allowed them to work and earn some money at the same time.  They gained vital experience on the job, which I firmly believe is the best way to learn.  The Minister of State might be able to enlighten us about the teachers or lack of same and the placements or lack of same.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1493" speakername="Niall Collins" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#G00600"><p>I thank the Senator for his question on an important issue for apprentices and for my Department of Further and Higher Education, Research, Innovation and Science.  The Senator will know that craft apprenticeships account for 25 of the existing available apprenticeship programmes.  Given the practical nature of off-the-job training for craft apprentices, the Covid-related shutdown of on-site learning activity over the past two years has had a significant impact on their ability to access such training.  The remaining 37 apprenticeships have not been delayed but may have had disruption to recruitment in, for example, hospitality.</p> <p>While I appreciate the frustration these delays are causing, I reassure the Senator that the education and training sector is doing everything possible to ensure all waiting lists for craft apprentices are cleared as soon as possible.  SOLAS, the Higher Education Authority and the education and training providers work together to deliver craft apprenticeship off-the-job training places and have worked closely to change how training is delivered.</p> <p>The apprenticeships with the longest waiting lists, namely, electrical, plumbing and carpentry, have seen significant reform measures.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Niall Collins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2205"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2205&amp;amp;pid=NiallCollins&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=01"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->These changes are now running through the system, with more apprentices being called for their off-the-job training than before.  In addition, classes that had been running at half capacity due to Covid-19 distancing measures are now back at full intake of 14 to 16 apprentices per phase.</p><p>An amount of &euro;20 million in capital funding was provided in 2020 to extend and upgrade craft apprenticeship facilities across the further and higher education institutions.  Some &euro;17 million of additional funding was provided under budget 2022 to facilitate the response to the backlogs across SOLAS and the higher education sector.  This included a significant recruitment campaign to increase the number of trainers.  The delivery structures for phase 2 off-the-job training have been changed to facilitate a third intake of apprentices per annum and an opt-in rapid employer assessment is being piloted for the final phase of craft apprenticeships.</p><p>At the end of December, 8,797 craft apprentices were waiting for access to phases 2, 4 and 6 off-the-job training.  This is down from the 12,000 apprentices that were on the list last August.  Subject to continuing access to workshops and training facilities, and in addition to the roll-out of more places, it is expected that the majority of craft apprentices waiting for off-the-job training at phases 4 and 6 will be called in the early months of this year.  It is expected that the phase 2 waiting list will be completely cleared by the end of the year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1652" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#H00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his comprehensive answer.  Undoubtedly, he will work on this as hard as he can to try to speed matters up.  I appreciate that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1493" speakername="Niall Collins" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#H00300"><p>I will outline for the House some other pertinent sources of information that may be of assistance to Senators, their offices and their constituents.  I encourage all Senators and everyone interested in apprenticeships to keep an eye on two portals - <i>gov.ie/therightcourse</i>and the interactive <i>apprenticeships.ie</i>website.  They are one-stop shops for information that people may want to access in order to discover and learn about apprenticeships.</p><p>We have 62 formalised apprenticeship programmes, a further 15 are in an advanced state of development and there are expressions of interest regarding 15 more.  Under our Action Plan for Apprenticeship, we have also established the National Apprenticeship Office, to which we have appointed a new director, to oversee the entire apprenticeship offering from the 62 current programmes to the emerging programmes.  We have modified the Central Applications Office, CAO, portal to allow students and interested people who want to apply for apprenticeships to resource themselves through it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#H00400"><p>The rationalisation of the CAO portal is very welcome.  I checked out gov.ie/therightcourse and was amazed by its information and the number of courses on it, which any of us can take at any stage.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.30" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#H00500">Northern Ireland</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1688" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#H00600"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it.  The nationalist people of the North in particular look to the Taoiseach, the Irish Government, this Chamber and the D&aacute;il to protect and defend their national, human and civil rights, and none more so than the thousands of people whose rights, including the right to life, have been trampled over by successive British Governments.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2477"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2477&amp;amp;pid=NiallODonnghaile&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=01"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->None more so than the thousands of people whose rights, including the right to life, have been trampled over by successive British Governments.  Hundreds of nationalists and Catholics were killed as a result of collusion by the British Government's armed forces and loyalist paramilitary groups.  Thousands of confidential files were handed over to loyalists by various intelligence agencies, all of the British Government.  Directly and through loyalist proxies, the British Government could be responsible for approximately one third of all deaths in the conflict.  <br/><br/>The Operation Greenwich report deals with the British Government's armed forces colluding with loyalists to kill 19 people, including Councillor Eddie Fullerton, a Sinn F&eacute;in councillor in Donegal, and Councillor Bernard O'Hagan, a Sinn F&eacute;in councillor in south Derry.  This report follows other official reports into collusion, including: the Oireachtas report into the Dublin and Monaghan bombings, which was described as state-sponsored terrorism; Stalker and Sampson investigations; the three inquiries carried out by Lord Stevens, the former commissioner of the London Metropolitan Police Service; Justice Cory's report; and the de Silva report.  <br/><br/>Former British Prime Minister, David Cameron, apologised to the family of the murdered human rights lawyer, Pat Finucane, for collusion in his murder.  The Minister of State, Deputy Byrne, will know that this House recently unanimously passed a motion calling for a full public inquiry into the murder of Pat Finucane.  Relatives organisations, such as Relatives for Justice and the Pat Finucane Centre, published reports on the collusion, including Collusion 1990-1994: Loyalist Paramilitary Murders in Northern Ireland and the book <i>Lethal Allies: British Collusion in Ireland </i>by Anne Cadwallader.  <br/><br/>All of these reports demonstrate clearly that there is an irrefutable paper trail of collusion leading to the front door of 10 Downing Street.  What is the British Government's response to this overwhelming evidence?  A proposed amnesty - a pardon, if you will - for all those involved in collusion.  The Irish Government must ensure that this does not happen by supporting actions by relatives of those killed through collusion, by supporting the Stormont House Agreement and by lobbying governments and human rights organisations across the world.  The British Government should abandon its amnesty plan, stop running away from the truth and implement the all-party agreed Stormont House legacy agreement, which is an independent process, is human rights compliant and can deliver what the families seek.  That is the truth.<br/><br/>I would like to finish on this before the Minister of State, Deputy Byrne, addresses the House.  Next week marks the 30th anniversary of the awful massacre at the Sean Graham bookmakers' shop on the Ormeau Road.  I raised that incident in this House last year.  Families will gather, as they always do, to recite a rosary and lay flowers at the bookmakers' shop.  Those families are expecting a further report from the police ombudsman which I have no doubt in its breadth and depth will go even further in highlighting the stark level of murderous collusion that existed between loyalist paramilitary gunmen and the British Government.  <br/><br/>It is important that the community in the North hear responses from the Irish Government.  As I said in my opening remarks, it is crucial that the Irish Government's voice on this issue continues to be heard on the international stage.  I note and commend the work of the Minister of State, Deputy Byrne, on this up until now.  This is where we are at.  It seems now one cannot go a week without another ombudsman's report or another case in the Belfast High Court, where families are, unfortunately, being forced to take the British Government to court because of the lack of truth and justice.  This is having a traumatic impact.  People are looking to the Irish Government to lead and to take actions.  I look forward to hearing the Minister outlining what actions he proposes to take regarding the Operation Greenwich report. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1503" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#J00200"><p>T&aacute; &aacute;thas orm bheith anseo inniu ar son an Rialtais chun an d&iacute;osp&oacute;ireacht seo a fhreagairt.  Gabhaim mo bhu&iacute;ochas leis an Seanad&oacute;ir &Oacute; Donnghaile as a smaointe a thabhairt d&uacute;inn maidir leis an &aacute;bhar t&aacute;bhachtach seo.</p> <p>The Police Ombudsman for Northern Ireland, Marie Anderson, last month published a report concerning the RUC's handling of paramilitary attacks carried out by the Ulster Defence Association, UDA, and Ulster Freedom Fighters, UFF, between 1989 and 1993, which resulted in murders and multiple attempted murders.  The report, as the Deputy well knows, has identified collusive behaviours and raised significant concerns about police conduct during this time.  Ms Anderson held that the concerns on the part of the families of those killed regarding collusive activity were legitimate and justified.  A range of factors included intelligence and surveillance failings, the failure to warn people about threats to their lives, the passing of information by members of the security forces to paramilitaries, the deliberate destruction of files related to informants and the passive turning a blind eye to apparent criminal activity.  </p> <p>It is undoubtedly a significant report and the Government will study its findings carefully.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Thomas Byrne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2203"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2203&amp;amp;pid=ThomasByrne&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=01"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is of course a deeply impactful moment for those families whose loved ones were killed in these acts of violence.  Our thoughts must be first and foremost with those families as they read and process the findings.</p><p>The report, however, serves to highlight the vital work of the office of the Police Ombudsman as an independent system for the handling of complaints about the conduct of police officers.  This is a work of great sensitivity and importance that is essential in order for society to have confidence in policing and the rule of law into the future.  Those families who are impacted by the report and every family who lost somebody in the Troubles deserve to know the truth about what happened to their loved one, to have access to effective investigations and to a process of justice, regardless of the perpetrator.</p><p>Addressing the legacy of the conflict on the island is a complex and sensitive task, but in 2014 the two Governments and the parties reached an agreement that mapped out a fair and balanced framework designed to do so, which would see the establishment of a historic investigations unit, an independent commission for information recovery and an oral history archive.  The Stormont House Agreement was based on the fundamental principles of facilitating the pursuit of justice, upholding the rule of law, meeting the legitimate needs of victims and survivors, and fulfilling our shared human rights obligations.  We have been working for the implementation of that agreement for families who need to see a system in place and a clear road they can take to access truth and justice.  Progress is essential and too much time has passed.</p><p>The UK Government, as the Senator knows, has put forward proposals, including a statute of limitations, that constitute a significant departure from that agreement into which it entered.  We have made it clear this is not something we can support.  We are totally opposed to it.  The proposals have faced strong and almost universal opposition from victims, civil society and every political party.  We have cautioned the British Government strongly against any unilateral action in this space.  We are ready to engage to find a collective and agreed way forward but it must be won based on access to justice, rule of law and one that has the needs of victims and survivors at heart.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1688" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#K00300"><p>Gabhaim bu&iacute;ochas leis an Aire St&aacute;it as an bhfreagra cuimsitheach a thug s&eacute; d&uacute;inn.  Admha&iacute;onn s&eacute; go bhfuil an Rialtas chun staid&eacute;ir a dh&eacute;anamh ar an &aacute;bhar seo agus tuigim go mbeidh an staid&eacute;ir sin de dh&iacute;th.  I appreciate the comprehensive response of the Minister of State.  While I appreciate his Department may need the time to absorb the full ramifications of this report, it is something that needs to be addressed because there is no hierarchy of victims, nor should there be.  All of these killings, as he said, impact deeply on the victims' families and indeed the survivors who were attacked or whose information was passed on for them to be attacked.  This has a slightly different edge in the sense that in this report we are dealing with British intelligence agencies handing over intelligence relating to an elected representative in this jurisdiction who was subsequently murdered by a UDA gang which crossed the Border and came into this jurisdiction to murder him.</p> <p>I appreciate the Minister of State has laid out his response at this stage.  I look forward to engaging with him as the Department studies this report and in regard to laying out what specific actions it plans to take.  That is what the families expect and want to hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1503" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#K00500"><p>I thank Senator &Oacute; Donnghaile for his remarks, which are well noted.  The position of the Government is clear and consistent.  No matter where you are from, whether the shot was fired by a state actor or a non-state actor, everyone deserves access to justice.  Every family deserves the truth on what happened to their loved one.  The truth cannot be hidden away or written off as something that happened too long ago.</p> <p>The Minister, Deputy Coveney, has underlined in his regular contacts with the Secretary of State for Northern Ireland, Brandon Lewis, that we must make progress on this issue and the approach must collectively be agreed between the two Governments and the political parties, and the Taoiseach has conveyed this message directly to Prime Minister Johnson.  Indeed, in my bilateral engagements this week, I will also be making that point.  I assure the Cathaoirleach and Seanad&oacute;ir&iacute; anseo inniu that the Government will continue to engage with the British Government on this and to pursue all possible avenues until a resolution is found.</p> <p>As the Senator has rightly said, there is no hierarchy of victims.  Specifically in the case of Councillor Fullerton who was murdered in this jurisdiction, it is a matter of regret that no person has been convicted of this brutal murder.  We have no Statute of Limitations in respect of crimes of that nature and the Garda investigation remains open and active.  Any new information from any quarter will be pursued fully by An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  Any other crimes of that nature in this jurisdiction are not and never will be subject to the Statute of Limitations.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.37" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 3.20 p.m. and resumed at 3.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.38" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#N00100">An tOrd Gnó - Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#N00200"><p>I ask the deputy leader of the Fianna F&aacute;il group, and the Acting Leader, to outline the Order of Business.  I wish her a happy St. Brigid's Day and congratulate her on all of her work on that particular issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#N00300"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach.  For the day that is in it, I am sure he will not mind if I read one of St. Brigid's prayers into the record.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#N00400"><p>It will not do us any harm, that is for sure.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#N00500"><p>When I mention the angels of God, I refer to whatever God means to Members.  L&aacute; Fh&eacute;ile Br&iacute;de shona daoibh.  Brigid means so much to people not just around Kildare and Ireland, but around the world.  I was in Strasbourg at the Council of Europe meeting last week.  There are three parishes outside Strasbourg called after St. Brigid.  St. Brigid's church in Strasbourg had a ceremony last Sunday, which was interesting.  I wish everybody well.  In the words of the blessing:</p> <blockquote> 	May no fire, no flame burn us;<br /><br />May no lake, no sea drown us;<br /><br />May no king, no chief insult us;<br /><br />May all the birds sing for us;<br /><br />May all the cattle low for us;<br /><br />May all the insects buzz for us;<br /><br />May the angels of God always protect us. </blockquote> <p>That shows Brigid's love of nature.  She was a great environmentalist.</p><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, motion regarding the Technological Universities Act 2018 (Section 36) (Appointed Day) Order 2022, back from committee, to be taken on conclusion of the Order of Business, without debate; and No. 2, Payment of Wages (Amendment) (Tips and Gratuities) Bill 2022 - Order for Second Stage and Second Stage, to be taken at 5 p.m., with the opening contribution of the Minister not to exceed ten minutes, group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes and all other Senators not to exceed five minutes, and with the Minister to be given no less than ten minutes to reply to the debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#N00600"><p>Before I call on the leader of the Fianna F&aacute;il group today, Senator Malcolm Byrne, I wish to welcome my father to the Chamber for the first time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1638" speakername="Malcolm Byrne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#N00700"><p>Gabhaim bu&iacute;ochas leis an gCathaoirleach agus ba mhaith liom f&aacute;ilte a chur roimh a athair freisin.  Gu&iacute;m beannachta&iacute; na F&eacute;ile Br&iacute;de oraibh go l&eacute;ir.  Ba mhaith liom comhghairdeas a dh&eacute;anamh leis an Seanad&oacute;ir O'Loughlin freisin agus &iacute; ag feidhmi&uacute; mar Cheannaire Gn&iacute;omhach.  I congratulate Senator O'Loughlin on the fact that it is her first day taking the Order of Business.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Malcolm Byrne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;MemberID=1111"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1111&amp;amp;pid=MalcolmByrne&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=01"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is St. Brigid's Day.  The Acting Leader has campaigned strongly for its recognition and we will not be here in the Chamber this day next year.  Today also marks the centenary of the day in 1922 when the then Irish Free State took responsibility for Irish education.  I am grateful to Emeritus Professor A&iacute;ne Hyland of University College Cork who pointed out that the task set for Irish education was as follows: "In the administration of Irish education, it is the intention of the new government to work with all its might for the strengthening of the national fibre by giving the language, history, music and tradition of Ireland, their natural place in the life of Irish schools."  While there have often been calls for reform in our education system, this is the centenary of a system which has, broadly, served us well.  It is appropriate that this House thanks educators and all those involved over the last century who have succeeded in bringing our education system to where it is today.</p><p>This brings me to an issue that I have raised regularly.  I refer to the proposal by the Minister for Further and Higher Education, Research, Innovation and Science, Deputy Harris, to cut the third-level registration charge aspect of student fees.  This is welcome.  It can only be done, however, in a context where there will not be a great loss of income for the higher education institutions.  Therefore, I call again for a debate on higher education funding.  It is nearly six years since the Cassells report was published and such a debate is long overdue.</p><p>Everybody here welcomes the return of Richard O&rsquo;Halloran.  It was a disgrace that he was detained against his will in China for three years.  We have had a debate on China, but our relationship with that country needs to be explored further.  It is completely wrong that an Irish citizen should be detained for such a long time.  I wish Richard O&rsquo;Halloran and his family a very happy future, as will everybody else in the House.</p><p>I also wish to raise a matter that I addressed during a Commencement matter debate several weeks ago and that I have spoken about on other occasions as well.  I refer to a competition mandate for the Central Bank of Ireland.  It is welcome and positive that Revolut has today announced that it will be making loans and other services available to Irish consumers.  The company, however, is also moving its operations from Ireland to Lithuania.  The Central Bank&rsquo;s lack of a competition mandate is one of the major problems that we have with that institution.  It must stop simply protecting the pillar banks and start to encourage financial technology and financial services industries.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#O00200"><p>I also commend the Acting Leader on her first day taking the Order of Business.  I also acknowledge that this is St. Brigid's Day.  It is a special day and I am glad that it is now going to be recognised as an official bank holiday.</p> <p>While I am speaking about women, I also wish to talk about a strong courageous lady who appeared on the "Claire Byrne Live" show last night.  I do not know if any of the Senators saw the programme, but anyone involved in policymaking or in the legal system should be duty-bound to watch it to see Aimee Foley outlining the horrendous experience she had with her father, who is now in prison.  I have known Aimee since she was a child.  Like everybody else, I was totally unaware of what she was going through and the horrendous experience she was suffering regularly.  She waived her right to anonymity and spoke openly about the value of victim impact statements, what they do for victims and the power they give to victims.</p> <p>She also spoke, however, about sentencing and how horrendously disappointed and outraged she was with the sentence in this case.  It is now subject to an appeal by the Director of Public Prosecutions.  As policymakers, however, we must reflect on what we must do to ensure that these types of situations do not happen in future.  It is phenomenal what Aimee has done for the thousands of victims of domestic and sexual violence by waving her anonymity.  I salute her for her courage and bravery.  We are all extremely proud of what she has done.</p> <p>I also wish to mention the leaving certificate.  Some 60,000 or 70,000 young people are going to be doing those examinations this year.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Martin Conway:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2347"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2347&amp;amp;pid=MartinConway&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=01"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We are now told it will be an exam-based leaving certificate.  I do not agree with that and I think it is wrong.  It should be a hybrid system.</p><p>The young people who are doing their leaving certificate this year are probably the most impacted as a result of the pandemic.  Some 25% of them did not get a junior certificate to start with.  They have been out of school for a large chunk of fifth year and a significant chunk of this year.  There are medically vulnerable young people who have still not gone back to school and have missed even more time.  Whatever way it is dressed up or down, an exam is an exam.  No matter how many choices there are in an exam, it has to be done within a two or three-hour period.  I appeal to the Minister, Deputy Foley, to re-examine this.  The right thing to do is to give young people doing their leaving certificate this year the same option students had last year and the year before.  It would be fair and equitable.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#P00200"><p>I propose an amendment to the Order of Business, that No. 15 be taken before No. 1 today, to introduce and advance the Personal Injuries Assessment Board (Amendment) Bill, which I am bringing before the Seanad for debate next Tuesday.  It is a remarkable fact that whereas it is an offence knowingly to provide false information if, for example, someone is applying for nursing home support or dealing with the Revenue Commissioners or a social protection matter, it is not an offence to do so in the context of making an application to the Personal Injuries Assessment Board, PIAB, or knowingly to supply false information, whether one is acting as the respondent or otherwise, in one's dealing with PIAB.  That is a real lacuna and one which ought to be addressed.  My short Bill proposes to address that and I would be very grateful to colleagues if, between now and when the Bill is taken, they examine and consider supporting it.  As we all know, it is difficult to quantify how much fraud actually takes place in the context of bringing personal injuries actions.  When we consider that 70% of the work of PIAB has to do with motor insurance, it is obvious that anything we can do to combat fraud should be done, starting with deterring it by establishing that it is an offence knowingly to provide false information to PIAB.  It is to be hoped that will eventually deter fraud and lead to lower insurance premiums, which is one of the key places we want to go.  I am not interested in the punishment side of this; I am interested in the deterrence side.  That is what the Bill is about and I would be grateful for the support of Senators.</p> <p>I want to welcome what an Leas-Treora&iacute; said about St. Brigid's Day.  It is an important and special day.  This was a real living, breathing woman of faith who has had a major influence on Irish life.  Looking at the various St. Brigid's crosses here today, I am sorry when I was in Ballinasloe church over the weekend, where Ballinasloe social services was selling St. Brigid's crosses as a fundraiser, that I did not bring one for everybody in the Seanad.  It was a lack of presence of mind on my part.  It is an important day and one I hope many people will reflect on even more into the future.</p> <p>I second and commend what Senator Malcolm Byrne said about the eventual and tardy release of Richard O'Halloran.  It is a disgrace that any country in the modern day would hold a person hostage in this way, which is, in effect, what happened.  We are now at the beginning of the Winter Olympics in Beijing.  They should not be taking place in Beijing, any more that there should not have been an Olympic in Nazi Germany in 1936.  The horrors of what the Chinese regime is perpetrating is something that must continue to attract our attention and censure.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1659" speakername="R&oacute;is&iacute;n Garvey" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#P00300"><p>Gu&iacute;m L&aacute; Fh&eacute;ile Br&iacute;de sona ar gach duine anseo.  Is &eacute; sin an L&aacute; Fh&eacute;ile Br&iacute;de deireanach nach mbeidh l&aacute; saoire poibl&iacute; againn.</p> <p>Finally we will have a public day of recognition for the first female saint in Ireland.  It is about time because, to be honest, we are all saints.  We need a lot of patience.  I am sure I wreck some people's heads.  I will give as good as I get.  It is good that we acknowledge the day.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator R&oacute;is&iacute;n Garvey:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=RoisinGarvey&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=01"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This brings me to something about which I feel very strongly.  It came up during the week in the newspapers.  I thank Cathy Halloran for the piece she did.  It is something I worked on in my previous job.  There are ten times more boys than girls cycling to school in Ireland.  This is not based on physiology or any challenge faced.  Even though it seems like a small thing it is massive.  We really need to look at it.  Why do ten times more boys than girls cycle to school?  Are they ten times as good at cycling?  Absolutely 100% not.  It says a lot about society that teenage girls do not feel like cycling compared with teenage boys.  There are many reasons for it including social issues.</p><p>A big issue I will mention briefly is that many girls schools still have mandatory skirts.  Girls in 2022 are not allowed to wear trousers.  It is an absolute disgrace.  I will do a national call.  I hope to do something whereby all of the female politicians will stand up and demand that every girl in 2022 has the right to go to school with a pair of pants on.  It is a very basic thing.  It is embarrassing that we have to ask for it in this day and age.  We have a female Minister for Education.  I really hope we can work together on this.  It is embarrassing for me as an aunt to young girls and as someone who knows women and girls in their teenage years and in their 20s.  I am embarrassed we still have many schools throughout Ireland that do not allow the girls to wear pants.  It influences how they cycle.</p><p>This brings me to my next point.  Next week we will celebrate Science Week.  I will be encouraging women in science because I did maths and physics myself.  We do not even have girls cycling bikes.  We do not have them wearing pants.  We have a long way to go.  This is a very basic ask and we need to work on it.  I am sure everybody here will support me on this.  It is embarrassing in 2022.  It is our legacy.  We are the middle-aged people now.  We are the older people.  We owe it to the younger generations to break it.  My mother was not allowed wear pants until she was 18 but that was 70 years ago.  We are saying the same to young girls now.  With this comes the fact that girls can move around and be independent.</p><p>In this day and age even though we are finally celebrating a female saint, women are still the primary carers.  They are the ones left on the school run.  They are left trying to do the cycle bus, the walking bus and the get-them-out-the-door bus.  To this end we see that infrastructure does not support them.  We really lack active travel and proper infrastructure.  Red paint on the side of the road is not enough.  We know the Department has given all of the funding needed for local authorities.  On this day as a feminist, a woman, a mother and a carer who wants better for the next generation I ask the local authorities to take this seriously.  It is a gender-based issue.  We need the confidence to use infrastructure.  The local authorities have the money.  They need to up their game.  I wish everyone the best of luck for L&aacute; Fh&eacute;ile Br&iacute;de.  I hope the Minister, Deputy Foley, will take seriously my demand for the basic right to wear trousers to school.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1688" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#Q00200"><p>Cos&uacute;il le mo chomhghleacaithe, gu&iacute;m beannachta&iacute; na f&eacute;ile Br&iacute;de ar achan duine.  Is c&eacute;ili&uacute;radh Br&iacute;de, c&eacute;ili&uacute;radh na mban agus c&eacute;ili&uacute;radh th&uacute;s an Earraigh &eacute; inniu.  I join colleagues in wishing everyone a happy St. Brigid's Day.  This is a celebration of Br&iacute;de.  It is a celebration of women.  Ultimately it is a celebration of the start of spring and the triumph of light over darkness.  I have been given a very special job by rang 4 i mBunscoil Bheann Mhadagain i mB&eacute;al Feirste.  The primary 4 class, whose teacher is my friend Diarmuid O'Tuama, has asked me to give a cros&oacute;g Bhr&iacute;de to President Michael D. Higgins.  I do not know as a branch of the Oireachtas whether he can be included in the internal mail.  It is a serious job that I will take very seriously.  I hope that on behalf of all of the dalta&iacute; i rang 4 i mBunscoil Bheann Mhadagain that he receives it well and it brings him good health and good luck.</p> <p>I commend the dignity, grace and determination of the Bloody Sunday family survivors.  Many of them have campaigned for decades for truth and justice for their loved ones.  Typically, and unsurprisingly, they are women and have led from the front in the campaign.  I appreciate and note the Cathaoirleach was in Derry on Sunday for the events as were the Taoiseach and leader of the Opposition.  It was important this range of political leadership joined the community on the streets of Derry for the 50th anniversary.  I send our best wishes and solidarity to those families and all those campaigning for truth and justice for their loved ones.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2477"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2477&amp;amp;pid=NiallODonnghaile&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=01"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> I hope that the Acting Leader will agree that we should have statements from the Minister for Foreign Affairs on the situation in Palestine given the shocking report that was released by Amnesty International this morning.  The report tells us what we have known all along, which is that Israel is implementing and rolling out an apartheid system of injustice, brutality and oppression against the Palestinian people.  While we often hear the Government talk about the role on the UN Security Council and the important place that this State has in the EU, it is really important that we hear from the Government what actions that it will take in response to the report and, indeed, in response to the proud Irish tradition of standing actively in opposition to apartheid in South Africa, and what we are going to stand against when it manifests itself against the Palestinian people.  I call for statements on Palestine with the Minister for Foreign Affairs.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" speakername="Mark Wall" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#R00200"><p>I congratulate the Acting Leader on taking the Chair today.  I join with her and colleagues in wishing everybody a happy St. Brigid's Day, L&aacute; Fh&eacute;ile Br&iacute;de.  We are all very proud of our association with St. Brigid where I live in County Kildare.  We recently learned, following a very successful campaign by so many in this House and, indeed, the Lower House, that we will celebrate a public holiday from next year.  It is, therefore, timely to send out an invitation to one and all to come to County Kildare next year for the first ever public holiday of 2023.  We will celebrate this date and the historic contribution of St. Brigid not just to my own county but to many parts of this island.</p> <p>As the Cathaoirleach will know, Kildare has a lot to offer.  &Aacute;ine Mangan and her team in Into Kildare are putting together a programme of events for 2023.  I encourage one and all to come to County Kildare to enjoy great heritage, sporting attractions and tourist amenities not just for February but all year round.  We will also commemorate the 1500th anniversary of the passing of St. Brigid the following year in 2024.  I know that Councillor P&aacute;draig McEvoy, as chair of county council committee, and the Kildare Decade of Commemorations Committee are working on events around this milestone.  I am sure that I will get the opportunity to talk about this once again.  I must add that with the performance of Glenn Ryan's Lilywhites last Sunday we may have another visitor to our famous county in the forthcoming months. </p> <p>I welcome the current conversations about the Defence Forces and where this will bring us to in the future.  She will be aware that I, along with a number of colleagues, have consistently highlighted the problems and issues that face the Defence Forces in this House over the past two years.  We have consistently been told that the Government will formulate its policy on the future of the Defence Forces following the publication of the report of the commission on the future of the Defence Forces.  It is worrying in the extreme then to hear a senior Minister say that the Cathal Brugha Barracks will be relocated before the report is even published.  Surely if we are to be serious about the future of the Defence Forces and their needs, including housing, then this cannot be the case.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1645" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#R00300"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" speakername="Mark Wall" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#R00400"><p>There is no doubt that we need to invest in the different capital and equipment projects that have been mentioned over the past number of days.  However, we must never forget that we must first invest in and provide security to those who serve us so loyally, and those who may wish to consider a future in the Defence Forces.  We must allow their representative bodies to affiliate with the Irish Congress of Trade Unions in order that the voices of Defence Families families, through their representatives, can be heard around that important table.  We must invest in the Defence Forces.  I look forward to that conversation in the coming weeks here but at the heart of those conversations we must once and for all address the terms and conditions for all those who serve.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1657" speakername="Eileen Flynn" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#R00500"><p>It is brilliant to see the Acting Leader in the seat today and I hope that she will be there many more times.</p> <p>I wish that leave be granted to introduce a Bill entitled Child Trafficking and Child Sexual Exploitation Material (Amendment) Bill 2022.  I am delighted to introduce my very first Private Members' Bill, which I believe addresses a very important language issue in our legislation.  I will start by introducing the Bill and will outline what it proposes to do.  I will explain why the Bill is necessary and what it aims to achieve.  </p> <p>The Bill aims to substitute the term "child pornography" with "child sexual exploitation material".<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Eileen Flynn:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=EileenFlynn&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=01"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The Bill will amend the language of the Child Trafficking and Pornography Act 1998, the Child Trafficking and Pornography (Amendment) Act 2004 and the references to child pornography contained in Irish legislation.  If the Bill is successful the legislation will be renamed the child trafficking and child sexual exploitation material Act 1998 and the child trafficking and child exploitation material (amendment) Act 2004.  Any reference to child pornography in legislation will be replaced with the term "child sexual exploitation".  It is not only important, but necessary.  The issue is that the language currently being used has been found to be harmful.</p><p>With regard to child abuse, child trafficking and child sexual exploitation material, the Luxembourg Guidelines provide a comprehensive and detailed breakdown of the importance of language.  According to a report conducted with the aid of a number of international bodies, including the UN, the term "child pornography" is not only incorrect, but dangerous.  Why is that?  One hears the term "child pornography" and understands what it means.  Why is it dangerous when our laws already provide for measures against it?  The reason is that what is happening in these awful incidents is not pornography.  It is abuse.  In the Harassment, Harmful Communications and Related Offences Act legislators were careful not to employ the term "revenge pornography".  While that term is widely used and understood, the term "image-based sexual assault" not only better reflects the nature of the abuse and the crime but also shifts the focus to the perpetrator, not the victim.  I wish to do the same.  Language is important and powerful.  What we say spreads throughout our community, country and globally.  Language shapes and defines our understanding.  It is not pornography; it is abuse.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#S00200"><p>I congratulate the Senator on the introduction of her Bill.  We will need a seconder.  However, can I clarify that the amendment proposed by the Senator is that No. 16 be taken before No. 1?  Is that the amendment?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1657" speakername="Eileen Flynn" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#S00300"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#S00400"><p>Thank you.  It is just a procedural issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1656" speakername="Mary Fitzpatrick" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#S00500"><p>Happy L&aacute; Fh&eacute;ile Br&iacute;de to everyone.  Ba mhaith liom bu&iacute;ochas a ghabh&aacute;il le Seanad&oacute;ir O'Loughlin.</p> <p>Today, I am thinking of everybody who is struggling with the enormous challenge of trying either to buy or rent a home.  It is very frustrating and stressful for people.  Last week we had the publication of the second quarterly report on Housing for All, the Government's &euro;20 billion plan to deliver more than 330,000 affordable, social and private homes both to purchase and rent over the next decade.  It is a massively important plan.  Despite Covid-19 last year, the shutdown of construction and the fact that we are emerging from a decade of undersupply, there is good news from the second quarterly report and there is hope for people who are genuinely struggling at present to either buy or rent their own home.  Of the 231 actions in the plan, 123 have commenced or have been completed.  It is important to recognise that last year, despite the shutdown, more than 20,000 homes were completed.  There were more than 39,000 planning applications and more than 30,000 commencements.  That all helps on the supply side.</p> <p>On the affordability side, this House and the D&aacute;il passed the Affordable Housing Act 2021, which is significant and game-changing legislation to address affordability.  There is real hope there and it is very important that Members of both Houses use the legislation we have passed and use all the resources available to the State to deliver increased housing supply and affordability.  Some people are engaging in a vile level of hypocrisy on this subject.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Mary Fitzpatrick:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=MaryFitzpatrick&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=01"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I urge them to stop doing so and to be constructive.  They should think of all the people who genuinely have a housing need and require help and for whom it is not a political debate.  They should support the State to actually deliver for those people.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1695" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#T00200"><p>I rise to raise two issues, the first of which relates to the leaving certificate.  I had called for a hybrid leaving certificate.  I have been contacted by many students, not just from Limerick, but from across the country.  I am really disappointed with the proposal brought forward by the Minister, Deputy Foley.  Last Monday, I was in a DEIS school where not only every student sitting the leaving certificate but every teacher in the school as well believes the right thing to happen is to have a balanced leaving certificate.  Many of the students who will sit the leaving certificate this year did not even sit the junior certificate.  They have been badly affected by Covid.  It would have been great to reintroduce the leaving certificate.  Obviously, all present realise it needs to be amended but I do not believe this is the right year in which to bring back the full leaving certificate.</p> <p>The second issue is that An Bord Plean&aacute;la decided today to defer its determination in respect of the road from Limerick to Foynes, which would include a bypass of Adare.  Limerick and Ireland are hoping to host the Ryder Cup in Adare in 2027.  It will be one of the biggest tourism events in the country.  The more often this decision is put off, the more likely it is that the road will not be built in time for the Ryder Cup to be held.  I strongly believe the Government needs to put pressure on An Bord Plean&aacute;la to deliver or to make a decision in respect of this project because it is so pertinent not only to the mid-west but to all of Ireland.  There is no point in hosting an event of this size if the roads are going to be congested.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1645" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#T00300"><p>I wish a happy St. Brigid's Day to the Acting Leader and all her friends in Kildare.  I second the amendment proposed by Senator Mullen to the Order of Business.  I would like to second the amendment proposed by Senator Flynn but I am not in a position to do so.  I ask one of my colleagues to do so for her because it is an excellent Bill.</p> <p>The case of Richard O'Halloran is over, thank God.  I do not think anyone can accept plaudits for taking three years to get a person out of China.  It is outrageous that it took that long.  I certainly would not be thanking the Chinese Government or its ambassador for anything.  It would be like thanking a kidnapper for kidnapping a person.  What happened was outrageous, in my view.  </p> <p>My colleague, Senator Wall, referred to Cathal Brugha Barracks.  I cannot for the life of me understand how any Minister would walk out and put a video up online announcing that the Government is closing Cathal Brugha Barracks.  It is the most iconic barracks in the country.  It is the barracks from which Michael Collins left when he took the State back from the British.  The bottom line is that it was a very poor show on the part of the Minister.</p> <p>My colleague Senator &Oacute; Donnghaile spoke about justice for the victims of Bloody Sunday.  I fully support that.  I do not believe anybody should be able to walk away under any amnesty whatsoever for atrocities carried out in Northern Ireland during the 40 years of the Troubles.  I support a truth and justice system, if we can get one in place, but I do not under any circumstances support the call by the British Prime Minister for an amnesty.  Those who are guilty of crimes must be brought to justice.  I looked at the Ballymurphy case in particular.  To me, that looked like a couple of thugs on top of a building using real live humans for target practice.  It is absolutely disgusting.  It is no secret that I served in the British Army, but I certainly have no time for and no truck with the individuals who were involved in either of those events.  To me, it was a complete breakdown of command and control in Derry on that day.  I know that people in Northern Ireland do not agree with me-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1688" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#T00400"><p>Neither does the Saville inquiry.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1645" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#T00500"><p>-----but no soldier can be ordered to murder.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1688" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#T00600"><p>The Saville inquiry says otherwise.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1645" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#T00700"><p>I understand that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1638" speakername="Malcolm Byrne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#T00800"><p>I am just glad Senator Craughwell did not have to fight the Russians.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#T00900"><p>We are not having a discussion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#U00100"><p>I agree with everybody that this day, St. Brigid's Day, is very important.  As others have said, Senator O'Loughlin has campaigned very strongly on this issue.  From speaking to her earlier, I am aware that she is very proud today.</p> <p>I want to return to the issue of Mr. Richard O'Halloran.  Like many in this House, I campaigned for his release.  It was great to see the five happy faces on Saturday.  Everywhere I went, including the most rural area in my constituency, people were saying it was a fantastic, happy day.  I wish the O'Halloran's well.  To see the picture of joy that was his children's faces was just something else.</p> <p>The O'Halloran case brings back into focus a case I have highlighted in this House on many occasions, which is that of Mr. Robert Pether, whose family lives in Elphin, County Roscommon.  He is an Australian citizen but his wife and children are Irish citizens.  His wife's family came from Dublin.  Her father, in his early days, went to Australia.  We now need to increase the pressure on the Iraqi authorities to release Mr. Pether from jail.  His family, no more than the O'Halloran's, is going through deep distress.  He is caught in quite a similar position to that in which Mr. O'Halloran was caught.  He is a top-class engineer who was in charge of the fantastic new central bank building in Iraq.  If people look it up, they will see it is an amazing building.   Apparently, there is an issue with over-expenditure of &euro;12 million.  Mr. Pether and his Iraqi colleague have been blamed in the battle between the Iraqi Government and the firm that employed them.  It is shocking and outrageous.  Mr. Pether and his colleague are in an Iraqi jail.  The Department is aware of it and has had some contact with the family.  I have been campaigning for a long time on this.  I ask everybody to do so.  The Acting Leader, Senator O'Loughlin, will agree with me and bring the message back to the Minister.  The Leader has been very helpful in this regard.  We must all work now to get Mr. Pether back to his home in County Roscommon.  What has happened is terribly unjust.  It is very upsetting, particularly for young kids.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1666" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#U00200"><p>I join other speakers in acknowledging St. Brigid's Day and its significance in marking springtime.  Outside, it is a fantastic spring day.  I acknowledge that spring is starting.</p> <p>There are two events I want to acknowledge.  The release of Mr. O'Halloran, particularly the work done by the Minister for Foreign Affairs and his Department, needs to be acknowledged.  It has been a long battle.  Diplomacy was the key.  I am not referring to microphone diplomacy but to making sure we got the man home.  That was a really positive step.</p> <p>We also need to acknowledge that the announcement on the leaving certificate this afternoon is one that the many households will discuss at length in the next few days.  At home, I have a niece who is to do the leaving certificate this year.  Her view last Saturday was that she would be in favour of having the system.  The big issue is reform, however.  There needs to be reform.  The reform talked about for the past decade or two, because of how the leaving certificate operates and the pressure exerted on examination day, is the key issue.  We need a genuine review of what the leaving certificate will mean after Covid.  That involves taking the stress out of the process for students, guardians and parents.  This involves a significant body of work.  Unfortunately, very little has been done on it in the past 24 months.  The work needs to be done.  We need to move away from the system that has been in place since the mid-70s, which is such that if a student has a bad day on one examination day, it can affect his or her entire life.  That is not appropriate.  We need to find a solution that is suitable for the longer term.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#U00300"><p>I second Senator Flynn's amendment.  I am very proud to do so on behalf of the Sinn F&eacute;in party.  I welcome the Acting Leader.  I very much acknowledge her work as part of the Irish delegation to the Council of Europe.  She has led that team in a way that means it is fitting she is Acting Leader today.  I wish everyone a happy St. Brigid's Day.  The Brigid I would follow would be more the pagan Brigid.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1688" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#U00400"><p>Hear, hear.  Me too.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#U00500"><p>However, once we are happy with the day, it is all good.  It will be a very welcome addition to our bank holidays next year.</p> <p>Do not be looking at me like that, Senator Mullen.  I am only having a laugh, all right.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#U00600"><p>It was only bemusement.  There was nothing hostile about it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#U00700"><p>I know there was not.</p> <p>The issue I want to raise relates to the leaving certificate.  There were voices on all sides of this Chamber last week appealing to the Government, particularly the Minister for Education, to work towards a hybrid model.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paul Gavan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2469"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2469&amp;amp;pid=PaulGavan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=01"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We made those calls because all Members have had contact from students and parents who are really concerned.  The idea of moving to a traditional leaving certificate during the year that could never be described as traditional, is just fundamentally unfair.  Last week I made the point that not only had the Ombudsman for Children called for a hybrid leaving certificate, it was hugely disappointing that the Minister for Education would ignore the advice of the Ombudsman for Children.</p><p>Unfortunately, through nobody's fault, there are significant sections of leaving certificate students who have not been able to cover the course.  This is the fundamental point.  They have not been able to cover the course, so how is it appropriate to stick with the traditional leaving certificate model?  All of us know the stress that students undergo with the leaving certificate.  I still wake up occasionally remembering the French exam back in 1983.  The stress of the past two years, however, has been so intense.  So many of our young people have had to undergo that stress in isolation.  Their usual social channels of meeting with colleagues and friends, which are so important when one is working towards the leaving certificate, and which give reassurance and knowledge and strengthen solidarity, have just not been there for so long.  People seem to forget that the leaving certificate is a two-year course and that most of last year was spent online.</p><p>I cannot understand this decision.  Fundamentally it lets down our students and parents, our friends and their families.  I would appeal to everyone to address this issue, to come back to the Minister for Education and call on her to revisit this urgently.  It is not fair and it is not just.  I am aware that the Department wants to keep a conservative line, and this is what civil servants often do, unfortunately.  Leadership would have been shown if the Minister had said, "No, we need to stick with the hybrid model".  This is a failure of leadership.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1670" speakername="John McGahon" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#V00200"><p>I wish to discuss an issue that affects people across the board and across all local authorities.  I want to ask for a unified approach from government or a directive from the Department about how local authorities should approach this matter because it is different in every local authority.  I am referring to the way people are removed from the housing list.  I can only speak for my own area and what happens in County Louth in this regard.  It is deeply unfair, and I have felt that it has been deeply unfair ever since I first got elected to politics in 2014.</p> <p>Every year, local authorities need to make sure that they have accurate housing lists.  They write to people to ask them if they are interested in staying on the housing list.  If the person does not respond to that letter then he or she is instantly removed from the housing list, which is fair enough.  Currently, where an individual can come back to a local authority and say that he or she did not update the local authority about the list or about a new address, or that the person may not have received the letter or had moved address but now wants to stay on the housing list, the person is allowed back onto the housing list but loses all of the years he or she had previously been on the housing list.  It is deeply unfair that somebody could lose five, six, seven or eight years waiting for a council house because he or she had not replied back to one single letter.</p> <p>With all due respect to local authorities, they have absolutely no proof that such letters get to individuals in the first place.  It is very important that there is a unified approach or that some sort of a directive would come from the Department down to all local authorities to say how the standard should be dealt with across the board.  If people are four years on the list, for example, and then discover that they have been removed, they should be entitled to the four years that they had previously been on the list, and should be allowed to go back onto the list with the same time that they had.  This would be the fair thing to do.  I ask that we would engage with the Department of Housing, Local Government and Heritage so that a directive is issued right across all local authorities, and that it is not a different process for people in Louth, Meath, Cavan or Monaghan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" speakername="Barry Ward" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#V00300"><p>Happy St. Brigid's Day, and a happy lunar new year, which so many people around the world and in Ireland also celebrate.</p> <p>I wish to raise the issue of the increase in the cost of a stamp.  Today we heard the news from An Post that it proposes, for the second time in a year, to increase the cost of postage nationally and internationally.  The cost of a stamp for a letter in Ireland will now go up to &euro;1.25.  I could understand if this was being done to stem the closure of post offices around the country.  Even in my own area, which is a suburban part of Dublin, we have had two post office closures recently at Woodbine Park, Booterstown, and in Dalkey.  These were two post offices that one would expect to be busy and functional post offices, but postmasters do not want to take over those offices because the pay and conditions are not sufficient to maintain them.  This is not why An Post is telling us it is increasing the cost of postage.  It is to meet the increasing costs of fuel and other things.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Barry Ward:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=BarryWard&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=01"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I accept that is happening for everybody in every industry.  However, few people have the privileged position or the market dominance that An Post has.  It is telling to look at An Post's accounts over recent years.  The most recent annual report from 2020, published last year, shows revenue and profits were up.  Profit was &euro;32.5 million in 2020.  Since then we have had a huge increase in the use of post and parcel services around the country, particularly during restrictions.  If An Post cannot make money during that time, it should ask why not.  It is certainly not channelling that money into provision for postmasters or into services.  It should recognise it operates a particular position in the Irish nation and economy to provide a service to the Irish people and it ill behoves it now, within a year of the last price increase, to seek to increase the price of a stamp again, thereby perhaps driving people away from its services, rather than encouraging them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1639" speakername="Miche&aacute;l Carrigy" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#W00200"><p>It is apt the Acting Leader is in the position she is in today on St. Brigid's Day.  I will raise a couple of issues.  First is the Covid bonus payment.  I was at St. Christopher's Services yesterday week with the Minister of State, Deputy Rabbitte, and met a number of staff, etc.   It is an issue that needs to be looked at.  It was welcome for our front-line staff but we have to look at such staff across all services, be they the section 38 and 39 employees who did tremendous work and kept people safe over 18 months or the family carers who provide a vital service and save our State significant expenditure by looking after people in their own homes.</p> <p>Numerous people have touched on the leaving certificate.  I have spoken about it and was in favour of a hybrid model.  However, the decision has been made.  Wide consultation took place across teachers' unions, students, etc.  The decision has been made in the best interests of students and based on the facts.  It is incumbent on all of us and all parties to accept that decision, move on and not complicate the thing any further for students.  I was reading through the various changes to the leaving certificate today.  They are acceptable for students.  They take into account the fact that people have not covered the entire course.  We should all get behind our students and support them in the coming months ahead of their leaving certifiicate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#W00300"><p>I welcome Senator O'Loughlin to the Chair.  It is befitting today, St. Brigid's Day, and I wish everyone well in the celebrations.  I had the pleasure yesterday to be in Kildare at an eve of St. Brigid's event.  It was a fantastic event and the people in the heart of County Kildare, which is Kildare town, were bowled over.  It was also great to see how they have reinvigorated and redefined that public realm and space in the heart of Kildare town.  I congratulate all those people, including public representatives here, who were involved in the run-up to that.</p> <p>I will talk about forestry, specifically forestry licensing.  I want to see a sustainable forestry sector emerge in Ireland that can achieve commercial, climate and biodiversity goals.  I want to see a reduction in the volume of imported timbers in this country.  I want improvements to the forestry licensing scheme, which is currently causing a tremendous backlog and damaging and impacting on the potential for the industry.  A recent harvest licensing dashboard indicated the private sector, mainly farmers, received 26 felling licences, while Coillte received almost double that at around 51.  There is a debate and an argument between farmers and private forestry owners and Coillte concerning the proportionality in the administration of licensing.  That is a real issue.</p> <p>The Department has clearly failed in its targets for 2021, with only 4,500 licences.  I call for a debate specifically on licences, not on the bigger issue of forestry.  We have an enormous demand for forestry, both for harvesting and felling.  We need to address the issue.  We have a Senator and Minister of State with special responsibility who would, I know, be more than happy to come to this House.  I would like a debate on the issue of planting licensing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1647" speakername="John Cummins" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#X00100"><p>Last week, "Prime Time" ran an excellent programme on the work being done in Waterford to tackle the issue of dereliction and vacancy.  It highlighted the success of the repair-and-lease scheme, the buy-and-renew scheme and the council's utilisation of compulsory purchase orders, CPOs, to tackle something that everyone in this Chamber and across society gets rightly vexed about in the midst of a housing crisis.  The Joint Committee on Housing, Local Government and Heritage is examining this issue at length, but it warrants debate in the House.  Why is it that a council like Waterford City and County Council accounts for 50% of all repair-and-lease units that have been delivered in the State?  It is having a positive impact in terms of delivering one- and two-bedroom units, predominantly in the city centre, which has reduced the need for bed and breakfast and hotel accommodation.  In fact, it has eradicated it.  That is a positive development in my county, but if it can be done in the fifth largest urban centre in the country, there is no reason it cannot be done elsewhere.</p> <p>I call for a debate on this matter.  It should not be the case that Waterford accounts for 50% of all repair-and-lease units.  While it is fantastic that we have so many, the scheme needs to be adopted more by other local authorities.  At last count, eight local authorities had not delivered a single unit and up to 20 had delivered five or fewer.  That is a dismal performance.  The Housing for All plan wants to focus on tackling dereliction and vacancy.  The tools are there to make a difference.  They just need to be utilised to a greater extent by local authorities.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1629" speakername="Garret Ahearn" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#X00200"><p>I acknowledge Senator O'Loughlin's presence in the Acting Leader position today on what is St. Brigid's Day.</p> <p>I welcome that, during Private Members' business tomorrow, we will debate passports with the Minister for Foreign Affairs and we will all have an opportunity to contribute on it.  As public representatives, we all encounter people who have forgotten that their passports are out of date.  Obviously, many people are also applying for first-time passports.  There is something that we and companies can do to improve the situation for people who have forgotten that their passports are out of date, namely, issue a reminder.  This month and next month, many people will be booking holidays abroad with Aer Lingus, Ryanair or travel agencies.  If those companies had a system whereby people were asked whether their passports are still six months in date and whether they could supply their passport reference numbers, people would have to look for their passports and check them, which would serve to remind them of whether their passports are in date.  We are always encountering situations where people have booked holidays or trips only to realise while packing their bags a week or a couple of days before they leave that their passports are out of date.  What if it was instead the case that someone could find out that his or her passport is out of date when booking a flight or a trip through a travel agency?  It would help the travel agencies, the airlines and the passport delivery service.  If people apply for passports earlier than they need them, they are more likely to be successful.  I call on the industries to come together and help the customers, the passport services and the industries themselves by putting in place this facility on their websites for whenever anyone is applying.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1648" speakername="Emer Currie" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#X00300"><p>If there was ever a weekend to demonstrate how wrong the British Government's proposals on legacy are, this was it.  In light of the dignity and resilience of the Bloody Sunday families and survivors this weekend and over the past five decades and the people of Derry who have supported them, to be there was moving.  The Cathaoirleach was there, too.  I am grateful to the journalists who covered the 50th anniversary in such depth.  Everyone, regardless of age or background, should know the horror of what unfolded on 30 January 1972.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Emer Currie:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=EmerCurrie&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=01"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->When they marched, they marched for no more than what were their civil rights.  When they campaign today, they campaign for no more than what is their right and the rights of hundreds of others who journey on the same lonely path, truth and justice and, for a fundamental of any civilised society, the rule of law.  </p><p>Mr. Michael McKinney, whose brother, William, was one of the 13 unarmed Catholics murdered by the British army's parachute regiment that day put it best, when he said, "They are trying to deny us justice because they are scared to face justice."  The British Government is not an observer.  It is an actor - a participant - in the Troubles, which adds to the hurt and injustice of its legacy proposes.  Its de facto amnesty for Troubles-related crimes is morally wrong and legally unsustainable.  </p><p>In this House, we came together to reject the proposals, joining all the main parties, North and South, and in the UK, apart from the Tories.  Events are taking over, both in the UK and in upcoming elections in the North.  Our voices have to remain strong.  We need to remain vigilant on this.  The British Government legacy proposals cannot go ahead.  The Irish Government has clearly stated it cannot, and will not, support them.  Promises were made through the Stormont House Agreement, comprehensive structures for investigations, truth and, where possible, a route to justice.  Those promises should be kept for all victims, regardless of the perpetrators.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1636" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#Y00200"><p>It is very apt that the Acting Leader is here as Acting Leader on this St. Brigid's Day.  We wish her well.</p> <p>To carry on from what Senator Cummins said, there is no reason every local authority would not good be as Waterford City and County Council because they have the tools, as he said, to do this.  They should be monitored and they should be made to do those things.  </p> <p>I would like to compliment the Minister of State, Deputy Peter Burke, on the changes that he intends to make to the Planning and Development Acts.  I would welcome a debate on planning and development.  It would be very useful because many projects have been refused or held up because of planning issues.  The system is not functioning the way we feel, as legislators, that the planning sections of the country should work.  We want a very efficient planning section in every local authority and a very efficient An Bord Plean&aacute;la.  I have to compliment An Bord Plean&aacute;la because it has become more and more efficient, even though it has had a bigger and bigger workload over the past number of years.  I would welcome a debate on this issue, and the role of the Residential Tenancies Board, RTB.  </p> <p>We have seen recently and many times, of course, where landlords have been ridicule not alone in this House, but in the other House as well.  However, we have never heard many of the problems that landlords have with tenants.  We have seen in the national media in the past couple of days where there has been quite a number of problems with tenants, where the landlord cannot get a rent.  This is not good enough and we could have a debate here with the Minister on this when he would come to discuss the upcoming planning and development Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#Y00300"><p>I hope I can read my own writing.  Being able to write as quickly as possible is the first test.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#Y00400"><p>We will prompt the Acting Leader.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#Y00500"><p>I thank the Senator.  I assure everyone it is pure coincidence that I am here as Acting Leader on St. Brigid's Day.  However, it is an absolute pleasure.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#Y00600"><p>It is a miracle achieved through the intercession of St. Brigid.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#Y00700"><p>I am very happy to be St. Brigid's representative in the Seanad today.  To follow what Senator Wall said, Members do not have to wait until next year to come to Kildare; they are welcome to come anytime.  In fact, Solas Bhride has a wonderful set of activities going on throughout the week.</p> <p>To turn now to the issues at hand.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Acting Chairman (Senator Fiona O'Loughlin):</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Senator Malcolm Byrne, like most Senators, recognised the importance today of L&aacute; Fh&eacute;ile Br&iacute;de and I thank them for that because she is synonymous with the environment, with farmers and with social justice not just in Kildare but around the country.  Senator Malcolm Byrne also spoke about &Aacute;ine Hyland's tweet, which I also noticed yesterday, on the fact that it is 100 years today since our education system was put in place.  The language, history, music and tradition that were mentioned 100 years ago are still hugely important today.  They are important for ourselves and they are important also for the new Irish who have come to live here so that they can appreciate our traditions and heritage.  </p><p>In regard to the issue of the Cassells report, I agree that it is regrettable that six years have gone by without any action in regard to that report.  Members may recall that the former Minister for Education, Deputy Bruton, suggested that the report go to the European Commission for economic evaluation.  My understanding is that it has been completed and has come back in the past month to the Government.  We certainly need a debate on that.  We have to invest in higher and further education going forward.  It is important, as Senators acknowledged, that students' costs go down.  We all support that but we must ensure there would not be a lacuna in regard to funding and support for higher and further education.  </p><p>The issue of Richard O'Halloran coming home was raised also.  Looking at the photographs of his children and his family over the weekend, the scenes testified to the unbridled joy in that family.  I cannot begin to imagine what the three years were like for them, and how happy they are to have their dad and husband back home.  We wish them all well.</p><p>Also mentioned was the competition mandate for the Central Bank, which is an interesting issue.  We could ask the Minister for Finance, Deputy Donohoe, to come and have a debate in regard to that issue.</p><p>Senator Conway spoke about RT&Eacute;'s "Claire Byrne Live" programme last night.  I did not see it but he has prompted me to look at it.  It gave recognition to Aimee Foley who, very sadly, was abused by her dad and showed great bravery in regard to waiving anonymity.  He also spoke about the lack of adequate sentencing.  On the day that Ashling Murphy was buried, a man was in court for murdering a woman and he got 12 years for murder.  This was on the same day that the whole country was absolutely rocked with grief and shame that this happened to Ashling Murphy.  There is an issue about sentencing and we need to address this.  We all join in saluting Aimee for her courage and bravery in coming forward.</p><p>Senator Conway also spoke about the leaving certificate, as indeed did Senators Byrne, Carrigy and Gavan.  It is a very difficult decision to make.  Much consultation was put in place over the past few months.  The big issue that everybody called for over the past few weeks was clarity, and for a decision to be made.  A decision has been made.  I accept there is disappointment with the decision but now there is clarity and arrangements have been put in place to ensure that in mathematics for example - and this is from looking at the press release earlier - where there would normally be ten questions to be answered, six can be answered.  English comprehension will have the required number of response halved.  The fact that many of those doing their leaving certificate this year did not have the opportunity to do their junior certificate had to come into play.  That was an added difficulty in regard to a hybrid model.  We will take the message back.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Fiona O'Loughlin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2441"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2441&amp;amp;pid=FionaOLoughlin&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=01"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Of that there is no doubt.  It is a worrying and stressful time.  There is never going to be a leaving certificate without stress no matter what form it takes.  It is a preparation for further exams.</p><p>Senator Lombard made a particular comment on leaving certificate reform and I am surprised he asked the question about such reform because his own party colleague, Deputy Kehoe, is Chair of the Joint Committee on Education, Further and Higher Education, Research, Innovation and Science and there have been 14 meetings in recent months on leaving certificate reform.  A total of 57 witnesses to date, between students, parent bodies, unions and teachers, have appeared before the committee on this issue.  I have no doubt there will be a very comprehensive report coming forward.  I agree we need to look at reform going forward.</p><p>I accept Senator Mullen&rsquo;s amendment and it has been seconded on the Order of Business.  I wish him well in the progress of his Personal Injuries Assessment Board (Amendment) Bill 2022.  As the Senator said, it is hard to quantify insurance fraud and we certainly need to deter it, without a shadow of a doubt.</p><p>Senator Garvey mentioned that ten times more boys than girls cycle to school and that girls should be allowed to wear trousers in schools.  I completely agree.  In fact, there was a particular hearing of the Oireachtas Committee on Education and Skills, as it was known under its last mandate, and there was a very clear direction that girls should be allowed wear trousers in school.  We need to support all of our young people to cycle and to support the cycling infrastructure throughout our towns and country. The point was well made.</p><p>Senator Garvey also made a point about science, technology, engineering and mathematics, STEM, subjects in schools.  I happened to see a small clip on television last night of Dr. Katriona O'Sullivan, who is a professor in Maynooth University, and she does tremendous work around equality in education.  It was a very interesting piece about working to support STEM within schools, particularly among girls in disadvantaged areas.  She is a wonderful woman and has made presentations before to the Oireachtas education committee and I would recommend following those.</p><p>Senators &Oacute; Donnghaile, Craughwell and Currie all spoke very passionately about Bloody Sunday and all of the coverage over the weekend.  My own father&rsquo;s anniversary was on Sunday.  In the midst of us going to mass and of our family meeting and our grief, I could not but be struck by the difference between what happened to our family and to the families on Bloody Sunday, together with the commemoration for Stardust victims.  As has been mentioned, the dignity of all the families who were interviewed, both in print and on television, was just incredible.  They deserve the truth and all of our support in all of the investigations that need to be done.  I certainly agree on the need to have truth and restorative justice and we will certainly bring those views forward to the Minister.</p><p>Senator &Oacute; Donnghaile also spoke about the report from Amnesty International on the Palestinian-Israeli conflict.  We all value the role of Amnesty International and we in Ireland have always been very forthright in expressing our solidarity with the Palestinian people.  We will look for a debate with the Minister for Foreign Affairs on this issue.</p><p>My county colleague, Senator Wall, has issued an invitation for everyone to come to Kildare, with which I completely agree.  Saint Brigid was certainly looking down on Glen Ryan and all of the lads on Sunday.  The international and national recognition of Saint Brigid and the work undertaken in Kildare in lighting the Hill of Allen etc. was exemplary.  We look forward to greater things to come, especially in 2024.</p><p>Senator Wall also mentioned the Defence Forces, as did Senator Craughwell.  I completely agree on the comments about the video announcing a change of use for Cathal Brugha Barracks.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Fiona O'Loughlin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2441"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2441&amp;amp;pid=FionaOLoughlin&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=01"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I looked into that myself and I understand there was no basis for it whatsoever.  It was an appalling lack of respect for the military and defence community, those who serve in Cathal Brugha Barracks and all of the families.  Particularly in the year of Michael Collins's centenary, words fail me in terms of why the Minister did that.  The Senator also mentioned the commission report.  We look forward to having a lengthy debate.  It is so important that we invest in our Defence Forces and that we look at recruitment and retention.  We should thank the Defence Forces for all they have done, particularly during the pandemic.</p><p>I wish Senator Flynn the very best of luck with her first Private Members' Bill.  I worked with her on the Criminal Justice (Hate Crime) Bill 2020 that I had brought before the House.  I know her absolute commitment to this whole area.  I am very happy to accept the amendment to the Order of Business which has been seconded now.  Sexual exploitation of anyone but especially children is absolutely horrific.  We all have to be committed to dealing with this in whatever way we can.</p><p>Senator Fitzpatrick spoke about the enormous challenge for those who are hoping to buy and those who are renting.  She spoke about the importance of hope to people who are locked out from owning their own home or indeed from renting a home.  We all need hope but we need practical actions as well.  She gave us good news that 123 of 231 actions have commenced or have taken place.  There were 20,000 houses completed and 30,000 commenced last year.  It is important to take the politics and the heat out of that debate and recognise it.</p><p>Senator Maria Byrne also spoke about the leaving certificate issue and about the An Bord Plean&aacute;la decision to defer a decision in respect of the Limerick to Foynes bypass.  I completely understand where she is at.  Delays on decisions like this do not help anyone.  We need to look for a decision on it.</p><p>Senator Craughwell spoke about Richard O'Halloran and Cathal Brugha Barracks.  Senator Murphy spoke about Robert Pether from Elphin and his family; indeed I have often heard him speak about the matter before.  The fact that we see Richard O'Halloran thankfully being released means we really should be able to try to put all diplomatic efforts into bringing about the release of Robert and ensuring that his family has the same opportunity to reunite.</p><p>Senator Lombard spoke about the leaving certificate, which I have mentioned.  Senator Gavan spoke about the pagan aspect of Brigid.  He is 100% correct.  In many ways Brigid was the bridge between the pagan world and the world of Christianity.  Today is also the first day of Imbolc.  No matter who Brigid was, whether she was a saint or a pagan, it is an important day to recognise everything that she and maybe many different Brigids stood for.  The Senator also raised the issue of the leaving certificate.</p><p>Senator McGahon spoke about the housing list and how people who did not update cannot go back on in the same position.  He is correct.  That is the way it is happening in Kildare and I assume it is happening around the country.  There needs to be uniformity.  It is an issue on which we need a debate with the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage.  There is no doubt about that.</p><p>Senator Ward spoke about the increase in the cost of the postage stamp and that it did not necessarily mean supporting the continuation of post offices or indeed staff.  I was surprised when I heard about it on the radio.  I do not really know what the rationale is.  We need to look for the rationale.  We also need to acknowledge the great service post offices and their staff gave, particularly during Covid.  They were just incredible in terms of the contact they gave to many elderly people who live on their own.  They did messages for them during Covid.  It is important to know that.</p><p>Senator Carrigy spoke about those working in long-term residential settings and suggested they should be included in the &euro;1,000 bonus.  My understanding is that the matter was clarified at Leaders' Questions in the D&aacute;il today.  Those in section 39 organisations will be covered.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Fiona O'Loughlin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2441"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2441&amp;amp;pid=FionaOLoughlin&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=01"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->That is most important.</p><p>Senator Boyhan spoke about forestry and harvesting and felling being a real issue and the need for a debate on the matter.  We had a debate on the issue last year but we will certainly look to organise another one.  On the issue raised by Senator Cummins, I wish to congratulate Waterford City and County Council on its achievement.  It is great that it is doing such incredible work.  I congratulate the leadership of the mayor, Joe Kelly, all the councillors, the chief executive and all the staff.  I did not see the "Prime Time" programme, but I will watch it.  It is important that when a local authority gets it right, we look at how it did it and the actions it had taken to see how we can follow that around the country.  It is a huge issue and a large light has been shone on it.  We must look to see if we can run some other pilot programme in other counties and see what we can do.  I thank Senator Cummins for bringing that to our attention.</p><p>Senator Ahearn spoke about the passports issue.  There is no doubt that the system needs an overhaul.  The Passport Office closed down completely during the first Covid lockdown.  At the time, I thought it was nonsensical that it was considered a non-essential service.  It is playing catch-up now.  The initiative that has been proposed that people should have to check their passport status when they book holidays, could be an interesting one.</p><p>Senator Currie spoke about survivors and how we need to support all victims.  I absolutely agree that we do.  Senator Burke spoke about the Planning and Development Act and requested a debate on the matter.  I think he is correct.  I know that the Minister of State, Deputy Burke, has outlined some initiatives that he wants to put in place.  I agree that it should happen, but I think it cannot happen without reference to Irish Water because many of the problems and issues that we have are down to problems with the Irish Water infrastructure.  I look forward to that debate.  The Senator also made a very pertinent point about the RTB and issues that are raised on behalf of landlords as well as residents.  There needs to be balance in the provision of support.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#CC00200"><p>Senator Mullen has proposed an amendment to the Order of Business: "That No. 15 be taken before No. 1."  The Acting Leader has indicated that she is prepared to accept the amendment.  Is the amendment agreed to?  Agreed.</p> <p>Senator Flynn has proposed an amendment to the Order of Business: "That No. 16 be taken before No. 1."  The Acting Leader has indicated that she is willing to accept the amendment.  Is the amendment agreed to?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.99" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Order of Business, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.100" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#CC00400">Personal Injuries Assessment Board (Amendment) Bill 2022: First Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#CC00500"><p>I move:</p> <blockquote> 	That leave be given to introduce a Bill entitled an Act to amend the Personal Injuries Assessment Board Act 2003.  </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.102" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#CC00700"><p>When is it proposed to take Second Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#CC00800"><p>Next Tuesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#CC00900"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.106" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Second Stage ordered for Tuesday, 8 February 2022.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.107" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#CC01100">Child Trafficking and Child Sexual Exploitation Material (Amendment) Bill 2022: First Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1657" speakername="Eileen Flynn" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#CC01200"><p>I move:</p> <blockquote> 	That leave be given to introduce a Bill entitled an Act to amend the title of the Child Trafficking and Pornography Act 1998 whereafter, following commencement of this Act, the Act of 1998 shall be titled the &quot;Child Trafficking and Child Sexual Exploitation Material (Amendment) Act 1998&quot;; to amend the title of the Child Trafficking and Pornography (Amendment) Act 2004 whereafter, following commencement of this Act, the Act of 2004 shall be titled the &quot;Child Trafficking and Child Sexual Exploitation Material (Amendment) Act 2004&quot;; to substitute the term &quot;Child Pornography&quot; with &quot;Child Sexual Exploitation Material&quot; within those Acts and other Acts. </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.109" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#CC01400"><p>When is it proposed to take Second Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1657" speakername="Eileen Flynn" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#CC01500"><p>This Thursday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#CC01550"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.113" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Second Stage ordered for Thursday, 3 February 2022.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.114" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#CC01700">Technological Universities Act 2018 (Section 36)(Appointed Day) Order 2022: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#CC01800"><p>I move:</p> <blockquote> 	That Seanad &Eacute;ireann approves the following Order in draft: Technological Universities Act 2018 (Section 36)(Appointed Day) Order 2022, copies of which have been laid in draft form before Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 29th November, 2021.&quot; </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.116" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.117" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#CC02000">Message from Joint Committee</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022020100002#CC02100"><p>The Joint Oireachtas Committee on Environment and Climate Action, at its meeting today, has completed its consideration of the Fisheries (Commercial Fishing Licences) (Alteration of Duties and Fees) Order 2022.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-01a.119" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 4.49 p.m. and resumed at 5 p.m.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>