<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.4" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Darragh O'Brien that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:<blockquote><br />The need for the Minister for Education and Skills to provide an update on progress in the provision of a new school for Gaelscoil Ros Eo, Rush, County Dublin and whether the Department has identified a permanent school site.</blockquote>I regard the matter raised by the Senator as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment and it will be taken at the conclusion of business.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.7" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300002#A00300">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.8" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300002#A00400"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, statements on the role of the SME envoy network, to be taken at 11.45 a.m., with the contributions of group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes and those of all other Senators not to exceed five minutes and the Minister to be called on to reply not later than 1.25 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300002#A00500"><p>On Tuesday I requested that the Attorney General be asked to come to the House under Standing Order 56 to explain her role in the current controversy and answer valid questions that many of us on all sides of the House had.  I will not rehash those questions, but my request is as valid today as it was on Tuesday.  I am proposing an amendment to the Order of Business that, under Standing Order 56, the Attorney General come to the House today to answer our questions and those of the public about her role in these issues, given that she knew about them last November and, apparently, did not tell anyone about them.</p><p>  Will the Leader arrange a debate on online savings and discount companies?  How are they regulated?  Like many others, I have been done by <i>completesavings.ie</i>.  The Leader might like to check this out for himself.  Irish Rail offers a &euro;10 discount on the next fare, but, unbeknownst to anyone, the website signs up the customer with <i>completesavings.ie</i> which takes &euro;12 a month from his or her bank account.  I have been in contact with Irish Rail and <i>completesavings.ie</i>.  Some of my colleagues have been duped in the same way.  More important, many hundreds of people have unknowingly been signed up for this payment in connection with future discount offers.</p> <p> Two questions must be asked.  One specifically relates to the appropriateness of a semi-State company like Irish Rail, for example, offering these types of "savings" to people, as it could cost &euro;144 per year to get &euro;10 off a rail ticket.  That is a specific example but, more important and in general, there is a question of how these types of online offers are regulated and who looks after them.  I have written to the Consumers Association of Ireland in this regard and I intend to take up the matter with the Minister, Deputy Varadkar, who I have no doubt will be concerned about a company in his charge having a commercial arrangement with a private company which is passing on bank, credit and debit card details from the Irish Rail website to a third party which happens to be an English company.  We could tease out the matter in the Seanad, as it is wholly inappropriate for Irish Rail to enter into an arrangement like this.  Other companies, like Ryanair, have such arrangements but they are private; although I do not agree with it, they can do as they like.  I believe Argos recently had a commercial arrangement with the company but has severed its links in that regard.</p><p>This is extreme sharp practice and many citizens are paying money for it from their accounts.  These do not show up as a direct debit but rather a point of sale payment with no other details.  We could have a job to do in looking at the regulations and highlighting these specific cases.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300003#B00200"><p>I welcome Mr. Michael Murphy and Ewald Hoffmann to the Gallery.  They are here at the invitation of Senator Mary White and have a long-standing connection with Waterford Glass.</p><p>Senator O'Brien has proposed an amendment to the Order of Business and I know the Leader dealt with the issue very comprehensively yesterday.  I also spoke to the matter and pointed out that it seems to be a rather desperate diversionary tactic by Fianna F&aacute;il to continue to do this.  Fianna F&aacute;il should reflect on this matter.  Even if the Attorney General was compelled to come before either House of the Oireachtas, she is bound by the same client-lawyer privilege as any other lawyer, and there are also considerations of Cabinet confidentiality that would clearly confine anything the Attorney General might have to say.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300003#B00300"><p>She has questions to answer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300003#B00400"><p>In that context I very much welcome the decision we took on the justice committee last night to seek to include certain matters in the terms of reference of the commission of investigation.  We have written to the Taoiseach today in that regard.  That decision was agreed by almost all the members on the committee.</p><p>I welcome two issues which emerged yesterday.  The first is a very welcome fall in the unemployment rate to 11.8%, and the Minister for Social Protection, Deputy Burton, has pointed out that this is the lowest rate of unemployment for five years.  Although the rate is still too high, it is now just below the EU average, which is very welcome.  I also welcome the publication of the universal health insurance White Paper yesterday and the debate in which people are becoming engaged that concerns the proposal to reform the health system by introducing universal health insurance.  It is an historic move and this Government should be very proud of it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300003#B00500"><p>It is just a tax.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300003#B00600"><p>For the first time it will do away with the two-tier health care system that we have had for far too long, with people being able to buy faster treatment and better outcomes in health care simply because they have more money.  For the first time we will move to a health care system based on need rather than means, which I welcome.</p><p>I will also mention the establishment of the new Educate Together together at Basin Lane in Rialto in Dublin 8.  I have been very involved with this campaign for many years and there is an existing Educate Together national school in Portobello that will move there.  I am pleased that Archbishop Diarmuid Martin, speaking at a ceremony to mark this change on Tuesday, noted the need to ensure greater diversity in the primary school structure and that the Portobello school would be moving to a site at Basin Lane formerly occupied by a Christian Brothers school.  It is an historic move towards diversifying patronage and ensuring greater parental choice in the education of children.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" speakername="Feargal Quinn" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300003#B00700"><p>I wish to move an amendment to the Order of Business: "That No. 9 be taken before No. 1."  This concerns the carbon monoxide detection Bill.  Senator Bacik has mentioned the economy and it is good that the jobless rate has come down.  We have a long way to go if we are to get back to where we were but it is the best figure for five years.  There are some other good figures related to the economy, and it is worth recognising that both the spending and the economic figures are coming in more favourably.  Nonethless, we cannot really relax.</p><p>It is interesting to hear on the radio this morning that the effort by the Insolvency Service of Ireland, with expenditure in the past few years of approximately &euro;5 million to &euro;7 million, has only yielded four deals with banks.  This is not down to a lack of work on behalf of the Insolvency Service of Ireland but rather poor legislation, and we should pay attention to that.  Comparing the insolvency system set up under our legislation with that in Northern Ireland, there is no competition.  We must have got something wrong if we only have that return for that length of time invested.  There is a good team in the service working well but it has only achieved four deals with banks after all those years despite 320 applications being received.  This matter needs a better attempt at legislation and this should serve as a reminder that it is not sufficient to have only one House examining legislation.  We must ensure we reform the Seanad so that in future years there will be two Houses with each working and keeping its eye on every piece of legislation coming through and improving what we do.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Ca&iacute;t Keane" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300003#B00800"><p>Yesterday was the 100th anniversary of Cumann na mBan but due to commitments in the Seanad we could not get to it.  The Council of Europe convention on preventing and combating violence against women and domestic violence is an acknowledgement of all the work that women have done in the past and will continue to do in future.  This Istanbul convention was signed by the Council of Europe in 2011 but Ireland has not yet signed it.  As a tribute to all women and men working for equity and equality, we should recognise this as a very important convention.  It is on the understanding that violence against women is a form of gender-based violence committed against women because they are women.  It is the obligation of the State to fully address this in all its forms and take measures to prevent such action, protect victims and prosecute perpetrators.  Failure to do so will make the issue a further responsibility of the State down the road.</p><p>In years gone by we have seen how the State had to take responsibility for past actions.  I ask that the Council of Europe convention be signed by Ireland.  If we fail to do that we will have to consider the issue in another light.  It is not only women who suffer domestic violence so everybody is asked to apply this convention.  I am asking that the terms be applied to men as well as women, as some men are subject to violence.  There is also abuse of children and the elderly.  The convention deals with such matters.</p><p>This is a serious issue and it can pertain within families.  I ask for a full debate on the matter and that we approve a motion to have the convention signed.  I wanted to raise this on the 100th anniversary of Cumann na mBan but to do so now would have the Seanad doing a great service not alone to women but to men who suffer violence, particularly gender-based violence.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300003#B00900"><p>Cumann na mBan was involved with violence.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Ca&iacute;t Keane" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300003#B01000"><p>This issue relates to the perpetrators.  Most violence is carried out by men and this is a small step.  I am sure there will be another opportunity to discuss the issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300003#B01100"><p>I second the amendment by our leader, Senator O'Brien.  I ask for an urgent debate on the Government's approach to rural and regional Ireland.  There is a front page headline indicating that the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Varadkar, has decided he is disposed to closing rail lines throughout the country.  There is no doubt my own Sligo to Dublin line, which a previous Government tried to close, will be under attack once again.</p> <p>At what stage will the Government's relentless attack on rural Ireland stop?  We have seen small and rural schools closed, Garda stations have been closed, health services have been centralised and we have seen the first ever reduction in CAP payments.  The Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Varadkar, and his colleagues must realise there is a culture in this country apart from that of Dublin.  People live outside of Dublin.  They live in small towns, in villages and on islands.  It is the Government's responsibility to support those communities, whether profitable or not to do so.</p><p>What will happen next?  Will they turn off the electricity at Mullingar or tell Irish Water not to provide water because it is not profitable to do so in the eyes of Deputy Varadkar, who lives in his ivory tower in Castleknock, Dublin 15?  People and citizens are entitled to the support of the Government, including support for public transportation and utilities, however profitable. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300004#C00200"><p>These are provided down the country at present.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300004#C00300"><p>The Minister is responsible for providing these services to the Leader's region also, which as he knows has been discriminated against in the context of health services.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300004#C00400"><p>Fianna F&aacute;il closed every railway line in the country when it was in power.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300004#C00500"><p>The fact Deputy Varadkar and some of his well heeled cousins in the gin and tonic belts of the nation do not feel there is a need for trains or public transportation for the people is not good enough.  I am sure the electorate outside of Dublin will take note of this on 23 May.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" speakername="Terry Brennan" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300004#C00600"><p>Yesterday I mentioned the success story of Ryanair.  We have spoken here previously about inviting people to the House to address us and I would like to make a proposal in that regard.  As far as I am concerned, one of Ireland's most successful business people -----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300004#C00700"><p>The Senator may bring any proposal he has on that to the attention of the Leader, who will bring it up at the Committee on Procedure and Privileges, or the Senator may write directly to that committee.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" speakername="Terry Brennan" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300004#C00800"><p>I suggest to the Leader that he propose to that committee that we invite Michael O'Leary to the House to -----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300004#C00900"><p>The Leader will bring that request to the committee.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" speakername="Terry Brennan" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300004#C01000"><p>That is what I ask.  I propose the Leader requests the committee to invite Michael O'Leary to address us on his story and his future plans for tourism.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300004#C01100"><p>I second Senator Feargal Quinn's amendment to the Order of Business.  This important Bill deals with the issue of carbon monoxide and I assume the reference to dwellings also refers to hotels.  There have been a number of tragedies in hotels involving the deaths of young people following inhalation of carbon monoxide.</p><p>I wish to condemn publicly the hate mail and other attacks on our colleague in the other House, the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Alan Shatter.  It is quite appalling that Nazi emblems were sent to him.  I deplore this obviously anti-Semitic attack.  I believe I was the first person to say he should resign, but I did so in a way that was proportionate.  I dealt with the facts and also paid tribute to his many remarkable qualities as a reforming Minister.  However, I have continuing difficulties with regard to the administration of justice.</p><p>I was contacted a couple of years ago by a woman in County Cavan whose son, Shane O'Farrell, was the victim of a hit and run accident.  I tried to bring to the attention of the Minister a series of unfortunate situations in this regard where there was clear Garda negligence and malpractice.  This young man was brilliant and talented.  He was knocked over by a Lithuanian heroin addict who had between 40 and 50 convictions for drug offences and larceny, on both sides of the Border, and was on the Interpol register as a criminal.  One hour before he killed this brilliant young man, this person was stopped by the drug squad.  He had no insurance on the car and there were a number of other complicating factors.  This man was registered on the PULSE system and should have been taken into custody.  This would have prevented the death of this vital and talented young man.</p><p>I wrote to the Minister about this case and the family wrote to the Minister.  We received replies that were emollient and which indicated the Minister could not interfere as he had no responsibility in the matter.  This precluded me from raising the issue as an Adjournment matter, because no Minister had responsibility for it.  Now however, in light of the various revelations that have come out, this case should be included in a public inquiry into hit and run incidents.  We should investigate in particular - I say this without any suggestion of racism - a cluster of accidents that have occurred for which drivers from eastern Europe have been responsible.  These drivers may have been unfamiliar with our roads and culture.  A predecessor of the Cathaoirleach, the late Liam Naughten, was killed in just such a tragic accident - a great loss to political life.  We need to ensure that people who drive in this country, no matter where they come from, are competent and that they are driving appropriate vehicles.  I call for a public inquiry into this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300004#C01200"><p>I want to bring to the attention of the House statistics published by the Insolvency Service of Ireland today.  These show the number of agreements that have been reached in regard to debt are significantly lower than expected.  In particular, only four out of 320 deals relating to mortgage debt have been successful since the setting up of the service.   The time has come to review the operation of the insolvency service and the legislation which established it.  Two issues have become obvious.  First, the banks are using their veto to prevent deals relating to mortgage debt and, second, by designating a significant number of borrowers as non-co-operative, they are precluding them from access to the insolvency service.</p><p>I find it amazing that non-statutory bodies like banks have the capacity to designate somebody as a non-co-operative borrower when there is no independent right of appeal.  We are dealing with a system that is entirely non transparent.  For example, people who are separated are being deemed non-co-operative because one party will not sign a document.  It is not right that we have a statutory solution, but banks, which are non-statutory bodies, are prohibiting access to that solution.  I call on the Leader, as a matter of urgency given the statistics, to bring the Minister to the House to discuss the operation of the legislation and the Insolvency Service of Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300004#C01300"><p>Ba mhaith liom labhairt inniu maidir leis an bP&aacute;ip&eacute;ar B&aacute;n at&aacute; foilsithe maidir le c&uacute;rsa&iacute; sl&aacute;inte agus an tseirbh&iacute;s sl&aacute;inte uil&iacute;och at&aacute; dh&aacute; chur chun cinn ag an Rialtas.</p><p>I would like to raise the issue of the White Paper on universal health care which has just been released.  Sinn F&eacute;in has serious concerns about this issue.  We believe the proposal is a flawed model based on competing private for profit health insurance companies and that it will lead to privatisation of the whole sector.  The White Paper is late and has been three years in the coming.  We have heard much of what would be in it, but it is only half baked in that it is scant on detail and specifics, with no costings worth mentioning.  We also need to look at what the costs will be for those currently without medical cards or private health care under the new regime.  </p><p>The consultation process that has been put in place is too short.  It seems to coincide with the EU and local elections, which is not appropriate for such a substantial change as is proposed here.  I find it quite strange that the leader of the Labour group in the House welcomes the White Paper, as it seems to be a long way away from that group's pre-election promise of a single State insurance provider.  We have had useful hearings previously in the Seanad on issues such as those affecting older people.</p><p>I suggest therefore that with a change as substantial as the universal health care model being introduced, it might be a worthwhile use of the Seanad to have similar hearings.  We could bring in people from jurisdictions where this model has worked and experts on the area of universal health care and tease out the issues further.  I know we have expertise in the House on some of the areas concerning the type of model proposed, so it would be good use of Seanad time if we could have such discussion.  No doubt, health issues will be raised frequently over the coming months, but perhaps we should deal with the issue in a focused way and bring in witnesses so we can delve into the issues in depth.  This would be very useful.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300005#D00100"><p>I support Senator O'Brien's call this morning for a debate on the online offers he spoke about, even if it does nothing but highlight the risks people take by revealing bank details and other details to unknown entities.  People need to be warned about the number of online scams being developed by agencies inside and outside the State.  There is grave cause for concern, particularly if a State agency is promoting an offer that will potentially cost consumers significant amounts of money.  I, too, welcome the publication of the White Paper.  I was going to ask the Leader to organise a debate in this House soon so we can tease out the many elements of it.  I would have no difficulty with the type of consultation process Senator &Oacute; Clochartaigh mentioned here this morning.  This is the most significant reform in the history of the State and will eliminate our unfair and inefficient two-tier system.</p><p>The consultation process is very important and significant and we need to consult as widely as possible.  This will build on the very steady progress the Minister, Deputy Reilly, has made since he became Minister for Health in reforming the health service.  He is to be applauded for the very significant reductions we are seeing in waiting lists and people on trolleys.  This is the most important element of the health reform we will see during the next decade.  It is important that we consult very widely and I look forward to having that debate or consultation process initiated in this House as soon as possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1142" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300005#D00200"><p>Like the last speaker I support the Leader of this side of the House, Senator O'Brien, in his remarks about these so-called online savings and bonus operations.  I am thankful to Senator O'Brien because when he raised it originally a council colleague of mine in Kerry contacted me to say she had looked up her Visa account and found out she had lost approximately &euro;36 over a three-month period.  I was laughing at the idea of it until I looked up my own and found I had been taken for &euro;60.  It happened when I booked online a train ticket from Charleville to Dublin and at the end of my transaction a pop-up box offered me a &euro;10 discount on my next Iarnr&oacute;d &Eacute;ireann fare.  I thought it was very good form and very good business on the part of Iarnr&oacute;d &Eacute;ireann to reward regular customers such as me.  I was chuffed at the idea.</p><p>I am very vigilant when signing off on any financial offers online and am reasonably computer literate and it must have been a very well-worded document for me to have clicked it without realising it would cost me &euro;12 per month in perpetuity had I not been alerted to the fact.  I am very disappointed that Iarnr&oacute;d &Eacute;ireann would be associated with such activity.  With Senator O'Brien and others I call on Iarnr&oacute;d &Eacute;ireann to desist immediately because there must be hundreds of people out there, some of whom may be sitting in this Chamber, who have not checked their balances yet.  There are some regular train users here such as Senator Paul Coghlan.  I hope everything is all right in his account.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300005#D00300"><p>Senators O'Brien and O'Sullivan made valid points, but I am no longer amazed at Senator MacSharry's performances and how he allows himself to get carried away.  The Sligo school of acting has much to answer for.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300005#D00400"><p>That is jealousy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300005#D00500"><p>Not at all.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300005#D00600"><p>It is.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300005#D00700"><p>His points were well made.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300005#D00800"><p>Senator MacSharry was disgraceful.  There are two issues involved here, and we would not want to get carried away.  One is cost control, which Irish Rail must address.  Its accounts show it has a job to do there.  Equally, we cannot expect, as Senator MacSharry implied, that the taxpayer must continually be screwed for everything, regardless.  We no longer live in such a State.  The Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Varadkar, is sounding a note of caution.  Senator O'Sullivan rightly points out that we do not have a difficulty on the southern route.  We are giving it good use and we often have difficulty fighting for a seat but more power to those who are coming from Cork, Kerry and joining the trains at Charleville, Limerick Junction and even Thurles.  The trains coming up in the mornings and returning in the evenings are full, as we know well.  Many of the inter-city services are very well used.  If what Senator MacSharry said about Sligo is true, it is up to the chamber of commerce and the local communities to be more active in promoting increased rail use if that is required.  We cannot expect the taxpayer to continue to fund it regardless.  That is the message.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300005#D00900"><p>The Senator should ask the Minister of State at the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Kelly, about his special train in Tipperary which carries approximately five people per day.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300005#D01000"><p>There might be one train service-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300005#D01100"><p>He got that in as a-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300005#D01200"><p>That service cold not operate for a long time.  With the floods we had during the winter it was effectively running through a portion of a flood plain.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300005#D01300"><p>Does Senator Paul Coghlan have a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300005#D01400"><p>We understand that particular line.  I am just saying-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300005#D01500"><p>Have you a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300005#D01600"><p>I am sure the Leader thoroughly agrees with me.  We just need to catch ourselves on, particularly Senator MacSharry, with respect.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300005#D01700"><p>Sometimes I think we do not live in the real world.  I heard the reports today that the Insolvency Service of Ireland, ISI, has concluded only four mortgage deals, as Senator Hayden said, in a year.  ISI said progress is slow; that is the understatement of the year.  It is ineffective.  My colleague, Senator Quinn, said it is time we brought that legislation back into the House to make it effective.  All the evidence shows that the system only works when there is intervention on behalf of distressed mortgage and personal or business debt holders who are able to negotiate write-downs and sustainable deals.  Organisations such as the Irish Mortgage Holders Organisation are doing that effectively with some of the institutions.  Nothing else is working.  Negotiation must be the first step.  The Government must put its energies behind that because the banks also need to clear off this debt and put sustainable arrangements in place so they can get on with their business.  I support the call for the Minister to come into the House to revisit that ineffective legislation.</p><p>I very strongly support the call for public consultation in this House on universal health insurance.  If we can deliver on this in a cost-effective way and offer reliable universal health care for the country, we will be successful and it will be great.  I  stood on this platform myself.  However all the indications are that we are going down the wrong road.  Last night I tabled an Adjournment matter before the Minister of State at the Department of Health, Deputy White on GP care for under-sixes.  He completely contradicted what 200 GPs said to me and other Senators in Galway City.  The Minister of State said that on three occasions he has offered the GPs an opportunity to negotiate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300005#D01800"><p>We are not discussing yesterday's business today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300005#D01900"><p>The GPs have said the opposite.  The Minister of State said the GPs could negotiate without influencing cost.  Is that negotiation?  I rest my case.  Let us have a proper public consultation that includes all the stakeholders who are needed to deliver universal health care.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" speakername="Eamonn Coghlan" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300005#D02000"><p>I must comment on Senator O'Brien's calling for an amendment to the Order of Business.  I understand his political motives.  He just wants to keep this issue going.  He said it is as valid today as it was on Tuesday when he asked for the Attorney General to come into the House to be questioned.  It is just another example of the Senator stirring the pot.  I remind him where and how long ago the seeds of this issue were planted.  I remind him that this is a corporate governance issue which has affected our corporate community, charitable negations, sporting organisations and, now, the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  This Government is dealing with the issue.  There is commentary from many quarters.  Bringing the Attorney General in here would be just a political game.  This Government will not take its eye off the ball but will keep its eye on the economy, jobs and reform, and that is what this issue is all about.</p> <p> With regard to the theatrics of Senator Marc MacSharry, the last thing the Minister, Deputy Leo Varadkar, wants to do is close rural railway lines.  This is another example of reform and it is about asking semi-State companies to perform with a business perspective.  I know it is a political ploy because the Senator referred to 23 May when the local and European elections will take place.  That is why he wants to stir it.  I commend what Fine Gael is doing in reforming this great country of ours.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300006#E00200"><p>Dublin West will be happy with Senator Eamonn Coghlan.  I feel a by-election run coming on.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300006#E00300"><p>He is being political now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300006#E00400"><p>I support the comments made by my colleague, Senator David Norris, in utterly condemning the attacks on the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Alan Shatter, at his home, involving his family and, more insidiously, the anti-Semitic nature of the attacks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300006#E00500"><p>Well said.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300006#E00600"><p>There is no place in Irish society for this type of behaviour and this message should go out loud and clear.  I know my colleagues in the other House, irrespective of their political differences with the Minister, have also condemned the attacks.  The Fianna F&aacute;il group in its entirety utterly and unambiguously condemns this outrageous uncivilised behaviour by a person or persons unknown and assures the Minister that we do not in any way support it.</p><p>  I want to cast minds back to when the Government was formed and concerns were expressed about what was seen as a very serious rural-urban imbalance in the appointment of Ministers.  It was stated at the time that it would come back to haunt the Government.  Far be it from me to disagree with my friend and colleague, Senator Paul Coghlan, on the most recent statements made by the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Leo Varadkar, but one reads headlines such as that on page 1 of the <i>Irish Independent</i> &quot;Varadkar's plan to close railways&quot; and another on page 17 about new fears of another blow to rural life amid a warning of train service cuts.  It is not coming from this side of the House; it is what the people believe what is happening, that the Government is systematically shutting down rural Ireland.  This is the perception, regardless of whether Senators like it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300006#E00700"><p>Newspaper headlines are an editor's responsibility.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300006#E00800"><p>I remind Senators, six weeks ahead of the local elections, of the old clich&eacute; that perception is everything in politics.  It is not about the reality.  Even Irish Rural Link has been chilled to the bone.  I am shocked by the statements of the Minister, Deputy Leo Varadkar, because it is a proven fact throughout the world that public services, particularly bus and rail services, are not expected to make a profit.  There is an obligation on the Government of the day to provide social services for the people they represent.  That is the bottom line.  This does not take in any way from their being efficient or run efficiently.  A cost benefit analysis was carried out approximately a decade ago by consultants employed by the then Fianna F&aacute;il Government which showed that irrespective of whether there would be increased numbers, the Dublin-Sligo rail service would never be viable.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" speakername="Eamonn Coghlan" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300006#E00900"><p>They got it wrong.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300006#E01000"><p>Is the Senator looking for a debate on the issue?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300006#E01100"><p>Yes.  The rail service would never be viable because there would always be a population imbalance between the west and east of the country.  It is a fact of Irish life.  If what the Minister stated is endorsed by the Government, woe betide the Fine Gael and Labour Party candidates who will go before the electorate in six weeks time, particularly those in my part of the country-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300006#E01200"><p>The Senator is over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300006#E01300"><p>They will rue the day they stayed quiet when the Minister threatened to shut down another service in rural Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300006#E01400"><p>It has to do with usage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300006#E01500"><p>I propose an amendment to the Order of Business that the Taoiseach or the Minister come to the House today to explain and clarify the Government's attitude to and policy on rural Ireland, not only on this issue.  It is long past time that the Government was brought to account for the measures it has taken in the past three years.  As has been explained by my colleague, Senator Marc MacSharry, it is totally unacceptable and the Government will reap the whirlwind on 23 May.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300006#E01600"><p>The issue of transport has been raised.  I agree with my good friend and colleague, Senator Terry Brennan, on his proposal that the Committee on Procedure and Privileges be asked to consider issuing an invitation to Mr. Michael O'Leary, chief executive officer of Ryanair, to address the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300006#E01700"><p>The Committee on Procedure and Privileges will deal with that issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300006#E01800"><p>I support my colleague, Senator Terry Brennan, simply because Mr. O'Leary is one of the greatest business people we have ever created.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300006#E01900"><p>He created himself.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300006#E02000"><p>The interruption is much appreciated.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300006#E02100"><p>It is a matter for the Committee on Procedure and Privileges.  Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300006#E02200"><p>I congratulate Ryanair.  The Taoiseach is on his way to Dublin Airport to officially open the new Ryanair block.  Ryanair has developed a global brand and is an example of what can be achieved by a small country.  It is the leading airline in Europe and went from carrying 1 million passengers to almost 90 million passengers and I understand that in the coming years that figure will grow to 150 million.  The airline will drive tourism in this country and make an indelible contribution to the recovery we are experiencing.  Senator Terry Brennan's proposal is inspired and I sincerely hope the Committee on Procedure and Privileges will look favourably on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300006#E02300"><p>I second the proposal made by Senator Paschal Mooney to amend the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1169" speakername="Mary Ann O'Brien" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300006#E02400"><p>I join my colleagues in condemning the desperate treatment afforded to the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Alan Shatter, by the cowards who delivered the package to his house.  I express my personal and professional sympathy to the Minister.</p><p>The Minister for Health, Deputy James Reilly, is definitely throwing the baby out with the bathwater with his White Paper on universal health care.  What seems to have slid under all of us is a further delay in the development of the national children's hospital.  Why is the Minister speaking about universal health care when we do not even have a building for children to go to when they are sick?  Some Monday or Tuesday when Senators are travelling to, or leaving, Dublin, I ask them to drive around the grounds of St. James's Hospital.  It will only take ten minutes for them to do so.  I have done so and met the people involved.  I will outline for Senators the Dolphin report which did not recommend St. James's Hospital as the perfect site.  It only met one or two of the criteria outlined by Dolphin.  The report stated 5.6 ha would be required, whereas St. James's Hospital extends to only 2.5 ha.  Demolition of the hospital will take four to five months.  I ask Senators to think about 35 trucks on rotas hauling filthy dusty debris five times a day.  There are two small entrances to the hospital grounds.  There is hardly a car parking space for the staff.  The new plans include an underground car park, but I would love the Minister to come to the House to discuss the issue because the Drimnagh sewers run under St. James's Hospital.  Most of the heavy electrical cabling under the hospital has not been mapped.  It will be extremely difficult to map and in doing so there will be huge time delays.  If St. James's Hospital is to be the location of the national children's hospital, staff will have to park off-site.  Imagine people from rural Ireland with a sick child getting out at the Red Cow to get on the Luas to bring the child to hospital.</p> <p> On the heritage note, there is a very fine Victorian church on the grounds of St. James's that must be destroyed.  It reeks of the Mater site scenario all over again.  The press reports state that the children's hospital will still be ready in 2018, to which my response is "balderdash".  We need to ask the Minister for Health, Deputy Reilly to come to this House.  St. James's hospital is not the site for the children's hospital.  Action must be taken on this and we need to discuss what should be done.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300007#F00200"><p>For the fourth time in a row, a proposed amendment to the Order of Business requests that we bring the Attorney General to the House.  On this fourth occasion, I will repeat that the Government has initiated a commission of inquiry investigation.  The Fianna F&aacute;il Party continues to play politics.  I think the Fianna F&aacute;il Members should quit doing this because they have done enough damage to themselves.  They should take time to take a pull.  People are fed up with the antics the Fianna F&aacute;il Members have been at for a number of weeks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300007#F00300"><p>Thanks for the advice.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300007#F00400"><p>The matter has been decided by the Houses of the Oireachtas when the motion of confidence was defeated in the D&aacute;il.  It should be left at that because I would hate to see the Members opposite doing more damage to themselves.</p><p>  Senators Darragh O'Brien, Mullins and O'Sullivan raised the question of online discount and savings offers from <i>completesavings.ie.</i></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300007#F00500"><p>Was that point okay?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300007#F00600"><p>What I heard today was disturbing, as I had not heard of it, but from what the Senators have mentioned, I think it is absolutely despicable.  Perhaps the forum to get further information on this from the Minister is to raise it on the Adjournment.  I think such practices should be carefully examined.  I am disappointed that State bodies would be involved in such schemes.</p><p>Senator Bacik welcomes the fall in unemployment to 11.8%.  This decrease in unemployment is to be welcomed by all.  To reiterate what she said, we cannot stop at that.  Jobs and the economy have been and will continue to be the first priority of Government.  We would not be happy that the rate of unemployment would remain at 11.8%.  This is the 21st month in a row that we have seen a fall in the unemployment figures, which is to be welcomed.</p><p>In relation to universal health insurance Senator Bacik was joined by Senators &Oacute; Clochartaigh, Mullins, Healy Eames and others in welcoming the White Paper.  A White Paper is a discussion document, so the Government is inviting comments on universal health insurance from all sides.  I am sure the Joint Committee on Health and Children will debate it at length and I hope we will get an opportunity to debate it in this House.  We have public consultation hearings organised for the next month or two, which will take us up to September but we can consider other matters.  We are dealing with human rights in the periodic review under public consultation.  Those hearings will take place sometime in May.  </p><p>Senators Quinn, Hayden and Healy Eames raised the fact that only four cases have been successfully resolved by the Insolvency Service of Ireland.  The Minister has stated that after this body beds down, and it is bedding down but it has only been in place one year, the Government would review the legislation.  I will certainly bring the matter to the attention of the Minister.  I think it is his intention that the legislation would be reviewed and amended if necessary.</p><p>Senator Quinn proposed an amendment to the Order of Business that No. 9 on the Order Paper would be taken before No. 1.  I have no problem acceding to that request.</p><p>Senator Keane raised the issue of violence against women and requested that we debate and sign the Istanbul Convention.  I will certainly have that examined.  Senators MacSharry and Mooney raised matters and the theatrical expertise of Senator MacSharry came to the fore this morning when he raised the proposed closure of railway lines.  Some people believe everything they read in the newspaper.  When we talk about the closure of railway lines, I can think of the wholesale closure of railway lines back in the 1960s by the then Fianna F&aacute;il Government.  Many of these lines were viable at the time, I can give one example in my constituency namely the closure of the line from Waterford to Tramore, which would be a goldmine now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" speakername="Terry Brennan" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300007#F00700"><p>What about Carlingford?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300007#F00750"><p>Many more lines were closed down.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300007#F00800"><p>Open it up - What about the Minister of State, Deputy Alan Kelly's line in County Tipperary and his special train? </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300007#F00900"><p>I am glad the Senator is showing concern for something that might close down.  The Fianna F&aacute;il Party closed down lines many years ago without any recourse to the public.  The lines are now gone, so it does make any difference what year it was.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300007#F01000"><p>We may as well be talking about Ernest Blythe and his pension.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300007#F01100"><p>The Senator is off track again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300007#F01200"><p>Does the Leader want a history lesson or does he want he want to return to reality?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300007#F01300"><p>Senators Brennan and Conway called for the chief executive of Ryanair to be invited to address the House, a matter which will be brought to the Committee On procedure and Privileges.</p><p>Senators Norris, Mooney and O'Brien referred to the hate mail sent to the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Alan Shatter.  This must be condemned by all.  I thank the Senators for raising that matter.  It is despicable that we have such people who would send hate mail.  Senator Norris had called for the resignation of the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Shatter previously but I fully respect that he said that Deputy Shatter had remarkable qualities as a reforming Minister.</p><p>Senator Paul Coghlan suggested that the taxpayers cannot always be asked to foot the Bill for non-performaing railway lines or other infrastructure, but I am sure a cost benefit analysis will be done on any railway line before closure is contemplated.  Senator Eamon Coghlan also outlined that the Government needs to continue to focus on jobs and the economy, which the Government has been doing for the past number of years.  This is beginning to bear fruit with the upturn in the economy.</p><p>Senator Conway welcomed the fact that Ryanair is driving tourism to Ireland and with the opening of new routes it is expected that an additional 1.4 million passengers will visit Ireland.</p><p>In response to Senator Mary Ann O'Brien, I will not get into a debate on the location of the children's hospital; it has been decided and it will proceed.  We have had many reports on the site and I think most if not all people - except some who may have vested interests - want the hospital to proceed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300007#F01400"><p>Senator Darragh O'Brien has moved an amendment to the Order of Business, "That in accordance with Standing Order 56, the Attorney General be invited to attend the Seanad today to discuss the taping of telephone conversations in Garda stations".  Is the amendment being pressed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300007#F01500"><p>Yes, it is.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" speakername="John Gilroy" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300007#F01600"><p>Again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.95/1" nospeaker="true" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300007#F01700"><p>Amendment put:</p><p>The Seanad divided: T, 12; Nl, 24.</p><p>Tellers: T, Senators Paschal Mooney and Ned O'Sullivan; Nl, Senators Paul Coghlan and Aideen Hayden.</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.95/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2014-04-03" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300007#F01700">
            <divisioncount ayes="12" noes="24" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1147" vote="aye">John Crown</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" vote="aye">Mark Daly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" vote="aye">Terry Leyden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" vote="aye">Marc MacSharry</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" vote="aye">Paschal Mooney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" vote="aye">David Norris</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1115" vote="aye">Labhr&aacute;s &Oacute; Murch&uacute;</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" vote="aye">Darragh O'Brien</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1142" vote="aye">Ned O'Sullivan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" vote="aye">Feargal Quinn</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1155" vote="aye">Kathryn Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" vote="aye">Mary White</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" vote="no">Ivana Bacik</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" vote="no">Terry Brennan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" vote="no">Colm Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" vote="no">Eamonn Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" vote="no">Paul Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1124" vote="no">Michael Comiskey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" vote="no">Martin Conway</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" vote="no">Maurice Cummins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" vote="no">Jim D'Arcy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1160" vote="no">Michael D'Arcy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" vote="no">John Gilroy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" vote="no">Aideen Hayden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1152" vote="no">Imelda Henry</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" vote="no">Ca&iacute;t Keane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1162" vote="no">Denis Landy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1167" vote="no">Fiach MacConghail</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" vote="no">Michael Mullins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1187" vote="no">Hildegarde Naughton</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" vote="no">Catherine Noone</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1169" vote="no">Mary Ann O'Brien</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" vote="no">Susan O'Keeffe</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" vote="no">Pat O'Neill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1163" vote="no">Tom Shehan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" vote="no">Jillian van Turnhout</mpname>
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.95/3" nospeaker="true" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300007#F01700"><p>Amendment declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300008#H00100"><p>On amendment No. 2 in the name of Senator Feargal Quinn, "That No. 9 be taken before No. 1," the Leader has indicated that he will accept the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.97" nospeaker="true" time="11:20:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300008#H00300"><p>Senator Paschal Mooney has moved amendment No. 3, "That a debate on Government policy on rural Ireland be taken today."  Is the amendment being pressed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300008#H00400"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.100/1" nospeaker="true" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300008#H00600"><p>Amendment put:</p><p>The Seanad divided: T, 12; Nl, 23.</p><p>Tellers: T, Senators Paschal Mooney and Ned O'Sullivan; Nl, Senators Paul Coghlan and Aideen Hayden.</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.100/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2014-04-03" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300008#H00600">
            <divisioncount ayes="12" noes="23" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1147" vote="aye">John Crown</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" vote="aye">David Cullinane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" vote="aye">Mark Daly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" vote="aye">Terry Leyden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" vote="aye">Marc MacSharry</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" vote="aye">Paschal Mooney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" vote="aye">David Norris</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1115" vote="aye">Labhr&aacute;s &Oacute; Murch&uacute;</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" vote="aye">Darragh O'Brien</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1142" vote="aye">Ned O'Sullivan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" vote="aye">Feargal Quinn</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1155" vote="aye">Kathryn Reilly</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" vote="no">Ivana Bacik</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" vote="no">Terry Brennan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" vote="no">Colm Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" vote="no">Eamonn Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" vote="no">Paul Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1124" vote="no">Michael Comiskey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" vote="no">Martin Conway</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" vote="no">Maurice Cummins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" vote="no">Jim D'Arcy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1160" vote="no">Michael D'Arcy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" vote="no">John Gilroy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" vote="no">Aideen Hayden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1152" vote="no">Imelda Henry</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" vote="no">Ca&iacute;t Keane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1167" vote="no">Fiach MacConghail</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" vote="no">Michael Mullins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1187" vote="no">Hildegarde Naughton</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" vote="no">Catherine Noone</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1169" vote="no">Mary Ann O'Brien</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" vote="no">Susan O'Keeffe</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" vote="no">Pat O'Neill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1163" vote="no">Tom Shehan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" vote="no">Jillian van Turnhout</mpname>
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.100/3" nospeaker="true" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300008#H00600"><p>Amendment declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.101" nospeaker="true" time="11:25:00" ><p>Question, &quot;That the Order of Business, as amended, be agreed to,&quot; put and declared carried.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.102" nospeaker="true" time="11:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300009#J00200">Building Control (Carbon Monoxide Detection) Bill 2014: First Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" speakername="Feargal Quinn" time="11:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300009#J00300"><p>I move:<blockquote><br />That leave be granted to introduce a Bill entitled an Act to provide for the installation of life-saving carbon monoxide detection devices in dwellings; to provide for certification of compliance; to provide for offences and penalties to apply in respect of instances of non-compliance and to provide for related matters.</blockquote>There have been a number of deaths in recent times and this is an effort to take the first steps towards solving the problem.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.104" nospeaker="true" time="11:25:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300009#J00500"><p>When is it proposed to take Second Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" speakername="Feargal Quinn" time="11:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300009#J00600"><p>On Tuesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300009#J00700"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.108" nospeaker="true" time="11:25:00" ><p>Second Stage ordered for Tuesday, 8 April 2014.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.109" nospeaker="true" time="11:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300009#J00800">SME Envoy Networks: Statements</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1081" speakername="John Perry" time="11:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300009#J00900"><p>I thank Members all for the kind invitation to address the Chamber on the important work to which Ireland is contributing at a European level to assist SMEs across Europe to grow and develop.  If I may, I would like to start by informing the Chamber of how and why the SME envoy network was established in the first place.</p><p>SMEs are the backbone of the EU economy and a key driver in the EU economic landscape.  SMEs provide millions of jobs and are continuously innovative in the provision of their goods and services.  Some 98% of all businesses in the EU employ fewer than 250 people.  This figure can be similarly applied to Ireland.  Some 85% of new jobs have been created by SMEs.  This is evidence that SMEs are the force behind job creation in Europe.  There are 23 million SMEs in the European Union.  If each SME were to take on one extra employee, the unemployment crisis in Europe would be over.</p><p>The Commission and the member states wanted to respond to the needs of SMEs by removing barriers for start-ups and through the introduction of the Small Business Act for Europe, SBA, which includes a wide range of measures which have been developed to make life easier for small businesses.  Vice President Tajani invited all member states to appoint a national SME envoy.  It is thanks to the close co-operation between the Commission and the member states that we have made concrete progress in the implementation of the SBA.</p><p>In 2008, at the start of the downturn, member states, along with the Commission, agreed to adopt the SBA.  Given the events over the past six years, it was a very challenging time and environment in which to implement a small business policy agenda.  The SBA is a set of ten principles which aim to guide the design and implementation of policies at both EU and national level.  The work is essential in order to ensure there is a level playing field for SMEs throughout the EU and to improve the administrative and legal environment that will allow these enterprises to unleash their full potential to create jobs and growth.</p><p>The policy-making process in the EU sees legislative proposals from the Commission debated both by Members of the European Parliament and by representatives of member states' Governments within the European Council.  Generally, the Commission consults with interested parties on a formal and informal basis before it draws up its proposals, as was the case with the SBA.  This provides an opportunity for those that may be affected by policy to make their views known at several stages in the process.</p><p>There are a number of clear difficulties involved in ensuring that SMEs are in a position to put their views across to policy makers.  SMEs do not usually have the resources that large firms dedicate to influencing policy making or lobbying.  It is for this reason that the Commission appointed an EU SME envoy and encourages effective and wide-ranging consultation of SMEs as one element of its principle of thinking small first.</p><p>Following a review of the SBA in 2011, the Commission asked each member state to appoint a high-ranking government official as the national SME envoy.  The Government, in showing how important the role of small business is to our economy, nominated me, as Minister of State with responsibility for small business, to be that envoy.  Ireland is one of the few countries in the network to nominate a Minister of State as envoy and I know, from speaking to my colleagues in the Commission, that the decision has been welcomed.</p><p>The purpose of the SME envoy is to ensure that Government bodies at all levels integrate the SBA principle into policy making, regulatory proposals and funding programmes.  SME envoys are the main channel between the Commission and national policy makers for contributing towards the dialogue on SBA implementation.  The SME envoy network also provides a great opportunity to learn from each other and helps in the exchange of good practices.</p><p>The SME envoy is an active interface with the SME business community, considering their specific interests and needs in EU programmes and policies.  The main objective of this function is to establish a close, direct link between the Commission, SMEs and their representatives.  The SME envoy network is supported in its work by the Enterprise Europe Network, which is the local entry point for SMEs looking for advice.  The Enterprise Europe Network provides information and advice on EU funding opportunities or on market opportunities in the language of the SME.  It also helps SMEs to find business partners in other countries and gives advice on how to overcome regulatory obstacles.</p><p>The SME envoy network ensures that SME interests and needs can be better identified at an early stage and highlighted to the relevant services, ensuring that their concerns are taken into consideration, that adequate and efficient measures are implemented, and that overall EU and national policy is more SME friendly.  Particular attention is given by the SME envoy network to the craft sector, small businesses and sole traders because of their specific needs.</p><p>The basis of the work programme for the network is delivery of the ten SBA principles of interest to SMEs.  These include entrepreneurship, second chance, the principle of thinking small first, responsive administration, state aid and public procurement, access to finance, the Single Market, skills and innovation, the environment, and the internationalisation of SMEs.  The SBA has been instrumental in putting SMEs at the centre of EU action and SME policy is now a top priority for all member states.  The Commission has given particular priority to the issues of access to finance, cutting red tape and expanding into growth markets outside the EU.</p><p>The European Commission reports annually on each member state's performance in implementing the SBA.  The latest available report for Ireland was published in 2013 and relied mainly on 2012 data.  The report shows that Ireland has a positive SBA profile and that we are above the EU average in eight of the ten areas concerned.  We are the top performer in Europe when it comes to second chance.  The report acknowledges that Ireland offers a friendly business environment, supported by an efficient administration which is responsive to business needs and that Ireland has an innovative and entrepreneurial business culture.  The Commission also acknowledges that Ireland has not adopted a specific strategy for implementing the SBA and that we do this through our Action Plan for Jobs process.  The report also references the Government's positive engagement with small business through the advisory group on small business and the high-level group on business regulation, both of which I chair.</p> <p> In the area of entrepreneurship the report shows Ireland is at or above the EU average in seven of the nine indicators identified under this heading.  These positive results cover issues such as self-employment rate, entrepreneurship rate, opportunity driven entrepreneurship, preference for self-employment, feasibility of becoming self-employed, the share of adults who think successful entrepreneurs receive a high status in society and media attention for entrepreneurship.  We are behind the EU average on two issues covering entrepreneurial intention and the share of adults who agree that school education helped them to develop an entrepreneurial attitude.</p><p> As Members of this House will be aware, the Government has supported the development of the national entrepreneurship policy statement - there are published documents in the antechamber if they wish to take them.  In order to help us in this work we established an Entrepreneurship Forum in May 2013, tasked with examining the current environment and policy framework and making recommendations aimed at further supporting entrepreneurship and business start-ups.  The membership of the forum consisted of entrepreneurs and academics, with representatives from my Department and Enterprise Ireland.  The forum considered all 74 submissions from a parallel public consultation process, as well as the outcomes of meetings with stakeholders in the development of its report.  The report contains 69 recommendations and is an important contribution to our current consideration of new policies to drive entrepreneurship in Ireland.  With a view to delivering a whole of government response to driving entrepreneurship, we are undertaking a cross-governmental feasibility and operational assessment to facilitate informed decision making on the recommendations made in the forum's report and their suitability for inclusion in the forthcoming national entrepreneurship policy statement.  We hope to be in a position to publish the policy statement shortly.</p><p> On the issue of a second chance, the report acknowledges Ireland as being the best EU performer.  This heading measures issues such as the time it takes to close a business, the cost of closing a business and the degree of support for a second chance.  In all three measures we are ahead of the EU average.  This area was helped by the introduction of the Personal Insolvency Act 2012 and the Civil Law (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act 2011, both of which deal with debt difficulties.</p><p> On the Think Small First measure, the report suggests Ireland performs slightly below the EU average and that at the same time the administrative burden on business regarding compliance with Government regulations is quite low, while the communication and simplification of rules and procedures are above average.  However, according to the report, Ireland is below the EU average when it comes to information on licensing and permits.  It should be noted that this indicator is based on the position in 2008 and I am confident this is no longer the case.  In 2012 my Department launched a business regulation website - <i>businessregulation.ie</i>- to help start-ups through relevant legislation on setting up a business and which provides tools and guidance for start-ups.</p><p> As part of An Action Plan for Jobs 2014, we are working on developing the single portal for SME retailer licences.  This portal will be a one-stop-shop integrated online system for a key sector of the economy.  Ultimately, the aim is to reduce the administrative burden for retailers.  It is hoped we will eventually roll it out to other sectors of the economy.  The Commission and other member states are eager to hear about our experience regarding licences and I intend to provide an update on the Irish experience of the SME envoy network in Naples during the year.  It will allow, where there are up to 23 licences and 15 State authorities involved, one portal where a person can access a one-stop shop for the issuing of licences.</p><p> Also, a number of Departments and agencies have attended the Taking Care of Business events which have taken place around the country.  The purpose of these events, the first of which was launched by Senator Feargal Quinn in Dublin Castle, is to provide advice and support for SME operators from a number of State bodies covering different regulations that may be of interest on general SME Government supports, including financial training.  The first event was held in Dublin last year and followed by events in Limerick and Galway.  The latest, which I attended, was held in Cork on Tuesday, with further events planned for later in the year.  One example of good engagement at these events is the National Standards Authority of Ireland.  As Senators will be aware, the NSAI is continuously encouraging SMEs in developing best practice and standards.  This is being undertaken to ensure our SMEs are the best in the world when it comes to standardisation which can assist in their internationalisation.  This work ties in with that of the Commission and the SME envoy network on standards.</p><p> There is no need to put in place a formal policy on the Think Small First principle.  Everyone is aware, across all levels of government and agencies, of the importance the Government places on job creation.  We have An Action Plan for Jobs which is now our yardstick for measuring the improving environment for businesses to create and sustain the jobs people so badly need. The Government has designated 2014 as the year during which it is all about jobs.  It is also important to note that every memorandum for the Government contains a competitiveness test which covers many of the issues contained in the SBA.  In addition, all legislation being proposed must be subject to a regulatory impact assessment.</p><p> The report shows Ireland has again outperformed the EU average in the majority of the responsive administration indicators and that Ireland has a business friendly administration.  It goes on to compliment the low cost and speed in creating a firm in Ireland and the relatively few bureaucratic hurdles to be jumped to create a business.  It also acknowledges the introduction of the Companies Bill 2012 which will establish the basis for a new legal framework for companies in Ireland.  The Bill will reduce red tape for small businesses and make it easier and cheaper to set up a company in Ireland.</p><p> There are two indicators identified which show Ireland performing below the EU average.  These are the time it takes to transfer a property and the cost to enforce contracts.  On the contracts issue, it is important to note that the Small Claims Court can now deal with business-to-business disputes up to the value of &euro;2,000.</p><p> Overall, Ireland scores above average in the indicators for State aid and public procurement.  This area also covers the issue of prompt payments and the indicator shows the average delay in payments from public authorities is well below the EU average.  My Department acts as a first contact point for businesses which want information on their rights under the prompt payments legislation.  If the problem lies with a public authority, my Department tries to resolve the issue with the public authority before an escalation occurs.  Furthermore, my Department is involved in a public information campaign on prompt payments as a result of the directive on late payments in commercial transactions.  This campaign started in December and is continuing at the one-stop shop events.  I encourage anyone with any issue with prompt payments to attend future events as the officials from my Department are there to help.  Alternatively, my Department can deal with their queries directly.</p><p> The report shows Ireland is below the EU average regarding the SMEs' share of the total value of public contracts awarded.  However, An Action Plan for Jobs aims to address this issue by identifying 13 actions which would be relevant to SMEs in having greater access to procurement opportunities.  Issues such as maintaining and updating the standard suite of tender documents to bring about a more consistent approach to procurement are being dealt with.  An Action Plan for Jobs will also transpose the new EU procurement directives and then revise procurement Circular 10/10 to encourage SME access to procurement.  The Office of Government Procurement will, with the Competition Authority, also provide information for SMEs on approaches to multi-party tendering from a competition and procurement perspective.</p><p> I am sure it will come as no surprise to Members of this House to learn that access to finance is the most difficult measure, not only for Ireland but for many other member states in the network also, on which to get a handle.  Although some of the data measuring the indicators are based on 2011 and 2012 figures, the results show Ireland is above the EU average in five of the 11 indicators dealing with issues such as the length of time it takes to get paid, the percentage of lost payments, venture capital investment, the strength of legal rights and depth of credit information index.</p> <p>The other six indicators are areas where we fall short of the EU average and include the number of rejected loans, access to public financial supports, including guarantees, willingness of banks to provide a loan, the difference in interest rates, the percentage allocation of European Union regional funds and percentage allocation of EU funds for business creation and development.</p><p>The report acknowledges the attempts made by my Department and others to address this important issue, including the introduction of the credit guarantee scheme and the establishment of Microfinance Ireland.  Support is now available to locally-traded sectors, given their crucial role in job creation.  The latest figures I have to hand show that the credit guarantee scheme has 84 live facilities in place with more than &euro;11 million available.  The credit guarantee scheme is increasing or maintaining almost 700 jobs.  According to the latest figures to hand, the Microfinance Ireland fund shows 192 jobs increased or sustained with a total approval value of more than &euro;3 million.</p><p>In 2014, through the Action Plan for Jobs, the Government is trying to further improve the access-to-finance environment for small business by expanding the activities and reach of the Credit Review Office, enhancing the take-up and impact of the credit guarantee scheme, improving the take-up and impact of loans from Microfinance Ireland and involving the National Pensions Reserve Fund and Enterprise Ireland in the developing investment opportunities aimed at small to medium-sized enterprises, SMEs.  In addition, the Government has put in place a number of measures aimed at developing new sources of finance, together with raising awareness of the supports available among the SME community.</p><p>The Commission itself supports access to finance by using financial instruments under the competitiveness and innovation framework programme.  These financial instruments include both loan guarantees and equity finance.  These instruments are implemented by the European Investment Fund via financial intermediaries in the member states.  The leverage effect of such instruments has shown that with &euro;1 billion of EU money, a further &euro;30 billion of new lending to SMEs can be leveraged.  By the end of 2012, &euro;13.2 billion in loans had been granted to more than 220,000 SMEs under the competitiveness and innovation framework programme.  The same programme has also helped venture capital funds to raise more than &euro;2 billion in venture capital.  It is important to note that 99% of SMEs benefitting from competitiveness and innovation framework programme, CIP, financial instruments are either micro or small enterprises.  The new competitiveness of enterprises and small and medium-sized enterprises, COSME, programme for 2014 to 2020 is the first ever specific programme for SMEs.  A total of 60% of the COSME budget is earmarked for financially supporting SMEs.</p><p>Ireland performs above the EU average on indicators such as the number of Single Market directives not transposed, the number of directives overdue and the average transposition delay for overdue directives.  On the skills and innovation side, Ireland ranks above the EU average on these indicators.  Ireland is particularly successful at participating in EU-funded research and in selling and purchasing online.  The areas for improvement include SMEs introducing product innovations, SMEs' collaboration and employees' participation rate in education and training.  Again, however, it is important to note that some of these indicators are based on 2008 data.  The report gives a positive welcome to the ICT skills action plan, the most recent version of which was announced by the Ministers for Education and Skills and Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation.  The Commission also acknowledged the report of the research prioritisation group, as well as the Management 4 Growth programme.   In addition, a number of training and mentoring opportunities have been identified for action in the Action Plan for Jobs.  In particular, a pilot project has just been launched by Skillnets, which seeks to develop the financial capabilities of SMEs and assist them in accessing finance.</p><p>On environmental issues, Ireland's performance is slightly better than the EU average.  Ireland's SMEs are keen to take on resource efficiency measures and offer green products or services in their own right.  Irish SMEs also have a higher proportion of their turnover being generated by green products or services.  The Commission acknowledges the publication of the Government's policy statement on growth and jobs in the green economy, namely, Delivering Our Green Potential.  Further actions emanating from this report are being dealt with under the Action Plan for Jobs 2014, including one that aims to develop an Internet resource signposting the range of supports available to Irish enterprises to help them to reduce energy, materials usage, water and waste and to develop new and innovative green products and services.  This action should help to address the one indicator in this heading where Ireland came in below the EU average.  This indicator provided details of the number of SMEs that have benefitted from public support measures for their resource efficiency actions.</p><p>The European Commission has claimed that Ireland is slightly ahead of the EU average on internationalisation issues.  We are ahead on issues such as the number of documents required to import, the time required to export and the number of documents required to export.  On the negative side, it costs slightly more to export from Ireland and the time taken to import is slightly above the EU average.  In addition, the cost required to export also is slightly above the EU average.  I am sure this is partly due to a cost competitiveness issue, in part because of the additional cost arising from the necessity to use sea and air to import and export goods.</p><p>Access to markets continues to be a key element of the Small Business Act for Europe, SBA, either within the EU or outside its borders.  The Commission has strengthened its contacts with strategic partners on SME policy including the US, China and Russia.  Such co-operation led to the memorandum of understanding on co-operation throughout the world between our business support organisations on the ground, the Enterprise Europe Network and the US international trade administration.  The Commission has also established intellectual property rights, IPR, helpdesks, including in China, to help industry but particularly to protect SME innovation.  Numerous missions for growth have been organised by Commission Vice-President Tajani, combining high-level political meetings with business matchmaking and participation of EU SMEs in commercial fairs and conferences.</p><p>The most recent meeting of the SME envoy took place on 10 March in Munich.  Issues that were discussed at this meeting included access to finance, with the discussion focusing on equity finance as an alternative to bank lending, helping SMEs to access EU framework programmes and implementation of the banking union.  As for burden reduction, more exemption and lighter requirements for SMEs were discussed, as were decreasing the burden on microenterprises, the exchange of best practices and focusing on compliance costs.  In respect of entrepreneurship, further actions on transfer of business and second chance are needed.  There is a need to promote entrepreneurship and innovation to increase productivity and create jobs.  As for access to markets, there is scope for further action in the energy markets and further actions required to help SMEs tap into global business opportunities should be continued.  In addition, new priorities were suggested such as skills, qualifications, education and training and promoting growth, as well as scaling up in terms of employment.</p><p>I believe the work of the SME envoy network and the implementation of the SBA are delivering for Ireland and for Europe.  I also wish to mention that the European Commission has started the discussion on the future of the SBA among the SME envoys.  In my opinion, the informal nature of the SME envoy network works well and this should continue.  The network should also continue to feed into the work of the informal Competitiveness Council but above all, it is important that one continues to think small first.  It is clear from both the SME envoys and the Competitiveness Council that tie four priority areas of the SBA, namely, access to finance, access to markets, reducing administrative burden and entrepreneurship, will remain the basis of the future SBA.  I acknowledge the work done to date by the SME envoy network in the important area of access to finance.  Indeed this was high on the priority of the SME envoys' work from the outset and in 2013 in particular, with the publication of SME envoys' paper and discussion, Where next for the SME Access to Finance landscape?  The Commission also hosted a seminar in Dublin during Ireland's Presidency last year, which presented the EU financial instruments to which SMEs have access from 2014 to 2020 under the COSME programme, as well as the Horizon 2020 and the European Structural Investment, ESI, funds.  In showing the importance Ireland places on SMEs, during its Presidency of the Council last year, the Government held an informal Council meeting dealing with access to finance and the internationalisation of SMEs.  The Council discussed the use of venture capital in global trading companies and the internationalisation of SMEs and the opportunities for EU enterprises in global markets, along with discussing how cities and regions are drivers of entrepreneurship and innovation.</p> <p>On the issue of access to markets and internationalisation, I acknowledge the work of the enterprise Europe network, EEN.  The EEN is a valuable network for providing information to SMEs on doing international business.  The promotion of clustering initiatives to help SMEs to internationalise and integrate into global value chains is an opportunity of which Ireland should take full advantage.  I acknowledge the work and co-operation of my fellow SME envoys throughout the SME envoy network and, in particular, the work of the EU SME envoy, Daniel Calleja Crespo, with whom I have a close professional relationship, and his colleagues in the European Commission.  However, as I have noted, we need to do more because neither the Government nor the European Commission have all the answers on how best to assist SMEs in growing and sustaining their businesses.  While the vast majority of the measures contained in the Action Plan for Jobs impact on SMEs, we would welcome Senators' thoughts on how we can better support our SMEs in accessing the supports they need to grow their business and ultimately create more jobs for our people.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="11:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300012#M00200"><p>It is a pleasure to welcome the Minister of State back to the House.  I congratulate the Government on lowering the level of unemployment to 11.8%.  It is a tremendous achievement and it proves that the Government's focus on unemployment has had a significant impact.  However, more than 250,000 people remain unemployed.  In his message for Lent the revolutionary pope, Pope Francis, warned that unjust social conditions like unemployment can lead to financial ruin and even suicide and that depriving people of the dignity of work, education and health care is a serious threat to their quality of life.  He also noted that two of the most urgent problems facing the Catholic Church are youth unemployment and the treatment of the elderly.  His key message was that it is unjust to deprive young people of jobs or to mistreat older people.</p><p>I commend the Minister of State on his passion for this issue.  I am sure he is familiar with the Fianna F&aacute;il policy paper on promoting women entrepreneurs in Ireland and fresh thinking on employment solutions, of which I am the author.  The policy paper makes ten recommendations.  I thank the Government for accepting my recommendation in regard to maternity leave.  It is not possible for a woman entrepreneur to take 28 weeks leave from her business.  For health and safety reasons a new mother is required to take six weeks' leave but I have proposed that a woman who has taken those six weeks should have the choice of allowing her partner to share her maternity leave.  Legislation to give effect to my proposal has passed Second and Committee Stages in this House and the Minister of State at the Department of Health, Deputy Kathleen Lynch, is now preparing it for Report Stage in the autumn.  I commend the Leader on his drive to secure this legislation.</p><p>The policy paper also recommends that a national office be established within Enterprise Ireland to promote women entrepreneurs, with the objective of raising the start-up rate of women entrepreneurs.  Nearly twice as many men as women start up businesses in Ireland.  We will not be utilising half of the intellectual power and creativity of the women of Ireland if we do not get them to start up as many businesses as men.  As the Minister of State knows better than anybody, new business start-ups are the most effective way of creating employment.</p><p>Since I wrote the paper last year, Ms Julie Sinnamon has been appointed as CEO of Enterprise Ireland.  My husband, Padraic White, is very proud that he offered her a job when in Enterprise Ireland when she started out as a young person.  I compliment Ms Jean O'Sullivan, who is in charge of dealing with women entrepreneurs.  She is also outstanding.  We now have a big team in Enterprise Ireland to encourage more women to start up businesses.  That is the only way to take people out of what the Pope has described as the injustice of people being unemployed and the potential for financial ruin.  Connie Doody and I started Lir Chocolates in 1986, during the last recession.  The company is currently owned by a long established German company and I remain involved as a board member.  In a competition between 200 companies over who could produce the best Easter eggs in the UK and Ireland, Lir Chocolates won first and second prizes, as well as four other prizes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1081" speakername="John Perry" time="11:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300012#M00300"><p>Well done.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="11:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300012#M00400"><p>The creativity is unbelievable and Connie and I worked together to get it started.</p><p>Another recommendation in the policy paper is that Enterprise Ireland and Bord Bia should advise women against going solo.  Making Lir Chocolates a success was incredibly demanding.  We had to go through steel walls every day but because there were two of us we were mentally able to sustain each other.  My role in the company was to create employment during the last recession.  When we started out in the 1980s the unemployment rate was 17%.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1081" speakername="John Perry" time="11:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300012#M00500"><p>It was some achievement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="11:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300012#M00600"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  Connie and I had complementary skills.  The recommendation in regard to getting women to work with other people is based on our experience.  It is a lonely station if one is working alone but when we had challenging problems we were able to talk them over.</p><p>Attitudes have improved since I was growing up, when an entrepreneur was regarded as the last career people should hope for.  Permanent, pensionable and safe jobs as teachers, civil servants or nurses were preferred.  The policy paper recommends that we should encourage people in middle management or at the midpoint of their careers in the public sector to go into the private sector.  The Clerk of the Seanad, Ms Deirdre Lane, would, for example, make a brilliant entrepreneur given all the experience she has gained from running the Seanad.  We should encourage more people to take that risk.</p><p>I was lucky when I was in secondary school that we had very good industries, one of which was Irish Ropes.</p> <p>The threat was that if one did not do well in one's leaving certificate, one would end up in the office of Irish Ropes.  </p><p>It is really important that we introduce entrepreneurial learning, which is a Fianna F&aacute;il recommendation, through the primary and secondary school system, so that we develop a real entrepreneurial culture.  I have no doubt we have changed but we still have a long way to go to get people to consider becoming self-employed and, in doing so, giving people jobs.  Some 250,000 people still do not have a job and one in four young people does not have a job.  The more people who start up businesses, the better for the future.</p><p>As I have said many times in the House, I saw with my own eyes the transformation in a young person who got and held on to a job.  The person began to walk straight, was self-confident and was smiling.  Not only was the person getting paid but the person had social interaction everyday as a result of meeting people instead of being at home lying in bed or watching television.  One man whose son had not been able to get a job for years told me he would go to mass every morning to pray that his son would be able to hold on to the job, although in later years, he went on to get a very big job in An Post.  He got experience on the ground.</p><p>I compliment the Minister of State who I know is very genuine about this and I thank him for being the envoy to the network.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1160" speakername="Michael D'Arcy" time="12:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300013#N00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State.  Is he the Irish envoy?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1081" speakername="John Perry" time="12:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300013#N00300"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1160" speakername="Michael D'Arcy" time="12:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300013#N00400"><p>I do not think that was clarified.  We must put where we are currently into context.  I think Senator White mentioned that unemployment is at 11.8%.  Much progress has been made from where we were two years ago when it was more than 15%.  In the first quarter of this year, the deficit has been reduced by &euro;1.4 billion since this time last year, which is an incredible achievement.  There has been a tax take increase year on year of &euro;633 million.  The two really important headings of income tax and VAT are both up.</p><p>That said, the really important aspect for small and medium-sized enterprises is that the public is able to purchase what those enterprises sell or create.  It is crucial, when the opportunity arises, that the Government takes it in order to give something back.  Taxes, which are all at the maximum level, including VAT, PRSI, which I consider a tax, USC and income tax, should be reduced so the public has more money in its pocket and can purchase the products small and medium-sized enterprises create.</p><p>I will focus on two aspects on which the Minister of State did not touch.  One is the benefit of examinership, which is important.  In the first quarter of 2014, 410 jobs were saved due to the benefit of examinership.  It is as important to hold on to the jobs we have as it is to create new jobs.  Yesterday on the Order of business, I mentioned the 654 jobs in Elverys.  Elverys was in examinership but as a result of a management buy-out, those jobs will be retained under certain terms and conditions.  It is important we create jobs but it is also important we do not lose jobs and take our eye off the ball.</p><p>I wish to touch on funding by the banks.  We are all dissatisfied with how the banks have been funding small and medium-sized enterprises.  It is important we start to move towards the model in other jurisdictions, in particular outside the EU - the US provides the best model - where non-bank funding is made available to companies, whether through an equity stake or another method in which non-bank funding can be put into an economic structure so that the small and medium-sized enterprises have an avenue in which to get funding.  It is something we are not good at but I know we are trying to improve on it.  I compliment the Department of Finance on its SME credit and funding newsletter, of which there have been three.  They contain a lot of information but when one speaks to small and medium-sized enterprises, they do not know about the information available on non-bank funding.</p><p>Another issue which has not had the focus required in terms of small and medium-sized enterprises, is rates.  Rates are having a detrimental impact on small businesses.  This was not an issue in the past when these businesses were more profitable and they were able to pay their rates.  Now the margins for many small businesses are being squeezed and they have great difficulty paying rates, which are not profit-driven.  I accept they cannot be profit-driven because rates are also being paid by some of the very large companies.  I am told that in County Wexford, the largest ratepayer is Tesco.  I am not here to advocate that Tesco in Wexford gets a break of any nature in what it is paying, or any other Tesco for that matter.  What I am saying is that smaller businesses employing one to five staff are badly in need of something original and inventive in regard to rates.  It is a criticism in that I am pointing out that we have not looked at this issue in an original and inventive way, which we should do.</p><p>I am reading Roy Jenkins's biography of Churchill.  When Churchill became Chancellor of the Exchequer, he got rid of all rates within six months.  The rates structure in place dates back to the 19th century and is based on the square footage of a business and the valuation of same.  It is out of date at this stage.  As I said, I am not trying to give companies such as Intel, for example, that has spent &euro;5 billion in the past number of years, which is really huge expenditure, a tax break.  It is about giving the guy in the corner shop whose margin is tight and profits are down an opportunity for a tax break of some nature, and rates are a tax.  </p><p>The last calculation I saw was that the rate collection via the local authorities was in the region of &euro;1 billion.  I do not have the staff to analyse the really large businesses, such as Apple, Google, Intel, Tesco and Dunnes Stores, and how much is paid by such businesses.  However, those very large employers have the capacity to pay more but, through their very efficient tax lawyers, they are paying less than they should.  I posed the question as to whether doing the analysis based on corporation tax should be reviewed.  The answer I got back was that it would not be reviewed, which I accept.  However, this is a method by which those very large employers could pay more.  The additional amount they pay should be given to the smaller ratepayers.  It is something at which we should look in an original and inventive way as these businesses are stretched.  I refer to those small shops which have a post office, a small deli counter and a little bit of hardware, which are very badly stretched.</p> <p>I cannot emphasise enough that this rebalancing could protect jobs in every one of those businesses the way the jobs in Elverys were protected and additional jobs could be created.  We have not taken the opportunity to do this.  Will the Minister of State conduct that analysis for the House?  I do not know how many hundreds of millions of euro are paid by large employers.  He said that 2% of all employment is provided by companies with more than 250 staff.  How much is paid by them?  If we are intent on protecting SMEs, which encompass post offices, small corner shops and so on, we need to do something on rates because, to date, nothing has been done.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" speakername="Feargal Quinn" time="12:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300014#O00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State and I am delighted he is here again.  I am also delighted with the steps he has taken and to hear about what is going on.  It was also interesting to hear Senator Mary White's story and experiences, particularly with Lir Chocolates.</p><p>I fear that the envoy network will become a talking shop.  I was president of EuroCommerce, which represents the retail, wholesale and distribution trade, for three years and a member for six years.  One of the rules I introduced was that at each board meeting we would take a break and every member had to come up with three initiatives that had been introduced in their country during the previous year.  The Minister of State might make a similar proposal at the next envoy meeting whereby each representative would come up with ten initiatives they have been taken in the previous five years that have helped SMEs to thrive.  On that basis, 28 countries with ten ideas would mean 280 ideas would be put forward.  If we picked half a dozen or a dozen of them, perhaps we could do something with them.  That would be of great benefit.</p><p>I was impressed by the proposal for a single portal for SME retail licences.  I had been talking about having one procedure on one sheet of paper or better still on the Internet to set up a business.  I would love the Minister of State to respond to this tangible idea to help create business.  According to the World Bank's cost of doing business report, in 2014, it takes four procedures and as long as ten days to start a business in Ireland.  I acknowledge the Minister of State is doing his best to change that.  I visited Panama five or six years ago where a target of only seven hours to start a new business had been set.  I do not know whether the target was reached but Singapore and New Zealand are doing well in this regard.  Four procedures and ten days is too long to set up a business and it is a disincentive to doing so.  If the process is made simpler, quicker and easier, more people will set up a business, whether they succeed or fail.  It takes one procedure and half a day to set up a business at a cost of &euro;100 in New Zealand.  That should be our target.  It should be possible to set up a business in Ireland with one procedure in one day at a low cost.</p><p>The four procedures to set up a company here are: first, the founder of a company swears before a Commissioner of Oaths; second, file necessary materials with the Companies Registration Office; third, get a company seal; and, fourth, register for corporation tax, social insurance, PAYE, PRSI and VAT with the Revenue.  These procedures could be dealt with on one sheet of paper in one location for a maximum once-off fee of, say, &euro;50.  If that was one of the Minister of State's ten suggestions at the envoy meeting, many other countries would jump at it.  This would make it very easy for a person to set up a business and to give it a try.  New Zealand has done it and we can do it as well.  Let us at least set a target of 2016 to do this.  Would the Minister of State be willing to set such a target?</p><p>The World Bank report highlighted that Ireland still has a problem when it comes to Sunday payments.  Business owners say this is a massive barrier to them taking on employees or expanding.  The Government has taken steps in this direction.  Will it ever be tackled to the extent of solving the problem?</p><p>Another issue is encouraging SMEs to use technology, particularly crowdfunding.  This has been recognised as a problem at EU level with many SMEs scared to go down that route.  I recall visiting what looked like a little shop in Estonia and upstairs the business owner had loads of people working on the Internet who were trading around Europe.  We would be able to do something in this regard if those barriers were reduced.</p><p>Businesses can benefit from cloud-based communications services such as Voice over Internet Protocol, VOIP, calls to ensure good co-operation with clients and suppliers at home and abroad.  At the same time, such technology would reduce costs for a huge range of small businesses.  How can small businesses be made aware of such opportunities?  The Minister of State should adopt more best practice from Europe regarding such technology and push it here through tax breaks and so on.  We should use the resources available in the SME envoy network.</p><p>Access to credit is a crucial issue.  Banks need to be analysed much more closely to make suer they give credit to viable businesses.  I am not sure if enough is being done to monitor whether loans are getting to the right SMEs.  I applaud the Government for setting up several microfinance schemes but for one reason or another, there has not been a large take-up and we must do something about that.  Much more needs to be done to make SMEs aware of such credit.  We need to encourage them to look beyond banks and consider crowdfunding.  Linked Finance is a great example.  I am involved in the company and, therefore, I declare my interest in it.  Businesses have to prove to customers and supporters online that they are worthy of credit.  It is interesting to observe how this works.  Unfortunately, many SMEs are not aware of the amazing credit opportunities available through Linked Finance.  It provides simple and straightforward access to finance.  If a butcher decides to build a new cold room at a cost of &euro;20,000, he can let it be known through the company.  It, in turn, lets people know that he is interested in doing this.  They offer him loans and he is able to negotiate an interest rate with them.  These loans are usually &euro;100.  If 200 people advance a loan of &euro;100, they feel like they have ownership of the shop, even though they do not, and they will give the butcher business as well.  There are win-win scenarios to be found in this area.  Crowdfunding provides simple, straightforward access to finance, which is not being used nearly enough.  It could be used much more in many different ways.</p><p>Britain is introducing a scheme to remove barriers.  The proposal is that the government makes a pledge to remove a piece of legislation for every piece of legislation it introduces that affects business.</p> <p> I would like to raise a specific example I have raised before.  The United Kingdom introduced a system called the "one-in, one-out" system, whereby if the Government introduced one measure that affected businesses, it had to remove another.  Our system is such that the burden of red tape grows every time we suggest new legislation.  I am as guilty as anybody else in this regard.  Every time one introduces new legislation, one should look back at old Acts and remove an unnecessary measure, thus reducing the burden.  That is another step that could take place.</p><p>The Minister of State's heart is in the right place and he is doing the right thing.  The envoy and network comprise a great idea and I am delighted the Minister of State is part of it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" speakername="John Gilroy" time="12:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300015#P00200"><p>The Minister of State is very welcome to the Chamber.  I read the address on stability through good governance that he delivered to the OSCE Economic and Environmental Forum some time ago and I was very impressed by it.  Most of the points made were very good.  The importance of good governance cannot be overstated.  While we have made good strides in this area recently, we still have some way to go.  Perhaps that is a conversation for another day.</p><p>I want to clarify a point Senator Mary White made.  She said one in four young people in Ireland is unemployed.  That is not quite true.  Some 60% of people are in employment, which means one in four, or 10%, of the remaining 40% is a young unemployed person.  It is very important that the message go out that it is not true that one in four people under the age of 25 is unemployed.</p><p>As the European Union becomes more important, there is a greater need for non-governmental organisations to have their voices heard.  It is often felt there is a disconnect between the EU institutions and national populations.  We hear this when canvassing for the European Parliament elections.  The SME envoy &mdash; the Minister of State is our national envoy &mdash; represents a good idea and it will help address the problem for certain sections of the community.  We should seek to extend the envoy role into other areas.  It certainly offers great potential.  A channel of communication between the SME sector and the Commission is vital.  It is vital that our SMEs exploit the opportunity the envoy mechanism affords to them.  Traditionally, Irish Governments, groups and organisations have been very good at taking advantage of opportunities afforded to them by the European Union but, as Senator Feargal Quinn stated, not all SMEs may be aware of the initiative.  Perhaps we could do a little more to promote it.</p><p>We need to embrace the initiative and encourage participation.  I cannot overstate the importance of the initiative for the SME sector.  The most important means of making it work involves ensuring everyone in the sector embraces it.  The promotion of SMEs' interests in this area is the key to success.</p><p>There are a couple points I wish to speak about today.  The importance of the SME sector is demonstrated by the fact that over 50% of the wealth created in Ireland is created by it.  The criterion associated with the envoy stipulates the employment of under 250 people.  By that definition, seven out of every ten workers in Ireland are employed in the SME sector.  The sector has a central role to play in our economic recovery but there are significant challenges.  A report produced by ISME only yesterday states retail sales for last month were down by 1.5%, which is very disappointing.  It is hardly surprising because when we drive down the high streets of any of our towns or villages we see the number of shops that have closed.  This is real evidence of the destruction wrought by the downturn.</p><p>Cashflow is one of the main problems facing the SME sector.  I was talking to an ISME representative in recent days in preparation for this debate and was informed that the organisation estimates the rate of refusal to lend to the SME sector is 54%.  This is sometimes described as constructive refusal and it has a camouflaging effect in the same way as constructive dismissal does.  Thus, the prospective borrower is blamed rather than the banks.  The Central Bank of Ireland reports that the banks' lending targets are being met so there seems to be a real disconnect between what those involved in business are saying and what the Central Bank is saying.  Perhaps the Minister of State could comment on this.</p><p>Professor Morgan Kelly, the economist, spoke rather gloomily recently about the level of debt being carried by the SME sector.  He estimates that property-related debt amounts to approximately &euro;30 billion, and that 60% of this might not be performing as well as it could be.  This is a very substantial percentage.  A resolution is very much required.  The banks are taking a piecemeal approach to this and would prefer to do deals with individual SMEs rather than take a strategic view and proceed on that basis.</p><p>Senator D'Arcy made a very good point on the saving of 450 jobs in Elverys by using the examinership process.  For SMEs employing fewer than 250 people, this process is very expensive.  It might not be the most appropriate.</p><p>I am glad to say it was at the instigation of the Minister of State that we introduced the Companies (Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill 2013.  It has been said it offers examinership-lite and represents a much more cost-effective resolution than might otherwise obtain.  Perhaps that is one of the routes SMEs could usefully go down in regard to this matter.</p><p>If Professor Morgan Kelly's figures and prognosis are correct they present a vista which, if not appalling, is not far from it.  Could we have the Minister of State's view on this?  We will certainly require the assistance of the European Union again in this matter.  The voices of the SME sector can be heard through the envoy system and network, and they will play a very important role.  We must listen to the views of those in the sector and take them on board.</p><p>While I have much more to say, I will leave it at that for the time being.  I look forward to hearing the Minister of State's views on some of the points I have raised.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="12:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300015#P00300"><p>I welcome the Minister of the State and wish him well on his appointment as SME envoy.  On going through the list of appointments across the SME envoy network, I found it rather interesting that Ireland, by way of its having appointed Minister of State, Deputy Perry, is the only state, with the exception of Malta, to have appointed an individual from a business background.  All the other appointees are civil servants attached to their relevant Ministries.  That is not a good start, to put it bluntly.  With all due respect to the permanent governments in the various countries, if one does not have a business background or experience of running a business in the hope people will spend money in it so it can continue to pay its bills and staff and remain in operation, one is at a significant loss when trying to frame solutions or proposals that will help SMEs.  As the Minister of State pointed out, more than 90% of businesses across Europe have fewer than 250 employees.  It is appalling that member states have seen fit to stay within the political establishment in making appointments.  In that regard, I applaud the appointment of Minister of State by the Government as he comes from a strong business background and has a full understanding of the importance of the SME sector.</p> <p>The other reason I am linking it is because in this country we do not have a strong entrepreneurial culture.  However, I am pleased to note that the report of the entrepreneurship forum entitled, Entrepreneurship in Ireland: Strengthening the Startup Community, published in early January, contains several recommendations which I am confident the Minister of State will take on board.  The ones I wish to single out include those under the heading of "Innovative 'Can-Do' Culture" in section two.  I will single out three of ten points which caught my attention.  First, "success is not begrudged and failure is not denigrated".  If there is any failing in the Irish psyche it is begrudgery.  An old story is told about the difference between the American attitude to entrepreneurship and the Irish attitude.  In America, when a person drives by in a big car, the immediate reaction of observers is to ask how can they get a car like that.  The Irish reaction is to question where did the person get the money to buy that car.  That is the difference and that is what is meant by begrudgery.  The sooner that begrudgery is eliminated from the Irish psyche, the better for small business enterprises and for this economy in general.  </p><p>Another aspect is that &quot;the media plays its part in highlighting the importance of entrepreneurial endeavours&quot;.  I propose that begrudgery reigns supreme across much of the Irish media, that when somebody gets into trouble in a business context, the first reaction is to hound him or her, rather than to analyse the contribution made by that person to the local, regional or national economy.  Again, the difference in America is stark where one is not deemed to be a success unless one has had two or three business failures.  In this country a business failure is regarded as showing inadequacy.  I commend the Government on its proposals to ensure that those who are declared bankrupt will not be prevented from standing for the D&aacute;il or Seanad elections in the future.  God knows, we need more, not less, business acumen and business expertise in these Houses.  If that initiative results in those who have gone through the fire of redundancies and of bankruptcy still wishing to make a contribution to the Irish nation, then they are to be applauded rather than denigrated.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" speakername="John Gilroy" time="12:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300016#Q00200"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="12:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300016#Q00300"><p>The third is that "immigrant entrepreneurs are encouraged to come to the country".  It has been proven down through the centuries that wherever shifts in population occur and people have moved to a country, those who have come as immigrants to Ireland have a strong entrepreneurial spirit.  They are rarely or never a liability on the State because they come here to work and to thrive.  If they thrive and prosper - usually in small businesses and possibly self-employed - then the country benefits.</p><p>I refer to Senator White's remarks about the education system and to the same report.  I was struck by the report's statement - about which the Minister of State will have a view - that a lack of specific entrepreneurship education modules in teacher education programmes creates challenges because most teachers lack the experience to deliver these specialised programmes.  In the view of the report's authors, teachers as well as students should receive some entrepreneurship education.  They further state that there is an immediate need to introduce modules, courses, boot camps, hackathons and start-up weekends at primary and secondary school level.  In my opinion these are very worthy and commendable proposals and I will be interested to hear any comments from the Minister of State.</p><p>I have very little time and I thank the Cathaoirleach for his indulgence.  In the context of access to credit it remains the responsibility of the banking system to provide credit to businesses.  That point should not be lost.  Senator Gilroy referred to Morgan Kelly and I had intended doing same but he has covered that aspect in his contribution.  Morgan Kelly has made a very serious commentary about the level of debt in the SME sector and what the Central Bank is doing about it.  It is a warning shot and a wake-up call.  In fairness to the Government the reaction of the Minister for Finance, Deputy Noonan, shows he has taken on board Professor Kelly's views in this regard.  Perhaps the Minister of State, Deputy Perry, will comment.  I wish him well in his very important role and one for which he is eminently suited.  He has shown in the conduct of his Ministry how he is succeeding against all the odds in a very difficult economic environment, both nationally and internationally.  He is highlighting these important issues about the need to create jobs, to sustain the economy and most important, as he and I come from the same neck of the woods, sustaining local communities.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="12:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300016#Q00400"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Perry, to the House and I welcome the creation of the SME envoy network and his nomination as our envoy.  I agree with Senator Mooney that the Minister of State is a very appropriate person to be appointed to that position.  He has many years of experience in business and has seen and experienced the many difficulties that business people encounter.  As Senator Mooney said it is regrettable that other countries have not seen fit to have nominated a person with a business background.  The Minister of State's contribution shows that he is passionate about supporting our SMEs and leveraging their potential to significantly reduce the unemployment figures.  We would not have been aware that there are 23 million SMEs in Europe and the creation of one job by all these companies would eliminate the massive unemployment problem across Europe.</p><p>The increase in the numbers at work here is very welcome but we have a long way to go.  The figures published yesterday show cause for significant hope because in 21 consecutive months there has been a drop in the number of people who are unemployed.  However, there is a long way to go.  As other speakers said, it will be the small indigenous businesses that will crack the unemployment problem.  We must do everything possible to support those small businesses.</p><p>I refer to the many innovative initiatives.  The creation of the entrepreneurship forum is a very welcome development as is the document which we received this morning and it makes some very interesting reading and makes important recommendations.  It was interesting to hear Senator Quinn speaking about a proposal that if at the next meeting all 28 countries could come up with ten good ideas.  We need people to come forward with good ideas about how the situation for small businesses can be improved.</p><p>Senator D'Arcy hit the nail on the head when he spoke about the very significant costs which are crippling small businesses, in particular, the commercial rates issue and local authority costs generally.  This issue needs to be addressed and some innovative solutions found as to how we can decouple the charging of rates to small businesses versus large multinationals.  We need to level the playing pitch.  For example, in my town a number of major multiples have located on the edge of the town and sucked the whole life out of the centre.  Small businesses are trying to compete in streets with paid parking while the large supermarkets can offer free parking in a one-stop location.  The situation is inequitable and the playing pitch needs to be made level.</p><p>Like Senator D'Arcy I welcome the hints from the Government that we will see some level of reductions in people's taxes so that they have more money to spend in the local economy.  The only thing that will kick start activity in the local economy is to have more people in the shops with more money in their pockets to spend on goods and services.</p> <p> One issue that must be examined is the competition from those who operate in the black economy, which is causing serious difficulty.  It is very difficult for legitimate operators running tight ships on low margins to compete with those providing much the same service from the backs of their houses and not paying VAT.  They can undercut legitimate operators and, in some cases, draw social welfare.  One way of getting around this problem is by every legitimate business providing a service for a customer having identification on the premises to show that it is legitimate, compliant and registered.  It would set out that people were operating legitimately.  We must also do something to encourage those operating in the black market to come into the legitimate economy, register, pay taxes and compete on a level playing field.</p><p>It is surprising that, with all of the technology available, many businesses are not fully aware of what is available through financial and information support.  I welcome the indication from the Government that we will soon have a portal that businesses will be able to access to obtain information.</p><p>I strongly support the recommendation made in the report of the entrepreneurship forum to promote entrepreneurship at an early stage through the education system.  We must teach entrepreneurship at school.  I recently attended a fine competition among local schools in my town.  Second level students at Garbally College and Ardscoil Mhuire in Ballinasloe came forward with fantastic ideas for potential start-up businesses and new products.  The level of interest and expertise young people are beginning to demonstrate must be nurtured.  They must be encouraged at an early stage to think about being able to create a job for themselves or jobs for two or three others.  There are wonderful ideas and young people have the potential to grow small businesses.  We must equip teachers in second level schools to give priority to the subjects of business and entrepreneurship.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="12:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300017#R00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State and his appointment as an SME envoy, which is most appropriate given his wide and diverse experience in business and government for the past three years, during which we have seen a significant turnaround in the fortunes of businesses.  However, it is a drop in the ocean and what we need to see are the ripple effects across the country in urban and rural areas.  There are SMEs in every parish and we need to ensure an equal spread of opportunities and their facilitation by the Government in rural Ireland, as well as in urban areas.</p><p>I note from the speech of the Minister of State that 98% of companies in Europe employ fewer than 250 people.  It is fantastic to have thousands of jobs in Intel, Facebook and Google which are extremely welcome and very important, but what will sustain and develop the economy on a long-term basis are the people creating 20, 30 or 50 jobs.  There are vast opportunities because of brand Ireland.  This is seen as a keen, environmentally friendly country, including from a tourism perspective, and our brands are unique and strong.  Brands like Ryanair and Guinness add enormously to the economy.  In sport the GAA adds enormously to our offering to those who come here.</p><p>I would like to see a significant reduction in the red tape associated with businesses.  If someone has a restaurant in the west, in Galway or Clare, a suite of requirements must be complied with to satisfy environmental health regulations, whereas a similar restaurant in the south of Spain or France does not appear to have to meet the same requirements in terms of toilet facilities and the HACCP.  Sometimes, common sense needs to prevail, as opposed to convoluted red tape, although I do not see too many people being poisoned because of poor food quality.  It does not happen on the Continent to the extent that it used to.  Common sense must, therefore, prevail and red tape must be significantly reduced.</p><p>We have seen the reform of local government in Waterford, where the city and county councils were joined to become one local authority.  There has been a significant reduction in rates as a result of the amalgamation.  This must continue to be the case and it percolate throughout the country.  Where town councils are being eliminated, reductions in the numbers of councillors, directors of services and senior managers must result in a reduction in rates which SMEs constantly describe as crippling.  A lady is opening a restaurant in Ennis and her rent is &euro;500 a week, while her rates bill is &euro;200 a week, which is bizarre.  A significant job of work needs to be done in that regard.</p><p>The Taoiseach said Ireland should be the best place in the world in which to set up a small business.  We should be world-class.  There is no reason this should not be the case, given that we have the ability, the skills set, the talent and entrepreneurial flair required.  Senator Paschal Mooney made interesting points on how we needed to drive entrepreneurial spirit within schools and universities.  Compared to where we were five years ago, we are showing much more confidence.  The position of envoy will help to ensure joined-up thinking within Europe.  If each of the 23 million SMEs could create one job, it would solve the unemployment problem in Europe.  I wish the Minister of State well.  He is the right man for the job and the results achieved are already tangible.  We will continue to see significant benefits.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="12:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300017#R00300"><p>I welcome the Minister of State and the opportunity to participate in the debate on the SME sector and the SME envoy network.</p> <p>I was part of a delegation last January from the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation.  Six of us travelled to Brussels to meet officials and several Commissioners.  We met one of the top officials who is heading up policy development for the SME sector.  He was very complimentary of steps this Government has taken to help SMEs, although obviously much more could be done. </p><p>In 2007 the European Commission launched the Small Business Act, SBA, which the Council of Ministers adopted in 2008.  This applies to all companies with staff of 250 or fewer.  The Commission states that the Act &ldquo;aims to improve the overall approach to entrepreneurship, permanently anchor the 'Think Small First' principle in policy making from regulation to public service, and to promote SMEs' growth by helping them tackle the remaining problems which hamper their development&rdquo;.  We all agree with, and aspire to, that approach and want to see action on it.</p><p>The SBA was reviewed in early 2011 and arising from this it was agreed that each member state would appoint an SME envoy working group which would work with the Commission and the EU representatives of the SME sector and the SBA advisory group.  The priority areas for the SBA following the review were making smart regulation a reality for European SMEs; paying specific attention to SMEs&rsquo; financing needs; taking a broad-based approach to enhancing market access for SMEs; helping SMEs to contribute to a resource-efficient economy; and promoting entrepreneurship, job creation and inclusive growth.</p><p>I want to dwell on key areas where SMEs need more help and Government policy needs to improve.  We have discussed legacy debt over recent months since Morgan Kelly gave a talk on its potential impact on the economy.  My party has called on the Government to direct a section of Enterprise Ireland to provide a service for SMEs before they fall off the debt cliff.  Enterprise Ireland should help these businesses to allow them separate the toxic element of their debt, normally property assets, from the functioning and profitable sections of their business.  Just as people in mortgage distress need their loans restructured, SMEs need their debt to be re-balanced or put on hold.  As long as the debt is a noose around the neck of an SME it is difficult for that business to expand and take on new people.  If this does not happen with some urgency viable businesses will continue to drown in legacy property debt, they will haemorrhage jobs and there will be a significant brake on growth.  These toxic elements resemble mortgage distress cases in that the debt needs to be restructured, written down, or parked, until the businesses can deal with it.  Uncertainty about resolution is damaging recovery.</p><p>The State needs to actively promote the growing needs of crowd funding.  The Oireachtas Joint Committee on Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation examined this by inviting experts in the field to give their view.  In the sector&rsquo;s short existence it has reduced the time it takes small enterprise to get loans and provide finance at a competitive rate.  Several crowd-fund providers have engaged in the Irish market and a State-funding partnership with one or more of these would help accelerate the sector&rsquo;s growth.  The development must, however, be monitored.  Crowd funding is innovative and exciting but unregulated.  We know that lack of regulation is a problem. </p><p>Other important issues include access to credit and opening up public procurement.  SMEs want big State contracts broken down, if possible, into small contracts that would enable them to tender for the work.  Much has been done to support SMEs but upward-only rents remain a problem, which we have debated several times in the form of Bills proposed by Senator Quinn that were not supported.  I will support any and all measures to support the SME sector because that is where the majority of jobs are now and will be created.  It is very important for our economy.  We should lend any support we can to help entrepreneurship and foster creativity, to make sure that if people have a viable business idea they get all the support they need to make that happen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1081" speakername="John Perry" time="12:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300018#S00200"><p>I welcome this very interesting debate.  I welcome Senator White's comments on my Department&rsquo;s support for entrepreneurship.  The entrepreneurship forum report to which she alluded is a very good document, which contains many elements we can implement in the one-stop shop for business that will go live in mid-April.  They are cost-effective but will provide support.  The report represents the views of entrepreneurs in Ireland after wide consultation.  It is important that it is not shelved but that we act on it.  We have also to overcome many barriers to grow and develop the ideas to create enterprises.</p><p>Senator White&rsquo;s point about women in business is very important too.  She referred to the success of Julie Sinnamon and Jean O&rsquo;Sullivan in Enterprise Ireland and mentioned Bord Bia.  Her own success is a good example.  I was recently at a big event at Enterprise Ireland where there was a strong emphasis on women in business.  Enterprise Ireland&rsquo;s sponsorship of entrepreneurship in second level schools is very successful.  We are hoping to upskill and develop that further.  Senator White&rsquo;s points are very well made and she speaks with knowledge of business.  We are considering the talent of women in business through Enterprise Ireland and Bord Bia. </p><p>In response to Senator Michael D&rsquo;Arcy, the advisory group I chair is working on priority taxation issues, which my Department will submit for budget 2015.  There is consultation on that now and the budget is being compiled to encourage enterprise.  Budget 2014 focused on SMEs and entrepreneurship and I hope this focus will continue.  My Department is working on new banking finance and the action plan for jobs refers to several initiatives.  We wish to continue to work with all relevant stakeholders and the Department of Finance to ensure opportunities in areas such as crowd-funding are available to SMEs in Ireland.</p><p>Rates are an important point for SMEs.  The Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government is conducting an overview of policy on them.  We have had discussions with the Department to explain the need for change, the fact that valuations date back to 1998 and the pressures this puts on small business.  The advisory group I chair has worked in this area and I will continue to liaise with the Department of the Environment, Heritage and Local Government.  There will be new local enterprise offices, LEOs, and the amalgamation of county and town councils will give the county manager much more discretion when councillors are appointed in June.  If rates were dropped by 1% there could be a derogation given on vacant units.  That power of devolved government will be very relevant in Sligo and Leitrim where the councillors will decide with the new CEO of the county that they can consider a derogation to encourage occupation of vacant units.  We are very conscious of the importance of encouraging the revitalisation of town and village centres.</p> <p> Senator Michael D'Arcy made the point relating to confidence and credit, and there is the issue of confidence to spend in a local community.  The point about examinership was very well made and the best example has been what happened with Elvery's this week.  With regard to funding for small and medium enterprises, there are simplified loan applications.  We met representatives of Bank of Ireland, AIB and Ulster Bank on Monday morning, and the simplified application form is applicable to the pillar banks.  Many people make a discretionary inquiry but they would be better off making a formal application.  The Credit Review Office has overturned every second loan refusal directed to the office.  I attended an event in Cork yesterday which had the Credit Review Office and up to 24 State agencies affecting business present.  Any loan application from &euro;1,000 to &euro;3 million can be reviewed, so people should go through the procedures.  The banks have indicated they are open for business so we encourage people to work in the area.</p><p>Senator Quinn commented that the small and medium enterprise, SME, network could become a talking shop.  The SME envoy, Mr. Daniel Calleja, is driven by the agenda of SMEs, and the issue has been to the forefront for the EU Presidency for a number of years.  There are 23 million SMEs across Europe and this network delivers on the formulation of ideas and sharing of best practice.  The best practice across 28 member states is invaluable, and when priority issues are identified, the network can request the issues to be progressed to formal Council meetings.  It is an important point.</p><p>I note the Senator's comments regarding company formations.  Ireland performs very well in this regard but there is always scope for progress, and I am very happy to bring up the point again.  The Senator indicated that there could be a simplification of procedures for the Companies Registration Office.  There are 159 different licences across the economy but we will establish a single licensing portal for retail trades.  There are 15 agencies and 24 licences for operating a supermarket or hotel.  A process will go to public tender through EU offices and we hope to roll it out after that.  We will consider the point about the Companies Registration Office.</p><p>I agree with the Senator's comments about ensuring small and medium enterprises maximise opportunities in areas such as crowd funding or cloud computing.  We are very active in this area and the Action Plan for Jobs and Departments are supporting and promoting initiatives for SMEs in Ireland.  The Senator has raised an important issue regarding the reduction of the administrative burden for business.  There is also the matter of apprenticeships and training young people for business.</p><p>Senator Gilroy mentioned the disconnect between institutions and I agree with the assessment of the success of the SME envoy network.  He mentioned that the SME sector in Ireland is worth over &euro;90 billion and that banks refuse up to 54% of applications in the area.  I strongly suggest that people make direct applications and appeal decisions if the loan is refused in the bank.  The Senator mentioned Mr. Morgan Kelly and the initiative is very much being taken on by the Minister for Finance, Deputy Noonan, based on evaluation of the restructuring of SME debt.  A Cabinet committee is to be set up under the Minister, Deputy Noonan, along with the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, Deputy Bruton, in that regard.  We must examine the issue of banks refusing to loan but there is money available and banks have indicated they are meeting targets.</p><p>Senator Mooney commented on the membership of the SME network.  I agree there are some very skilled people on it and some representatives of trade bodies also attend the meetings, so it is not dominated by politicians or civil servants.  All the retail and business associations across Europe attend the meetings and contribute, so it is an inclusive membership.  There was an interesting point regarding the change of culture of education in schools, which is important.  The Senator also mentioned trade agencies and Mr. Kelly's report, and the Minister for Finance is working on it.  The Senator also mentioned the importance of local communities.  There is a matter of a one-stop shop for business in every county and that is relevant in identifying an appreciation of business in the community.</p><p>Senator Mullins noted the issue of costs and rates, as well as the black economy, and that is an area which the Government is considering.  We have produced a report on the matter and we are examining the trafficking of illicit goods such as cigarettes, alcohol and other products.  The Government is determined to promote entrepreneurship in schools, and the knowledge that is out there is evident from the young entrepreneurs going to the Young Scientist event in Dublin.</p><p>I thank Senators for their positive contribution.  Senator Cullinane mentioned red tape and the regulatory burden on business.  I know he has been in Brussels and met people in the SME envoy network.  The success of Europe is the 23 million small and medium enterprises and within that the 200,000 Irish companies, employing 700,000.  There must be meaningful direct access to credit and we must cut red tape so as to support enterprise.  Local government must work with enterprise and trade and there should be a joined up network with Enterprise Ireland.  We must create jobs and confidence in the Irish economy.</p><p>We have met representatives of the banks and discussed the relevant issues.  The issue of procurement was mentioned and there is a clear policy in that regard.  There is a national procurement office and we are engaging with small and medium enterprises, particularly to see how directives can be interpreted to include the clustering of small companies to avail of over &euro;8 billion in procurement.</p><p>I hope I have not left out anybody.  There has been mention of local economies and local enterprise units.  The local enterprise offices have been rolled out and they will be very important in bringing mentoring and banking supports.  A new tool is being launched allowing a potential business owner to figure out what is required to establish a business.  Legacy debt is another problem that is being addressed by the Cabinet sub-committee on mortgage arrears and credit availability, and progress is being made in that regard.</p> <p>It is essential this work is continued, to ensure viable small businesses can look to the future and grow their businesses without being crippled by legacy debt.</p><p>I thank Senators for their positive contributions to our discussion today.  The SME network provides an important forum for member states to share best practice, prioritise issues of relevance to SMEs and ensure the small business agenda remains at the forefront of EU policy.  The development of the LEOs is important and we will have a LEO in every county in Ireland with a service level agreement to deliver a targeted suite of supports to SMEs in the local economy.  I agree with the Senator's comments regarding regulations.  Common sense is the primary element in policy making in this regard.  Senator Mooney knows only too well that we are encouraging enterprise in every village and town.  I believe that with the involvement of local government and the newly elected councils in June we will have a new forum which will have a big impact on the re-emergence and retention of jobs.  Many ideas have come forward from the Government in regard to the issues of viability and access to credit and banks, such as the Credit Review Office, the microfinance fund and loan guarantees and better procurement.  </p><p>The Government understands and respects the concerns of small businesses and will provide a service to small companies as these are the backbone of our &euro;90 billion economy.  The small business sector is the driver of this engine.  As the Taoiseach has said repeatedly, this is the year of jobs.  If we have 200,000 companies in Ireland, one job created in every company would dramatically reduce unemployment.  We have our Intreo offices, the back to work scheme and apprenticeship schemes giving significant encouragement to businesses to retain jobs.  These schemes provide support and acknowledgement of the costs of doing business.</p><p>I am conscious of the issue of commercial rates, but I am confident that the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government, Deputy Hogan, will introduce a situation similar to that in Northern Ireland, and that we will have tiered rates.  Rates have been reduced in some areas.  Ultimately, it is the customers who pay the rates as these are part of the stacked up costs of business and if one is working on a net margin of 2% or 3%, the rates are built into the cost base.  Business people who do not incorporate rates into their margins end up with them being a cost of doing business.  It is the job of the Government to ensure it gives encouragement to use vacant units and to encourage a fair system.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="13:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300020#U00200"><p>When is it proposed to sit again?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1160" speakername="Michael D'Arcy" time="13:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300020#U00300"><p>At 2.30 p.m. on Tuesday, 8 April 2014.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.141" nospeaker="true" time="13:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300020#U00400">Adjournment Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.142" nospeaker="true" time="13:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300020#U00500">Schools Building Projects Status</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="13:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300020#U00600"><p>Chuir m&eacute; an cheist seo faoi bhr&aacute;id an T&iacute; ar son dalta&iacute;, tuismitheoir&iacute; agus m&uacute;inteoir&iacute; Gaelscoil Ros Eo, Baile &Aacute;tha Cliath.</p><p>I call on the Minister to provide an update on the progress of the provision of a new school for Gaelscoil Ros Eo in Rush, County Dublin, and on whether the Department has identified a permanent site.  As the Minister of State will know, this school was approved for the 2015-16 building programme, yet it remains in temporary accommodation at St. Maur's GAA club in Rush.  This club has accommodated the growth of the school to date.  The last time I raised the issue of the Gaelscoil was on 13 January 2012.  At that stage, the school had 96 pupils in the school.  I am glad to report there are now over 133 pupils in the school.</p><p>The school would like some information regarding its position.  While it has been approved on the building list, where is the new school to be situated?  Has the Department identified a site and how quickly can the school expect movement on that issue?  I appreciate the fact the Minister of State at the Department of Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, Deputy Perry, is here to answer on this issue and I will respond in due course.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1081" speakername="John Perry" time="13:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300020#U00700"><p>I am taking this Adjournment matter on behalf of my colleague, the Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy Quinn.  I thank the Senator for raising the matter as it affords me the opportunity to outline the process used to ensure that there will be adequate accommodation in schools at primary and post-primary level to meet the demographic needs arising.</p><p>  The forward planning section of the Department of Education and Skills has carried out a study of the country to identify the areas where, due to demographic changes, there may be a requirement for significant additional school provision at both primary and post-primary levels over the coming years.  School accommodation requirements throughout the country have been considered as part of this detailed study.  The five-year school building programme, which was announced by the Minister in March 2012, provides for a &euro;2 billion school capital investment programme to 2016, of which &euro;1.5 billion is being allocated to fund major school projects.  The five-year programme prioritises major school projects in areas where future significant demographic changes have been identified.</p><p>  With regard to Gaelscoil Ros Eo, Rush, County Dublin, this school is an all-Irish co-educational school, under the patronage of An Foras P&aacute;tr&uacute;nachta, which has been operating with permanent recognition since 2011.  The school is currently located in rented accommodation which is grant-aided by the Department at St. Maur's GAA club, Rush, County Dublin.  A project to deliver a new 16-classroom school with ancillary accommodation for Gaelscoil Ros Eo was included in the five-year school building programme to proceed to construction in 2015-2016.</p><p>  The site acquisition for Gaelscoil Ros Eo is currently under way.  The Senator may be aware that the Minister for Education and Skills signed a memorandum of understanding between his Department and the County and City Managers' Association in 2012.  This memorandum fosters increased levels of co-operation and formalises the part of local authorities in identifying and securing suitable sites for educational use.  In that context, the Department of Education and Skills is working closely with Fingal County Council in regard to identifying and acquiring a suitable site for a new school building for Gaelscoil Ros Eo.  This process is ongoing.  Therefore, due to the commercial sensitivities associated with land acquisitions generally, it is not possible to provide further information at this time.</p><p>  Once the acquisition of a suitable site is concluded, subject to no issues arising, a design team will be appointed and the project will proceed to tender and construction thereafter.  Information in respect of the current school building programme, along with all assessed applications for major capital works, including the project for Gaelscoil Ros Eo, is available on the Department's website at <i>education.ie.  </i>I thank the Senator again for giving me the opportunity to outline to the Seanad the current position regarding Gaelscoil Ros Eo.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="13:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300020#U00800"><p>Gabhaim bu&iacute;ochas leis an Aire St&aacute;it as ucht a fhreagra.  T&aacute; d&iacute;om&aacute; orm &aacute;fach mar go bhfuil c&uacute;pla ceist agam f&oacute;s.  Is  the Minister of State satisfied that the school is still on line for construction in 2015-2016?  This is crucial.  I understand the process and appreciate the fact the Minister of State has taken the time to come to the House.  The reply to my question however has been pretty general and could probably be applied to almost any school on the building programme list.  I will take the matter up further with Fingal County Council, because contrary to what was stated in the response, I understand there is no contact with Fingal County Council on the issue currently and that is our concern.  I ask the Minister of State to bring this message back to the Department of Education and Skills.  I will do the same.</p><p>This school is an excellent, popular and growing school.  We were all delighted when it was included in the five-year programme, but it appears we have now hit a brick wall.  At least the response provided today gives us something to work on and I appreciate the Minister of State's presentation of it.  I will seek clarification from the Department as to whether it believes the Gaelscoil is still on course to be built in 2015-2016.  I would also like to know what contact there has been with Fingal County Council on this issue, because I understand there has been no contact in recent times.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1081" speakername="John Perry" time="13:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014040300021#V00100"><p>The Minister's reply was clear and the information in it positive.  I suggest the Senator engage directly with Fingal County Council.  It is impossible to indicate the possible location of the site but the Minister has said very clearly that once the site has been identified, the Department will appoint a design team.  I suggest the Senator contact the Minister's office directly on this so he can clarify who the contact person in Fingal County Council is.</p><p>Officials in the Department of Education and Skills strive to achieve best value for money on land acquisitions.  Once the site acquisition process has been completed the school authority will be informed.  We should move in that area.  The Department has published technical guidance documents on the identification and suitability assessment of sites for primary schools which set out the criteria to be used in assessing potential school sites.  These guidance documents recommend that as part of the evaluation of site suitability a number of factors be taken into account including zoning, existing services, site orientation, topography, transport and access.  Working in conjunction with the relevant local authority, the Department uses its in-house staff.  I suggest the Senator arranges a meeting with the Department officials and Fingal County Council, who may be able to move that issue forward for him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-03a.147" nospeaker="true" time="13:25:00" ><p>The Seanad adjourned at 1.52 p.m. until 2.30 p.m on Tuesday, 8 April 2014.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>