<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.4" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#A00100">Gnó an tSeanaid - Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#A00200"><p>I have notice from Senator Kevin Humphreys that he proposes to raise the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government to introduce a scheme to address legacy building deficiencies in apartment blocks, similar to the repair scheme he has put in place to support homes affected by pyrite and mica.</blockquote> <p>The matter raised by the Senator is suitable for discussion and it may be taken now.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.7" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#A00300">Nithe i dtosach suíonna - Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.8" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#A00350">Defective Building Materials</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#A00400"><p>I thank the Chair for selecting this Commencement matter, because it is very important for up to 100,000 apartment owners who are affected by structural defects caused by light-touch regulation and ineffective building controls during the 2000s.  These people purchased their apartments on the understanding they were fit for purpose and, unfortunately, as we see now, they are not, and it is going to cost thousands of euro to repair them.</p> <p>I very much welcome the pyrite and mica proposals that will assist homeowners who have bought houses affected by pyrite or mica.  Why, therefore, is there discrimination against apartment owners and why has there been no assistance whatsoever in resolving the latent defects and the legacy issues caused by light-touch regulation under previous Administrations?  This problem stretches from Blanchardstown to Cork, from Galway to Dublin, from the Beacon centre in Sandyford to the docklands area in the middle of Dublin city.  Residents purchased their starter home and are not able to move on because the money is not in the management company funds to carry out these repairs.</p> <p>Will the Minister of State, Deputy English, explain why there is one set of rules for one and not for the other?  While I welcome that homeowners whose houses have pyrite or mica are being assisted, I want to know from the Minister of State why the Government is treating two sets of citizens differently.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1264" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#A00500"><p>I thank Senator Humphreys for raising this important issue.  At the outset, I acknowledge the very distressing and stressful circumstances which the owners and residents of buildings face where building defects emerge.  In general, building defects are matters for resolution between the contracting parties involved - the homeowner, the builder, the developer and-or their respective insurers, structural guarantee or warranty scheme.  While my Department has overall responsibility for establishing and maintaining an effective regulatory framework for building standards and building control, it has no general statutory role in resolving defects in privately owned buildings, including dwellings, nor does it have a budget for such matters.</p> <p>Primary responsibility for compliance with the requirements of the building regulations rests with the owners, designers and builders of buildings.  When a building is constructed and occupied, statutory responsibility for safety is assigned by section 18(2) of the Fire Services Acts 1981 and 2003, to the "person having control" of the building.  The person having control is required to take reasonable measures to guard against the outbreak of fire and to ensure the safety of persons in the event of fire.  In multi-unit developments, the person having control is generally the owner management company.  Under the Multi-Unit Developments Act 2011, which is under the remit of the Minister for Justice and Equality, the owner management company must establish a scheme for annual service charges and a sinking fund for spending on refurbishment, improvement or maintenance of a non-recurring nature of the multi-unit development.</p> <p>It should be noted that, in terms of addressing fire safety issues, my Department published a framework for enhancing fire safety in dwellings where concerns arise in 2017.  This framework is a guide for the owners and occupants of dwellings where fire safety deficiencies have been identified or are a cause for concern.  It is generally this area where issues have been raised with Departments.  It includes a range of actions that may reduce risk and improve the level of fire safety where deficiencies arise in dwelling houses, apartments or the common areas of apartment buildings.</p> <p>Furthermore, in the aftermath of the Grenfell Tower tragedy in June 2017 and in recognition of fears expressed for fire safety, my Department&rsquo;s national directorate for fire and emergency management was asked to convene a task force to lead a reappraisal of our approach to fire safety in Ireland.  In its report, the task force acknowledges the importance of fire safety in apartment buildings.  It makes a number of recommendations focusing on fire detection and alarm systems, evacuation arrangements, and prioritising life safety.  The directorate&rsquo;s management board has been tasked with implementation of the recommendations within its remit and oversight of the implementation of the remaining recommendations.</p> <p>It is not possible for the State to take on responsibility or liability for all legacy issues of defective building materials or workmanship, nor would it send the right message to the industry regarding its responsibility for compliance.  As the Senator said, part of the issue is that there are over 200,000 apartments in total.  As the Minister, Deputy Murphy, has noted previously in the D&aacute;il, there is no way of knowing what the exposure to the taxpayer would be if the Department took on responsibility in this regard.  It is quite clear who the responsibility lies with.  This is a private situation and that is how it is.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Damien English:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1781"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1781&amp;amp;pid=DamienEnglishFG&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The task force has also been involved with the fire safety aspect, and this is certainly an area where we are working with apartment owners to try to find a resolution.</p><p>Such interventions by the State have been limited to very particular circumstances and that is as it should be because of potential exposure of the taxpayer.  There has been an issue with pyrite in Dublin and north Leinster.  Approximately 1,200 houses have been fixed but approximately 700 or 800 have had problems identified that must be looked at.  There are approximately 300 or 400 houses affected by mica in Mayo, with approximately 1,200 houses affected in Donegal, although there is potential for 2,000 or 3,000 to be affected on top of that as well.  Those are the rough numbers.  In both those cases, expert panels were set up to examine the problems.  In a similar fashion to the task force on apartments, different recommendations have been made.</p><p>Finally, in response to the building failures that have emerged over the last decade, my Department has advanced a robust and focused building control reform agenda.  That happened since 2014 and was one of the major changes made under the Fine Gael-Labour Party Government, as we recognised there were failings in the area in the years before.  There were amendments to the building control regulations, the establishment of a shared services national building control project and the ongoing development of new legislation through the Building Control (Construction Industry Register Ireland) Bill 2017.  These reforms have already brought and will continue to bring a new order and discipline to bear on construction projects, creating an enhanced culture of compliance with the building regulations.  I hope that in future we will not see a repeat of what happened in the past.  There are far too many defective properties out there, as we are aware.  I understand why the matter has been raised and the difficulties being experienced by people.  I hope this brings some clarity on where or how we can intervene, and we do that when we can.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#B00200"><p>Perhaps the Minister of State might arrange a meeting with me as various options could help apartment owners in the short term to access money at low interest rates, and these have not been given due consideration.  There is an all-party recommendation on redress that was made in 2017 but there has been no progress in that regard.  The Minister of State's response is a little hypocritical.  He has said responsibility and liability for legacy issues and defects will not be addressed because of numbers, as it is possible that 70,000 to 100,000 apartments will have such legacy issues.  The Government will not deal with them as a result.  If a person is in Donegal or Mayo and there are only 300 such properties, the Government will give a dig-out.  All our citizens must be dealt with equally and honestly.  This is not happening.</p> <p>I could read quote after quote from Ministers about the mica problem.  I welcome efforts to remediate the mica problems but apartment owners are not being addressed with the same sense of fairness.  What is the difference between a redress process for problems arising from pyrite and mica and one for an apartment owner who purchased the property as a family home and who is now left high and dry?  One group of citizens in the country is to be dealt with in one manner while the apartment owners will be dealt with differently.  That is unacceptable.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1264" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#B00300"><p>I cannot be much clearer on this.  Difficulties arising from pyrite and mica are different from difficulties with apartments.  The key issue is defective material versus defective workmanship.  In the case of pyrite and mica, the houses will become uninhabitable.  These are very different circumstances.  Expert groups and panels were set up in both cases for a number of years.  The pyrite matter took approximately seven or eight years and we were a little quicker in dealing with mica.  In both cases, expert panels considered how best to intervene to help people who lived in these houses.  A house with mica or pyrite will eventually become uninhabitable, and that is the bottom line.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#B00400"><p>People will eventually be unable to live in these apartments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1264" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#B00500"><p>We have also looked at apartments and a task force made recommendations.  In all cases when the evidence is gathered and examined, we act on recommendations.  That happened with pyrite, mica and problems with apartments.  The Minister, Deputy Eoghan Murphy, has been very clear on this in the D&aacute;il.  I am happy to meet the Senator to discuss options and I have met others to try to discuss the potential solutions.  If there are solutions that can be worked with and are quantifiable, we will consider them.  The potential exposure to the taxpayer is an issue and there is also the matter of who is responsible.  This is about workmanship and not materials.  These were private rather than State contracts.  The problems with pyrite and mica arise from the materials used, which is a different issue.</p> <p>I am happy to meet the Senator and discuss this.  There is no point shouting or roaring and there is no need for it.  I am happy to sit down with him and go through this.  The Minister has again been clear that we are happy to work with management groups and apartment owners to try to find solutions.  We recognise the difficulties and the first thing to be done is to make apartments safe from a fire safety perspective.  That is the priority and the main issue for most apartment owners.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#B00600"><p>The Minister of State has, quite fairly, committed to meet Senator Humphreys and that should be taken up.  I am quite sure that before the year is out, if we are still here - we may well be - Senator Humphreys will not let the matter go.  I thank both the Minister of State and the Senator for their co-operation.  As we had a paucity of matters to be discussed on the Commencement today, my task of choosing this matter was easy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.17" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 10.45 a.m. and resumed at 11.30 a.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.18" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#G00100">An tOrd Gnó - Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#G00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, motion of referral to Joint Committee on Justice and Equality of Regulation (EU) 2018/1727 of the European Parliament and the Council of 14 November 2018 on the European Union Agency for Criminal Justice Cooperation, EuroJust, to replace and repeal Council Decision 2002/187/JHA, to be taken without debate at the conclusion of the Order of Business; No. 2, motion re Sectoral Employment Order (Electrical Contracting Sector) 2019, back from committee, to be taken without debate at the conclusion of No. 1; No. 3, Private Members' business, Farm Safety Agency Bill 2018 - Second Stage, to be taken at 12.45 p.m., with the time allocated for the debate not to exceed two hours; No. 4, Gaming and Lotteries (Amendment) Bill 2019 - Committee Stage, to be taken at 3.30 p.m.; and No. 83, non-Government motion No. 9 re mental health services, to be taken at the conclusion of No. 4, with the time allocated for the debate not to exceed two hours.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#G00300"><p>I would like to raise two issues, the first of which is about the elections.  Like many other colleagues in this House, over the weekend I was involved in tallying and adjudicating on spoiled votes.  What we have learned is that there were record numbers of spoiled votes in the European Parliament elections, while there were many spoiled votes in the local elections.  Obviously, we all have a right to spoil our vote, but from what I viewed - I saw that many had written the word "Yes" or an "X" - people do not know how to vote.  We all think it is straightforward and simple, but many people simply do not know what to do.  It is incumbent on the Government, therefore, to ensure an education programme is put in place prior to the next election.  Perhaps the Electoral Commission might place advertisements showing people how to vote.  It is a real pity that there were thousands of spoiled votes across the country and the people concerned probably did not know that they had spoiled their votes.  It is very unfair and undemocratic not to show people how to vote.</p> <p>The second issue I would like to raise is related to services for young people, not just for those on the autism disorder spectrum but also for young people with mental health issues.  We know that the number on the waiting list for child and adolescent mental health services, CAMHS, has jumped by 6%.  At the end of March, the number on the waiting list was 2,738.  When we consider what has happened in the case of speech and language therapy services, as well as other therapies, we know that the allocation of money actually works.  In 2016 when an extra &euro;4 million was allocated for speech and language therapy services, the number on the waiting list reduced by 10%.  We need more than &euro;4 million as there are 7,000 waiting to be assessed for speech and language therapy services and 11,444 to receive them.  These are huge figures.  These kids are our future and, as we all know, early intervention is critical.  In the scheme of things and particularly when we consider the amount of money to be spent on the national children's hospital and under the broadband plan, &euro;4 million is a pittance.  If extra money can help to make a dent in the waiting list, let us give it because this is where it matters and there would be a positive impact.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#G00400"><p>The counts in the local elections have now been completed and 949 county councillors elected.  I salute them because it takes courage to put one's name on a ballot paper, no matter what party one chooses to represent or whether one runs as an Independent candidate.  We have learned something from the local and European Parliament elections and the referendum.  We must acknowledge that voter turnout, at 50.2%, was disappointing and is an issue of concern for democrats and those who engage in the political system and process.  As Senator Ardagh said, we need to consider not only educating the electorate but also assisting and supporting it.  We cannot shy away from the fact that many people are disengaging from the political process.  We must ask ourselves why that is the case and they do not think it is relevant to vote in local authority elections, a referendum or European Parliament elections.  There are serious questions that we, as politicians, need to ask in that regard.</p> <p>We also saw that electoral registers were in a mess.  Yesterday we heard that people's names had been removed from them.  I spoke to a person living in a row of terraced houses - Nos. 8, 9 and 10 - and all of the people living in multistorey flats had had their names removed from the electoral register.  They were gravely disappointed and angry.  </p> <p>The counts started on Saturday at 9 a.m. and some were only completed last night.  That is not an efficient way to count votes.  It is unfair and we need to learn from it.  There are many issues that we need to address in the administration and running of elections.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Victor Boyhan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2463"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2463&amp;amp;pid=VictorBoyhan&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This is timely, and I hope we can have a speedier roll-out of the details of the proposed independent electoral commission.  It is important work, and we should not delay it.  I, therefore, ask the Leader to ask or arrange for the Minister of State with responsibility for electoral reform and local government - he has both briefs - to come before the House for an engagement and a discussion on this.  We all have our own unique experiences of what is happening on the ground, and we need to consider this.  Clearly, in legislative terms, it is important that the independent electoral reform commission be engaged.  I again remind Members that legislation can be initiated in this House.  If this means spending longer days and nights and more time in the House doing legislative work, let us do it.  We have the willingness and the commitment to do so, and we might have more expertise on this legislation, given our electorate, than Deputies.  I, therefore, ask the Leader to consider having a discussion with the Minister of State to see whether we can progress this legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#H00200"><p><i>The Kildare Nationalist</i>on 14 May 2001 carried an article that stated, &quot;Widespread availability of drugs in rural Ireland is one of the most frightening developments of recent years.&quot;  That was 19 years ago.  Since then, availability has increased, and now I sincerely believe the supply and use of drugs in rural Ireland has become an epidemic.  When I say &quot;rural Ireland&quot;, I do not just mean the major towns in the counties; I mean a penetration right into rural areas.  In most pubs in rural Ireland one will find some kind of drug activity.  This is of enormous concern.  The reason I believe this is happening is that there are far too few drugs arrests in rural Ireland and, when arrests are made, the sanctions are too lenient, with people often just getting off with supplying drugs.  There are various reasons this happens.  Cocaine is the drug of choice.  Instead of people going into a pub and having a couple of vodka and tonics, a glass of wine, a couple of pints or whatever it may be, they fill up on cocaine at the weekends.  It is a serious problem for young people, older people and parents.  We have spent more than 100 hours on the Judicial Appointments Commission Bill in this House but these are the types of issues we need to discuss.  I want the Minister for Justice and Equality to come before the House to discuss rural crime and the drugs aspect to it.</p><p>On the wider issue of rural crime, I commend my colleague, Deputy &Oacute; Laoghaire, who produced a document on tackling rural crime.  As he states in the document, people deserve to be safe in their communities but, unfortunately, in recent times, due to the reduction in Garda visibility and increases in certain crimes, many do not and they feel isolated and vulnerable.  We need to tackle crime in rural areas, but the cutbacks in policing and Garda numbers, stations and resources mean that families and elderly people feel isolated and in danger.  Deputy &Oacute; Laoghaire has come up with a number of recommendations to tackle rural crime, including an increase in the number serving in the force to more than 16,000; a request for 550 civilian staff per annum to free garda&iacute; from office work; a reform of the joint policing committees, JPCs, to give them more powers to give local communities more influence on policing; the putting in place of restorative justice schemes; and access to broadband in all Garda stations.  There are many recommendations in the document.  I ask that the Minister come before the House to discuss the issue of rural crime and drugs in rural Ireland in a meaningful way.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#H00300"><p>Before Senator Higgins commences, I wish in one sense to commiserate with her but also to acknowledge her huge courage in going for election and taking on the European challenge.  She is a very brave woman, even though she did not get over the line.  I know what defeat tastes like.  I ran for the D&aacute;il seven times.  Beidh l&aacute; eile aici.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#H00400"><p>Go raibh maith agat.  At least I have the opportunity to continue as a European parliamentarian in the Seanad, if not in the European Parliament.  I thank the Cathaoirleach very much for his kind thoughts.  I am very happy to be still in this House and to be able to use this Chamber.</p> <p>I agree with the sentiments expressed by Senator Ardagh, who raised concerns about spoiled votes.  They would not have affected my results, but there was clear confusion among many voters.  In addition, issues with the EP1 form denied many European citizens from other European countries who live here in Ireland their vote.  The case for an electoral commission has never been clearer.</p> <p>I also refer to the issuing of licences to drill off the south coast - drilling which, as we know, is happening this week, even in the wake of a green wave and the declaration of a climate emergency.  The former Minister, Deputy Naughten, has made it clear that he believes there should be a cessation of the issuing of licences.  During my travels in recent weeks, I had the opportunity to sit on panels with a number of members of the current and former Governments who were grilled and questioned about their decisions regarding the issuing of oil exploration licences or the expansion of oil and gas exploration.  The responses often rang very hollow, but however hollow they were, they will be nothing compared with the justification by anyone in this Government, in some future room, in response to some question from his or her constituents, of the decision to continue with, and to expand drilling, after what we know now.  Frankly, there will be no justification.  Deputy Naughten is rightly coming out to say we need to hold off and stop these licences because he knows they are not justifiable, and every member of this Government and all those who agree to these decisions will have to stand over the indefensible.</p> <p>I have previously stated the issues of biodiversity and climate change are linked, and this is one of the clearest examples of how a divide-and-conquer approach can be used to set us backwards.  As I understand it, in deciding to issue the licence to drill, no climate assessment was carried out; there was simply an assessment of the impact on the marine biology of the Porcupine Basin.  Of course the significant impact on marine biology is bad, but it was not considered bad enough to delay drilling.  Climate impact will be assessed later, when extraction begins, but of course the environmental damage will have been done by then.  It is very simple.  In making a decision about oil and gas exploration, the obvious answer should be "No", but if one proceeds, an environmental assessment should assess both the ecology and the climate impact at every stage.  I say this as someone who is very passionate about these issues, as the House will be aware.  These will be debating points in the future, and I urge the Leader to convey to the Government at this point that it is not too late for it to reconsider these options.  Let us not double down on this.  As Deputy Naughten said, we know that the arguments regarding our resilience and our vulnerability no longer stand up.  Let us take action on this.  It is a small action to take and an opportunity to send a signal this week that the Government has listened to the people.</p> <p>I thank the Cathaoirleach for his kind words.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" speakername="Gabrielle McFadden" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#H00500"><p>I would like to raise the issue of funding for the various community healthcare organisations, CHOs.  I would like us to ask the Minister for Health to come before the House to have a debate on this.  I myself live in CHO 8, which includes Laois, Offaly, Longford, Westmeath, Louth and Meath.  Recently I have constantly been told there is not enough funding for CHO 8 and that it has less funding than other CHOs.  I would like to know how this funding is determined and worked out.  I acknowledge there is no additional money for disability services.  I know of a case of a young man with a disability who is in an acute bed in Tullamore hospital.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Gabrielle McFadden:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2399"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2399&amp;amp;pid=GabrielleMcFadden&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->They say that this is costing approximately &euro;1,000 per day.  I know there is a service elsewhere available for that chap for about &euro;110,000 per year but the funding is not there.  There is something fundamentally wrong if we can pay &euro;1,000 per day on one side but cannot pay &euro;110,000 per year on the other side.  How is this all determined?  It is appropriate that we ask the Minister for Health to come to the House to debate the issue with, explain it to us and hear from the different CHOs about how it is affecting our constituents.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#J00200"><p>We all know well that the life of a farmer is a tough one.  Farmers work long hours, many work seven days a week, and much of that time is spent working on their own.  The HSE recently conducted a survey, on which I compliment it, on farmers' health generally.  It conducted a pilot scheme in livestock marts throughout the country.  The findings are very worrying.  Farmers are more inclined to suffer from stress, social exclusion and isolation.  They are also more susceptible to cancer and heart conditions.  Clearly, there is help available but, unfortunately, many farmers are unaware of it.  It would be very worthwhile to ask the Minister for Health and, at some future point, the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine to come to the House to debate this subject.  It is very worrying that the farming community and farmers are susceptible to serious mental and physical health issues.  I would welcome it if the Leader organised a debate on this at the earliest opportunity so we can clearly outline to the farming community what benefits and help are available to it and so we can identify shortcomings in the system so that we can rectify them so that help will be available to all members of our farming community who work very hard and put in many hours every day, seven days a week, with much of that time being spent on their own.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#J00300"><p>I propose an amendment to the Order to Business, that No. 4, Gaming and Lotteries (Amendment) Bill 2019 - Committee Stage, be adjourned at 5 p.m. and that No. 83, motion 9, which is Private Members' business, be taken at that stage.  This is just to give certainty and clarity to those who wish to speak on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#J00400"><p>What is the Senator referring to?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#J00500"><p>No. 83, motion 9, which is Private Members' business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#J00600"><p>What is it that the Senator wants clarity and certainty about?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#J00700"><p>I want clarity so that people who wish to engage in that debate will have certainty about the starting time.  Last night, the Taoiseach uttered the famous words that many a football manager has been awarded, namely, "I have full confidence".  He has full confidence in the Minister of State at the Department of Defence, yet the Defence Forces are falling apart.  The Taoiseach threw out a figure of &euro;50 million yesterday that was being invested by the Defence Forces in buying ships, aircraft and hardware with some for pay.  The Taoiseach needs to take responsibility for the Department he awarded himself.  He is the Minister for Defence, the de facto Minister for Defence, and he cannot abdicate that responsibility to a junior Minister no matter how much he would like to.</p> <p>Tomorrow morning at 9.30, the Representative Association of Commissioned Officers, RACO, will appear before the Oireachtas Committee on Foreign Affairs and Trade, and Defence, and it will put forward the situation as it stands.  Nobody likes hearing every day of the week about the problems of the Defence Forces but yesterday was an onslaught in all of the media.  A retired brigadier general discussed the current situation, the wife of a soldier discussed a situation, while a brave young commandant threw his Sam Brown on the table and said he wants no more.  The Taoiseach needs to step up to the plate.  It is his Department, not that of the Minister of State, Deputy Kehoe.</p> <p>My colleague, Senator Ardagh, addressed the issue of speech therapy.  It is important that we bring the Minister for Health to this House to discuss speech therapy because I am being told that instead of delivering speech therapy on a one-to-one basis with children, we are delivering speech therapy practice or theory to teachers and special needs assistants and asking them to deliver the actual speech therapy to children.  It is a highly specialised game, not something that we should try to amateurise, so to speak, over time.  The Minister should come to the House to discuss the matter, which I thank Senator Ardagh for raising.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1380" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#J00800"><p>I would like to raise an issue I raised previously regarding Dublin Port.  We have seen how the port will either limit or stop tourist cruise ships from coming into the port.  This is because of space at Dublin Port.  It is worse than that, and we need the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Ross, to come to the House to discuss Dublin Port.  The port does not start loading lorries until 6.30 a.m. to 7 a.m. and finishes at 6 p.m.  It is possible to go into any of the English ports like Liverpool or Manchester and load a container at any hour of the day, any day of the week.  This is not the case in Dublin, which starts at 6.30 a.m and closes at 6 p.m.  On Saturday, it operates from about 8 a.m. to noon while no work is done on a Sunday.  This country might be facing a hard Brexit in the not too distant future.  We have a port that is in crisis.  As a matter of urgency, the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport must address this issue.  There is no reason Dublin Port should not operate around the clock.  It would have many benefits for this city from the point of view of traffic.  When the lorries are loaded at 7 a.m., they go straight onto the M50, so they are clogging up the M50 during the day, whereas if these lorries were loaded at night-time, it would have a major benefit in terms of traffic in Dublin city because the traffic would be moving into the port and onto the M50 after 7 p.m. or 8 p.m.  I ask that the Minister would come to the House to discuss Dublin Port.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#J00900"><p>Last week, on the Order of Business, Senator Mullen raised issues arising from an unnecessary abortion that took place in a Dublin hospital.  He spoke in a modulated and reasonable voice and his tone was perfectly appropriate but he was heckled and barracked in a concerted fashion until he had to stop.  He was told among other things that it was disgraceful that he was raising issues arising from a tragedy, but we all do that.  We do it in the wake of tsunamis, the murder of families and so on.  I do not agree with Senator Mullen's views on many issues, including abortion, but it is very important that a voice like Senator Mullen's be heard in this House and heard with respect, unless and until he makes, as he sometimes does, inflammatory comments.  Then it is fine to go after him, but to try to stop somebody speaking in this House is quite wrong.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#J01000"><p>I think I did my utmost on that occasion to defend Senator Mullen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#J01100"><p>The Cathaoirleach certainly did.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#J01200"><p>I have a toss of a coin between Senators &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh and Mullen but seeing as Senator Mullen is in the limelight, we will let him go first.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#J01300"><p>I thank Senator Norris for what he just said.  As I mentioned last week, I did not ask it for myself.  I am well able to defend myself but I think there is an issue about where public discourse is going.  We must set an example in here.  I acknowledge that the Cathaoirleach chaired that incident very properly.</p> <p>I second Senator Craughwell's amendment to the Order of Business.  I do so in the context of the motion I brought forward on the important issue of mental health, which was kindly supported by Senator Norris, a number of other Independent Senators and, I am sure, some party people as well.  Generally speaking, it is better for the running of our business if we know when debates begin and end, not least when, as I expect today, people may be coming from outside to listen to debates, as I understand there may be.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2250"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2250&amp;amp;pid=RonanMullen&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I would be grateful if the Leader would accept that proposed amendment to the Order of Business, which I second.</p><p>In regard to what was said earlier by a number of Senators, including Senator Boyhan, about the confusion in the voting at last weekend's elections, the remarkable thing was not so much the confusion about voting, although that continues to be a problem, but the confusion about counting.  I was and am astounded that, at this point in our democracy, we found ourselves with an imbroglio such as arose in the context of the counting of the European election votes.  It is not merely out of possible future or other-world self-interest that I think we would probably be served better by having one constituency for the entire island of Ireland because we have unrealistically drawn boundaries based on seat allocations that might not, in fact, come to pass.</p><p>The most important point is that if three people from a particular constituency are competing to go to Brussels now, the quota should reflect that and, if necessary, there ought to be a parallel counting of votes, whereby one would be on the basis of the fact that three candidates will be elected, and where there is an additional candidate to be elected, as is the case in Dublin, there would be a separate counting of the votes - this would not involve the same amount of work again - on the basis that there are four candidates, because, as we know, it could produce two completely different results.  There could be a situation under a quota for three seats where one person would be elected whereas, under a quota for four seats, a person who might have been elected under the quota for three might not get elected at all under the other quota.  No matter which way we went yesterday, we were doomed to possible inaccuracy, and that has to do with the question of the distribution of surpluses.  It is an issue we need to look at.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1431" speakername="P&aacute;draig &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#K00200"><p>T&aacute; d&iacute;reach c&uacute;pla pointe agam.  I strongly support my colleague, Senator Craughwell, on his points in regard to the members of &Oacute;glaigh na h&Eacute;ireann and the work they do in protecting our people and our country, which, unfortunately, is very undervalued.  We are having a huge issue because, with unemployment at just above 5.2%, it is very difficult to keep them and we need those people.  We never see 99% of their work and it is only when we have floods around the midlands that we see what these people do.  They are protecting our seas and our country.  I am very proud we have those people doing what they do for us.  Well done to the Senator and long may he keep that flag flying.  Go raibh maith aige.</p> <p>Inniu t&aacute;im ag iarraidh labhairt leis an Teach seo mar gheall ar "shadow banking".  Has the House ever heard of shadow banking, which is a major issue?  In fact, it could be the single biggest reason that this world goes into another recession.  We do not have figures for this in Ireland, the UK or Europe.  In the US, however, the traditional, normal commercial banks that we are used to have a turnover of in the region of $12 trillion per year, whereas shadow banking has in the region of $18 trillion per year, or about 50% more.  I ask the Leader to ask the Minister to come to the House to talk to us about shadow banking and explain it to us because the public need to know and they are not aware of it.</p> <p>The traditional, normal banks are regulated by the central bank in all countries.  Regulation means there is a safety net for the public - for people who have loans and people who pay in deposits.  Shadow banking is, by and large, totally unregulated.  In the US, and it is probably similar in Europe, shadow banking is 50% larger than traditional banking, so the unregulated sector is 50% larger than the regulated.</p> <p>I will give a straightforward example of how one key part of shadow banking operates.  Let us say a person goes for a loan of &euro;200,000 to buy an apartment and, although the person will not get an apartment in Dublin or Galway for that amount, there are some places where they might where people are leaving rural Ireland.  The person goes to the bank, which says it will give a loan and will charge the person 6% interest, and that is regulated.  If the person goes to an unregulated bank and asks for a loan, it will give the loan at 4.5% or 5% interest.  Why can it do it cheaper?  It is because regulation costs money.  It is probably making the same profit, if not more.  What happens?  The person goes with whoever they get the best deal from.  What does the shadow bank do?  It has a couple of thousand people, like the Leader and myself, who get these loans, it bundles the loans and it sells them on.  There are good loans and bad loans.  Does that remind anyone of the recession, and of Freddie Mac and Fannie Mae?  That is exactly what happened.  An organisation like Lehman Brothers was totally unregulated.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#K00300"><p>Time, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1431" speakername="P&aacute;draig &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#K00400"><p>I am sorry about the time.  This is very important for our economy and our people.  Will the Leader ask the Minister to come to the House to give us an outline of shadow banking in Ireland?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#K00500"><p>Unfortunately, while it is an interesting tale, I have to abide by the time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1431" speakername="P&aacute;draig &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#K00600"><p>That is just one small element and there is a lot more to it than that.  I understand the constraints on time but I would explain it a bit more if I could.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#K00700"><p>The beauty of this Chamber is that so many varied topics are raised by various people, many of them very interesting.  Long may that openness of debate continue.  I ask the Leader to respond to the varied topics of today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#K00800"><p>I thank the ten Members of the House for their contributions.  I commend and thank Senator Higgins for her participation in the European elections.  As the Cathaoirleach said, beidh l&aacute; eile aici.  She had a good result and she had the courage to run.  She may have been unsuccessful but, to be fair, she was and is an excellent parliamentarian and, as she said, she can be a European in this Chamber as well.  We wish her well and thank her.</p><p>A number of Senators, including Senators Ardagh, Boyhan and Craughwell, raised the issue of the election in the context of turnout.  On the issue around the spoiled ballots, it is interesting that in Ireland South, 5% of the votes were deemed invalid, in Dublin, it was 4%, and in Midlands-North-West, it was 3.5%.  Therefore, I am not sure it is an unusual figure in terms of the volume of spoiled votes.  However, I agree that, as Senator Boyhan said, we need an electoral commission to be established and to be up and running.  It is important, as part of a functioning democracy, that we have an independent electoral commission because there are issues around education and the dissemination of information, for example, in a plebiscite or a referendum campaign.</p><p>I will support anybody on the need to increase and enhance education.  At a time when we have civic, social and political education, CSPE, and policy modules in our schools, there is an onus on people to be <i>au fait</i>themselves with how to vote.  We cannot lose that element of personal responsibility.  Nonetheless, anything that can enhance the democratic process is something we should all support.  I would be happy to have the Minister come to the House.</p><p>Senators Craughwell and Ardagh raised the issue of child and adolescent mental health services, CAMHS.  In the area of mental health, we need to see a continuing improvement of access to waiting lists, and that is a priority for Government.  The number of people waiting is 2,738, which has declined marginally from this time last year.  The number of those waiting longer than 12 months is currently 336, which is 56 fewer than last year.  In saying that, both Senator McFadden and Senator Ardagh have made the case for the need for funding in the HSE service plan for the different community healthcare organisation, CHO, regions.  I hope the Minister of State, Deputy Jim Daly, who I would be happy to have come to the House, will look at the issue of CAMHS in the context of out-of-hours services, seven days a week cover, eating disorders, specialist services, prevention and early intervention.  In tandem with an improvement in the number of acute beds and the issue of access to services and referrals, I hope we will see an improvement in the service.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I will be happy for the Minister of State, Deputy Jim Daly, to come to the House to discuss the issue.  </p><p>Senator Conway-Walsh raised the issue of drug use in rural Ireland.  I am a member of the JPC for Cork city and county.  While the figures show that crime levels have reduced, the increase in the incidence of drug-driving is alarming.  We need to be more vigilant in that regard.  I will be happy to have the issue discussed again in the House.</p><p>Senators Higgins and Conway-Walsh raised the issues of exploration, drilling and the climate emergency.  We all recognise the need to take significant steps to respond to climate change.  The Government has committed to publishing the climate action plan, with actions in every sector, one of which will be looking at our reliance on fossil fuels and increasing our use of renewable energy sources in electricity generation from 30% to 70% by 2030.  A debate on the matter is badly needed, but it is interesting to note that neither the Oireachtas committee nor the Citizens' Assembly made any recommendation that exploration be banned, as contained in a Bill on the subject.  We must ensure we have a back-up supply when the wind is not blowing and the sun is not shining.  If we do not have energy and electricity supplies, we will have another argument.  I ask those Members who support the Bill from where are we going to source our power supply in the future.</p><p>Senators Craughwell and &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh referred to the Defence Forces, as Senator McFadden did yesterday.  As this is International Peacekeepers Day, we should all pay tribute to and salute the men and women in the Defence Forces.  It is not only about floods but the security they provide and the peacekeeping in which they engage.  The Government values the Defence Forces and holds their members in high esteem.  That is why the Minister of State, Deputy Kehoe, established a pay commission to look at their pay and conditions.  When its report is published, Senator Craughwell will see further action being taken.  Let us wait for it to be published.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#L00200"><p>It was leaked last week.  I d6id not leak it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#L00300"><p>I know.  The Senator would not dare do so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#L00400"><p>Will Senator Craughwell, please, allow the Leader to conclude?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#L00500"><p>There is an independent body was set up by the Minister of State who sits and participates at the Cabinet table.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#L00600"><p>He is not a Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#L00700"><p>The Minister of State sits at the Cabinet table.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#L00800"><p>Who holds the portfolio?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#L00900"><p>That is an academic exercise, as the Senator knows, no matter how much he throws his eyes up to Heaven.  The Minister of State sits at the Cabinet table and is at the heart of the decision-making of the Government.  We must await publication of the report, in tandem with, as I said yesterday, the restoration of pay and the withdrawal of the FEMPI legislation.  We have seen pay increases, from 6.2% to 7.4%, for those with salaries under &euro;70,000.  As a committed former member of the Defence Forces, the nominating body he is representing in this Chamber, the Senator should pre-empt what will be contained in the report.  When we have it, we can have another debate on the issue.  All of us on this side of the House, including Senator McFadden, speak to the Minister of State.  I meet members of the Defence Forces every day, some of whom are my friends and former classmates.  I understand the situation and we are committed to implementing the report.  I am happy, therefore, to accept the amendment proposed to the Order of Business as the Senator has a genuine motivation for bringing it forward.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#L01000"><p>That is very kind of the Leader.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#L01100"><p>I, too, thank the Leader.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#L01200"><p>Senator Paddy Burke referred to the very important issue of Dublin Port and cruise liners.  The decision made by the port could have a knock-on effect on economic activity throughout the country, not just in Dublin.  I hope it will reconsider its decision.  The Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Ross, should demand that it do so.  Cobh and Cork have benefited from the great work done by the Port of Cork.  Cruise liners should not be discouraged from coming to the capital city; rather, they should be encouraged.  I hope we will send that message from this Chamber.  I will be happy for the Minister to come to the House to discuss the matter.</p> <p>Senator Norris spoke about the response to what Senator Mullen had said last week.  That matter has been dealt with.  </p> <p>Senator Mullen spoke about the elections.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#L01300"><p>That is the issue I raised today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#L01400"><p>Senator &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh raised the important issue of shadow banking.  It is a source of concern.  I read an article on the matter in the <i>Irish Examiner</i>during the week in which it was stated this was the sixth largest centre in the world for shadow banking, which is incredible.  Therefore, it has an impact.  Oversight and regulation need to be improved as it can have an effect on the traditional banking system.  The Senator said it was worth trillions of dollars in the USA and I understand Bank of America was involved in it.  The Senator also said we must act to deal with it and educate and inform people of it.  I will be happy for the Minister responsible to come to the House to discuss it because it is such an important issue.  The Cathaoirleach said that while the Senator's piece was interesting, we had to be careful about it.  Some of the commentary on the issue is interesting and a Google search throws up a high number of articles on it.  We sleepwalked into the banking crash.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1431" speakername="P&aacute;draig &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#L01500"><p>I agree 100%.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#L01600"><p>I welcome the members of the Castledaly branch to the House.  They are guests of Senator McFadden.  I hope they will all have a very pleasant visit.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#L01700"><p>Senator Craughwell has proposed an amendment to the Order of Business: "That No. 4 be adjourned at 5 p.m., if not previously concluded, and that No. 83, non-Government motion No. 9, be taken at 5 p.m."  Is the amendment agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.65" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Order of Business, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.66" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#L01900">EU Regulation: Referral to Joint Committee</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#L02000"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That the proposal that Seanad &Eacute;ireann approves the exercise by the State of the option or discretion under Protocol No. 21 on the position of the United Kingdom and Ireland in respect of the area of freedom, security and justice annexed to the Treaty on European Union and to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union to accept the following measure: Regulation (EU) 2018/1727 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 14 November 2018 on the European Union Agency for Criminal Justice Cooperation (Eurojust), and replacing and repealing Council Decision 2002/187/JHA,a copy of which was laid before Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 2nd May 2019, be referred to the Joint Committee on Justice and Equality, in accordance with Standing Order 71(3)(<i>k</i>), which, not later than 18th June 2019, shall send a message to the Seanad in the manner prescribed in Standing Order 75, and Standing Order 77(2) shall accordingly apply.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.68" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.69" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#L02200">Sectoral Employment Order (Electrical Contracting Sector) 2019: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#L02300"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That Seanad &Eacute;ireann approves the following Order in draft:Sectoral Employment Order (Electrical Contracting Sector) 2019,a copy of which has been laid in draft form before Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 9th May 2019.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.71" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.72" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 12.20 p.m. and resumed at 12.50 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.73" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#O00100">Farm Safety Agency Bill 2018: Second Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1383" speakername="Paul Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#O00200"><p>I move: "That the Bill be now read a Second Time."</p> <p>I welcome the Minister to the House.  I will begin by providing some background information on farm safety issues and fatalities on farms, of which not everyone may be aware.  Unfortunately in the year to May, nine of the 17 recorded workplace deaths happened on farms or in the agricultural sector.  The sector accounted for more than 50% of workplace fatalities but only accounts for 5% of the workforce.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paul Daly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2464"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2464&amp;amp;pid=PaulDaly&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->There are also many non-fatal accidents.  To provide one quick statistic on that, the Teagasc national survey for 2012 to 2017 showed that there were 2,814 accidents on Irish farms, which is to say that there were accidents on 11% of all farms surveyed.  The amount of accidents - whether minor or otherwise, they are still accidents - which go unreported must also be factored in.  It is up to individuals to report them and, as we can all appreciate, many accidents are never reported.  </p><p>Based on what I have outlined and on my lifetime of involvement in agriculture - I was born on a farm and still farm part time - I was very aware of this issue when I came into the Seanad and beforehand, when I was on the council.  One sees these figures, which are astounding, throughout one's life, especially when one has a vested interest.  With what might be called a burst of enthusiasm or, perhaps, political naivety when I came in here I took on this issue, along with some other things, as something I believed I could do something about or something I could influence in order to help to reduce the figures I have mentioned.  </p><p>I was appointed to the Joint Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine.  When we were setting out a work programme at the start of our term I proposed that farm safety be included on it.  I thought I could start to achieve my goal from there.  Unfortunately, I was informed on the day that I was at the wrong committee, that it was a matter for the Joint Committee on Business, Enterprise and Innovation, and that the Health and Safety Authority, HSA, and the Minister under whose aegis it falls had ultimate responsibility.  I was told that it was outside the remit of the Joint Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine to deal with farm safety.  Despite this, on the three occasions on which I have been here for farm safety week, it has been the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine who has come before us.  When one raises questions about farm safety, as often as not Teagasc is quoted or one is referred to Teagasc.  </p><p>I began to look at this conundrum and as I carried out research and looked into it I saw that many agencies, both State agencies and NGOs, are doing good work but that many of the problems we have are caused by issues falling through the cracks and by a lack of co-ordination or contact between the various bodies, both State and non-State.  I started research on this project 18 months ago and we are only discussing it today.  During my research and studies I did a lot of reading up on the Road Safety Authority.  At some stage the penny dropped with me.  The reason for its success since its inception and formation in 2006 was that it provided a direct link between the Department of Justice, Equality and Law Reform, which policed the roads, the Department of Transport, which was responsible for the roads and, to an extent, the Department which had authority over the HSA.  The Road Safety Authority was formed in 2006.  In that year there were 365 fatalities on our roads; in 2018 there were 147.  Fatalities have more than halved.  </p><p>What I am proposing is not identical, but it is based on this model.  I am not saying that it will or can produce the same results, but it is a starting point.  I want to make it clear that what I am proposing in this Bill, the farm safety agency I would like to see set up, is a starting point.  I am quite prepared to meet with Members from all parties and none to work through the procedures in place.  I would hope to do that on Committee Stage.  I am prepared to look at amendments.  I hope that people can improve the Bill.  I will accept any constructive criticism or improvements to what I am proposing.  </p><p>What I am proposing is a farm safety agency.  This would be a body within the HSA.  Some people to whom I have spoken have said that they like the idea, which they believe is good, has potential, and could make a difference, but ask whether we are setting up a new body, or "quango" as they are called in some circles.  Section 2(1)(d) of the Bill refers specifically to, "a work programme prepared by the Agency and submitted to the Authority".  The new section 35(1A) to the Safety, Health and Welfare at Work Act 2005 proposed in section 4 states, "Where the Authority considers it appropriate in the circumstances, additional functions conferred on it under this section may, in whole or in part or for specified purposes, be performed by the Agency under section 36A(3)(l)."  This proposed new section in turn states, "There is established a body within the Authority to be known as [...] the Farm Safety Agency".  I am not looking for a brand new body.  I am not trying to reinvent the wheel.  What I want to introduce is an agency within the Health and Safety Authority which would have sole responsibility for safety issues relating to farms and agriculture.  This agency would not just be a sub-committee or forum, but an agency with statutory and legislative footing.  It would, could and should create a link between the two interested and relevant Departments, namely, the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine, and the Department of Business, Enterprise and Innovation.</p><p>The reason a specific individual farm agency is needed, as opposed to the arrangements in place under the Health and Safety Authority, is that, as workplaces go, farms are unique and very different from the average industrial workplace.  There are 140,000 family farms in Ireland; "family" being the operative word.  The farmyard can be a playground for the younger generation or a focus of interest for the elder generation who like to be out and to see how things are going.  By its nature, farming is very much dependent on the weather, which brings with it a lot of pressures.  One can have three wet days in a season, such as the silage season in which we are in at the moment, and then one can have four days' work to do in one day when the fine weather comes.  That is a pressure not felt in every other sector.  </p><p>People will have heard me raising issues of farm income, subsidies and the lack of disposable income farmers have nowadays on numerous occasions.  That lack of spendable money means that health and safety issues are often, although not always, put on the long finger.  The money is just not there to spend on the necessary repairs to equipment and so on.  In farming one is faced with the combination of machinery, animals and chemicals.  There are many different dangers.  It is a unique way to earn one's livelihood.  There are a hell of a lot more possibilities for accidents to occur than in many other sectors.  That is why it is so vitally important to have an agency that will look at this sector specifically, taking into consideration the risks and constraints I have mentioned, and which will make a link with the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine to incentivise, if needs be, some of the measures that need to be taken.  </p><p>Having said that, while I am specifically proposing the formation of this agency, I am not touching upon, proposing or mentioning any policies that agency could or should enact.  I will leave such matters to the agency when it is formed.  As I said at the outset, I started out with the hope that I could influence policy direction in respect of farm safety but, because of the difficulties I encountered in my research, I quickly realised that an agency was needed to co-ordinate the good work being done.  I do not want to be in any way critical of any of the personnel or agencies, whether Government or non-Government, who are doing fine work.  We do not know whether the figures I have quoted would be a lot worse if it were not for the great work being done by the HSA, Teagasc, AgriKids, Agri Aware, Bord Bia and the farm representative bodies.  I am not coming in here to be critical of anybody.  I am coming in here to try to help all of those people who are working diligently.  I am trying to start the conversation and to show that we care and will do something to help the many families who have been bereaved or whose family members have been incapacitated.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paul Daly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2464"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2464&amp;amp;pid=PaulDaly&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->When there is a bereavement or serious injury on a farm it affects many people.  For example, it affects the parents and the extended family if a young person is involved.  If a farmer is involved, it affects the running of the business and, in turn, puts extra strain on those left behind.  Given the nature of rural Ireland and the farm family set-up in rural Ireland, a farm fatality affects an entire community.  It can bring down a parish or locality.  The people affected come together and rally.  Those helping out a family who have had some difficulty may be unable to do their own work and this puts extra pressure on their work.  That in itself creates a chain reaction.</p><p>We need to have a frank and open debate on this topic.  I hope I receive the support of the House.  What I am proposing may not be what will come out at the other end, but at least we have to analyse it, look through it, go through it, tease it out and see its merits.  I believe that after 18 months of work and research, this is a credible solution to the problem we have.  It is a solution that can and will help to change the numbers I read out at the start.  Some people may say it will be costly or may use money reasons to argue for why it may not work.  I genuinely believe that it will be cost-effective and cost-efficient.  I am not talking about setting up a brand new agency.  It might involve sideways movements of staff.  If it is efficient enough it might curtail or cut expenditure being spent by so many different bodies and agencies.  In the long run, if we save a life or save people from injury, we would save money that would be spent indirectly through the health services and other supports.  I do not think it will be any more expensive to operate but I believe it will be far more efficient and effective.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#Q00200"><p>I am delighted to welcome the Minister of State to the Chamber this afternoon.  On a personal level, I am delighted to second the Farm Safety Agency Bill 2018 put forward today by my colleague, Senator Paul Daly.  At this point I wish to compliment Senator Daly on bringing forward this important legislation.  I wish to compliment him on the many long hours and days he has put in to bringing this critical legislation to the House this afternoon.</p> <p>We all know that the farm is potentially a dangerous place to work.  Unfortunately, the statistics available to us highlight this fact.  During the past ten years, on average, Irish farms account for more than 40% of all workplace fatalities.  Like Senator Paul Daly, I wish to acknowledge that good work is being done by many groups on the farm safety issue.  However, the statistics show that something different needs to be done and that a new approach needs to be taken.  The contents of the Bill put forward by my colleague clearly give good guidelines and direction to what needs to be done to reduce the fatalities on a farm.</p> <p>We all know farmers work long hours.  It is certainly not a nine-to-five, Monday to Friday occupation.  Many farmers spend much of that time working on their own.  As we know many dangers arise in working on Irish farms, whether those related to machinery, working livestock or chemicals of one kind or another.</p> <p>When any fatality occurs it is heartbreaking for those involved but when a fatality occurs on a farm it is equally or even more heartbreaking.  Unfortunately, the statistics show, more often than not, that the victim is a child of a farmer or someone connected with that family.  As we know, when it happens on a farm there is a permanent reminder.  Every day the farmer goes out to work there will be a permanent reminder of what happened and when and where it happened.  That will stay with such farmers for the remainder of their lives.</p> <p>Clearly, something needs to be done and a new direction needs to be taken.  I believe the Bill put forward by my colleague, Senator Paul Daly, clearly gives some direction to what needs to be done.  The bringing together of all the different agencies currently doing good work in this area would give them more focus and direction.  It is to be welcomed.</p> <p>Since I come from a farm background, I understand what it is like to work on a farm.  Unfortunately, as Senator Paul Daly outlined this afternoon, the statistics show there are many dangers, as I outlined earlier, on Irish farms.  In light of that fact, I spoke earlier this morning on a survey conducted recently by the HSE in respect of farming and farming practices.  The survey came away with the conclusion that farmers are more at risk than any other occupation from mental health issues and physical health issues as well because of the time they spend on their own and the social isolation many of them go through.</p> <p>I am delighted and honoured to be associated with this legislation.  I compliment my colleague, Senator Daly, on bringing this forward.</p> <p>Any work that can be done, the result of which might reduce a single farm fatality, has to be worthwhile.  I hope all Members will embrace this legislation as a genuine attempt by my colleague, Senator Daly, to address this heart-breaking issue for many farm families.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#Q00300"><p>Senator James Reilly is next.  I understand you wish to share your time, Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#Q00400"><p>I intend to share my time with Senator Paddy Burke, taking six and two minutes respectively.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#Q00500"><p>That is fine.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#Q00600"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House.  I welcome Senator Paul Daly's Bill.  I believe it is important that it highlights an area that is of considerable concern.  There are many reasons for the statistics, which the Senator has read into the record.  He noted that in the past ten years, between 2009 and 2018, the number of workplace fatalities in agriculture was 486 or 41% of the total number of workplace fatalities.  Yet agriculture staff represent only 6% of the total workforce.  Clearly the types of accidents happening on farms arise for a host of different reasons.  I grew up on a farm myself.  I spent every summer there.  People become very familiar with cattle and large animals.  People take things for granted.  There is heavy machinery around the place.  Children are playing in yards.  Farmyards and farms are now places of work.  That is the culture shift of which we need to ensure that people take cognisance.  There has been a considerable number of farm visits by the Health and Safety Authority and those responsible take this issue seriously.  I understand in the region of &euro;500,000 has been spent on this area.  Nonetheless, we have an unacceptability high incidence rate.  There are terrible tragedies and children are particularly vulnerable.  There is an old saying holding that familiarity breeds contempt.  In this instance, familiarity breeds a little indifference and comfort.  I am always taken aback at how many older farmers walk with their back to large cattle and take the view that they are quiet.  Sometimes they are unpredictable and that can result in terrible damage.  It is not only the fatalities we are concerned with but the lifelong injuries that many suffer as a consequence of activity around farmyards.  As we know, many farmyards are now busy places as farms expand.</p> <p>I hear precisely what Senator Gallagher said in respect of the social isolation that farmers feel, but that is for another day.  Some good advertisements have been made by the HSA on farm safety.  One such advertisement is running at the moment.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator James Reilly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2180"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2180&amp;amp;pid=DrJamesReilly&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->There were older ones, too, notably those highlighting the danger of children falling into large collection vessels for water.  Those types of tragic accidents did happen over the years.  We need a major effort to educate farmers and farming families that the yard is a workplace that can be dangerous and is not, as it used to be, an extension of the home.</p><p>I welcome Senator Paul Daly's efforts to address these issues in the Bill.  I am pleased the Government is not opposing it but will instead seek to explore, with the Senator, how to forward his ambition of reducing the number of fatalities and injuries that occur on farms.  I agree that the Health and Safety Authority is in a position to take a leading role.  The Senator does not intend that a separate agency be established but, rather, that a body within the HSA be given this function.  How that might work in practice is a matter for further exploration.  I welcome the emphasis placed on the serious issue of health and safety on farms.  It is something that requires special attention as we seek to keep rural communities intact and encourage people to settle in rural areas instead of migrating to cities.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1380" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#R00200"><p>I thank Senator Reilly for sharing time to allow me to comment on this important issue.  I was part of a delegation from the transport committee which went to Australia in 2004 in advance of the establishment of the Road Safety Authority.  Australia was the world leader on road safety at the time, and probably still is, and we brought back the information we gathered there and presented it to the committee.  What was done in Australia was put into law here, with great results, as Senator Paul Daly noted.  Fatalities on the roads have reduced from 348 in the year the RSA was set up to some 150 per year now.</p><p>I welcome the Senator's Bill and am delighted the Government is not opposing it.  An issue I wish to bring attention to relates to a particular change in farming practices in the past 20 years.  When I was a youngster growing up on a farm, although there was less machinery available to us, younger people were more familiar with the handling of machinery and livestock than they are today.  It seems to be the norm now on many family farms that the young people, first of all, are not interested in most of the work involved in running a farm and, second, are not asked to do it by their parents.  This is an issue that should be examined because, as colleagues noted, young people are at risk where the family farm is also their playground.  They should be <i>au fait</i>with how machines operate, how silage is cut, how cattle are herded, handled and so on.  Senator Paul Daly is probably right that there needs to be a separate agency to oversee and direct these matters.  It is different from road safety because there are so many different aspects to farming, including silage making, slurry disposal, working with animals, spraying crops, operating heavy machinery and managing traffic in yards where people are under pressure of work and changing weather conditions.  There are dangers and risks where family members are not knowledgeable about how things work on a farm.  This is an area that might be considered for inclusion in the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1439" speakername="Ian Marshall" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#R00300"><p>I support Senator Paul Daly's Bill, which addresses a very important issue.  We underestimate the seriousness of health and safety practice on farms and farm businesses, and the related statistics on injury and death.  As Senator Paul Daly notes, one cannot treat a farm like another business because, very often, the business and the home are inextricably linked, if not one and the same.  It is a unique set-up.  As the president of a farming union in Northern Ireland some years ago, I am aware that it is probably easier to regulate, control and issue a set of directives for the management of risks in other areas of business.  A farm, however, is not like a building site, being often more extensive and more spread out.</p> <p>I was involved in setting up the Farm Safety Partnership in Northern Ireland at a time when one farmer per month was losing his or her life through farm fatalities.  It was a completely unacceptable statistic which we knew we had to address.  The partnership approach was essential to the success of that initiative, incorporating the Health and Safety Executive for Northern Ireland, the Department of Agriculture, Environment and Rural Affairs, the Ulster Farmers Union, the Northern Ireland Agricultural Producers Association and the Young Farmers Clubs of Ulster.</p> <p>We found that a vital part of improving safety on farms was raising awareness of the risks.  If we can elevate awareness, we often will mitigate some of those risks immediately.  Another important aspect is driving behavioural change.  An interesting phenomenon one encounters when having this discussion with farmers is that they are a unique bunch of individuals in that they do not fear death, which is a frightening thing to observe.  What they do fear is leaving their spouses and children with the mess and horror of having to cope if they are injured.  It is the fear of the consequences of their being taken out of the farm business.  When it came to behavioural change, we found early on that the key drivers in this were children, grandchildren, wives and partners.  They were the people who, by their interaction with the alpha male in the business, drove changes in practice.</p> <p>It is important to keep the message simple.  In the North, we came up with the acronym SAFE, which stands for the four main farming hazards, namely, slurry, animals, falls and equipment.  It was also important that we identified at the outset the two key vulnerable groups, namely, the young and the old.  It is sometimes the case that farmers with a lifetime of experience of working the land reach the point where they are not as mobile and agile as they used to be and cannot react to a situation quickly enough to avoid an accident.</p> <p>On a note of caution, the Farm Safety Partnership worked in Northern Ireland because there was only a small number of partners.  When an attempt was made to replicate the same model in Great Britain, a meeting which had involved four or five partners in Northern Ireland was attended by 62 stakeholders.  It was so unwieldy and unmanageable that it was difficult to deliver effective change.  Anything we can do to prevent loss of life on farms must be supported and encouraged.  The key thing is partnership and co-ordination, working together rather than having a silo mentality.  I support the Senator's important Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#R00400"><p>I commend Senator Paul Daly on his proactive approach not only in bringing forward this legislation but, in addition, providing an excellent explanatory leaflet which outlines the case for his proposals.  In the rural parts of my home county of Donegal, as in other rural areas, we have lost too many lives to farm accidents.  As other speakers noted, a farm is not a like other workplaces because it is where families live and children grow up and play.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator P&aacute;draig Mac Lochlainn:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2321"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2321&amp;amp;pid=PadraigMacLochlainn&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I was looking at this publication from the Health and Safety Authority and Teagasc.  It teaches about farm safety but is clearly aimed at young people and their parents.  This is an excellent example but there is not enough of it.  There is not enough focus on it.  </p><p>Senator Paul Daly made a comparison with the Road Safety Authority.  I must commend him on this comparison because we had a serious problem and there is never any room for complacency in terms of road safety in Donegal.  At one stage, my home peninsula of Inishowen lost 18 young people under the age of 25 within 18 months.  It was horrific.  There is a lot of discussion about what we are going to do about this.  Such was the scale of the tragedies we had at national level that many good people offered assistance.  What emerged from that was, thankfully, a dedicated focus on road safety through the Road Safety Authority with public information campaigns where shocking stories were told to people.  When one looks at this information leaflet from Senator Paul Daly, one can see that the statistics are devastating.  Half of the accidents are on farms.  Clearly, what we are doing is not working.  </p><p>We always worry about the idea of another dedicated agency.  Remember that years ago, there was all this talk about too many quangos but I commend the model because the Senator talks about how it will be an independent agency under the authority of the Health and Safety Authority.  This is a really thoughtful approach.  The Senator has put a lot of thought into it.  It is unusual.  Sadly, much legislation in here does not have explanatory memoranda or an attempt to win support for it.  I am pleased to confirm that my party is supportive and am thankful to the Senator for the amount of the work and effort he has put into this and the imaginative and thoughtful way he has approached it.  It is worthy of support.  The Health and Safety Authority does its best with the resources it has and has a wide spectrum within workplaces to consider but, unfortunately, we clearly need a dedicated focus on farm safety.  On that basis, we support the legislation and look forward to working with the Senator through the next few Stages as the Bill progresses.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1419" speakername="John Dolan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#S00200"><p>This is becoming repetitious but it still needs to be said.  I thank Senator Paul Daly for bringing forward this legislation.  The Title, which refers to a farm safety agency, is a critical element of the Bill.  While there are businesses and workplaces - even family businesses - where perhaps somebody lives over the shop, with a farm, the person lives in the machine workshop.  The person lives where the work goes on, which is the issue.  It is a precious thing to arrest people with that idea, namely, that this is not just a place of work but a place where people live.  When they run out to the car to get something, they are going into the workshop - the place where the work happens.  That is a critical issue.</p> <p>Senator Reilly and others have spoken about children while others have mentioned older farmers and isolation.  It is a mystery as to why there are not more injuries and fatalities.  There are many elements that conspire to make this an important and focused piece of legislation.  I come from rural Ireland.  I grew up on a pig farm but that was not exciting enough for me.  All the farms around me were dairy farms, which was where the action was, but none of them had tractors at that time.  Taking out the pony and horse and bringing in machinery was fuelled by the EU, although I am not blaming it.  Getting into the EU, getting fertilisers on farms, improving production, speeding things up and farmers being able to get credit and buy a little Mickey Mouse tractor for the first time along with a milking machine, are great things that have put us right up there in terms of our exports and our reputation as an exporting nation.  For the first few years of the recession, the only good story in this country involved our farming exports.  We were on our knees and everything had gone wallop.  I make that emotional appeal and statement that farming has served this country well.  It was the only thing we had going for us during those first few years to give us a chance to recover.  </p> <p>I had my own experience of walking across a covered slurry pit but I stood on a sheet of galvanised material that was covering it up.  I did not know this at the time - I am not that stupid - but I stood on the sheet of galvanised material, which was lovely and shiny on the outside but was totally corroded underneath.  Only for the fact that I threw myself forward, they would be looking for me.  I am thinking of a lovely nephew of mine who is crazy about farming.  He is 12 and would be good at it.  As a young man, his grandfather, who only died seven or eight years ago, was mangled with a power take-off, PTO, shaft.  He survived and much of it was down to his youth and fitness.  Another ten years later, it might have been different.  We all have those stories.  We cannot easily keep children from wanting to be active and out and about.  </p> <p>It is important for us to struggle with this issue.  It is great that it has come into this House, which has a better tradition of talking things through and hearing what other folk are saying, first.  I emphasise the Title and branding of this Bill, which focuses on farming being a black spot when it comes to safety.  As mothers, daughters and wives, it is women who are more involved in farming than they would have been in the past, who worry every day and every night when the lads are out, be it in winter or summer, day or night.  We owe it to them to give them a bit more peace of mind by improving safety.  Senator Marshall spoke about changing the culture and mindset and that was very much around the women on the farms.  </p> <p>I am delighted the Government is supporting this Bill.  I heard very positively what Senator Paul Daly said.  It may not end up the way it started.  That is not the point.  The point is that we get into this, have it over and back and get a piece of legislation that will serve rural Ireland.  At the start, Senator Paul Daly said that an accident can bring down a parish.  These kinds of things do bring parishes down so it is not just about a person or family.  It is a community thing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#S00300"><p>I commend Senator Paul Daly for the body of work he has done to bring this item before the House today and thank him for putting this issue centre stage.  It is so important that we try to do what we can to reduce fatalities and serious life-changing injuries arising out of farm accidents.  It is a real weak spot for farm families.  Senator Paddy Burke spoke about the change in farming over the past number of years.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Michelle Mulherin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2309"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2309&amp;amp;pid=MichelleMulherin&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We could safely say in the past 30 to 40 years, the mechanisation of farming have brought us to this point.  We need to catch up with that and be prepared and respond appropriately.  The largest amount of incidents involve tractors, followed by farm machinery and then livestock.  We all know that livestock are not handled as previously; there is not the same familiarity with human beings etc.  A myriad of things need to be addressed there.</p><p>I was concerned to read that in the past four years the number of Health and Safety Authority inspections of farms had halved.  I believe this is something Senator Paul Daly's Bill can serve to highlight.  When I talk of inspections, many of these inspections can simply be an intervention where a bad habit has been formed in dealing with machinery such as not covering a PTO shaft etc.  Sometimes such an intervention from an outside person highlighting the danger of the practice can assist.  I know the Health and Safety Authority also sends notices.  It is not all about prosecutions.  It is about prevention and guiding people in the right way.</p><p>Other things could assist in the matter.  Youngsters in secondary school can study agricultural science just as they can study other practical subjects such as woodwork and technical drawing.  I believe there is scope to introduce secondary school courses in manual handling and courses equivalent to the Safe Pass for farming.  Many secondary school students who want to continue on in the family farm or to get into farming know it at that stage.  Why not equip them in a practical way for what is ahead of them and allow them to develop awareness that they are dealing with dangerous equipment?  We would be giving them a life skill and helping their families.  There are farmers further along and obviously that is not a suggestion for them.  We can all be educated about the dangers of this machinery.  I ask that for the issue of education to be looked at.  It would mean that when they leave school and go to a farm college or whatever they are ready to go out in the farm.  At least we can be confident that we have gone some way towards that education piece.</p><p>As has been said, injuries arising from farm accidents can affect young and old.  It pierces very deep in communities, as has been highlighted.  With the objective and underlying purpose expressed in the Bill, I hope we can see immediately some more prioritisation with the Health and Safety Authority regarding its approach to farming practices and then in due course taking into account further what Senator Daly has proposed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1272" speakername="Pat Breen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#T00200"><p>I am delighted we are having this debate.  I am delighted that my Oireachtas colleagues in the Seanad are raising the awareness of farm safety.  It is a really good forum for raising it.  I thank Senator Paul Daly for raising the issue.  It is really important to have a debate about it.</p> <p>I work with the Health and Safety Authority on a regular basis given the remit I have as Minister of State.  I have seen at first hand the professionalism of the Health and Safety Authority not just in farming, but also in the pharma and construction sectors.  I am very proud to be associated with the Health and Safety Authority.</p> <p>I know Senator Daly said in his introduction that this is about having a new approach.  As I also come from a farming background, I am also interested in the subject.  I have also taken a new approach to this and worked hand in hand with the Health and Safety Authority, the Department of Agriculture, Food and Marine, and the farming organisations.  I will say more about that later.  I am passionate about this subject.  I know many people who have died as a result of farming accidents, as I am sure the Senator also does.  I could probably name ten people who have died as a result of a careless accident, most of the time in the blink of an eye.</p> <p>The difference from the pharma and construction sectors is that those areas are regulated and controlled whereas most of the time, farmers are working on their own.  It is good that most of the speakers highlighted the dangers on the farm.  We are having success at this, with a 27% reduction in farm accidents last year on family farms.  There was a 40% reduction in accidents in the workplace, indicating that the Health and Safety Authority policies are working.  There have been nine deaths this year so far.  As Senator Paul Daly has said this is still far too high and we need to reduce it further.  We will do our best to ensure this.  As some speakers said, farmers need to take their safety into their own hands because they are working alone.</p> <p>I commend Senator Paul Daly and other Senators on the keen interest they have shown in this issue which can be very emotional.  As many Senators have said too many people are killed and that is a life-changing situation on the family farm.  In many cases it can result in the sale of that family farm.  It is also important to mention the life-changing injuries that can happen, including people losing hands, legs and other limbs.  It is a serious area on which the Health and Safety Authority is working.  The Government is very conscious of the matter and I am delighted it has been raised here today.</p> <p>The intention behind this Bill is clearly very well motivated in seeking to set up a farm safety agency whose principal function will be to the safety, health and welfare of persons on farms and in other agricultural places of work.  However, my major reservation about the Bill is that there is already in existence an Exchequer-funded State agency, the Health and Safety Authority, which already has the required statutory functions envisaged for the proposed new agency.  The remit of the Health and Safety Authority is to regulate occupational safety and health in every place of work within the State, including in farms.</p> <p>Ireland&rsquo;s record in respect to occupational safety and health is highly thought of throughout Europe.  Ireland is one of the few member states to have extended occupational safety and health legislation and the responsibilities that come with that to include the self-employed.  As a large portion of Ireland's farmers are self-employed it means that all occupational safety and health legislation is effective for all farmers.</p> <p>The Bill envisages establishing a farm safety agency within the present structure of the Health and Safety Authority with its own governance obligations.  The Bill also imposes an obligation on to the Health and Safety Authority to consult the new agency on any proposed regulations relating to farms or agriculture.</p> <p>Under the Safety, Health and Welfare at Work Act 2005, the entity responsible for the introduction of any statutory regulation is the Minister, who must be is a position to carry out this responsibility without impediment, notwithstanding the practicality of utilising any resources available to consult if so desired.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Pat Breen:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1766"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1766&amp;amp;pid=PatBreen&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->As Members will know, a large portion of occupational safety and health legislation originates from the EU.  The Minister needs to introduce equivalent national legislation to give effect to the EU legislation in this State.  Most of the EU legislation is applicable to all places of work, which includes farms.  The consultation requirement would create an anomaly whereby the Minister might ask the HSA to produce a draft transposing text, but the HSA could not respond to the Minister without having formally consulted the proposed agency on the matter.  Such a scenario would create an unhelpful and unwanted additional administrative obstacle to the successful transposition by Ireland of a piece of EU legislation.</p><p>In its annual budgeting procedures, the HSA allocates funding directly to its agricultural programme.  This allows the HSA to assign dedicated personnel resources to the farming sector.  In addition, other inspector, educational and promotional resources within the HSA can be used to supplement the dedicated farming sector resources.  As we have all seen for ourselves, the HSA maintains a significant presence at many agricultural events, including the National Ploughing Championships.  I am sure Senator Paul Daly has seen the HSA's displays and exhibitions at the ploughing championships.  Having been there for the past two years, I must say that the HSA's live displays, which show the dangers associated with working on farms, driving quad bikes, working on roofs and working with animals, create a lot of attention among those who are interested in seeing how accidents happen and can be prevented.  Representatives of the HSA also attend the Tullamore show and the beef exhibition that is organised by Teagasc.  I have been there and seen this for myself.  The HSA uses such events to interact directly with the farming community and to provide practical advice and documentation, where possible.  Senator Mac Lochlainn has highlighted one of the many documents on farm safety and accident prevention that are available.  Such documentation can be accessed at Teagasc offices, from the HSA and from the various farming bodies throughout the country.</p><p>I have spoken about demonstrations of good farm safety practice.  The results of bad farming practice are sometimes demonstrated to highlight the devastating results and effects of farm accidents on farmers and their families.  One of the most poignant moments I experienced last year was at a display of the wellington boots of dead farmers and children who were killed in farm accidents.  They were displayed in a line along with the names of the people who died.  I suggest that anyone who sees this display will have a greater understanding of the impact of the loss of a loved one on a family farm.</p><p>Another reason I think it is unnecessary to establish a farm safety agency is the presence of the farm safety partnership advisory committee.  I do not know whether Senators are aware of the existence of this long-established committee.  Senator Marshall referred to the partnership committee in Northern Ireland.  The committee in this jurisdiction has over 20 members, including: representatives of farm relief services; Macra na Feirme; Teagasc; the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine; professional agricultural contractors, who have an important role to play; Irish Rural Link; the Irish Creamery Milk Suppliers Association; the Irish Farmers Association; Coillte; the Irish Cattle and Sheep Farmers Association; Carlow Institute of Technology; University College Dublin; the Institute of Occupational Safety and Health's rural industries section; Veterinary Ireland; the Veterinary Council of Ireland; Agri Aware; and the HSA.  The partnership committee is very active and works really well.  It reports to the HSA.</p><p>As I have said, it is important that the fundamentals of the occupational safety and health legislative regime apply to all sectors of the economy, including farming.  I fear that an agency exclusively dedicated to farm safety would not change or improve the situation and could dilute the impact of the HSA's current cross-sector programmes and activities.  Having said that, I accept that the level of farm fatalities is excessively high.  I welcome Senator Paul Daly's desire to bring about important change in this regard.  When we discuss issues relating to the death or injury of a farmer or any other worker, we must be aware that we are talking about human beings.  We must not sanitise the facts by referring to cold statistics without acknowledging that behind every number there is a face, a family and a community.  As previous speakers have said, 200 people have lost their lives while working on Irish farms in the last ten years.  We must consider the impact of these deaths on families, friends and communities, as various Senators have outlined this afternoon.</p><p>Since responsibility for occupational health and safety was passed to me in 2016, I have been alarmed at the high levels of fatalities that occur on family farms.  The number was very high in 2017, when 25 people died.  That is why I met the Minister, Deputy Creed, in that year.  We called together a group from all areas of the agricultural family.  The purpose of this gathering was to ask the community to consider the possible interventions the Government could make to improve the situation with regard to safety.  I called this meeting in the Department of Business, Enterprise and Innovation.  Each organisation that was represented submitted suggestions, many of which overlapped or were similar.  Last year, based on these suggestions, I asked representatives of various Departments to examine the suggestions to ascertain what was possible.  Four specific recommendations were ultimately identified.  First, it is important that there should be a requirement for farm safety training under CAP 2021.  Second, dairy companies should promote farm safety training certification as part of their supply chains.  Third, there is a need to ensure the HSA and the Road Safety Authority continue to work collaboratively, especially on the safety standards of agricultural tractors and quad bikes.  Fourth, progress needs to be made with actions that ensure a greater use of protective head gear when driving quad bikes on family farms.  All of these issues are really important.</p><p>Officials from the Department of Business, Enterprise and Innovation, the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine and the HSA are working on ways to bring these policy issues into being.  I will ask the HSA to use the farm safety partnership advisory committee to bring forward a new farm safety action plan as a matter of urgency.  The aim of this plan will be to identify how to bring about an improved co-ordination of efforts from all stakeholders and to examine the scope for better strategic alliances.  As I said earlier in this debate, during my time as Minister of State with responsibility for occupational health and safety I have found that farmers must ultimately be the main driver of cultural and behavioural change in the farming sector.  Other speakers have made this point as well.  Farmers must take responsibility for their own safety.  In March 2017, I launched a report, Risk Taking and Accidents on Irish Farms, which was completed as part of an ESRI-HSA research programme.  The report has been particularly helpful in developing a deeper understanding of the mindset of farmers.  It explains why unsafe practices are occurring and what triggers risk on farms.  The report highlights the significant risk associated with not getting help with difficult jobs, especially on small farms.  The need to check machinery is significantly associated with accidents and near misses.  Farmers on larger farms are more likely to take risks by not routinely using safety gear.  The likelihood that a farmer will fail to use such gear is nearly three times as high on a larger farm of more than 100 ha than on a smaller farm of less than 20 ha.</p><p>The HSA is using knowledge transfer groups to emphasise the importance of getting help with difficult tasks on the farm.  Research indicates that failing to get such assistance is associated with a higher risk of accidents and near misses.  Without a change in culture and behaviour, no amount of legislative interventions will have an impact on this problem.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Pat Breen:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1766"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1766&amp;amp;pid=PatBreen&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Given the sensitive nature of the subject and the progressive spirit in which the Senators have introduced this Bill, the Government has decided that not to oppose it.  However, I would add that there is a need for further scrutiny of the Bill to be carried out in terms of cost-benefit analysis and other factors.  Furthermore, due to the costs associated with establishing a new agency, a money message would be required.  </p><p>I thank all the Senators for their contributions to the debate today.  This is a very sensitive subject.  So far this year, nine people have died on Irish farms, which is far too many.  Anything we can do to reduce the number of accidents on family farms is very welcome.  That is why I welcome all initiatives and inputs by Senators today, particularly those of Senator Paul Daly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1383" speakername="Paul Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#V00200"><p>I thank all my colleagues for their support today.  As I said at the outset, this is such an important issue but I am a little taken aback by the Minister of State's response, to be honest.  Perhaps the Minister of State had to take the approach he took but I had hoped that under the circumstances and given the topic of conversation, he would not take a defensive attitude.  I was very complimentary of the Health and Safety Authority, HSA, and every other body mentioned in the Minister of State's summation.  I was very complimentary of their work and was not critical of anybody, the Minister of State included.  I said in my opening remarks that the numbers would be far worse were it not for the good work that is being done by a number of different agencies.  That said, I did identify cracks in the system and argued that the numbers are still too high, as the Minister of State acknowledged.  The reason I am proposing this Bill in its current form is to try to seal the cracks.</p> <p>The Minister of State mentioned the HSA stall at the National Ploughing Championships.  I ploughed at the championships in Waterford in 1983 and have attended the championships every year since then.  Until I became aware of this issue, I was one of those who, on walking around the championships site in the evenings would walk by the HSA stall, thinking that it would never happen to me.  Expecting people to call to the HSA is not going to work.  That is why I am proposing that this agency would have a statutory and legislative footing.  I acknowledge the farm safety partnership and the good advice that it gives.  However, in its implementation, it is falling between the cracks.  Teagasc operates on the agriculture front but if one is not a Teagasc client, one does not receive its literature.  If one is not involved in the green certificate programme, one is not getting safety training from Teagasc.  If one does not attend a knowledge transfer course, one does not get Teagasc training.  Even if nine out of ten people are attending such courses, the one person who is not attending is still vulnerable.  It is that one person who, unfortunately, has added to the figures that have been quoted here today by so many Senators.</p> <p>The IFA is playing an important role, as are the ICMSA and the ICSA.  They all have safety officers but not every farmer is a member of those organisations.  We have NGOs that are doing fantastic work but not on a national basis so there are areas and pockets of the country that are being missed.  Bord Bia is also part of this process.  If a farmer applies to be quality assured, the first thing that Bord Bia does is insist that he or she erects a calving gate.  I had to do that myself and it is a fantastic measure.  I appreciate its value and wonder at times how I or some member of my family did not have an accident when a cow was calving before we had that gate.  Had I not joined the quality assurance scheme, I probably would not have installed a calving gate.  These are just a few of the many organisations that are doing great work on the back of the farm safety partnership advice.  However, as I have said already, there are faults and cracks in the system and people are being missed and falling between those cracks.  The issue is how we get to those people who are being missed.  How do we reach those with the "it won't happen to me" attitude?  They are not going to approach any of the aforementioned organisations.  These people are not clients of Teagasc, they have never engaged in the green certificate programme, are not involved in knowledge transfer groups and are not members of any farm representative body.  They live in areas where NGOs cannot reach them because of time, personnel and financial constraints.  </p> <p>I am trying to help to provide a solution.  I am not being domineering or critical and I am complimentary of what has been done to date.  I am here to try to solve a problem, the existence of which is undeniable.  The figures, unfortunately, speak for themselves.  Everybody today said that it is great to start the conversation but I want this to be more than a conversation.  Having a conversation is scant consolation for those families who have been bereaved and those who have family members at home who can no longer do the work they did previously because of an accident.  Everyone in here understands how the legislative system works in terms of Bills proposed by the Opposition and money messages.  It is very unfortunate that the Minister of State's closing response to a debate on such a serious and concerning issue is that money is more important than the lives of our farmers, who have kept this country viable since its foundation.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.94" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#V00400"><p>When is it proposed to take Committee Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1383" speakername="Paul Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#V00500"><p>Next Tuesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.97" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Committee Stage ordered for Tuesday, 4 June 2019.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.98" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 1.56 p.m. and resumed at 3.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.99" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#FF00100">Gaming and Lotteries (Amendment) Bill 2019: Committee Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.100" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>SECTION 1</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#FF00300"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Stanton, to the House.  As amendment No. 1 is consequential on amendment No. 12, amendments Nos. 1 and 12 are related and may be discussed together by agreement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#FF00400"><p>I move amendment No. 1:</p><blockquote>In page 3, between lines 8 and 9, to insert the following:&quot;(2) In this Act &quot;Act of 1931&quot; means the Betting Act 1931.&quot;.</blockquote> <p>I thank the Minister of State for coming to the House to take this important legislation.  Amendment No. 1 seeks to include reference to the Betting Act 1931 in the section on definitions.  Amendment No. 12 relates to the ability of people to bet on the outcome of lotteries.  Those bets may be placed outside the jurisdiction and, therefore, there is no recourse for the Government in seeking to control and regulate them and ensure there is a return to the taxpayer.  We intend to press these amendments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1277" speakername="David Stanton" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#FF00500"><p>I am delighted to be in the Seanad for the debate on this important legislation.  As I said on Second Stage, the Bill seeks to address certain deficiencies with regard to the conduct of gaming and lottery activities regulated under the Gaming and Lotteries Act 1956.  Pending a comprehensive reform of gambling laws, which we are working on, the Bill proposes a number of interim reform measures for the licensing and regulation of gaming and lottery activities covered by the 1956 Act.</p> <p>Section 1 states that the principal Act is the Gaming and Lotteries Act 1956.  I have tabled a later amendment to amend the Betting Act 1931, and it should be subsequently added to the Acts referred to if my amendment is carried.  I do not believe it is correct to add to the definition of principal Act in the way proposed by the Senator.  The Office of the Attorney General is supportive of that view.  There is a risk of uncertainty and poor drafting practice, I am told.  There is reference to the Betting Acts in the Gaming and Lotteries Act 1956, which did not require its mention in the definition of the principal Act in section 1.  Such an addition as proposed by the Senator would serve no purpose, would be superfluous from a drafting perspective, and would give rise to uncertainty, and I am sure none of us wants that.  I ask the Senator to consider withdrawing the amendment.</p> <p>I want to make a number of points on amendment No. 12.  I have no function in respect of the national lottery, its regulation or licensing.  That is a matter for the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform under the National Lottery Act 2013.  The Minister did not provide in that legislation for any prohibition on licensed remote bookmakers offering bets on the outcome of the national lottery draw on Wednesdays and Saturdays.  My Department's role in regard to licensed bookmakers is limited to the provision of certificates of fitness for applicants for bookmaker's licences, remote bookmaker's licences and for remote betting intermediaries.  The licences are issued by the Revenue Commissioners.  I am not aware that any conditions are imposed in those licences as to the nature of the bets that such licensees might offer.</p> <p>Therefore, I must take my guidance in this matter from the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, who engaged on this particular point with Deputy Burton in the other House on 5 March last.  The Minister noted on that occasion that there is no particular evidence that the offers of bookmakers have any significant impact on the sales of national lottery products.  I note that the turnover of the national lottery increased from &euro;670 million in 2015 to &euro;750 million in 2016, to &euro;800 million in 2017, and to &euro;805 million in 2018.  This certainly does not suggest much impact.  Senators cited the contribution of the national lottery to good causes each year.  This is to be welcomed, although such contribution is a critical consideration in having the national lottery in the first place.</p> <p>The European Lotto Betting Association, ELBA, members, myLotto24 and Lottoland, commissioned a report by a leading economic analyst, Mr. Jim Power, entitled An Assessment of the Online Gambling Market in Ireland and its Impact on Good Causes Funding by the National Lottery.  Contrary to the position adopted by the national lottery licence holder, the report found no evidence that lottery betting, either online or via retail betting shops, was undermining good causes funding or that it threatened it in the long term.  The report found that there are only six lottery betting providers licensed and active as remote bookmakers in Ireland.  Based on the 2017 performance figures provided by the three leading ELBA members licensed and active in Ireland, their total combined draw-based betting turnover was &euro;1.4 million, a mere 0.25% of the &euro;559 million draw-based sales turnover achieved by the national lottery in the same period.  Rather than damaging good causes funding, the report found that the long-term presence of these operators actually should have a beneficial impact by creating more competition, choice and innovation in what otherwise might be effectively a monopolised market.</p> <p>The report found that a decline of &euro;43 million, or 16%, in good causes funding from the national lottery occurred in the past decade.  It was &euro;268 million in 2008 and &euro;225 million in 2017.  The ELBA contends that to suggest that online lottery betting presents any meaningful threat to good causes funding from the national lottery is factually incorrect and that the sustainability of good causes funding requires a broader analysis, including in respect of the treatment of unclaimed prizes associated with the national lottery, which is another issue.  I appreciate that the Senators may point out that this report was commissioned by an interested party, and that would be a fair observation.  However, in the interests of transparency and clarity, it should also be pointed out that the text of a Bill submitted by the national lottery to my Department in 2018, the text of the National Lottery (Protection of Central Fund) Bill 2018, a Private Members' Bill initiated by Deputy Jim O'Callaghan in September 2018, and the text of amendment No. 12 are essentially the same.</p> <p>The essence of the proposal from the Senators is to enhance the monopoly position of the private operator of the national lottery by ending the currently licensed possibility for licensed bookmakers, both land-based and remote, to offer bets on the outcome of the national lottery draws.  Should such a proposition be accepted, I foresee legal uncertainty and potential challenges from such bookmakers.  I am not aware of advice to suggest that the outcome of weekly national lottery draws are somehow sacrosanct and exempt from being bet upon.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy David Stanton:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1053"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1053&amp;amp;pid=DavidStanton&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Such is the position with football matches or races.  I may bet on their outcome without hindrance by the organisers of the event, and I am aware of no argument to suggest that the national lottery draw numbers are afforded some special form of intellectual property protection.  A particular concern of mine would be that if this amendment were to be accepted, how long it might be before we see a suggested amendment to the Gaming and Lotteries Act 1979 to prohibit the local lotteries that support our sports clubs and community organisations.  A similar argument could be made that they impact on the turnover of the national lottery.  I do not believe that Senators would countenance this possibility.  For the reasons I have outlined, the Government position must continue to be opposed to this proposal.  The advice of the Office of the Attorney General is in agreement with this position.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#GG00200"><p>The Minister has neatly batted away the two amendments we are discussing quite convincingly.  The first was on the grounds that if a Government amendment is accepted, this matter will be resolved.  That is fairly satisfactory, and one assumes that this Government amendment will pass.  The second was because he does not have responsibility.  It is not part of his ministerial responsibility so that seems to be that.  However, I would make a couple of comments on what the Minister of State said.  The national lottery gained &euro;805 million last year, as I understand it, and I am sure I will be corrected if I am wrong.  First, that shows there is an enormous amount of gambling going on in the country.  It is a huge, vast sum of money.  The usual little caveats are put in when advertising it, telling people to please gamble responsibly, which is a bit like telling people to please drink responsibly.  There was &euro;805 million and the Minister of State said that &euro;225 million went on good causes.  That leaves an enormous gap of nearly &euro;600 million.  Can the Minister of State tell us where this money goes?  That is an enormous amount of money and it suggests that only about a quarter of the money generated goes to good causes.  Therefore, three quarters go somewhere else.  That is rather worrying.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#GG00300"><p>The points made by the Minister of State are very relevant.  In the context of the debate and the amendment, we cannot ignore that there has been an increase in gambling, for whatever reason.  The previous section was dealing with the issue in terms of the report, but my concern is that this is no longer about using one's identification at the door of a casino and walking in and gambling.  This is about access to gambling in our pockets, on our screens and on our devices.  That is the concern many of us have.  To be fair to the Minister of State, he has been very proactive in the matter.  I hope we can come back to speak at the end of the Bill as to its overarching principle.  Is that permissible?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#GG00400"><p>We are dealing with amendments Nos. 1 and 12 at the moment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#GG00500"><p>Will we be allowed come back in at the end of the Bill?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#GG00600"><p>Yes.  Someone may make a brief comment when we have concluded Committee Stage, but this is not Second Stage either.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#GG00700"><p>I know that.</p> <p>The UK Gambling Commission claims that there are 25,000 children between the ages of 11 and 16 who are problem gamblers, and many of them are learning to gamble and bet online.  That means they are using their computer games, and to be fair to the Minister of State again, he has met with myself on the whole issue of loot boxes and with a friend of mine, Mr. Eoin Barry, who has been doing work on the issue of loot boxes and social media.  The big worry I have is that in using online gambling and the lottery, we are sleepwalking into future problems because we are giving people a habit.  I will come back again in a minute if that is okay.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#GG00800"><p>The issue of us turning around and restricting local lotteries is a fairly tenuous argument.  What we are aiming to do here in amendment No. 12 is to deal with unregulated offshore companies which are providing this service where one can bet on the outcome of our lottery.  There is no benefit to the State at all in people being allowed to bet on the outcome of our national lottery.  None whatsoever.  We would prefer that they bear in mind that a large amount of the money that is placed on the national lottery when people put in their numbers does go to the national lottery operator.  I would not be in favour of that, but at least a proportion of the money goes to charities and causes which we can all support, whereas none of the money that is put forward by betting companies when they put out those betting terms on the outcome of the national lottery comes to the State, whether in taxes or in money to charities.  We are not proposing in any way, shape or form to do anything else other than make sure it is part of a betting licence that the holder does not offer the opportunity to bet on the outcome of the national lottery.  If people want to bet on the national lottery, they can do so and there is some benefit to the State.  If they want to bet on the outcome of soccer matches, rugby matches or horse racing, that is what betting offices do.</p> <p>This deals with the national lottery in particular, but Senator Buttimer has pointed out the issue of online gambling, all of which is disastrous.  It is really bad for society because of the fact that it is on one's phone.  There was a man on the radio this morning who used to bet on his laptop as he was driving to work.  This was from before the app was available.  That is how addictive gambling is, and now it is available on one's phone.  I know people in my own town and there are people in every town in the country where this is a huge problem.  Before, there was some restriction in the fact that one had to physically go in to a betting office.  In this particular element we are not talking about silver bullets.  This is incremental.  We have to look at each place where it can be made more regulated regarding the benefit to the State.  Speaking specifically on this amendment, offshore companies offering bets on the outcome of our national lottery is of zero benefit to the State.  That is what we are trying to do with this particular amendment, and we are not trying to do anything other than that.  There are many other amendments we would like to see where the opportunity for problem gambling is restricted.</p> <p>I have spoken to people in Paddy Power, who are watching this as we go.  The dark art works in such a way that they target people.  They know the person who is a problem gambler by the size of his initial bet, and then they put bets in front of him.  They have an individual operator controlling the games, and knowing that that person is a problem gambler, they know that if they do the following, which they have worked it out mathematically, it will entice him to bet again and again.  That used to be the problem if one went to Las Vegas, but Las Vegas is on everyone's phone now.  The State has a responsibility to protect citizens from themselves.  In this amendment we are trying to protect the State so that the money goes to the national lottery, a proportion of which goes to good causes, and that people cannot bet on the outcome of the national lottery.  We want to stop that.  If people are going to bet on the national lottery they must put their money down on the outcome by picking their numbers.  That is simply what we are trying to do in this amendment and nothing else.  It is of some benefit to the State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#GG00900"><p>While I sympathise with the intention of Senator Mark Daly's amendment as I understand it, which is, among other things, to control online betting from this country with companies that are registered offshore, I am not sure that is possible.  It is very difficult to control the Internet and I am not sure what control this country would have over a company.  I do not see how we can force the company to pay tax and I am not sure how the Government or the authorities would come into possession of information that somebody had actually gambled using this method.  Perhaps it is possible, but I have heard the argument made many times that it is impossible to control online gambling and companies that are registered outside of this country.  If it is possible, of course it should be done, but I do not believe it is.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#GG01000"><p>While the Minister of State said that it is not within his remit, we are saying that any legislation is within the Government's remit, whether it be cross-departmental or not.  What we are aiming to do is to make it a condition of the bookmaker's licence that they cannot offer that product.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Mark Daly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2246"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2246&amp;amp;pid=MarkDaly&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->They cannot offer the ability to bet----- </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#HH00200"><p>One will have to get it directly online from the offshore company.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#HH00300"><p>One needs a licence to operate within the jurisdiction.  Even if a company is outside the jurisdiction - and this is the result of being behind the curve regarding the Internet - and if it becomes a condition of a bookmaker's licence to operate within this jurisdiction, it cannot lay a bet on the outcome of the national lottery.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#HH00400"><p>The offshore companies have done so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#HH00500"><p>Then they must be shut down.  One can find anything online if one wants.  A condition of a bookmaker's licence should be not to lay a bet on the outcome of our national lottery.  We are adding this provision to the licensing requirements for bookmakers in order that they would no longer be allowed to do so.  The Minister of State has pointed out that this does not come within his remit but as we are discussing the Gaming and Lotteries (Amendment) Bill we are saying it should be.  As the Senator Norris will be aware, legislation is often cross-departmental and amends other Acts, and that is what we are trying to do here.  We want to make it a condition under the licence that bookmakers cannot offer a bet on the outcome of our national lottery because there is no benefit for the State, especially when it comes to offshore betting.  If an offshore bookmaker is laying bets on the outcome of our national lottery, it is the State's responsibility to say it is breaking the law and, therefore, its site would have to be unavailable in Ireland.  Companies can have their sites wherever they want but we need to control the world wide web as it pertains to Ireland when our laws are being breached, which I know is difficult to do.  The world wide web offers loads of services that are illegal in this State and that is where the other element-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#HH00600"><p>We tried the same with alcohol advertising-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#HH00700"><p>Exactly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#HH00800"><p>-----and it proved not to be possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#HH00900"><p>The intent is to address this because there is no benefit to the State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#HH01000"><p>We will have to consider appointing a Minister with responsibility for the Internet because the Internet is part of daily life.  Many people conduct most of their business online so issues such as this will become significant.  The Minister of State said this area cannot be addressed by this legislation but it should be possible for the State to regulate it.  If the technology exists to actively target a particular group, it equally exists to actively avoid it and, therefore, companies should be compelled in this regard.  We have heard a great deal about this at the Joint Committee on Children and Youth Affairs when it came to the targeting of children with advertisements for alcohol, confectionery and so on.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#HH01100"><p>This issue has nothing to do with alcohol.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#HH01200"><p>No.  People said they could not do it but it can be done.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#HH01300"><p>So the Minister, on that occasion, misled the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#HH01400"><p>No.  I do not know what the Senator is talking about exactly.  The technology exists to target certain groups with advertising on the Internet and, conversely, if companies play ball, the technology exists to actively avoid them.  Whether that is physically possible to enforce is another day's work but it is technically possible and the option should be explored by the Department.  We come across this a lot when it comes to the Internet.  Other states in Europe have done this but we need to consider creating a ministerial post so that a Minister is responsible for the Internet because so much of life is online now, and will protect citizens.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#HH01500"><p>I support Senator Noone's message regarding the need for a different approach and setting up a Department.  The initiative is interesting for a number of reasons.  First, there is the issue of digital safety or Internet usage.  The Acting Chairman will tell me that I cannot name people but I refer to the way in which Facebook, Twitter or whoever interacts with either the US Congress or with us here in Ireland.  Deputy Hildegarde Naughton is the Chair of the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Communications, Climate Action and Environment.  She along with other committee members met Mark Zuckerberg but they had to do across the road; they did not meet in Leinster House.  I am sure the keyboard warriors are ready to start typing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#HH01600"><p>They are typing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#HH01700"><p>This is not just about protecting children; it is also about protecting vulnerable adults.  Even though the world is being made smaller and more accessible and information is at our fingertips, it is important that we consider a few issues.  To be fair, the Minister of State deserves immense credit for the work that he has put into this issue----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#HH01800"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#HH01900"><p>-----the approach he has adopted and for all of the consultation that he and his officials have engaged in.  Anybody who uses his or her phone, laptop or iPad to go on YouTube or Facebook, advertisements will appear, as Senator Noone said.  If it is a casino advertisement, there will be temptation to click on it.  What happens then?  One could be opening a Pandora's box.  That is fine on one level but not on another level.  How does one regulate the use of these ads?  One needs to regulate access to these ads because there is none.  Recently, I travelled on a train where I saw people watch and gamble on virtual racing as opposed to the 2.30 p.m. race at Leopardstown racecourse, which is located close to the home of the Acting Chairman.  From my perusal of legislation, there does not appear to be provision for regulation on the odds or the obligation to pay out for a win.</p> <p>Regarding the national lottery, the licence was sold.  This issue is a minefield and I support Senator Noone's call for technology to not just block the ads but for a governmental change in terms of how we interact with the Internet.  It is something that we have to address.  While climate change has become the issue of a generation, we are sleepwalking into problems associated with gambling addiction.  I am concerned for the future as I have learned a bit about gambling addiction.  Similarly to Deputy Martin Heydon in the D&aacute;il and the Minister of State, I have spoken to people about the issue and this legislation is a very good start.  However, the future must be circled as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1277" speakername="David Stanton" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#HH02000"><p>I again thank Senators for their contributions and acknowledge the sincerity and seriousness by which colleagues here take this significant issue.</p> <p>This Bill is interim legislation.  As I have said here previously and in the other House as well, we are working hard on bringing forward a Bill to regulate the entire sector and to set up a gambling regulator.  That is a very large piece of work and we expect to employ more than 100 people.  Recently I held a seminar where we brought everyone associated with this area together, including those involved in the industry and in all of the problem gambling centres and treatment facilities.  All of the individuals and groups made a contribution.  We are listening to all of them and everybody wants a regulator.  Our aim is to establish a national regulator for gambling that is underpinned by legislation and we are serious about the issue.  Recently I secured permission from the Government to go ahead with the initiative and we have support for that from both Houses.  We are all working together and I am open to suggestions and proposals for how to move this forward.  We have also engaged with colleagues from different parts of the world that have a regulator in place.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy David Stanton:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1053"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1053&amp;amp;pid=DavidStanton&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->As Senators Noone, Buttimer and others have noted this particular area changes by the day with technology, artificial intelligence, the Internet and so on.  It is very challenging and difficult.  However, we are working hard on it and we are determined to go ahead and get it done.</p><p>Amendment No. 1 is not required as we already have a reference to the 1931 Act in a later Government amendment.  It pertains to that and that only.  If that amendment is passed, it is covered, and if it is not passed, there is no need for this.  I ask that would be withdrawn.</p><p>On amendment No. 12, Senator Mark Daly is correct that the licensing companies do pay the licence fee and a 2% turnover tax.  Some five or six companies do this.  The national lottery is a very big advertiser compared with the companies that are allowing or promoting betting on the numbers.  The national lottery is a monolith.  It is massive in comparison.  I am concerned that this legislation is not the place to do this.  I know what the Senator said and I acknowledge that it can be done if we want to but this is not the place to do so.  It was not the intention of the Bill, which is to update the 1956 Act in certain areas to remove uncertainty in the courts and in the system about stakes and prizes and raise the age to 18 years across the board, which everyone agrees with, as well as a few other technical things which were needed immediately.  We are anxious to move this through.  I am concerned that if we accept the amendment we might delay the Bill, and I want it to pass before the summer recess if possible.</p><p>The issue of the national lottery is a matter for the Minister of Public Expenditure and Reform.  It is his particular responsibility.  We are in discussions with him on the regulation of all gambling and whether all gambling regulation should come under the auspices of a gambling regulator in time.  That is part of the discussions we are having.  It was proposed when the lottery was first established and its regulator was established.  I suggest that is when we can look at this legislation but this Bill is not designed for that.  It is not focusing on the national lottery which is not under the remit of the Department of Justice and Equality but of the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform.  The Minister recently debated this issue with colleagues in the D&aacute;il.  He has not come down on any particular view on this point yet.  I ask that we park the amendment for now as it is not really part of the Bill, so that we can proceed with the Bill and have it enacted.  We can keep the conversation and the debate open on the wider area of gambling.  I know Senator Norris has a real personal interest, for which I thank him, on problem gambling.  I acknowledge that this is a huge issue in Ireland and is something we are very aware of.  If someone has an addition, it could be argued that it is also a health matter and that they need health and treatment in that regard, so the Department of Health and the HSE would come into play.</p><p>The regulation of gambling can help a bit - it can make it fairer - and things can be done around it, which is another day's work, but that only goes so far.  I would not like to give the impression that establishing a gambling regulator would solve all the problems around gambling and gambling addition.  I have had discussions and meetings with colleagues in other jurisdictions which have had very robust gambling commissions and regulators for some time but they still have serious issues with problem gambling.  I am not saying a regulator would not have some impact - it would - but I want to caution against it being seen as a panacea or a silver bullet for problem gambling because it is not.  If someone has an addition, he or she will find a way around it.  We are talking about self-exclusion registers.  I have discussed this with others in other jurisdictions and they have big question marks over these.  A person might self-exclude from five different agents but not from the sixth and they will find a way.  There are things we can do with a regulator but if someone has a problem with gambling, he or she needs to get treatment and help because it is a health matter.  We should focus on that end, although we need to have a regulator as well.</p><p>I thank colleagues for the debate and discussion but I ask that this amendment would not be pressed now.  Let us keep the question open.  It is not crucial to move it forward now but the context of the overall gambling regulation and legislation that we are working on is probably the better time to have that discussion and debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#JJ00200"><p>I commend the Minister of State on his last comment that there is no silver bullet.  He is right.  We require a whole-of-government approach.  As the Minister of State noted, it is a matter of health, education, and justice, and ultimately it is about changing minds.  One can have all the regulation and regulators in the world but one must change the human condition and the culture.  When a person lands in Las Vegas, the first thing he or she will encounter is slot machines at the carousel in the airport.  It is the culture.  It is not only the casino or the betting shop that we must worry about but online gambling.  The Minister of State's remarks were the most pertinent point we have heard all day.  It is about those things I mentioned, but it is also about all of us collectively changing our mindsets and having role models who have the courage to talk about their experiences, their past and leading us in how we can change behaviour.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#JJ00300"><p>Will the Minister of State address the concerns I expressed about the apparent fact that only a quarter of the lottery proceeds go to good works and where the rest of it, the &euro;600 million, goes?  That seems like a very poor return.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#JJ00400"><p>Following what Senator Buttimer said, there is no silver bullet, we all know that, but the fact that there are gambling machines in the airport in Las Vegas is down to a lack of regulation.  If they are not there, people do not bet.  If they were in Dublin Airport, would people use them?  Of course they would, but the reason we do not allow them in Dublin Airport is that we do not want to encourage it.  The State's role is one of protecting citizens from themselves in many cases.</p> <p>There was a situation at one stage, as Minister of State will be aware, where citizens were able to buy synthetic drugs and we introduced legislation to shut down these establishments so that they could not sell them.  The lack of availability meant that there was less uptake.  I knew parents in Killarney who thought that it was okay to buy synthetic cocaine because it was available in the shop.  They thought that because it was available.  We knew it was bad for citizens, but they were buying it for their children because their attitude was, God help us, that if the State was allowing it to be sold, then it must be okay.  We had to shut the shops down, which the State did, and that was the State acting to protect citizens from themselves.  Something that was very harmful, all manner of synthetic drugs, was available because we had not made our way around the legislation.</p> <p>It is interesting that the Minister said that the idea of a regulator was discussed when the national lottery was being set up, which was more than 30 years ago.  The regulator is not in place yet and we are still talking about it.  We should use any vehicle we can to make changes to protect citizens, although this amendment is to protect the State.  I believe we are all in agreement on the issue of problem gambling.  The more opportunities that people have to gamble, the more opportunities there are to create problem gamblers.  Australia is a great example of that where it is possible to bet inside a pub.  We do not allow it in Ireland and this is because it has creates problems.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Mark Daly :</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Obviously, the ability to make a good judgment when one has taken alcohol is diminished and therefore we do not allow it.  That is to protect the citizen from himself or herself.  The problem now is that one can bet from one's phone and one can do it from anywhere.  That requires regulation in whatever shape or form we can do it.  The individual is up against a monolith when it comes to online gambling.  These people are hiring the best actuaries, the best in terms of trying to draw as much money out of people as possible.  That is not what this amendment is about.</p><p>This amendment is a minor amendment on the issue of those who are offering people the opportunity to bet on the outcome of the national lottery.  I know we have drifted into other areas but I think there is no silver bullet.  This is not the silver bullet either, it is just one more area instead of the money going outside the State when people bet on the outcome of the lottery.  If they are going to bet on the lottery, they bet on the lottery and there is some return.  I agree with Senator Norris when he talks about some but limited return in terms of the amount of money that is bet on the national lottery compared with the amount of money that goes to the good causes.  There is a significant gulf but at least some of the money goes to good causes whereas none of the money spent on the betting on the outcome of the lottery comes to the State in any way, shape or form to be redistributed to good causes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1277" speakername="David Stanton" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#KK00200"><p>Let me respond to Senator Norris's question.  The national lottery is the big one, the sums of money are enormous.  The rest of the money goes on prizes, administration and advertising.  It is a major advertiser.</p> <p>Senator Mark Daly has acknowledged that in order to offer a betting service in Ireland, one must be licensed.  If one is licensed one has to pay taxes and licensing fees.  Those companies pay licensing fees and taxes here, so they are actually contributing to the State in that way.  It is a tiny element.  </p> <p>We might prevent the betting on the national lottery, but that will not prevent people from betting on the Italian lottery, the English lottery and all the other lotteries.  It will just stop betting on the national lottery and people will continue to bet.  This Bill was not designed initially to do that.  While I agree that one can bring in amendments and change the Bill, the thrust of the Bill is different.  I ask Members to wait until we bring the major legislation, which we are working very hard on and setting up a lottery, which is a mammoth task.  The Senator is very astute in pointing out that it is a significant task.  </p> <p>The industry in all its manifestations states it wants regulation.  It said that again in Farmleigh House a couple of weeks ago when more than 120 people attended a seminar and none said he or she did not want regulation.  Everybody wants regulation.  There is nobody pushing against it.  We are getting no lobbying about not having regulation.  The industry wants it.  We are anxious to move it forward as quickly as we can, but it is a significant job of work.  I want to get it right this time.  I ask Senators, with respect, that we have debated this important issue but it is not a significant issue in the overall scheme of things.  In the overall scheme, Senator Norris is correct, the national lottery is extremely successful, massive sums of money are being made compared with what this amendment will address, which is tiny.</p> <p>I think this is not the Bill to do this.  I hope that answers the questions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#KK00300"><p>I wish to pursue the Minister of State a little further but I quite understand if he does not have the answers immediately to hand.  Will he give us some information either now or by dropping me an email on the amount that is spent on prizes and how much is spent on advertising.  I have a feeling that there is enormous profit for the company running the lottery.  I was very much against privatising the lottery.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1277" speakername="David Stanton" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#KK00400"><p>The lottery is run by a private company, so it is private.  I am not sure whether that information is publicly available.  We can endeavour to see if we can get that information.  It is a private operation.  It is a large successful operation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#KK00500"><p>I presume it has to register its profits with the Revenue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#KK00600"><p>I think the Minister of State has made a very compelling case to the House in terms of the need to allow the amendment to lapse because it is the wrong place, anti-competitive, and in terms of marketing activity.  I appeal to Senator Mark Daly and to Fianna F&aacute;il not to press the amendment.  I think the Minister of State has made a good point and a very compelling case.  I support him in that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#KK00700"><p>Is the amendment being pressed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#KK00800"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.146/1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#KK01000"><p>Amendment put:</p><p>The Committee divided: Tá, 10; Níl, 18.</p><br/><br/><p>Tellers: Tá, Deputies Gerry Horkan and Mark Daly; Níl, Deputies Gabrielle McFadden and John O'Mahony.</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.146/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2019-05-29" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#KK01000">
            <divisioncount ayes="10" noes="18" abstain="0" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1408" vote="aye">Frances Black</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" vote="aye">Rose Conway Walsh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" vote="aye">Gerard Craughwell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" vote="aye">Mark Daly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" vote="aye">Gerry Horkan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" vote="aye">P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" vote="aye">R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" vote="aye">David Norris</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" vote="aye">Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" vote="aye">Fintan Warfield</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" vote="no">Colm Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1380" vote="no">Paddy Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" vote="no">Jerry Buttimer</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" vote="no">Maria Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1422" vote="no">Paudie Coffey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" vote="no">Paul Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" vote="no">Martin Conway</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1429" vote="no">Billy Lawless</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1438" vote="no">Anthony Lawlor</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" vote="no">Tim Lombard</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" vote="no">Gabrielle McFadden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" vote="no">Michelle Mulherin</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" vote="no">Catherine Noone</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1431" vote="no">P&aacute;draig &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1374" vote="no">Kieran O'Donnell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" vote="no">John O'Mahony</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" vote="no">Joe O'Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" vote="no">James Reilly</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="abstain">
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.146/3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#KK01000"><p>Amendment declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#MM00100"><p>On a point of order, I was told recently that I could not move an amendment as I had been asked to do by the Labour Party, which is part of the Technical Group of which I am also a part.  I understand Senator Mark Daly's name is not on the amendment and I believe no communication was made with the Cathaoirleach's office.  That reinforces my point that this is the noxious introduction of a completely new and arbitrary rule and I object to it.  It has never been done before.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#MM00200"><p>Apparently it is a long-standing rule and practice of the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#MM00300"><p>I have been a Member for over 30 years and I do not remember it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#MM00400"><p>That does not mean the Senator is right.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#MM00500"><p>If it is a party, as in the case of Senator Mark Daly, the Chair will normally allow that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#MM00600"><p>I am a member of the Technical Group.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#MM00700"><p>There is a distinction that we all accept between a group and a party.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#MM00800"><p>That is rubbish.  You are equivocating.  It is nonsense.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#MM00900"><p>Respect the Chair.  It is independent.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#MM01000"><p>The Senator should have respect for the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#MM01100"><p>I do.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#MM01200"><p>Stop squeaking and interrupting like a clockwork mouse.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#MM01300"><p>Stop being personal just because the Senator is wrong.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#MM01400"><p>This is the last I will say on the matter.  It is a long-standing practice of the Chair, whether you agree or disagree with it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#MM01500"><p>It is not.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#MM01600"><p>I am moving on.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#MM01700"><p>The Senator does not know everything.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#MM01800"><p>It is open to the Members to change Standing Orders.  If they wish to do so they can write to the Committee on Procedure and Privileges.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#MM01900"><p>It is not in Standing Orders.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#MM02000"><p>It is in Standing Orders.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#MM02100"><p>Check them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#MM02200"><p>The basic rule is in Standing Orders and it is up to the Cathaoirleach to decide how to apply it.  I am merely enforcing a precedent that has generally been observed in the House.  I am moving on.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.169" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Section 1 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.170" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>SECTION 2</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#MM02500"><p>Amendments Nos. 2 and 3 are related and may be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.172" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 2:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.173" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1277" speakername="David Stanton" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#MM02700"><p>Amendment No. 2 is a textual amendment removing a full stop to reflect the fact that a further definition is being proposed for insertion.  Amendment No. 3 is occasioned by section 7 of the Bill, which inserts a new section 19A in the principal Act.  In the proposed new section 19A(3)(d) there is a reference to relevant officers.  This is based on the comparable provisions in sections 8A(2)(d) and 8B(2)(c) of the Betting Act 1931, as amended.  While the term "relevant officer" is defined in section 1 of the Betting Act 1931, there is no similar definition in the principal Act, which is the Gaming and Lotteries Act 1956.  This omission is now being addressed by providing for a similar definition in section 2 of the Bill as is already contained in section 1 of the Betting Act 1931.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.174" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.175" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 3:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.176" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.177" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Section 2, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.178" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>SECTION 3</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.179" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That section 3 stand part of the Bill."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#MM03400"><p>In the United States the Loot Box Bill has been introduced by Senator Josh Hawley of Missouri on the issue of gaming.  It has bipartisan support, and such agreement is rare in America.  We must try to work with the gaming industry to deliver innovative and compelling changes regarding loot boxes.  There is nothing innovative or compelling about loot boxes - it is gambling.  If one looks at the psychology used to market gambling, the laws regarding gaming are less scrutinised.  It is important that we examine the issue of e-gambling and loot boxes in order that there can be more regulation.  The issue of permits and licences arises here so we can adapt to and work within the digital space more easily and effectively to ensure children and vulnerable people are protected and that anybody who participates in e-gambling will be treated fairly.  As I said earlier, the casinos of tomorrow will not be only on the high street.  They will be on our screens and in our pockets.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.181" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.182" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>SECTION 4</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.183" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#MM03700"><p>Amendments Nos. 4 and 5 are related and may be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.184" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 4:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.185" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.186" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 5:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.187" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.188" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Section 4, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.189" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sections 5 and 6 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.190" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>SECTION 7</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.191" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 6:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.192" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.193" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Section 7, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.194" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sections 8 to 11, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.195" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>SECTION 12</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.196" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#MM05000"><p>Amendments Nos. 7 and 8 are related, as amendment No. 8 is consequential on amendment No. 7.  Amendments Nos. 7 and 8 may be discussed together, by agreement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.197" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 7:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.198" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.199" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 8:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.200" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.201" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Section 12, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.202" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sections 13 to 18, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.203" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>SECTION 19</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.204" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 9:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.205" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.206" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Section 19, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.207" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sections 20 to 25, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.208" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>NEW SECTIONS</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.209" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#MM06200"><p>Amendments Nos. 10 and 13 are related as amendment No. 13 is consequential on amendment No. 10.  Amendments Nos. 10 and 13 may be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.210" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 10:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.211" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.212" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#MM06500"><p>I move amendment No. 11:</p><blockquote>In page 16, between lines 16 and 17, to insert the following:<b>&ldquo;Report on prevalence of problem gambling</b><br /><br /><b>26. </b>The Minister shall, within three months of the passing of this Act, prepare and lay before the Oireachtas a report on the prevalence of problem gambling in Ireland.&rdquo;.</blockquote> <p>We discussed this with regard to problem gambling and the Minister of State outlined some of the discussions he has had in Farmleigh and other places with various stakeholders.  This amendment provides that within three months of the passing of the legislation, which is some time away, the Government will lay a report on problem gambling in Ireland before the Oireachtas.  That comprehensive report would outline recommendations and actions.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Mark Daly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2246"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2246&amp;amp;pid=MarkDaly&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I attended a good presentation on a report brought forward by Senator &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh, which sets out how the issues faced by small and medium-sized businesses need to be tackled and contains in excess of 100 recommendations.  As Senator Marshall has said, those recommendations should be grouped on the basis of timelines - those which could be done immediately, those which could be done in the medium term and those which could be done in the long term - and responsibility for implementing them should be allocated to specified bodies.  Rather than merely setting out recommendations, all reports which contain recommendations should also allocate responsibility for implementing those recommendations and set out timelines for their implementation.  I ask the Minister of State to accept the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.214" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#NN00200"><p>I support this amendment.  Three months seems like quite a short time.  I take it that there would be no requirement to take account of the operation of the Bill.  It is not dealing with the operation of the Bill; it is dealing with the problem of people having an addiction to gambling.  I support that strongly.  I imagine that the Minister of State will support it too.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.215" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#NN00300"><p>We are on Committee Stage and we are not likely to get beyond that today.  If this amendment is passed, it will put the Government on notice that it will have three months from the date on which this Bill is enacted, which is months away yet.  We are setting a tight timeline.  Much of the work, including the consultation with stakeholders, has started.  The issue here is the setting of a tight timeline.  We could provide for a six-month timeline and change it on Report Stage.  The Government has six months, in effect, because it will be at least three months before this Bill is signed by the President and enacted.  This provision will come into effect three months from that date.  The timeline could extend to 12 months depending on what the Minister of State would like to do.  He might say in his reply that this is about changing the 1956 Act.  When the national lottery was being established more than 30 years ago, it was suggested that there might be a regulator.  There is still no regulator.  We should wait for more discussion on a regulator.  The report that will be drawn up if this proactive amendment to the Bill is accepted will outline the problems with betting and lottery activity.  We all know that such problems exist.  We need to make sure we put in place a report that will be enacted.  Actions will have to be put in place by the Government on foot of the report.  I am seeking to include in legislation a requirement for the Government to put a report together, rather than promising that a report will be put together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.216" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1277" speakername="David Stanton" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#NN00400"><p>I acknowledge the thrust and intention of the Senator's amendment.  I have some good news for him.  I share with Senators-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.217" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#NN00500"><p>I am delighted to hear good news.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.218" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1277" speakername="David Stanton" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#NN00600"><p>The Senator will be even more delighted in a minute.  I hope we can have a meeting of minds on this.  There are deep concerns about the best way to address the issue of harmful gambling, which has an impact on the lives of people who are addicted, on their families and on wider society.  There is no doubt that we all share these concerns.  I agree that we must seek to better understand the issues involved and to obtain credible evidence of the nature and extent of the problems arising from gambling, which is a large and complex activity.  As we said earlier, increasingly it is taking place in an online environment.</p> <p>On 27 February last, this House debated a motion relating to the report of the interdepartmental working group on the future licensing and regulation of gambling, which was impending at that time.  During that debate, I mentioned that the drug prevalence survey for 2014-15 had been published by the Minister of State with responsibility for health promotion and the national drug strategy, Deputy Catherine Byrne, and myself.  The survey, which represented the first set of data on the extent of gambling in Ireland, was based on fieldwork carried out between August 2014 and August 2015.  This general population survey of more than 7,000 people was a collaborative project between the national advisory committee on drugs and alcohol and the public administration and health research branch of the Department of Health in Northern Ireland.  Ipsos MRBI in Ireland carried out the fieldwork on this occasion.  My Department contributed to the costs of the survey, which provided a baseline of data to assist in policy formulation and future planning and action on gambling.  The survey found that the prevalence of problem gambling in the general population was 0.8% and that problem gambling was most common among young males, occurring in 1.9% of males between the ages of 18 and 24 and 2.9% of males between the ages of 25 and 34.</p> <p>The Senator is probably ahead of himself in some of this.  This is usual and not surprising.  The good news is that the Health Research Board, HRB, is undertaking a 2018-19 prevalence study to assist in policy formulation, planning and action in this area.  The results of this survey, which are expected in 2020, will contain a specific section on gambling prevalence with an extended range of questions.  The Departments of Justice and Equality and Health are contributing to the cost of the study.  The Senator is ahead of the game in proposing this.  I am sure he will be pleased to know it is happening already.</p> <p>Senators should note that neither I nor the Department of Justice and Equality has direct responsibility for the wide range of interests concerned with gambling, problem gambling or addiction generally.  Such responsibility rests with my colleague, the Minister of State, Deputy Catherine Byrne, and the Department of Health.  Problem gambling and, in particular, gambling addiction are health matters.  Somebody who needs treatment for an addiction must go down that route.  We can do a certain amount through regulation - we can help and assist - but if someone has a serious addiction, it is a health issue.</p> <p>While I welcome the concern and intention behind the amendment, I believe the work that is being done by the HRB will address the concerns that exist.  A great deal of money is being spent on the survey, which is already happening.  I cannot see any circumstances in which the amendment could be achieved with the resources and expertise currently available to my Department.  It is again a health issue.  As I have said, a survey is happening.  It is not sensible to engage a professional market research company at considerable expense to conduct further research, particularly when the Departments of Health and Justice and Equality are contributing in a significant way to the 2018-19 prevalence study, which is under way.  The research the Senator is looking for is happening.  In light of this, I ask him to consider withdrawing his amendment and to await the results of the prevalence study, which will come out around the time envisaged by the Senator.  His support for this initiative would be welcome.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.219" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#NN00700"><p>I welcome the news that a survey is being done, or that there is talk about it being done.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.220" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1277" speakername="David Stanton" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#NN00800"><p>It is being done.  It is happening now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.221" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#NN00900"><p>It will come out in 2020.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.222" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1277" speakername="David Stanton" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#NN01000"><p>Yes, it will.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.223" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#NN01100"><p>Experienced Senators such as Senator Norris and I will be aware that there is no measurement of the outcome or impact of much of the legislation that is passed in this House.  Such measurement should take place.  According to an expression that is used in business, "If it is not being measured, it is not being done".  We often fail to measure whether legislation that has been passed by this House is being implemented.  We need to consider the impact that such legislation is having and whether it needs to be amended to make sure it has the intended impact.  I will give some brief examples.  As a result of legislation that was passed by the Oireachtas more than 20 years ago, the courts have the power to put electronic tags on people who are out on parole or on early release.  However, the necessary statutory instruments were never put in place by the Department of Justice and Equality.  We are still talking about electronic tagging.  Legislation passed by this House is not being implemented by the Government.</p> <p>The Minister of State will be more aware of the next example I will mention.  The Irish Sign Language Act 2017 gives the Government three years to put in place structures to enable members of the deaf community to access Government services.  The Act requires all Departments to put in place interpreting facilities and systems to facilitate any member of the deaf community who arrives at an accident and emergency unit, appears before a court or calls into a Garda station.  There are 12 months of that three-year period left, but no provision has been made by any Department to date.  We insisted that the legislation would provide for a three-year implementation period.  In 2020, when the next 12 months have passed, the Government will be breaking the law.  Timelines are important because things do not get done without them.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Mark Daly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2246"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2246&amp;amp;pid=MarkDaly&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->If the Bill required the Government to undertake a report without placing a timeline on it, I guarantee that the report may or may not be done in 2020.  It might be an idea to make a further amendment so that there would be a report on problem gambling every year.  The recommendations made in a previous year's report and on which we all agreed could be analysed by the Houses and we could ask what had or had not been implemented.  That is measurement of progress.  We have had too many reports that have made recommendations but on which there was no follow-up.  That is why we are insisting on the inclusion of a reference to a report, with all of the recommendations such a report would have, being compiled by the Government within three months of the Bill's passage.  All too often, issues are placed on the back burner and are not addressed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.225" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#OO00200"><p>The Senator is relatively unimpressed with the good news.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.226" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#OO00300"><p>To be clear, I am delighted with the good news.  We all like to have something in writing, but I would prefer this measure to be included in legislation so that not only will promises be made in this House, but they will also be delivered on.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.227" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#OO00400"><p>Is the Minister of State's word not good enough?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.228" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.229" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#OO00600"><p>For a man who was involved in a Seanad campaign, Senator Conway should know that someone's word is often not as good as it should be.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.230" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#OO00700"><p>This Minister of State is different.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.231" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#OO00800"><p>I was not talking about him.  I was talking about other people's word.  As the Leas-Chathaoirleach knows, people's word is not always their bond when it comes to Seanad campaigns.  That was my point.  I know the Minister of State well from other areas.  I fully take on board what he has promised and I am sure it will happen.  I just want it provided for in legislation that, if he is moved higher up the ranks and promoted, as he might well be due to the current Government problems-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.232" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.233" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#OO01000"><p>-----the person who inherits his job will be forced to publish the report regardless of whether he or she wants to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.234" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1277" speakername="David Stanton" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#OO01100"><p>I take the Senator's point, but significant moneys are already being expended by the Department of Health and my Department on the prevalence study, which does not just relate to gambling, but also drugs.  We are serious about this.  The Senator is right about the need to measure.  The money is being spent and the study is happening right now.  As soon as it is ready, it will be published.  We are all anxious to see and discuss it.  The amendment risks forcing us to undertaking a second study in parallel that duplicates the other and wastes money.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.235" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1422" speakername="Paudie Coffey" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#OO01200"><p>There is no need for it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.236" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1277" speakername="David Stanton" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#OO01300"><p>What the Senator is looking for is already happening.  There is no need for the amendment.  I respectfully ask him to withdraw it.  Let us not waste money.  Let the work that is under way continue and let us get on with the business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.237" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1422" speakername="Paudie Coffey" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#OO01400"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.238" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#OO01500"><p>That report is the one we want.  We do not want another one.  We are just trying to put in writing that it will happen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.239" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1277" speakername="David Stanton" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#OO01600"><p>It is happening.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.240" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#OO01700"><p>I know, but the Minister of State should bear something in mind.  I do not know which report on Seanad reform we are on at the moment.  There is one thing about reports-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.241" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1277" speakername="David Stanton" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#OO01800"><p>There is a risk that we could double the money to do the same thing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.242" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#OO01900"><p>We want it stated in legislation that this report will be done.  I am not asking the Minister of State to duplicate the ongoing report.  I am just saying that it is the report we want and that we want its production within three months of the Bill's passage stated in legislation.  As the Minister of State pointed out, some surveys were done in 2015 and their reports came three years later.  We need the reports to be actioned on the basis of current information, which the Minister of State says is being compiled now.  I am delighted to hear that, but we would like to see the report published in a timely manner.  Just to be clear, I am not asking for it to be duplicated or for more money to be spent.  That money is already being spent and we just want to make sure the report is published.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.243" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#OO02000"><p>Is the Senator withdrawing his amendment?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.244" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#OO02100"><p>No.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.245/1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#OO02200"></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.245/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2019-05-29" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#OO02200">
            <divisioncount ayes="0" noes="0" abstain="0" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="abstain">
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.245/3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#OO02200"><p>&nbsp;<img src="../images/clock5.gif" border="0"/>&nbsp;<i>5 o&rsquo;clock</i></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.246" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Progress reported; Committee to sit again.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.247" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#QQ00100">Mental Health Services: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.248" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#QQ00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Jim Daly, to the House.  I understand the motion will be seconded by Senator Freeman.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.249" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#QQ00300"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That Seanad &Eacute;ireann:<br /><br />notes that:- adequate mental health services are vital to secure the dignity and wellbeing of all those within the State, including asylum seekers within the direct provision system;<br /><br />- Ireland's spend on mental health services is now just 6.6% of the total health budget, compared to 13% in the 1980s;<br /><br />- there are now 472 consultant psychiatrists in Ireland, approximately 240 less than are recommended by the Hanley Report to provide safe and effective psychiatric services, and that 20% of consultant posts are currently vacant;<br /><br />- Ireland has the fourth-lowest number of in-patient psychiatric beds in the European Union, at 2.3 beds per 1,000 population;<br /><br />- almost 2,700 children and adolescents are awaiting appointments with psychiatrists, with almost 400 waiting over 1 year; and<br /><br />- there continues to be major shortfalls in 24-hour access to mental health services, including weekend and out-of-hours services; recognises in particular that:- persons seeking asylum in the State who are within the direct provision regime have particular mental health needs which are not being addressed;<br /><br />- the Royal College of Surgeons has found that depression and mental health problems are five times higher among asylum seekers in direct provision than in Irish society generally;<br /><br />- the mental health and psychological development of young people is particularly affected by long stays in the direct provision system; and<br /><br />- many of those who have undergone trauma prior to or in the process of seeking asylum, and particularly those who have fled war and/or persecution, may have complex mental health needs which require intervention;and calls on the Government to: - ensure that staff shortages in this sector are resourced as a priority in order to meet current requirements;<br /><br />- work with the College of Psychiatrists of Ireland to maximise the number of specialist training posts for psychiatrists, to alleviate the shortage of suitable candidates for vacant positions;<br /><br />- ensure that a designated consultant psychiatrist is identified in each area in which a direct provision reception centre is located;<br /><br />- establish multidisciplinary teams led by consultants on a regional basis, to support all mental health services that provide treatment to asylum seekers; <br /><br />- introduce early and adequate assessment of asylum seekers for mental health issues and referral to specialised services as required;<br /><br />- ensure that specialised services, such as psychotherapy for survivors of torture and other violence, can be accessed by those who need them; and<br /><br />- ensure that interpreters are available to assist professionals to deliver services, and that existing core staff receive additional linguistic training where possible.</blockquote> <p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it, an Teachta Jim Daly.  Creidim gur &oacute;c&aacute;id th&aacute;bhachtach &iacute; seo.  T&aacute; &aacute;bhar an-t&aacute;bhachtach &aacute; phl&eacute; againn inniu.  It is fair to say that Ireland's attitudes to mental health have transformed for the better over the past five decades.  The most recent staging post in the development of our services was the Government strategy, A Vision for Change, which was launched in 2006.  Thirteen years on, its implementation has been uneven at best.  There has been partial delivery across all its core elements, but a substantial amount remains to be done.  Progress on the strategy was hindered by severe staff shortages and funding cuts during the recession.  I will give two examples.  Despite the recommendations of the strategy and the code of practice issued by the Mental Health Commission, children continue to be admitted into adult mental health inpatient services.  There were 84 such admissions in 2018.  The strategy puts a focus on the need to provide mental health treatment in primary and community care settings and to avoid premature recourse to specialists.  The failure to make such provision is forcing people onto psychiatrists' waiting lists.  Almost 2,700 children and adolescents are awaiting appointments with psychiatrists at present, approximately 400 of whom have been waiting for more than a year.  I understand that some 6,000 people are waiting for appointments with psychologists, approximately 1,600 of whom have been waiting for over a year.  These figures are stark.</p><p>There are continuing shortfalls in 24-7 access to mental health services.  All these problems are persisting despite record funding of our health service.  The State is spending more than &euro;20 billion on health this year.  According to an OECD study last year, we spend &euro;4,706 <i>per capita</i>on health each year, which is approximately 30% more than the average across the OECD.  Are the mental health services available to our young people 30% better?  I am afraid not.  Have they improved in line with the increase in the health budget?  Absolutely not.  If anything, our mental health services are treading water, at best.  Far from being among the best internationally, we are very much towards the bottom of the table.  We have the fourth lowest number of inpatient psychiatric beds in the EU, where community care is desired.  We have approximately 2.3 psychiatric beds per 1,000 people.  As I said last week, our spend on mental health services as a proportion of the overall health spend is just half of what it was in the 1980s, which was a time of crippling unemployment and economic stagnation.  We spend 6.6% of the overall health budget on mental health services, compared to 13% in the 1980s.  I admit that the total amount was lower back then.  As this House will recall, the Government has twice - in 2012 and in 2016 - raided the budget for mental health to plug holes elsewhere in the health service.  This will not have helped the yawning gap in the number of psychiatrists in Ireland.  According to the Hanly report, an additional 240 consultants are needed to provide a safe service.  Some 20% of posts are currently vacant and approximately one third of the posts that are filled are filled by locums, which is not satisfactory. </p><p>One of the greatest tragedies of modem Ireland is the prevalence of the mental health problems faced by young people.  I am honoured to have Senator Freeman, who needs no lessons on the importance of this topic, here to second this motion.  W.B. Yeats wrote that this &quot;is no country for old men&quot;, but is it a country for young people, given that so many of them are forced to struggle - often alone - with problems which make them question the value of their own lives?  There is an average of just over one suicide per day in Ireland.  While men account for 80% of suicides, a recent study showed that the rate of suicide among young and adolescent girls in Ireland is the highest in the EU.  Some 9,103 people presented to hospital due to self-harm in 2017, which represented an increase of 21% on the 2007 figure.  Remarkably, or perhaps unremarkably, self-harm is 30 times higher among homeless people.  This reality is all the more startling when we consider that more than 10,000 people are homeless in Ireland at present.  Factors such as alcohol and drug abuse, decreased involvement in social and sporting activities, a decrease in religious belief, spiritual life and religious observance and pressure to perform well academically are recognised as being linked to the problem we are discussing.  Bullying on social media is a factor we must consider.  As a society, we need to get grips with the ugliness that has entered much of our discourse in politics and across all levels of society.  I am mindful that Senator Freeman has sponsored the Children&rsquo;s Digital Protection Bill 2018.  I hope her Bill will give the Seanad a good opportunity to develop our discussion of this dimension of these issues.</p><p>The issue of direct provision has also been discussed in the Seanad on many occasions.  Sadly, the plight of people in direct provision has not improved much since I introduced a Private Members' motion on the subject in September 2014.  At that time, more than 4,000 asylum seekers were in direct provision centres.  This number has increased to 6,100.  As we know, many of the 40 centres are above their capacity.  While waiting times have reduced somewhat, applicants still have to wait between 18 and 20 months for initial hearings.  For children in the system, a significant portion of their young lives are lost in the limbo of direct provision.  As many Senators have said on many occasions, the direct provision system is an affront to the dignity of human beings.  The working group on the protection process and direct provision, chaired by Mr. Justice Bryan McMahon, recommended that people in direct provision should be given the right to work.  This right is key to human dignity and is a positive for a person's mental health and well-being, just as the absence of that right is a negative.  Under a new Government regulation, 1,743 people have been granted access to the labour market.  Nasc has criticised the slow implementation of many of Mr. Justice McMahon's other recommendations.  The mental health needs of asylum seekers, or of ethnic minorities more generally, was not considered in A Vision for Change.  In recent years, research into their mental health needs has demonstrated the impact on them of long stays in the system.  According to a paper published in 2016 by the faculty of public health medicine of the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland, &quot;refugees and asylum seekers often have unique and complex physical and mental health needs that require specific and comprehensive healthcare attention&quot;.  The paper in question, which was entitled &quot;The Health of Asylum Seekers, Refugees and Relocated Individuals&quot;, also found that &quot;people fleeing war and persecution in traumatic circumstances may have complex mental health needs requiring intervention&quot;.</p><p>According to a paper that was published by the College of Psychiatrists in Ireland in 2017, children &quot;are the frequently forgotten element of the migrant crisis&quot; and &quot;failure to deal with their needs can result in the storing up of social difficulties and mental pain that could have serious problems for the individual as well as society in the future&quot;.  The paper in question cited a range of studies from Sweden, Denmark and other countries in support of its findings.  Other research has drawn a clear link between the length of the asylum application process and adverse effects on mental health.  Doras Luimn&iacute; has found that &quot;residents frequently speak about how the uncertainty of their future, the overcrowded living conditions, and the prolonged periods of inactivity impact upon their well-being and mental health&quot;.  This conclusion has been supported by other research for the Royal College of Surgeons in Ireland.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2250"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2250&amp;amp;pid=RonanMullen&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->A range of measures can be taken to assist and improve the well-being of those in direct provision, and there is broad agreement on what can be done.  We need to do all we can to ensure that staff shortages in this sector are minimised.  The College of Psychiatrists of Ireland has suggested that more could be done to bring suitable candidates for consultant psychiatrist posts through the system, and the Government should work to maximise the numbers.  It needs to be ensured that a consultant psychiatrist can be identified in each area where there is a direct provision reception centre, which would allow for the provision of early and adequate assessment of asylum seekers for mental health issues and referral to specialised services as required.  Such specialised services, including psychotherapy for survivors of torture and other violence, should be accessible immediately for those who need them.  It also needs to be ensured that interpreters are available to assist medical professionals, and to avoid remarkable and unacceptable situations where children have to act as interpreters for their parents, as often happens.  These are just some measures which, with increased investment, could lead to a clear and genuine improvement in the well-being of those in the direct provision system.</p><p>I turn to what can be done to help young people within the school system.  Dr. Eve Griffin of National Self-Harm Registry Ireland has said that there is "an unmet need in terms of mental health services for children and adolescents ... School-based programmes to promote positive mental health should also be a priority.".  I strongly agree with this, and based on my own interactions with teachers and parents, a number of measures could be taken, which could have a significant impact on problems faced by children and adolescents at an early stage.  The State should make psychotherapists available to schools, perhaps on a shared basis between a number of schools within a district.  I know of one school in Leinster which engages a psychotherapist for one day per week who sees 15 of their 700 students each week, and this is funded from the school&rsquo;s own resources.  Clearly, the vast majority of schools cannot afford to do this on their own, unsupported by the State.  Professional development for teachers in mental health is needed since they face these issues in classrooms.  This kind of training should be as routine as first aid training, and it should apply to people in management in all workplaces, not just schools.  Pieta House runs an excellent six-week resilience programme for 14 year olds entering their second year of secondary school.  Perhaps this should be rolled out throughout the second-level sector.  One important point is that there needs to be strict regulation of qualifications and standards for all psychotherapists and cognitive behavioural therapists.  There are some concerns about the quality of some of the services on offer, and the cost of these services needs to be more affordable for families.  The HSE runs a programme which allows schools to become health promoting schools, which schools with a focus on mental health can avail of.  That is very much to be commended.  More needs to be done to advertise and promote this scheme to schools.  These are just a brief selection of measures which could be addressed by the Government.  I do not believe that it need involve significant additional expenditure within the health or education systems, particularly given our economic circumstances at this point.  However, investment would result in tangible improvements in outcomes for the mental health and well-being of our young people and those in direct provision in particular, on whom I seek to place particular focus today.  I look forward to seeing what colleagues have to say.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.251" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1428" speakername="Joan Freeman" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#RR00200"><p>I second the motion of my colleague Senator Mullen.</p><p>I feel apologetic every time I see the Minister of State, because I know I am going to attack him.  I am sorry, but he is the face of his Department so I know he will not personalise it.  What does it take for the Government to listen to the people of Ireland when it comes to the mental health services?  If we look back over the past 18 months to two years, we have done some positive things.  I am not talking about the Department of Health; I am talking about outsiders, including Senators and Deputies who have singly done things to try to improve the mental health services.  I know the Minister of State is trying very hard too.</p><p>Let us recap what has been achieved.  We had our first public consultation days on mental health, which were the first in the history of the State.  It was a wonderful opportunity to bring people who use the service, people who provide the service, and policymakers together to let the people of Ireland know what is happening.  We then formed the Oireachtas Joint Committee on the Future of Mental Health, which again was incredible as it was the first in the history of the State.  It allowed us to hold the HSE accountable.  That, more than anything, was the most perfect part of that committee.</p><p>The other positive development is that legislation was passed by the House, which tries to end the placing of children in adult psychiatric units.  It has not gone through the D&aacute;il but it has at least gone through the Seanad.  There have been marches outside Leinster House, in Wexford, and all around the place, which shows that people are not satisfied with what is going on in our country.  Organisations such as the Mental Health Commission<b></b>have suddenly had a change of attitude insofar as they are saying it is not acceptable any more.  They published reports stating that there were problems with mental health services but they did not do anything else other than mouth it; now they are complaining vocally and bringing it to the attention of the media.  Mental Health Reform has written report after report about the gaps, the needs, and the limitations of our services, and yesterday, we had the announcement of the My Voice Matters report in the AV room,<b></b>which is a good report, again listening to the voice of the people of Ireland.</p><p>The final positive development is that I had a formal meeting with the Taoiseach about a year ago that lasted an hour.  I could not believe it.  I brought two issues to his attention.  One was to make the Oireachtas Joint Committee on the Future of Mental Health a permanent committee and he agreed to that.  Second and I hope no one finds this an underhanded, I asked him if the Child and Adolescent Mental Health Services, CAMHS, could<b></b>be removed from the HSE and put under the remit and care of the Department of Children and Youth Affairs.  I do not get why children are lumped in with adults, especially when it comes to mental health.  They need their own care, and they need to be minded because they are desperately neglected.</p><p>How has the Government responded?  It formed a committee to review the A Vision for Change report<b></b>which was published 13 years ago.  It then formed another committee to review the review of A Vision for Change<b>.</b>Is this the third review?  It is a lovely example of kicking the can down the road.</p><p>One of the things the Minister of State has been doing, which I can see the advantage of, is updating Oireachtas Members.  He has had two information days in the AV room and while they were good, interesting, and very professional, he did not tell us anything new.  He is forgetting the basic things that need to be done.  He should forget the new stuff, including the digital stuff.  Let us examine the basic stuff, such as waiting lists, children being turned away because they are in the wrong queue, and other children being placed in adult psychiatric units.</p><p>I hope the Minister of State will be reply on another issue.  A few weeks ago, a Fianna F&aacute;il Member announced in the House that there will be a permanent committee on mental health.  That was followed by the Minister of State's statement in the newspapers that there would be a permanent committee on mental health.  I then formally asked him via email whether there was going to be one, because I was the chairman of that committee after all, and I think the chairman should know and be able to pass it on to the committee's members.  I was told that he does not know, and that he is still investigating it.  That upsets me deeply because that says that there is no need for a mental health committee because we are highlighting and putting a spotlight on too many problems.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Joan Freeman:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2483"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2483&amp;amp;pid=JoanFreeman&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I am asking him, in his role as a Minister of State with responsibility for mental health, to make sure that a permanent committee is put in place.  I do not care who is the Chairman, by the way.  I have nothing to lose because the chances are that I am never going to be called back to Seanad &Eacute;ireann.  I am talking here on behalf of the people of Ireland.  </p><p>Finally, the Government is not in good health at the moment.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.253" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#SS00200"><p>That is not true.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.254" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1428" speakername="Joan Freeman" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#SS00300"><p>It is in lots of trouble and there has been lots of bad publicity.  There is one thing that could turn things around, which is the Government looking after the mental health of our country.  This Government must stop losing the appetite for mental health and must put it first on the agenda.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.255" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#SS00400"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House.  This morning, the Oireachtas heath committee met representatives of the Mental Health Commission and of a group campaigning for mental health reform.  Presentations were made to the committee and many interesting issues arose at that meeting.  I raised a number of issues myself about which I am concerned but it is important to recognise the progress that has been made.  The budget for mental health has increased from &euro;711 million to &euro;987 million over the past four to five years, which is a substantial increase.  The number of CAMHS units has increased from 49 to 70 and the number of new posts created is over 1,700.  Progress is being made in relation to mental health.  A new national forensic mental health hospital is being built.  It will have 130 adult beds, as well as a ten-bed unit for children and a 30-bed intensive care rehabilitation unit, giving a total of 170 beds.  That project is progressing, is being built and will be delivered.</p> <p>The Mental Health Commission provided figures at the meeting this morning relating to regulatory compliance, which is improving.  Regulatory compliance went up from 74% in 2016 to 76% in 2017 and it reached 79% in 2018.  One of the examples given to us related to the department of psychiatry in Roscommon hospital, which was only 52% compliant over 12 months ago but at the last inspection was found to be 83% compliant.  Similarly, St. Brigid's Hospital in Ardee was way down the list but has now reached 93% compliance.  Progress is being made in relation to mental health, albeit not enough and not fast enough.  That said, it is important to note that it is not static and that the necessary changes are being made.  </p> <p>Senator Mullen referred to the number of beds in the system but we have now changed the whole focus of mental health services.  The focus is on community and working in community teams.  This is not just about in-care beds but also about working within the community; it is about working not only with the patients but also with their families, which is extremely important.  Families are so important in terms of providing support and we must make sure that they are involved in the care of their loved ones who have difficulties in their lives.  People need care and must have someone available to them when they have a down-time and need support.  </p> <p>I raised a number of issues at the health committee meeting this morning about which I have concerns.  One is the issue of adolescent mental health, with which I have been dealing over the past 12 months.  It is an enormous challenge at the moment, particularly with regard to geographical boundaries.  In the Glanmire area of Cork city, for example, no adolescent mental health consultant was available.  As a result, parents with whom I was dealing could not get access to consultant assessments for their children because they were living in a particular catchment area.  It is unfair that people living on one side of a boundary cannot get access to a service while those who are fortunate enough to live on the other side of the boundary can access such services.  That issue must be addressed.  I have never heard previously of boundaries being created in respect of healthcare but that appears to be what has happened in the psychiatric services.  This is something that needs to be examined further because there is a reluctance to roll over access to services for those who need immediate care.  </p> <p>Another issue is the fact that there is no intermediate support for people if they have not been assessed by a psychiatrist.  They cannot get access to a CAMHS team because of the way the system is currently structured.  That needs to be examined again in the context of making sure people can get access to services.  The other issue that must be dealt with is one that requires forward planning.  We have a large number of people living in this country now who were not born here.  I dealt with a very difficult case recently where a GP told a landlord whose tenant had serious mental health problems to contact me and that I would sort it out for him.  Eventually, after four weeks of back and forth, we got the GP to call to the person, who was then admitted to the psychiatric unit in Cork University Hospital.  The sad part of this is that the person involved does not have family support.  We are going to have a problem in the future with people who have come into this country but who do not have the support of immediate family or relatives and we need to start planning for that.  The person to whom I referred has now been discharged from the psychiatric services but is facing issues with regard to accessing accommodation and the necessary supports.  We must look at these two areas.</p> <p>Finally, I wish to refer to the connection between drug abuse and the development of mental health problems.  We are not doing enough to educate people that the use of illegal drugs can lead to mental health problems.  We need to do a lot more to educate people in that regard, just as we did with tobacco and how smoking affects health.  The use of illegal drugs causes mental health problems in the long term and we need to get that message out.</p> <p>I thank the Minister of State for the work he is doing and commend his Department and the HSE on the work they are doing in this area.  However, there are issues for which we must start planning now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.256" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1408" speakername="Frances Black" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#SS00500"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the Chamber.  I thank Senators Mullen, Freeman and all those who put their name to this motion for tabling it.  I was glad to co-sponsor it.  We all know that mental health is a hugely important issue.  It is important to me as a legislator and through my work with the RISE Foundation.  I have been working with the RISE Foundation for many years, as I have said previously in this Chamber.  We work with families who are struggling with mental health issues.  In reality, if somebody one loves, whether it be an adult child, partner, brother, sister or a parent, has an alcohol, drug or gambling problem, then one will really struggle with anxiety.  One wakes up in the morning thinking about that person and one goes to bed at night thinking about them.  One cannot eat or sleep.  One must watch the person going down a route of self-destruction, slowly killing him or herself.  Senators have spoken about families and the impact this has on the mental health of families is serious.  It is absolutely soul-destroying.  I am working in the area, at the coalface but there is absolutely no support for the work of the RISE Foundation.</p> <p>Senator Mullen referred to the figures, which speak for themselves.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Frances Black:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2474"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2474&amp;amp;pid=FrancesBlack&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Some 2,700 children and adolescents are waiting on appointments, 400 of whom have been waiting for more than one year.  These figures are not acceptable.  They are also dangerous.  If a young person is feeling depressed or suicidal, he or she cannot be asked to wait a year to be seen.  It is not feasible.  There is only a small window in which to deal with that person.  I received a phone call from a woman whose daughter was in Galway.  Only 14 years of age, she had attempted suicide numerous times.  She is attending CAMHS and has been in hospital before.  She needs to return to hospital, but there are no spaces available.</p><p>We have made major progress in our attitudes towards mental health.  Thankfully, the stigma is slowly being peeled back and people are being encouraged to speak out and seek help if they are struggling, but we cannot ask them to seek help without ensuring that someone will be there to listen when they make contact, be it their doctors, Pieta House or anyone else.  This is a resourcing and staffing issue.  My latest figures show that, since 2014, demand for mental health services has increased by approximately 30%, yet the resources are not being allocated to meet it.  People are being let down.  The Minister of State is aware of all of this, though, and I do not want to repeat myself.</p><p>I wish to touch on another issue.  I am a member of the Joint Committee on Justice and Equality.  I would love the Minister of State to read the presentations that I listened to this morning.  The committee is reviewing the direct provision system.  We were joined this morning by a group of incredibly brave asylum seekers.  I was very emotional listening to their stories.  They explained to us what it was like to live in the system, and they spoke about the dehumanisation, indignity and damage being done to residents' mental health.  They spoke about people coming from countries where they had been tortured and sexually violated, only then to come to direct provision centres where they face disrespect and a lack dignity.  We would not treat our animals that way.  There is barely any support for such people.</p><p>At a previous meeting, I heard of a heavily pregnant woman who needed to walk miles just to make a hospital appointment.  When she eventually had her child, she had to walk miles back to the direct provision centre carrying her newborn baby in her arms.  There was someone at the centre who gave her a hand every so often and drove her back and forth, but such an experience has an impact.  We heard from women about having children while in direct provision and how their children had become institutionalised.  One woman spoke this morning about how her nine year old child was suicidal.  The meeting was upsetting.  Last week, the Immigrant Council of Ireland told the committee about the number of women arriving in the system who had been trafficked and sexually abused.  They have been through unspeakable trauma, yet they are being placed in a system where they cannot access mental health services.  These people are being retraumatised in the centres.  I would love it if the Minister of State read this morning's presentations.  They were very upsetting.</p><p>We are a humane country.  We have great humanity, but I sometimes wonder whether we are losing it.  If Ireland is to have a humane and sensible asylum system, it must be based on reality.  We must accept the fact that people who have fled war and persecution and who have sought asylum have been through traumatic experiences and have specific and complex needs.  We cannot compound that trauma by placing them in a dehumanising system that lacks proper supports.  We must acknowledge the increased mental health needs of highly vulnerable people and ensure that centres are equipped to deal with them.  I urge every Member present to listen to the residents when they say that hotel managers and security are not suitable for or trained to help people who have been tortured and sexually abused.  They need proper, specialised attention.  Without it, the system will not be fit for purpose.  There are many larger issues with the system, but they are all linked, and we will not be able to address the mental health issues properly without addressing their causes, for example, a meaningful right to work, the ability to cook their own food and the chance to make small, dignified choices about their daily lives.  One woman talked about looking for toilet paper and being refused.  She had to talk to her children about the reason.</p><p>All of this has an impact on the mental health of residents in direct provision centres.  We must highlight it.  It is up to us to refuse to let it go away.  At a minimum, we should support the call in this motion and ensure that reception centres are equipped to deal with the vulnerable people whom they are supposed to be helping.  Proper mental health services are a crucial part of that.  I have spoken a great deal about direct provision, although I could have discussed mental health in Ireland.  I would love it if the Minister of State considered this issue.  This morning's meeting was upsetting.  Everyone in my office was crying while listening to the stories.  It was difficult for me not to cry.  The residents are people like the Minister of State and me.  They have children and are going through horrific experiences and indignity.  Last week, a man was asked about his current legal status.  He said that he had a wife and three children and that he did not care about or want to discuss his legal status.  All he wanted to do was work.  He just wanted to be allowed to get up in the morning, go to work and return in the evening and tell his three children that he had done a day's work.  He said that he did not even want payment, that he would have done it for free.  He just wanted to be given back his dignity so that he could show his children that he was a proud man and that he was going to work.  This is the system's impact on people.  We must consider this matter.  Apart from that, there are issues of mental health, sex trafficking, what women must go through, and children being leered at in corridors.</p><p>I have said it all already.  Please, will the Minister of State examine this vital matter?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.258" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#TT00200"><p>I commend my colleagues, Senators Mullen and Freeman, on placing this most important matter before Seanad &Eacute;ireann.  It is a very significant issue that we in this country must face.  When I ran for the Presidency in 2011, I isolated three main planks, the first of which was mental health.  I visited Pieta House and various other institutions and was impressed by the work being done.</p> <p>No one could object to the first phrase in the motion.  I am glad to understand that the Government will not oppose the motion.  That is a positive sign.  No one could disagree with the statement that "adequate mental health services are vital to secure the dignity and wellbeing of all those within the State, including asylum seekers within the direct provision system".  I am glad that Senator Mullen has isolated for particular attention people who are in the direct provision system.  I introduced a Bill a couple of years ago that would have addressed most of the problems that were faced by asylum seekers.  I believed it would get through, but at the last minute Sinn F&eacute;in Members changed their vote and voted against it.  I think that was because they had an interest in the issue and wanted to keep it for themselves.  I notice that no one from Sinn F&eacute;in is present now.  They said that I had not addressed working or the introduction of cooking facilities.  I told them to look at pages 6, 7 and 8, where all of those issues were specifically mentioned.  They did not have a leg to stand on.</p> <p>It is shocking that, since the 1980s, the amount of money spent on these services has dropped by half.  Presumably, that is as a result of the financial emergency, but we are assured by the Government that the emergency is over, everything is back on track and we have full employment.  There certainly should be an increase in this area.</p> <p>It is not acceptable that young people should be kept waiting before they get access to psychiatric services.  I will quote the motion: "almost 2,700 children and adolescents are awaiting appointments with psychiatrists, with almost 400 waiting over 1 year".<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator David Norris:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1758"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1758&amp;amp;pid=DavidNorris&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->How, in God's name, is it conscionable that someone with severe mental issues and issues of distress or someone who is possibly suicidal can be told to come back in a year's time?  It is madness.  That is madness.  That is mental illness in my opinion.</p><p>I am a bit of a grammarian and I want to point to one grammatical flaw.  The motion states "there continues to be major shortfalls" rather than "there continue to be major shortfalls".</p><p>The next section of the motion deals with asylum seekers.  It is perfectly appropriate to say they have particular problems with mental stress; of course they do.  They have been wrenched out of their family circumstances and wrenched away from the country and culture in which they were brought up into an alien culture in very difficult circumstances.  They are given an absolute pittance - pocket money.  Most children in this country get more pocket money than we give to asylum seekers.  The Royal College of Surgeons in Ireland has found that depression and mental health problems are five times higher among asylum seekers and I am not at all surprised.  Many of these people are suffering from post-traumatic stress.  I have dealt with people from Iraq who have been tortured.  It takes a lot of recovering from a situation in which one human being has decided as an instrument of policy to inflict severe pain on another.</p><p>I am particularly pleased to note that Senator Mullen has included the phrase at the end stating "specialised services, such as psychotherapy for survivors of torture and other violence, can be accessed by those who need them".</p><p>I will end on that note.  I commend my colleagues on putting this matter before the House.  I acknowledge that the Government will not be opposing this motion.  That is a very good day.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.260" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#UU00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House and thank him for coming.  I know he has special responsibility for this.  I wish to thank in particular my colleagues, Senators Mullen and Freeman, for drafting and working on this comprehensive motion.  It is worthy of support and I was delighted to co-sign it.</p> <p>Three words that jumped off the page when I read the motion were: dignity, respect and well-being of the person.  We can never deny dignity, respect or well-being of anyone.  That flows and ebbs through every word of the motion and it is important to acknowledge.</p> <p>I wish to acknowledge the great work of the former judge, Mr. Justice Bryan McMahon.  Senators may have heard him recently on RT&Eacute; in an interview.  He is a wonderful man and advocate for reform especially for people who are seeking asylum and for the issues around how their welfare or lack of welfare is being cared for and the attention being given to them.  We are lucky to have this brave and courageous man and advocate.</p> <p>The motion refers to the 2,700 children and adolescents who are waiting for appointments.  That is a shocking indictment on the Government and the issue needs to be addressed, as does the issue that so many people are waiting for over a year.</p> <p>I wish to focus on the issues of asylum seekers and direct provision because I believe these particular aspects do not get the same attention.  Many of these people are not involved in the political process.  Many have not embedded themselves in the community and do not have advocates.  We hear horrendous stories of abuse of these people, whether mental, physical or emotional.  They are particularly vulnerable when they are isolated and that is a terrible story in itself.  I spoke to one woman - I will not mention the centre where she stayed.  She described to me how, at night time when she got back into her room with her husband, they pulled up the mattress to the door to keep her children in so that they would be safe.  For a mother to have to pull up the mattress from the floor and prop it up against the door and lie down and sleep there to keep her children safe is startling.  She spoke about her deep concerns for the safety of her children and their welfare.  No family should be put through that.</p> <p>I am reminded of a good speech by the Taoiseach in Sligo recently in the context of the Famine.  He talked about our people as a migrant people and our experiences of going from or fleeing these shores and our homeland.  He spoke of how many of our ancestors sought refuge, support and shelter whether in the USA or wherever and how many people there were badly treated.  They were our people.  Many people had good experiences too.  One would imagine we would be more sympathetic to people in asylum or waiting for asylum in these centres, as well as those in direct provision.  That is really important.</p> <p>I am not going to rehash all the things people have said because they have made excellent contributions.  What is this motion attempting to do?  The motion is asking the Minister of State to commit to seven simple principles.  These are set out in the motion.  The motion calls on the Government to ensure staff shortages in the sector are resourced as a priority to meet the current requirements.  It refers to working with the College of Psychiatrists of Ireland to maximise the number of specialist training posts for psychiatrists to alleviate the shortage of suitable candidates for vacant positions.  It calls for a designated consultant psychiatrist to be identified in each area where a direct provision reception centre is located.</p> <p>I want to focus on the next two priorities set out in the motion.  They call for the introduction of early and adequate assessment for asylum seekers for mental health issues, as well as referrals to specialist services as required.  The motion also calls for specialist services, such as psychological services for survivors of torture and other violence, to be available for access by those who need them.</p> <p>I am keen for the Minister of State to spend the next portion of his time in the House today addressing these seven key points.  They are simple.  I am pleased that, as Senator Norris has said, the Government is accepting the motion.  I would be appalled if the Government did not accept it.  I really want the Minister of State to use his time constructively today.  He should deal specifically with these seven key points and where he sees difficulties.  I see no difficulties but if the Minister of State has difficulties, we want to hear them.  It is grand for all of us to come to the House and talk about the issues we all know about, but I would like to leave the Chamber today knowing that the Minister of State is absolutely committed to the delivery of the seven key points that the motion attempts to secure.  I want to hear the Minister of State address these seven issues one by one.  If we can go away with some assurance then at least that is a start.  It is then up to us to keep engaging with the Minister of State and the people in authority to ensure the calls are realised.</p> <p>Let us be clear about something: people are entitled to their dignity, respect and well-being.  We should do nothing less than support these reasonable objects.  We live in a republic.  We guarantee principles of security and respect for the citizens of our Republic.  The Constitution sets out and covers many aspects of the entitlements and rights of people.  I am keen to hear what the Minister of State has to say on the matters we have raised.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.261" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1261" speakername="Jim Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#UU00300"><p>I thank Senators and welcome the motion as the promotion of positive mental health is a common objective within the Oireachtas and throughout Irish society.</p> <p>The issues raised by the Senator provide the opportunity for us to consider the various and ongoing initiatives aimed at enhancing our mental health legislation, policy and services.  These issues are being addressed in the context of progressing the commitments and priorities for mental health under A Programme for a Partnership Government.  We are, for example, modernising the Mental Health Act 2001, refreshing A Vision for Change and we have been improving the existing capacity of our mental health service while introducing new initiatives.</p> <p>My core objective, as Minister of State, is to improve how we plan services with an emphasis on delivering assessed and appropriate services to all of our population, especially those most needing care.  We face increasing demands, evolving needs and heightened expectations.  We also face limits in staffing resources.  To meet these challenges, we need to look at new approaches and imaginative solutions.</p> <p>I appreciate that the Senator has raised comparison of mental health funding as a proportion of overall health expenditure with 1980s figures.  This, I suggest, should be considered in the context of changes to the health system as a whole.  This includes, for example, various new service elements introduced across our health system in such areas as disability or services for older people.  Such services simply did not exist in the past.  In addition, the mental health system has totally transformed from primarily institutional-based care to largely community care, allied of course to modern inpatient care units that emphasise short-stay and recovery.</p> <p>Significant mental health promotion and expenditure is undertaken in other areas for both children and adults, such as in HSE primary care or across other sectors such as education, Tusla or the judicial systems.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Jim Daly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2328"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2328&amp;amp;pid=JimDaly&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Expenditure comparisons with other countries should also allow for the fact that they can have significantly different healthcare, social care or funding systems.  Notwithstanding this, I reiterate that developing mental health services remains a priority for me as Minister of State and for the Government.  This is being realised in practical terms by the additional &euro;55 million to progress new developments this year, which brings overall mental health funding to nearly &euro;1 billion.  The HSE mental health budget has increased by more than &euro;275 million since 2012, a significant investment by any measure or viewpoint.</p><p>In recent years, our services have broadened.  They now range from mental health promotion and early intervention through to specialist acute forensic care.  They extend also, for both adults and children, beyond the traditional HSE mental health programme to other areas or sectors.  This involves, for example, better links to primary care, disability services and health and well-being.  Increasingly, an improved response is also occurring across other sectors spanning education, childcare or the justice systems.</p><p>In recent years, the mental health system has received, rightly, considerable scrutiny from politicians, the media, advocate organisations, service users and many others.  I welcome this scrutiny because it helps us to identify any areas in which performance can be improved.  In this regard, I acknowledge the contribution of the Oireachtas.  While mental health is a complex area relevant to us all, often involving profound issues and implications, steady and real progress has been made collectively over recent years.  From my extensive interaction with many Members on many fronts, I am confident that this positive direction will continue, as it must do if we are to realise the further improvements we all wish to see.  On this note, I held a presentation late last year in Leinster House to inform Members of the Oireachtas about our mental health service overall, and I arranged another one about a month ago specifically on child and adolescent mental health services, CAMHS.  Many of the issues being aired today were covered in detail on these unique opportunities by officials of both the Department of Health and the HSE.</p><p>I will now update Members on some of the strategic developments on mental health and then address the more specific issues raised.  The Department of Health is drafting a general scheme of a Bill to amend mental health legislation to reflect the recommendations of the expert group review of the Mental Health Act 2001.  It is anticipated that draft heads of a Bill will be completed by the end of June next.  The draft legislation at that stage will then be referred to the Mental Health Commission for its consideration.  Mental health legislation must always seek to strike a fine balance between the rights of the person and the requirement to protect others.  The comprehensive updating of the Mental Health Act 2001, along with the recently enacted Mental Health (Amendment) Act 2018, will ensure that in future a greater emphasis will be placed on the autonomy of the individual rather than relying on the principle of "best interests", as set out in the 2001 Act.  It is accepted that people should have the right to make their own choices and that, where necessary, supports should be available to ensure a person's "will and preferences" are fully respected.  The updated Act will put the focus firmly on protecting and promoting the human rights of those with mental health difficulties, thus ensuring their voice will be more clearly heard.</p><p>When launched in 2006, A Vision for Change was universally welcomed as a progressive, evidence-based and realistic document that proposed a new model of service delivery that would be patient-centred, flexible and community-based.  The Government accepted A Vision for Change as the basis for developing our mental health services, and significant success can be noted in how the delivery of mental health services has changed in the intervening years.  One important principle within this document reads: "Mental health services must be accessible to all who require them; this means not just geographically accessible but ... provided at a time and in a manner that means individuals can readily access the service they require."  This relates more than ever before to the issues at hand today.  It is generally accepted that A Vision for Change has been highly regarded, both nationally and internationally, for its underlying principles and objectives.  The refresh of this policy, which will conclude shortly, will reinforce and improve these fundamentals while taking account of emerging needs and changing best practice for future years.  We should recall where we have come from in that bed numbers have been reduced and old institutions closed.  The new focus on mental health and deinstitutionalisation, which will be further supplemented and informed by updating A Vision for Change, looks beyond traditional psychiatric provision to include a more holistic approach and an agenda for social inclusion.</p><p>Of relevance also today is our suicide policy in that the Connecting for Life cross-sectoral steering group has an agreed national implementation plan.  This was published in January 2018.  In addition, all 17 local Connecting for Life plans have been launched and are being progressed satisfactorily throughout the country.</p><p>Improving access to the range of HSE specialist mental health services, whether they relate to CAMHS, general adult services or those for psychiatry of later life, is a priority under the recently agreed HSE service plan 2019.  The plan highlights delivering timely, clinically effective and standardised mental health services in adherence with statutory requirements.  It is important to note that mental health services are available to the entire population.  Specialist consultant-led mental health teams are configured for this purpose and every person is eligible to avail of services.  This includes asylum seekers and those in direct provision.  These services are accessed mainly through primary care referrals, although referrals to community mental health teams can be made by any doctor who considers a psychiatric review necessary.  This again is usually through primary care but these can sometimes come through emergency departments or other sources.  The location of direct provision centres does not specifically feature in HSE resource allocation models or the available resources in specific catchment areas.  However, each HSE community healthcare organisation allocates resources to provide the best possible level of service based on the needs of all the population served, including asylum seekers and those in direct provision.</p><p>Mental health services are mainly provided by community mental health teams.  A HSE review of out-of-hours services in 2017 revealed that 60% of these teams were already providing seven-day-a-week services.  Additional funding provided by Government in 2017 was allocated to increase this coverage to 100%.  HSE mental health services are in the final stages of completion of this project, which will allow for the provision of 7-day-a-week services nationally.</p><p>As reflected in its service plan, the HSE is developing its prevention and early intervention services at primary care level.  This includes a 24-7 mental health contact line, a crisis text line and a range of online e-mental health digital responses.  The first of the electronic GP referrals to mental health services went live very recently.  I will look at the potential of such initiatives in the context of the specific issues under discussion here today.</p><p>CAMHS is understandably an issue that is of interest to us all.  It is designed for children and adolescents presenting with moderate to severe mental health disorders, as opposed to other HSE supports at different levels of care provision.  The number of referrals accepted to CAMHS has increased by 24% between 2012 and 2018.  Despite this increase, the CAMHS waiting list has increased by only 4%, or just over 100 cases, since 2012.  The HSE service plan 2019 commits to developing all aspects of CAMHS services.  This includes developing a seven day a week service to ensure improved supports for vulnerable young people as well as related initiatives around enhanced early intervention and day hospital care.  When a referral is accepted, CAMHS teams are expected to offer an appointment and see an individual within 12 weeks.  All community teams screen referrals received and those deemed urgent are seen as a priority.  This can sometimes impact on seeing other cases within three months depending on local resources and circumstances.  There has been an overall 8.2% increase in the number of referrals accepted between April 2018 and April 2019.  In that time, the CAMHS waiting list decreased by 3.9%.  At the end of April 2019, there were 2,606 cases waiting to be seen.  This is an increase of 105 cases on the same period in 2018.  The number of cases waiting more than 12 months decreased by 36, or 10%, to 316 in April 2019 compared with the same period last year.  The HSE has established a CAMHS waiting list initiative to reduce waiting lists with a focus on those waiting more than 12 months.  The community healthcare organisations with individuals waiting more than 12 months are taking dedicated actions to ensure no child is waiting beyond this period.  However, this can be influenced by various factors such as an increase in population, increase in referrals, staffing retention issues and challenges in recruiting.  CAMHS inpatient units operate a 24-7 tertiary model of care to young people with severe or complex mental health issues. There are 74 CAMHS inpatient beds in four units in Dublin, Cork and Galway.  This number will increase to 104 with the opening of the new forensic complex in Portrane next year and the new children's hospital in the longer term.</p><p>Medical workforce planning within the HSE is the responsibility of the national doctors training and planning group, which considers the needs of service delivery across the healthcare system.  It aims to bring the number of doctors in postgraduate medical training programmes in line with future demand for specialists in the health service and to help inform the consultant appointments process.  The HSE maintains a doctors integrated management system that collates the registration, training and employment details of all consultant posts and whole-time equivalents on a single national system.  The recording of all consultant posts allows for greater reporting at local and national levels and otherwise informs workforce planning decisions.  A total of 452 consultant psychiatrist posts are documented on this system, with 418 consultant psychiatrists in post.  The national task force on medical staffing was a Government policy document in 2003 that recommended that a ratio of 15 consultants per 100,000 of the population be achieved by 2013.  This was followed by A Vision for Change, which recommended a target of 9.4 consultants per 100,000 of the population.  In England, the current ratio of consultants to the population is similar to Ireland at 9.8.  Workforce planning is under consideration in the refresh of A Vision for Change.  I understand that around 12% of all consultant psychiatrist posts are either vacant or unmatched.  Therefore, around 88% of all consultant psychiatrist posts are currently filled.</p><p>Regarding the question of bed ratios, I again stress that international comparisons often fail to take account of variations within countries in terms of mental health policy.  Our health policies, Sl&aacute;intecare and A Vision for Change, emphasise the importance of modern, high-quality care in the community with, of course, equivalent provision in hospital settings as appropriate.  In Ireland, there are 1,035 acute beds for a population of 4.761 million.  This means we have 65 acute adult beds per 300,000, or 21.6 per 100,000.  This is in a context where A Vision for Change recommends a total of 16.6 beds per 100,000 population.  Therefore, we have more than the recommended number of beds.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Jim Daly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2328"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2328&amp;amp;pid=JimDaly&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I acknowledge, however, that continued investment in community services will be necessary to deliver fully on national policies.</p><p>Through its mental health engagement and recovery team, the HSE now has local fora for service users and their family members across the country.  The HSE is ensuring that the views of service users, their family members and carers are central to the design and delivery of services.  This is evidenced by service user participation on the HSE's management team.  Improvements relating to embedding a recovery culture within teams and services are being supported through the implementation of the national framework for recovery in mental health.  The talk therapy national service improvement project will further improve mental health services.</p><p>There is a whole-of-Government approach to direct provision in Ireland.  The Reception and Integration Agency, RIA, provides material reception conditions - accommodation and related services - in line with the European Communities (Reception Conditions) Regulations 2018 to those in the international protection process.  Other sectors are responsible for providing services directly through a mainstreamed approach.  The Department of Education and Skills provides education services; the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection provides daily expense allowances and other exceptional needs payments.  Some Departments and agencies have seconded staff to the RIA, and this system works extremely well in the provision of effective and efficient services to recipients.  Mainstream health services, including mental health services for those in the international protection process, are provided directly through the HSE and the Department of Health.  The HSE and other health providers arrange for translation services as required.  The RIA works collectively with all agencies and Departments to co-ordinate the provision of services.  There is ongoing liaison between the HSE and the RIA to best meet the health and related needs of protection applicants.  There is a specific health screening team funded and managed by the HSE and located on the site of the Balseskin reception facility to assess recipients who have just arrived in the State.  The team comprises GPs; a medical officer; a clinical nurse specialist and two nurses; a primary care social worker; two primary care psychologists; and clerical and administration support.  The team offers a range of individual services and screening for medical and psychosocial needs, with onward referral as necessary.  The individual professionals communicate with the RIA - within the bounds of patient confidentiality - if a need is identified that will affect the applicant's accommodation requirements.</p><p>The HSE social inclusion unit has commissioned research to explore the concept of vulnerability, good practice in assessment, timing of same and implications for effectively improving on the processes already in place.  It is important to emphasise that all agencies involved in the delivery of direct provision services play a part in identifying and supporting applicants who present as vulnerable.  This is particularly the case where vulnerabilities may become evident at different times in the protection process.  Applicants can also obtain a General Medical Services, GMS, card on receiving a temporary resident card or a PPS number and can therefore visit a local GP or primary care service as required.</p><p>The next few years will see considerable change in the mental health landscape, with new legislation, improved infrastructure and refreshed policies in place.  I assure the House of my personal commitment to a high-quality, person-centred mental health service, including for asylum seekers.  Mental health problems, of whatever nature, do not differentiate.  Everyone deserves the best possible response our care system can give.  In this context I will give full and proper consideration to all contributions made today.  I thank my officials, Mr. Gerry Steadman and Mr. Michael Murchan, who are here with me for their work on this issue and their presence today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.264" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#WW00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for what was a pretty detailed response.  I compliment him on concluding five seconds ahead of time.  I now call Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen, who has five minutes to wrap up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.265" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#WW00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his response.  I thank Senator Freeman for seconding the motion and Senators Colm Burke, Black, Norris and Boyhan for their contributions.  I thank especially Mental Health Reform and all those who are active in agitating and lobbying for a better quality of mental health services in this country.  I do not wish to single out Mental Health Reform as our leading national coalition of organisations campaigning to transform mental health and well-being supports.  I wish to note some of the excellent contributions and I acknowledge what Senator Colm Burke had to say.  He always has the unenviable task of defending Government policy, which he does very faithfully, but it would be unfair to him to leave it at that because he did point out some of the challenges that are definitely there.  He mentioned that there is no immediate support for people who have not been assessed by a psychiatrist.  You could sing that.  It was also very important he mentioned people with mental health problems who are non-nationals and have no family support.  Senator Black referred to her work with the RISE Foundation, and I am very grateful she mentioned her experience of asylum seekers and people in direct provision coming before the justice committee.  Senator Norris always finds a way to say something very memorable.  He pointed out that most children get more pocket money than we give to asylum seekers.  Senator Boyhan properly paid tribute to Mr. Justice Bryan McMahon and others.</p> <p>I know the Minister of State will not take this comment personally but I recall, I think it was in the 1980s, Ronald Regan sitting down with Mikhail Gorbachev and starting off his commentary in the presence of the media by saying, "Let me tell you why we do not trust you."  It is not the Minister of State personally I am talking about here, but let me tell him why we do not trust Government responses such as the one he has given.  It is long on history, analysis and purported explanation, but when I see a ministerial speech that talks up and finds the positive spin on statistics but which is not at the same time honest about what are manifest shortcomings in the system, I really worry because I get the impression - it is hard not to - that we are being spun a line.  I ask the Minister of State to accept that he has not directly expressed support for the seven deliverables mentioned in the motion that Senator Boyhan rightly went through.  I ask the Minister of State to take the opportunity, before we break up today, to do so.</p> <p>I will give an example of what I am talking about in terms of the statistical analysis in which the Minister of State engages.  He talks about the number of consultants, for example.  It is beyond dispute that Ireland has half the number of consultants per 100,000 population of the EU average.  We rank below countries such as Romania, Slovakia and Greece in this regard.  We have less than a quarter of the number of consultants Finland employs.  The Minister of State cannot explain this away simply by reference to the fact that there are different systems in different countries because it is psychiatrists themselves who are pointing out the starkness of this problem.  It was Professor Patricia Casey who said such an argument was preposterous and inconceivable - those are the terms she used - in pointing to the grave shortage and deficit in posts being filled, not just psychiatric consultancy posts, but also psychologists, social workers and occupational therapists.  It is right to point out that we have moved to a community-based system but it is wrong not to acknowledge that there are severe shortages.  There is no sense of urgency, worry or acknowledgement in the speech of the problems that are there.  What I am getting is a massaging of statistics in order to put the best possible l&eacute;amh ar an sc&eacute;al, but that is not good enough given the real human suffering.  Only recently I was listening to a GP in Cork talk about persons attempting suicide, going into accident and emergency departments, being sent home with an appointment with a psychiatrist some weeks hence and then further attempting self-harm, forcing the family to go private in order to get the urgent care required.  That is the system as it is now affecting real people, and the problem this presents to us as a society needs to come across much more in ministerial speeches.</p> <p>I thank my colleagues for what they have said.  I would greatly appreciate it if there were a much clearer and franker acceptance that there are real problems and that they cannot just be wished away by taking the most optimistic view of comparative statistics.  We are not where we should be, and mental health services in particular are the poor relation because twice the budget has been raided.  The money that was to accrue from the sale of psychiatric institutions was supposed to benefit mental health services.  As far as I know, this did not happen.  The &euro;12 million that Deputy Varadkar when Minister for Health said he was taking from the budget in 2016 was supposed to improve 24-7 mental health services.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2250"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2250&amp;amp;pid=RonanMullen&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=29"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Time and again it seems to me that mental health services have been treated as the poor relation in order to fill gaps.  We must shudder at the consequences of the overspend on the children's hospital for mental health services as well as other important areas that need public funding.  I am sorry to say I am not satisfied with the Minister of State's response although I appreciate the difficult position he is in personally.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.267" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.268" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#XX00300">Message from Joint Committee</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.269" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#XX00400"><p>The Joint Committee on Housing, Planning and Local Government has completed its consideration of the Planning and Development Act 2000 (Exempted Development) (No. 2) Regulations 2019. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.270" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#XX00600"><p>When is it proposed to sit again?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.271" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052900002#XX00700"><p>At 10.30 a.m. tomorrow.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-29a.272" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>The Seanad adjourned at 6.25 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Thursday, 30 May 2019.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>