<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.2" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 14:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.4" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.5" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#A00100">Gnó an tSeanaid - Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Martin Conway that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Education and Skills to outline why a national school, details supplied, in County Clare is unable to avail of broadband which is critical for the school and particularly critical for a visually impaired student to access vital classroom equipment to overcome his disability.  </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Lorraine Clifford-Lee of the following matter: </p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Justice and Equality to provide an update on the proposed reopening of Rush Garda station.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Fintan Warfield of the following matter: </p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade to make a statement on the difficulties Irish-registered parents in same-sex marriages abroad are experiencing in obtaining Irish passports for their children.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Kevin Humphreys of the following matter: </p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government to outline the progress being made on delivery of Part V housing in the dockland areas in Dublin.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Colm Burke of the following matter: </p><blockquote>The need for the Minister of State with responsibility for the Office of Public Works and flood relief to outline the number of vacant residential properties which are owned by the OPW and the proposals he has to bring same into use. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Michelle Mulherin of the following matter: </p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Business, Enterprise and Innovation to make a statement on the efforts of IDA Ireland to deliver foreign direct investment and jobs to north and east Mayo, including the construction of an advanced technology building in Ballina.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Neale Richmond of the following matter: </p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs to provide an update on the planned nationwide roll-out of baby boxes. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill of the following matter: </p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Finance to undertake a review of the criteria surrounding eligibility for a primary medical certificate.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Jennifer Murnane O'Connor of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister of Transport, Tourism and Sport to make a statement on the lack of public transport infrastructure for patients in Carlow travelling to Kilkenny hospital.</blockquote> <p>Of the matters raised by the Senators suitable for discussion, I have selected those raised by Senators Conway, Clifford-Lee, Warfield and Humphreys and they will be taken now.  I regret that I had to rule out of order the matter raised by Senator Murnane O&rsquo;Connor on the ground that the Minister has no official responsibility in the matter.  The other Senators may give notice on another day of the matters they wish to raise.</p><p>I welcome the Minister for Education and Skills who is here to respond to the first matter, which is from Senator Martin Conway.  The Senator is obliged to be here to raise his issue but he is not here yet.  The train is about to leave the station and he will be left behind.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.7" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#B00100">Nithe i dtosach suíonna - Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.8" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#B00200">Broadband Service Provision</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#B00300"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House.  It is always great when a senior Minister comes in to deal with this type of very serious issue.  I do not want to give its name, but a small school in west Clare has a student who is visually impaired.  A vital piece of equipment has been purchased between the school and the parents of the child, in order for him to access vital statistics from the whiteboard and to be able to operate on a level playing pitch with the other boys and girls in the school.  This piece of equipment costs in the region of &euro;4,000 to &euro;5,000 and is available for the young person so he can progress with his learning.</p> <p>We all want to see young people, whether they have disabilities or are able bodied, being able to go to integrated schools and benefit from the wonderful environment of a small rural school.  However, this piece of equipment which cost so much money is rendered inoperable because there is no broadband.  The broadband in the school is not at a suitable standard for this piece of equipment to work.</p> <p>I have liaised with the broadband officer in Clare County Council, who has been out to the school, tested the lines and determined that the speed is totally inadequate to operate any kind of equipment, not to mention this particular piece of equipment.  The nearest Eir connection is over 1 km away from the school.</p> <p>I am raising this matter on the Commencement of the House today because I do not know what else to do.  It is grossly unfair that a school in rural Ireland would not have broadband in the first instance.  While I understand there are a number of schools in this situation, and something was done for many of them, there are some exceptional cases such as this where nothing is happening.  What compounds the situation and makes it all the more urgent is the fact that there is a student whose parents want him to learn, yet who cannot learn because of his disability and because the equipment provided to him is rendered inoperable by the lack of broadband.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1290" speakername="Joe McHugh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#B00400"><p>Gabhaim bu&iacute;ochas leis an Seanad&oacute;ir f&aacute;choinne an cheist th&aacute;bhachtach seo.   I welcome the opportunity to provide an update on the status of broadband services in schools.  The delivery of high quality Internet connectivity for all schools is a key objective of my Department.  It is accepted that good connectivity is essential to ensure that schools can progress the embedding of digital technologies in teaching and learning and facilitate the implementation of new and revised curriculums.  An interdepartmental group involving my Department and officials from the Department of Communications, Climate Action and Environment is working to determine how best to address high-speed broadband connectivity to all primary schools.  This group will take account of developments in the Government's national broadband plan and its associated intervention strategy, which targets areas for the State intervention element of the national broadband plan.</p> <p>Broadband capacity can vary due to geographical location and local available infrastructure, which can impact on the level of service that can be provided.  The policy of my Department is to offer the best quality connectivity to all schools in line with the technical solutions available in the school location.  In terms of the broadband services in the school referred to by the Senator, it should be noted that the school is located in the national broadband plan intervention area and services in this area are targeted under the national broadband plan.  This school currently has a service which provides broadband speeds of up to 3 Mbps on a DSL line.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Joe McHugh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2018"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2018&amp;amp;pid=JoeMcHugh&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->In an effort to improve services to the school, it was recently the subject of a broadband mini-competition organised by the Department.  The provision of service to the school has been awarded to a wireless service provider, which will deliver upgraded speeds of 17 Mbps.  The provider is currently working with the school to arrange installation and to deliver this improved service to the school.</p><p>To assist children with particular educational needs, the Department operates a scheme of grants towards the purpose of essential assistive technology.  Equipment under the scheme is provided for children with more complex disabilities who, in order to access the school curriculum, require essential specialist equipment.  Funding was provided under this scheme to the school in the case referred to by the Senator.  It should be noted that the equipment provided does not require an ongoing broadband connection to facilitate access to the curriculum.  If the school has concerns or needs advice, it may consult the visiting teacher service of the NCSE, which will be able to assist.</p><p>Under the current schools broadband programme, the Department's practice is to review constantly the availability of broadband with the aim of improving services to all primary schools as broadband connectivity improves throughout the country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#C00200"><p>I thank the Minister.  It is certainly news to me that an organisation is engaging with the school because I understood that was not the case.  Perhaps it has started engaging in recent days.  When the IT section of Clare County Council tested the lines going into the school, it found that the speed was just 1 Mbps, which is very poor.  I would appreciate it if the Minister's could use his good offices to double-check with the provider, come back to my office with an update on the situation and, most important, provide a timeline for when this equipment will be operable.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1290" speakername="Joe McHugh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#C00300"><p>That is a reasonable request.  With regard to whatever information is available to me, I will certainly ensure the Senator will be able to connect with the school and, hopefully, with the contractor who has won the tender for the wireless option.  Wireless has been a solution for rural Ireland for many years.  It is not the preferred solution if one is trying to get up to 1,000 Mbps.  A similar scheme has been announced by SIRO in the larger towns.  Ennis in County Clare might have been covered by that.  There are other options through Eir and through copper connectivity.  The focus in the short to medium term - not the medium to long term - has to be on the national broadband plan.  The schools that are not getting broadband at the moment will be covered by that.  It is important.  I appreciate the Senator's decision to raise this matter.  It is about equality of access.  People cannot be discriminated against just because of geography.  That is the reason I wanted to come to the House.  If there is anything the officials in the Department of Education and Skills can do to expedite this, I will be happy to ensure it is done.  Gabhaim bu&iacute;ochas ar&iacute;s leis an Seanad&oacute;ir f&aacute; choinne an cheist seo a ard&uacute;.  Beidh m&eacute; s&aacute;sta na sonra&iacute; &oacute; mo chuid oifigigh a chur in i&uacute;l don Seanad&oacute;ir.  Beidh m&eacute; i dteagmh&aacute;il leis.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#C00400"><p>Go raibh maith agat.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.15" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#C00500">Garda Stations</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#C00600"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Stanton, back to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#C00700"><p>I thank the Minister of State for coming to the House to debate this important issue.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Lorraine Clifford-Lee:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2461"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2461&amp;amp;pid=LorraineCliffordLee&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I am looking for an update on the reopening of Rush Garda station.  Rush station was one of the six Garda stations that were announced in November 2017 to be reopened as part of a pilot project.  That was November 2017 and now we are in February 2019 and I am looking for an update.  The people of Rush were delighted when it was announced they would get their Garda station back.  They severely felt the loss of the Garda station and the diminishing of the Garda numbers in north County Dublin.</p><p>In case the Minister of State does not know, Rush is a small coastal town in north County Dublin with a population of some 10,000.  It has grown rapidly in recent years and that growth is set to continue.  Like all of north County Dublin, the population is exploding there, but we have seen a 20% decline in Garda numbers in the area.  This particular Garda station was closed back in 2012.  The people in Rush are very anxious about their personal security and the security within the town.  We were very happy when this reopening was announced.  I would like an update on what stage it is at.  The last time I raised this issue was in May 2018 and at that point there was a discussion between the OPW and An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na with regard to an assessment of needs.  I was informed that this assessment was nearing an end.  I would appreciate if the Minister of State could give us an update and, as far as possible, a timeline for when we could see Rush Garda station open.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1277" speakername="David Stanton" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#D00200"><p>I acknowledge the serious interest taken by the Senator in this matter.  I know that she is speaking about a very nice part of north County Dublin.  I compliment the Senator on her work for the people there.  The Minister, Deputy Flanagan, sends his regrets as he cannot be here today due to other commitments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#D00300"><p>I believe we will see him later.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1277" speakername="David Stanton" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#D00400"><p>I am sure you will.</p> <p>The Senator will be aware that A Programme for a Partnership Government commits to a pilot scheme to reopen six Garda stations, urban and rural, to determine the possible positive impacts that such openings would have on criminal activity, with special emphasis on burglaries, thefts and public order.  The Garda Commissioner's final report, which is available on my Department's website, recommends that Rush Garda station be reopened along with the following stations: Ballinspittle, County Cork; Bawnboy, County Cavan; Leighlinbridge, County Carlow; Donard, County Wicklow; and Stepaside, County Dublin.</p> <p>It is important to recognise that the programme of replacement and refurbishment of Garda accommodation is progressed by the Garda authorities working in close co-operation with the Office of Public Works.  The OPW has the responsibility for the provision and maintenance of Garda accommodation.  The Minister for Justice and Equality has no direct role in these matters, as the Senator will appreciate.  The Minister has been informed, however, that at the outset of the pilot reopening process the Garda authorities provided a brief of requirements to the OPW on the reopening of each of these six Garda stations and requested that the OPW carry out technical surveys to determine the works necessary to enable the stations to reopen.</p> <p>The Senator is aware that following the consideration of the OPW technical surveys of each of the six stations, the Commissioner identified the organisation's preferred way forward bearing in mind operational needs, costs, timeframe for delivery and other factors.  Engagement between the OPW and An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na has continued, providing further necessary detail to allow the pilot programme of reopenings to proceed to the next stage of implementation.</p> <p>As the works required at each station are different it can be expected that the six stations will be reopened at different times.  The Department has been informed that the necessary works were completed at Donard station in December 2018 and the station has now been handed over to An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na by the OPW.</p> <p>Finalisation of design planning, where required, and the procurement for works at each of the five remaining stations included in the pilot programme are at different stages but are being processed by the OPW in conjunction with An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na in line with all applicable processes and procedures.  In advance of today's debate the Minister requested an update from the OPW and the Garda authorities specifically on progress on Rush Garda station.  From the OPW we understand that a revised brief of requirements regarding Rush station was received from An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na in August 2018.  We are informed that the OPW prepared and submitted a proposed plan to the Garda authorities for review and that a final design plan was agreed and signed off in December 2018.  We are informed that the OPW is currently preparing tender documents to procure the required works at Rush station via the OPW measured term maintenance contract.  Some interim minor maintenance works such as clearing pathways and so on will be carried out by the OPW regional office in advance of those works.  The OPW has said it expects works to be complete and the Rush station to be handed over to An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na by this year, summer 2019.  After the hand over of the building the exact date of reopening of the station will be an operational matter for An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy David Stanton:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1053"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1053&amp;amp;pid=DavidStanton&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I assure the Senator that implementation of a pilot Garda station reopening project and reopening of all relevant stations will be pursued as a priority.  The Office of Public Works expects that work will be completed in all remaining stations this year.  I hope that is useful to the Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#E00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his comprehensive answer.  It is great that the project is progressing at this rate.  I am pleased the Minister of State has given a final date of summer 2019.  I have tried to pin down the Minister on several occasions.  Obviously, things were progressing.  It is good the Department is moving towards the final point in this and I note the tender documents are being prepared.  It would be assumed that relatively minor works remain to be done on the Garda station if the Minister of State envisages the handover taking place this summer.  I hope that An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na can staff the station at that stage.  I will make a request to the Minister to provide extra Garda resources for north County Dublin, including extra Garda cars and the other resources that the Garda needs.  There is no point having the Garda station reopened if there are not enough resources in place.  I thank the Minister of State for the update.  I appreciate it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1277" speakername="David Stanton" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#E00300"><p>I compliment the Senator on her interest in pursuing this important matter and I thank her for raising.  Again, I assure her of the Government's commitment to the pilot Garda station reopening scheme, which is intended to determine possible positive impacts that such openings would have on criminal activity.  That is the reason it is going ahead.</p> <p>As I have said, An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and the OPW are working closely together to allow for the reopening of the stations concerned, including the station in Rush.  I have heard the Senator's views and I reassure her that the OPW and Garda authorities are working closely together to allow for the reopening of each of the six stations.  The station in Donard has been completed and has been handed over and the others will hopefully be completed this year as well.</p> <p>It is not possible for me to say at this stage when exactly Rush Garda station will reopen because that is a matter for the Garda Commissioner.  I am informed by the OPW that the necessary remedial works will be completed by the summer of this year.  Staffing and other resources are matters for the Commissioner and the Minister has no direct role in directing that, as such.  The exact opening date is an operational matter for An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  I thank the Senator for her interest and for raising this matter.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.25" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#E00400">Passport Applications</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#E00500"><p>I welcome the Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade, Deputy McEntee.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#E00600"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach for selecting this Commencement matter.  I was contacted recently by an Irish woman whose British wife recently gave birth to their son, who was conceived through assisted human reproduction methods.  They are both legally recognised as parents in Britain on all statutory documents, including the birth certificate.  However, when the Irish mother, who is the non-biological mother, wished to apply for an Irish passport for her child, she was told that she was not recognised as a mother under law and, therefore, was not entitled to apply for an Irish passport for her child.</p> <p>The reply from the Department to a recent parliamentary question that I submitted through Deputy Crowe confirmed the position and stated that, for the purposes of Irish law and with specific reference to the Irish Nationality and Citizenship Act 1956, a parent is understood to mean either the mother or father of the child.  It further stated that for the purposes of Irish law the mother of a child is the person who gives birth to the child or a female adopter of the child.  What this means in reality is that same-sex parents are excluded.  These parents frequently rely on assisted human reproduction methods to conceive.  Parents who are legally recognised and hold Irish citizenship cannot extend their citizenship rights in the same manner as everyone else.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Fintan Warfield:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2458"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2458&amp;amp;pid=FintanWarfield&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This is clear discrimination and a very real denial of rights and would certainly not withstand legal challenge.</p><p>It bears some resemblance to the time when we did not have marriage equality, before we held the referendum on civil marriage equality, and the relationship of couples who had been married elsewhere was relegated to a civil partnership in this State.  As the Minister of State knows, the Zappone and Gilligan case was an example of that.  The referendum that followed brought with it very hurtful conversations on the validity of same-sex parent-led families, when posters stating "Every child deserves a mother and a father" were put up around the State.  The people's vote said that there is no single proposition for a family in Ireland, only diversity.</p><p>We urgently need relevant legislation to catch up and it is unacceptable that a passport form in this day and age would ask for a mother and a father and exclude same-sex parents.  There is also an unprecedented demand for Irish passports so we have to ensure that our passport laws are robust and that we are not leaving anyone behind.  Does the Minister of State agree that the Act needs to be updated and will the Government bring forward such legislation in this term?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1337" speakername="Helen McEntee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#F00200"><p>I thank the Senator for raising what is a very important issue.  While much of my response is quite technical in outlining the situation as it stands, the Senator has brought it back to what it should be about, namely, families, children and their parents.  While he, I and many others would recognise both people in the example he gave as parents, the letter of the law says otherwise.  We have to work to bring about change, as we have done in the past and as the Senator outlined.</p> <p>All passports are issued in accordance with the provisions of the Passports Act 2008, as amended.  Pursuant to section 7 of the Act, a passport cannot be issued unless the Minister is satisfied that the person is an Irish citizen and as to the identity of the person.  Citizenship is governed by the Irish Nationality and Citizenship Act 1956, as amended, which is under the responsibility of the Minister for Justice and Equality.  Legislative measures relating to citizenship do not fall within the remit of the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade.  I will therefore confine my remarks to an explanation of the current citizenship legislation under which the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade operates.  I will also explain the current legislative situation relating to guardianship of children.</p> <p>The Department, specifically the passport service, is tasked with processing passport applications in line with the requirements of the Passports Act.  The passport service has received several applications from same-sex married couples seeking to obtain Irish passports for their children born abroad and, in giving due consideration to these applications, has rightly raised a number of issues relating to both citizenship and guardianship with the relevant Departments and the Office of the Attorney General.</p> <p>I would like to set out the current legislation on citizenship.  Section 7 of the Irish Nationality and Citizenship Act 1956, as amended, addresses citizenship by descent and provides that a person is an Irish citizen from birth if at the time of his or her birth either parent was an Irish citizen, although an additional requirement of registration is imposed in respect of children born outside the island of Ireland where the Irish citizen parent was also born outside the island of Ireland.</p> <p>For the purposes of the 1956 Act, a parent is understood to mean either the "mother" or "father" of the child.  For the purpose of Irish law, the mother of a child is the person who gives birth to the child or a female adopter of a child.  In general, the "father" is the person identified as the genetic father of the child or a male adopter.</p> <p>The passport service has received passport applications for children born outside the State to same-sex couples where one member of the couple is an Irish citizen and the other is not.  Following consideration of the 1956 Act, the passport service understands that, under the current legislation, where the Irish citizen is neither the birth mother nor the genetic father or neither the male nor female adopter of the child, the child does not qualify for Irish citizenship by descent.  The passport service sought and received advice on its understanding of the 1956 Act from the Office of the Attorney General.</p> <p>While the passport service's understanding was confirmed, the Office of the Attorney General was of the view that further confirmation from the Department of Justice and Equality was required.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Helen McEntee:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2394"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2394&amp;amp;pid=HelenMcEntee&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The passport service has sought clarification  from the Department of Justice and Equality on this and many other related matters, including the effect on citizenship of Parts 2 and 3 of the Children and Family Relationships Act 2015, once commenced by the Minister for Health.  </p><p>I would like to outline the current legal status and position on guardianship.  There are particular provisions in the Passport Act dealing with applications for children.  Under the terms of the Act, the passport service requires the consent of a guardian or guardians before issuing a passport for a child under the age of 18 years, subject to very limited exceptions.  Section 14(1) of the Act provides, "The Minister shall, before issuing a passport to a child, be satisfied on reasonable grounds that where a child has two guardians, each guardian of the child, and where a child has two or more guardians, at least two of those, consent to the issuing of a passport for the child".  In line with section 2 of the Act, "guardianship" is a term with a defined legal meaning.  For the purposes of that section, "a guardian" means a person who, first, is a guardian of the child pursuant to the Guardianship of Infants Act 1964 and, second, is appointed to be a guardian by either the child, deed, or will or order of court in the State and has not been removed from that office.  In cases where a child has only one guardian within the meaning of the legislation, the guardian is required to complete a sole guardian affidavit to confirm that there is no other person to confirm that no other person holds guardianship rights in respect of the child applying for a passport.  This is necessary in order to verify that the requirements for guardian consent have been satisfied.  It is my understanding the Minister for Health has recently met civil society representative groups from the LGBTI community to discuss a range of issues, including the rights of same-sex couples and their children.  I will bring this debate to the attention of the Minister, the Minister for Justice and Equality and my colleague, the T&aacute;naiste, Deputy Coveney.  This is an issue we need to address and it is an area in which I would like to see further progression.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#G00200"><p>I hope the Minister of State will appreciate that she has provided a lot of information and that I will not be able to extract the key points in just one minute.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#G00300"><p>I might give the Senator some latitude.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#G00400"><p>People have a reasonable expectation, after the big national conversation we had on foot of the referendum, that relevant obstacles will be dealt with.  This does not affect a huge number of people, but there is an expectation that the obstacles will be removed.  Often, when working on LGBT rights, people are surprised because we have had that national conversation to hear that certain issues have not been sorted out or dealt with.  However, these issues still arise; this is not the only such circumstance.  Legislation only allows mothers to avail of adoptive leave; therefore, two men who adopt do not have shared or equal adoptive leave entitlements.  This is but one of many issues which include the Children and Family Relationships Act.  I will keep in touch with the Minister of State and her office and appreciate her response.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1337" speakername="Helen McEntee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#G00500"><p>There have been recent discussions on this matter which do not just follow on from the Attorney General's request for further clarification from the Department.  There have been other legislative developments, led by the Department of Justice and Equality, the Department of Health and the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection which will I hope have a positive impact in this area in dealing with some of the concerns that have been raised.  Most importantly, there must be continued engagement with civil society groups on the issues faced by same-sex couples to try to address some of the outstanding issues raised by the Senator.  I am happy to engage with my colleagues and, on a personal level, with the Senator to progress them further.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.35" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#G00550">Housing Provision</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#G00600"><p>Last Saturday I marched with the communities of Sandymount, Ringsend and Irishtown on Pearse Street because of the fear of the loss of social and affordable units within them.  Last week there was an announcement that the 40 housing units to be provided in the South Lotts Road area, which is in a strategic development zone, SDZ, were to be provided instead in Rialto.  The units were to be part of the community gain from the SDZ covered under Part V of the legislation.  Following on from the media coverage of the issue, it was announced by senior officials at Dublin City Council that there would be no social housing in Dublin 2, Dublin 4 or Dublin 6 without a special case being made for it.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Kevin Humphreys:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2289"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2289&amp;amp;pid=KevinHumphreys&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Another senior official said there would be no affordable housing in Dublin 2, Dublin 4 or Dublin 6.  The best they can expect is to build them out in the suburbs.  This has led to fears, which I can understand, that the 350 social units promised for the strategic development zone in Poolbeg West will not be delivered, never mind the 550 affordable and affordable rental homes promised by the then Minister, Deputy Coveney.<br/><br/>The deposits have been paid on the sites in the strategic development zone, SDZ, in Poolbeg West and on the Poolbeg Peninsula.  Some &euro;30 million has been set aside for a bridge over the River Dodder to give access to the Poolbeg West development site.  The taxpayers paid for the decontamination of the site and there is a blank cheque from the Department for the plinth that has to be put in place but which is, so far, uncosted.<br/><br/>It is unacceptable for senior city council officials to say there will be no social or affordable housing in these areas and to be left unchallenged by the Department.  The previous Minister, Deputy Coveney, gave a firm commitment to the delivery of 900 units and this is written into the strategic development zone plan that is before An Bord Plean&aacute;la at the moment.  Fine Gael has been saying that the housing crisis can only be solved by delivery but we know there is a strong lobby for going higher.  I do not necessarily have a problem with height or density but there are three strategic development zones in the Docklands - the North Lotts, the South Lotts and Poolbeg West.  There is speculation that building on the North Lotts will go higher.  The Minister needs to take note of the fact that strategic development zones have clear objectives and integrated planning schemes.  If one goes higher in one location one has to do the same for all developments in that location and if one increases commercial development, one also has to increase residential, and <i>vice versa</i>.  With the height strategy outlined by the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government, Deputy Eoghan Murphy, the Government is running the risk of undermining the three strategic development zones.  The outcome will be that over 5,000 units in this city will be delayed.<br/><br/>I am not sure if the Government has the competence to manage this issue.  All I see in the attempts to increase the supply of housing is mistake after mistake.  There have been three delays in supply, all caused by the Department of Housing, Planning and Local Government.  These were the change in apartment sizes, the change in car parking spaces and the change relating to the height strategy.  All led to further planning applications, even though developments of over 100 units can go straight to An Bord Plean&aacute;la.  There has been delay after delay with applications being withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1264" speakername="Damien English" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#H00200"><p>I will try to deal with the question that was asked, as well as the ten other questions that were added in during the Senator's contribution.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#H00300"><p>They are related issues.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1264" speakername="Damien English" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#H00400"><p>My role regarding Part V of the Planning and Development Act 2000 is to provide the policy and legislative framework, while the day-to-day administration and operation of Part V are a matter for the local authorities.  Senator Humphreys will, no doubt, be aware that following an independent review of Part V, completed in 2014, which included a detailed and lengthy consultation process and which took into account the general housing market trends at that time, the requirement was reduced from 20% to 10%, effective from 1 September 2015.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Damien English:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1781"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1781&amp;amp;pid=DamienEnglishFG&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->My Department subsequently issued statutory guidelines to local authorities on the amended Part V rules.  These guidelines recommended that the acquisition of units on the development site be the preferred option for local authorities.  However, each local authority must make sure its Part V agreements constitute the best use of financial resources available and that unit sizes meet social housing requirements.</p><p>My Department considers all requests from local authorities for sanction for funding of the acquisition of units under Part V in light of construction costs in the area, and also one of the key aims of Part V, the general social integration, which is a very important one. </p><p>Senators will know that Part V is just one constituent part of the significant efforts being made by this Government to deliver the social housing supports that Ireland needs in the coming years.  These efforts are backed up by an unprecedented level of investment under the Rebuilding Ireland action plan.  More than &euro;6 billion of taxpayers' money will be spent during the lifetime of that plan delivering in excess of 50,000 social housing homes, as well as many more supports through the private rental market.  Part V homes are expected to deliver just under 5,000 of the overall total and as the construction sector recovers and delivery increases, so too does our dividend in terms of Part V.  It is encouraging to see their numbers increase year on year because they not only deliver additional stock but make a vital contribution, as I mentioned, in terms of promoting social integration and developing more positive sustainable communities - a benefit to all of Irish society.  I know Senator Humphreys agrees with that.  That is probably part of what the debate on this Commencement matter is about, namely, to ensure that we still achieve that.  </p><p>We are very much about delivering the social housing we need as a nation.  We are also very well aware of the need to build those sustainable mixed tenure communities all over Ireland.  In general, this approach works well across the country.  Unfortunately there are occasions when our two key objectives of increased delivery and social integration can come into some conflict.  When this happens we must be pragmatic, constructive and seek to strike the right balance.  Such a scenario tends to happen in what might be termed more "high-end" developments.</p><p>As to areas such as the Dublin Docklands, all options for the delivery of Part V homes are explored, including the most cost-effective way of delivering much-needed social housing units in these specific electoral areas.  Alternatives can, if required, be explored, particularly off-site development nearby which delivers more homes for the same price.  In other words, there is the option in some scenarios for some land swaps or for some land to be given in terms of housing.  My Department is committed to working with the council to help find that balance and to deliver solutions that increase our social housing stock in the places where they are needed but at a price that is acceptable to the Exchequer.  That is a decision that has to be made locally as we tease through the different sites.</p><p>On the Deputy's attempt to suggest that changes we have made with respect to apartments sizes, car parking spaces, and height strategy are delaying matters, we have to make necessary changes to effect the overall supply of housing now and well into the future.  We have the Rebuilding Ireland document, which is a strategy for social housing and housing in general.  We are reaching all the targets set in terms of what we want to deliver, both in the private sector and the public sector.  We are bang on target right across the board.  The Central Statistics Office figures confirmed that last week.</p><p>Furthermore, the changes we have made might in some cases on different sites generate new applications, but it has been confirmed that the overall supply of housing is up by 25%.  Commencement notices are up by more than 50%.  With respect to some sites, there will be chop and change but the overall delivery is up and the trend is positive.</p><p>We believe the changes we have made regarding the height strategy, car parking spaces and so on will increase the supply and mix of housing coming onstream which we badly need.  Those are changes that were probably put off for many years by previous Governments but we have made them now and I have no doubt they will effect supply in a positive way in the future.  One can select one or two sites and argue over them but we have had to make decisions in the round to increase the supply of housing well into the future.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#J00200"><p>The Minister of State clearly knows what I have said to him.  Council officials have probably blown the whistle on him if they are saying there will be no social or affordable housing in the areas of Dublin 2, 4 and 6.  They are already implementing that policy.  The Minister of State mentioned provision in an off-site development nearby.  That is not what happened in the South Lotts strategic development zone.  The units are being provided in Rialto, a different housing area, more than 3 km away.  Therefore, the Minister of State, with respect to any of the answers he has given, has not satisfied my concerns.  He has confirmed that the community's fears in this respect are real.  The 350 social units on the Poolbeg West site are now in danger.  The Minister of State's commitment to the 550 social and affordable units is now questionable.</p> <p>I have asked the Minister of State for clear answers but he has not given any.  He has avoided a straight answer.  I will give him a clear warning.  If there are changes in the strategic development zones, that may very well undermine all the strategic development zones not only in Dublin but across the country and cause a further worsening of the housing crisis.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Kevin Humphreys:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2289"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2289&amp;amp;pid=KevinHumphreys&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The Minister of State and the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government, Deputy Eoghan Murphy, are in charge of housing and have a responsibility to deliver on the objectives of the SDZ, but they are not doing so.  They have allowed the officials in Dublin City Council to choose not a nearby off-site location but a distant off-site location.  This is not acceptable to the communities of Ringsend, Irishtown and Pearse Street and the Government must pull its socks up and start to deliver on the objectives of the SDZ and under Part V which clearly states there can be an off-site allocation but that it must be nearby.  That is not happening in the city and it is not the intention of the Department's officials for it to happen in the city.  The Government needs to wake up and smell the roses.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1264" speakername="Damien English" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#K00200"><p>On the Dublin docklands and Part V, the cost of purchasing units in the docklands area can often far exceed the cost ceilings we try to maintain.  In some cases, land and development costs are extremely high, the units have a high specification or there are high management fees for services such a a concierge, gyms and so on beyond what the Department generally funds through the local authorities.  In some cases, the purchase would not be deemed to be value for money, leading the city council to determine that off-site provision be considered to comply with Part V.  For example, it determined that on-site affordability was not possible at the Capital Dock development and procured the Part V units off-site in Rialto.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#K00300"><p>Rialto is not nearby.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1264" speakername="Damien English" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#K00400"><p>There is another development under consideration by the city council, namely, the Landings as part of Project Wave, which will deliver 30 units on-site.  The cost of these units will also be high, at more than &euro;400,000 per unit, but the council considers them to be good value for money compared to the estimated cost of sourcing and possibly upgrading on-site units.  While the Department has asked the council to consider alternative options for the delivery of the Part V portion of the development, the council is preparing a submission to the Department which will restate the suitability and affordability of the on-site units.  The council is, therefore, making a case.</p> <p>I stress that in the case of Part V projects and certain areas of high pressure, site by site decisions must be made in conjunction with the local authorities and the Department.  Dublin City Council has eight active developments in the docklands area to which Part V applies and we are working through them.  Three of the developments have received planning permission, while the city council has made contact with the other developers.  In general, for Part V projects, delivery is agreed at commencement stage of the planning application.  It is not the case that we are making only general comments.  The Senator is perhaps trying to make a different argument.  We must work through each site, which is what we are trying to do as well as we can.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#K00500"><p>There are 1,720 planning applications, but there have been only 26 deliveries-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#K00600"><p>The Senator does not have an opportunity to respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.49" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 3.20 p.m. and resumed at 3.35 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.50" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#N00150">An tOrd Gnó - Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#N00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, Judicial Appointments Commission Bill 2017 - Committee Stage, resumed, to be taken at 5.15 p.m. and to adjourn at 7 p.m. if not previously concluded; and No. 2, Personal Injuries Assessment Board (Amendment) (No. 2) Bill 2018 - Second Stage, to be taken at 7 p.m., with the contributions of group spokespersons not to exceed ten minutes and those of all other Senators not to exceed six minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#N00300"><p>I call Senator Ardagh.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#N00400"><p>Senator Clifford-Lee.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#N00500"><p>Senator Ardagh is not present today, so it is me.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#N00600"><p>Senator Clifford-Lee is very welcome.  I should have been more observant.  I apologise.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#N00700"><p>No bother.  I forgive you.  I continue to raise the concerns about the national children's hospital.  I was once again out and about in north County Dublin knocking on doors and it was again the main topic of conversation.  Everyone wanted to talk about the massive overruns.  There is now a shift in focus from the massive overruns to where we are going to get the money to plug the gap.  We learn that &euro;100 million is to be taken out of capital expenditure this year alone.  This sum must be found to plug this outrageous gap due to the overspend on the national children's hospital.  I therefore continue the call of my colleague, Senator Ardagh, last week that we get the Minister for Health into the Chamber as soon as possible this week to talk about the overruns at the children's hospital and specifically to outline where the cuts will come.</p> <p>We have learnt through the media that &euro;100 million is what must come out of the capital budget this year but, astonishingly, &euro;30 million must come out of the transport budget, with all the other Departments contributing approximately &euro;3 million each.  It is astonishing that the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport must plug the gap in the Department of Health's expenditure.  As well as the Minister for Health, I would like the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport to come to the House because we want to learn what transport projects will be cut.  We have-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#N00800"><p>Stepaside Garda station.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#N00900"><p>Perhaps one of the reasons &euro;30 million is coming from the transport budget is that the Minister's focus is elsewhere.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Lorraine Clifford-Lee:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2461"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2461&amp;amp;pid=LorraineCliffordLee&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We will be back debating the Judicial Appointments Commission Bill following the Order of Business.  He is concerning himself with judicial appointments and the reopening of Garda stations and taking his eye off the ball.  A total of 30% of this year's overrun must be borne by the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport.  What transport infrastructure project will bear the brunt of this?  Will BusConnects be rolled out?  Will we have the greenways that have been promised?  What about the carriages for the northern commuter line?  I face into packed carriages when I get on the train in the morning in Donabate, as do all my constituents.  Will we see this resolved?  We need the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport to come to the House.  Will this create a precedent for following years?  We know the gap will have to be plugged in the coming years.  Will the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport have to plug the gap?  I could go on and on about the failings of the Minister in that Department.  This is an important issue, particularly in north County Dublin, which has the fastest growing population in the country and where the transport infrastructure that does not cater for the needs of the people living there currently or who will live there in future.  The Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport must plug the gap caused by the Department of Health.  The Ministers for Health and Transport, Tourism and Sport need to come to the Chamber to answer our pressing questions on this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#O00200"><p>I welcome Valerie and Martin Hurley, neighbours of mine from west Cork to the Public Gallery.  Martin is celebrating his 50th birthday.  They are accompanied by Deputy Murphy O'Mahony.  I hope they have a lovely day and that Martin has a great 50th birthday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#O00300"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#O00400"><p>I want to address the issue of the national children's hospital and other associated matters.  I have also been addressed and spoken to by members of the public about the waste of parliamentary time in calling for Ministers' heads every time something goes wrong.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#O00500"><p>Exactly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#O00600"><p>What changed in the Department of Justice and Equality when Deputy Frances Fitzgerald's head was taken?  What changed when Deputy Dennis Naughten's head was taken?  What changes in any Department when a head is taken?  The same people are left behind doing the same job they always did.  I have spoken previously about how the Carltona doctrine protects those who are behind Ministers.  If the Minister, Deputy Harris, had been watching the children's hospital all day every day and was not watching the nurses, people would have said we needed his head because he had not been watching the nurses.  That would mean he must divide his time between the nurses and the hospital but what about the GPs?  This bloody nonsense has to stop.  It is debasing politics and both Houses of the Oireachtas.</p> <p>The Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport has been mentioned with regard to the Judicial Appointments Commission Bill.  There have been 86 hours of debate so far.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#O00700"><p>More.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#O00800"><p>Half of the Government has no faith whatsoever in the Bill.  The bottom line on it is another little deal was done.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#O00900"><p>Senator-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#O01000"><p>I am sorry but I am trying to get something across.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#O01100"><p>Senator Craughwell is almost succeeding.  He should continue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#O01200"><p>Members of the public are entitled to fair representation in the House and we have had the nonsense for 86 hours.  Now, I am told the Leader is to step up debate on the Bill to two days a week but for what?  Why are we doing this?  Half of the Leader's party does not believe the Bill is worthy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#O01300"><p>Does Senator Craughwell have Senator McDowell's single transferable script?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#O01400"><p>If the Leader wants to play that old game, we can play it.  The bottom line is if the Government was honest-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#O01500"><p>Please observe the dignity of the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#O01600"><p>Through the Chair.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#O01700"><p>-----it would pull the Bill and let us get back to proper parliamentary work.  We have had 86 hours of debate for what?  The chances are when the Bill is eventually dragged through the House, the President will send it to the Supreme Court and it will be struck down because it is unconstitutional anyway.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#O01800"><p>And the Minister knows it is not constitutional.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#O01900"><p>Please, this is-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#O02000"><p>It is a pity Senator Craughwell is not the President.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#O02100"><p>I did try.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#O02200"><p>He had the chance.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#O02300"><p>I did not get the Leader's backing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#O02400"><p>Please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#O02500"><p>The white flag was raised before the off.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#O02600"><p>This is not the Supreme Court so------</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#O02700"><p>Among ourselves, we need to find time to decide where we should debate and what we should debate.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Gerard P. Craughwell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2402"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2402&amp;amp;pid=GerardPCraughwell&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->However, it is a nonsense to call for a Minister's head every time there is a little glitch outside the door.  What happens?  The same people stay in place and the same things go on.  Perhaps the &euro;30 million is being taken from the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport as the <i>quid pro quo</i>for the Judicial Appointments Commission Bill.  I do not know.  We need to stop this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#P00200"><p>Today, our MEPs will vote on an EU-Singapore trade agreement and the associated EU-Singapore investment protection agreement.  I raise this issue because the House voted to express concern about the prospect of an investor court system that would allow corporations to sue states for lost future profits when new regulations are introduced by elected representatives in response to the needs of the electorate.  There would be what has been termed a significant chilling effect on our ability to pursue good policy, respond politically and regulate.  With these courts comes the risk that any new regulatory decision could be a hostage to fortune because a blank cheque had effectively been given to any corporation looking for lost future profits, which is a wide scope.  The House debated the matter at length.  It is unfortunate that problematic elements in the Transatlantic Trade and Investment Partnership, TTIP, and the EU-Canada Comprehensive Economic and Trade Agreement, CETA, are raising their head again in the EU-Singapore investment treaty.  I have urged our MEPs to vote "No" because we can have a better kind of trade deal.  We all want trade, but it has to work for citizens as well as corporations.</p> <p>The House will hold further debates on the issue, as we cannot afford to introduce such courts, particularly in light of our climate change commitments.  The idea that strengthening those commitments would come with a "hostage to fortune" cost is in conflict with our international obligations.  Of particular concern is that the EU-Singapore treaty also asserts the right to overturn local government decisions.  I say this on a day when Dublin City Council produced a climate change action plan for Dublin, for which I applaud it, that is more ambitious than the Government's action plan for the State.  Dynamic actions are being taken on issues like climate change at local level, but these new treaties would not only lead to challenges to the State, but also to local authorities, and would have a chilling effect on them and stop them taking proactive actions.</p> <p>I wish to make a specific request.  I thank the Leader for arranging improved debates on climate change in recent weeks, with witnesses appearing before us.  However, there is a linked, but different, crisis.  Will the Minister for Communications, Climate Action and Environment address the House on the ecological crisis?  Certain areas are seeing a 60% extinction level and there are reports of a 40% decline in the number of insects, something that has been called a catastrophic collapse.  At the beginning of our term in the Seanad, we debated the pollinator plan, our hedgerows, and the importance of insect life and green corridors.  These issues are linked to, but distinct from, climate change.  Will the Leader arrange a specific debate on this matter and will he pass my request on to the Minister?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#P00300"><p>I pay tribute to the determination and dignity of the nurses.  Union members are yet to be balloted and will reach their own decisions around what is on the table for them, but regardless of the outcome, they have done a great public service by highlighting a problem that would only have worsened with time.  The reasons for the dispute need to be addressed.  I thank those who, despite having their appointments postponed and their personal needs unmet, stood steadfast behind the strike.  They know how necessary it is for those working in the system to shout "Stop".  I also thank the care staff and others within the health system, not only for the vital work they do, but for recognising that all workers have the right to work within a safer system.</p> <p>Regarding the &euro;450 million overspend at the national children's hospital, Senator Craughwell wondered what the point would be of asking for someone to be accountable or for someone's head on a plate.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Rose Conway-Walsh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2462"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2462&amp;amp;pid=RoseConwayWalsh&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I ask the Senator and others to explain what we mean by accountable.  Do we mean there should be a number of apologies?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Q00200"><p>There should be an explanation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Q00300"><p>There are some things that cannot just be explained away.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Q00400"><p>They have, which is the point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Q00500"><p>We have been doing this for years.  It is interesting to look back to 2008 and 2009, when Fine Gael vigorously criticised Fianna F&aacute;il for wasting money, describing the Health Service Executive as a bureaucratic monster that eats money.  It rightly accused Fianna F&aacute;il of cancelling services rather than cutting waste.  Fine Gael was going to do things differently.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Q00600"><p>Just like the Senator's party.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Q00700"><p>Have a bit of manners, Senator.  I am speaking.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Q00800"><p>Is that directed to me?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Q00900"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Q01000"><p>All right.  Very good.  The Senator was not looking at me.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Q01100"><p>Ci&uacute;nas, le bh&uacute;r dtoil.  Senator Norris, sometimes your interjections are unhelpful.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Q01200"><p>I appreciate that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Q01300"><p>They are what?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Q01400"><p>They are unhelpful.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Q01500"><p>Sometimes they are unwelcome.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Q01600"><p>They are intended to be.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Q01700"><p>Only sometimes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Q01800"><p>Senator Conway-Walsh has the floor and should be allowed to continue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Q01900"><p>I hope I will be allowed another minute for that.  It is about where accountability stops and how many times somebody must be made accountable.  The Minister for Health, Deputy Harris, has apologised for not giving a fuller account in a parliamentary reply but this is not the first time he has had to apologise.  He is a serial apologiser.  We have had the CervicalCheck scandal, the treatment waiting lists, the trolley crisis, problems for scoliosis patients and many other failings.  The public are wondering at which point we say the buck must stop somewhere.  The question is how many apologies make up accountability.</p> <p>There is now a &euro;450 million overspend on just one project.  There may be people in the Chamber who think that is okay and one can just apologise for that.  It does not matter what pot this comes from, as it all comes from the same pockets.  These are the same pockets that have absolutely nothing left to give.  They are the same pockets that get fleeced for everything despite us going to them time and again to pay for things.  Somebody must pay for this and it is the Irish citizens and taxpayers who do so.  It is decision time for each and every Fianna F&aacute;il Member in these Houses.  Do they still have confidence in a Minister who conceals vital information while pretending to negotiate a budget?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Q02000"><p>Sinn F&eacute;in has no Ministers in the North.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Q02100"><p>They were negotiating a budget.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Q02200"><p>It is allowing civil servants to run it.  It may as well do what it is doing in the North.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Q02300"><p>This could not be made up.  Do the Senators not feel they are being taken for fools?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Q02400"><p>It is peak Mary Lou.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Q02500"><p>Senator Norris should not join those benches as well.  Is he joining the unaccountable-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Q02600"><p>Who is this woman?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Q02700"><p>Senator Norris should take a seat.  I ask Senator Conway-Walsh to conclude as I have been very fair.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Q02800"><p>Do the Senators not know they are being taken as fools by the people to my right?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Q02900"><p>They are.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Q03000"><p>Senator Clifford-Lee called into question the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Ross, and I have called him into question numerous times.  At the beginning of this term, I spoke about collective Cabinet responsibility and the Minister was not very good at following that concept.  In considering what has happened in recent days, it is the Cabinet that is responsible rather than individual Ministers.  There is a collective responsibility and those decisions are made collectively.  There has been a change with the structures in Cabinet.  In looking at accountability for this, we must consider why this problem occurred and how we can ensure it does not happen again.  A previous Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform challenged all spending, as Senator Reilly, a former Minister for Health, will attest.  It was a challenging environment in the previous five-year Government term when it came to expenditure matters, and each item of spending was put under a magnifying glass to ensure we could get full value for money for the taxpayer.</p> <p>There has been a change in the structure of the Department of Finance and it has caused cost overruns, including with the children's hospital.  When we speak of accountability, we must understand the reasons.  We cannot lay this at the door of one person as there is collective Cabinet responsibility.  This must be taken seriously as too often, under every Government, there have been overruns.  We must examine the people getting the contracts and how they legally challenge those contracts if they do not win them.  We must consider how they enlarge their cost base when they get those contracts.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Kevin Humphreys:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2289"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2289&amp;amp;pid=KevinHumphreys&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I want to raise a very serious issue which was on the front page of<i>The Irish Times</i>today.  The article said that families who turn down offers of social housing are to face a five-year wait.  To be honest, I believe this is spin.  This is about blaming people who are on the housing list for the housing crisis.  I know of very few people on the housing waiting list who have refused housing units.  I deal with a huge number of applicants week in and week out and the vast majority are delighted when they get an offer.<br/><br/>There have been some refusals.  I accept that.  Sometimes there have been very good reasons and sometimes there have been poor reasons, but we should not blame people who are on the housing list.  The issue should not be spun on the front page of <i>The Irish Times </i>and it should not be suggested that all those poor people on the waiting list are refusing housing, which is the subliminal message.  They are not.  I am only aware of one person who refused an offer of housing from Dublin City Council in the last six months and that was because the person would have had to give up their job because they would have had to surrender the support of their family in minding their children, which allowed them to go out to work.  The person would have then been caught in an unemployment-based poverty trap and housed well aware from their family.  I was disappointed.  The headline was spin rather than substance and blamed the people who are on the housing list.  It gave the message that they get loads of offers and keep saying &quot;No&quot;.  A tiny percentage refuse.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#R00200"><p>I want to raise a very important issue which affects the entire north of Dublin city and county, namely, metro north.  On Thursday Fingal County Council will present details of four master plans for Swords, involving 67 ha of land, 218,000 sq. m of commercial space, and 55 acres of office space in buildings four, five, six and seven storeys high.  Some 18,000 jobs will eventually be created in this area.  The plans include 2,700 badly needed homes.  There will be 10,000 new residents.  Another 3,500 homes are to be constructed as a result of the funding the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government has made available under the local infrastructure housing activation fund, LIHAF.  That represents another 12,000 residents, so there are to be 22,000 extra residents for Swords.  Swords has a population of 40,000 at the moment.  The Fingal development plan for 2017 to 2023 projects that the population will grow to 100,000.</p> <p>I would like the Leader to bring in the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport because we need the first phase of MetroLink to start as soon as possible.  I know there are issues and disputes about the route on the south side but there are no such disputes on the north side.  This has been in planning for more than 20 years.  It is very clear that MetroLink will take pressure off the city of Dublin by allowing access to the city from these lands by rapid transport.  It will connect the airport, DCU and Swords with the city.  As previous speakers have said, Fingal has the youngest population in Ireland and, possibly, in Europe.  These are talented, well educated people who are looking for jobs and who want to stay in Fingal.  The north end of the MetroLink line has to go ahead while the south side sorts itself out.  </p> <p>This initiative is close to my heart.  I fought for it during my time in Cabinet when there was no money and people wanted to kill it.  I wanted it to be kept alive.  We have the money now and we have a plan and preferred route for the north side.  Can we please proceed with this?  The Minister needs to come in here urgently to explain to us why it cannot go ahead on the north side now while the arrangements for the south side of the city are finalised.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#R00300"><p>I would like to raise my concerns about the imposition of the 23% VAT rate on food supplements.  This decision makes no sense.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Robbie Gallagher:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2471"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2471&amp;amp;pid=RobbieGallagher&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is wrong and it should be reversed.  I call on the Minister for Finance, Deputy Donohoe, to revisit this decision before any further decisions are made on it.  This proposal will affect and hurt the most vulnerable in our society, namely, the people who are under severe financial pressure due to the rising costs of living.  People take food supplements for a variety of reasons, but they primarily take them to stay healthy, to stay away from their local GP and to stay away from hospitals that are already under pressure.  With Brexit just around the corner, the timing of this proposed increase is wrong.  I am disappointed to say that it is yet another example of the Government's total lack of understanding of what life is like for those of us who live in the Border counties, or what life is like for those who are trying to run a business in the Border counties.  It is difficult enough without making decisions like this.  If this decision goes ahead, it will result in people travelling across the Border to shop, which will have a very negative impact on the businesses that are struggling to stay open along the Border counties.  Consider the fact that this also follows on from the increased VAT rate for the hotel industry.  It does not fill me with confidence that the Government gets it when it comes to businesses and people and what they are going through in the Border counties.  I ask the Leader to bring our message back to the Minister for Finance, Deputy Donohoe, to press the stall button on this decision, for the benefit of people's health and for those who are trying to run and keep open businesses while employing people in Border counties.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1431" speakername="P&aacute;draig &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#S00200"><p>T&aacute;im bu&iacute;och as ucht deis labhairt anseo inniu mar gheall ar ch&uacute;rsa&iacute; gn&oacute;tha&iacute; beaga small and medium sized enterprises.  I totally echo and support Senator Robbie Gallagher's comments.  T&aacute; an ceart aige go hioml&aacute;n.  It is a major issue.  We in both Houses are neglecting small and medium-sized businesses in Ireland and particularly in the Border counties.  These are the heart and soul of sustaining employment throughout the State with 97% of businesses being SMEs.</p> <p>Will the Leader speak to or connect with the Minister for Business, Enterprise and Innovation, Deputy Humphreys, to ask her to come to the House?  There is a major issue with insurance.  The Irish Small and Medium Enterprises Association, ISME, has conducted research recently on 850 SMEs that shows 83% of those SMEs are experiencing increases in insurance premiums.  We will debate the Personal Injuries Assessment Board (Amendment) (No. 2) Bill 2018 in this House later.  I very much welcome that legislation.  I received a phone call this morning on my way to the House from a person who has a business in the midlands.  Three years ago he employed 65 people and today he is employing about 115 people.  He has four cases of people looking to bring insurance claims against him.  A person can bring a claim against an employer and I have no problem with that.  I do have a problem, however, when on some occasions the claims are vexatious and may not be 100%.  I very much welcome the Bill.</p> <p>I am the rapporteur for the Seanad Public Consultation Committee, which has drafted a comprehensive report that is very near completion and will be published shortly.  This report will give us an indication of the roadmap of the SMEs in Ireland.  Subject to the committee's approval and under the chairmanship of the Leas-Chathaoirleach of the Seanad, Senator Coghlan, it is hoped we will have an opportunity to debate the issue and have a full session debate in this House with the relevant Ministers.  It affects tourism, transport, enterprise, farming and Bord Iascaigh Mhara.  I would very much welcome the comprehensive discussion and debate around that, if the Leader could facilitate that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1399" speakername="Neale Richmond" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#S00300"><p>I listened with interest to the Commencement debate earlier.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Neale Richmond:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2472"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2472&amp;amp;pid=NealeRichmond&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->A pertinent matter was raised by Senator Warfield on passport applications for children of same-sex couples abroad.  It was very important and I really hope that issue can be resolved.  It led me to the idea that we really need a debate in the House on the passport system and the future of the passport system for a couple of other serious reasons as well as the reasons raised by Senator Warfield this afternoon.</p><p>First and foremost, regardless of what happens in the next period of fewer than 50 days, Brexit is coming.  We have already seen tens of thousands of people in the UK and farther afield take the opportunity to seize Irish citizenship and apply for a passport.  The numbers of those applying to the Irish Embassy in Britain have multiplied every year-on-year.  We have serious questions to ask about the capacity of the passport service to meet these demands.  The passport service, much to the credit of the Ministers and officials working there, has vastly and greatly improved in recent years with the rapid online system and improvements in many others processing areas.  However, I have fears in respect of the capacity and I believe it is our absolute responsibility to meet the demand with a proper information campaign for the Irish diaspora.  This is something Senators Lawless and &Oacute; Donnghaile have worked hard on, whether in the US or the North, to ensure those who are Irish citizens know their entitlements, the processes and procedures and their rights.  We should ensure the process is met in the most speedy and proper manner.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#T00200"><p>Thank you for your brevity, Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#T00300"><p>I salute my colleagues, the nurses and midwives of Ireland, following their great successful rally on Saturday and the extraordinary support of the public through the streets of Dublin.  It was almost like a festival or carnival everywhere they were celebrated.</p> <p>I want to ask Senator Clifford-Lee and her colleagues where they were.  Where were they to support the nurses?  They all seemed to go into a huddle or they hid away, because they could not answer the question one way or another.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#T00400"><p>I was not.  I was on the picket line.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#T00500"><p>At the rally there was no sign of anyone from Fianna F&aacute;il whatsoever.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#T00600"><p>I have to take one day a week to mind my children.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#T00700"><p>There was not a sign or any presence of Fianna F&aacute;il one way or the other at the rally.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.132" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#T00900"><p>I want to know where they all were.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#T01000"><p>Please, Senator Devine, address the Chair.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#T01100"><p>That is rubbish.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#T01200"><p>With respect, I cannot have Senators talking over my head.  I am the Cathaoirleach.  Senator Devine, address your issues through me to the Leader and not to anyone else.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#T01300"><p>On a point of order, Fianna F&aacute;il was well represented.  It is a fairly low blow for the Senator to point me out in particular for not being at it.  I am on the picket regularly with the nurses.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#T01400"><p>Senator Clifford-Lee, that is not a point of order.  Resume your seat, Senator.  That is not a point of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#T01500"><p>I think the 50,000 people and the public who were there on Saturday will want to know why.  They were questioning where they were and why they were not there.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#T01600"><p>I doubt it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#T01700"><p>You are being unhelpful now, Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#T01800"><p>We were there.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#T01900"><p>The Senator should go and answer to those 50,000 who were asking that question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#T02000"><p>Please, Senator Devine, do not address an issue to another Senator.  Address the Chair and the Leader will respond, not someone else.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#T02100"><p>Okay, I will do so.  Gabh mo leithsc&eacute;al.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#T02200"><p>I am trying to be fair here.  This is not helpful.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#T02300"><p>This morning, the Minister for Health, Deputy Harris, said on his way that he was going into the Cabinet to put before it the proposals by the Labour Court that saw the suspension of the industrial action, including this strike and the three days due.  I put it to the Minister that it is not really up to the Cabinet to agree or disagree to this.  It is up to the 50,000 members of the Psychiatric Nurses Association and the Irish Nurses and Midwives Organisation to agree or disagree.  We await their deliberations, which are taking place now, and we will respect the results of those deliberations.</p> <p>The motion of no confidence arises because of the fiasco or debacle, or whatever we want to call it, ongoing in health.  Two Fianna F&aacute;il Deputies, Deputies Cowen and Donnelly, said yesterday that they were misled and that no one could have confidence in the Minister for Health, Deputy Harris.  However, today again - this is not lost on the public - those in Fianna F&aacute;il are still sitting in their huddle.  They should give us an apology because the polls are not right.  It is not simply that the polls are not right.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#T02400"><p>I am sorry: we are doing better in the polls than Sinn F&eacute;in.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#T02500"><p>They reckon that because Brexit is coming they cannot upset the nation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#T02600"><p>That is the typical Sinn F&eacute;in <i>modus operandi</i>.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#T02700"><p>Please, Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#T02800"><p>The two-year period of Brexit is extended-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#T02900"><p>Senator Devine, please conclude.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#T03000"><p>They want to cause chaos.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#T03100"><p>Please, Senator Devine, you are being unhelpful.  I have admonished you before.  If you want me to suspend the sitting for 15 minutes, the blame will be on you.  Please conclude now, Senator Devine.  You have had almost four minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#T03200"><p>The excuse we are getting is that Brexit is coming.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator M&aacute;ire Devine:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2468"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2468&amp;amp;pid=MaireDevine&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Brexit is going to probably extend it by two years.  We wait then.  Is this the excuse until the polls are in-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#U00200"><p>How does the Senator know that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#U00300"><p>How does the Senator know that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#U00400"><p>-----their proper order and the atmosphere is correct?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.161" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#U00600"><p>Is the Senator texting Teresa May?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#U00700"><p>Leader.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.164" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#U00900"><p>Matters affecting the other House should not be discussed here.  If there are motions in this House, we deal with them.  What happens in the other House stays there and is dealt with there.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#U01000"><p>Would the Cathaoirleach ask Senator Devine to give us the proper numbers tonight?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#U01100"><p>There is no point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#U01200"><p>Senator Buttimer is the Leader.  He will have ample time to respond.  I call Senator Grace O'Sullivan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1385" speakername="Grace O'Sullivan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#U01300"><p>Last week I visited a number of primary schools in Tramore, Gl&oacute;r na Mara, Holy Cross, Gaelscoil Philib Bar&uacute;n, Educate Together and Fenor national school.  Right now F&oacute;rsa estimates that 10% of the country's approximately 3,500 school secretaries are paid directly by the Department of Education and Skills, with their salaries varying from &euro;24,000 to &euro;44,711 per year.  The other 90% are paid through their schools' ancillary grant leaving some of the salaries as low as &euro;12,000 per year.  This grant is decided by the Department of Education and Skills and is sent to the school each year.  It then has to be paid out to the secretaries.  The majority of schools are forced to employ their school secretaries through their ancillary grant.</p> <p>This two-tier system means that in some schools there can be two secretaries doing exactly the same job in the same office, but one is paid &euro;44,000 per year and the other &euro;12,000 per year.  In any other walk of life this discrimination would be illegal.  Currently the majority of Ireland's school secretaries have to work for poor pay and without the most basic of employment rights such as sick pay or secure contracts, and they are mostly let go for the summer months and have to sign on for social welfare.  I know school secretaries who have been signing on for the summer or Easter breaks for years.  It is degrading to have to go to a social welfare office every July, and it is frustrating as the money they are entitled to can take up to six weeks to process.  </p> <p>Approximately 90% of all school secretaries have no pension rights.  These are people we all know in our communities.  This is a scandal.  I am crying out to all parties in the House to please support the school secretaries.  There is a F&oacute;rsa Support Our Secretaries campaign.  In addition, will the Leader please ask the Minister for Employment Affairs and Social Protection, Deputy Regina Doherty, to come to the House to discuss this issue?  This is absolute, sustained discrimination.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" speakername="Gabrielle McFadden" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#U01400"><p>The Organisation of National Ex-Servicemen and Women, ONE, started when three veterans died on our streets.  These people served the Tricolour with pride, often in places of conflict, as the UN's most distinguished peacekeepers, and often in the North of Ireland during the Troubles.  It is a charity and it needs support.  Former members of the Defence Forces are going to highlight the plight of homeless veterans by camping on the streets of Dublin in sleeping bags made of fabric in the colours of the national flag.  It is atrocious that anybody who wore the Army's uniform would have to do this to raise funds for their veterans.  ONE has houses in Donegal, Athlone and Dublin.  It provides 44 beds per night and has looked after more than 900 veterans in its time, and 16,000 bed nights in a year.  I urge all Members to go online and support the campaign.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Gabrielle McFadden:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2399"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2399&amp;amp;pid=GabrielleMcFadden&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I also ask that we contact that Minister and ask him to support this charity.  It should not have to be a charity in the first place; it should be supported.  It receives funding from the Department of Defence, but it is obviously not enough.  This has to be addressed.  No veteran who has served his or her country should have to rely on charity.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#V00200"><p>I propose an amendment, that item No. 11 of non-Government motions, regarding Shane O'Farrell, be taken at the end of the-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.173" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#V00300"><p>After item No. 2.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.174" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#V00400"><p>Yes, after item No. 2, and that we have a one hour debate at that point.</p> <p>I would like to refer to the demands that the Minister for Health and the Minister for Finance should withdraw.  It is absolute and utter nonsense.  In my 30 years of experience, the Minister for Finance, Deputy Donohoe, and the Minister for Health, Deputy Harris, are two of the best Ministers this country has ever had.  They are quite outstanding.  Members of the Opposition have instanced the case of Deputies Fitzgerald and Naughten.  They were rather foolish to bring them up, because both Deputies Fitzgerald and Naughten were subsequently vindicated.  They were got rid of unnecessarily, and it is an absolute waste of talent that excellent Ministers should be the victims of these demands for heads on a plate.  It is nonsense.  We should start thinking in terms of the good of this country and not just party politics.  I certainly will be supporting the Minister for Finance and the Minister for Health, both of whom have done extremely good jobs in very difficult and trying circumstances.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#V00500"><p>As much as I like Senator Devine, I have to say that I will take no lectures from a party that is elected to two parliaments and will not take its seats, yet claims massive expenses and wages in both.  When the gauntlet was put down-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#V00600"><p>That is not true.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.177" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#V00700"><p>That is not true.  The Senator should get his facts right.  He stands up all the time and does not know the facts.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#V00800"><p>I did not open my mouth when Senator Devine was talking.  When the gauntlet was thrown down to Sinn F&eacute;in to form the Government here it ran away.  We will take no lectures from Sinn F&eacute;in; its words are shallow.</p> <p>I would appreciate it if the Leader could ask the Minister for Communications, Climate Action and Environment to come to the Chamber to discuss the need to protect local and regional newspapers.  I am calling on the Minister to set up a commission to review local and regional print media before it is too late.  The Cairncross review was recently published in Britain.  It came up with logical answers to protect credible local journalism, which is so important for the health of local democracy and local news.  The Cairncross review also found that finding a way to support local news is now a matter of urgency.  It recommended a study of online advertising, often called "news feeds", which are widely known from Facebook and Google.  These often contain anything but news.  </p> <p>I recently discussed these findings with Mr. Johnny O'Hanlon, who most of us know from Local Ireland, which represents 35 local newspapers and printers throughout Ireland.  He is adamant that an immediate review and revival plan for local media is urgently required.  The Leader might ask the Minister, Deputy Bruton, to come to the Chamber to discuss local and regional print media with us.  I know that the issue is close to the Leader's heart, and that he has commented on it here before.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.179" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#V00900"><p>As a frequent user of trains I have become concerned, on a few levels, about the staffing of stations and trains, where unfortunately incidents of anti-social behaviour are on the increase.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paul Coghlan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1881"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1881&amp;amp;pid=PaulCoghlan&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I am disturbed that Irish Rail is proposing that stations such as Banteer, Millstreet-Sr&aacute;id an Mhuilinn, Rathmore and Farranfore will be left without any member of staff.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.181" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#W00200"><p>What will I do with my luggage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.182" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#W00300"><p>That is exactly the point.  Who will help the Senator with his luggage?  This will affect disabled people and elderly people, who need assistance from time to time.  It is not going to be a runner.  By contrast, the larger stations are well manned.  Given the extent of anti-social behaviour, it is essential to have one train host on every train.  I wonder what Irish Rail's policy is on drinking.  I recently met a group of four who went on board with drinks in their hands.  I do not know if they got more drink on board but they were certainly boisterous.  They upset everybody else in the carriage but there was no train host to deal with them.  I took this up with Joe, my own train host, on an early train this morning and he told me the story of a customer who used the intercom to communicate with the driver and got him to deal with it at the next station.  There was an altercation, the driver suffered an injury and the train was held up for two hours while they waited for a substitute driver.  CI&Eacute; does a good job but the company has to be very careful about staffing levels at certain stations.  A train host on every service is essential.</p> <p>I support Senator &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh in his request for a debate on the worthwhile report in which he has been very much involved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.183" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#W00400"><p>I second Senator Norris's proposal to amend the Order of Business.  I do not intend going into any great detail on Shane O'Farrell because I hope we will have the support of the House to make that amendment.  Investigations are needed into his untimely death.  I support the family's request for a commission of investigation into his death to be carried out.  I acknowledge the enormous work that Fianna F&aacute;il's Deputy Jim O'Callaghan has done on this.  He spoke in the D&aacute;il in great detail on 12 March 2018 and has, along with Senator Norris and others, championed the case.  I ask Members to reference his words if we have this debate.  His contribution in the D&aacute;il was succinct and clearly set out a compelling case for the Government to act.  I am happy to second the amendment and I hope that colleagues support this move.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.184" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#W00500"><p>I saw quite a number of photographs of Fianna F&aacute;il local authority members at the rally online.  I was not tracking everybody's Twitter account but I saw the Dublin Central candidate, Ms Mary Fitzpatrick, Councillor Paul McAuliffe from Dublin North West, and Councillor Frank O'Flynn from Cork.  We do not necessarily assemble in a militaristic fashion-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.185" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#W00750"><p>They must be plumpers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.186" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#W00775"><p>-----like some other parties do.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.187" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#W00800"><p>Who would that be?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#W00900"><p>Enough said.  Senator Richmond mentioned passports, which I was going to raise myself.  Last Wednesday, I helped somebody apply online for a passport renewal.  The office was reluctant to accept the photograph but we managed to produce one of sufficient quality.  They said it would take ten working days, which would mean Wednesday of next week, but it arrived in the post this morning, after less than four working days.  I commend the Minister, the Department and the staff who work in the production facility in Balbriggan.  I urge anybody who is remotely able to use technology to use this service.  I urge those who are not able to use it to ask somebody to help them.  The process is incredibly simple and it is cheaper at &euro;75 instead of &euro;89.50 through Passport Express.  It is much faster and it saves a lot of work.</p> <p>I ask the Leader for a debate on the immediate skills shortage in secondary schools.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Gerry Horkan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2476"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2476&amp;amp;pid=GerryHorkan&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Many school principals, particularly in Dublin, and across the country are finding it difficult to recruit teachers of many subjects, including physics, chemistry, home economics, languages, especially Spanish, French, German and Irish in particular.  I ask the Leader to arrange for the Minister for Education and Skills, who is fairly new to his brief, to come into the House to discuss this matter.  Senator Norris might not want to interrupt the Leader when I am trying to talk to him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.190" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#X00200"><p>I called him, to be fair.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.191" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#X00300"><p>I would like the Leader to schedule a debate regarding what the Minister for Education and Skills and his Department plan to do to relieve this situation.  It is becoming incredibly difficult to find teachers to fill vacant posts when they arise.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.192" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#X00400"><p>Last week in this Chamber I was critical of the Minister for Justice and Equality in terms of the inability of Senators to get an adequate debate on Garda resources and the responsibility of the Minister for Justice and Equality over An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na as a result of a number of incidents that happened on the north side of Dublin.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.193" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.194" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#X00600"><p>I cited the issue of a pipe bomb in Edenmore and the upsurge in anti-social behaviour.  Since I made that contribution last week, we have had a fatal shooting in Darndale.  In his response to my request for a debate with the Minister for Justice and Equality, I appreciate the Leader was minded to do that.  I want to get an assurance from him that he will see to that request.</p> <p>I have expressed my frustration at an inability to get further than the suggestion that the Minister has no responsibility for operational matters in An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  I encourage the Leader to arrange such a debate in the House and to see how we can work together to ensure that people in communities across the city, northside, southside, outside Dublin and across the country, can feel safe and secure.  It is not normal for somebody to be shot dead at 6.30 a.m. and then for children in that community to go to school as if it is something perfectly normal and for it not to feature that heavily in the news cycle of that day.  When an incident occurs where somebody gets shot dead at 6.30 a.m. and it does not rock the foundations of these Houses, then something has gone very badly wrong.  I suggest, respectfully, and perhaps I was not respectful last week-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.195" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#X00700"><p>That is for the sure.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.196" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#X00800"><p>-----that we would have a debate in this House with the Minister for Justice and Equality on the issue of crime, criminality, anti-social behaviour and fatal shootings.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1380" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#X00900"><p>I support Senator Coghlan on the issue he raised regarding services on trains and at various stations throughout the country.  My station in Castlebar is no better.  We have a station master, Mr. Noel Hogan, who is very approachable and does a great job but when he is off at various times during the week or at the weekend there is no cover for him.</p> <p>As Senator Coghlan pointed out, if people board the train carrying booze and there is no train host onboard anything can happen.  He outlined an incident where a train driver was injured and the train was held up for two hours.  I support Senator Coghlan's call for the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport to come to the House to address the services provided at train stations and by train hosts.  Such abuse in this respect brings the issue of ensuring passenger safety into disrepute.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.198" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#X01000"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.199" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1380" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#X01100"><p>We need the Minister to come to the House to discuss this matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.200" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#X01200"><p>I wish to speak in support Senator Norris seeking a debate on the death of Shane O'Farrell.  We debated this issue on 14 June 2018 on the same day that the D&aacute;il voted by a clear majority on the basis that the matter did warrant a public inquiry.  I and others have been in correspondence with the Minister, Deputy Flanagan, since then.  He said in the Seanad on 14 June last year that he would reflect on the comments of Senators, that he would reflect on the D&aacute;il vote and that he would repeat a commitment given to Lucia O'Farrell, Shane O'Farrell's mother, and the O'Farrell family regarding the question of a further investigation.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Ivana Bacik:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2248"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2248&amp;amp;pid=IvanaBacik&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I know that Senator Norris has been proactive on the matter, as have others.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.202" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Y00200"><p>Senator Norris is like a hen with an egg today.  He has been very restless.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.203" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Y00300"><p>I am looking after my colleagues' eggs.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.204" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Y00400"><p>Senator Bacik to continue, without interruption, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.205" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Y00500"><p>I am sure Senator Norris was being as proactive as usual on the issue.  Nearly one year after the vote, we still have not received a response, or at least I have not.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.206" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Y00600"><p>There has been a response.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.207" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Y00700"><p>I have not received a response to my correspondence with the Minister, in which I asked him what he would do about the motion and so on.  Will the Leader accede to Senator Norris's request for a debate on the issue in order that matters can be progressed?  It is important for the family and to ensure public confidence in the policing system, particularly in dealing with road accidents.  I ask the Leader to look favourably on Senator Norris's request.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.208" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Y00800"><p>I thank the 20 Senators who spoke for their contributions on the Order of Business.</p> <p>Senators Craughwell, Conway-Walsh and Devine raised the issue of the national children's hospital.  The Minister for Health has appeared before the D&aacute;il and apologised.  For some, it is now a question of who said what and who knew what when, rather than whether the hospital will be built, whether it will be the best hospital in the world and whether a political head on a plate will be demanded.  The Sinn F&eacute;in Party has reverted to its usual playbook in seeking a resignation or dismissal, but that will not help to build the hospital.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.209" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Y00900"><p>It is called accountability.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.210" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Y01000"><p>I will respond to the Senator's comment.  I reiterate that all Senators are disappointed, frustrated and annoyed at the cost overrun.  It should not have happened, but it did.  We must now ensure there will be value for money in building the hospital which will be the best children's hospital in the world, although it will not be the most expensive.  We need to maintain a sense of perspective, rather than hysteria, in our debate.  We are reprofiling a figure of &euro;100 million out of a capital budget of &euro;7 billion.  Having regard to the cancellation of &euro;27 million in funding for the A5 to Derry road project, I ask the Sinn F&eacute;in Senators to reflect on their lack of involvement and engagement at Stormont.  On the question of accountability and apologies, we know well that Sinn F&eacute;in's approach to them is non-existent, unless its members are dragged in and forced to apologise.  We know well how they behave.</p> <p>In response to Senators Conway-Walsh and Devine on the nurses issue, I welcome the intervention of the Labour Court and its recommendation.  I acknowledge that Senator Devine is trying to play to her gallery and constituency, but I am sure she knows that the Government has no part to play in the INMO process and its executive council which will now begin to ballot its members.  It is independent of the Government-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.211" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Y01100"><p>On a point of order, I did not say that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.212" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Y01200"><p>The Senator did.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.213" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Y01300"><p>I know more about the issue than the Leader is suggesting.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.214" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Y01400"><p>It was not a point of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.215" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Y01500"><p>In any case, the Leader was wrong.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.216" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Y01600"><p>The Leader to continue, without interruption, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.217" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Y01700"><p>The Government believes the agreement reflects three principles, namely, that it is fair to taxpayers, public servants and nurses.  I hope nurses will accept the recommendation of the Labour Court.  We all recognise their value, centrality and importance in the health system.</p> <p>To respond to Senator Higgins's question, I will be happy for the Minister for Communications, Climate Action and Environment to come to the House to discuss the ecological matters she raised.  The new EU-Singapore trade deal will lead to the creation of hundreds of jobs in this country.  The House voted on a non-binding motion dealing with the CETA which was not necessarily related to concerns about investor quotas.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.218" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Y01800"><p>It certainly was.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.219" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Y01900"><p>Those on the Fianna F&aacute;il benches still do not know on what they abstained or what they stand for, but, in fairness, we had a good debate in the House.  The CETA is already a success, despite the misplaced concerns of others who should perhaps know better.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Senators Clifford-Lee, Humphreys, Reilly, Coghlan and Paddy Burke all referred to the issue of transport.  I would be happy to have the Minister come to the House to discuss the issue and will come back to the issues that individuals have raised.<br/><br/>Senator Humphreys should recognise that under regulation 12 of the Social Housing Allocation Regulations 2011, a household that refuses two reasonable offers of tenancy in any 12 month period other than an offer in the choice-based letting procedure will not receive any further offers from any housing authority for a period of one year from the second refusal.  That is already <i>in situ</i>.  We need to get some perspective on the issue of housing.  People refuse housing for a variety of issues.  Some are serial refusers.  Others have particular reasons and we accept that, but we must try to get a balance.<br/><br/>Senator Gallagher raised the issue of food supplements.  It is an interpretation of the tax code by Revenue which is independent of Government.  The Minister, Deputy Donohoe, has a tax advisory group.  As I said in the House last week, some people are peddling a specific line but should also recognise that certain medicines, folic acids, vitamins and mineral products, as licensed by the Health Products Regulatory Authority, are still zero and will remain at that.  We should have balance in what we say about the matter here.  I hope that we can have common sense with regard to some of the issues addressed by Senator Gallagher.<br/><br/>Senator &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh will be the author of a very fine report regarding small and medium enterprises.  The Minister, Deputy Humphreys, coming from the Border, is well aware of the complexities and importance of small and medium enterprises.  I would be happy to have her to come to the House to address the matter.<br/><br/>Senators Richmond and Horkan raised the issue of passports and the need for debate on the passport system, which I would be happy to have.<br/><br/>Senator Grace O'Sullivan raised the issue of the F&oacute;rsa campaign to support school secretaries.  It is an important issue which requires clarity and parity.  We would all support it.<br/><br/>Senator McFadden raised the ONE campaign.  To be fair to the Senator, she has raised the matter on many occasions, both in and outside this House.  There is an issue relating to bed nights.  We need to compliment ONE which has provided 44 bed nights, which I think the Senator said has covered 900 veterans and includes approximately 16,000 bed nights per annum.  It is important that we support it and that we work to ensure that visibility and recognition is given to our veterans.  To be fair to the Senator, she has raised this in the past.<br/><br/>Senator Norris raised the issue of the inquiry into Shane O'Farrell's death.  We want the O'Farrell family to have full information, there has to be due process, and there has to be full accountability for those involved.  On completion of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na Ombudsman Commission inquiry, the Minister appointed Mr. Justice Haughton to carry out a scoping exercise.  From any point of view, that should be able to continue and to carry out its work rather than having a debate on that.  I am cognisant of the involvement of Senator Norris and do not want to be seen as offensive or unhelpful to the O'Farrell family and the need for full action.  I know the Minister is not available today and he is certainly not available tomorrow, because if he was, he would be having more debate on the very important Judicial Appointments Commission Bill, about which I will speak to Senator Craughwell.  I am prepared to offer Senator Norris a debate on the matter tomorrow afternoon without the Minister being present, if the Senator is amenable to that.  I do not want to be unhelpful and do not want to be seen to be obstructionist.  That is not my style.  A scoping inquiry has been put in place.  A process has been established.  I do not think that we should have debates in the House in parallel with that.  If Senator Norris is amenable to having a debate for an hour tomorrow without the Minister, I would be happy to do that, but otherwise I do not think that I can ask the Minister to come to the House at such short notice, knowing that he is not available today or tomorrow.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.221" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Z00200"><p>Will the Government oppose the motion?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.222" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#Z00300"><p>On the basis of Senator Norris wanting the Minister to be here today, I will oppose it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.223" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA00100"><p>The Government will oppose it tomorrow.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.224" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA00200"><p>No.  I am offering Senator Norris an hour's debate tomorrow, without the Minister's presence, to allow the Senator the opportunity in the Seanad to have-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.225" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA00300"><p>I am asking the Leader whether the Government will oppose the motion tomorrow.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.226" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA00400"><p>I am making an offer to the Senator of an hour's debate tomorrow on the Senator's motion without the Minister's presence.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.227" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA00500"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.228" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA00600"><p>I cannot answer the Senator's question right now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.229" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA00700"><p>The Leader does not know whether the Government will oppose the motion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.230" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA00800"><p>As of right now, I do not, but I will make-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.231" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA00900"><p>I see.  I thank the Leader.  That is helpful.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.232" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA01000"><p>I am trying to be helpful to the Senator in terms of having-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.233" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA01100"><p>I know.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.234" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA01200"><p>Perhaps if the Leader could clarify his position on tomorrow morning's Order of Business, the Senators could decide-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.235" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA01300"><p>The motion, as far as I understand, is just to have a debate on the Shane O'Farrell case.  Is that correct?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.236" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA01400"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.237" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA01500"><p>The motion, as worded, is to have the debate today, so it is a matter for Senator Norris-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.238" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA01600"><p>I would be happy to have the debate tomorrow without the Minister's presence.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.239" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA01700"><p>I understand that, but what concerns me is whether the Government will vote against the motion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.240" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA01800"><p>I cannot answer the Senator right now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.241" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA01900"><p>That is fine.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.242" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA02000"><p>The Senator has the option to press the amendment or not.  I do not think the Leader can say any more about it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.243" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA02100"><p>I would be happy to have the Minister come before the House to discuss the issues Senator Davitt raised about newspapers.  His colleague, Senator Leyden, last week very eloquently and very colourfully debated the matter of local radio stations.</p> <p>Senator Coghlan raised the very important issue of our small stations.  I almost closed my eyes as Senator Coghlan was speaking about Banteer, Millstreet, Rathmore, Mallow and parts of Kerry.  It was like going to the Munster football final long ago, when we were young.  Senator Paddy Burke raised the issue as well.  I am not sure we will be travelling to Killarney much with the Cork footballers at present, but we live in hope.  Senator Coghlan might be best advised to table a Commencement matter on the issue, but in essence I would be happy to have the Minister come to the House to discuss the matter.</p> <p>Senator Horkan raised the skills shortage in education.  We had a debate on education recently but we will have one again soon.  I would be happy to discuss that element with the Senator in the House.</p> <p>Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in respectfully asked that the Minister for Justice and Equality come before the House.  We have put the request in.  It is important to recognise that the Minister has been in the House dealing with the Judicial Appointments Commission Bill.  Contrary to what Senator Craughwell believes, it is very important legislation which is a central part of the programme for Government.  It is the obfuscation and filibustering of some of the members of the Senator's group that is causing the Minister to be here inordinately to discuss the Bill rather than having it passed-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.244" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA02200"><p>I am the one who is filibustering.  I am not part of Senator Craughwell's group.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.245" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA02300"><p>-----which then precludes the Minister from being able to come back in to discuss other justice issues.  Senator Craughwell might talk to his own group about allowing the Bill to be fast-tracked.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.246" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA02400"><p>It is doomed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.247" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA02500"><p>I ask Senator Norris to accept my olive branch to him.  If not, I will have to oppose today's Order of Business on that basis.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.248" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA02600"><p>I will put the matter to Senator Norris.  He has proposed an amendment to the Order of Business, that No. 83, motion 11, be taken for one hour on the conclusion of No. 2.  In view of what the Leader has said, is the Senator pressing the amendment?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.249" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA02700"><p>The Leader is very amenable but he cannot tell me whether he will vote against the motion.  He obviously will vote against it.  I have the numbers today.  I am not sure I will have them tomorrow.  I must therefore press the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.250" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA02800"><p>On a point of information, I have offered Senator Norris a debate tomorrow.  Whether the motion is put tomorrow is immaterial.  We can oppose it tomorrow or oppose it today.  It does not matter.  The point is that he wants a debate on the issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.251" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA02900"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.252" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA03000"><p>To be fair to the Senator, I do not want to put him in a position but-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.253" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA03100"><p>I think there is an impasse here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.254" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA03200"><p>The impasse is solvable, though, because the Senator is getting what he wants tomorrow.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.255" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA03300"><p>Yes, but Senator Norris is in pole position because he has proposed an amendment-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.256" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA03400"><p>Today he is not in pole position at all.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.257" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA03500"><p>That is true.  I am prepared to take the chance.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.258" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA03600"><p>The Senator is pressing the amendment then.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.259" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA03700"><p>I am.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.260" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA03800"><p>The question is that the amendment be made-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.261" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA03900"><p>Senator Horkan wants to speak.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.262" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA04000"><p>I think this is genuinely a point of order because we are discussing the Order of Business.  Senator Norris seems to be concerned that tomorrow he will not get an opportunity to debate the motion because it will be shot down.  However, my understanding from what the Leader has said - he might clarify - is that he is offering, without any vote-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.263" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA04100"><p>Correct.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.264" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA04200"><p>-----to put on the schedule tomorrow an hour's debate, without the Minister, on the matter, and tomorrow morning he will read out the Order of Business, including an hour of debate on the case of Shane O'Farrell-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.265" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA04300"><p>Correct.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.266" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA04400"><p>-----and he will not try to avoid doing that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.267" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA04500"><p>That is what I said.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.268" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA04600"><p>But he will oppose it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.269" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA04700"><p>He will not - not tomorrow.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.270" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA04800"><p>I did not say I would oppose it.  To help Senator Norris, I have offered him an hour's debate tomorrow-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.271" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA04900"><p>And the Leader will not oppose it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.272" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#AA05000"><p>-----on the issue he proposed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.273" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#BB00100"><p>The Leader will not say that he will not oppose it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.274" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#BB00200"><p>On a point of order the Senators are at cross purposes.  Senator Norris is concerned that the Leader may oppose the motion to be debated tomorrow.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.275" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#BB00300"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.276" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#BB00400"><p>I am offering Senator Norris the motion tomorrow, without the Minister, for an hour.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.277" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#BB00500"><p>I think the nub of the issue-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.278" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#BB00600"><p>But the Leader will not say whether he will vote against it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.279" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#BB00700"><p>I am offering-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.280" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#BB00800"><p>It is a motion on the Order Paper that Senator Norris wants to debate.  It is not just statements.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.281" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#BB00900"><p>The nub of the issue is that Senator Norris wants an answer, which the Leader may not be able to give, on whether, if the motion is debated tomorrow, he will oppose or accept it.  Senator Norris is still in pole position.  Does he want to move the motion?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.282" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#BB01000"><p>I do.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.283" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#BB01100"><p>That is very clear.  The Senator may be wrong or otherwise.  The question is that the amendment be made-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.284" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#BB01200"><p>Can I ask a question before it goes to a vote?  When does Senator Norris propose to have the motion put tonight?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.285" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#BB01300"><p>Immediately after the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.286" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#BB01400"><p>The proposal is that it be taken after No. 2.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.287" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#BB01500"><p>The Minister, Deputy Flanagan, is around anyway.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.288" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#BB01600"><p>We are going around in circles.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.289" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#BB01700"><p>On a point of order, if the Leader really wanted to be helpful to Senator Norris he would suspend the Judicial Appointments Commission Bill this evening and take Senator Norris's motion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.290" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#BB01800"><p>That is another option.  I will put the question.  Senator Norris, is the amendment being pressed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.291" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#BB01900"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.292/1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#BB02000"><p>Amendment put:</p><p>The Seanad divided: Tá, 25; Níl, 19.</p><br/><br/><p>Tellers: Tá, Senators David Norris and Diarmuid Wilson; Níl, Senators Gabrielle McFadden and John O'Mahony.</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.292/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2019-02-12" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#BB02000">
            <divisioncount ayes="25" noes="19" abstain="0" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" vote="aye">Ivana Bacik</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1408" vote="aye">Frances Black</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" vote="aye">Victor Boyhan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" vote="aye">Lorraine Clifford Lee</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" vote="aye">Rose Conway Walsh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" vote="aye">Gerard Craughwell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1383" vote="aye">Paul Daly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" vote="aye">Aidan Davitt</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" vote="aye">Maire Devine</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" vote="aye">Robbie Gallagher</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" vote="aye">Paul Gavan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" vote="aye">Alice Mary Higgins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" vote="aye">Gerry Horkan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" vote="aye">Kevin Humphreys</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1430" vote="aye">Colette Kelleher</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" vote="aye">Terry Leyden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1439" vote="aye">Ian Marshall</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" vote="aye">Gerald Nash</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" vote="aye">David Norris</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" vote="aye">Marie Louise O'Donnell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1385" vote="aye">Grace O'Sullivan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" vote="aye">Ned O'Sullivan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1431" vote="aye">P&aacute;draig &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" vote="aye">Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" vote="aye">Diarmuid Wilson</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" vote="no">Colm Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1380" vote="no">Paddy Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1423" vote="no">Ray Butler</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" vote="no">Jerry Buttimer</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" vote="no">Maria Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1422" vote="no">Paudie Coffey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" vote="no">Paul Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" vote="no">Martin Conway</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1415" vote="no">Maura Hopkins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1429" vote="no">Billy Lawless</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1438" vote="no">Anthony Lawlor</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" vote="no">Gabrielle McFadden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" vote="no">Michelle Mulherin</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" vote="no">Catherine Noone</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1374" vote="no">Kieran O'Donnell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" vote="no">John O'Mahony</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" vote="no">Joe O'Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" vote="no">James Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1399" vote="no">Neale Richmond</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="abstain">
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.292/3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#BB02000"><p>Amendment declared carried.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.293" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#EE00100"><p>Is the Order of Business, as amended, agreed to?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.294" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#EE00200"><p>No.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.295" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#EE00300"><p>It is most unusual, in a vote like this, to defer an item to a later time in the evening.  I have never known it done.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.296" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#EE00400"><p>Well-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.297" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#EE00500"><p>I am sorry, I just want to finish this.  When this proposal came from the bench, I remember wondering why the debate was to be after No. 2.  I thought it must have been because something was going through without a vote.  I am going to check the record to see what happened here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.298" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#EE00600"><p>On a point of order-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.299" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#EE00700"><p>Hold on a second.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.300" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#EE00800"><p>The Order of Business-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.301" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#EE00900"><p>Please-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.302" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#EE01000"><p>Can we just clarify-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.303" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#EE01100"><p>It is a matter for me to clarify.  Senator Norris has posed a question.  My understanding is clearly that our very esteemed and learned Clerk believes that what was put is exactly what the Senator proposed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.304" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#EE01200"><p>Well, it is not.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.305" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#EE01300"><p>It may not have been what the Senator intended, but the Clerk is quite clear on it.  We cannot undo what is done.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.306" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#EE01400"><p>I know.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.307" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#EE01500"><p>Is the Order of Business, as amended, agreed to?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.308" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#EE01600"><p>No.  To be helpful, and to be fair to Senator Norris, while I do not want to aggravate the situation, it is still the case that the Minister is not available.  What Senator Norris proposed was to be after No. 2.  I am prepared to have the debate without the Minister tomorrow.  I am also prepared to allow for debate on the motion subject to the availability of a Minister, if the House will agree to that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.309" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#EE01700"><p>Can we agree the Order of Business now?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.310" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#EE01800"><p>I am quite prepared to be moderate on this issue.  Will the Leader give me an undertaking that he will at least attempt to find a Minister for tomorrow?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.311" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#EE01900"><p>I will talk to the Members and to Senator Norris and I will do my best, but I cannot give a guarantee now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.312" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#EE02000"><p>I understand that.  In that case, I will accept the Leader's proposal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.313" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#EE02100"><p>I will do my best but I cannot guarantee anything.  I have offered the Senator the option of having the debate without a Minister tomorrow.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.314" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#EE02200"><p>The amendment has been passed.  The Leader can consider it but if, as he has suggested, he opposes the Order of Business, the whole Order of Business for today will collapse.  He should think clearly.  I asked whether the Order of Business, as amended, was agreed to and the Leader opposed it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.315" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#EE02300"><p>On a point of order, is it possible for me to accept the Leader's offer at this stage?  We can then pass a revised Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.316" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#EE02400"><p>I suggest that we agree the Order of Business, as amended.  The Leader can then come back in an hour and tell the House that he has agreed with Senator Norris to do X or Y.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.317" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#EE02500"><p>It should only take five minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.318" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#EE02600"><p>All right.  He can come back in five minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.319" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#EE02700"><p>Is the Order of Business, as amended, agreed to?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.320" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019021200002#EE02800"><p>The Leader will come back inside five minutes with his suggestions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.321" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Order of Business, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-02-12a.322" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 5 p.m. and resumed at 5.15 p.m.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>