<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.4" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#A00200"><p>I have notice from Senator Paschal Mooney that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Social Protection to outline why her Department is refusing to provide the necessary funding under the community services programme to provide for the imminent increase in the national minimum wage and to consider the serious impact on the voluntary sector unless she reverses her decision.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh of the following matter:</p><blockquote>Go dtabharfaidh an tAire Coimirce S&oacute;isiala&iacute; soil&eacute;iri&uacute; maidir lena bhfuil beartaithe &oacute; thaobh cothrom na f&eacute;inne a thabhairt do saoist&iacute; ar an sc&eacute;im s&oacute;isialta tuaithe i gcom&oacute;rtas le saoist&iacute; na sc&eacute;imeanna fosta&iacute;ochta eile a thagann faoina c&uacute;ram &oacute; thaobh socraithe fosta&iacute;ochta de.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Mary Moran of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Education and Skills to clarify the position on teaching practice hours for teachers who are pursuing the masters degree in education and already have contract hours in a school.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Lorraine Higgins of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation to introduce a salary scale for workers in the child care sector to ensure that, in the interests of quality, qualifications are reflected in salary achieved for workers.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Colm Burke of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to clarify why Xolair, an approved treatment for severe allergic asthma, has not yet been introduced under the HSE drug payment scheme or reimbursement scheme for persons who are asthmatic.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Catherine Noone of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Justice and Equality to outline, in view of the perception of an increased threat to Ireland from within the Middle East, what security arrangements have been made in Ireland.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Averil Power of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs to state when he will publish the adoption (information and tracing) Bill, if it will include the recommendations of the Oireachtas Committee on Health and Children which called for changes to the draft scheme of the Bill, and if it is expected to be passed into law before the general election.</blockquote> <p>I regard the matters raised as suitable for discussion.  I have selected the matters raised by Senators Mooney, &Oacute; Clochartaigh, Moran and Higgins and they will be taken now.  Senators Burke, Noone and Power may give notice on another day of the matters they wish to raise.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.7" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#A00300">Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.8" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#A00400"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Deenihan, to the House.  The first motion is Senator Mooney's.  As Senator Mooney is not present, is the Minister of State taking any other Commencement matter?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1046" speakername="Jimmy Deenihan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#A00500"><p>Yes, the second Commencement matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#A00600"><p>I call Senator &Oacute; Clochartaigh.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.11" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#A00650">Rural Social Scheme Administration</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#A00700"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it.  T&aacute; na saoist&iacute; ar na sc&eacute;imeanna s&oacute;isialta tuaithe ag obair an-mhaith ar fud na t&iacute;re.  Dar leo, t&aacute; easpa cothroma&iacute;ochta idir na coinn&iacute;ollacha oibre ata acu f&eacute;in agus na coinn&iacute;ollacha at&aacute; ag saoist&iacute; ar na sc&eacute;imeanna eile.</p> <p>I am sure the Minister of State will be well aware of the considerable work that is done on the rural social schemes throughout the country.  It is a very important scheme that has provided significant supports in local rural communities for those on meagre enough incomes and subsistence to try to keep people in their communities.  There have been a lot of questions in the past year or so on the pay and conditions of the supervisors on these schemes that fall within the remit of the Department of Social Protection.  Senator Higgins organised a good presentation from the supervisors of the rural social schemes where they highlighted quite a number of these issues.</p> <p>Much of the work done on roads, piers, graveyards, community halls and across the community is done in conjunction with some of the other schemes, such as T&uacute;s and the community employment schemes, particularly in recent times when there was bad weather.  It is felt that a lot of the work being done is on a par with the work being done under those other schemes but that the working conditions of the supervisors are not comparable.  This has been subject to an application to the Workplace Relations Commission to try to have these issues resolved.  What dumbfounds me is how the Department of Social Protection, with two Labour Party Ministers, has not even engaged with the Workplace Relations Commission to try to resolve these issues.  That is unacceptable.</p> <p>I asked a number of months ago and the Minister of State at the Department of Social Protection, Deputy Kevin Humphreys, came to the House to address this issue.  I do not see that there has been any real progress made on it.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2363"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2363&amp;amp;pid=TrevorOClochartaigh&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is important that we try to resolve this issue before year's end, if possible.  The schemes' supervisors deserve parity of esteem with other supervisors doing similar work.  It is incumbent on the Department of Social Protection to treat them fairly.  They do not feel as if they are being treated.  The Labour Minister and Minister of State in the Department should uphold workers' rights, respect the wishes of the unions that are involved, treat this as a matter of urgency and try to resolve it before the Christmas break.  It has gone on for too long.  I hope that the Minister of State will, on behalf of his ministerial colleagues in the Department, have some light at the end of the tunnel for us.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1046" speakername="Jimmy Deenihan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#B00200"><p>I am taking this Commencement Matter on behalf of my colleague, the Minister of State, Deputy Kevin Humphreys.</p> <p>Senators will be aware of the many communities in rural areas that benefit from the services supported by the rural social scheme, RSS, and the positive impact that the scheme has had on the livelihoods of farming families and the social fabric of communities along the western seaboard.</p> <p>The Department of Social Protection operates a number of programmes and initiatives in support of jobseekers and those in receipt of long-term social protection payments.  Senators will be familiar with initiatives such as T&uacute;s, the community work placement initiative, RSS, Gateway and the community employment programme.  These are funded by the Department and delivered and administered at community level by local development companies, &Uacute;dar&aacute;s na Gaeltachta, county and city councils and local not-for-profit sponsor groups.</p> <p>The primary objective of these interventions is to offer those in receipt of social protection payments the opportunity to engage in work-related training, work experience and-or income support.  The rural social scheme, to which the Senator referred, provides income support to those involved in the farming and fishery sectors where the level of income from their primary economic activities is insufficient to provide an adequate income.  The scheme is delivered by 35 local development companies and &Uacute;dar&aacute;s na Gaeltachta.  These companies are funded to employ 130 supervisor staff in full-time positions to support the delivery of the scheme.  Each company is individually responsible for setting the terms and conditions of employment.  The Department of Social Protection has no role in such matters, but requires that each company meet at least the minimum requirements of employment contracts set out by the various employment statutes.  The Department also meets the cost of employment and related operational costs for these supervisors through the provision of funding and fees to the companies.</p> <p>The Senator referred to disparities in the terms of employment of supervisors on RSS and supervisors on similar job activation schemes that the Department funds.  The only scheme that could be considered comparable to RSS is T&uacute;s, the community work placement initiative.  T&uacute;s is delivered by the same local development companies and &Uacute;dar&aacute;s na Gaeltachta.  That initiative has many similarities to RSS in terms of the structure of delivery, funding and fees paid to the companies, placement of workers with community organisations and undertaking work in support of community initiatives.  I understand that, when considered broadly, the terms and conditions of employment are similar across both programmes within individual companies and the rate of payment on each is similar.</p> <p>The terms applying to other programmes such as community employment and Gateway differ significantly and reflect a number of other factors.  For instance, the Department of Social Protection provides funding to sponsor organisations under the community employment programme to support the management of each organisation's services and provide dedicated training and activation services to participants.  Managers of community employment sponsor organisations have responsibility relating to the management of the community employment payroll, training grant, associated service provision and the organisation itself.  Many of the elements of work outlined in respect of community employment do not arise in the case of RSS or T&uacute;s.  The Department does not fund the provision of supervision on Gateway, as that is a matter for each county and city council.</p> <p>I know at first hand the benefits that have been achieved for individuals and communities that have participated in these schemes or have had services supported.  I am also aware that the work of supervisors and participants is greatly valued.  Their work has played a critical role in the maintenance of services during the past few difficult years.  The House should note that, despite difficult funding conditions, the budget for RSS has been protected each year since 2011, with participant levels holding constant at 2,600 and full-time work being maintained for 130 supervisory staff.  This underlines the Government's commitment to the scheme and rural communities.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#B00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his response, but it was splitting hairs.  The communities on the ground do not see a major difference between the schemes.  The Department and various agencies do not see a difference when they ask people to work with the other organisations that have been mentioned.</p> <p>According to the Minister of State, he is "aware that the work of supervisors and participants is greatly valued".  If so, would he mind asking his relevant ministerial colleagues why they have not engaged with the Workplace Relations Commission, WRC, on the issues that have been raised by the supervisors?  One would assume that, if they were so valued, the Department would at least sit down at the WRC.  If everything in the Department's response is correct, surely the WRC would find in its favour and it should have no fear in that regard.  At least the supervisors would have closure on these issues.  Will the Minister of State convey to his colleagues that they should engage with the WRC as a matter of urgency to bring that closure?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1046" speakername="Jimmy Deenihan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#B00400"><p>I will do that for the Senator.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.17" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#B00500">Departmental Funding</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#B00600"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach for including this matter on the Commencement list and the Minister of State for taking this debate.  I was informed by the Department of Social Protection that neither the T&aacute;naiste nor the Minister of State, Deputy Kevin Humphreys, was available this morning, so I am particularly grateful that the Minister of State, Deputy Deenihan, is present instead.</p> <p>The matter is self-explanatory.  Community support groups are doing invaluable work, but a decision seemingly taken in recent weeks has been causing them some consternation.  I have been in contact with groups in my county of Leitrim.  I know of an example in County Mayo that my colleague, Deputy Calleary, mentioned in the Lower House, that being, Killala.  The Department's decision not to incorporate the increase in the minimum wage, which becomes effective on 1 January, in the annual allocations will have an adverse financial impact on community support groups, which struggle for money normally and rely to a large extent on fund-raising to pursue their valuable activities.</p> <p>Childhood Days is a special needs group in Drumshanbo.  It does extraordinarily good work with severely handicapped children.  It provides a wonderful service in our hometown and is open to everyone in the country and the wider catchment area.  Like other support groups, it raises funds and receives State allocations.  It was the first to raise the red flag with me regarding this issue.  When it attended a meeting in Mayo of similar support groups a few weeks ago, word came through from Pobal that the imminent increase in the minimum wage to &euro;9.15 would not be absorbed.</p> <p>I appreciate that a significant number of people employed in community support services are paid more than the minimum wage, but there are those who are not because of the nature of their work.  I was disappointed to learn through Deputy Calleary's raising of the issue in the Lower House that the Department's response was that this had never been the case.  I queried that with the support groups, which assured me that increases had been incorporated in their allocations since 2006.  Obviously, there is some distance between what the Department and the support groups are saying.  I hope that the Minister of State will clarify, as I have raised this issue with the Department in the past 24 hours.</p> <p>Overall, this is an opportunity to raise an important matter and express our solidarity with the support groups.  I hope that the Department will not leave them swinging in the wind and that, if the support groups find themselves in financial difficulty after the implementation of the increase, there will be a positive response from the Department, under whose aegis they fall.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1046" speakername="Jimmy Deenihan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#C00100"><p>I thank Senator Mooney for raising this matter.  I am taking this Commencement matter on behalf of my colleague, the Minister of State at the Department of Social Protection, Deputy Kevin Humphreys.</p> <p>Senators will be aware of the many community companies that provide services across the country.  The Department of Social Protection supports service provision through a number of programmes and schemes.  The community services programme, CSP, only supports community companies that operate on a community business or social enterprise model.  Companies supported by the CSP generate and use income from the services they provide to pay staff, meet overhead costs and to contribute to future development.  The CSP provides a contribution to the wage cost on the basis that the services are not fully self-financing or the cost of provision would be prohibitive on users.</p> <p>Today there are 398 active contracts in place with community companies, representing commitments from the Department of Social Protection of &euro;42 million per annum.  The programme directly supports 2,110 full-time positions.  Of these positions, a financial contribution of &euro;32,000 per annum is made to support the employment of managers - 312 at last count.  Funds are also provided as a contribution to employing people in some 1,800 full-time equivalent positions.  The Department estimates that some 2,800 people are employed across these companies with direct CSP support.  Another 1,100 people are employed in these companies without public funding support.  Additionally, the companies provide some 1,500 work placements under CE, the rural social scheme and T&uacute;s.  These companies are valuable to the social fabric of the country and provide very good quality services, particularly in poorer urban areas and rural villages where services are few and far between.</p> <p>In recent days, a number of service providers on contract to the community services programme raised queries about the value of grants in 2016.  Since the CSP became operational in 2006, it has helped companies to move from a situation where the minimum wage was paid to a position today where 60% of employees are paid above this level.  The Department of Social Protection is committed to working with the remaining companies to work towards paying a reasonable wage.  The resurgent economy will support this move.  A core requirement of the programme is that service providers generate non-public revenue from their operations by the sale of goods, charging fees for services delivered or fundraising.  Companies in contract with CSP must be a not-for-profit, social enterprise or community business in nature.  That does not mean that they should not aspire to make reasonable returns from their activities that allow for a good wage to be paid.  I recognise that this is a challenge, but there is a commitment to work towards achieving it.  CSP funding is expressed as a fixed annual contribution towards the costs of employing a specified number of full-time equivalent positions and, in the case of 312 contracts, a manager position.  The current value of contribution is &euro;19,033 per full-time equivalent and &euro;32,000 per management position annually.  The CSP operates very clearly on the basis that it provides "a contribution only&rdquo; to offset the wage costs of service provision.  It is entirely a matter for each service provider to set its own wage levels.</p> <p>An analysis of the June 2015 returns from the companies indicated that 45% of full-time equivalents were paid the minimum wage, contrary to the requirements of the programme to pay the local pay rate; 10% were paid above the proposed living wage of &euro;11.50 per hour; and the remaining 45% were paid between these ranges.  The development of the programme and the companies in recent years has ensured that the majority of companies do not continue to operate with a low-pay model.  I commend that commitment and achievement.  The Department of Social Protection is working with Pobal to put in place arrangements that will allow companies to apply in a structured manner to access short-term financial support if that is needed to deal with the issues identified in recent days.  Companies will be advised of the arrangements which are being prepared early in the new year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#C00200"><p>I am grateful to the Minister of State.  Like myself, he will be aware from his long experience that when it comes to Commencement motions, it is not so much about the devil being in the detail, but it is usually the last two paragraphs that give the real meat and drink of any of these replies.  I am particularly grateful that the Minister of State has addressed the core of the issue, in that the Department is now working with Pobal to put arrangements in place for anybody who needs financial support in the context of the increase in the minimum wage, which is to be welcomed.  I should have stated on the record that I unequivocally welcome the increase in the minimum wage and I am sure that, like myself, the Minister of State, Deputy Deenihan, would wish it were more and that it would come closer to the living wage of &euro;11.50.  Can I take it that in the context of the remarks contained in the last line of the second last paragraph, "short-term financial support if that is needed to deal with the issues identified in recent days" really means the issues we are talking about, that a concern has been expressed that they may not be able to meet their financial requirements?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1046" speakername="Jimmy Deenihan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#C00300"><p>I thank Senator Mooney for raising this matter.  A number of companies were in contact with me about it in recent days, so I am delighted to be here just to clarify that position.  That is my understanding of the response I have given here today to Senator Mooney's motion.  That is my interpretation, namely, that companies that have a need will be able to work with the Department in resolving issues if they have them.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.22" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#C00400">In-service Training</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" speakername="Mary Moran" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#C00500"><p>I presume the Minister of State is taking this motion on behalf of the Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy O'Sullivan.  I brought this Commencement matter to the House to ask the Minister to clarify the position regarding teaching practice hours for teachers who are pursuing a master's degree in education and who already have contract hours in school.  I have been contacted by several people who are in this predicament, who already have contract hours within a school and who are now required during the second year of the PME course to teach for a minimum of one and a half to two hours in an alternative school.  As it stands, the Teaching Council requires all PME students, regardless of their university, to undertake teaching practice in two school settings.  The alternative arrangement made for the students who are employed by a school one year before commencing the PME course allows for them to teach in a block of ten weeks for one and a half to two hours a week.</p> <p>I have been contacted by principals and school management who say this will cause serious problems for them in that these teachers who are already contracted, some of them for 15 to 17 hours, will have to move to a second school, while maintaining their place in the first school, to teach for one and a half to two hours per week for a ten-week block.  It also occurs during January and Easter, which is the time for every school when pre-examinations or mock examinations and oral examinations are going on.</p> <p>For example, if a teacher who is teaching Irish and is contracted for 15 hours in one school has to leave the school to go and teach in a second school for one and a half to two hours a week, principals have informed me that they are now going to have to get substitute cover to cover the teacher for the hours for which they have to move to a second school.  The whole thing is going to be very disruptive and unsettling for everybody involved: for the students who are pursuing the postgraduate degree in education; for the teaching staff; and especially for the pupils, some of whom might have these teachers for junior or leaving certificate Irish and who now find their teacher is going to be absent for a block of ten weeks to fulfil these criteria.</p> <p>Will the Minister go back and have a look at this?  There needs to be consultation between the Teaching Council and the Department again, to get something concrete, satisfactory and clear for the students who are pursuing this course.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Mary Moran:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2388"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2388&amp;amp;pid=MaryMoran&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Many students remain unclear, as do some of the universities, as to exactly where this is going.  They have ironed it out for students who have one school for one year, which is fine where they have gone in and had to do the minimum of four hours.  However, a huge problem is being opened up for people who have already been employed with contract hours and everybody involved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1046" speakername="Jimmy Deenihan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#D00200"><p>I thank Senator Mary Moran for raising the matter this morning.  I respond on behalf of the Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy Jan O'Sullivan.  I will first set out for the House the role of the Teaching Council in programmes of initial teacher education, or ITE.  The council has statutory responsibility for the review and accreditation of ITE programmes and all programmes that lead to registration must have professional accreditation from it.  Changes to initial teacher education were proposed in the National Strategy to Improve Literacy and Numeracy among Children and Young People 2011 to 2020 and the Teaching Council published criteria and guidelines for providers of ITE programmes in order to ensure that their programmes meet the council's accreditation requirements.  Improvements to ITE courses include the reconfiguration of their content and an increase in their duration.  Programmes now include substantial periods of school placement as central to student teacher development.  In this regard, the Teaching Council has determined that 25% of student time over the four years of undergraduate programmes and 40% of student time over the two years of postgraduate programmes should be allocated to school placement.</p> <p>The Teaching Council has prepared school placement guidelines in partnership with stakeholders.  The guidelines contain information on the duration, structure and timing of placements, the settings and activities which are appropriate and the roles of all the key stakeholders.  Specifically, the guidelines state that in accredited ITE programmes, there must be a school placement component, which must take place in at least two settings while the second half of the programme should include one block placement for a minimum of ten weeks.  In relation to the specific issue referred to by the Senator, the Teaching Council has advised that, earlier this year, one higher education institution with an accredited ITE programme proposed that an arrangement regarding school placement be made available to the small number of its students who were in employment as teachers.  The Minister is informed that the arrangement is consistent with the council's school placement guidelines.  The council has approved the proposal in respect of students from the 2014 and 2015 entry cohorts who meet the specified criteria.  The arrangement will be reviewed by the institution concerned and a report will be submitted to the council in line with normal arrangements.  The overall student placement arrangements are, of course, subject to the normal quality assurance procedures of the council.</p> <p>The Minister reminds the House that the Teaching Council is the statutory body responsible for the regulation of the teaching profession and the maintenance of standards in the profession.  As already stated, the council has statutory responsibility for the review and accreditation of ITE programmes and has published criteria and guidelines for providers in order to ensure that their programmes meet the council&rsquo;s accreditation requirements.  The Minister is satisfied that the arrangements agreed by the council in this case are in accordance with best practice, as set out in the school placement guidelines.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" speakername="Mary Moran" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#D00300"><p>As Senator Paschal Mooney said, one always gets the nub of the answer in the last paragraph of a reply.  I am very disappointed because the reply does not reflect the question I asked on what arrangements are in place and how they will deal with the fact that a teacher who is employed in a school for a certain number of hours will now have to have substitute teaching hours.  It is students who will lose out if a substitute teacher comes in to take the hours for somebody to allow them to move to another school for a minimum number of weeks.  Something could be done to address that.  While I appreciate and agree that it is the Teaching Council that needs to look at it, the Minister should be aware that there is a huge problem.  It is going to be a much bigger problem as this course unfolds and more and more people come on stream every year who have hours.  I will write to the Minister herself to take this up.  I would appreciate if the Minister of State, Deputy Deenihan, would also pass this on to her.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1046" speakername="Jimmy Deenihan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#D00400"><p>I will certainly convey the Senator's concerns about the matter to the Minister, whom I hope to meet later today.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.28" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#D00500">Early Childhood Care Education</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#D00600"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Gerald Nash, to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1173" speakername="Lorraine Higgins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#D00700"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the Chamber.  It is the first time I have had the opportunity to address my former director of elections in the Chamber.  How different things were this time last year.</p> <p>I ask the Minister of State if there have been any moves by his Department to introduce a salary scale for workers in the child care industry to ensure that their qualifications are reflected in their salaries in the interests of quality.  The Minister of State will be aware that staff in the child care sector work an average of 39 hours per week.  In return, they receive only two paid sick days per year and 20 days holidays.  I am aware of a case in my home county, Galway, where four staff with full degrees working in a community child care facility are earning between &euro;22,000 and &euro;25,000, at the maximum, per year while their manager earns just &euro;27,000.  In addition, there is no in-work pension entitlement accrued by these workers.  The resultant frustration from talking to these staff on their burn-out is only compounded by the fact that they are subject to regular HSE and Pobal inspections as well as having the responsibility of introducing a new curriculum to be overseen by Tusla.</p> <p>While it is only right that standards should be so high within the child care sector, when these pressures and expectations are not reflected in the wages paid to employees, it does a huge disservice to them.  One of the greatest issues facing the sector is retention of staff.  It has been brought up with me by a number of people working in the child care sector.  I worry that there will be a considerable drain of talent from the industry.  In fact, it is already happening as a result of the stressful working conditions and the low pay involved.  As a result, many child care workers are choosing instead to go into teaching as an alternative where they will have training times and will not have to comply with the expectation of weekend and long evening work.</p> <p>My worry really is that at a time of greater than ever need of child care places we are driving graduates out of the industry and making the discourse surrounding work in the child care sector a net negative.  A wage structure such as those in place for the construction and house hospitality sectors is needed.  I appreciate fully that the Minister of State cannot introduce wage structures in every industry, but it is very important in the child care sector in particular.  It would be a welcome move for the thousands who work in the sector and would advance the dignity at work agenda which has been at the heart of Government policy.  Will such a salary scale be considered by the Department in light of the qualifications achieved by workers and in recognition of the great service they provide in fostering the future of our nation?  I thank the Minister of State for attending and look forward to his response.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#D00800"><p>I thank Senator Higgins for putting down this matter for discussion and for her kind remarks at the outset.  I look forward very much to continuing to work with her next year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1173" speakername="Lorraine Higgins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#D00900"><p>And a wonderful director of elections he was.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#D01000"><p>I thank the Senator.  That is appreciated.  The amount of pay an employee receives is a matter for negotiation and agreement between the individual and the employer subject only to the provisions of the National Minimum Wage Act 2000.  There is nothing to prevent employees reaching individual or collective agreements with employers on higher rates based on qualifications or other agreed criteria.  As the Senator will be aware, I have created a legislative framework to allow that to happen.  The Low Pay Commission, which I established earlier this year, will, on an annual basis, examine and make recommendations to the Minister of the day on the national minimum wage with a view to ensuring that the national minimum wage, where adjusted, is adjusted incrementally having had regard to changes in earnings, productivity, overall competitiveness and the likely impact any adjustment would have on employment and unemployment levels.  The commission submitted its first report to me last July and recommended an increase of 50 cent per hour for an experienced adult worker.  I will introduce that positive change on 1 January 2016, which will benefit approximately 124,000 of the lowest paid workers in our society.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Gerald Nash:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=2281"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2281&amp;amp;pid=GeraldNash&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The Government has moved on a number of fronts to facilitate other forms of wage setting, in contrast with the view taken by other western European democracies in a post-recession scenario.  We have enhanced wage-setting mechanisms and our collective bargaining legislation to support low-paid workers.  The Industrial Relations (Amendment) Act 2012 provides a framework within which employers and employee representatives, through the joint labour committee, JLC, system, can come together voluntarily and negotiate terms and conditions of workers in their sector.  When it reaches agreement on terms and conditions, the JLC publishes details and invites submissions.  If, after consideration of any submissions received, the committee adopts the proposals, it will submit them to the Labour Court for consideration.  The Labour Court will then make a decision on the adoption of the proposals.  If the court decides they should be adopted, it will forward a copy of the proposals to the Minister.  If it is considered appropriate, an order giving effect to such proposals will be made by the Minister.  Such orders will be known as employment regulation orders.  I signed two such orders on 1 October last for the security and contract cleaning sectors.  These two orders will benefit, on a net basis, approximately 50,000 workers.  Pay rates negotiated in the JLC fora have tended to be above the national minimum wage.</p><p>The Industrial Relations (Amendment) Act 2015, which came into effect on 1 August, provides for a revised legislative framework to replace the registered employment agreement, REA, framework that was deemed invalid by the Supreme Court in 2013.  The legislation sets out a replacement framework for REAs in individual enterprises and a new mechanism whereby pay, pension and sick pay provisions in a particular sector can be established, agreed and enforced by order.</p><p>I have outlined the legislative frameworks available to various sectors across the economy in terms of wage-setting mechanisms.  There are opportunities for individual sectors to have their pay and terms and conditions examined in a structured way, for example, through the JLC system.  While they are voluntary systems, where a JLC system is active, the legislation insists that a trade union that is representative of workers in the sector be active on the JLC and that it include representative bodies that represent the employer bodies.  Thus the organisations can come forward and agree on improvements in the sector and the improvements can be approved by the Labour Court and, subsequently, adopted by the Minister of the day by way of employment regulation order.  There are opportunities available under legislation to every sector to engage wage-setting mechanisms to improve their pay and terms and conditions and the position of the industry in general.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.35" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 11.15 a.m. and resumed at 11.40 a.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.36" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#H00100">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#H00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na (Policing Authority and Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill 2015 - amendments from D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann, to be taken at 12.45 p.m. and to be brought to a conclusion not later than 1.45 p.m., if not previously concluded; No. 2, motion regarding the earlier signature of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na (Policing Authority and Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill 2015 to be taken on the conclusion of No. 1, without debate; No. 3, Prisons Bill 2015 - amendments from D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann, to be taken on the conclusion of No. 2 and to be brought to a conclusion not later than 2 p.m. by one question which shall be put from the Chair and which shall, in relation to amendments, include only those set down or accepted by the Government; No. 4, Finance (Tax Appeals) Bill 2015 &ndash; all Stages, to be taken at 2 p.m. and to be brought to a conclusion not later than 3.15 p.m. by one question which shall be put from the Chair and which shall, in relation to amendments, include only those set down or accepted by the Government, with the time allocated for Second Stage to group spokespersons not to exceed six minutes and to all other Senators not to exceed four minutes, with the Minister to be called on to reply for five minutes no later than 3.05 p.m.; No. 5, Houses of the Oireachtas Commission (Amendment) Bill 2015 &ndash; all Stages, to be taken at 3.15 p.m. and to be brought to a conclusion not later than 4.15 p.m. by one question which shall be put from the Chair and which shall, in relation to amendments, include only those set down or accepted by the Government, with the time allocated for Second Stage to group spokespersons not to exceed six minutes and to all other Senators not to exceed four minutes, with the Minister to be called on to reply for five minutes no later than 4.05 p.m.; No. 6, Criminal Justice (Burglary of Dwellings) Bill 2015 - Committee and Remaining Stages, to be taken at 4.15 p.m. and to be brought to a conclusion not later than 6 p.m. by one question which shall be put from the Chair and which shall, in relation to amendments, include only those set down or accepted by the Government; and No. 7, Harbours Bill 2015 &ndash; Committee Stage, to be taken on the conclusion of No. 6 and to conclude not later than 8 p.m., if not previously concluded.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#H00300"><p>I welcome to the Gallery Mary Leyden, wife of the good Senator Terry Leyden, her daughter, Councillor Orla Leyden, and her granddaughter Donata.  They are very welcome.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#H00400"><p>Her full name is Donata Maria.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#H00500"><p>I thank the Senator for the clarification.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#H00600"><p>I wish to raise a number of issues.  In recent days there has been a series of actions throughout the country which have compounded the difficulty caused by the Government and previous Governments in shutting down rural communities, in particular the closure of Garda stations.  In west County Sligo we had the closure of Easky Garda station some years back and despite officials from the OPW visiting the location with me and members of the community, who had a project for community use, the infrastructure was sold for a mere &euro;65,000 at auction on Monday.  This has been repeated throughout the country.  Another action is proposed in Keshcarrigan, County Leitrim.  The measly gain of &euro;65,000 on the part of the OPW is insignificant when we consider the loss in value in the uses it could have had for community initiatives.  It also wipes out the potential for these communities to have, at a future date, the return of community Garda stations when resources permit.  This is a retrograde step.  I again wrote to the Minister of State, Deputy Harris, on the issue this morning.  I beseech all members of Fine Gael and the Labour Party to put a stop to this because it is wrecking rural communities throughout the country.</p><p>We welcome the White Paper launched today by the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources, Deputy Alex White, on the future energy needs of the country and how we will provide them.  Not directly connected to energy, it provides the community in Ireland with the opportunity to state - in a final way - that this is a country which is not in favour of fracking and is not prepared to gamble our tourism and agriculture infrastructure, and our clean air and clean water for what still remains an unknown quantity in the context of its impact on communities.</p><p>The main issue I want to raise is the health budget, about we heard this morning.  Articles in <i>The Irish Times</i>underpin what we have been saying for many years, namely, that when the service plan for the HSE is published, it remains a bogus account of what lies ahead.  Still we see, and it surpasses even the terrible days of the former Minister, Deputy James Reilly, that the Minister for Health, Deputy Varadkar, has adopted a punditry and commentary role on health instead of realising he is captain of the ship and the one who is supposed to be driving the bus.  He spoke on &quot;Morning Ireland&quot; and used phrases like &quot;We projected this&quot; and &quot;We probably will not have enough money for that&quot;.  Next year, under the fiscal treaty rules, we will not be able to have a supplementary budget of &euro;605 million such as that which has been brought forward this year.  Next year we will have to make do without.  However, the budget for next year is only marginally above it.  When will we have somebody in charge of the Department of Health who will take responsibility for the general management of it, budget appropriately for what is needed by the health service in the year ahead and acknowledge the crisis we are experiencing?</p><p>With regard to one crisis in particular, we propose an amendment to the Order of Business to the effect that No. 15 be taken before No. 1 or at any stage today.  It relates to the cystic fibrosis, CF, drug Orkambi, which, as Members probably know, has had huge results in other countries, with up to a 40% reduction in hospital admissions for cystic fibrosis patients.  It is quite simply a wonder drug in terms of its effects and benefits.  It would help at least 60% of the patients in Ireland.  It is very effective for the most common CF gene alteration in Ireland, which is delta F508.  Mr. Tony O'Brien, the CEO of the Health Service Executive, stated there is not enough money in the purse to provide this drug to people, without even considering the benefits we would have in reducing the number of patients.  This is before the National Centre for Pharmacoeconomics has even negotiated on the provision of the drug.  I have been through this before, along with Senator Crown, in respect of access to cancer treatment.  He and I were rubbished for our efforts to try to change the focus to the benefits to the patient rather than the cost per life saved, which is very different from patient to patient.  We believe this is a retrograde step and we will put to a vote today that we take this motion and we will not agree to the Order of Business until it is taken because the cystic fibrosis patients of Ireland, their families and many people affected by this deserve better than somebody in the HSE in an ivory tower or a Minister simply saying we do not have the money to help.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#H00700"><p>I am sure the Leader will deal with the issue Senator MacSharry has raised regarding the health service.  However, I heard the same interview as the Senator and took a completely different impression from it.  In fact, it was gratifying to hear in particular about the fall in the number of people in need of medical cards because they have been able to return to work.  This was the most gratifying of all.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Aideen Hayden:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2384"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2384&amp;amp;pid=AideenHayden&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It enables us to invest more money in the other areas of the health system.  If I remember correctly what the Minister, Deputy Varadkar, said, the headline figures in almost every area are heading in the right direction.  However, I am sure the Leader will have more to say on that.</p><p>I welcome the announcement by the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government, Deputy Alan Kelly, that he will be allocating an additional &euro;8 million to local authorities to facilitate and support the meeting of the cost of the clean-up in communities in the aftermath of Storm Desmond.  I am sure we all agree this is good news.</p><p>The environment committee's report is expected to be published today.  It will cover, in particular, the issue of insurance that I raised yesterday in this House and the plight of people who find themselves unable to obtain insurance for properties that were previously flooded.  I was somewhat disappointed by comments attributed to the Taoiseach to the effect that he did not believe it would be in the interest of the State to step in with regard to insurance for people who have been flooded.  However, if we are to go by what is happening in a number of other European jurisdictions, we must realise there needs to be a backstop for people who find themselves in these circumstances.  We must not rely on private companies to provide appropriate insurance for people in these circumstances.</p><p>I welcome the announcement that the number of unfinished housing estates has dropped by 75%.  This is excellent news.  Along with the flooding issue, it gives rise to the need for a serious debate on planning.  The Minister, Deputy Alan Kelly, has announced that agreement was reached at Cabinet level on Tuesday on the publication of a major package of legislative and policy reforms to the planning system, including the publication of a planning and development Bill that will set up an independent office of the planning regulator.  That is most important and has been called for over a very long period by a number of organisations, not least the Irish Planning Institute.</p><p>I welcomed the statement by the Government that it aims to boost diversity in third level education.  It is particularly unfortunate that significant groups of people are still excluded from third level education in this country in spite of the fact that the participation levels in third level education have increased very significantly over the past decade.  However, as the report states, nearly all young people from Dublin 6 go to college but just 16% of people from Dublin 17 or Dublin 10 do so.  This is an outrageous statistic that needs to be addressed.  The lack of student accommodation is a very significant factor, particularly for people from rural areas, in gaining access to third level education.  I am sure the Leader, being from Waterford, is aware of this.</p><p>I do not know whether I have any time left but the Cathaoirleach was very generous to Senator Marc MacSharry.  On a lighter note, I welcome the commission of a commemorative stamp in honour of the Irish war poet Francis Ledwidge, who unfortunately, after having survived the battle of Gallipoli, died in Passchendaele during the First World War.  It is totally appropriate that there will be a commemorative stamp on the centenary of his death in 2017.  I welcome the fact that he has been put back on the leaving certificate syllabus.  He was on it in my day.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" speakername="Jillian van Turnhout" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#J00200"><p>I, too, welcome Senator Leyden's granddaughter, whom I know has had her interest in the work of the Seanad sparked recently.  However, I will let Senator Leyden elaborate on that.</p><p>I welcome the appointment of Professor Geoffrey Shannon to the District Court.  His contribution will be a tremendous addition to the work of that court, particularly in respect of family law.  He will be sorely missed as special rapporteur for child protection in his role as chairman of the Adoption Authority of Ireland.  He has given <i>pro bono</i>advice to countless NGOs across Ireland.  We will miss him greatly but he is joining the District Court at a critical time.  His appointment is an inspired choice, and I very much welcome it.</p><p>I noted the launch yesterday by the ISPCC of its special helpline for children who are homeless.  I congratulate the society on this but I am extremely saddened that it has to resort to this to ensure homeless children will be able to contact Santa Claus to ensure he will know where they are on Christmas Day.  We must all ask what more we can do when we see the increasing number of families, including children, who are finding themselves homeless because of any of the myriad reasons we have discussed here in the House.  I really hope we do not need the special helpline and that it will not be needed this time next year.</p><p>I congratulate the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources, Deputy Alex White, on the launch of his White Paper on a carbon-free Ireland.  I was at the launch, where I met a tremendous youth ambassador, Ms Aisling O'Boyle.  I encourage everybody to look at her speech.  If one needs a compelling reason to secure climate justice in Ireland, she will convince one.  I commend her on her speech at the launch this morning.  She certainly convinced me and re-engaged me on the need for us to do more.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#J00300"><p>I wish to ask the Leader about the Criminal Law (Sexual Offences) Bill.  We were left with a number of Committee Stage amendments pending and Report Stage is to come.  I do not see the legislation on the Order Paper for this week so I take it that the remaining Committee Stage amendments and Report Stage amendments will be taken in the new year, if at all.  I notice there is quite a lot of guillotining to occur today, which is regrettable.</p> <p>I spoke on the health Bill dealing with raising the price of alcohol, and I spoke about it on the wireless also.  The subject of people on social welfare was raised.  I said, perfectly logically I believe, that social welfare was intended for the clothing, food and warmth of people in distress and that it should not be spent on drink.  I indicated I felt there was a good reason for this given the plight of many people, including elderly taxpayers.  Elderly, poor taxpayers do pay tax and I thought it offensive for their tax money to be spent on alcohol.  That is a point of view.  It led to a considerable schemozzle.  Somebody wrote an article in one of those downstream newspapers in which it was stated the D&aacute;il bar is apparently swimming with totally drunken Members of both Houses-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#J00400"><p>Terrible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#J00500"><p>-----and that one cannot stir in it.  How this young creature &mdash; I have never heard of her before &mdash; manages to get inside the D&aacute;il bar, to which she has no access, is simply beyond me.  In 30 years, I saw a drunk Member only once; it was a Member of the other House and he was dealt with effectively.</p> <p>I am told I have received &euro;56,000 in transport guarantees or whatever they are.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#J00600"><p>Expenses.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#J00700"><p>Expenses of &euro;56,000.  Yahweee, but where is it?  I would like to know; it would be just wonderful.  I could be backwards and forwards like I was a yo-yo on that amount of money.  Apparently, this story is granted credibility.  It is said we have these huge salaries, enormous grants and allowances but I just wonder why it is that the 3,000 civil servants who are receiving so much more than we do want to break with us.   It is because we are so timid in getting money.  They fear they will be held back.  They are already 30% below the general population.  We are 30% below as well and now we are going to be shafted by the civil servants abandoning us.  I want to know, before the ship goes down, where my &euro;56,000 in travel expenses is because I have not got it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#J00800"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#J00900"><p>I want to know where it is.  Every kind of looney in the country rises to the service and tries to take a gobble at me.  I have received all kinds of correspondence.  Senators will excuse the vulgarity of the remarks made.  My secretary got a telephone call yesterday and she had to put down the phone.  The fellow on the line asked whether he could speak to me and she said I was not available as I was working at a committee.  He said, "Well, do you know what he wants?  He wants a red-hot poker stuck up his arsehole."  She put the-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#J01000"><p>Senator Norris, that is not parliamentary language.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#J01100"><p>You can say that again.  By God, it is not parliamentary language and certainly should not be stated to my secretary and parliamentary assistant.  I will just read another statement.  There is very little that is offensive-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#J01200"><p>Is the Senator seeking a debate?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#J01300"><p>It is a wonderful catalogue of what I am.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#J01400"><p>Is the Senator seeking a debate on this matter?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#J01500"><p>Absolutely, yes.  The correspondence is from a Mr. John Tierney.  Hello, John.  This is what he said and wants me to read out, "You gay shit, read this about you cunning little toady, creep, crawler, fawner, flatterer, flunkey, truckler, groveller, doormat, lickspittle, kowtower, obsequious person, minion, hanger-on, leech, puppet, spaniel."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#J01600"><p>The Senator is way over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#J01700"><p>That is me and here I am.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator David Norris:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=1758"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1758&amp;amp;pid=DavidNorris&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->He should send more - I absolutely love them - but would he please-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#K00200"><p>Senator, you are way over time.  Please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#K00300"><p>-----leave my poor secretary out of it?  She does not like it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#K00400"><p>I call Senator Comiskey.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#K00500"><p>I laugh at it; she does not.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1124" speakername="Michael Comiskey" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#K00600"><p>I assure Members that neither my secretary nor I nor anyone working for me ever received such a telephone call, thanks be to God.</p> <p>I welcome the news of the deal done yesterday evening by the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine on fishery quota, whereby there will be an increase of 10% in the whitefish quota and of 8% in respect of prawns.  This is good news in particular for those fishermen who own smaller vessels and are trying to eke out a living in difficult circumstances off the coast.  The other point is discards have been done away with.  I always have called for the abolition of discards because it is a waste of perfectly good fish and there is no point in discarding them, as they can be brought to market and used.</p> <p>In recent days and again this morning, a number of colleagues have mentioned the issue of flooding.  Now the floods appear to have started to recede, it is time to give consideration to putting in place a national drainage scheme along the Shannon, as well as for some smaller rivers.  I refer in particular to rivers in the part of the country from which I come, such as the Owenmore in County Sligo, as well as a number of other rivers in counties Sligo and Leitrim.  It now is time for a drainage scheme to be put in place.  I have been contacted in recent days by many farmers whose lands are under water and who have lost considerable amounts of fodder.  Moreover, some of them have been obliged to move their cattle out of their sheds.  This is a terrible time for those farmers and for the small businesses that are affected.  In my native county of Leitrim, Carrick-on-Shannon and Leitrim village are badly affected.  Thankfully, all the towns are open for business, but, as Christmas approaches, it is difficult for those people to be able to conduct their business.  It is time to give real consideration to undertaking a complete drainage scheme along the Shannon and the other rivers affected by drainage issues.  I believe it is past time to put in place such a scheme.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#K00700"><p>I second Senator MacSharry's amendment to the Order of Business.  I also thank the Cathaoirleach for his welcome to my family today.</p> <p>On 10 December 2015, the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs, Deputy Reilly, signed the commencement order on the removal of the defence of reasonable chastisement in cases of corporal punishment under section 28 of the Children First Act 2015.  This amendment came about through the work of Senator van Turnhout and was supported unanimously by this House.  It was a marvellous step forward and Members have provided and done the State great service and have done the children of Ireland a great service henceforth.  Furthermore, on the eve of the 100th anniversary of the 1916 Rising, is it not appropriate, in that the Proclamation refers to treating children equally?  Senator van Turnhout tabled that amendment, which was accepted by the Minister, Deputy Reilly, which has been brought into force.  It does not change family relationships at all but takes away the defence of immunity from criminal liability essentially for striking a child.  This is of great importance and I make the point to the Cathaoirleach, the Leader of the House, the Minister, Senator van Turnhout and every Member of this House - which unanimously supported this move - that it was not initiated in D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann but in this House.  This House deserves credit for this, as well as for many other amendments that have been made over the course of 2015.  The Leader has brought much innovation to the House in his own way, which has resulted in amendments being accepted by the Government on his initiation.  Moreover, I note that most debates are given unlimited time, although I accept there is some tidying up under way at present.  However, throughout the year, the Leader has given adequate time for detailed debates, which have resulted in Ministers returning after Committee Stage to table amendments on Report Stage on the basis of amendments tabled by Members of this House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" speakername="Mary Moran" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#K00800"><p>I congratulate Phil Donnelly, one of the ushers in the House, who is with Members this morning, on her recent promotion as team leader.  It is a huge recognition for Phil, who becomes the first ever female usher to be promoted within the Houses, but it is also a stark reminder that although female ushers were first appointed in 1994, it has taken 21 years for a female usher to win promotion.  I wish Phil all the best in her future role.  It is a great day but it is also a sign for the men to watch out - the women are coming.  Let us hope it is a sign of things to come.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#K00900"><p>The Senator is here already.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#K01000"><p>There are other vacancies coming up very shortly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" speakername="Mary Moran" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#K01100"><p>Absolutely.</p> <p>I also welcome the passage through the Seanad last night of the Assisted Decision-Making (Capacity) Bill 2013 with unanimous support from all parties.  This was a momentous and historic day in the history of the Seanad, particularly for those who lack capacity, as it will allow them to have more control and more of a say over their financial property and personal affairs into the future.  It was a great day for people with disability or who lack capacity in any form, and it was one of my proudest days, if not my proudest, in my four and a half years in the Seanad.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" speakername="Feargal Quinn" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#K01200"><p>I wish to ask the Leader whether anything is being done about the jihadists who are returning to Ireland after going to the Middle East to fight for ISIS.  I believe there is a need to ensure there is a massive disincentive for those who live in Ireland to go abroad to fight and then take an Aer Lingus aeroplane back to Ireland.  I read recently that a number of people in Cork were refused, but, to the best of my knowledge, we do not have a penalty for them.  I believe it is necessary to prosecute those who try to recruit these people online.  While I am unsure how it would be done, a massive disincentive is needed to prevent people from being coaxed to go and fight with ISIS, and a range of countries in the European Union and elsewhere have introduced legislation to do precisely that.  Its specific purpose is to target returning ISIS fighters.  For instance, in Italy there is an eight-to-ten-year jail sentence for those who fight in an armed group that is illegal.  Could this be the framework of an anti-terrorism law?  The Criminal Justice (Terrorist Offences) Act 2005 prosecutes those who engage in terrorist activities outside the State; however, it appears as though the penalties listed in that Act must be upgraded in light of what has happened in Paris and elsewhere.  It appears to me that one could provide for a minimum of 20 years' imprisonment for those who go to fight for entities such as ISIS and then return to Ireland.  I believe it is a matter to which Members should be giving consideration and attention, and while I am unsure whether it could be done without all-party approval, I imagine it probably would have all-party approval.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#K01300"><p>I welcome the appointment of Mr. Justice Peter Kelly as President of the High Court.  As Members are aware, he is an able and most distinguished judge, and I believe no more able or fitting person could be found for the post.  He will bring tremendous leadership to the role, as he already has brought to the Commercial Court in his time there, when he pioneered some great work.  I believe no one has proved his worth as much as has this man in the role of judge.  Consequently, I greatly welcome the appointment and wish him well.</p><p>I am delighted that Senator Norris referred to that grossly inaccurate piece which appeared in the centre page of yesterday's edition of the <i>Irish Independent</i>.  One would swear to God that all Members were drinking until the wee hours of the morning every night.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#K01400"><p>Senator Coghlan should never believe anything he reads in the <i>Irish Independent</i>.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#K01500"><p>Every night in both bars.  My experience here in recent years has been that Members use the Members' Bar mainly for teas, coffees, scones, lunches and so on.  While I am not normally there at closing time, I believe the bars close at what would be considered to be normal hours.  As to where the journalist got this, I note that the facts she had were not facts; they were completely wrong about the number of Senators who are elected on panels and so on.  She should check her facts before she writes further about this House or the other House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#K01600"><p>It was rubbish.  It was beneath journalism.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#K01700"><p>Absolutely correct.  Senator Mooney is quite right.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#K01800"><p>The Senator should stop buying it then.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#K01900"><p>I would not give her any publicity.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#L00100"><p>There must be a spy in the bar.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#L00200"><p>Renamed the coffee shop.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#L00300"><p>I do not know because the bar is not open at the hour she was claiming.  We will leave it at that.  The Senator is quite right.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1176" speakername="Katherine Zappone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#L00400"><p>Today I am publishing and presenting my fourth and probably final Bill during this term.  It is the Residential Tenancies (Amendment) Bill 2015 and it aims to reform the terms of private renting in Ireland by addressing both the high insecurity when renting long-term homes and the financial challenges faced by landlords.  It also provides an immediate community-based and people-led solution for the ongoing homelessness crisis.  I acknowledge the excellent work of the National Economic Social Council and the DKM report which I consulted during the policy-making process.  I also thank Mr. Mike Allen of Focus Ireland and Mr. Fintan McNamara of the Residential Landlords Association for their expert commentary during the drafting of the Bill.  I especially thank my assistant, Ms Magdalene Hayden, for her work on this.</p> <p>The Bill provides for three voluntary rent agreement schemes which offer better security of tenure and certainty of rent for tenants than is currently available, even with the changes made by the Government in the previous Bill.  It also provides for a more favourable tax treatment for landlords who voluntarily provide better protections for their tenants.  I have included three proposed tenancy schemes.  The first is the home tenancy scheme which is open to all households regardless of income or rent.  The second scheme is social tenancy which is available for tenants who receive rent supplement and their landlords.  The third scheme is solidarity tenancy which provides the highest level of incentives for landlords who offer medium-term accommodation to households who are either homeless or refugees.  It is a way to offer an immediate resolution to the homeless and refugee crises.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#L00500"><p>That Bill is not published yet.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1176" speakername="Katherine Zappone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#L00600"><p>It is published today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#L00700"><p>It is not on the Order Paper.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1176" speakername="Katherine Zappone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#L00800"><p>I have it in my hand here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#L00900"><p>It is not on the Order Paper for today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1176" speakername="Katherine Zappone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#L01000"><p>I apologise.  I thought it was on the Order Paper.  Will the Cathaoirleach allow me still to welcome it and mention it?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#L01100"><p>No, it is not on the Order Paper.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1176" speakername="Katherine Zappone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#L01200"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach.  I will conclude by asking the Leader for time to debate this in the new year or to bring it to the attention of the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government, and I ask also that my colleagues consider it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#L01300"><p>I am concerned about the amount of time being allocated to discuss the Prisons Bill 2015 which, I understand, will only be 15 minutes.  We welcome the Prisons Bill because it seeks to close St. Patrick's Institution, but the Department of Justice and Equality, during the D&aacute;il debates, sneaked in a provision on certain persons who are serving sentences of imprisonment for the purposes of deportation or removal from the State and to change the Title of the Bill to take account of that.  There are also technical amendments related to warrants issued by courts in Dublin.  I imagine they are topics which Senators would wish to debate in this House.  When these matters have arisen previously, there has been debate around them.  It seems strange these topics are being sneaked into a Bill that is about the closure of St. Patrick's Institution.  I am concerned there has not been a proper chance to debate it in the Seanad and I ask the Leader to consider the amount of time being allocated for that discussion.</p> <p>I also propose an amendment to the Order of Business, if possible.  I request that the Minister of State, Deputy Joe McHugh, be invited to the House to debate yesterday's High Court ruling on the levies charged on ferry services to the Aran Island ports of Kilronan and Inis M&oacute;r.  Based on the ruling, the ferry company has said it will discontinue the ferry service to Inis M&oacute;r in January 2016.  This comes on foot of the decoupling of a public service obligation, PSO contract for the ferry service to the Aran Islands by a previous Minister of State, Deputy Dinny McGinley, which split the three Aran Islands into separate contracts.  Consequently, there is now no PSO to Inis M&oacute;r which means the islanders are at the behest of the private company which runs the ferry service.  The island could be without a ferry service from January onwards.  We are running out of time before Christmas and it must be addressed urgently.  Will the Leader call on the Minister of State, Deputy McHugh, to see if he has one hour today to discuss what his Department will do to try to reinstate the PSO contract and to get the stakeholders - the islanders, the private ferry company in question, Galway County Council and his Department - to resolve the situation this side of Christmas in order that the service can be continued.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1173" speakername="Lorraine Higgins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#L01400"><p>I commend a parish priest in Ashbourne, County Meath, for the novel approach he has taken to confirming children in his parish.  Usually children who are being confirmed take a pledge not to consume alcohol until they reach 18 years of age.  Fr. Darby is insisting that children take a different pledge not to cyberbully others.  He has also invited garda&iacute; to speak at masses, from the pulpit, on the dangers of the Internet and to encourage the 250 students to take a pledge against cyberbullying for their confirmation.  It is most welcome.  Garda&iacute; in Ashbourne have been proactive in delivering the anti-cyberbullying message.  They have visited schools to alert children to online behaviour and responsibilities.  The garda&iacute; there are doing such good work that it should be a model of excellence for others in similar roles.  Garda Connor, who has been out to schools and who will be speaking from the pulpit-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#L01500"><p>I ask the Senator to refrain from naming people on the record of the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#L01600"><p>I will pass on Senator Higgins's regards to Garda Connor.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1173" speakername="Lorraine Higgins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#L01700"><p>I thank Senator Byrne.  I know she is a constituent of his.  It is great to see this proactive measure being taken.  It is a great move but it is only happening because there is a legislative vacuum in this area, which is a huge failure.  Many people have contacted me over the past year and a half with concerns about online abuse and so on which I have documented in this House, particularly when I brought my Bill to Second Stage.  I remember a headline from 2013 which stated that cyberbullies claimed the lives of five teenagers.  I am sure all Senators would agree that for five children to have taken their own lives is five too many.  It is clear there is a massive problem and the parish priest in Ashbourne has recognised this.  It has been allowed to fester as a result of a lack of legislation.  The reality is that adults and children in this State have been exposed to sustained and sometimes orchestrated campaigns of online abuse and their mental health and well-being has suffered.  Unfortunately, they have no recourse.  I call on the Minister for Justice, Deputy Frances Fitzgerald, to return to the House to debate my Bill on Committee and Report Stages and conclude the matter for the betterment of our online world.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#L01800"><p>I am pleased that reference was made to the individual who wrote that scurrilous article, which was riddled with ignorance, about this House and the D&aacute;il.  I will not enhance or otherwise refer to her further which would give her more publicity.  She should check her facts.  My late father, God be good to him, always bemoaned the fact that journalists, even in his time, did not check their facts.  If there is any criticism, facts must be checked.</p> <p>I wish to be associated with remarks made by Senator Hayden about Francis Ledwidge.  I also grew up with his poetry and the opening line of his poem, Lament for Thomas MacDonagh, about the 1916 signatory whom he befriended, "He shall not hear the bittern cry", still rings true to this day, and I was not one to remember poetry all that well.  I visited the spot where Francis Ledwidge was killed.  A stray shell came over a hill.  He was ganger on Meath County Council and his expertise was used.  He was with a bunch of other soldiers who were clearing a road, actually more of a laneway, but the imagery I remember in particular is the Irish tricolour flying proudly on the spot where an Irish patriot died.  It is wonderful that An Post is going to acknowledge him.</p> <p>Last Monday was the 60th anniversary of Ireland's accession to the United Nations.  Although the United Nations was formed in 1945, Ireland did not become a member until 1955 because the Soviet Union objected to Ireland's membership.  The de Valera Government applied for membership of the UN but the Soviet Union blocked it because Ireland did not have diplomatic relations with Moscow.  However, in the early stages of the foundations of the Free State, strong representations were made to the then emerging Soviet Union and there was developing ties between the Soviet Union and Ireland in the context of independence.  All that fell away primarily because of the 1930s, fascism, anti-communist feeling and the strong influence of the Catholic Church at that time.  The Soviet-Irish relationship lay fallow, and when Ireland applied for membership of the UN, it was blocked by the Soviet Union.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paschal Mooney:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=1990"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1990&amp;amp;pid=PaschalMooney&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->In 1927, when the Fianna F&aacute;il Party first entered Leinster House, one of the platforms included in its manifesto was the opening of diplomatic relations with the Soviet Union.  This calls to mind a comment my dad used to make that Fianna F&aacute;il was viewed as a group of communists and radicals and its members were ex-communicated by the church left, right and centre.  I like to think that radicalism remains at the heart of the party to this day.  I wish to record that this is the 60th anniversary of Ireland's accession to the United Nations.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#M00200"><p>In the past 18 months, I have dealt with cases involving local authority housing tenants who have a family member with a severe physical and intellectual disability and have been waiting for adaptation works to be done to their homes.  In one case, a family has been waiting more than seven and a half years for this work to be done.  In two cases, the parents involved are providing full-time care to children with severe physical and intellectual disabilities.  If the children were being cared for in an appropriate setting, it would cost the State approximately &euro;3,500 per week to meet the needs of each child.  I ask that the Minister come before the House to discuss the inadequate funding provided to local authorities for housing adaptation grants.</p> <p>A significant amount of funding is being provided to local authorities to provide grants to enable private home owners to carry out adaptation works.  While these grants are also necessary, the amount provided for local authority houses is small.  I ask that local authorities be allowed to exercise discretion in 2016 with regard to funding for housing adaptation grants.  This would enable them to provide grants for priority cases in local authority housing.  It is unacceptable that many families in Cork city have been waiting for between seven and eight years for adaptation works to be done, especially where the parents are providing full-time care and going far beyond what is required to care for a child.  We are not providing the support these families need.  Co-ordination is required between the health service, the local authority and the relevant Departments to ensure these parents are given the support they require.  I ask that the Minister come before the House to discuss this extremely important issue for those who have been waiting such a long time. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1196" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#M00300"><p>I am not sure if Senators are aware that our colleague in County Kildare, Councillor Willie Crowley, was the victim of a hit and run accident last night.  His condition is critical and I am sure all Senators will join me in sending our good wishes to him.</p> <p>This morning, representatives of the Organisation of National Ex-Service Personnel and the Irish United Nations Veterans Association appeared before the Joint Committee on Justice, Defence and Equality.  I commend both organisations on the tremendous work they have done in the past 25 or 30 years improving the welfare of retiring and departing members of the Defence Forces.  The establishment of a house for ex-service personnel in Smithfield is a credit to them. </p> <p>A former member of the Defence Forces residing in the Smithfield house suffers from Huntington's disease and urgently needs to be transferred to a medical facility.  I understand the facility in question has indicated it will accept him but there is a problem with a bed.  The Organisation of National Ex-Service Personnel is extremely worried that the individual in question will be injured in the house because he is no longer capable of looking after himself.   I will not name the individual but I will pass on his personal details to the Leader.  I ask him to request that the Minister, who I know is sympathetic to the man's case, try to make the necessary arrangements on his behalf before Christmas.  The individual in question cannot be left in the house in his current condition.  </p> <p>While I accept that volunteers are working to relieve the floods across the country, members of the Defence Forces do not have a choice in the matter.  They are issued with an instruction and must mount their trucks and work in the most horrendous conditions every day and the House must acknowledge this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#M00400"><p>To add to Senator Mooney's comments, the Soviet Union was the first country to recognise the Irish Republic in 1919 and no less a man than Leon Trotsky was its foreign Minister at the time.</p><p>I second the amendment regarding the taking of No. 15, the non-Government motion on cystic fibrosis.  I will read out a note I received from a person who suffers from cystic fibrosis.  He writes:</p><blockquote>I suffer from cystic fibrosis, a debilitating disease which affects many organs of the body, eventually leading to premature death in many cases.  I am 26 years of age with a life expectancy of 41.  I spent three months of this year on intravenous antibiotics, a debilitating chest infection and I spent six months in hospital as an inpatient.  Just last September, my lung capacity went to its lowest level ever of 23%.  My condition will continue to deteriorate and I too, along with many other young Irish people, will have their lives cut short by cystic fibrosis.  However, for the first time, there is now hope.  A new drug that treats the underlying cause of cystic fibrosis has become available in Europe.  Orkambi targets sufferers who have two copies of the cystic fibrosis gene.  It has shown to reduce lung exacerbation by 40% and greatly limits the amount of time that cystic fibrosis sufferers have to spend in hospital.  And our hopes were shattered on December 6th by Tony O'Brien of the HSE who said he would not fund Orkambi.  It is estimated the treatment will cost &euro;160,000 per patient.  This brings the total amount to &euro;92 million.  Orkambi will now under undergo a rapid review within the national centre for pharmacology and pharmoeconomics.  It is most likely that a health technical assessment will then be required to further assess the drug regarding cost-effectiveness and overall benefit to the patient.  However, due to the costs, Orkambi will fail the HTA-----</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#M00500"><p>Is the Senator supporting the call for a debate on this issue?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#M00600"><p>Yes, I am calling for a debate.  The note continues:</p><blockquote>The Health Minister, Leo Varadkar, has stated if it gets to the point where this drug gets through the process and gets approved by the NCPE and the National Drug Committee I will go to Government and seek money for it.  I hold the opinion that Mr. Varadkar is very much aware that Orkambi will fail the NCPE-----</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#M00700"><p>The Senator may make these points during the debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#M00800"><p>He continues:</p><blockquote>We are tired of putting our lives on hold.  I spend three hours per day taking treatment to alleviate the symptoms of cystic fibrosis.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#M00900"><p>We are not having a debate on the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#M01000"><p>The note continues:</p><blockquote>This isn't even a guarantee of prolonged good health because my efforts will be in vain.  I will still end up battling consistent chest infections, enduring long hospitalisation stays, which will lead to my eventual death sooner rather than later.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#M01100"><p>The Senator is out of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#M01200"><p>He continues:</p><blockquote>I can't even hold down a job because of regular illness.  I simply ask that I and my fellow CF sufferers be given a chance to lead a normal life without constant interruption and fear of the road ahead.  </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#M01300"><p>The Senator is way over time.  He is out of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#M01400"><p>The note concludes as follows, "For that to happen, the HSE needs to approve Orkambi."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1205" speakername="Paul Bradford" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#M01500"><p>I will try to remain within the time limit.  I support the comments of Senator Colm Burke on adaptation grants.  He cited a number of cases in the Cork City Council area but the problem is nationwide.  Until a few years ago, local authorities operated an uncomplicated, flexible and locally generated scheme known as the disabled person's grant.  When this scheme was transformed to become the housing adaptation grant scheme, the level of administration increased.  Occupational therapist reports were required and the costs of the scheme and the red tape surrounding it caused many of the delays we are now experiencing.  While further investment is clearly required, it would be helpful if council officials showed much greater flexibility and discretion.</p> <p>Senator Burke referred to cases where applicants for home adaptation grants have been waiting for six or seven years.  This is deeply regrettable.  A disabled person's grant provides immediate assistance to families and disabled persons who may otherwise need to be institutionalised or cared for by the State in alternative accommodation.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paul Bradford:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=73"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=73&amp;amp;pid=PaulBradford&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We should try to re-establish the flexibility of these valuable schemes.  In most cases, the amount of grant aid is modest.  The requirements are small, but it is of importance to the applicants and their families.  I support Senator Colm Burke.  We should be able to make progress on such schemes and return to the days when the local authority had much greater flexibility and there was less bureaucracy and less need for all the reports.  Up to five or ten years ago, applications were processed, certainly in the northern area of Cork County Council, within months rather than five or six years because of the flexibility that was allowed.  I would like to see a return to the procedure at that time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#N00200"><p>I support the calls in the Seanad today, and second Senator Daly's amendment if it is necessary, because we were not sure if it was properly called the first time, for a debate in the Seanad and calling on the Minister for Health and the HSE to make funding available for the drug, Orkambi.  There is another drug, called Kalydeco, which is already available for the relatively small percentage of cystic fibrosis, CF, sufferers in Ireland who need it, and it is life-changing for them.  The majority of CF sufferers in Ireland, as I understand it, would benefit from the drug, Orkambi.  As Senators will be aware, Ireland has the highest rate of CF in the world.  This is where CF happens to the greatest extent.  We all know persons who suffer from it and who have died from it.  The least we can do is lead the way on this issue.  What was most hurtful, for those with CF and those who have family members with CF, were the comments of Mr. Tony O'Brien of the HSE when he ruled the drug out before it had gone through any of the processes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#N00300"><p>Senator Byrne should not name officials from the Department.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#N00400"><p>This is in the public record.  This is how this debate started.  People could not believe that this process appeared to be done and dusted with the HSE.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#N00500"><p>He is not here to defend himself.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#N00600"><p>We need a debate on this issue today in the Seanad.  We need to support those affected.  Ireland needs to lead the way on this issue.  We should not be rubbishing drug companies all the time like we did in the case of the drug Soliris last year because the hope of these CF sufferers for a relatively normal life depends on the research and development done by many of these drug companies.  We should applaud these drug companies for the research they have done, some of which, it must be said, has been funded by charitable and other sources.</p> <p>A considerable amount of research has gone into this drug.  I understand it would be of immense benefit to almost 60% of Irish CF sufferers and we need to show the way.  When the drug Soliris was granted last year, there was a major injustice when two patients out of 12 were refused access to it.  We debated the matter here in the Seanad on a number of occasions, it went to the D&aacute;il and, eventually, that fight, which was a fight for justice, was won.  I support the proposal for an amendment to the Order of Business.</p> <p>I thank my colleagues, Senators Hayden and Higgins, for mentioning Meath - ears will be burning in Meath today - and the late Francis Ledwidge.  We are delighted that the stamp is being issued.  I am also delighted that the Ledwidge committee has launched a CD of Francis Ledwidge's poetry and I recommend that to colleagues as it would make an excellent Christmas gift.  Indeed, I will pass on Senator Higgins's praise for Fr. Darby in Ashbourne, who is a wonderful priest, because that is a wonderful idea.  He is a great churchman but also, as one can hear from what Senator Higgins said, an extremely practical man as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#N00700"><p>Lots of valuable items are being discussed in the House today.  I add my voice to the urgent call for a debate on the provision of the new drug, Orkambi, for cystic fibrosis sufferers.  We are talking about not only quality of life, but life or death.  One can rule it out of order all one wants but if it was one's life that was on the line, one would like to think that Parliament would at least hear a motion on a drug that could save one's life.</p> <p>I would like to be strongly associated with the words of Senator &Oacute; Clochartaigh about the need for the PSO to be put in place for the ferry to Inis M&oacute;r.  Once again, we are in a mess when it comes to the Aran Islands.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#N00800"><p>Is Senator Healy Eames seconding the amendment?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#N00900"><p>I certainly am.</p> <p>It is as simple as this.  Bad decisions are being made about the Aran Islands all the time.  A few months ago, it was an eitle&aacute;in.  Anois, an b&aacute;d.  Would the Minister of State, Deputy McHugh, and others get their act together when it comes to the Aran Islands, not make their Christmas a mess and stop isolating them?  They are on an island in the Atlantic.  They are off our coast, not on the mainland, so let us cut them a bit of slack.</p> <p>I also support my good friend, Senator Quinn, about the importance of a debate on how we treat terrorists in this country.  We should not think it is down the line of priorities.  I refer to those who go to fight with ISIS or jihadists.  We need to give a clear message that we do not tolerate that in our country and that we are a peace-loving nation.  Regrettably, some of our own people could be joining those forces.  That is an important debate to have in the new year.  I do not expect it will be this week.</p> <p>I am concerned that there is one Bill not on the Order Paper, that is, the Criminal Law (Sexual Offences) Bill.  Could the Leader tell the House if that Bill will come in by the end of tomorrow?  We have waited for years for the Criminal Law (Sexual Offences) Bill.  We have waited for years to decriminalise the women and penalise the buyer.  The Leader should not tell me that this term, and D&aacute;il and Seanad, could rise without this Bill going through this House.  There is speculation that the Taoiseach may call an early election in January.  If that is the case and if this Bill is not through, I bid "good luck" to all our brave comments and support for women who are marginalised, in poverty and at the mercy of pimps.  I hope it is coming in this session.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#N01000"><p>I note today a publication from the Department of Education and Skills and the Higher Education Authority on addressing inequality in participation in third level education.  This is commendable but one also must respond that addressing inequality in education when students are aged 18 rather than between the ages of four and 18 misses a large part of the problem of inequality in education.  Perhaps those issues should be addressed by the new Oireachtas.</p> <p>I also note the ESRI report today that families are still on average 10% worse off due to the combined impacts of the budgets since the crisis began in 2008.  It is a challenge for all of us in this House in its remaining days and in the new Oireachtas that such losses of income to families still have not been made up.  We have made a lot of progress and we are going in the right direction, but 10% is still missing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#N01100"><p>Senator MacSharry raised the closure of Garda stations, particularly Easky Garda station in County Sligo, and the fact that the OPW sold that Garda station for &euro;60,000.  The Senator complained that these Garda stations should be available for community use.  I believe it was the intention that if communities showed an interest, serious consideration would be given to community use.  I do not know what happened in the case of that particular Garda station.</p> <p>Senator MacSharry moved an amendment to the Order of Business, that No. 81, motion 15, be taken before No. 1.  The motion relates to cystic fibrosis, a matter raised by a number of Senators.  The facts of the matter are that this drug has not yet been approved by the HSE for usage and the Minister is on record as saying that if the drug is approved for usage, he will go to Government to seek more funding for it.  That is what the Minister would say if he was here.  The Minister is on record as saying that and there is no need to bring him in here today.  I do not propose to accede to the amendment to the Order of Business.  I assure Senator MacSharry that the Minister, as soon as the drug is approved, will make the funding available.</p> <p>Senator Hayden welcomed the additional &euro;8 million for local authorities regarding the clean-up after the flooding.  All local authorities in the various areas will appreciate that funding.  The Senator also raised unfinished housing estates, a matter which was addressed on many occasions in this House.  It is welcome that the number of unfinished housing estates has been reduced by 75%.  Tremendous progress has been made in that regard and, hopefully, we will see an end to them completely within the coming year.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Maurice Cummins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2003"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2003&amp;amp;pid=MauriceCummins&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Senators Hayden and Barrett referred to inequality of access to third level education.  Senator Barrett stated that the inequality starts when children are four years of age or so.  I am sure that we will discuss this matter with the Minister for Education and Skills early in the new year.<br/><br/>Senator Hayden outlined the need for further student accommodation, particularly in Dublin, given its exorbitant cost currently.  She had a lot to say this morning, because she also referred to the commemorative stamp for Francis Ledwidge, which was also mentioned by Senators Mooney and Byrne.  It is to be welcomed.  Like Senator Mooney, I had the pleasure of visiting Francis Ledwidge's grave last year when the British-Irish Parliamentary Assembly, BIPA, visited a number of war graves.<br/><br/>Senator van Turnhout welcomed the appointment of Dr. Geoffrey Shannon to the District Court.  On the question of judges, Senator Paul Coghlan welcomed Mr. Justice Peter Kelly's appointment as President of the High Court.  We wish both judges well.  Senator van Turnhout also discussed the special helpline for homeless children, expressing the hope that we will not need it next year.  That would be the hope of every Senator.<br/><br/>Senators Norris and Healy Eames discussed the sexual offences Bill.  It will not be before the House again this year.  We had Committee Stage last week but did not finish it.  There was no prospect of finishing Committee and Report Stages by the end of the session, but we hope that it will be passed by the Houses early in the new year.<br/><br/>Among other Senators, Senator Norris commented on an article in yesterday's <i>Irish Independent</i>.  There were some glaring errors and it certainly was not factual.  One error that stood out was the statement that 54 Members of the Seanad would continue to be elected by Deputies, Senators and local councillors.  Any child entering the House would know that 43 Senators are elected in that way, not 54.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#O00200"><p>That is a reflection on the quality of the journalism.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#O00300"><p>Boycott the <i>Irish Independent</i>.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#O00400"><p>Journalists were always known for examining and researching their facts before publishing anything, but obviously there is a need for------</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#O00500"><p>Traditionally, but there is a new generation that obviously does not need to do any research.  These journalists just pick things off the top of their heads.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#O00600"><p>Senator Comiskey complimented the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine, Deputy Coveney, on the fishery quotas.  The Minister has done well in that regard in recent years.  The Senator welcomed the increased quotas for whitefish and prawns in particular and the abolition of the policy on discards.  The Senator also outlined the difficulties for businesses and farmers resulting from the floods and discussed the need for an agency to deal with the question of drainage of the Shannon, a suggestion that was addressed yesterday.</p> <p>Senator Leyden complimented the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs, Deputy Reilly, on the Bill relating to the reasonable chastisement of children.  I appreciate the Senator's comments in that regard.</p> <p>Senator Moran complimented our usher, Ms Phil Donnelly, on being appointed team leader of the ushers and welcomed the passage of the Assisted Decision-Making (Capacity) Bill through the House yesterday.</p> <p>Senators Quinn and Healy Eames discussed jihadis returning to Ireland and what penalties they would face.  The Senators mentioned the need for the Criminal Justice (Terrorist Offences) Act 2005 to reflect the changes that we have witnessed in recent years.  I agree, and am sure that the Department of Justice and Equality and the Minister are considering proposals to change the Act to reflect the current circumstances.</p> <p>Senator Zappone outlined the fact that she intended to publish a residential tenancies (amendment) Bill.  I am sure that it will be debated in the new year.</p> <p>Senator &Oacute; Clochartaigh asked for time for the Prisons Bill.  We have an hour for the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na (Policing Authority and Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill, but I expect that will be concluded in a short period.  We will run straight into the Prisons Bill and I expect there to be more time for it than indicated.  Regarding both Bills, I omitted to mention Report and Fifth Stages while outlining the Order of Business.</p> <p>Senator &Oacute; Clochartaigh was supported by Senator Healy Eames regarding the difficulties with the public service obligation, PSO, licence for the ferry to the Aran Islands.  I suggest that a Commencement matter be submitted for debate so that we might get an answer from the Minister.</p> <p>Senator Higgins complimented those garda&iacute; who were visiting schools to outline the dangers of online abuse.  Garda&iacute; are to be complimented on their efforts in this regard because it is a serious issue that needs to be addressed.</p> <p>Senator Mooney stated that last Monday was the 60th anniversary of Ireland's membership of the UN and outlined the historical background to that.</p> <p>Senators Burke and Bradford discussed house adaptation works for people with disabilities, particularly those in local authority housing.  I cannot understand how any council could stand over people waiting six or seven years for these grants.  The Senators are seeking greater flexibility in the funding.  This year, Waterford's local authority put an extra &euro;88,000 of its own resources into grants for disabled persons.  It is unbelievable to think that it has taken six or seven years for adaptation works to be carried out.  The council should examine the issue.</p> <p>Senator Craughwell wished Councillor Crowley of Kildare, who was seriously injured in an accident yesterday evening, well.  We would all like to join the Senator in that regard.</p> <p>The Organisation of National Ex-Servicemen and Women, ONE, which is a great organisation, is concerned about the health of one of its members in Springfield House.  I suggest that Senator Craughwell submit the matter for a Commencement debate tomorrow to get an answer from the Minister.  I join him in complimenting the Defence Forces on their work, particularly during the recent flooding when they did a tremendous job.  They continue to do so.</p> <p>Senator Barrett mentioned the ESRI's report, which I am sure will be examined and acted upon by the Government.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#O00700"><p>I am sure that all Senators would like to congratulate and wish Ms Phil Donnelly well in her new role.  Senator MacSharry has proposed an amendment to the Order of Business, "That No. 1, motion No. 15, be taken today."  Is the amendment being pressed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#O00800"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.131/1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#O00900"><p>Amendment put:</p><p>The Seanad divided: T, 18; Nl, 24.</p><br/><br/><p>Tellers: T, Senators Paschal Mooney and Diarmuid Wilson; Nl, Senators Paul Coghlan and Aideen Hayden..</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.131/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2015-12-16" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#O00900">
            <divisioncount ayes="18" noes="24" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" vote="aye">Sean Barrett</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1205" vote="aye">Paul Bradford</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" vote="aye">Thomas Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1196" vote="aye">Gerard Craughwell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" vote="aye">Mark Daly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" vote="aye">Fidelma Healy Eames</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1209" vote="aye">James Heffernan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" vote="aye">Terry Leyden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" vote="aye">Marc MacSharry</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" vote="aye">Paschal Mooney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" vote="aye">David Norris</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1115" vote="aye">Labhr&aacute;s &Oacute; Murch&uacute;</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" vote="aye">Darragh O'Brien</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" vote="aye">Denis O'Donovan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" vote="aye">Feargal Quinn</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" vote="aye">Mary White</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" vote="aye">Diarmuid Wilson</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1176" vote="aye">Katherine Zappone</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" vote="no">Ivana Bacik</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" vote="no">Terry Brennan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" vote="no">Colm Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1208" vote="no">M&aacute;ir&iacute;a Cahill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" vote="no">Eamonn Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" vote="no">Paul Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1124" vote="no">Michael Comiskey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" vote="no">Martin Conway</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" vote="no">Maurice Cummins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" vote="no">Jim D'Arcy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1160" vote="no">Michael D'Arcy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" vote="no">Aideen Hayden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1152" vote="no">Imelda Henry</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1173" vote="no">Lorraine Higgins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" vote="no">John Kelly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" vote="no">Marie Moloney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" vote="no">Mary Moran</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1134" vote="no">Tony Mulcahy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" vote="no">Michael Mullins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" vote="no">Catherine Noone</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" vote="no">Susan O'Keeffe</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" vote="no">Pat O'Neill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1163" vote="no">Tom Shehan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" vote="no">Jillian van Turnhout</mpname>
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.131/3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#O00900"><p>Amendment declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#Q00050"><p>Senator Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh has moved an amendment to the Order of Business, "That a debate on the future of ferry services to the Aran Islands, in view of the levies being imposed on contractors, be taken today."  Is the amendment being pressed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#Q00075"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.134/1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#Q00100"><p>Amendment put:</p><p>The Seanad divided: T, 20; Nl, 24.</p><br/><br/><p>Tellers: T, Senators Fidelma Healy Eames and Trevor  Clochartaigh; Nl, Senators Paul Coghlan and Aideen Hayden.</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.134/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2015-12-16" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#Q00100">
            <divisioncount ayes="20" noes="24" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" vote="aye">Sean Barrett</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1205" vote="aye">Paul Bradford</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" vote="aye">Thomas Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1196" vote="aye">Gerard Craughwell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" vote="aye">David Cullinane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" vote="aye">Mark Daly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" vote="aye">Fidelma Healy Eames</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1209" vote="aye">James Heffernan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" vote="aye">Terry Leyden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" vote="aye">Marc MacSharry</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" vote="aye">Paschal Mooney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" vote="aye">David Norris</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" vote="aye">Darragh O'Brien</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" vote="aye">Denis O'Donovan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" vote="aye">Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1115" vote="aye">Labhr&aacute;s &Oacute; Murch&uacute;</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" vote="aye">Feargal Quinn</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" vote="aye">Mary White</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" vote="aye">Diarmuid Wilson</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1176" vote="aye">Katherine Zappone</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" vote="no">Ivana Bacik</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" vote="no">Terry Brennan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" vote="no">Colm Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1208" vote="no">M&aacute;ir&iacute;a Cahill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" vote="no">Eamonn Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" vote="no">Paul Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1124" vote="no">Michael Comiskey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" vote="no">Martin Conway</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" vote="no">Maurice Cummins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" vote="no">Jim D'Arcy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1160" vote="no">Michael D'Arcy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" vote="no">Aideen Hayden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1152" vote="no">Imelda Henry</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1173" vote="no">Lorraine Higgins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" vote="no">John Kelly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" vote="no">Marie Moloney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" vote="no">Mary Moran</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1134" vote="no">Tony Mulcahy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" vote="no">Michael Mullins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" vote="no">Catherine Noone</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" vote="no">Susan O'Keeffe</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" vote="no">Pat O'Neill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1163" vote="no">Tom Shehan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" vote="no">Jillian van Turnhout</mpname>
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.134/3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#Q00100"><p>Amendment declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.135" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question, "That the Order of Business be agreed to", put and declared carried.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.136" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#R00100">Garda Sochna (Policing Authority and Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill 2015: [Seanad Bill amended by the Dil] Report and Final Stages</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#R00200"><p>This is a Seanad Bill which has been amended by the D&aacute;il.  In accordance with Standing Order 118, it is deemed to have passed its First, Second and Third Stages in the Seanad and is placed on the Order Paper for Report Stage.  On the question "That the Bill be received for final consideration", the Minister may explain the purpose of the amendments made by the D&aacute;il.  This is looked upon as the report of the D&aacute;il amendments to the Seanad.  For Senators' convenience, I have arranged for the printing and circulation of the amendments.  The Minister will deal separately with the subject matter of each related group of amendments.  I have also circulated a proposed grouping in the House.  A Senator may contribute once on each grouping and I remind Senators that the only matters which may be discussed are the amendments made by the D&aacute;il and nothing else.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.138" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That the Bill be received for final consideration."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#R00400"><p>I call the Minister to speak to the subject matter of the first grouping.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1009" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#R00500"><p>I thank the House for facilitating the debate this morning.  The purpose of the first amendment is to impose a statutory timeline on the Garda Commissioner for the provision by the Commissioner to the authority of the Garda strategy statement.  Essentially, once we set up the new policing authority on 1 January, the Commissioner will be obliged to present the strategy statement to the authority within six months and then every three years thereafter.  It is really to get the authority up and running and to have the strategy statement presented to it within six months.  That is quite demanding, and rightly so, on the Commissioner in terms of having a discussion on the new strategy statement with the new Garda authority.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#R00600"><p>I ask the Minister to speak on the second grouping which comprises the subject matter of amendments Nos. 2 and 3.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1009" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#R00700"><p>Amendment No. 3, which involves the insertion of a new subparagraph, takes into account what a number of Opposition Deputies and Senators were seeking, namely, that there should be a provision which makes explicit the authority's function to keep under review the adequacy of the arrangements for managing and deploying the resources available to An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na so as to ensure the most beneficial, effective and efficient use of those resources.  This simply was not spelled out originally and, as such, we have included an arrangement by way of the amendments for managing and deploying the resources available to An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na so as to ensure the most beneficial, effective and efficient use of those resources.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#R00800"><p>I welcome the Minister and thank her for coming in.  She might clarify an issue raised with me again and again by local garda&iacute;, which is rostering and the change in Galway - as a result of the working time directive - from four rosters to five.  I am informed that has had the knock-on effect of having garda&iacute; available for fewer hours, which, in turn, has had an impact on rural Garda stations which it is harder to man during the evening time.  Where does the policy issue arise here?  Obviously, the working time directive is connected into a different Department.  How much of that is left to the authority to decide and how much to the Commissioner?  What input will the Minister of the day have in having that changed?  I understand that the matter of rostering is up for review again at present because the scheme in place was a pilot.  The chief superintendent in Galway has sent forward a submission on the working of the pilot scheme.  I am not sure if the Minister is aware of when the pilot scheme will be reviewed and if there is any move afoot to revert to the previous system or to put a system in place that would better suit rural areas.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1009" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#R00900"><p>This issue was addressed in the Garda Inspectorate report.  There was a great deal of consultation before the new roster scheme came into operation.  Obviously, as more garda&iacute; are recruited - and we have ongoing and continuous recruitment - some of the issues the Senator raises will be addressed.  The Garda roster scheme is being considered under Haddington Road by Mr. Ray McGee.  Clearly, this is an operational matter for the Garda Commissioner and there is also a question of compliance with the working time directive.  We have asked for the Haddington Road review to be completed by the end of February.  We will see what recommendations are made.  It took a great deal of time to get to the new roster but there are some operational issues that have arisen.  It may be that changes to some aspects of the rosters may be negotiated which deal with the situation the Senator outlined.  There are some real operational issues that have arisen and I have no doubt that the Commissioner will address them.  As I say, it is being dealt with under the Haddington Road review.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#R01000"><p>I ask the Minister to speak to the subject matter of amendments Nos. 4 and 5.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1009" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#R01100"><p>Amendments Nos. 4 and 5 are straightforward.  They relate to a proposal to request the authority to submit to the Minister a report on any matter relating to policing services.  The authority is required to submit that report as soon as it is in a position to do so.  This is to ensure that there is an option for the Minister of the day to request a report on a particular topic from the Garda authority.  It is a sensible thing to do because issues may arise in the D&aacute;il or Seanad on policing.  They may be operational matters that the Garda authority has been looking at.  These amendments give the Minister the power to request a report from the Garda authority.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#R01200"><p>I take into account the fact that the Minister may not be in office within the next six months, not for personal reasons, but on foot of the cycle in which ministerial rotation happens in any administration.  The future is uncertain and no one knows it.  The Minister has been reported as welcoming the recommendations contained in the recently published Olson report.  We have raised the report here, as have colleagues from other parties, and it is a shocking indictment of 30 years' of governance in respect of policing matters.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paschal Mooney:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=1990"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1990&amp;amp;pid=PaschalMooney&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->For example, the report states that the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na has behind technologically for nearly 30 years and that it takes four years for child abuse investigations to be processed because it does not have the necessary technology.  Friends and family of mine who are members of the Garda tell me morale in the force is at a very low ebb, primarily due to top-heavy management, as addressed in the Olson report.  This heavy-handed management results in questionable promotion practices.  The Minister will be more aware of it than I.  I am only an ordinary citizen who picks up on these matters.  Individual rank and file garda&iacute; who have merit and who in the normal course of events, or in any other occupation, would be promoted are not being promoted.  They are not being mentored by senior management, who are ensuring their own futures and feathering their own nests, not financially but in the system, to ensure their continuance in the positions they hold by ensuring the people they recommend for promotion are singing from the same hymn sheet.  These are very serious issues which garda&iacute; are telling me about and which have come out in the open through the Olson report.  Does the Minister have an opinion on this?  In the context of her acceptance of the recommendations of the report, will she take positive action in the short time left?</p><p>I hope the Minister continues in her role, given that she is doing a fine job in the most difficult and complex Ministry.  She is responsible for range of issues, not least ensuring the personal security of every citizen in the State.  It is a heavy burden for anybody to carry, and the Minister is doing it well.  I am sure the Minister agrees that the issues raised by the Olson report, and in the context of the amendments and the policing authority, will recur.  I hope the Minister will take the opportunity today to indicate her thinking on it.  I have not seen the detail of her response, except that she has generally welcomed the report and accepts the recommendations.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#S00200"><p>I welcome the Minister and I welcome the fact that the Bill is on this Stage.  It is a very important Bill in terms of providing, at last, for a policing authority which will oversee the performance of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  It has been widely welcomed across the House, will be a notable achievement of the Government and will have important benefits for the future of policing.  I refer to what Senator Mooney said about the recent Garda Inspectorate report, Changing Policing in Ireland, known as the Olson report.  The Garda Inspectorate will come before the Joint Committee on Justice, Defence and Equality at 2.30 p.m. today to discuss the 81 recommendations for change made in the report and explain how they could be implemented.</p> <p>While the inspectorate is saying there must be a strong implementation group to drive a process of reform, it will take time.  Some of the suggestions for change are fundamental, including a reduction in the number of Garda regions from six to three and a significant reduction in the number of senior managers.  The report merits much wider discussion, which I hope we will have at the meeting of the justice committee.  I particularly welcome the amendment allowing the Minister to require the policing authority in future to prepare a report on particular policing matters.  The matters on which the inspectorate has reported are very important and deserve a more substantive debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1009" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#S00300"><p>With regard to Senator Mooney's point about Garda morale, the Garda Inspectorate held its focus groups with members of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na approximately two years ago.  Given that the Government is managing the economy effectively, we are able to invest in ongoing Garda recruitment.  We have 1,150 new garda&iacute; and have allocated an investment of several hundred million euro for the refurbishment and development of the kind of facilities the Garda needs.  This year, we have made a much-needed investment in Garda vehicles that will help garda&iacute; do their jobs effectively and efficiently. When garda&iacute; are receiving the resources they need and there are new members joining the force, it is good for morale.</p> <p>Approximately 800 recommendations on the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na have been made by a variety of reports over several years.  The Government accepted all the recommendations of the report on criminal investigations, which was published before this report.  Last year, a programme of implementation started, and the changes outlined in the report are already happening.  It is reassuring and important.  By the end of the year, PULSE will record crime investigations, not just the fact that a crime took place.  It is a development of the technology.  There was a need for investment in technology, and it is under way.  Rosters, as mentioned by Senator &Oacute; Clochartaigh, will be on computers.  It is extraordinary to think that rosters are not computerised and no HR system is available to the Garda.  The tendering process is in place to ensure it happens next year.  All of this is important in dealing with the issues in the inspectorate report.</p> <p>I have asked the Garda Commissioner and some other stakeholders to respond in the first instance to the recommendations.  Many of the recommendations are very far-reaching and, if implemented, will lead to a fundamental restructuring of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na across the country.  I therefore want the full implications of the recommendations to be clearly discussed and understood.  I agree that the inspectorate report needs wider discussion and I am very pleased that the justice committee will meet representatives of the inspectorate this afternoon.  Given the history of community policing, which we want to maintain, and the need for community policing, there are questions about how the recommendations would impact on it and how we can ensure it continues.  The report makes general points about culture, and there are many recommendations.  We must carefully consider what an implementation plan would look like.  We need feedback from the front line on the implications of the recommendations.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#S00400"><p>We move on to group 4, which deals with the subject matter of amendments Nos. 6 to 8, inclusive.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1009" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#S00500"><p>The purpose of the amendments is to enable the authority or the Minister to refer matters to GSOC for consideration as to whether GSOC should initiate a public interest investigation under section 102(4).  This is an important provision.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.153" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.154" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question, "That the Bill do now pass", put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.155" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#S00900">Garda Sochna (Policing Authority and Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill 2015: Motion for Earlier Signature</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#S01000"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That pursuant to subsection 2&deg; of section 2 of Article 25 of the Constitution, Seanad &Eacute;ireann concurs with the Government in a request to the President to sign the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na (Policing Authority and Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill 2015 on a date which is earlier than the fifth day after the date on which the Bill shall have been presented to him.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.157" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.158" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#S01200">Prison Bill 2015: [Seanad Bill amended by the Dil] Report and Final Stages</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#S01300"><p>This is a Seanad Bill which has been amended by the D&aacute;il.  In accordance with Standing Order 118, it is deemed to have passed its First, Second and Third Stages in the Seanad and is placed on the Order Paper for Report Stage.  On the question "That the Bill be received for final consideration," the Minister may explain the purpose of the amendments made by the D&aacute;il.  This is looked upon as the report of the D&aacute;il amendments to the Seanad.  For Senators' convenience, I have arranged for the printing and circulation of the amendments.  The Minister will deal separately with the subject matter of each related group of amendments.  I have circulated the proposed grouping of amendments.  Senators may speak only once on each grouping.  The only matters that may be discussed are the amendments made by the D&aacute;il, and no wider issues.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.160" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That the Bill be received for final consideration."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1009" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#S01500"><p>Regarding group 1, amendments Nos. 1 and 3, there was a court case earlier this year, NBO <i>v.</i>the Minister for Justice and Equality, during which the High Court considered the temporary release of a person who was subject to a deportation order and was deported immediately after being granted temporary release.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Frances Fitzgerald:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=401"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=401&amp;amp;pid=FrancesFitzgerald&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The High Court decided that the temporary release provision does not permit the temporary release of prisoners who are subject to deportation orders for the purpose of their deportation.  I refer to convicted prisoners, that is, people who have committed a criminal offence and are in prison.</p><p>Given the implications of the judgment, a clear legislative basis was needed to allow non-national convicted prisoners to be transferred into the custody of garda&iacute; or immigration officers for the purpose of giving effect to the deportation order.  This new section will permit a prisoner to be transferred into the custody of a garda or immigration officer to facilitate his or her deportation or removal from the State in accordance with a deportation order or a removal order before the end of the person's sentence.  It is proposed that the new section will only apply in respect of prisoners who have one year or less of their sentences remaining to serve when remission is taken into account.  A prisoner transferred into the custody of a garda or immigration officer under the new section will be required to remain out of the State as required by the deportation order or removal order.  A person who does not comply with this condition will be deemed to be unlawfully at large and may be arrested and returned to prison.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#T00200"><p>It seems strange to insert this miscellaneous provision in a Bill that has closed St. Patrick's Institution.  It seems a little bit out of place.  The Minister said it was a convicted prisoner who was to be deported.  How serious a case was this?  Is there a danger that, for people seeking asylum, the process could be deemed to be exhausted because of a deportation order against them?  Is there any fear that someone seeking asylum could be jailed for the failure to pay a fine or a smaller offence and could be deported quickly under this mechanism rather than having the full range of his or her international rights?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#T00300"><p>I welcome this Bill, on which we spoke in the Seanad last week.  It is a notable achievement of this Government finally to see the closure of St. Patrick's Institution and it is a notable achievement on children's rights as well as on penal reform.  Last week the Minister highlighted the fact that she would bring forward this amendment in the D&aacute;il, so it is not a surprise to see the new Part 5, section 24 in the Bill.</p> <p>I agree in general with what Senator &Oacute; Clochartaigh said on the widespread practice of using particular Bills to make amendments to other Bills in a piecemeal reform.  It is unfortunate to see this provision in a Bill that otherwise has such a key core purpose.  At the same time, I accept the need for this change.  I assumed the change would be by way of an amendment to existing legislation but section 24 is just a stand-alone provision.  What was the basis for the power?  Was there no statutory power previously?  I have not read the High Court judgment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#T00400"><p>I thank the Minister for bringing forward this legislation and for the change relating to St. Patrick's Institution.  I have visited Oberstown and have seen young people coming into the criminal justice system.  We need a more comprehensive co-ordination of services at local level involving education, health and justice to keep the maximum number of people out of the system.  I am concerned by the lack of co-ordination and that each Department seems to pass the responsibility to other Departments.  I also welcome the amendment proposed by the Minister, which has been dealt with in the D&aacute;il.  It is an important amendment and it is important there is co-ordination in dealing with deportation orders.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1009" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#T00500"><p>I assure Senator &Oacute; Clochartaigh that the amendment will not affect the operation of existing procedures under immigration legislation, for example, where a person wishes to appeal or seek a review of a deportation order.  It is not intended in any way to cut across the person's rights.  If they are in prison or seeking an appeal or review, that process has to be completed.  It is not a shortcut or something which will cut across any legislation on immigration or refugee rights.</p> <p>On Senator Bacik's point, the court decided that section 2 of the Criminal Justice Act, which governs the temporary release of prisoners, does not permit the temporary release of prisoners who are subject to deportation orders.  Given the practical implications of that, it was felt that a clear legislative basis was needed for this section.  We decided to do it as a section of this Bill, although I take the points made by Senators &Oacute; Clochartaigh and Bacik that it is not associated with the closure of St. Patrick's Institution.  We are using this legislation because it is important to have a clear legislative basis for deporting people who are convicted criminals, in prison and subject to deportation orders.  To deal with what the High Court had found on temporary release, I have used this opportunity to bring it to the House in this legislation.  The central issue we are addressing, though, is the closure of St. Patrick's Institution.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#T00600"><p>Will the Minister reassure the House that, given the current international climate relating to terrorism, garda&iacute; under her watch continue to monitor those coming in and out of the State?  Will she assure us that undesirable people, once identified, will be locked up and deported immediately?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1009" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#T00700"><p>A serious terrorist threat faces Europe and some countries are under severe threat from terrorists.  While we in Ireland know that an attack is possible, we do not consider it to be likely.  Having said that, we have to be very rigorous in our monitoring of the situation and of anybody who might raise concerns.  I assure the Senator that An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, which acts as the security service in this country along with the separate but important role the Defence Forces play, will continue to monitor this issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#T00800"><p>Group 2 comprises technical amendments, the subject matter of amendments Nos. 2 and 4.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1009" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#T00900"><p>Of the second group of amendments, amendment No. 2 is a technical amendment relating to warrants issued by courts in Dublin for the committal of persons to prison.  It arises from an issue that has emerged in very recent High Court proceedings.  Outside of the Dublin district, warrants are addressed to An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na in accordance with very old legislation.  However, the District Court rules permit committal warrants in Dublin to be addressed directly to the governor of the prison to which a person is to be committed.  The courts have operated on this basis for a very long time.  In a recent judgment, a judge of the High Court expressed the view that the relevant provision of the District Court rules may be inconsistent with this very early Act.  It opens up the prospect of uncertainty at least in the legal provision, and it is appropriate to amend the relevant legislation to make it clear that the arrangements made for Dublin and the rules of court are permitted.  Amendment No. 2 proposes to insert a new section amending an 1851 Act.  The effect of the amendment is to declare that a committal warrant issued by the District Court in Dublin can be addressed to the governor of a prison.  This is the position that has been taken to apply in Dublin for many years.</p> <p>On amendment No. 4, because the new section to the Bill will broaden the scope of the Bill as published, I have had to amend the Long Title.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#U00100"><p>I have a question on the issuing of warrants.  I presume this is in the context of committal to prison.  The Minister knows better than most that the prison population has been increasing.  Does she have an opinion on the imminent implementation of the law next month?  It will have implications for those who are, or could be, committed to prison for non-payment of fines, as happened in two high-profile cases last week involving two Members of the other House.  This appears to be a recurring problem.  The change in the law and the use of attachment orders should reduce the prison population, which means that those who should be in prison will be imprisoned.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#U00200"><p>That might be a little <i>ultra vires</i>, but the Minister may respond if she wishes.  It is Christmas time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.173" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#U00300"><p>On the subject of committal, I welcome the Minister's announcement last week that the legislation will be commenced in the new year, so we will no longer see people committed to prison for non-payment of fines.  Senator Mooney raises a pertinent issue.  There will probably be a reduction in the number of committals, one hopes, but perhaps not a reduction in the numbers incarcerated, given how short a period of time people tend to spend in prison when they are committed for non-payment of fines, as we saw last week.  Perhaps the Minister can comment on that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.174" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#U00400"><p>On that matter, I saw the figures and they are quite frightening.  Between 2008 and 2010, the number of people arrested for non-payment of fines increased from 2,500 to 6,500, even in that short timeframe.  In fact, over 50% of all arrests for committal to prison, where people are going into the prison system, are for non-payment of fines.  That will all stop, and rightly so.  It has been a huge waste of Garda time as well.  At least now we are setting up the proper structures to deal with this through attachment of earnings.  Hopefully, it will reduce the amount of Garda time spent on this matter, which is welcome.  It is a change that is long overdue.  I thank the Minister and the Department for the work they have done in that area.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#U00500"><p>I call on the Minister to respond to those pertinent and not-so-pertinent questions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1009" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#U00600"><p>The Bill before the House is a straightforward effort to deal with the case of Grant <i>v.</i>the Governor of Cloverhill Prison.  It is right to introduce this amendment to ensure that the arrangements are clear for Dublin and that it is permitted in the District Court rules.</p><p>Regarding the broader point that Members have made, the Government introduced legislation on the payment of fines, which was passed a couple of months ago.  Since it was passed, the courts have been working hard to ensure that they can implement it.  Some technology had to be implemented and other arrangements had to be put in place before the legislation could be implemented effectively by the courts.  That was important work.  It is completed now and the legislation will be implemented from 11 January next year.  It means that attachment orders can be made, and there is the new opportunity to pay fines by instalment.  Clearly, that should result in more efficient management where fines have been ordered to be paid.</p><p>If people still refuse to pay fines, the penalties are more severe in terms of both fines and jail sentences.  Those who insist that they will break the law and who do not use the various opportunities that will be provided through the implementation of the fines legislation from 11 January will face much more severe punishment.  I believe that is right.  If one breaks the law and does not pay what the law tells one to pay, and one is given every opportunity to pay it, ultimately there will be a severe penalty if one insists on breaking the law.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.177" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.178" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question, "That the Bill do now pass", put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.179" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 1.45 p.m. and resumed at 2 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.180" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#W00100">Finance (Tax Appeals) Bill 2015: Second Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.181" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That the Bill be now read a Second Time."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.182" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1106" speakername="Simon Harris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#W00300"><p>The purpose of this Bill is to provide for reforms of the role, functions and structure of the Office of the Appeal Commissioner and the tax appeals system.  The overall objective is to ensure an enhanced and cost-effective appeal mechanism for tax cases, while providing transparency and increased certainty for taxpayers.  The Appeal Commissioners are responsible for carrying out the statutory duties assigned to them under the Taxes Consolidation Act 1997 and related legislation, principally the hearing of appeals by taxpayers against decisions of the Revenue Commissioners concerning taxes and duties.  The commissioners hear appeals relating not only to income tax, but also to corporation tax, value added tax or VAT, capital gains tax, stamp duties, capital acquisitions tax, customs and excise duties, vehicle registration tax and local property tax.  Most appeals relate to the amount of an appellant's tax liability.</p><p>As is appropriate for an administrative tribunal, the Appeal Commissioners are independent in carrying out their functions.  I acknowledge the valuable role the commissioners play in the operation of a fair and efficient taxation system.  Mr. Ronan Kelly recently retired as an Appeal Commissioner, having served in that role for over 20 years.  I understand the term of the other commissioner of long standing, Mr. John O'Callaghan, will end in a few days.  On behalf of the Minister, Deputy Noonan, I thank both for their diligent service since the early 1990s.  I am pleased that, following an open competition conducted by the Public Appointments Service, Mr. Mark O'Mahony took up his post as Appeal Commissioner on 9 November last.  Ms Lorna Gallagher will commence as Appeal Commissioner in the next few days.  I look forward to both playing a central role in the reform of the appeals system and I wish both well in their work.</p><p>Our tax appeal system has been examined over the years and the following reports and tribunals have made recommendations about the Appeal Commissioners in that time: the steering group on the Revenue Commissioners; the D&aacute;il Committee of Public Accounts final report on the DIRT inquiry; the Revenue powers group report; the Law Reform Commission report on a fiscal prosecutor and a revenue court; and the Commission on Taxation report.  Proposals for changes to the appeals system have been made by stakeholders, including the professional representative bodies, such as the Irish Tax Institute and the accountancy bodies.</p><p>The Minister announced in budget 2014 his intention to instigate a reform of the appeal system for tax matters, including reform of the role, functions and structure of the Office of the Appeal Commissioner.  This Bill represents the culmination of a process that involved constructive dialogue with stakeholders on the oversight and operation of the tax appeals system towards a common objective of reform to enhance the system for all participants.</p><p>The reforms proposed will bring appeals through the initial stage in a more streamlined fashion, with enhanced case management procedures to facilitate a more efficient and structured flow of appeals.  The proposed reforms in the Bill will end the practice of appeals being made via the Revenue Commissioners and will involve a significant change to the process for appeals by way of the &quot;case stated&quot; procedure for the High Court, and the removal of the Circuit Court rehearing stage of the appeal process.  This issue was the subject of much debate in the other House and I expect it to be the subject of some debate in the Seanad.  The Minister remains convinced that, with the strengthening of the roles and procedures for the Tax Appeals Commission and given trends in relation to other expert administrative tribunals, retention of the Circuit Court stage of the appeals process would be anomalous.  Opportunities for redress also exist in certain circumstances by way of judicial review and appeal to the Court of Justice of the European Union.</p><p>In accordance with the agreed protocol for pre-legislative scrutiny by Oireachtas committees, the heads of Bill were sent to the Joint Committee on Finance, Public Expenditure and Reform, which issued its report on 16 April last.  Following consideration of the report of the joint committee and concerns expressed by stakeholders prior to and during the pre-legislative scrutiny process, the Minister decided to change the provisions in the heads of Bill regarding public hearings of tax appeal cases.  The heads had envisaged that hearings before the Appeal Commissioners, heretofore held privately or<i>in camera</i>, would in future he held in public session following enactment of the legislation.  While the default position will still be for public hearings, the Bill has been drafted to provide that where an appellant requests it, the hearing of his or her tax appeal will be held in private.  I consider that this provision will meet the concerns of the committee and stakeholders, although I appreciate that diverse views were expressed.  The committee considered that transparency, which had been one of the objectives of the original public hearings proposals, would be enhanced and clarity provided to taxpayers and the general public if all hearings were accompanied by written determinations, as is proposed.</p><p>The key elements of the Bill are as follows: the establishment and structure of the commission; the appointment and removal process for Appeal Commissioners; the terms and conditions of Appeal Commissioners; the provisions for staffing and funding of the commission and its accountability; a new Part 40A of the Taxes Consolidation Act 1997, providing for a wide range of amendments to the legislation governing appeals in regard to the various taxes under the care and management of the Revenue Commissioners; and a schedule of consequential amendments to the various tax and duty Acts arising from reform measures and from the effect of the new Part 40A.  The main thrust of the reform is to strengthen the independence, and the perceived independence, of the Appeal Commissioners.  The measures to achieve this contained in the Bill include appropriate selection and appointment provisions involving the Public Appointments Service, fixed-term appointments, a clear statutory statement of independence, new funding and staffing arrangements and the making of appeals directly to the Appeal Commissioners, and not Revenue, as currently happens.</p><p>The Bill is in five Parts and has two Schedules.  I will outline the provisions of Part 2 in some detail.  As the provisions of the subsequent sections are extensive and complex, I will give an overview of their essential components.  I am aware that Members of the Seanad may wish to address some specific issues on Committee and later Stages.</p><p>Part 1 is preliminary and general.  It contains standard provisions comprising the Short Title and commencement provisions, together with interpretations and definitions for the Bill.</p><p>Part 2 contains provisions relating to the establishment of the tax appeals commission, its membership and functions and the appointment, terms and conditions of the individual Appeal Commissioners and their staff.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Simon Harris:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=2338"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2338&amp;amp;pid=SimonHarris&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The more important of these provisions are described as follows.</p><p>Section 6 sets out the functions of the Appeal Commissioners with regard to the acceptance, refusal, adjudication and determination of appeals, the conduct of hearings, the provision and publication of determinations, the stating and signing of cases for the High Court and the establishment of efficient and effective systems and procedures for the processing of appeals.  The commissioners are required to conduct appeal proceedings in a way that is accessible and fair and as expeditious as possible.  The functions of the commissioners can be performed by any one of them acting individually, unless they have provided otherwise in their rules of procedure.</p><p>Section 8 deals with the appointment of Appeal Commissioners.  The Minister is required to have the Public Appointments Service assess and select candidates for appointment as commissioners and to recommend suitable candidates to the Minister.  The Minister is given powers to specify requirements with which candidates must comply, such as practical experience or academic qualifications.  The Minister is permitted to appoint a serving commissioner for a second term, without recourse to the Public Appointments Service, where the commissioner&rsquo;s first term of office has expired.  A commissioner is precluded from serving for more than two consecutive seven-year terms.</p><p>Section 9 provides for temporary commissioners in cases where the full-time commissioners have recused themselves.  In such cases, the Minister can appoint a Circuit Court judge as a temporary commissioner.  The Minister can also appoint a person as a temporary commissioner in non-recusal situations where circumstances require such an appointment, for example, in a situation where there has been a significant increase in appeals and a temporary commissioner is required to help deal with it.  Section 10 establishes the independence of the tax appeals commission and its Appeal Commissioners in the performance of their functions.  Section 13 provides that the term of office of Appeal Commissioners will be seven years, with scope for the Minister for Finance to reappoint a commissioner for a second and final seven-year term.  Section 17 provides for the Minister&rsquo;s powers to remove commissioners from office for stated reasons, subject to the Minister laying a statement before the D&aacute;il giving the reasons for any such removal.</p><p>Section 18 provides for the cessation of a commissioner&rsquo;s tenure where she or he is adjudicated a bankrupt, makes a composition or arrangement with creditors, is convicted of an offence or ceases to be ordinarily resident in the State.  The section also provides for the cessation of a commissioner&rsquo;s tenure on his or her nomination or election to various public offices such as the Oireachtas, a local authority or the European Parliament.  Section 19 provides for the funding of the commission to be as determined by the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform.  Section 20 provides that staff numbers of the tax appeals commission are to be determined by the Ministers for Finance and Public Expenditure and Reform.  Section 21 requires the Appeal Commissioners to submit annual reports to the Minister for Finance, who will lay them before the Houses of the Oireachtas.  These reports are to contain specified statistical information with regard to appeals where this is required by the Minister or by any enactment.  The commissioners also will be able to report to the Minister on other matters as they consider appropriate.  The Minister may require the commissioners to report on various matters but this is subject to the commissioners not being required to include information on matters that would prejudice the performance of their functions.</p><p>Part 3 provides for the treatment of existing appeals when the new appeal process comes into operation.  It contains provisions relating to the arrangements for transitioning from the old appeal process to the new model.  On the commencement date for the new appeal process, appeals already will have been made and will be at various stages of the old appeal process.  Many of the steps in the old appeal process will continue under the new process.  The general rule is that existing appeals will move on to the next stage in the process.  Thus, for example, appeals that have already been made to Revenue will be transferred to the Appeal Commissioners and the revised case stated procedure for appeals to the High Court will apply to Appeal Commissioners&rsquo; determinations made after the commencement date.  However, there are exceptions to this general rule, for example, a taxpayer whose appeal has been heard but not determined still will be entitled to a rehearing before a Circuit Court judge, should he or she lose the appeal.  There also are provisions to allow a different Appeal Commissioner to finalise an appeal in circumstances where the Appeal Commissioner who started the adjudication is unable to so do for reasons such as retirement.</p><p>Part 4 concerns the insertion into the Taxes Consolidation Act 1997 of a new Part 40A, which deals with appeals to the Appeal Commissioners.  Part 40A contains provisions relating to the entire appeal process and to the appeal commissioner's conduct and management of that process, commencing with the making of appeals and their acceptance or refusal, progressing to adjudication, hearing, determination and publication of determinations and finishing with appeals to the courts against determinations of Appeal Commissioners.  It facilitates a more active case management approach by the Appeal Commissioners.  In straightforward cases, they will not be required to hold a hearing but can adjudicate and determine the appeal based on paper submissions, subject to the agreement of the taxpayer to this approach.  The Appeal Commissioners will be able to dismiss appeals where the taxpayer does not co-operate with them by, for example, providing information such as accounts requested by the commissioners.  Responsibility for the preparation of a case stated for an appeal to the High Court, subject to a time limit, is being given to the Appeal Commissioners themselves instead of the parties to the appeal.  Increased transparency and certainty will result from the requirement that all Appeal Commissioners' determinations must be published.  Part 40A contains provisions relating to whether a hearing, or part of a hearing, is to be held in public or in private.  As I outlined already, the default position is that all hearings are to be held in public, subject to exceptions relating to, for example, issues involving public order or sensitive issues.  However, the Appeal Commissioners must hold a private hearing or a part-private hearing where an appellant submits a request for this.  As I indicated earlier, this represents a change from the original proposed provisions following the views expressed during pre-legislative scrutiny and by many stakeholders.</p><p>Part 5 contains amendments to 137 separate sections and Schedules in the Taxes Consolidation Act 1997.  A consequence of the changes being made to the appeal process is the need to make a large number of consequential amendments to provisions relating to appeals in the Taxes Consolidation Act 1997 and in various other taxation Acts contained in Schedule 2.  While there are a large number of individual amendments, given they are being made with regard to several different types of taxes and affect a wide range of provisions, most of them are of a similar nature.  For this reason, each individual amendment is not explained.  The most common amendment is that necessitated by the fact that under the reformed system, a taxpayer will be obliged to appeal directly to the Appeal Commissioners and not via Revenue, as currently happens.  Various cross-references that no longer are relevant are being removed such as, for example, references to Part 40 of the Taxes Consolidation Act 1997, which is being phased out and replaced with the new Part 40A.</p><p>Another type of amendment will clarify and make more explicit a right of appeal that is currently only implicitly stated in the various tax and duty Acts.  A valid appeal under the revised appeal process will require a specific right of appeal to be given in the relevant tax and duty Act.  The opportunity presented by the reform of the appeal process is being taken to rectify any anomalies and inconsistencies that currently exist and to standardise as far as possible the appeal provisions for the various taxes and duties.  One example of such standardisation relates to the number of days allowed for the making of an appeal.  While 30 days is the usual time limit, this has not been standard across all of the taxes and duties.  Another example is the alignment of the preconditions for the making of an appeal against different types of Revenue assessments such as, for example, the requirement to have submitted outstanding returns to Revenue and to have paid the part of the tax liability not in dispute before an appeal can be made.</p><p>The origins of the Appeal Commissioners date back to the Act of Excise 1662 and thus it is a body that predates the foundation of the State.  At present, the Minister for Finance appoints Appeal Commissioners pursuant to section 850 of the Taxes Consolidation Act 1997.  Effectively, the Minister has had discretion as to who was appointed and on what terms, subject only to laying details of the appointment before the Houses of the Oireachtas.  This Bill proposes to change this by requiring that appointments will be made by the Minister only following an open competition run by the Public Appointments Service.</p><p>The role of the Appeal Commissioners is to act as an independent administrative tribunal in adjudicating disputes between taxpayers and the Revenue Commissioners.  This Bill is designed to enhance the independence of the Appeal Commissioners, increase transparency and provide a more efficient appeal system in tax disputes to the benefit of compliant taxpayers and the Exchequer alike.  I commend this Bill to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.184" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#X00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for outlining the provisions of this Bill.  The single fact that will shock people is the Revenue Commissioners sometimes get things wrong.  In response to a question tabled by Fianna F&aacute;il's finance spokesperson in the D&aacute;il, Deputy Michael McGrath, it was revealed that in approximately 26% of cases, appeals were decided in favour of the taxpayer.  This demonstrates there is a requirement for an appeal mechanism.  Fianna F&aacute;il welcomes this Bill because it will update and modernise the appeal system.  The Minister of State has outlined from where this derives and it effectively dates back to the 17th century.  All Members seek to have this process modernised, particularly when one considers the delays in processing some appeals.  While there may be some valid reasons, more than 600 appeals have been pending for more than five years and 30 appeals have been pending for more than ten years.  Such figures and instances certainly means the system should be streamlined.  It will help greatly that decisions will be made within 90 days and will be published in public via the Internet.  I certainly welcome this because other potential appellants will be able to see on the public record how other appeals were heard and how they were found.  This then could lead to someone deciding whether to take an appeal in certain instances and this is to be welcomed.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Darragh O'Brien:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2178"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2178&amp;amp;pid=DarraghOBrien&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It was mentioned in the D&aacute;il, and I repeat it here, that removing the option to appeal to the Circuit Court is a concern, but it does not mean we will not support the Bill.  We will support the Bill, but the appeal issue should be looked at again.  By removing the option to appeal to the Circuit Court, the only appeal would be on a point of law.  Anyone going into court to argue a specific point of law knows that it remains on that item alone.  I am not sure why that appeal option has been removed and I cannot see the reason in the Minister of State's speech.  Perhaps he could address that specific issue in his response to the House and it may be possible to have this reviewed next year to see how it works.  I will not detain the House.  Fianna F&aacute;il supports the Bill but once it is in place, the historical appeals should be tracked and a review held into how the backlog is to be tackled.  It can then be established if the target of 90 days is being reached in which appeals are heard and decided on.</p><p>I welcome the Minister of State's comments that any future appointments would be made through the Public Appointments Service, PAS, an open process, and ratified by the Minister.  The positions will still be decided by the Minister but through the PAS, which is an important step forward.  The Circuit Court concern is the one point on which Fianna F&aacute;il would want further consideration.  We support the Bill, it is very welcome and it will make a difference to many people.  There are instances where over 25% of appeals have been found in favour of the taxpayer, which shows the importance of having an appeals system.  It is hoped this legislation will allow a more streamlined and efficient approach.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.186" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1160" speakername="Michael D'Arcy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#Y00200"><p>I welcome the Bill which has been a long time coming.  In 1662 Cromwell was not long gone from Wexford after he sacked it in 1649.  This Bill should have been brought forward much earlier.  The Revenue Commissioners are very good at their job, but as Senator O'Brien has said, on occasion they do get things wrong.  Over 25% of appeals were overturned by Revenue itself.  When people are appealing to an independent and objective office rather than going back to Revenue, perhaps the expectation is that even more cases may be overturned or more will be taken to appeal.  The 26% figure could be higher but we will never know because we do not know how many people would be more likely to take an appeal when they can go to an independent office.</p> <p>I welcome the matter of the appeals being made public but there are concerns around tax matters being private until they are concluded.  If Revenue finds that somebody has done something wrong, perhaps unintentionally, and there is a finding against somebody, penalties and charges apply.  However, in the number of appealed cases which were found to be correct, where the taxpayer is found to have done nothing wrong or where the case had gone against Revenue, I am sure some people would not like that information put out there.  It is a space we need to consider.  I understand there is an option for the appeal to be held in private.  I would appreciate it if the Minister of State could clarify this matter further.</p> <p>The target of 90 days in which to make findings on appeals is welcome.  A person may have a bill from Revenue and the clock is ticking.  If the matter is dealt with within 90 days, whether it is in favour or against, at least the clock is no longer ticking and the person has their determination of what is due or not.</p> <p>I welcome the transparency around the appointment of people to these important commissions, now and in the future, via the Public Appointments Service.  The way things were done, where a person got a job because they were a friend of or knew someone, was not good practice  That is old hat from an older era that no longer has a place in society.  I am broadly supportive of this proposal.  I was a bit surprised to see the Act went back to 1662.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.187" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" speakername="Feargal Quinn" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#Y00300"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House.  I welcome the Bill and I hope it means that customers, that is, citizens, will benefit from a more transparent and efficient tax system.  However, there are a few issues, one of which was raised by Senator O'Brien.  The removal of the right to appeal to the Circuit Court is one of the more contentious parts of the legislation.  For instance, sections 35, 36 and 38 delete references in the 1997 Act where a party can make an appeal to the Circuit Court.  Unfortunately, amendments in the D&aacute;il on Committee Stage to reintroduce the possibility of appeals to the Circuit Court were not accepted.  These amendments also included a proposal to allow a party who wanted to appeal to the Circuit Court regarding a determination by the new tax appeals commission.  The references to the Circuit Court should be retained to give people another option for redress.  The Circuit Court would also give people a viable and reasonable option for appeal if they were not satisfied.  The appeal to the Circuit Court would not always happen but it is a safeguard in place if a person is not happy with a determination of the appeals commission.  The massive costs associated with going to the High Court mean that it is not a reasonable option for many people.  It must be remembered that people have to appeal on a point of law rather on their own case <i>per se</i>.  If the legislation is passed as it stands, it will simply stop many people from appealing and I hope that is not the intention of the legislation.  It am sure it is not the intention but it may be the end result.</p><p>There is much concern about removing the possibility of the Circuit Court even getting involved in these matters.  This is not about clogging up the courts system but about retaining checks and balances.  It is about allowing the largest number of people to access redress, which is something the Circuit Court could provide given that the High Court is not a practical option.  We know that cases can be very complex and having the Circuit Court as a backup is very worthwhile.  One of the members of the Select Sub-Committee on Finance, Deputy Pearse Doherty, said &quot;This is one of the areas in which there was no division among committee members on the question that the right of appeal to the Circuit Court should be maintained&quot;.  The Government should take that opinion on board.  If having the reference to the Circuit Court in the legislation helps just 1% of cases, then it is worth reinstating it into the legislation.  I would support this and would appreciate a response from the Minister of State on these concerns.</p><p>The Bill provides for the online publication of determinations.  Is it envisaged that customers would in future lodge their appeals online?  Section 949C, inserted by section 34 of the Bill, covers appeals to the appeals commission via electronic means.  Subsection (3) says, &quot;The Revenue Commissioners and the Appeal Commissioners may each, in their discretion, put arrangements in place for, or approve, the use of electronic means for any purpose of this section.&quot;  I do not think it is good enough in this day and age to leave it to the discretion of Revenue and the appeals commission if they want to introduce an online appeals system.  Will the Minster of State consider amending this section to compel Revenue and the appeals commission to introduce an online appeals system within one year on the Bill coming into force?  I believe that is what the customer and citizen wants.  Substantial work has been done on the Bill and yet this very obvious target has been deliberately left ambiguous.  An amendment should be included in the legislation to provide for the introduction of a set date by which the appeals commission would implement an online appeals system.  It is a vital aspect if the Government is serious about providing an improved tax appeals system.  Is there a target date for responses to the customer? Our current system is overloaded and I would like to see a response time being set in order that the efficiency of the current system could be improved.  Perhaps the Minister of State could comment on these areas.</p><p>The Bill is about improving the overall tax system in the State and a good effort has been made, but it could be argued that we had a setback in the past year.  In its <i>Doing Business 2016</i>, the World Bank reported on Ireland's system.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Feargal Quinn:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=1972"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1972&amp;amp;pid=FergalQuinn&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It states, "Ireland made paying taxes more costly and complicated for companies by increasing landfill levies and by requiring additional financial statements to be submitted with the income tax return."  This report, which is one of the most important in comparing conditions for doing business worldwide, indicates that we are imposing more red tape on business.  Will the Minister of State address this concern, particularly in respect of the increased paperwork imposed on companies in the past year as a result of the requirement to provide additional financial statements with their income tax returns?</p><p>On vehicle registration tax, section 2 outlines the various taxes the new system will cover, including income tax and the local property tax.  It states the Act will also cover, "any instrument made thereunder and any instrument that is made under any other enactment and which relates to tax", including in respect of stamp duties and of duties related to Customs and Excise.  Will the Minister of State confirm that the legislation will cover vehicle registration tax, VRT, which is one of the most contentious taxes?  When people import a car the rate of vehicle registration tax is determined based on the so-called open market selling price.  Revenue purportedly arrives at a figure by comparing similar models of vehicles.  However, this method is highly unscientific when the model is rare or obscure.  While this may not affect a large number of vehicles, these types of cases certainly arise and the system has caused much public satisfaction.  In the interests of customers, it would be useful if the open market selling price arrived at by Revenue could be appealed.  </p><p>These are only some of my thoughts on the Bill.  I am particularly concerned that Ireland has slipped back from 17th to 23rd place in the rankings of the best places to do business, especially as the Taoiseach's objective is to make the country the best small country in which to do business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.189" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#Z00200"><p>I broadly welcome the Finance (Tax Appeals) Bill 2015.  As a member of the Joint Committee on Finance, Public Expenditure and Reform, I was involved in the pre-legislative scrutiny of the legislation.  I am pleased, therefore, that a number of the issues about which members of the joint committee raised concerns have been addressed in the drafting of the Bill.  The pre-legislative scrutiny process has proved a useful way of evaluating a proposed change to the tax code that is perhaps more fundamental than people realise.</p> <p>I have been struck by a number of issues and it may be useful to place them on record.  The joint committee met one of the Appeals Commissioners.  Members were struck by how effective the current appeals process is and the incredible work that is done by a team of four people, consisting of two Appeals Commissioners and two members of staff.  I understand the annual cost of the Office of the Appeals Commissioners is &euro;447,000 per annum.  The service the office provides to the general public is highly successful.  </p> <p>One of the issues that arises in the context of the legislation is transparency in the tax code.  In an international context, transparency is highly desirable, particular for those who want to do business here, as they will seek clarity and transparency around the tax code.  No one disputes the need for transparency.  One of the proposed changes was to have all appeals heard in public.  A number of stakeholders and members of the joint committee raised concerns about this proposal.  The first of these was that Ireland is a small country.  While a number of members indicated we should align the system with those in place in larger countries such as the United States and Canada, a number of other stakeholders pointed out that in a country with such a small population - there are only approximately 5 million people on the island as a whole - having all appeals against Revenue decisions heard in public would have a negative effect in terms of achieving the desired outcome of bringing about the level of engagement that people should have with the tax system and the transparency desired.  I am pleased this concern has been addressed in the Bill.  I understand the Revenue Commissioners agreed that public hearings could act as a disincentive to people considering lodging an appeal against a Revenue decision.  The provision that private information related to the family should not be brought into the public domain solely on the basis that a person wants to appeal a decision of the Revenue Commissioners is a positive step.  </p> <p>The fundamental change the Bill makes is that all appeals will be held in public, except where a person requires that an appeal be held in private.  Under the current system, all appeals are heard in private.  One of the criticisms made of the current position was the lack of transparency arising from the failure to report decisions, in other words, the failure to record them on the website of the Office of the Appeals Commissioners.  From memory, the Appeals Commissioners responded to this criticism by pointing out that the service has four staff with which to deal with 400 cases per annum.  They indicated that they could place all the necessary information on any website if they had more resources.  It is important to bear this in mind when we decide to throw the baby out with the bath water.  Sometimes we need to be conscious that systems may work more effectively without the introduction of fundamental changes.</p> <p>I am disappointed that one or two of the recommendations made by the joint committee have not taken on board.  The first of these was the recommendation not to remove the role of the Circuit Court as a court of appeal.  This recommendation should be noted for the record.  I understand one of the reasons it was not accepted was that, as the law stands, the Revenue Commissioners cannot appeal certain cases.  I believe they can only appeal cases involving capital gains tax to the Circuit Court and cannot appeal under any other circumstances.</p> <p>I wonder why the Bill does not simply allow the Revenue Commissioners the right to appeal to the Circuit Court.  I am conscious that a number of the stakeholders were aware that having to go to the High Court in a case stated is a much more expensive procedure than taking an appeal to the Circuit Court.  On the other hand, I accept that introducing an appeal to the Circuit Court delays the process and makes it less speedy and perhaps less effective because, as was made clear by the Appeals Commissioners, the level of detail required to hear some of these complicated tax cases requires extensive knowledge of the tax code, which is not necessarily available at Circuit Court level.  I found this argument persuasive. </p> <p>A number of the improvements made also remove the necessity to go to the Circuit Court.  One relates to the fact that decisions can effectively be heard at a pre-hearing stage.  The Bill introduces - if not in fact, then certainly in practice - a pre-hearing stage to the Appeals Commission phase of the process.  This is a positive development.  On balance, while the joint committee recommended that the Circuit Court stage of a tax appeal be retained, I am not persuaded that it was completely correct in that respect.  Having read the legislation in more detail, I do not believe the Bill would have been improved by retaining the role of the Circuit Court.  </p> <p>As I am under time pressure, I will raise other matters on Committee Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.190" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#Z00300"><p>All Stages are being taken today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.191" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#Z00400"><p>I am aware of that.  The engagement between all stakeholders was good and demonstrated the positive impact of pre-legislative scrutiny.  This process could be useful in many more areas of legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.192" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1155" speakername="Kathryn Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#Z00500"><p>I will briefly pick up on Senator Hayden's concluding point in which she welcomed the pre-legislative scrutiny process.  Scrutiny of all aspects of public policy is needed and we should engage in the process to the best of our abilities.  I welcome the Bill, which Sinn F&eacute;in will support.</p> <p>While many members of the public will not be familiar with the work of the Appeals Commissioners, it is an important office.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Kathryn Reilly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2355"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2355&amp;amp;pid=KathrynReilly&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->My party's approach to this Bill, as during pre-legislative scrutiny, is to ensure transparency and fairness in the appeals system open to citizens when dealing with their tax affairs.  After much debate, my party still believes that this Bill should be improved in two ways, one of which was mentioned here earlier.</p><p>The first issue is the removal of private hearings in the appeals process.  It has been mentioned here a good deal.  I am aware that during the pre-legislative scrutiny process many stakeholders expressed views on that and that, in itself, brought about the changes in relation to the hearings.  We are told that as a rule, hearings will be in public but the reality is that by giving an opt-out few, if any, will opt for a public hearing.  This could be seen as a step backwards and a climbdown on one of the core issues of this reform.  My party has tabled amendments on this issue but I will speak to it here this afternoon, and I know the Minister of State will come back to it.</p><p>All hearings will be accompanied by written determinations but I do not know whether this, in itself, will be sufficient.  It is a good Bill but this issue might be seen as a weakness.  It is often said that not only must justice be done; it must also be seen to be done.  Senator Hayden reflected on some of the concerns on this during pre-legislative scrutiny.  I was not a member of the committee involved and some of these issues were new to me.  It would be good to hear in the House the Minister of State reflect on the debate that occurred during pre-legislative scrutiny and why the Department agreed to change the draft heads of the Bill.</p><p>The second key issue my party would have relates back to what other Senators were talking about, namely, the removal of the right of appeal to the Circuit Court.  The Government is sticking to its guns here on this issue and going against the members of the committee who sought that the right of appeal to the Circuit Court be maintained.  Like other Senators, I would ask the Minister to reconsider this.</p><p>There is a pattern to remove the right of access to the Circuit Court for citizens.  We have seen this in the Customs Act 2015 which was recently passed and in the Financial Services Ombudsman process.  The idea that persons abuse the appeal system would not stand up to scrutiny.  The Minister will say this is the way it is for other State bodies, but that does not make it right and that is not the issue before us.  The question has to be whether we want citizens to be able to have their day in court or whether it is to be made more difficult and only available in certain circumstances.  For example, I note Senator Quinn mentioned the issue of only being able to appeal on a point of law.  That is an important consideration.</p><p>There is a lot to be welcomed in this legislation.  A more transparent system with decisions recorded systematically for the first time is a positive move.  The idea of a record of decision to provide guidance is clearly sensible.</p><p>As I stated, my party will support this Bill.  We have tabled some amendments.  However, I think the issues have been thrashed out on Second Stage.  As I stated, I would like it if the Minister of State could respond to the issues about the pre-legislative scrutiny and the issue of the public versus private hearings.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.194" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1106" speakername="Simon Harris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#AA00200"><p>I sincerely thank the Senators who contributed to this debate and, indeed, for the broad welcome that all Senators have given to this reforming legislation.</p><p>The reform of the tax appeal system will bring positive reform of the role, the functions and the structure of the Office of the Appeals Commissioner and of the tax appeals system.  It will serve a dual function: first, in providing transparency and increased certainty for taxpayers; and, second, bringing about an enhanced and cost-effective appeal mechanism for taxpayers and for the Exchequer.  It is timely to proceed with this reform process which will see appeals being brought through the initial stages in a more streamlined fashion with enhanced case management procedures to facilitate a more efficient and structured flow of appeals.</p><p>In my opening speech, I have already gone through the improvements and the various sections of the Bill and in the time available to me, I will focus on the two issues of concern that have been raised during Second Stage, on which there are Committee Stage amendments from Senator Reilly.</p><p>In relation to the hearings in public, I share the view that the pre-legislative scrutiny stage was valid and helpful in teasing out and discussing a number of issues and hearing from stakeholders.  The Senator is correct that the Minister, Deputy Noonan, when he originally published this Bill, envisaged a situation whereby all appeals would be in public.  However, there were, I will accept, diverse but strong views at the committee on the unintended negative consequences this could have.  Senators Hayden and Michael D'Arcy articulated them.  This is a small country.  We do not want to have an appeals system that would in any way discourage persons from their right of appealing a decision of the Revenue Commissioners and while the default position in the legislation will be for public hearings, on application by an appellant for a hearing or part of a hearing to be held in private, that will be granted.  That is the balance the Minister is trying to achieve in this legislation.  He believes and I believe that this will meet the concerns of stakeholders, particularly as voiced by a number of Members of the Houses at pre-legislative stage on behalf of small business people.  For example, small shopkeepers could find themselves in a public hearing with their customers in attendance, with material from the hearing being reported locally, and such publicity could undermine their business even if the appeal was upheld.  It is a balance we are trying to achieve here.  The publication of determinations will be valid and important in terms of increased transparency.</p><p>In relation to the issue of the Circuit Court, I refer Senators to a Supreme Court judgment in 1997 in the case Henry Denny and Sons (Ireland) Limited <i>v</i>. the Minister for Social Welfare.  It is a particularly relevant quote which I wish to put on the record of the House.  It states:</p><blockquote>I believe it would be desirable to take this opportunity of expressing the view that the courts should be slow to interfere with the decisions of expert administrative tribunals.  Where conclusions are based upon an identifiable error of law or an unsustainable finding of fact by a tribunal such conclusions must be corrected.  Otherwise, it should be recognised that tribunals which have been given statutory tasks to perform and exercise their functions, as is now usually the case, with a high degree of expertise and provide coherent and balanced judgments on the evidence and arguments heard by them it should not be necessary for the courts to review their decisions by way of appeal or judicial review.</blockquote> <p>This is a message from the courts, one might argue, to the Oireachtas about the role of expert administrative tribunals.  What we are trying to do in this legislation is further ensure that taxpayers, when they take an appeal, have an opportunity to appeal to an independent expert administrative tribunal that will have a level of expertise, with no disrespect to the courts, that the Circuit Court itself would not profess to necessarily have in tax matters.</p><p>I take the point that Senator Hayden raised in relation to cost and the cost of a High Court hearing obviously being more than the cost of a Circuit Court hearing.  While some of the costs that I have heard bandied about in other parts of this debate are not quite accurate, I appreciate that the high cost may be a barrier to participation but it must be pointed out that even if we were to retain the Circuit Court stage, it would remain open to the Revenue Commissioners to appeal the Circuit Court stage, if they lost, to the High Court, and the idea that the taxpayer may not find himself or herself in the High Court does not really stand up to scrutiny in that regard as well.</p><p>The intention of this Bill is to produce reforms which will ensure a more robust, transparent and streamlined tax appeal procedure.  In my view, a route of appeal from the reformed Appeal Commissioners stage to the Circuit Court does not make sense and it is not one that the Minister could stand over.  The Appeal Commissioners are the specialist expert tax tribunal and the Minister is determined that this status be acknowledged and, where possible, even strengthened.</p><p>Furthermore, the current tax appeals process is out of step with the procedures of other expert appellant tribunals.  Some examples of decisions made by public bodies that can be appealed only by way of an appeal to the High Court on points of law are decisions made by An Bord Plean&aacute;la, the Financial Services Ombudsman, the Information Commissioner, the Irish Financial Services Appeals Tribunal, the Labour Court, the Refugee Appeals Tribunal, the Rent Tribunal, the Social Welfare Appeals Office, the Tenancy Tribunal of the Private Residential Tenancies Board, the Valuation Tribunal in respect of commercial rates and the Workplace Relations Commission, WRC, where unfair dismissal cases were appealable from the Employment Appeals Tribunal to the Circuit Court but this, too, has now ceased following the WRC's recent establishment.  The Houses have considered these issues on many occasions and, I would contend, have favoured establishing the expert independent administrative route to a tribunal rather than the Circuit Court route.  I hope I am explaining, even though we may not fully agree on this, the rationale behind our thinking in that regard.</p><p>In the interests of absolute clarity, I need to point out that the 90 days that have been referred to throughout this Bill is not a target for processing an appeal.  The 90-day time limit is for the publication of the determination after the Appeal Commissioner has made the determination.  There is no time limit for processing appeals because each case will be different and the Appeal Commissioners have to be given the space to deal with issues based on the complexity.</p><p>On the point Senator Quinn made, I will certainly read that report.  The Senator is correct that as we move into a recovering economy it is important that we keep our relentless pursuit of making this a good country in which to do business.  I will certainly consider those recommendations and discuss them with colleagues.</p><p>The new commission will develop electronic case management systems.  There may in time be greater facilities for dealing with claims online.  It is certainly something I would like to see.  In the interests of clarity, there is no specific requirement in the Bill to migrate all processes to electronic systems.</p><p>I am pleased with the broad welcome for the Bill by Senators.  I thank the Senators who were involved in the pre-legislative stage and the officials from the Department of Finance and Revenue who have worked so hard on this legislation.  I hope I have provided some clarity on the points of concern.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.195" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.196" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#BB00400">Finance (Tax Appeals) Bill 2015: Committee and Remaining Stages</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.197" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sections 1 to 33, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.198" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>SECTION 34</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.199" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#BB00700"><p>Amendments Nos. 1 and 2 are related and may be discussed together by agreement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.200" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1155" speakername="Kathryn Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#BB00800"><p>I do not intend to move the amendments at this point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.201" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendments Nos. 1 and 2 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.202" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#BB01000"><p>Amendments Nos. 3 to 9, inclusive, are related and may be discussed together by agreement.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.203" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1155" speakername="Kathryn Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#BB01050"><p>I do not intend to move the amendments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.204" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendments Nos. 3 to 9, inclusive, not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.205" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Section 34 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.206" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sections 35 to 42, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.207" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Schedules 1 and 2 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.208" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Title agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.209" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Bill reported without amendment, received for final consideration and passed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.210" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 2.25 p.m. and resumed at 3.15 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.211" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#DD00100">Houses of the Oireachtas Commission (Amendment) Bill 2015: Second Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.212" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That the Bill be now read a Second Time."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.213" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#DD00300"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Harris, to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.214" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1106" speakername="Simon Harris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#DD00400"><p>I am pleased to present the Houses of the Oireachtas Commission (Amendment) Bill 2015 to the House.  The Bill passed all stages in the D&aacute;il last Friday.  The Houses of the Oireachtas Commission came into existence on 1 January 2004 under the Houses of the Oireachtas Commission Act 2003.  The founding of the commission through legislation passed in 2003 had two consequences: the commission became the sanctioning authority for expenditure and for deciding on staff numbers up to the grade of principal officer 2, and for the provision of services and related matters to the Oireachtas, which authority formerly rested with the Department of Finance; and the system for the allocation of budgets to the Oireachtas changed from the annual civil service Estimates procedure to a different process involving a three-year budget drawn from the Central Fund.  The new budget is set every three years following negotiations with the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform, formerly the Department of Finance, and is approved at political level by the commission, and the amending legislation is passed by both Houses.</p> <p>Under the terms of the inaugural commission Act, a three-year budget, covering the period 2004 to 2006, was provided for the commission.  Further Acts were enacted in 2006, 2009 and 2012.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Simon Harris:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=2338"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2338&amp;amp;pid=SimonHarris&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->In addition, legislation was enacted in 2013 to give the commission responsibility for the translation into Irish of statutory instruments and the publication and periodic review of An Caighde&aacute;n Oifigi&uacute;il.  Senators will recall the recently passed Houses of the Oireachtas (Appointments to Certain Offices) Act 2015, under which the method of appointing the Clerks and Clerk Assistants of the D&aacute;il and the Seanad was revised.  They will also be aware of the recent announcement of an open competition for appointment to the post of Clerk of the D&aacute;il and Secretary General of the Houses of the Oireachtas Service.<br/><br/>The Houses of the Oireachtas Commission (Amendment) Bill 2015 is now required as the financing provided under the 2012 Act expires on 31 December next.  The Houses of the Oireachtas Commission is an independent body.  It is, in effect, the governing body which oversees the provision of services to the Houses and their Members by the Houses of the Oireachtas Service in accordance with the Houses of the Oireachtas Commission Acts.  The primary functions of the Houses of the Oireachtas Commission are to provide for the running of the Houses of the Oireachtas, to act as governing body of the service, to consider and determine policy in respect of the service and to oversee the implementation of that policy by the Secretary General.  The commission is composed of 11 members under the chairmanship of the Ceann Comhairle.  The Cathaoirleach of the Seanad is an <i>ex officio</i>member, as is the Secretary General.  There are also seven ordinary members, four of whom are appointed by the D&aacute;il and three of whom are appointed by the Seanad, and one member appointed by the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform.  The Minister&rsquo;s representative must also be a Member of either House.<br/><br/>The Houses of the Oireachtas Commission has no role in regulating the business of the Houses, which is a matter for the Committee on Procedures and Privileges of each House.  The commission is not responsible for the management and day-to-day operations of the Houses.  The Secretary General has overall responsibility for these functions in accordance with the Houses of the Oireachtas Commission Acts.  The commission does not set the level of remuneration payable to members of the Houses.  Salaries, pensions and allowances are determined by the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform.  The commission is accountable to the Parliament.  It presents annual reports on its work to both Houses together with estimates and accounts of its expenditure.  The Houses of the Oireachtas Service is the public service body that administers the Houses of the Oireachtas on behalf of the commission as the governing authority.  The functions of the service are set out in legislation.  They can be broadly summarised as the provision of professional advice and support services to the commission, the Houses and their committees and the Members of both Houses.<br/><br/>The primary purpose of this Bill is to make available the funding for the Houses of the Oireachtas commission for the coming three-year period.  The Bill proposes to make available to the commission a sum not exceeding &euro;369 million to carry out its functions for the three-year period from 1 January 2016 to 31 December 2018.  This sum has been agreed between the commission and the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform.  It takes account of foreseen expenditure over the three-year period.  The figure of &euro;369 million over three years comprises &euro;131 million in 2016, &euro;120 million in 2017 and &euro;118 million in 2018.  The &euro;131 million figure for next year represents an increase of &euro;19 million over the expected outturn of &euro;112 million for this year.  The bulk of the increase - over &euro;14 million &ndash; relates to the forthcoming general election and covers payments in respect of termination allowances and pensions for former Members and secretarial assistants.  The remainder of the increase - just under &euro;5 million - relates to: the increase in staffing levels that is required to support enhanced security arrangements, as recommended by An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na; the Oireachtas television channel, which now runs 24 hours a day, seven days a week; enhanced ICT services; D&aacute;il reform measures, such as longer sitting hours, increased budget scrutiny and pre-legislative scrutiny; the much-needed updating of the various forms of technological equipment in operation in both Houses of the Oireachtas, including the electronic voting, sound technology, voting panel and broadcasting systems; and an increase in the provision of legal services arising from legal cases being taken against committees of the Houses.<br/><br/>In summary, the extra expenditure projected for 2016 over 2015 is either a direct consequence of the forthcoming general election or emanates from demands to meet unavoidable security, technological and legal cost pressures on the commission.  The Estimates for 2017 and 2018 show a decrease from the 2016 levels, due primarily to a reduction in general election-related costs.  While the funding issue is the primary purpose of the Bill before the House, as I have said, this opportunity is being taken to make a number of amendments of a more technical nature.  I would like to give Senators details of some of the amendments in question.  First, under section 8 of the Ethics in Public Office Act 1995, as amended, the initial assessment and transmission of complaints from the public against Members of the Houses can only be undertaken by the Clerk of the relevant House.  This creates an impediment to the processing of such complaints when the relevant Clerk post is vacant.  The proposed section 8 in the Bill before us allows the relevant Clerk Assistant explicitly to exercise the necessary powers.<br/><br/>Second, with regard to section 2 of the Bill, which deals with copyright, Oireachtas copyright was vested by section 195 of the Copyright and Related Rights Act 2000 in each House.  This provision was enacted before the Houses of the Oireachtas Commission was established.  The right of the commission to exercise such powers on behalf of the relevant House, together with the power to delegate the exercise to the Secretary General, is being made explicit in this Bill.<br/><br/>Third, with regard to paragraphs (b) and (c) of section 6, the Oireachtas wishes in the interests of administrative convenience to have an enabling provision included in the Bill to allow the secretarial assistants of Members who are elevated to posts at Minister or Minister of State level to continue to remain under the scheme for secretarial assistance, rather than being seconded to Government Departments as is currently the case.  In addition, these costs will be borne by the commission, rather than being spread over the Votes of the relevant Departments or offices as they are at present.  Currently, the commission bears the cost of secretarial assistance for non&ndash;office-holding Members under Schedule 1 to the Houses of the Oireachtas Commission Act 2003.  The amendment being proposed here would extend that arrangement to secretarial assistance for all Members.<br/><br/>Fourth, I draw the attention of Deputies to amendments being provided for in sections 2, 5 and 6(a) in connection with the substitution of the term &quot;grant&quot; for &quot;grant-in-aid&quot; in section 4 of the 2003 Act and Schedule 1 to that Act.  This follows a change in Government accounting procedures that was instigated by the Public Expenditure and Reform, whereby arrangements under which bodies and funds, etc., were allowed through grants-in-aid to retain unspent moneys at the end of the year have been superseded by grants systems in the interests of expenditure control.  The term &quot;grant-in-aid&quot; is no longer in use and, therefore, references to it in individual sections of the Houses of the Oireachtas Commission Acts and the Schedules thereto need to be amended.  Fifth, section 4 corrects a typographical error in the 2003 Act and section 7 of the Bill is a cross-referencing update to Schedule 2 to the principal Act concerning the treatment of the commission's receipts in its accounts.  Sixth, section 9 provides for the repeal of provisions in the 2003 Act which have been made redundant by the repeal of the Freedom of Information Acts 1997 and 2003 and their replacement by the Freedom of Information Act 2014, the repeal of the Civil Service Commissioners Act 1956 and certain amendments effected by the Civil Service Regulation (Amendment) Act 2005.  I commend the Bill to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.216" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#EE00200"><p>We support the Bill.  One thing that was missing from the Minister of State's speech was a reference to the performance of the Houses of the Oireachtas Commission in recent years.  I understand that as a result of the savings which have been provided for, there has been a year-on-year reduction in costs other than those associated with the banking inquiry or general elections.  That is a testament to the efforts of the Ceann Comhairle and the members of the Houses of the Oireachtas Commission, of which I am one.  I think Senator Bradford is a former member of the commission.  Frankly, the multi-annual approach that is taken to funding the Houses of the Oireachtas is one that should be replicated across all Departments.  The Department of Health would certainly benefit from such an approach if it were possible, as would HSE executives such as Tony O'Brien, about whose day-to-day work many of us are critical.  The lack of multi-annual budgeting in other Departments impedes the ability of organisations to correctly plan or identify savings over periods of two to three years.  I think we would benefit from an Oireachtas perspective if they were in a position to plan in that way.</p> <p>I would like to make a point about the issue of legal defences, which came up recently.  As a member of both the Houses of the Oireachtas Commission and the banking inquiry - I am not publicly discussing any of the evidence the inquiry is considering - I am aware that the issue of the members of the inquiry signing off on the report if there were any legal challenges against us has arisen.  It has been suggested that, theoretically, we could be on our own.  If there is a challenge, presumably it will be a matter for the next commission, which will be put in place in six or eight months' time after the general election has taken place, to determine whether it is a defendable challenge.</p> <p>I am aware, from my experience as a member of the banking inquiry and of the Houses of the Oireachtas Commission, that from time to time the Houses of the Oireachtas Service consults Members of the Oireachtas on what they feel is best but on other occasions it does not consult Members and instead does what it feels is best.  I will give an example.  Those of us who worked on the banking inquiry for 23 months or thereabouts were told that we could make a decision but that we could be on our own thereafter.  At the same time, funds from the Oireachtas pool were presumably used in preparation for a review of an allegation made under the Protected Disclosures Act 2014 by a confidential informant.  That review, which was carried out and paid for independently, in effect vilified the confidential informant without carrying out any level of investigation that would be required in terms of interviewing key witnesses or considering material that would have a material relationship with the allegations being made.  I would be happy to say that publicly and not just under privilege.  I am sure that legal review was paid for.  I doubt very much that it was run through the Houses of the Oireachtas Commission.  I did not attend all of the meetings of the commission at that time because of my banking inquiry obligations.</p> <p>Although Members of the Oireachtas in their elected roles on committees should be driving the bus, it seems at times that officials are doing so.  I suggest that decisions must be made by elected Members from all parties and none, regardless of who they are and what committees they have chairmanship or membership of, rather than being signed off by them retrospectively as in the instance I have cited.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Marc MacSharry:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2010"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2010&amp;amp;pid=MarcMacSharry&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The members of the banking inquiry were wished the best of luck and told they had done great work and could be on their own.  By contrast, the whistleblower who had come forward with concerns about that process was in a position to be vilified in a quasi-independent review by an external senior counsel who, presumably had to be paid taxpayers' euro, without what I would see as a reasonable investigation.  That said, it is a broader issue that Oireachtas committees, the Houses of the Oireachtas Commission and elected bodies under the auspices of the Houses of the Oireachtas - the people's representatives as elected - must be the ones in control.  There are the civil servants, directors general and public servants who work so hard and on whom we depend so much for their expertise and advice, but the people driving the bus must be the elected representatives, not unelected people.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.218" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#FF00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State back to the House.  He has been a regular visitor this afternoon.  The Bill's main purpose is to deal with the funding of the Oireachtas for a number of years.  I note that there is a &euro;14 million increase connected to the forthcoming general election.  I also note from the Minister of State's speech that much of this will cover termination allowances.  I hope that not all the Members here will be availing of them and that we will be back here again after the next Seanad election.</p> <p>There are a number of other sections dealing with other technical amendments which are necessary and which the Minister of State has outlined.  I have no problem in commending the Bill to the House and complimenting the members of the commission who did Trojan work over the last five years.  I thank them for their efforts and wish them every success for the future.  The commission seems to have been working quite well since it was set up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.219" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1205" speakername="Paul Bradford" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#FF00300"><p>I welcome the Minister of State and support the legislation.  As Senator MacSharry said, I was previously a member of the second commission, I think.  I enjoyed my membership and got a very good insight into the workings of all those associated with it.  It is commendable that we have this three-year budget model.  It allows for review and overview.  It could be reflected upon by all Departments.  It gives us a greater long-term view of expenditure coming down the line, of future plans and developments and how to fund same.</p> <p>The increase being sought today is quite modest yet it has hit the media and the news in a typically negative fashion in respect of money being set aside, not just for Members of the Oireachtas but for members of staff who, as a result of the electorate's decision in D&aacute;il and Seanad elections, will lose their seats or their jobs.  The fact that we are setting aside a sum of money to provide for same should not be an extraordinary moment in Irish politics.  One would hope in today's world of advanced labour relations that most people who lose their jobs would be entitled to some degree of allowance, compensation, redundancy or pension on the way out.  What applies now to Oireachtas Members is radically different from what applied to them five, six or seven years ago.  It is fair and balanced.  The Bill is brief and I have no suggested amendments.</p> <p>In respect of the overall presentation of Houses of the Oireachtas Commission business, the dedicated Oireachtas channel notwithstanding, from a public relations perspective we have a long, long way to go in providing a complete view of the work and worth of the Oireachtas and responding to some of the - to put it mildly - erroneous, sometimes deliberately created hysteria which applies.  If the Minister of State had been here this morning he would have heard Senator Norris refer to media reports yesterday or the day before about completely manufactured so-called goings on in the D&aacute;il bar.  Some journalists present an entirely false view of facts but for many readers, that view becomes reality.  It gives politics, politicians and the whole system of democracy a bad name.  We need to be much more responsive to that.</p> <p>We occasionally see a letter written on behalf of the Oireachtas to a national daily newspaper or two but it is not really sufficient.  The damage has already been done and the public mindset changed.  The commission, our staff and the staff serving as public relations officers for the Houses will certainly have to be much more responsive.  They are not responding on behalf of individual Members; I think they are responding on behalf of the Oireachtas itself and of the democratic process and procedure in the State.  If I was to be slightly negative I would say we have more work to do in that regard.</p> <p>I welcome the Bill and the three-year budget.  The figures are the cost of democracy and, in the overall scale of Government expenditure, not over 12 months but over three years, the provision and maintenance of democracy, democratic Houses and open, transparent government is value for taxpayers' money.  I am happy to support the Minister of State in respect of this Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.220" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Moloney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#FF00400"><p>I welcome the Minister of State and support the Bill.  It is very brief.  If the Cathaoirleach will pardon the pun, it is getting our Houses in order here and gathering up a few ends.  I have not sat on the commission but compliment it, as Senator MacSharry did, as it has achieved an overall reduction over the years.  Of course it will go up in line with a general election when the redundancy payments will be paid out to people.</p> <p>As Senator Bradford said, a lot of our staff beaver away in the background.  They work late nights at the drop of a hat.  We could be sitting until 11 p.m. and the staff and the clerks here are sitting recording and doing what they do without any complaint.  It is time we paid tribute to the staff who work in our offices as secretarial staff and to the staff of both Houses.  I have never heard a comment or complaint from them.  The guys up there at the back are always there to help keep us on the straight and narrow when we are sitting in as Acting Chairman.  There is great credit due to them.  If some of them are retiring, they are more than entitled to their redundancy payments.  When there is forced retirement of our staff, in terms of us losing our seats, they are certainly entitled to it.  They are only earning a day's pay and they are entitled to their redundancy. </p> <p>I just asked the Minister of State if the refurbishment of this House and the offices here came under the commission's remit, but apparently that project is under the OPW.  After the next Seanad election there will be big changes.  There will be no House here as this Chamber will not be in operation for the best part of two years, I think.  I do not know if the decision has been made as to where the Seanad is going to be located.  If we are outside the Leinster House complex and are going across the street to take votes and things, it is going to be awkward for staff and Members.  It will be dealt with in due course by whomever will be here.  </p> <p>It is so important to put our words of thanks to both Houses.  I support the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.221" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1106" speakername="Simon Harris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#FF00500"><p>I thank all Senators who took part in the debate for their very constructive responses to the Bill.  To take up Senator Moloney's point, and in my role as Minister of State with responsibility for the OPW, it is important that we remember that while this building is a Parliament, it is also a historic building which we have a duty to protect and preserve.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Simon Harris:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=2338"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2338&amp;amp;pid=SimonHarris&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->There are a number of things that need to be done in that regard to ensure that we keep this historic building in the safe and protected manner which is our legal obligation and to pass it on to the next generations.  While that will cause significant inconvenience around the House, it will leave us with a Parliament and, more importantly, a historic building in good care and stead to pass on.</p><p>This is a suitable opportunity to make some general comments on the commission, especially as the current D&aacute;il and Seanad draw to a close.  The Houses of the Oireachtas Commission is an expression of a fundamental tenet of the doctrine of separation of executive and legislative powers.  The financial independence of Parliament is essential to ensure the effectiveness of the process of holding Government to account.  The commission built from a low base the services and connectivity essential for Members, including information and research services and transparent and accountable financial and governance systems.  Examples of new or enhanced services include increased ICT facilities, new library and research services, the establishment of Oireachtas TV, which rightly allows members of the public to track our work here, and the introduction of a parliamentary legal service.  Through prudent financial management, for which I pay it tribute, the commission has consistently managed its budgets so as to return a significant surplus.  It has fully implemented all Government policy for the Civil Service in the areas of governance, planning, accounting, audit and value for money.  Fundamentally, it operates in a transparent manner through the publication on the Oireachtas website of commission minutes, strategic plans and corporate business plans.</p><p>It is of great significance that a new Clerk of the D&aacute;il will soon be appointed following an open completion.  This competition was recently announced.  The new Clerk will be expected under the terms of the Civil Service renewal plan published by the Government last year to play a key role in raising morale and productivity among staff, creating opportunities for staff to develop their talents, strengthening strategic planning capacity, assigning the appropriate staff to the right areas so that they can encourage and develop excellence and drive the modernisation process in the Oireachtas service and, overall, in ensuring that the Oireachtas service has a strong culture of leadership, excellence and continuous development.  With these demands being placed on whoever becomes Clerk of the D&aacute;il, Senators can be re-assured that the substantial progress made under the various commissions to date will be continued.</p><p>I take this opportunity to place on the record my gratitude, and I think that of all Members, for the work of all members of staff in the Houses of the Oireachtas.  I refer to our personal staff and the staff who work in the Seanad, D&aacute;il and committees to keep Parliament going.  It is a very important role that they play.  When people talk about remuneration and termination payments, they tend to focus on the public face of the office of the Deputy or Senator.  However, it is right and proper that a number of Senators acknowledged the role played by our staff who work very hard to assist in our work.  Sometimes, as part of the democratic process, they find themselves without employment after an election.</p><p>I draw Senators' attention to the fact that during the passage of this Bill through the D&aacute;il, my colleague, the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, Deputy Brendan Howlin, recorded his view that we need a mechanism to allow the incoming commission after the forthcoming general election to be as representative as possible of the Houses.  It is a view that I share.  Real powers are devolved to the commission and the exercise of such powers needs to have as broad a mandate from Members as possible.  It is a responsibility that will fall to the membership of the next D&aacute;il and Seanad.  Overall, the commission has been able over the last 12 years to develop into an organisation which can validly be regarded as being fit for purpose for current demands.  I thank the commission for its work and I hope the Bill provides clarity and transparency in terms of the funding envelope for the next three years.  I commend the Bill to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.223" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.224" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#GG00300">Houses of the Oireachtas Commission (Amendment) Bill 2015: Committee and Remaining Stages</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.225" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sections 1 to 10 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.226" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Title agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.227" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Bill reported without amendment and received for final consideration.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.228" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That the Bill do now pass".</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.229" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#GG00800"><p>The Minister mentioned two points in his contribution on Second Stage on which I wish to touch.  He said that the Minister, Deputy Brendan Howlin, wants the commission to be as representative as possible.  I agree and have no doubt that the Minister of State does too.  Perhaps the Minister did not have any input into it.  The current commission is the only one in history so far where the Government did not use the ministerial appointment mechanism to put in somebody independent.  As such, the only non-government representatives on the commission were Deputy John Browne and me.  That is poor practice.</p> <p>While the commission did a good job and we worked well together with not too many rows, it is not a good practice.  Ministerial and Government appointments, while ensuring that there are adequate Government representatives, should also be used to ensure that small parties and Independent Members are represented.  There were ten or 12 of us on the commission, only two of whom are not from Government parties.  It raised issues at times because certain groups were not represented.  We tried to represent them, but they were not happy about it.  I make the point in the interests of transparency.</p> <p>I note another thing the Minister of State might bring back to the Department and the Minister and his efforts.  Obviously, the commission is responsible in people's eyes for salaries and expenses and all of those types of things, but the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform is the body that determines rates.  That is not for the commission.</p> <p>The other thing that came up several times over the five-year period was that there was a change to the expenses regime which we all supported.  Expenses went down and things became a great deal more transparent.  That is very much to be commended.  We all welcomed it.  What did not change, notwithstanding the fact that it needed to, was that Senators in particular were entitled to claim for certain expenses but did not have a list of tangible things they were allowed to put expenses towards, as Members of the D&aacute;il did.  The Minister consistently ignored it for no reason other than that it might not have played out that well in the media from an aesthetic point of view.  There was a pool of money there and it was not going to make it any more expensive, but the menu of issues permitted for Senators to draw down was much smaller and much narrower than for Deputies.  One could argue that this was necessary as Deputies certainly have expenses which Senators do not incur.  I get that.  However, it was prohibitively narrow and made life extremely difficult for Senators in trying to do their work over the course of the last five years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.230" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Moloney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#GG00900"><p>I support Senator MacSharry on that point very strongly.  Senators from country areas cannot use the facilities of the House on the days we are not sitting.  As such, many of us have set up offices in what I call our constituencies but referring to our home bases.  We never asked for expenses for those offices.  We asked to be allowed to put the expense of our offices under the &euro;12,000 we get for our expenses.  It was never going to cost more money, but for some reason heels were dug in.  There was a view that it would give us bad press or something.  In the meantime, we are all laying out big money for offices, but cannot put that in as an expense.  It is crazy because we are providing the service and working for the people.  I know they keep telling us we do not have constituencies and that our constituency is Ireland and I understand the point.  However, we have to have a base from which to work and a place our secretaries can be if they are in our local areas.  It is fine for people in Dublin.  Things are really geared around Dublin people who can come in every day to Leinster House and use their offices here.  We cannot do so.</p> <p>Speaking for myself because everyone does things differently, I note that I rent an office and have photocopying, electricity and other costs.  I bear those costs out of my wages.  I am not complaining about that because I am well paid, but we should be allowed to put those costs in under our expenses.  It is not about giving us any more money.  The ones who ended up gaining out of all of this have been the newspapers because we ended up spending a lot of the expenses money on advertising.  That is what we can put under our expenses as well as a bit of extra secretarial staff support.  I cannot understand why we are not allowed to put our offices in as an expense under the same amount.  I support Senator MacSharry very much on that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.231" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#GG01000"><p>This matter was the subject of meetings with the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, Deputy Brendan Howlin.  While he was very sympathetic towards us, nothing happened.  I do not think we were even talking about offices but rather about some small areas where Senators were looking for parity of esteem with their colleagues in the other House.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Maurice Cummins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2003"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2003&amp;amp;pid=MauriceCummins&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->These matters should be dealt with and should never have happened.  There was a variation between what people in the other House and the Seanad could do.  In one ridiculous instance, a Senator could not buy a laptop and claim it under expenses whereas a Member of the D&aacute;il could.  These simple matters should be addressed, and I hope they will be addressed as a matter of urgency by whoever makes up the next Government.  There are restrictions and anomalies that must be addressed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.233" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1106" speakername="Simon Harris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#HH00200"><p>I thank the officials who worked so diligently on the Bill to get it through both Houses.  I thank Senators for their constructive engagement on the Bill.  I will relay their views to the Minister, Deputy Howlin, although it sounds like he is very aware of them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.234" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Moloney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#HH00300"><p>He is.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.235" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1106" speakername="Simon Harris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#HH00400"><p>I imagine all the issues will be a matter for the next D&aacute;il to consider.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.236" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.237" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 3.50 p.m. and resumed at 4.20 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.238" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#LL00100">Criminal Justice (Burglary of Dwellings) Bill 2015: Committee and Remaining Stages</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.239" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#LL00200"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.240" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sections 1 to 3, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.241" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Title agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.242" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Bill reported without amendment and received for final consideration.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.243" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That the Bill do now pass."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.244" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1009" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#LL00700"><p>The Bill was developed following detailed consultation with Garda management and with the detectives working on the ground to tackle burglary every day.  It addresses two key problems they identified, namely, the relative ease with which repeat offenders can obtain bail and the fact relatively short sentences can be imposed by the courts when multiple burglary offences are taken into account.</p> <p>The Bill will provide that for bail applications previous convictions for domestic burglary, coupled with pending charges or recent convictions, shall be considered as evidence that an accused person is likely to commit further domestic burglaries.  The Bill will also require a court which decides to impose custodial sentences for multiple burglary offences committed within a 12-month window to impose such sentences consecutively.  It is important legislation which carefully balances the right to an inviolable dwelling with the right to liberty, both of which are guaranteed by the Constitution.</p> <p>The legislation, together with Operation Thor and the joint agency response to crime, is focused on tackling and managing prolific offenders.  It forms part of a comprehensive package aimed at reducing the scourge of crime, and burglary in particular.  The package is supported by the Government's significant investment in Garda vehicles, ICT and buildings, but most importantly in recruitment to the force.  I have secured the funding that will see 1,150 new recruits enter the college between 2014 and 2016.  I thank all Senators who contributed to the debate during our discussions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.245" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#LL00800"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House and the very speedy passage of the legislation.  We did all point out on Second Stage last week how important the Bill is and how real a concern there is about levels of burglary throughout the country, in particular high levels of recidivism.  Last week, the Minister quoted the very high level of recidivism, particularly arising in statistics on burglary offences.  The Bill is particularly focused and targeted.  It seeks to ensure preservation of safeguards and protections for the rights of due process of accused persons, but it is targeted specifically at recidivist offending.  We all welcome this in the interests of victims' rights.</p> <p>We just heard from the chair of the parole board a moment ago in the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Justice, Defence and Equality, and we spoke about the need to ensure rehabilitation of offenders.  Of course the Bill, as a criminal justice measure, is only part of a package of measures aimed at dealing with recidivism and tackling repeat offending.  The Minister pointed out the need for the interagency approach and we all very much welcome this.  Clearly a range of other interventions are necessary to prevent re-offending and crime.  I thank the Minister for coming to the House and note the speedy and welcome passage of the legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.246" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#LL00900"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House and concur with the sentiments expressed by the Minister and Senator Bacik.  The legislation has been called for by many people, particularly those who have been the victims of crime.  It certainly will equip the courts to impose appropriate sentencing.  I hope it will act as a serious deterrent for people who repeatedly engage in criminal activity, which is something that must be welcomed.</p> <p>We all share Senator Bacik's view, and the Minister holds the same view, that rehabilitation is ultimately what is necessary.  The House has had motions on community courts and restorative justice.  When it comes to justice, the House is leading the way.  I commend the Minister for initiating legislation in the Seanad.  We are always delighted to co-operate with the Minister's busy programme.  It is a busy legislative programme to make this country safer and better and to make citizens feel safe in their homes.</p> <p>It is very poignant and worth noting that a Behaviour &amp;amp; Attitudes survey done in 2014 found only 67% of Irish people had confidence in An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, but a survey carried out in the past two or three months has shown the figure is now up to 87%.  This is worth noting, and the newly-appointed Commissioner, N&oacute;ir&iacute;n O'Sullivan, the Minister and the senior management team in the Minister's office and in An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na deserve credit because we came from a low place where public confidence was very poor.  The Garda always had the confidence of the Irish people.  Unfortunately there was a little bit of erosion but thankfully we are back to where we want to be and it will only improve from here on in.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.247" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015121600002#LL01000"><p>I welcome the Minister, Deputy Fitzgerald, back to the House.  As did Senators Conway and Bacik, I very much welcome the speedy passage of the Bill through the House.  It makes very important changes to the bail laws and sentencing policy.  As we are all aware, burglary must be one of the most horrific crimes that can be visited upon ordinary people in their own home.  Several Senators, including Senator Barrett, quoted what Mr. Justice Hardiman of the Court of Criminal Appeal stated, which is that the offence of burglary committed in a dwelling house is in every instance an act of aggression, an attack on the personal rights of the citizen as well as a public crime and a violation of the victim.  This sums up exactly how horrendous the crime is.  Any attempt to deal with the people who are, in some cases, habitual offenders of burglary is welcome.  I thank the Minister and welcome the speedy passage of the Bill through the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.248" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.249" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 4.30 p.m. and resumed at 5 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-12-16a.250" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Additional debate to follow.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>