<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.4" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#A00100">Gnó an tSeanaid - Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#A00300"><p>I have received notice from Senator M&aacute;ire Devine that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, she proposes to raise the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Education and Skills to provide a statement on the recent AsIAm survey on school exclusion and children with autism.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Colm Burke of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to provide an update on proposed improvements to the medical care service for patients who suffer from fibromyalgia.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Robbie Gallagher of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Finance to make a statement on the actions he is taking to counteract the property tax trap that will force pensioners and people on low and fixed incomes to pay property tax rather than defer payments.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator P&aacute;draig Mac Lochlainn of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government to provide an update on the mica redress scheme for affected homeowners in County Donegal.</blockquote> <p>Of the matters raised by the Senators that are suitable for discussion, I have selected Senators Devine, Colm Burke and Gallagher and they will be taken now.  I regret that I had to rule out of order the matter raised by Senator Mac Lochlainn on the ground that it is a repeat of a Commencement matter raised on 20 December 2018.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.7" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#A00350">Nithe i dtosach suíonna - Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.8" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#A00400">Special Educational Needs Service Provision</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#A00500"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it.  I wish to extend a c&eacute;ad m&iacute;le f&aacute;ilte to two groups in the Public Gallery this morning, AsIAm, which does Trojan work in raising awareness of autism throughout the country, and the Crumlin-based autism parent support group.</p> <p>I raise this issue on foot of AsIAm's recent report entitled Invisible Children - Survey on School Absence and Withdrawal in Ireland's Autism Community.  It is a national scandal that the right to an education is out of reach for so many autistic children at primary and secondary levels.  A mother in her 30s is in jail this morning having been prosecuted for failing to send her children to school but this Government should be in the dock being prosecuted for the lack of places for autistic children at preschool, primary and secondary levels, which is preventing them from vindicating their right to an education.  </p> <p>There are several issues that the Minister for Education and Skills must address.  He must ask the National Council for Special Education, NCSE, to develop policy advice on school exclusion and school refusal.  He must also ask the council to improve the level and quality of engagement by special education needs organisers, SENOs, with families, particularly those that are in crisis because of the lack of school places.</p> <p>When the aforementioned report was published on Monday, the Department said that it was satisfied that there were enough suitable school places.  It must be accepted that there is a shortage of autism classes and moreover, a shortage of suitable placements in mainstream and special schools.  I ask that the Minister for Education and Skills commits to publishing plans on how every autistic child can access a suitable school placement for the next academic year.</p> <p>We finally ratified the UN Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities late last year but we are not living up to our commitments in that regard.  It is estimated that one in every 59 or 60 children in this country has autism and we are failing those children.  This Government is failing Ireland's autistic children.  I hope that the Minister of State will provide some succour in her response this morning.  The Minister for Education and Skills must instruct schools to open ASD units.  That has not happened yet and I do not know how far the Minister is prepared to go in that regard.  Schools need instruction as well as support and resources in order to ensure that children with autism grow up healthy, happy and secure and are educated within their own communities.  They should not have to travel for miles to access a school place.  I look forward to the Minister of State's response.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1307" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#B00100"><p>I thank Senator Devine for raising this very important issue.  I am taking this matter on behalf of the Minister, Deputy McHugh.  I wish to acknowledge the important role stakeholders like AslAm play in promoting education and the inclusion of children in education.  The Minister, Deputy McHugh, recently met with AslAm and was impressed with its work.  Officials are studying the report published yesterday and the Minister will be discussing its recommendations with them.</p> <p>Enabling children with special educational needs, including autism, to receive an education appropriate to their needs is a priority for this Government.  At present, we are investing heavily in supporting our children with special educational needs, with &euro;1.8 billion being spent annually, which represents approximately &euro;1 in every &euro;5 of the education budget.  This includes an allocation of more than &euro;300 million towards providing additional resources specifically to support students with autism in schools.  The number of autism spectrum disorder, ASD, special classes has more than doubled in the last five years from 511 in 2014 to 1,196 across the country now.  In addition, 124 special schools provide for children with autism and very complex special needs.</p> <p>The work of the Department of Education and Skills in respect of special education is informed by evidence-based advice from the National Council for Special Education.  The NCSE consults extensively with stakeholders, including parents, experts and organisations like AslAm, which has provided useful insights into difficulties experienced by children and families in getting an education.  The NCSE is currently developing advice for the Department on education provision in special classes and special schools.  The council is examining whether there are any students for whom both specialist and mainstream educational settings are currently not working and, if there are, will consider what might be contributing to this.  Schools are required to have policies in place for the promotion of student well-being, positive behaviour and an environment that is conducive to good teaching and learning.  The thrust of these policies is early intervention and provision of supports so that every child receives an education appropriate to his or her ability.  Advice and support is available to help schools in this regard.</p> <p>The National Educational Psychological Service supports children with ASD, including those who may also present with anxiety.  This involves working with teachers to build whole-school capacity to work with children with special educational needs, including autism and anxiety.  It also involves working with individual children who are experiencing difficulties.  There are legal provisions around the exclusion and expulsion of students and these are the responsibility of Tusla.  Fair procedures are a key requirement.  Expulsion should be a last resort and reduced timetables should not be used as a behavioural management technique.  Where students are excluded from school, the Department provides home tuition as a short-term measure until a more permanent solution is identified.</p> <p>The NCSE is aware of the recent demand for additional special class and special school placements in the Dublin area.  Planning is actively under way to ensure that children without a suitable placement for next year are provided with such a placement.  We expect a clearer picture to emerge in the coming weeks when schools have finalised their enrolments.  The NCSE is leading the work in this regard with significant support from the Department.</p> <p>Responsibility for ensuring all children have access to a suitable education is a shared responsibility.  The Minister, Deputy McHugh, is confident that through the work of the NCSE and the co-operation of schools we can address the current difficulties.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#B00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State, although I would have liked a more reassuring response.  The Children's Ombudsman is overwhelmed.  I have spoken with him at length about this issue.  He is considering what to do next.  I reiterate that nobody should tolerate any child not having a place in a school, let alone a child with extra needs.  It is as if the child is a burden on the system.  The partial schooling being offered throughout the country is illegal.  It goes against the law of the land.  The assessment the NCSE is going to carry out is long overdue.  When is that going to happen?  When will an uplifting, embracing and worthwhile announcement about what will be done be made?  We will listen to the likes of the parents who are in the Chamber today.  They are loud, they will speak boldly, and they will not stop.  This movement has commenced.  It is the next thing we need to blow out of the water and lift the lid on.  We need to ensure suitable education for our children.  We will get everybody involved, including the Children's Ombudsman who has indicated that he is frustrated by the number of cases.  There are solicitors in Cork who are prepared to take cases in respect of the waiting list for assessments of need.   We could go on and on.  Disability and, in this instance, autism are being left out in the cold.  It will happen no longer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1307" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#B00300"><p>I welcome the Dublin 12 and AsIAm groups.  As was set out in the opening statement the Minister, Deputy McHugh, provided, the Minister has already met with AsIAm and is very confident that some of the recommendations in its report will make a significant difference in children's lives.  I will read back the last paragraph of the statement I was given:</p><blockquote>Responsibility for ensuring all children have access to a suitable education is a shared responsibility.  The Minister, Deputy McHugh, is confident that through the work of the NCSE and the co-operation of schools [and principals and teachers] we can address the current difficulties.</blockquote> <p>As a public representative and Minister of State, I believe that no child should be left without access to education no matter what disabilities he or she may have.  I will continue to support efforts to deal with the difficulties I see in my role as a local Deputy such as the problems parents face in getting access to special classes in schools for their children.  I will raise the issues the Senator has raised with the Minister when I meet him during the next week.  I thank the Senator again.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.13" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#B00350">Fibromyalgia Support Services</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#B00400"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House.  I wish to raise the issue of fibromyalgia and the need for an improved medical service in this area.  As the Minister of State will know, this condition involves nerve dysfunction and causes chronic pain and fatigue.  People who have the condition suffer a lot from migraine.  Restless leg syndrome, irritable bowel syndrome, and difficulty in regulating one's body temperature are all part of fibromyalgia.  There is a need for a proper structure to deal with this issue.  A group presented to the Joint Committee on Health on this issue in July 2012 and very little progress has been made since.  Changes have been made in respect of the recognition of this condition and the need for a planned approach to healthcare in Northern Ireland and the UK.</p> <p>It is in that context that I am raising the issue of the need for a structure to be put in place not only within the Department of Health and the HSE, but within the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection.  This Department made a protocol, protocol 6, accessible online.  This protocol is a 63-page document dealing with chronic pain and fibromyalgia.  People who have this condition have difficulty in getting through the social welfare system in order to qualify for disability benefit or long-term illness benefit.  It is in that context that I raise the issue of recognition for this condition and of a planned approach for dealing with patients who have this condition.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1307" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#B00500"><p>On behalf of the Minister, Deputy Harris, I thank Senator Colm Burke for providing the opportunity to update the House on this important issue.  I took a debate on this issue on the Minister's behalf in the D&aacute;il last week, during which a number of Members spoke.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Catherine Byrne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2186"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2186&amp;amp;pid=CatherineByrne&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=04&amp;amp;day=11"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Some of the speakers in the D&aacute;il spoke about fibromyalgia as a disabling disease and how many doctors find it difficult to diagnose at its early stages.  I thank Senator Colm Burke for his contribution.<br/><br/>The Minister for Health, Deputy Harris, acknowledges the seriousness of the symptoms of fibromyalgia and the many challenges that people with this condition encounter in their daily lives.  The exact prevalence of fibromyalgia in Ireland is not known, but it is estimated to affect approximately 2% of the population with many symptoms which tend to vary from person to person.  The main symptoms of fibromyalgia, include pain, stiffness, fatigue and even depression.  Anyone can develop fibromyalgia, although the condition typically affects more women than men and generally occurs between the ages of 30 and 60.<br/><br/>Fibromyalgia is a difficult condition to diagnose as there is currently no specific test for it and its symptoms can be similar to those associated with other conditions and unfortunately there is currently no cure.  A GP will diagnose fibromyalgia based on the patient having a typical mix of symptoms and ruling out any other conditions that could be causing these.<br/><br/>Treatment for the condition requires intervention from various medical specialists in order to manage its associated symptoms as and when they arise.  As fibromyalgia has several different symptoms, no single treatment will work for all symptoms and for all patients.  There are, however, a number of treatments that may ease symptoms.  It is likely that the person will need to try a variety of treatments to find the most suitable approach for them.  This approach to treatment will be decided jointly between the patient and the GP, depending on what is preferred, what is available and what is clinically appropriate for each individual patient.  This will normally be a combination of medication and lifestyle changes.  Several different healthcare professionals in addition to a GP may also be involved in the treatment depending on the complexity and specific symptoms arising for the individual patient, for example, a rheumatologist or a neurologist.  As well as medications that may involve pain medications and antidepressants, there are some other treatment options like exercise, physiotherapy or cognitive behaviour therapy that can be used to help cope with the symptoms of fibromyalgia.<br/><br/>In the context of improved medical care, it is important to note that the national clinical programme for rheumatology in the HSE has produced a model of care for rheumatology in Ireland that seeks to address the needs of patients with fibromyalgia and those of all patients with rheumatological diseases.  This model of care aims to ensure that a patient is seen and assessed and treated by the right person, in the right place and in the timeliest manner.<br/><br/>This Government is committed to the expansion of primary care.  In line with the vision set out in Sl&aacute;intecare, the aim is to ensure that all citizens, including those suffering from fibromyalgia, can be offered the right care in the right place at the right time and be supported in their local community wherever possible.<br/><br/>The Minister, Deputy Harris, is aware that there have been calls to include fibromyalgia as a specified condition under the long-term illness, LTI, scheme.  These requests have been considered carefully, however, currently there are no plans to extend the LTI scheme.  I note that it is proposed that the LTI scheme will be included as part of a review of the basis for existing hospital and medication charges which is to be carried out under commitments given in the Sl&aacute;intecare action plan.<br/><br/>Those suffering financial hardship may also be eligible for a medical card.  In accordance with our overall eligibility framework, this decision is not based on a particular illness, but rather on the overall financial situation of an individual and family.  It is important to note that, under the drug payment scheme, the maximum monthly amount that anyone is required to pay for their medicine is being reduced from &euro;134 to &euro;124.  As such, all those with fibromyalgia are urged to check their eligibility for a GP visit card and medical card and can apply for the drug payment scheme at their local health office or through <i>mydps.ie.  </i>It is the Minister's sincere hope that as many people as possible with fibromyalgia benefit from these measures.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#C00200"><p>As the Minister of State is aware and dealt with in her reply, this is a complicated issue.  It is difficult because the condition presents in different ways but enough research has now been done to clearly show that this illness is long term and does not resolve.  There are 15 different conditions recognised under the long-term illness scheme.  We should be trying to take a more planned approach to this condition.  The Minister of State was with me on the health committee when we dealt with this issue back in 2012 and, seven years later, we should be trying to take a more proactive and planned approach to dealing with this condition from the perspective of healthcare and through the social welfare system.  I ask that this issue is reviewed by the Department of Health to see what new actions can be taken to help people with this condition.  It will not go away and sufferers face many challenges, both medically and financially, and therefore we should have a more planned approach to dealing with it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1307" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#C00300"><p>I again thank the Senator for raising the issue.  As I said, I took a similar matter for the Minister in the D&aacute;il last week after a number of Members spoke about fibromyalgia.  One of the things that came out of that debate was that I approached the Minister about the issues that were raised, particularly around long-term illness.  Some of the issues that were raised in the D&aacute;il, and which Senator Colm Burke has raised, are everyday issues that are making it difficult for people with fibromyalgia to even live out their daily lives.</p> <p>I will bring the Senator's concerns back to the Minister and ask that a more appropriate process be put in place to care for people with fibromyalgia.  I will ask about the prospect of putting a step-by-step model in place, under Sl&aacute;intecare, for people suffering from the disease.  It is debilitating.  I know two people who have the disease and I know that, on a daily basis, life can be very hard for them.  </p> <p>I understand, after speaking to him, that the Minister welcomed the agreement on GP contractual reform that will see structures to care for patients with chronic conditions in primary care settings from 2020 and will benefit over 430,000 medical card and GP card holders over the next years.</p> <p>I reiterate to the Senator that I will do my best to convey his concerns and ask the Minister to come back to the Senator on this.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.19" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#C00400">Property Tax</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#C00500"><p>The Minister of State is very welcome and I thank him for taking time out of his busy schedule to be here.  I want to discuss the Government's decision to defer the recommendations from the review of the local property tax, LPT, and the implications that may have for pensioners and those on low incomes.  A review of the controversial tax on homeownership, the local property tax, LPT, recommended that the Minister for Finance, Deputy Donohoe, increase the threshold for deferring property tax to ensure that pensioners were not excluded because of the rise in their weekly pension incomes.  However, the Government has failed to bring forward any reforms to the local property tax.  One could be cynical and suggest that is for political reasons due to the forthcoming European and local elections but I will await the Minister of State's comments on that.</p> <p>There are serious consequences for the Government's inaction on property tax.  Many low and fixed-income households will no longer be able to defer the property tax when it is due.  As the Minister of State knows, a couple who are both on the maximum State pension of &euro;248.30 per week, which gives them a total annual income of &euro;25,800, are now above the threshold to qualify for deferral which was &euro;25,000 for a couple.  It appears that the message to pensioners now appears to be that it is tough luck but they have to pay up.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Robbie Gallagher:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2471"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2471&amp;amp;pid=RobbieGallagher&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=04&amp;amp;day=11"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This is a particularly mean approach by the Government.  It does not cost it anything to allow those on modest incomes to defer.  Homeowners can currently defer their property tax charge if their income is below &euro;15,000 for a single person or &euro;25,000 for a couple.  The property tax review recommended increasing this threshold to &euro;18,000 for a single person and &euro;30,000 for a couple.  It appears the Minister's review of the controversial tax dismissed several proposals which would have made life easier, particularly for pensioners.  Waivers for homeowners on low fixed incomes and people with disabilities were suggested.  Both were rejected.  The review group also dismissed a proposal to give property tax relief to people over 80 with long-term illnesses, despite this measure being previously recommended in a Government report.  The report also ruled out cutting interest rates charged on property tax deferrals, which are mostly availed of by older people.</p><p>Approximately 328,000 people, mostly older people, are eligible for the deferral scheme but only a limited number take up the option.  The possibility is that, as this is a relatively new tax, they might not be aware they are entitled to put off the payment.  More needs to be done on this.  Over 56,000 homeowners chose to defer their property tax last year.  A deferred payment incurs a 4% interest rate annually which is permanently fixed as a charge on the property which must be paid on the sale or transfer of the home.  As it is a relatively new tax, people need more information as to how the deferred payment system works.  An information campaign is needed.  Many people, including older people, have a fear of Revenue and are afraid to seek a deferral.  I would hate to think that older people are stretching themselves just to pay a property tax when they may not be aware a deferral is available to them.</p><p>It is disappointing that many of the recommendations of the review into the property tax have not been implemented.  Many of its good and worthwhile suggestions would have assisted those on low incomes and in financial hardship to be outside the property tax net.  Unfortunately, that has not been the case.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1267" speakername="Patrick O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#D00200"><p>The Minister for Finance initiated a review of the local property tax, LPT, in 2018.  The Minister believed it was important the Government was able to make its position clear on LPT in order that households would be aware of plans for the tax well in advance of the November 2019 revaluation date, as well as the associated 2020 and beyond LPT liabilities.</p> <p>The Minister further considered it was essential that the principle that formed a central part of the terms of reference for the 2015 review of LPT, namely, achieving relative stability in LPT payments of liable persons both over the short and longer terms, would inform the deliberations on this matter.  By relative stability in LPT liabilities, the Minister meant that any increases should be modest, affordable and fair.</p> <p>The review of the LPT has now been completed by the Department of Finance in conjunction with the Departments of the Taoiseach, Public Expenditure and Reform and Housing, Planning and Local Government, as well as with the Revenue Commissioners.  The review focused on the impact of house price movements under a series of scenarios involving different rate and tax band structures.  However, against a background of significant but geographically uneven increases in residential property price levels, the Minister believes it is necessary to engage in further consultation to identify a scenario which would deliver on the condition he set that there should be relative stability for all taxpayers in their LPT liabilities and that any increases should be modest and affordable.</p> <p>Having considered the findings of the review report, the Minister has decided to defer the valuation date from 1 November 2019 to 1 November 2020.  This should give sufficient time for the Committee on Budgetary Oversight to consider the review report in the context of the committee's recommendations in its report on the LPT of 21 March 2018.  Importantly, as a result of the Minister's decision, the LPT bills of those liable for the tax will not be increasing in 2020.</p> <p>Under the LPT legislation, a deferral option is available in circumstances where the annual gross income of the liable person does not exceed &euro;15,000 for a single person and &euro;25,000 for a couple.  Marginal relief applies for owner-occupiers whose income is not more than &euro;10,000 above the income limits to permit deferrals of up to 50% of the LPT liability.  The Minister understands from Revenue that, while over 300,000 people fall within the current income thresholds for the LPT deferral, only about 15% of these actually seek a deferral on these grounds.</p> <p>State contributory and non-contributory pension rates have recently risen by &euro;5 per week.  For the majority of persons in receipt of such pensions, their eligibility for LPT deferral will not change as a result of this pension increase.  In the small number of cases, where the pension increase brings a person over the LPT deferral threshold, such persons may still qualify for a reduction of up to 50% of their LPT liability.</p> <p>The LPT review recommended the income thresholds for LPT deferrals be reviewed regularly by reference to movements in the consumer price index, wage growth in the economy and changes in fixed income payments by the State.  From the next valuation date, the review recommended the deferral thresholds be increased to &euro;18,000 for a single owner and &euro;30,000 for a couple.  This recommendation, along with the other recommendations in the review report, have been referred by the Minister for Finance to the Committee on Budgetary Oversight for its consideration.</p> <p>The committee's 2018 report on the LPT indicated it was against proceeding with automatic revaluation of properties in 2019, as provided for in current legislation, as this would result in significant increases in LPT liabilities.  The committee supported revaluation with an adjustment to rates nationally to maintain LPT yield or revaluation with an adjustment to rates locally to maintain LPT yield.  The committee also recommended the cessation of exemptions on new and unused properties on equity grounds and because it would broaden the tax base.</p> <p>The deferral of revaluation until November 2020 provides time and space for the Committee on Budgetary Oversight to consider the report of the interdepartmental review and to provide its views to the Minister.  In his engagement with the committee, the Minister will seek to promote the policy objectives which should underpin any changes to the tax.  These comprise protection of the overall yield; modest and affordable increases, if increases occur, in LPT liabilities; integration of new properties into the LPT base; maintenance of the tax base with a small number of exemptions; upholding the progressivity of the tax.</p> <p>The Minister considers that the reformed LPT needs to be based on a model of band widening combined with rate changes.  The Minister supports retention of the option for local authorities to reduce the LPT rate for their areas.  The Minister will also engage with the Committee on Budgetary Oversight on the issue of LPT relief for persons in apartment complexes, etc., who are paying management fees.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#D00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his comprehensive reply.  He stated only 15% of households are taking up the option to defer the payment.  That speaks volumes in itself.  As I said earlier, it is a relatively new tax and I feel not enough people are aware of this option to defer payment of the property tax every year.  Will the Government look into an information campaign to make people aware that this option is available?</p> <p>It may have been an oversight on the Department&rsquo;s part that it did not take into consideration the increases in pension payments could result in some people falling outside the threshold.  Will the Minister of State take that into consideration?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1267" speakername="Patrick O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#D00400"><p>In discussing this we need to be honest.  The LPT yields &euro;500 million.  Any changes to it will have a knock-on effect.  While there could be a suggestion that people might not be aware of the possibility of a deferral, there are many who understand their tax liability and that when a tax is levied it must be paid.</p> <p>Five scenarios were put forward by the review group and their impacts were considered.  The Minister has said they need to go back to the Committee on Budgetary Oversight for its views on them.  I have not heard from any Opposition party as to which of the five scenarios it would opt for.  Each of them has its own pros and cons.  There was much media coverage about one scenario which would have had an impact on rural homes.  However, I have not heard any of the Opposition spokespersons from the three main parties say which scenario they would opt for.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Patrick O'Donovan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2316"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2316&amp;amp;pid=PatrickODonovan&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=04&amp;amp;day=11"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->As in other debates we have had, such as on climate change, budgetary matters, education or health, a little bit of tax honesty would be a good thing.  The Minister for Finance is providing an opportunity for the Oireachtas to state its view and he will, ultimately, take it.  There is a role for local authorities.  Some have decided to reduce their property tax rate, which could make a small but welcome difference to a householder, but they have shoved up commercial property rates.  There is some in-built hypocrisy in that.</p><p>We need an honest debate on the issue and we need to debate the scenarios put forward by the review group.  It behoves every party in the D&aacute;il and Seanad to state the way it would do it, while maintaining the tax base and being fair.  If changes are to be made, the parties should say what those changes should be but the base has to be maintained.  When there are deferrals there is a cost implication and local authorities will have to increase their overall rate, meaning there will be an impact on both urban and rural areas.  The Minister for Finance has put this off so that people can have a say.  Everybody says the Oireachtas should have a say and the Committee on Budgetary Oversight was established so that Senators and Deputies could have an input into the budget.  Now is the chance for that.  I look forward to hearing the views of Senators and to learning which option they would go for.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.26" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 11.10 a.m. and resumed at 11.30 a.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.27" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#G00100">An tOrd Gnó - Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#G00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, motion re Protocol No. 19, annexed to the Treaty on European Union and to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, back from committee, to be taken on the conclusion of the Order of Business, without debate; No. 2, motion re Protocol No. 21, annexed to the Treaty on European Union and to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, back from committee, to be taken on the conclusion of No. 1, without debate; No. 3, Thirty-eighth Amendment of the Constitution (Dissolution of Marriage) Bill 2016 - Committee and Remaining Stages, to be taken on the conclusion of No. 2; and No. 4, motion re Thirty-eighth Amendment of the Constitution (Dissolution of Marriage) Bill 2016 - statement for the information of voters, to be taken on the conclusion of No. 3, without debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#G00300"><p>I wish to raise the issue of home help hours.  There is a serious crisis regarding home care packages, with elderly and other persons in need of hours or increased hours.  In November, we learned that 550 extra home care packages would be made available, but this has not made a dent in terms of what is required.  By way of a parliamentary question tabled by my colleague, Deputy Browne, we have learned that, in the constituency of Dublin South-Central alone, 184 people are waiting for home care packages.  That is not just 184 people, it is 184 families that are struggling without such packages.  Some of the people in question might be looked after by relatives and others might be blocking beds in hospitals.  We do not have an accurate number, but in its response the HSE stated, "While resources for the provision of Home Support ... are substantial, they are finite." and "We are currently operating a waiting list as we do not have funding available to meet increased demands for home care package or home support services."  Clearly, the HSE is stating that it is not being funded properly and that it needs more funds to ensure that those in need of home support services get them.  It is incumbent on the Minister to ensure that these services are properly resourced.  I would like the Leader to relay to him my call for him to do so.</p> <p>I also wish to discuss the Educate Together campaign for a secondary school to serve Dublin 8 and Dublin 12.  The campaign group met the Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy McHugh, nearly two months ago but has not received any reply or follow-up from him.  We have learned that a site has been acquired in Rathmines for a new school, but this will only serve the students of Dublin 2 and Dublin 4.  Three new schools will be built - two in Dublin 6 and one in Dublin 4 - yet the children of Dublin 8 are told to go to Sandymount for school and the children of Dublin 12 have been told that they cannot attend any of these new schools.  That is significantly unfair when there is a school in Harold's Cross on the doorstep of children who live in Dublin 12 and they are not being allowed access to it.  This is a serious issue.  Despite the Minister's meeting with the group, there has been no real feedback.  What follow-up will there be?  I will contact the Minister separately.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1429" speakername="Billy Lawless" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#G00400"><p>Will the Leader call on the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport to attend the House in order to debate the provision of driver licences to asylum seekers?  On a number of occasions I have raised the Supreme Court decision in NVH. <i>v</i>. Minister for Justice and Equality and ors.  A judgment of profound significance and compassion, it was delivered by Mr. Justice Donal O'Donnell, who stated:</p><blockquote>In my view, the point has been reached when it cannot be said that the legitimate differences between an asylum seeker and a citizen can continue to justify the exclusion of an asylum seeker from the possibility of employment.  The damage to the individual's self worth, and sense of themselves, is exactly the damage which the constitutional right seeks to guard against.  The affidavit evidence of depression, frustration and lack of self-belief bears that out.</blockquote> <p>Since this decision, the Government has announced that asylum seekers who have been waiting more than nine months for a determination on their first applications for refugee status will be able to apply for permission to work.</p><p>In the state of Illinois, which is my other home, we lobbied for and achieved the introduction of temporary visitor driving licences for undocumented persons working across the state.  There is no reason for the same not to be done in Ireland.  If asylum seekers are to be given the dignity of work in this country, something that I wholeheartedly support, it should follow that they have an entitlement to obtain a temporary driver licence for as long as they are lawfully allowed to work in this country.  In light of the fact that many direct provision centres are outside main towns and cities, the Minister, Deputy Ross, informed the Lower House in September 2018 that he had asked his officials to re-examine the question of whether we should issue driver licences to asylum seekers.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Billy Lawless:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2485"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2485&amp;amp;pid=BillyLawless&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=04&amp;amp;day=11"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The Minister told the D&aacute;il that he had asked his officials to re-examine whether we should issue driver licences to asylum seekers.  He noted that some EU members states do so.  I am calling on the Minister to come to the House to provide an update on the position and whether he will now introduce a system which facilitates those asylum seekers who have a legal right to work to obtain a driver licence.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#H00200"><p>I commend Senator Lawless on raising this very important issue.  I work on many issues which relate to the rights of asylum seekers and those living in direct provision centres.  The Mosney direct provision centre is in my area and I am proud to say I have many friends who, unfortunately, have occupied places in that centre for far too long.  Given that the Supreme Court has adjudicated that asylum seekers in this country have a right to work, albeit restricted, to ensure that right to work is fully vindicated it should surely follow that those in direct provision centres should have the opportunity in Irish law to have access to a vehicle to enable them to get to their workplace.  I fully support Senator Lawless's call for the Minister to come to the House.</p> <p>I raise the issue of the Flemish Decree case with which many Members, particularly those from rural areas, will be familiar.  The decree was issued by the European courts a short few years ago.  Essentially, it calls into question the legitimacy of Ireland's very strict and restrictive local needs rules on once-off rural housing.  I deal with many cases in my own area, in areas such as Clogherhead, Termonfeckin, Monasterboice and Tullyallen, involving individuals who find themselves on the wrong side of the local needs restrictions and are awaiting a determination from the Department of Housing, Planning and Local Government on new guidelines that would reflect the Flemish decree case.  We have very restrictive guidelines and many people are waiting to make decisions about purchasing sites.  They may be living on the fringes of villages in areas where they are unable to buy a suitable home because none is available.  The delay in the working group and Minister making a decision and issuing new guidance to local authorities means they are not purchasing sites which would enable them and their families to build the homes they need.</p> <p>In response to a parliamentary question last year, the Minister stated very clearly that he and his Department would issue new guidelines to local authorities before the end of the year.  However, in a more recent reply to my colleague, Deputy Jan O'Sullivan, it was clear that the Minister has kicked the can down the road once again.  I sense and fear that he is afraid to make a decision this side of the local elections.  Young families who are hoping to build homes need clarity and certainty on this matter.  As the European Courts have suggested, our rules are overly restrictive.  I understand and accept that our rural planning guidelines need to be sustainable.  I think everyone agrees on that point but we are in a difficult position owing to the current lack of clarity or certainty.  People in County Louth, east Meath and throughout the country seek such certainty. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#H00300"><p>Thar ceann an gr&uacute;pa Sinn F&eacute;in, ba mhaith liom c&aacute;s Emma DeSouza agus c&uacute;rsa&iacute; saor&aacute;nachta &oacute; Thuaidh a ard&uacute; ar&iacute;s.</p> <p>I draw Senators' attention to a motion in my name and the names of my Sinn F&eacute;in colleagues on the ongoing concerns about citizenship and citizenship rights in the North under the Good Friday Agreement, not least in the context of Brexit.  Anyone who has been following these issues on social media will have seen the hashtag #weareIrishtoo and #IstandwithEmma.  I have consistently raised Emma DeSouza's case in this House over the past two years.  The case has brought the unimplemented aspects of the Good Friday Agreement relating to our citizenship rights into sharp focus.  We know that the Good Friday Agreement confers on all of us the right to be accepted as Irish, British or both.  I seek the support of the House for the motion, which I will not move until next week to give Senators an opportunity to digest its content and engage with the issue.  I will seek an opportunity for the House to discuss the motion and the issues it raises.  The latest extension in the Brexit fiasco has given us a degree of breathing space and of room to home in on this issue.  A rally will be held at Belfast City Hall at 12 noon next Saturday under the banner "We are Irish Too".  It has been organised by Ms DeSouza and the Think32 lobby group to draw attention to the issue, bring people together and, it is hoped, focus the minds of the two Governments on finding a resolution to this issue in the context of the Brexit negotiations and the implementation of the Good Friday Agreement.</p> <p>Last week, the Minister of State, Deputy McEntee, responded to a Commencement matter I tabled on this matter.  The thrust of her response was that the Government would await the review of these issues announced by the British Prime Minister, Theresa May.  It has subsequently transpired that the British Government will not hold a formal review and there are no terms of reference or timescale for the review.  A vast glaring anomaly is staring at us as a result of Brexit and it illustrates how this crucial part of the Good Friday Agreement remains unfulfilled.  If we do not sort it out, people will be further disenfranchised and a third tier of Irish citizenship will be created.  We will no longer be second class citizens in the context of Brexit; we will be third class citizens.  I ask that Members read the motion to get a feel for it.  All parties have indicated support for Ms DeSouza and for securing a resolution to this issue.  I hope that next week we will get the opportunity to discuss the motion with the Government prior to the Easter recess and as we face into the Brexit extension.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#H00400"><p>I welcome the outcome of talks held in Brussels late last night between the United Kingdom and the European Union.  The extension to Brexit until 31 October gives some breathing space.  There are now three options, namely, a referendum in the UK, a cross-party deal or an orderly Brexit.  I congratulate all involved.  We are not sure what will happen in the European elections.  The UK has until 22 May to decide whether it will contest the elections.  It is a complete mess.  I thank all the negotiators involved for arriving at this solution which is in the interests of Ireland, the UK and the EU.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#H00500"><p>I ask the Leader to request that the Minister of State with responsibility for the elderly, Deputy Jim Daly, appear before the Seanad as soon as possible and that he overrule a decision taken by the Health Service Executive.  Before Senator Feighan leaves, I should say that this is another blow to Roscommon, even if he campaigned for it.  It seems that under the watch of his party's Government, community healthcare west has decided to evict ten male and two elderly patients from the Rosalie community psychiatric unit in Castlerea, County Roscommon.  The decision was announced yesterday, 11 April, at a letter read at 8 a.m. to staff by Mr. Tony Canavan, HSE chief for the west.  The families of the 12 patients were informed by letter yesterday.  The campaign to overturn the HSE's decision and retain the Rosalie unit, which is led by Mr. Liam Walsh, a son of one of its residents, Breda, will continue.</p> <p>Commitments were given by the former Minister of State, Kathleen Lynch, that the Rosalie unit would be retained.  The facility was established when the former Don Arms Hotel was converted to a long-stay psychiatric unit following the closure of St. Patrick's psychiatric hospital in Castlerea, now Castlerea Prison.  With accommodation for 32 patients, it is ideal for a nursing home for patients with Alzheimer's and other forms of dementia.  It has trained and qualified professional staff and first-class facilities.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Terry Leyden:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=636"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=636&amp;amp;pid=TerryLeyden&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=04&amp;amp;day=11"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I call on the Minister of State, Deputy Jim Daly, the Minister, the Fine Gael general election candidates, Senators Hopkins and Feighan, and Fine Gael council candidates to retain the Rosalie Unit.  It is disgraceful that a Department and Minister would evict vulnerable elderly people.  Michael Davitt would turn in his grave to think that an Irish Government would inflict this hardship on patients who need their home.  They live there.  It is their home.  If they leave, it will kill them quickly.  That is what it is all about.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#J00200"><p>I wish to raise the issue of overall care in the private hospital sector.  It is interesting that in the UK, a person was convicted in the past few weeks with regard to carrying out unnecessary operations.  It has been established that unnecessary mastectomies were carried out and that over 750 patients must now be compensated.  This issue concerns accountability in the health service.  While we have accountability in the HSE and I fully accept that every medical and nursing professional in the Irish health system, regardless of whether he or she works in the voluntary or private sector, works extremely hard and is extremely dedicated and committed, there is a need to make sure we have adequate supervisory capacity regarding procedures carried out to ensure that what occurred in the UK does not occur in any of our medical facilities here.  Could we have a debate on this matter to see whether we have adequate supervisory mechanisms?  While they exist in the public health system, I am not sure about accountability in the private system.  I am not saying that there is an issue in any of our private hospitals.  I have no doubt whatsoever that there is no such issue but it is important that we learn from the lesson in the UK to make sure it never arises here and that we have the procedures in place.  Could this issue be brought to the Minister's attention and included in a debate in the near future?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#J00300"><p>I note a recent report on Dublin cycling figures.  For the first time in over ten years, those figures have fallen.  One would not have thought they were falling in my area because it is great to see so many people cycling, particularly with the weather yesterday.  It is good for traffic.  Reducing the number of people using cars is good for people's health, CO2 emissions and in many other ways.  We need a debate here with the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport that focuses purely on cycling.  What tends to happen is that we have statements on transport matters, the Minister comes in and gives us a very long speech about his wonderful Department and his wonderful brief and we end up with people trying to chip in as quickly as they can covering a multitude of topics with a very short period of time in which to respond.</p> <p>Cycling can be found in urban areas and also relates to sport and recreation but I am talking in particular about commuting in our major urban centres.  We need to look at and tackle it.  I would say that there are many reasons for the drop in the number of people cycling.  It might be that the Luas has improved or the weather was bad or because of the effects of the cross-city Luas service, but we need to look at the issue.  I cycle on occasions and have often cycled in here.  It is a very reliable way of getting around, particularly when the weather is better, and is good for people who are still in cars.  They should not be antagonistic towards cyclists, although only some of them are, because having fewer cars on the road benefits those who still drive.</p> <p>I ask the Acting Leader to schedule a debate on open spaces and playing facilities, particularly in urban areas, because the same demand versus supply issue tends not to exist in more rural areas.  It is an issue in many urban areas.  I know Senator Ardagh has raised the issue of green spaces.  There are many very successful clubs that are always crying out for more facilities and pitches to cope with the demand they are creating for the great service they provide.  Clubs like Kilmacud Crokes, Ballinteer St. John's GAA Club and Naomh Olaf GAA Club in my area along with soccer and rugby clubs are all under pressure to deliver facilities for adults and particularly children.  We talk about obesity.  The Acting Leader has been very vocal and outspoken in a positive way about the dangers of screen time and not getting enough physical activity.  I urge her to arrange a debate on that issue.  We need sufficient facilities for all ages to use.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#J00400"><p>I wish to raise the plight of MS Ireland and the fact that about 12 months ago, sanction was provided for the post of specialist MS nurse at University Hospital Limerick to cover the mid-west.  This position has not been filled.  While there were all sorts of promises relating to the position being advertised, etc., and it has been advertised, it has still not been filled, which is very worrying.  The number of people being diagnosed with MS is increasing.  In the report that was done at the time, it was recognised that there should be at least three to four nurses in the mid-west region but even one would be of some support and consolation to MS Ireland.  Could the Minister for Health come to the House to tell us when this post will be filled because we are now at a crucial point for MS Ireland?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#J00500"><p>I wish to raise the cross-border health directive and the urgent need for additional staff in that unit.  As Members are aware, people who have been on a waiting list for a long time can avail of healthcare in another EU state and recoup the costs from the HSE.  It can be availed of anywhere in Europe but the reality is that most people, including people from Monaghan, Cavan and elsewhere, will avail of that service in Northern Ireland.  The scheme has proved very popular among those who, unfortunately, languish for long periods of time, many of them in pain, on waiting lists.</p> <p>The scheme's popularity has exploded.  In 2014, 57 processed applications for reimbursement went through that unit.  In 2018, the figure exploded to 5,379.  The one difficulty people have with this is the long delay in reimbursement.  Some people are waiting up to five or six months to get money back, which puts great stress, strain and financial pressure on people awaiting reimbursement.  I understand that the cross-border health directive unit has made representations to the Department on a number of occasions seeking additional funding for more staff but so far, that has not happened.  I call on the Minister for Health to give additional resources and staff to that unit so that the backlog of people awaiting reimbursement for procedures undergone in Northern Ireland or elsewhere is fast tracked and expedited.  Hopefully, the Acting Leader will put my request to the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#J00600"><p>Senator Gallagher was the last speaker but people come out of the woodwork.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#J00700"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach for his indulgence-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#J00800"><p>But the Cathaoirleach will take me.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#J00900"><p>I will try.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#J01000"><p>The appearance of FAI officials before the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Transport, Tourism and Sport yesterday raises some issues, mainly those to do with procedure, that we should also consider in this House.  I have not been a fan in the past of Oireachtas committees going too far and I certainly opposed the referendum that would have given Oireachtas committees the power to make findings and judgments that were adverse to people's reputations.  At the same time, I do not like to see Oireachtas committees and elected representatives effectively treated with contempt by people with no respect for what they stand for, who they are supposed to represent and the process under which they are supposed to work</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#K00100"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#K00200"><p>I must intervene at this juncture.  First, we have no role in how Oireachtas committees work.  Second, if there is an issue, the Chairman is the Chairman of that particular committee.  I am not the Chairman of the committee.  I have no function.  I am not going to comment.  Other avenues are open to anyone who feels harshly treated.  It is very difficult.  The committee system is independent of both Houses, and so it should be.  If that were not the case, perhaps the Seanad or the D&aacute;il would be able to put fetters on how the committees do their work.  All I am saying to the Senator is to be very c&uacute;ramach.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#K00300"><p>Beidh m&eacute; c&uacute;ramach.  I am getting to the point I want to make.  I want to demonstrate how we can have an input into procedures.  If a committee has a mandate to look into the governance of an organisation, it has to be able to ask questions that are pertinent to making judgments or bringing to light issues that may exist in relation to such governance.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#K00400"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#K00500"><p>That is the first point.  If a person wishes to claim that he or she, on legal advice, cannot answer certain questions, it would be far better if that issue were teased out beforehand.  For example, the specific questions to be asked could be disclosed, as far as possible, to the person being invited to come before the committee.  There should be an onus on the witness to disclose in advance whether he or she believes certain questions go beyond the remit of a committee. We need to get to a situation where some kind of judgment can be made on that.  We have seen it here in terms of how the Executive deals with the Legislature.  It is too easy for people to rely on the idea that legal advice means they do not have to deal with a pertinent issue that is being put before them.  I have no problem with compelling people to come before a committee to answer certain questions.  The committee or the public can then judge how those questions are answered.  There needs to be a way to deal with this situation in order that some kind of judgment can be made in advance to empower the committee to ask certain questions.  The second issue was brought out in the comments made by the president of the FAI.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#K00600"><p>The Senator's time is running out.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#K00700"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach.  He moved to reassure people that the funding which was received from Sport Ireland - from the State, in effect - had nothing to do with the employment and appointment decisions which the FAI made in respect of Mr. Delaney recently.  That was both very unhelpful and very helpful.  It was helpful in the sense that it revealed a certain mindset which considers that there is no need for the Oireachtas to worry about how an organisation is being governed as long as the money it provides to that organisation is being spent properly.  That mindset ignores the obvious reality that money is fungible.  If the Cathaoirleach gives me &euro;50,000 to do a particular job, I can spend that &euro;50,000 doing the job for him, but it also frees up other resources that I have from other sources to do whatever job I want.  If the State is giving money directly or indirectly to an organisation, there has to be much more accountability than we saw at the committee yesterday.  Having said that, people are within their rights to complain if politicians are grandstanding in the media one minute and asking questions at committees as representatives of the public the next minute.  While the committee has to do its job of asking questions on behalf of the public, as Deputy Coppinger and others said, it is obvious that this situation calls for a very specific inquiry to be established by legislation.  Somebody trustworthy should be able to ask any questions that need to be asked, get whatever answers he or she considers appropriate and put a report before these Houses.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#K00800"><p>I thank the Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#K00900"><p>I am calling for an inquiry to be established.  It is the only way to get at the truth of these matters.  People are worried.  They have a fear of corruption.  They do not know what is true and what is not true.  Yesterday's committee meeting did very little to help people to get a better understanding of the situation.  Obviously, this points to an inquiry.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#K01000"><p>I gave the Senator a lot of latitude.  He should be aware that I was involved in the Abbeylara inquiry and I was the Chair of the Judge Curtin committee.  Since then, the courts have put certain fetters on the workings and rights of committees and so on.  That is still a live issue.  This matter should be brought before the D&aacute;il Committee on Procedure and the Seanad Committee on Procedure and Privileges.  I am not sure what avenues are open to those committees.  I will certainly not pass judgment on what happened yesterday, other than to say that certain court decisions in some instances have poured scorn on and put serious roadblocks and fetters on the workings of committees in the direction suggested by the Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#K01100"><p>I had not intended to contribute today, but I have just heard the newsflash about the arrest of Julian Assange at the Ecuadorian Embassy in London.  As the founder of WikiLeaks, Mr. Assange is an important and critical figure in international politics.  I understand he may have been a fairly difficult guest.  He was skateboarding along the corridors and everything.  I do not wish to trivialise matters.  There are very serious human rights implications here.  It is possible that Mr. Assange will be extradited to the United States, where he is very unlikely to receive a fair trial.  The American military is very aggravated by the release of information.  As citizens of the world, we are deeply in the debt of Mr. Assange and WikiLeaks for the release of information about the surveillance of the public, military operations and so on.  Mr. Assange did a remarkable job and so did WikiLeaks.  Every decent fair-minded person should stand up and support him in the situation he finds himself in at the moment.  It is a very awkward and very dangerous thing.  He spent seven years in the Ecuadorian Embassy.  The Ecuadorian authorities have terminated this arrangement now.  They invited the police in and the police arrested him.  He will be appearing in court shortly.  It is important for this House to send a message of support to Julian Assange.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#K01200"><p>I thank those who have raised issues on the Order of Business.  I note the presence of Councillor Mike Cubbard from Galway in the Gallery and welcome him to the Seanad.</p> <p>Senator Ardagh raised the long waiting list for home care packages.  It is very unsatisfactory that almost 200 people are on the waiting list in Dublin.  It strikes me that it might be worthwhile to raise this as a Commencement matter.  I do not know the specific details.  It seems to be a funding issue.  If the Order of Business is anything to go by, there are plenty of issues that we could have the Minister for Health in to discuss.  This is one of them.</p> <p>Senator Ardagh also mentioned a campaign for an Educate Together secondary school.  I do not want to keep saying that the matters raised on the Order of Business are suitable for Commencement debates, but I noted at least six such matters today.  It seems from what the Senator said that an Educate Together secondary school is very much required in the areas of Dublin 2, Dublin 8 and Dublin 12.  It seems to me that the Senator might get a satisfactory answer if she raises this as a Commencement debate matter.  I can relay her concerns to the Minister for Education and Skills.</p> <p>Senator Lawless highlighted the important issue of the provision of driver's licences to asylum seekers.  He referred to Mr. Justice Donal O'Donnell's important judgment.  I agree with the Senator that this needs to be looked at.  We could debate this issue in the House with the Minister for Tourism, Transport and Sport in the near future.  Senator Nash expressed his support for Senator Lawless on this issue.</p> <p>Senator Nash spoke about the Flemish decree, which has been issued by the EU courts.  It seems to me, having looked into this case recently, there is a certain unfairness at its core.  I will come back to the Senator after I have spoken to the Minister about the matter.  It needs to be looked at because it means that people cannot build in areas where they and people belonging to them have lived for many years.</p> <p>Senator &Oacute; Donnghaile raised the case of Emma DeSouza, as he has done on numerous occasions.  It is very relevant in the context of the Brexit debate.  He said that we are awaiting a review by Theresa May.  I cannot imagine that her focus is on a review at the moment.  It seems that the review might not happen in any event.  I will bring this issue to the attention of the Minister.  Clearly, it is unsatisfactory that citizens' rights are not being implemented in the manner that was intended in the Good Friday Agreement.  I understand the Senator's frustration in this regard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#K01300"><p>Go raibh maith agat.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#K01400"><p>Senator Feighan spoke about Brexit developments and complimented those involved in bringing us to a point at which another interim solution has been proposed.  It is a little like Groundhog Day.  For our part, we have done our bit in supporting the UK in getting the best result it can.</p> <p>Senator Leyden raised the issue of a home in County Roscommon.  I am trying to find the name of the property.  Having spoken to Senator Hopkins recently, I know for a fact that she has been working very hard on this issue.  The Minister of State, Deputy Jim Daly; the Minister, Deputy Harris; and the Taoiseach's office have been working on it for the past year and a half.  There is a need for constructive and proactive action.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Catherine Noone:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2354"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2354&amp;amp;pid=CatherineNoone&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=04&amp;amp;day=11"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We need answers on how we support these residents and deal with the future of this unit.  It strikes me as an issue that would be worth raising as a Commencement matter.  Senator Colm Burke raised the issue of the health service supervisory role and I think the debate he suggested on the supervisory mechanism, particularly in the private sector, is a very good suggestion.  As usual, the Senator is very much in tune with the health service.</p><p>Senator Horkan raised the issue of cycling and I commend him for doing so.  His suggestion that we have a debate on that is a no-brainer.  It is disappointing if numbers are reducing.  Like the Senator, I feel there are more people on bikes but maybe there are not.  The debate could perhaps address activity levels and cycling generally.  The point the Senator makes about drivers being frustrated with cyclists and not treating them as well as they might is valid.  Not many of them actually think, "thank God he is on a bike because otherwise I would be a longer time waiting at traffic lights."  That debate would be very worthwhile.</p><p>Senator Byrne referred to the MS society and the need for a specialist nurse in Limerick, and indicated that three or four are necessary although one has been promised.  It seems to be a funding issue and, going back to contributions from other Senators, it is something we clearly could raise with the Minister in a debate.  There is a need for the Minister for Health to come into the House sooner rather than later.  It would also be a good issue to raise on a Commencement debate.  </p><p>Senator Gallagher raised the cross-border health directive unit, which is a very important issue.  It is an excellent initiative.  I spoke to somebody recently who had a hip operation and it all went very smoothly.  Perhaps that person was not as concerned as others might be about getting the refund quickly.  That is a significant issue for people as the amount can be up to &euro;10,000 or &euro;15,000.  It needs to be fast-tracked.  It strikes me as an issue that would be suitable for a Commencement debate to get a more specific answer from the Minister.</p><p>In response to Senator Mullen, I think we were all frustrated by how things developed yesterday at the committee before which the FAI appeared.  It is extremely frustrating that witnesses who were there to facilitate the committee in coming to conclusions and getting to the bottom of an issue could just use legal advice and show an unwillingness to answer questions.  I agree with the Cathaoirleach's point that reviewing this issue at the Committee on Procedure and Privileges is probably the most appropriate course of action.  As the Senator said, there is a necessity to empower committees in that sense.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#L00200"><p>My final point was that we need to go to inquiry stage.  We can see the limitations of the committee now.  It is inquiry time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#L00300"><p>I am coming to the Senator's final point about an inquiry.  The question as to whether there will be an inquiry is above my pay grade as such but when we see what happened yesterday, unless there are serious changes in the FAI, one would imagine there just has to be an inquiry.  I cannot imagine how the FAI could leave a committee meeting like that after all that was put to it and not seriously change how it does business.  There may be political intervention and, if there is, it is something I would welcome.</p> <p>Senator Norris raised the issue of Julian Assange, which is just unfolding.  I am not sure of the exact details.  As the Senator said, there is potential for serious human rights issues and no doubt our Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade is keeping an eye on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.63" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.64" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#L00500">Treaty on European Union and Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union: Motions</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#L00600"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That Seanad &Eacute;ireann approves the exercise by the State of the option or discretion, provided by Article 4 of Protocol No. 19 on the Schengen Acquis integrated into the Framework of the European Union annexed to the Treaty on European Union and to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, to request to take part in the following measure to the extent that it relates to the operational management of the Visa Information System (VIS), the establishment, operation and use of which are governed by Council Decision 2004/512/EC, Regulation (EC) No 767/2008 and Council Decision 2008/633/JHA, the operational management of the Entry/Exit system (EES), established by Regulation (EU) 2017/2226, the operational management of the European Travel Information and Authorisation system (ETIAS) established by Regulation (EU) 2018/1241, and the operational management of the parts of the second generation Schengen Information System (SIS II) governed by Regulation (EC) No 1987/2006 in which Ireland does not participate: Regulation (EU) 2018/1726 of the European Parliament and of the Council on the European Union Agency for the Operational Management of Large-Scale IT Systems in the Area of Freedom, Security and Justice (eu-LISA), and amending Regulation (EC) No 1987/2006 and Council Decision 2007/533/JHA and repealing Regulation (EU) No 1077/2011, a copy of which was laid before Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 22 November 2018.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.66" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#L00900"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That Seanad &Eacute;ireann approves the exercise by the State of the option or discretion under Protocol No. 21 on the position of the United Kingdom and Ireland in respect of the area of freedom, security and justice annexed to the Treaty on European Union and to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union to accept the following measure, insofar as the measure relates to the operational management of Eurodac, as governed by Regulation (EU) No 603/2013, and the operational management of DubliNet, established by Commission Regulation (EC) No 1560/2003:Regulation (EU) 2018/1726 of the European Parliament and of the Council on the European Union Agency for the Operational Management of Large-Scale IT Systems in the Area of Freedom, Security and Justice (eu-LISA), and amending Regulation (EC) No 1987/2006 and Council Decision 2007/533/JHA and repealing Regulation (EU) No 1077/2011,a copy of which was laid before Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 22 November 2018.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.68" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.70" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#M00200">An Bille um an Ocht&uacute; Leas&uacute; is Tr&iacute;ocha ar an mBunreacht (Scaoileadh ar Ph&oacute;sadh) 2016: C&eacute;im an Choiste agus na C&eacute;imeanna a bheidh F&aacute;gtha - Thirty-eighth Amendment of the Constitution (Dissolution of Marriage) Bill 2016: Committee and Remaining Stages</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#M00300"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House.</p> <p>Before Committee Stage commences, I would like to deal with a procedural matter relating to Bills to amend the Constitution.  The substance of the debate on Committee Stage relates to the wording of the proposed constitutional amendment which is contained in the schedule to the Bill.  The sections of the Bill are merely technical and, therefore, in accordance with long-standing practice, the sections are postponed until consideration of the Schedule has been completed.  I ask the Acting Leader to formally move, in accordance with the precedent and Standing Order 152, that consideration of sections 1 and 2 of the Bill be postponed until the Schedule shall have been disposed of.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.72" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>AN SCEIDEAL</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.73" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>SCHEDULE</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#M00800"><p>Amendment Nos. 2 and 1 in the name of Senator Ruane are related.  Amendments Nos. 2 and 1 are to taken together by agreement.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1404" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#M00900"><p>Tairgim leas&uacute; a 2:</p><blockquote>I leathanach 7, idir l&iacute;nte 1 agus 2, an m&eacute;id seo a leanas a chur isteach:<div>&quot;CUID 1</div>2º F&eacute;adfar socr&uacute; a dh&eacute;anamh le dl&iacute; chun scaoileadh ar ph&oacute;sadh a rial&aacute;il.<div>CUID 2</div>2º Provision may be made by law for the regulation of dissolution of marriage.&quot;.</blockquote> <p>I move amendment No. 2:</p><blockquote>In page 6, between lines 1 and 2, to insert the following:<div>&quot;PART 1</div>2º F&eacute;adfar socr&uacute; a dh&eacute;anamh le dl&iacute; chun scaoileadh ar ph&oacute;sadh a rial&aacute;il.<div>PART 2</div>2º Provision may be made by law for the regulation of dissolution of marriage.&quot;.</blockquote> <p>I thank the Minister for being in the Seanad this afternoon.</p><p>I am moving my amendments to the Bill to amend the Constitution on the dissolution of marriage.  This continues from our discussion on Second Stage where Senator Bacik and I expressed concerns about the scope of the proposed referendum as it currently stands.</p><p>As we discussed on Tuesday, the current provision of Article 41.3.2&deg; reads that three main conditions have to be satisfied before a court can grant a divorce: that the spouses have lived apart for four out of five years; that there is no prospect of reconciliation between the spouses; and that proper financial provision has been made for spouses, children and dependants.</p><p>I welcome that the Bill and the proposed constitutional amendments will remove the provisions on time limits from the Constitution.  However, it leaves the rest of Article 41.3.2&deg; intact, ensuring these relatively complex and detailed provisions will remain in the Constitution to further govern how dissolutions of marriage will be granted after the referendum would be, hopefully and presumably, successful.</p><p>There is concern regarding this decision to leave these provisions in the Constitution as while the time limits will be gone, they may pose unnecessary barriers, delay, and distress to those seeking dissolution of marriage.  While these provisions remain in the Constitution our ability to legislate on these ambiguous terms is limited and will always be open to judicial interpretation and reinterpretation.  Without the possibility of stability and continuity in this area, the State risks posing additional and unnecessary distress on former spouses and their children as it will not be able to guarantee with confidence how dissolutions of marriage will proceed through the courts.</p><p>This is the concern, and one which I believe is valid under the current proposals.  These provisions were originally inserted in the Constitution with the expressed intention of making access to divorce more restrictive and it is not comprehensive to fail to touch the remainder of the article in question.</p><p>My proposed amendment, therefore, would delete the entirety of the current Article 41.3.2&deg; and replace it with the language drawn from the empowering provision on the termination of pregnancy inserted into Article 40.3 by last year's successful referendum repealing the eighth amendment, and states: &quot;Provision may be made ... for the regulation of dissolution of marriage.&quot;  This would ensure that reference to the dissolution of marriage would be retained in the Constitution and would be in line with the advice given by the Attorney General on similar concerns relating to the termination of pregnancy provision.  It would ensure the Oireachtas would be free to legislate for these exact same issues, that is, time limits, the prospect of reconciliation, and proper provision in the ordinary primary legislation and outside of any constitutional restrictions.  It is a legally robust proposal that draws from established legal and constitutional precedents and would withstand the high levels of scrutiny required for any proposed change to the Constitution.</p><p>If this change were accepted, we would then be able to provide a clear legal route in legislation for how a marriage would be dissolved with straightforward provisions that would be clear to the public and the Judiciary and would allow for a divorce case to proceed along a clear, transparent and reliable process in the courts.  It would be a superior way to conclusively deal with this long debated issue in Irish politics and to avoid the prospect of a fourth referendum on divorce which, I am sure, fills everyone with dread.</p><p>I hope that the Minister could clarify a couple of issues as a result.  Have there been discussions in the Department as to how these constitutional provisions might play out with the accompanying time limits in the courts?  Was he planning to account for these issues in the primary legislation that he will bring forward if the referendum is successful?  Has the Attorney General been consulted on how much space there will be to regulate these provisions legislatively?</p><p>I welcome that the Law Reform Commission, LRC, will include an examination of the proper provision requirement as part of its next programme of work, but will the Department monitor how, for example, the prospect of reconciliation provision is interpreted?  As I mentioned on Tuesday, concerns were raised by Dr. David Kenny of Trinity College that the time limit provided some form of cover for the reconciliation provision and we want to ensure that the prominence of the reconciliation provision after the referendum does not ensure that Ireland moves away from its system of no-fault divorce.  Concerns have been raised that judges may feel obliged to make substantive inquiries and investigations of the factors causing a marital breakdown to be fully satisfied that there is no prospect of reconciliation.  Judges would, of course, just be fulfilling their duties under the Constitution by doing so but would greatly increase the distress to the individuals involved as their private romantic lives were opened up and analysed in court.  With the provision remaining in the Constitution, this remains a possibility.</p><p>It is Dr. Kenny's view that there would be space to set out guidance in the primary legislation for the criteria and factors that the courts may have regard to when considering whether to grant a dissolution of marriage - nothing that would be binding on the courts but merely some form of indiction of the view of the Oireachtas on how these issues could be dealt with and managed fairly by the Judiciary.  Is this an approach that the Minister is considering in the legislative changes that will come if the referendum is successful?  If we are assured that he was aware of these issues and looking to see how they play out in the courts, perhaps these concerns could be tracked and responded to as needs be.  However, that would seem to be an inferior approach to removing the provisions altogether.</p><p>These are complex issues, and that is  why I table the amendment.  If the amendments were to be accepted, we would be going to the people confidently saying that the issue of divorce will never be on the ballot paper again.  Without the change I propose, I do not believe we could do so with that same confidence.</p><p>We are close to the date planned for the referendum.  None of us wants any undue delay to this important change but these issues are worth debating and teasing out further.  I look forward to the Minister's response.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#M01000"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House.  I welcome this important Bill of which, as I have said, the Labour group, and, indeed, my colleagues in the D&aacute;il, are supportive.  We will campaign strongly for a Yes vote.</p> <p>We recognise that the referendum, if passed, will significantly reduce the current legal delays, and, indeed, financial burdens placed in front of couples who are suffering the trauma of marriage breakdown.  I spoke, on Second Stage, about the unnecessary barriers for couples that the current position represents with the requirement of four out of the previous five years living apart being unduly onerous.  Certainly, we neither wish to see any delay to the holding of the referendum or wish to see the process disrupted.</p> <p>As a veteran of many referendum campaigns, I understand why Governments and those campaigning for a Yes vote tend to be cautious about referendum proposals.  Nonetheless, as I stated on Second Stage, we could be somewhat more radical at times.  Certainly, on the blasphemy referendum in November last, we should have gone further and not only removed blasphemy from the Constitution but removed the other offences in the same article.  It is unfortunate we did not take that opportunity.  I note the Minister's expression.  Caution was probably advised in that regard.  On the other hand, the Constitution is neither the place to be providing for criminal offences or for providing for complex detail of issues of family law, marital breakdown or reproductive health law.</p> <p>I appreciate Senator Ruane's approach in these amendments.  It builds on the approach taken in the 2018 referendum where we simply inserted into the Constitution a facilitative provision enabling the Oireachtas to legislate without setting down the parameters or criteria on which it would have to legislate.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Ivana Bacik:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2248"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2248&amp;amp;pid=IvanaBacik&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=04&amp;amp;day=11"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->That is generally preferable.  It is generally preferable that we do not seek to be too prescriptive in the Constitution as to the detail of family law.  On the other hand, I very much welcome the fact that the Minister has published the general scheme and that he has indicated in advance what the legislation will look like if the referendum is passed.  As I said, I will seek a comprehensive debate on the shape of that legislation on Second Stage.  I will debate whether it is necessary to go for the current proposal of people having to have been separated for two out of the previous three years and whether we should instead look to reduce the requirement to one year out of the previous two, which would deal with the issues around proving irreconcilable breakdown.  It would also be more in keeping with EU norms in respect of requirements for time spent living apart.  If the referendum passes, we will have the opportunity to deal with other means of tackling the legal resolution of marriage breakdown and divorce proceedings through the legislation.  We can have this debate at that time.  I thank Senator Ruane for giving us the opportunity to debate the concept of this amendment to the Constitution.  While I accept the need for caution, very much welcome the current proposal, and will campaign strongly for a Yes vote in the referendum, the point the Senator made is worth considering.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#N00200"><p>I welcome the Bill to the House and I support of my colleague, Senator Ruane's, amendment.  She referred to the fourth referendum.  I remember the first referendum on divorce.  It was probably the scariest public speaking I have done in my life as I was studying in the Gaeltacht at the time - I was nine or ten - and was the only child in the class to speak in favour of the concept of divorce, in quite poor Irish I remember.  Of course that referendum did not pass.  Much later, as a student in UCD, I joined staff and other students in campaigning for the right to divorce.  In the intervening period the debate had evolved and the divorce referendum passed.  In the years since, there has been massive change and evolution.  The understanding of equality issues within families has changed.  Ireland did not experience the great wave of divorces that was feared at the time, rather we gained a greater openness and transparency around issues of equality in the family.  Since then we have had changes to rights in different areas.</p> <p>The reason I support Senator Ruane's amendment is that it provides space for the Legislature to respond to the evolving landscape.  Even in the past few years there has been a greater understanding of issues like coercion and control, which may not previously have been reflected in efforts to understand whether reconciliation was authentic.  The Istanbul convention has been ratified, which again looks to legislation and protection in respect of issues of violence, which can be a contributory factor.  We have, at last, introduced a very strong provision on the rights of the child to our Constitution.  This may alleviate the necessity for the current provision on the welfare of children.  It is a wider constitutional provision to which the Judiciary can give consideration rather than the more detailed and directive content that also exists.  I understand that the legislation is coming and that there is scope to set the tone of how it might be interpreted.  I understand that this will be addressed in the guidelines to be provided to the Judiciary, which will be non-binding.</p> <p>This is often a difficult decision for people to make.  Marital breakdown is often very sad.  This is an opportunity to move on this issue and to have a Legislature responding appropriately to the evolving national and international understanding of these issues rather than having to come back to the issue in another decade to amend the Constitution again.  If we have to come back in a decade, we will.  That will happen at that time.  I would love it if the Minister could share his views on the proposals and valid concerns of Senator Ruane.  I will support the Bill and the referendum to implement a more humane and practical understanding of martial breakdown in Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#N00300"><p>I will check to see who was in the Chair because I am sure that eminent chairperson will, like Senator Higgins, have a recollection of the first time this issue was put to the people back in 1986.  Senator Higgins says she was nine.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#N00400"><p>I may correct the record.  I now realise I was, in fact, 11.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#N00500"><p>The Senator was 11, to be accurate for the record of the House.  I remember that campaign quite well and, in particular, an extraordinary incident during its course.  I do not wish to digress but I was a keynote speaker on behalf of the newly-formed Divorce Action Group in my constituency of Laois-Offaly on a date between April and June.  I believe the referendum was held on 23 or 24 June.  I was a guest speaker but, in the same hotel, my father was a keynote speaker at a meeting organised by the Traditional Values anti-divorce group.  Indeed, he was supported by many of his colleagues in the D&aacute;il.  When I was on my feet in the course of my address to a room of approximately 15 people I could clearly hear the thunderous voice of my father addressing a meeting of approximately 550 at the same time in the same hotel.  We met on the stairs on the way down and he asked me how my meeting went.  He did so in a way that could be described-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#N00600"><p>Was he that tolerant?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#N00700"><p>-----as tongue-in-cheek.  I recall however - and I say this in the context of all referendums - opinion polls in April and May 1986, which showed that in excess of 60% of the Irish people were in favour of change.  When the preferences were counted in June, the percentage in favour had fallen from 61% to 36%.  A total of 63% of the electorate rejected the proposition at that time.  When we, as politicians, put questions to the people, we need to exercise the type of caution mentioned by Senator Bacik.  My concern about the amendments before us is that, through them, Senator Ruane proposes to remove from the Constitution a requirement for proper provision and the requirement that a decree of divorce must be granted by a court.  The requirement that there be no reasonable prospect of reconciliation between the spouses would also be removed.  I heard the reasons put forward.  In the context of this issue, I was keen that we would achieve consensus on the question that would be put to the people with a view towards gaining their approval on 24 May.  In looking at the D&aacute;il debates of some weeks ago, it was clear that many contributors favoured the retention of the requirement for proper provision.  This was also reflected in the outcome of consultations I have had with other Oireachtas Members over recent months and in my consultations with party groupings.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Charles Flanagan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=414"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=414&amp;amp;pid=CharlesFlanagan&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=04&amp;amp;day=11"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I am of the view that proposing an amendment that would remove the proper provision requirement would have the potential to complicate matters and add a degree of complication to the question to be put to the people in the referendum.  I am also firmly of the view that it would open up a wider sphere of debate on what might be described as a clean-break divorce and on the matter of prenuptial agreements.  While there may certainly be merit in having these debates, my concern is that they would divert public attention from the immediate primary purpose of the minimum living apart period and the issue of the recognition of foreign divorces.  As I mentioned on Second Stage, the Law Reform Commission has included in its fifth programme of law reform an examination of the proper provision requirement for divorce.  The outcome will inform future proposals for any legislative reform in this area.  I would, however, be reluctant - I will go further and say it would not be prudent - to propose an amendment to the proper provision requirement in advance of an examination of the issue by the Law Reform Commission of the substantive debate on the issue involved, both in the Seanad and the Lower House and in the wider public sphere.  I am very keen that we now act in such a way that the focus will be on reducing complexity and mitigating the vexed issue of financial exposure, which is an important factor in current family law proceedings.</p><p>Regarding the requirement that there be no reasonable prospect of reconciliation, I would defer to Senator Bacik and other Senators, but my understanding is that this requirement does not often prove to be a difficulty in the matter of a practical application for a divorce.  I have not been in practice in this area for some years, but my understanding, as someone who engaged in the practice of family law, is that the requirement that there be no reasonable prospect of reconciliation is viewed as a formal proof which must be satisfied.  Because of this, I believe the retention of this requirement is unlikely to impede any significant number of persons in bringing applications for divorce in any event.  I am also conscious of a not insignificant degree of hardship now faced by couples in the context of the current delay imposed by the constitutional reference to four out of the preceding five years.  I am keen, however, that we put a question to the people that is reasonably straightforward, answers to a legitimate public demand and can be approached with a fair wind from these Houses.  This is why I will conclude by suggesting to the Senators, or Senator Ruane specifically, that the introduction of a greater level of complexity at this stage is not consistent with the fair wind we received in the D&aacute;il and which I was pleased to note on Second Stage in the Seanad.  I am anxious to proceed, insofar as I can, on the basis of consensus.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#O00200"><p>I will offer a few thoughts on this subject but will reserve most of them for the end of-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#O00300"><p>We are on amendment No. 2.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#O00400"><p>Agreed.  That is what I was about to say.  I will not go beyond what is addressed by the amendments but will respond to one or two things the Minister said, and I welcome him to the House.</p> <p>I was on my way into the Chamber on Tuesday with a half-polished Second Stage speech to deliver when I met Senator Norris on the way out, and he said, "You are too late."  It strikes me that the Bill did not just get a fair wind on Second Stage; it was an almighty gust of wind.  The Second Stage debate was over within a very short period.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#O00500"><p>I think we debated Second Stage for well over an hour.  I was in the Chair.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#O00600"><p>It was not well over an hour because I was coming up to the Chamber at 6.50 p.m. or 6.55 p.m. and the debate was over.  I do not think it started until about 6.05 p.m. or 6.10 p.m., so unless Senator Bacik thinks there are 50 minutes in the hour-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#O00700"><p>It was 6.57 p.m.  I was late for a meeting that was supposed to be-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#O00800"><p>No.  I can show Senator Bacik-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#O00900"><p>We will not argue about it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#O01000"><p>I felt the pang of lateness more than she did.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#O01100"><p>We will stick to the point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#O01200"><p>Two things the Minister said prompted a reflection on my part.  Regarding the requirement that there be no reasonable prospect of reconciliation between the spouses, it is extremely important that provision be made in this regard as a condition of providing for the dissolution of marriage.  Those of us who come from a rural background know that this issue keeps coming up.  Without casting any judgments on any of the individuals or perspectives involved, there are people in possession of land who think twice about getting married and choose to cohabit, and I hear from time to time people calling for the recognition of prenuptial agreements and all kinds of things.  I do not know whether one would describe it as an intended or an unintended consequence, but the very necessary requirement that provision be made shows, in the context of divorce and laws providing for the dissolution of marriage, that this can, unfortunately, have a chilling effect on people getting married at all.  For reasons that I will touch on at a later point in this debate, this is very regrettable.  Regarding the business of there being no reasonable prospect of reconciliation between the spouses, the Minister has effectively just said he is not aware that it is ever invoked or ever critical.  I do not wish to put words in his mouth but I have never heard of a situation in which a divorce was delayed in this regard.  I may be wrong, however.  I do not practice law now, I do not practice in the family courts and hardly ever did, and I would be happy to be contradicted on this if there were evidence to the effect that this requirement is ever even a factor in delaying a process or-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#O01300"><p>Carol Coulter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#O01400"><p>Yes, and has the requirement ever been the cause of an outright refusal of divorce?  I would be interested to know.  I am a big fan of evidence-based political debate.  I talked about this in recent days.  This is another area where I would be glad to be better informed, and the House, while contemplating and considering these issues, should inform and re-inform itself.  It seems to me that if the requirement that there be no reasonable prospect of reconciliation between the spouses is in the Constitution, it is always a strange thing if something that is expressed in the Constitution has no real effect in practice.  At most the requirement should be in the "Directive Principles of Social Policy" section of the Constitution, but it does lead one to ask the question as to why things are aspired to in the Constitution but not delivered on.  If there is a lack of evidence - and I say "if" in case I am wrong and there are mountains of evidence - to the effect that the requirement that there be no reasonable possibility of a reconciliation does affect decision-making in this area, although I do not think there exists such evidence to any significant degree, if the requirement is not having any effect in reality and if divorce is in fact seen as a right and this condition is being given lip service but not being followed through on in any way, it should make us reflect why it is considered desirable to mention that a divorce will only be granted where there is no real prospect of reconciliation.  Of course, there are people here who say that this should not be a requirement, that it should be completely a matter of personal choice.  If the requirement is there, however, how come it has not - if it has not - found any real expression in support of promoting marriage?<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2250"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2250&amp;amp;pid=RonanMullen&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=04&amp;amp;day=11"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Is it a bit like the clause supporting a woman giving care in the home?  We all agree the clause needs to be changed to be less gender specific but, to judge by our economic policy in recent years, it has had absolutely no effect on public policy and I regard this as deeply regrettable.  The Minister's points have caused me to reflect on this.  It is appropriate, as we consider the referendum legislation, that we say a word or two about it, if things are as I have described.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1404" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#P00200"><p>The importance of having this discussion is to ensure the previous case law carries through after the referendum so there would not be undue stress or delay caused by the reconciliation provision as a result of removing the time limit from the Constitution.  Will we begin to interpret the Constitution differently?  Will there be scope to set out guidance, which the Judiciary can take on board or not, whereby previous case law would still be the normal way forward in terms of the dissolution of marriage?</p> <p>In 1986, I was two years old and I am glad to say I do not remember the referendum.  I am sure my parents remember it, and if it had passed at the time, perhaps my family and I would not have had to go to court to change our names to our father's name and he would have been able to get a divorce and marry my mother.  That is my great regret from 1986.  If the referendum had passed, I would not have had to ask for his name to be carried on in mine by changing it through the courts.  I want to put that on the record.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#P00300"><p>Is the amendment being pressed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1404" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#P00400"><p>I will withdraw it.  I do not want to hold up the legislation but I wanted the matter to be considered.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#P00500"><p>I appreciate that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#P00600"><p>I acknowledged the points raised by Senator Ruane.  I have taken careful note of the points raised.  I am confident we will have an opportunity to debate them in further detail on a future occasion.  I acknowledge Senator Ruane's actions in the spirit of consensus I spoke of.  I greatly appreciate the manner in which Senators Ruane and Higgins have approached this.  I am grateful for it and I believe it will be important in the context of the public interaction on this issue.</p> <p>To respond to Senator Mullen very briefly, it is important that anything said is not unduly misinterpreted.  I make clear that any application brought to the courts seeking a decree of divorce is done having regard to the constitutional provisions and having regard to the legal advice on these provisions that is given to both parties.  The requirement that we have a process is time honoured and I want to make it clear, in case there is any misinterpretation or misunderstanding, that the removal of the minimum living apart period in the Constitution will not open the door to what has been described as a form of quickie divorce, automatic divorce or divorce without process.  It will still be possible for the Oireachtas to prescribe a minimum period in legislation in any event.  If the referendum is passed, I intend to introduce the family law (divorce) (amendment) Bill 2019.  I have published the draft scheme of the Bill, which proposes to amend section 5 of the 1996 Act.  This will specify a minimum living apart period of two years out of the previous three.  We will have the opportunity to revisit that in the course of the debate.  I am making clear that this is my proposal, as Minister for Justice and Equality, and it is the proposal that has been accepted by the Government and in a vote of the other House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.104" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Tarraing&iacute;odh siar an leas&uacute; faoi chead.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.105" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.106" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Aonta&iacute;odh an Sceideal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.107" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Schedule agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.108" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>ALT 1</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.109" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>SECTION 1</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.110" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>N&iacute;or tairgeadh leas&uacute; a 1.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.111" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment No. 1 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.112" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Aonta&iacute;odh alt a 1.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.113" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Section 1 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.114" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Aonta&iacute;odh alt a 2.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.115" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Section 2 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.116" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Aonta&iacute;odh an R&eacute;amhr&aacute;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.117" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Preamble agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.118" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Aonta&iacute;odh an Teideal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.119" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Title agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.120" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Tuairisc&iacute;odh an Bille gan leasuithe, glacadh &eacute; chun an breithni&uacute; deiridh a dh&eacute;anamh air agus ritheadh &eacute;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.121" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Bill reported without amendment, received for final consideration and passed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#P02500"><p>Does Senator Mullen wish to make a brief remark?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#P02600"><p>I would like to take a couple of minutes, if I may.  I want to make a few quick remarks.  I probably would have covered them on Second Stage.  It is appropriate, given that we are speaking about important legislation.</p> <p>We live in a culture that seems dismissive of long-term commitment.  To say that marriage is a social good or that it should be for life has become almost taboo.  There are various reasons for this.  For a long time, the idea that the State should recognise an institution such as marriage has been viewed by some as restrictive of their freedom and judgmental of their choices.  This might be called the libertarian critique of marriage.  Then came feminism with all that is legitimate and necessary in its analysis and all that was reactive and destructive in elements of it.  The perception of marriage as an institution that in the past was restrictive of women's choices, well-being and economic independence caused many to desire its overthrow.  Then came what we might call the affirming culture, one in which it is seen as necessary to affirm all choices equally.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#P02700"><p>This is not Second Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#P02800"><p>I know that.  I just want to make a few points.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#P02900"><p>The Senator is allowed to make a few brief comments-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#P03000"><p>It is Thursday afternoon.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#P03100"><p>-----but I ask him to keep them as brief as he can.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#P03200"><p>I promise I will do that.</p> <p>In certain areas of human life, to stress the benefits of one way of doing things is seen as tantamount to causing a negative judgment of those who do not do things in a particular way.  All of this is unfortunate because it is hard to deny that most credible evidence suggests that marriage has always been, for the most part, a social good and that it still is a social good.  In the past, it provided women in particular with stability and protection at a time when women's equal dignity was not recognised and their equal rights denied or at least only taken into account when men's aspirations were fulfilled.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2250"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2250&amp;amp;pid=RonanMullen&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=04&amp;amp;day=11"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Marriage is a good thing for couples.  It provides them and their children with the basis for a stable family unit.  It improves their lot in life, socially and economically, and this, in turn, is a good thing for the State and society as a whole.  That is why it is enshrined in our law in the first place.  To state these facts should not be seen as stigmatising single parents or unmarried couples with children.  I have talked in recent days about evidence-based legislation.  Marriage and the family is another area in which State policy is not evidence-based.  It would be difficult for the Minister to deny this if he heard his predecessor, Deputy Frances Fitzgerald, say during the debate on the Children and Family Relationships Act 2015 that there should be no hierarchy of families in denial of the argument that public policy should encourage a situation in which each child is brought up by a father and mother and, where possible, his or her own father and mother.  Without judging others, it should be a cornerstone of public policy to encourage marriage and assist those whose marriages have broken down to reconcile to the greatest extent possible while acknowledging that this will sometimes be impossible.</p><p>I hope the debate we have when the legislation comes in will be very different to the debate we have had on the referendum proposal.  This referendum proposal merely gives the Legislature the power to change the situation.  During the debate which has taken place so far, there has been no discussion of children's welfare and no discussion about whether we should have public information campaigns on the importance of marriage and greater Government investment in pre-marriage courses.  I will finish very shortly but I compare it to-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#Q00200"><p>It is unfortunate that the Senator missed Second Stage but contributions now are meant to include only a few brief closing remarks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#Q00300"><p>I accept that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#Q00400"><p>There will be a further debate when the referendum is provided for.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#Q00500"><p>When one considers that this is a big change, that the issue will now go to the people and that I will not be-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#Q00600"><p>I cannot allow a lengthy debate at this stage.  There was a lengthy debate on Second Stage and those who were here spoke at length.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#Q00700"><p>I accept that.  I will finish shortly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#Q00800"><p>I am allowing the Senator a few brief closing remarks and have no doubt he will find plenty of other opportunities to be more fulsome.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#Q00900"><p>Indeed, albeit "fulsome" is not a word I like as it actually has a pejorative meaning which the Leas-Chathaoirleach does not intend in this instance.  We need to discuss why the first significant Government policy since the redefinition of marriage in 2015 is about making it easier to bring a marriage to an end.  When are we going to discuss what we can to proactively as a society to promote not just marriage but life-long marriage and to promote as a specific social good the long-term union of men and women for the upbringing of children?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#Q01000"><p>I totally agree.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#Q01100"><p>That would be an evidence-based situation.  In conclusion, I look forward to a debate when we can consider how marriage has been impacted since the last divorce referendum, for example.  Reference was made earlier to the idea that people said the floodgates would open.  That was not a significant part of the debate in 1995.  People were talking then about the impact of divorce on children and the connection between divorce and financial status, poverty and other such challenges.  Those questions have not gone away and we should not be afraid to discuss them.  I hope that at a later point, if the referendum passes-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#Q01200"><p>I hate to hurry the Senator as a I probably agree largely with his views.  I am trying to apply the correct procedure.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#Q01300"><p>I understand and the Chair has to do that.  I hope, in conclusion, that if the referendum passes, which I suspect it will, although I will certainly not campaign against the proposal, of which I am sceptical, all the more so since I have not seen the energy around promoting stable marriage, we will have a sincere discussion-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#Q01400"><p>I have no doubt the Senator will.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#Q01500"><p>-----about what we can do as a society to promote marriage, not just as one choice among many, but as a social good that serves the welfare and well-being of children.  It is something this Government and other Governments have ignored for far too long.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" speakername="Gabrielle McFadden" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#Q01600"><p>I thank the Minister and his officials for their work thus far on the Bill and I thank the House for its co-operation today and on previous days.  I welcome the Bill very much.  I remember the 1980s also, although I was not two years old.  As with the Minister and his father, there was a split in my family.  My father campaigned with Paddy Cooney on one side while my aunt campaigned on the other.  One does not know anything about a situation until it visits one's own home.  When my sister went through a marriage break-up in the early 1990s, through no fault of hers, my father changed his opinion very quickly.  Until it visits one's own family, one cannot really say.  Marriage is not about stability for women or anything like that.  Marriage is a partnership and if it breaks down and cannot be reconciled, no one should have to go through four years of living in a bad situation.  I thank the Minister and his officials and welcome the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#Q01700"><p>If for no other reason than to place it on the record, I must note the scant application of the rules and Standing Orders of the House.  We have had a Second Stage speech from Senator Mullen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#Q01800"><p>The Minister only got part of it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#Q01900"><p>I would be happy to listen to Senator Mullen but it should be in accordance with the Standing Orders of the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#Q02000"><p>I hate to interrupt the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#Q02100"><p>I am interrupted on all occasions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#Q02200"><p>I am in the Chair and am advised that the application of the rules is a matter for the Chair.  I am not going to interrupt the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#Q02300"><p>I have done in excess of 100 hours here on a Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#Q02400"><p>I appreciate that.  I have been in the Chair for a large part of it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#Q02500"><p>Of those 100 hours, we had four yesterday and I have to note my disappointment at the lack of application of Standing Orders and rules here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#Q02600"><p>I assure the Minister that I am doing my best.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#Q02700"><p>I say one thing to Senator Mullen, who is going to interrupt me.  He based the entirety of his criticism of the proposal on the matter of children.  For the benefit of the House, I note, as I did on Second Stage, that children will not be rendered more vulnerable if the minimum living apart period is removed from the Constitution because the courts will still be required to consider whether proper provision has been, is being or will be made for spouses and children.  That is in accordance with the Constitution and it is not being changed.  That is why I seek the consensus which is desirable in the circumstances.  I welcome Senator Mullen's statement that he will not campaign against the proposal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#Q02800"><p>On a point of order-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#Q02900"><p>I will take a point of order, but it must be a point of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#Q03000"><p>The issue here is with the concluding remarks.  I do not know where it is defined in Standing Orders, but for the reassurance of the House, I am certainly not-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#Q03100"><p>It is not defined anywhere.  It is a tradition.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#Q03200"><p>-----playing silly buggers when I get up here and make a few sincere points.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#Q03300"><p>Everything is permitted at the discretion of the Chair.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#Q03400"><p>The Minister will be generous enough to acknowledge a distinction.  I do not play procedural games to draw debates out.  I never do.  What causes me regret is the fact that there is not enough seriousness in this place sometimes to have a full debate on important issues.  The Minister then digressed into contradicting a point I never made.  I did not make any claim about the content of the legislation.  I lamented the lack of attention to children's welfare generally by way of evidence-based policies in all of these areas in which political correctness now dominates to the exclusion of what the evidence might tell us is in children's best interests, most particularly where children are actually killed with the support of the law.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#Q03500"><p>Senator, the Bill has passed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#Q03600"><p>The Bill, as discussed on Committee, Report and Final Stages, will help children by not putting them through the trauma many children and families are enduring currently because of the lengthy time lapse.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#Q03700"><p>I look forward to the Minister's support for my amendments on positive things the Government might do.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.168" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#Q03900">An Bille um an Ocht&uacute; Leas&uacute; is Tr&iacute;ocha ar an mBunreacht (Scaoileadh ar Ph&oacute;sadh) 2016: An R&aacute;iteas mar Fhaisn&eacute;is do V&oacute;t&aacute;laithe: Motion - Thirty-eighth Amendment of the Constitution (Dissolution of Marriage) Bill 2016: Statement for the Information of Voters: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#Q04000"><p>Tairgim:</p><blockquote>GO nD&Eacute;ANFAR an r&aacute;iteas at&aacute; leagtha amach sa Sceideal a ghabhann leis an R&uacute;n seo a fhorord&uacute; mar fhaisn&eacute;is do v&oacute;t&aacute;laithe, de bhun alt 23 d&rsquo;Acht an Reifrinn, 1994 (Uimh. 12 de 1994), i nd&aacute;il leis an togra chun an Bunreacht a leas&uacute; at&aacute; ar &aacute;ireamh sa Bhille um an Ocht&uacute; Leas&uacute; is Tr&iacute;ocha ar an mBunreacht (Scaoileadh ar Ph&oacute;sadh), 2016 agus is &aacute;bhar do reifreann bunreachta.</blockquote> <p><b>An Sceideal</b></p><p><b>An Bille um an Ocht&uacute; Leas&uacute; is Tr&iacute;ocha ar an mBunreacht (Scaoileadh ar Ph&oacute;sadh), 2016</b>- An p&aacute;ip&eacute;ar ball&oacute;ide uaine</p><p><b>An R&aacute;iteas mar Fhaisn&eacute;is do V&oacute;t&aacute;laithe</b></p><blockquote>Fiafra&iacute;tear d&iacute;ot, sa reifreann seo, an aonta&iacute;onn t&uacute; leis an togra &ndash;(a) chun an mh&iacute;r seo a leanas a scriosadh as Airteagal 41.3.2&deg; den Bhunreacht:<blockquote>&lsquo;i go raibh, ar dh&aacute;ta thionscnamh na n-imeachta&iacute;, tr&eacute;imhse ceithre bliana ar a laghad, n&oacute; tr&eacute;imhs&iacute; ceithre bliana ar a laghad san ioml&aacute;n, caite ag na c&eacute;il&iacute; ina gc&oacute;na&iacute; ar leithligh &oacute;na ch&eacute;ile le linn na gc&uacute;ig bliana roimhe sin,&rsquo;, agus</blockquote>(<i>b</i>) chun an fo-alt seo a leanas a scriosadh as Airteagal 41.3 den Bhunreacht:<blockquote>&lsquo;3&deg; I gc&aacute;s p&oacute;sadh duine ar bith a scaoileadh faoi dhl&iacute; shibhialta aon St&aacute;it eile agus an p&oacute;sadh sin, agus bail dl&iacute; air, a bheith ann f&oacute;s faoin dl&iacute; a bheas I bhfeidhm in alt na huaire taobh istigh de dhl&iacute;nse an Rialtais agus na Parlaiminte a bhuna&iacute;tear leis an mBunreacht seo, n&iacute; fh&eacute;adfaidh an duine sin p&oacute;sadh ar a mbeadh bail dl&iacute; a dh&eacute;anamh taobh istigh den dl&iacute;nse sin an fad is beo don duine eile a bh&iacute; sa chuing ph&oacute;sta a scaoileadh amhlaidh.&rsquo;,</blockquote>agus an m&eacute;id seo a leanas a chur in ionad an fho-ailt sin:<blockquote>&lsquo;3&deg; F&eacute;adfar socr&uacute; a dh&eacute;anamh le dl&iacute; chun aitheantas a thabhairt faoi dhl&iacute; an St&aacute;it do scaoileadh ar ph&oacute;sadh arna thabhairt faoi dhl&iacute; sibhialta st&aacute;it eile.&rsquo;.</blockquote>M&aacute; <b>thoil&iacute;onn </b>t&uacute; leis an togra, cuir X os coinne an fhocail <b>T&aacute; </b>ar an bp&aacute;ip&eacute;ar ball&oacute;ide.<br /><br /><b>Mura dtoil&iacute;onn</b>t&uacute; leis an togra, cuir X os coinne an fhocail <b>N&iacute;l </b>ar an bp&aacute;ip&eacute;ar ball&oacute;ide.<br /><br />F&eacute;adfar f&eacute;achaint ar ch&oacute;ip den Bhille ar an idirl&iacute;on ar www.oireachtas.ie.</blockquote> <p>I move:</p><blockquote>THAT the statement set out in the Schedule to this Resolution be prescribed for the information of voters, pursuant to section 23 of the Referendum Act 1994 (No.12 of 1994), in relation to the proposal to amend the Constitution which is contained in the Thirty-eighth Amendment of the Constitution (Dissolution of Marriage) Bill 2016 and is the subject of a constitutional referendum.</blockquote> <p><b>Schedule</b></p><p><b>Thirty-eighth Amendment of the Constitution (Dissolution of Marriage) Bill 2016</b>- Green ballot paper</p><p><b>Statement for the Information of Voters</b></p><blockquote>You are being asked, in this referendum, if you agree with the proposal &ndash;(<i>a</i>) to delete the following paragraph from Article 41.3.2&deg; of the Constitution:<blockquote>&lsquo;i at the date of the institution of the proceedings, the spouses have lived apart from one another for a period of, or periods amounting to, at least four years during the previous five years,&rsquo;, and</blockquote>(b) to delete the following subsection from Article 41.3 of the Constitution:<blockquote>&lsquo;3&deg; No person whose marriage has been dissolved under the civil law of any other State but is a subsisting valid marriage under the law for the time being in force within the jurisdiction of the Government and Parliament established by this Constitution shall be capable of contracting a valid marriage within that jurisdiction during the lifetime of the other party to the marriage so dissolved.&rsquo;,</blockquote>and to substitute that subsection with the following:<blockquote>&lsquo;3&deg; Provision may be made by law for the recognition under the law of the State of a dissolution of marriage granted under the civil law of another state.&rsquo;.</blockquote>If you <b>approve </b>of the proposal, mark X opposite the word <b>Yes </b>on the ballot paper.<br /><br />If you do <b>not approve </b>of the proposal, mark X opposite the word <b>No </b>on the ballot paper.<br /><br />A copy of the Bill may be viewed on the internet at www.oireachtas.ie.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.170" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Cuireadh agus aonta&iacute;odh an cheist.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.171" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#Q04200"><p>When is it proposed to sit again?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.173" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041100002#Q04300"><p>Next Tuesday, at 2.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-11a.174" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>The Seanad adjourned at 1.10 p.m. until 2.30 p.m. on Tuesday, 16 April 2019.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>