<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.2" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 14:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.4" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.5" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#A00100">Gnó an tSeanaid - Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from the following Senators that they propose to raise the following matters:</p> <p>Senator Fiona O'Loughlin - The need for the Minister for Justice to establish a domestic violence register in Ireland.</p> <p>Senator Martin Conway - The need for the Minister for Health to make a statement on his plans to deliver a package of appropriate healthcare supports and compensation package to Thalidomide survivors.</p> <p>Senator Paul Gavan - The need for the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage to make a statement on the application from Limerick City and County Council for a dedicated affordable homes team.</p> <p>Senator Lisa Chambers - The need for the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage to increase the qualifying income threshold for council housing assistance supports for a qualifying family in band 3 and implement a commensurate increase in bands 1 and 2.</p> <p>Senator Malcolm Byrne - The need for the Minister for the Environment, Climate and Communications to provide an update on the implementation of the provisions of the Circular Economy and Miscellaneous Provisions Act 2022, with regard to the deployment of CCTV and other technologies to address illegal dumping.</p> <p>Senator Se&aacute;n Kyne - The need for the Minister for Health to provide an update on the delivery of a new emergency department at University Hospital Galway.</p> <p>Senator Lynn Boylan - The need for the Minister for the Environment, Climate and Communications to make a statement on the possibility of mobile phone and broadband blackouts this winter in the event of power cuts.</p> <p>The matters raised by the Senators are suitable for discussion and I have selected Senators Fiona O'Loughlin, Martin Conway, Paul Gavan and Lisa Chambers and they will be taken now.  The other Senators may give notice on another day of the matters that they wish to raise.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.7" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#A00300">Nithe i dtosach suíonna - Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.8" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#A00400">Domestic Violence</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#A00500"><p>I welcome the Minister, Deputy McEntee, to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#A00600"><p>I thank you, a Chathaoirligh, for affording me the opportunity to address the need for a domestic violence register in the country.  I appreciate the Minister's taking the time to come to the Chamber to respond to this important Commencement matter.</p> <p>Saturday, 1 October should have been Jennifer Poole's 26th birthday.  She was a lovely, vivacious young woman with two young children.  Very sadly her life was taken from her in April last year and this certainly should not have happened.  At the recent Fianna F&aacute;il Ard-Fheis, Jennifer's brother, Jason, joined Deputy O'Callaghan and me to talk about the horrific trauma his family suffered, not just with the loss of Jennifer's life and the way her life was taken in just seven minutes in a brutal and vicious way, but the fact that Jennifer was taken from her family by a former partner who was known for domestic violence.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Fiona O'Loughlin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2441"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2441&amp;amp;pid=FionaOLoughlin&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The main reason we had this conversation was to try to ensure a register of domestic abuse offenders could be set up.  Jennifer was a strong woman.  She had a previous relationship where sadly, she was subjected to domestic violence.  She would have been very nervous of knowingly going into another relationship with someone who had a pattern of domestic abuse, but she did not know.  Her former partner said he had been living in Spain for two years.  Sadly, as her family found out later, she was subjected to domestic abuse, but had the strength, power and courage to leave her situation.  This brings up so much for so many women and indeed for many men.  Many choices have to be made and some people ultimately make the choice to stay in a relationship.  Jennifer gathered her courage and wherewithal to ensure this man left her home but in a moment of vulnerability, she allowed him back in because he said he needed access to a warm shower.  In the time after Jennifer's death one of the most difficult aspects of the case came to light - that her murderer had been jailed for more than two years for attacking his former partner with a knife.  If a domestic violence register was in place in the same way as a sexual abuse register, there is no doubt but that An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and Jennifer would have been aware of his past and she would never have entered a relationship in this situation.  It is clear we need a domestic violence register.  It is absolutely something we need to implement.</p><p>Sadly as we know, violence against women is an epidemic in this country.  In 2021 Women's Aid reported 28,096 disclosures of abuse and 96% of those supported on the freefone helpline were women.  In the aftermath of the brutal death of Ashling Murphy, the women of Ireland came together in solidarity with the Murphy family.  Many of us attended vigils outside Leinster House and around the country.  The hurt, anger and sorrow was palpable and the Minister has put many measures in place since.  She has doubled the number of places in refuges and we need to go further than that.  We need to look at a number of areas but what Jason Poole has highlighted is an important issue.  </p><p>At the time of Ashling Murphy's death, I stood here in this very spot and said, "As a person, I am horrified; as an aunt and friend to young women, I am frightened; as a woman, I am furious, but as a legislator, I am determined to respond."</p><p>That is what this Commencement matter is about.  It is about responding, raising awareness and protecting those who need to be protected, so I ask the Minister what the Department will do to establish a domestic violence register and what the Department is doing to support local garda&iacute; to deal with domestic violence cases.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1502" speakername="Helen McEntee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#B00200"><p>I thank Senator O&rsquo;Loughlin for tabling this issue specifically and more generally raising the issue of domestic violence and the work we are doing collectively to respond to it.  We can all agree it is an issue that has not had the attention or focus it should have had for many years, but that is changing.  While I will respond on a number of different fronts to the Senator's questions, I will say from the outset, having met Jason Poole and discussed the tragic circumstances of his sister's death - she was a beautiful young woman who should not have been killed in the way she was - I have asked this to be examined as a priority and that is ongoing.</p> <p>In response to the Senator's last question about how we are supporting An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and how we are responding to this issue more generally, I published our most ambitious strategy to date on domestic, sexual and gender-based violence at the beginning of June this year.  It is a whole-of-government strategy and is based very clearly on the four key pillars, namely, prevention, protection, prosecution and policy co-ordination.  I assure this House and anyone else listening that our zero tolerance strategy is not the end achievement to our work in this area; it is just the start.</p> <p>We hosted European counterparts last month at the Council of Europe ministerial conference on violence against women, and I explained to some of my colleagues exactly what we mean by "zero tolerance".<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Helen McEntee:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2394"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2394&amp;amp;pid=HelenMcEntee&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It means ensuring that strategies aimed at preventing and combating violence against women also address the specific role of men and boys in preventing violence.  Zero tolerance means greater education and greater awareness to change attitudes and to teach respect from an early age.  It means teaching our children equality, respect and healthy sexuality, again making sure that it is done in an age appropriate way.  It means supporting victims with compassion and with care when they come forward and when they take what is an extremely brave step in coming forward and seeking help.  It means effective training for all relevant professionals, including our medical professions, our legal professions, our doctors, our nurses, our Judiciary and so many others, in particular our garda&iacute;.  It means recognising the importance of long-term and systematic changes that need to happen and that is why there is a huge amount of structural changes happening within Government in terms of where services in the future will be provided and the establishment of a domestic violence agency.</p><p>It also means having robust legislation in place and Senator O'Loughlin mentioned the fact that the individual in question had served time for a previous offence against a partner.  To make sure that we have effective sentencing, what I brought forward the Criminal Justice (Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill 2022 is an increase in the maximum sentence of assault causing harm from five years to ten years, and it passed through the Second Stage last week.  We have seen too many cases where victims have had bones broken and where, as I mentioned before, sugar and boiling water thrown over them and where they have been stabbed, but the sentence has not been high enough because the bar has not been high enough.  We need to make sure those options are there for the Judiciary.  It also means making sure we tackle human trafficking and sexual exploitation.</p><p>The fundamental weapon we have in combating domestic violence is prevention.  It is the core pillar on which our strategy is built but it is prevention that is in mind today when we talk about this topic.  When Jason Poole talks about a register, it is with prevention in mind.  We cannot change what has happened to Jennifer, unfortunately, but we can make sure insofar as we possibly can that this does not happen to another person, to another young woman.  That is obviously what we all want to achieve here.</p><p>As I mentioned, setting up a domestic violence register was something I discussed with Jason Poole when we met earlier this year.  I have spoken to him in the last few days.  We have discussed this with Garda Commissioner Harris.  I have had a number of conversations with the Garda Commissioner and we agreed that it should be included in the third national strategy as a priority for in-depth analysis and consideration.  As Senator O'Loughlin will know, it is a key action in the strategy published in June.  I have continued to engage with the Garda Commissioner on this matter, as recently as last week, and I am awaiting a report on this matter.  It is important that I do not move ahead on something without understanding how it works in other jurisdictions, how it might possibly work here and the views and potential approaches of the people who are due to implement it.  Simply importing a model from another jurisdiction with a different constitutional arrangement to our own, where we have a written Constitution and judicial oversight of the Oireachtas in our work on enacting legislation, runs a risk of potential challenges and also that it might not work in the same way.  While there is a register in some areas of the UK, we have to look at how that would potentially work here.  We do not want something to be challenged.</p><p>We also have other complications around the fact that we have European General Data Protection Regulation, GDPR, legislation that we need to comply with.  We need to ensure there is no situation where a person could be falsely identified.  All of these things have to be thought through.  However, I stress there should never be a situation where someone's personal privacy overrides another person's right to be safe.  I have always had that to the forefront of anything I do.</p><p>The Department of Justice is funding the Dublin Rape Crisis Centre and the National Women&rsquo;s Council to undertake research to identify and address issues arising from the interface between civil and criminal courts, where there might be a criminal trial happening where a person has attacked a partner and where there might be a civil trial happening where they are then seeking access to a child and maintenance.  I am informed that the question of a register has been raised in that draft report and once I get that report and the report from the garda&iacute;, we will see how the two could potentially work together.  Instead of replicating something that might work in the courts, we will look how we could maybe merge the two together.</p><p>I reassure Senator O'Loughlin that work is ongoing with the Garda Commissioner and his team and with the specific family justice oversight group and on the work that has been commissioned by the Dublin Rape Crisis Centre and the National Women's Council of Ireland.  I hope once I get the two of those we will be able to pave a pathway forward.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#C00200"><p>I thank the Minister, Deputy McEntee.  I apologise that the clock was out by two minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1502" speakername="Helen McEntee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#C00300"><p>I was looking at the clock thinking I had more time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#C00400"><p>No, we have a problem with the clock.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1502" speakername="Helen McEntee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#C00500"><p>That is okay.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#C00600"><p>Senator O'Loughlin has one minute to reply.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#D00100"><p>Any time we are discussing domestic violence, it is important to say to those listening that if they recognise these signs in regard to somebody else or themselves, there is help and support out there.  The helpline number is 1800 341 900.</p> <p>I thank the Minister for her response.  It is important and it is clear that this is a priority for the Minister and the Government given that the Minister is actively looking at setting up a register for those who have committed domestic violence.  I accept that it is simply not good enough to adopt legislation from another jurisdiction because we are very blessed in that we have a Constitution and everything has to be constitutionally sound.</p> <p>It is really important we keep the pressure on.  Last Saturday was not the first time I heard Jason speak.  Each time I hear him I hear the trauma, sadness and desperation.  It is really important we deliver on this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1502" speakername="Helen McEntee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#D00200"><p>While this is obviously a key priority for Jason, I know there are many other issues he has been focused on and I am pleased to work with him and many others to make sure we can make those changes.  We have seen an increase in reports and numbers of people going to the Garda reporting domestic violence and sexual offences over the last year.  We can look at that in two ways.  First, unfortunately with Covid-19, there have been new cases as well as an increase in violence across the board.  Second, I see it as a positive in that more people are coming forward.</p> <p>The whole focus of so much of what we are doing is that we can encourage people to come forward where they are victims, separate from prevention which is absolutely key, and that when people do come forward that as many measures as possible are in place through the criminal justice system and the courts system in support from individuals who come into contact with victims and survivors.  It is just one part of a wider puzzle that would help and hopefully support people to get themselves out of difficult situations or to prevent them from getting into potentially very critical situations.  This is a priority for me and something I will continue to work on.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.21" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#D00250">Thalidomide Victims Compensation</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#D00300"><p>I welcome Finola Cassidy to the Visitors Gallery.  She is very welcome.  I know she is an amazing champion.  I commend the Senator on raising this issue.  I welcome the Minister.  The Senator has four minutes to set out his Commencement matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#D00400"><p>Go raibh maith agat, Acting Chairperson.  I fully agree with your sentiments in welcoming Finola to the Public Gallery.  Finola is the spokesperson for the Irish Thalidomide Association and it is fitting and appropriate that she should be in the House today to hear the response from the Minister.  Two weeks ago tomorrow in D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann, the Lower House, the Taoiseach responded to a question from Deputy Bacik based on the "Scannal" documentary which had been broadcast the night before.  It laid bare the facts of the effect that the thalidomide drug has had on people in this country.  </p> <p>There are four women who are in their 90s and who have survived.  They took the drug through no fault of their own.  The drug was removed from the market 61 years ago next month.  Even though it had been removed internationally, it was not removed in a timely manner in Ireland.  There are four issues here that need to be responded to.  First, it needs to be acknowledged by the Government that it did not act in a timely manner in terms of removing the drug and the consequences thereafter were as a result of this delay.  Once the knowledge was available, the drug should have been removed instantaneously, as happened in other countries.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Martin Conway:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2347"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2347&amp;amp;pid=MartinConway&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->That should have been removed instantaneously as was the case in other countries.  The second thing that needs to happen is that there needs to be a State apology delivered by the Taoiseach in D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann, similar to other apologies that have happened in the context of other victims who were let down by the State.  The third thing that needs to happen is negotiations need to happen immediately with the survivors to put in place an appropriate healthcare package that will deal with their needs going forward.  There are just under 30 people who the State acknowledge have been damaged long term and permanently as a result of their mothers taking this drug.  The fourth thing that needs to happen relates to the approximately 12 people internationally who have had an expert opinion that they have been affected as a result of this drug, and that needs to be acknowledged by the State.  That would bring the number up to 40.</p><p>There are four asks, and they are clear.  The first one is an acknowledgment in the first instance.  The second is an apology, which everybody across the political divide appreciates needs to happen.  The third is the compensation package in terms of healthcare supports and appropriate compensation needs and again, this is accepted across the political divide.  The fourth relates to the remaining women who have not had an acknowledgement from the State that this drug has caused them the problems they have, even though irrefutable international evidence from renowned experts supports their case and indicates that this has happened.  They are very simple asks.  Court cases have been ongoing for the bones of a decade and they should not be ongoing.  Quite frankly, the cost of these ongoing court cases would more than fund the care package that is required and the compensation that is needed.</p><p>The Taoiseach spoke in the D&aacute;il almost two weeks ago.  He gave a commitment that he would be back in touch with Finola Cassidy within two weeks.  That two weeks will be up tomorrow, so this Commencement matter is timely.  In the first instance, it reminds the Taoiseach of his commitment.  I know that he is an honourable person and that he will follow up on it.  It also reminds the Minister of State, Deputy Feighan, and the Department that this scandal has been ongoing for a decade and that it needs to be resolved.  Next month will be 61 years since this drug was removed from the shelves of Irish pharmacists and yet the consequences are still ongoing.  The people have not been compensated.  The people have not had an acknowledgement or an apology.  I await the Minister of State&rsquo;s response.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#E00200"><p>I thank the Senator, who made a crystal-clear ask.  The Minister of State has four minutes to respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1608" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#E00300"><p>I want to thank Senator Conway at the outset and indeed many others for raising important matter and for providing me with an opportunity to speak about it in the House.  I am sure that the Senator will appreciate that because a number of cases concerning thalidomide are before the High Court, it is not possible to comment on matters that are <i>sub judice</i>.  However, the Government recognises that thalidomide survivors face very real challenges in everyday life in the context of their injuries.</p><p>I am glad to inform the House that the Minister met with members of the Irish Thalidomide Association in February.  At that meeting, he listened to their health concerns and assured them of the Government's commitment to provide thalidomide survivors with the necessary health supports to meet their related needs.  The HSE has designated a senior manager to liaise with Irish thalidomide survivors and assist them in accessing health and personal social services.  Following the meeting with the association, the HSE thalidomide liaison commenced a process to develop recommendations for future planning and pathways for survivors&rsquo; healthcare needs now and into the future.</p><p>The recommendations will also inform the work that is already under way in the Department of Health to place the provision of these health and personal social supports on a statutory footing, as committed to by the Government.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Frankie Feighan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2014"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2014&amp;amp;pid=FrankFeighan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Since 1975, the Government has provided financial assistance to each Irish thalidomide survivor, including an <i>ex gratia</i>lump sum and an <i>ex gratia</i>monthly allowance for life.  The annual figure for the Irish monthly payments ranges from &euro;6,175 to &euro;13,313 for each individual.  As the Senator said, there are currently 29 Irish people in receipt of these supports from the Department of Health.  Irish survivors are also eligible for monthly payments and a range of annual special payments from the Contergan Foundation, which is established under German legislation.  Both the German payments and the Irish <i>ex gratia</i>monthly payments made to survivors are exempt from tax, including deposit interest retention tax, and are not assessable as means for the purpose of Department of Social Protection payments.  Each survivor is also eligible for a medical card on an administrative basis regardless of means.  In addition, survivors are eligible for aids and appliances, equipment, housing adaptations and access to the full range of primary care and hospital and personal social services.<br/><br/>It is also important to note that the German Contergan Foundation has confirmed that since 2013, it is accepting applications from individuals for compensation for thalidomide-related injury.  It is open to any Irish person to apply to the foundation for assessment of his or her disability as being attributable to thalidomide.  Any Irish person who establishes that his or her injury is attributable to thalidomide will be offered appropriate supports by the Irish Government, commensurate with those currently provided to Irish thalidomide survivors.  I assure the House that the Irish Government is committed to the continued support of the health and personal social service needs of Irish thalidomide survivors to enable them to live independent lives.<br/><br/>The Senator mentioned four issues, one of which was that the drug was not removed in a timely manner and the Government should have acted at that time.  The Senator has called for a State apology in the D&aacute;il.  He also stressed the need for negotiations with survivors to ensure an appropriate healthcare package to continue.  He also said that 12 further people have received expert opinions that they have also been affected by thalidomide.  He asked for them to be included in the State's response to bring the number of cases that require acknowledgment to 40.  I will bring those details to the Minister and will try to get the Senator a response as quickly as possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#F00200"><p>I know the Minister of State is going to meet Ms Finola Cassidy after this Commencement matter.  I appreciate that and thank him for doing so.  I also thank him for his reply.  There is no time here.  Six of the women who took this drug are in their 90s.  These people, sadly, do not have an enormous amount of time left.</p> <p>I know what is involved in organising a State apology.  It needs to happen soon.  There needs to be an acknowledgement that the State was wrong and acted in an inappropriate way by not removing the drug.  Those things both need to happen quickly.</p> <p>In respect of compensation, while I accept what the Minister of State has outlined in his reply, an awful lot more needs to be done.  These people's lives have been impacted, and very seriously in some cases.  They have not been adequately compensated at all.  Their medical needs are not being dealt with in the way they ought to be.  We need to urgently resolve the situation of the 12 people in this country who are suffering and are not being recognised by the State.</p> <p>As time goes on, people's lives move forward.  We are dealing with elderly people.  We are dealing with 40 people who are struggling on a daily basis because of thalidomide.  I ask the Minister of State to make a call to the Taoiseach's office to remind him and his officials of the commitment he made in the D&aacute;il two week ago.  The timeline outlined then expires tomorrow.  I have no doubt but that the Taoiseach will want to honour his commitment.  When the Minister of State goes to his office this evening, he might make that call.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1608" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#F00300"><p>I again thank the Senator for raising this important matter.  I have heard the debates on this issue in the Houses in recent years.  As I said, it is, unfortunately, not possible to comment on matters that are <i>sub judice</i>.  I reiterate the Government's commitment to continuing to provide the range of supports, including monthly payments, health and personal social services, to thalidomide survivors.  We want to continue to provide for the complex and unique health and social service needs of survivors to enable them to live with dignity, particularly as some of them are more than 90 years old.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Frankie Feighan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2014"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2014&amp;amp;pid=FrankFeighan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I am confident the process underway to develop recommendations for pathways of care for survivors' current and future healthcare needs will greatly enhance the provision of these services.  I also look forward to the development of statutory proposals, which will be informed by this process and will place the provision of these supports and services on a firm statutory footing.  I will notify the Taoiseach and his office about meeting with the group as soon as possible.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.31" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#G00200">Local Authority Staff</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#G00300"><p>I wish to raise the issue of resourcing for the housing department of Limerick City and County Council, specifically the need for a dedicated team to drive affordable housing targets forward.  Right now, the same staff are trying to keep their social housing targets on track while also having to share time to keep their affordable housing projects up to speed.  Clearly, this is neither ideal nor sustainable.  I will set out the context for what we are dealing with in Limerick so the Minister of State will understand the extent of the housing emergency.  Homelessness figures have gone up to 10,805, including 3,220 children, throughout the State.  The number of homeless children in need of emergency accommodation in the mid-west last August saw a 251% increase in the same period last year.</p><p>Rents are rising.  The figure for Limerick is &euro;1,400, which is way above housing assistance payment, HAP, limits.  I took a look at <i>daft.ie</i>today.  Just seven properties are available on <i>daft.ie</i>, three of which are completely out of the price range of any normal family.  The HAP allowance is just &euro;650 for a couple with one child but a two-bedroom apartment will cost them &euro;1,500 per month.  The HAP allowance for a single person is just &euro;420 but a studio apartment in Limerick will cost him or her &euro;1,300 per month, so there is no reality when it comes to the allowances and the soaring cost of rents in Limerick.  We are running out of options for emergency accommodation.  Indeed the homeless action teams have told us this.  We also have the phenomenon of adult children stuck living their adult lives with their parents.</p><p>I think the Minister of State will agree with me that Limerick City and County Council has a huge task on its hands.  Looking at the targets towards which it is working, approved homes are at 42% of the five-year target of 2,138 new homes.  In other words, the council has a deficit of 1,247.  I understand the focus for this year and next year is to acquire more land and gain more approvals to ensure the targets are met, but frankly, the council is nowhere near being able to do that as things stand.  Again, the targets are particularly poor in some areas.  In Castleconnell, where I live, there are 443 applicants and the current plan is for five new social or council houses.  That is an appalling target.</p><p>We need significant additional resources within Limerick City and County Council to deal with this.  An application was submitted to the Department of Housing, Local Government and Heritage for funding for a dedicated affordable housing team in March 2022.  It begs the following question.  In the middle of a housing emergency, how long does it take the Department to make an approval?  I heard from my colleague Councillor Sharon Benson today that, coincidentally, the council received a decision today regarding additional new staff.</p><p>Why has it taken seven months to make a simple decision to add resources to Limerick City and County Council?  Furthermore, I understand the council made a request initially for 12 additional staff and then reduced it to ten, but what has been granted by the Government is just staffing of four, of which two are already in place, so after seven months of waiting, the decision of the Government is to add just two additional staff members.  The Minister of State should bear in mind that once that funding is approved, as it apparently was this morning, we are probably looking at a further six months to advertise and interview and for people to give notice and actually fill those positions.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paul Gavan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2469"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2469&amp;amp;pid=PaulGavan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It has taken more than a year, during the worst housing emergency we have ever seen, for a decision to be made and for the relative follow-up to happen.</p><p>The Government&rsquo;s Housing for All plan is not working.  Overall targets for new social and affordable homes are falling short throughout the country, and that is no wonder.  If every other council is waiting on resources just like that in Limerick, the national targets will continue to be missed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1595" speakername="Peter Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#H00200"><p>I thank the Senator for his question regarding the application by Limerick City and County Council for a dedicated affordable homes team.  In September 2021, the Government published its Housing for All strategy, which sets out plans to increase the supply of housing to an average of 33,000 homes per annum over the next decade.  Increasing the supply of affordable housing is a central element of Housing for All, with an ambition to deliver more than 55,000 new affordable and cost-rental homes in the period 2022 to 2030, with 28,730 of those homes being delivered over the next five years.</p> <p>Housing for All is supported by a major investment package of more than &euro;4 billion per annum through an overall combination of &euro;12 billion in direct Exchequer funding, &euro;3.5 billion in funding through the Land Development Agency and &euro;5 billion in funding through the Housing Finance Agency.  With the support of the housing delivery co-ordination office in the Local Government Management Agency, the Department undertook a review of the requirements for affordable housing staff resources in 18 local authorities with an identified strong demand for housing from households with an affordability constraint.  Limerick City and County Council was one of those councils. </p> <p>The housing delivery co-ordination office undertook a detailed analysis with each local authority to assess its existing housing delivery capacity and skill set and identified any additional staffing requirements, having regard to the level of affordable housing to be delivered in that local authority.  Key consideration has been given to the type of structure and administrative or professional staff necessary to deliver affordable housing, the scale of the delivery programmes and alignment with the additional support provided for social housing delivery earlier in 2022.  The staffing required and identified for Limerick is divided into both administrative and professional staffing grades and a higher requirement in most areas for administrative support is acknowledged due to the operation of the various schemes in terms of agreements, engagement with eligible applicants and other, longer term requirements. </p> <p>Limerick City and County Council has developed a housing delivery action plan to underpin its delivery of social, affordable-purchase and cost-rental housing in the period to 2026.  The Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage recently approved an application by Limerick City and County Council for funding of &euro;1.8 million for 25 affordable homes in Castletroy, Limerick, under the affordable housing fund, which will be delivered in 2023.  An application is ongoing with Limerick City and County Council for a dedicated homes team, notice of which the Senator received today.  I have no doubt that any additional staff Limerick City and County Council receives will help expedite its efforts to deliver new affordable homes in key locations throughout the city and wider county.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#H00300"><p>I acknowledge that the Minister of State is handed a script to read out in response to these Commencement matters but, with respect, I request an answer as to why it has taken the Government seven months to decide to appoint new staff.  Moreover, why has that decision been taken to appoint just two additional staff given Limerick City and County Council requested a team of ten, given it has been well acknowledged that the council, like so many other councils, is way behind its targets and given it has also been acknowledged that the Government is way behind its targets?  Indeed, its target this year for social and affordable housing was 9,200 homes but at the halfway point it had delivered just 1,966.  Similarly, its target for affordable housing was 2,100 but it had reached fewer than 700 by the halfway point of the year.</p> <p>With the crisis getting worse month by month, how can the Minister of State explain the seven-month delay in appointing essential staff for the council, and where does this leave the people of Limerick, who are already in despair at the housing crisis?  Are we looking at a future of adult children living adult lives in their parents' homes?  Is that the best the Government can offer?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1595" speakername="Peter Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#H00400"><p>I must correct the Senator; the Government is on target to meet its social housing numbers this year.  We are almost approaching the figure of 9,000 new social units having been added, which will be the key to resolving so many housing issues for our citizens, and we are on course to build in excess of 25,000 homes this year, which will meet our target.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Peter Burke:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2457"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2457&amp;amp;pid=PeterBurke&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->That will be critical in implementing the Housing for All strategy.  It is important to correct the record on that.  The notion that we have only built in excess of 1,500 homes this year is almost farcical.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#J00200"><p>There were only 980 from 2020 and 2021.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#J00300"><p>The Senator should allow the Minister of State to finish.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1595" speakername="Peter Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#J00400"><p>There are 31 local authorities in the country.  The Affordable Housing Act was put through this year and the fund was established.  It is key to ensuring we will not be behind in making sure all local authorities have the resources.  In many areas it is not about the resources; it is about councils getting good applications in and having their land serviced and ready to go for affordable housing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#J00500"><p>The Minister of State is blaming the councils now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1595" speakername="Peter Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#J00600"><p>Many can go through private developers and we have seen a number of acquisitions from the affordable housing fund in that regard.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.43" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#J00700">Housing Policy</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" speakername="Lisa Chambers" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#J00800"><p>The Minister of State is welcome.  I tabled this matter in order to ask the Government to consider increasing the income threshold for housing assistance supports from the current rate of &euro;30,000 for a family in band 3 - which includes those in my county of Mayo - to &euro;50,000.  I have tabled this matter on foot of a motion that was passed by councillors in Mayo calling for just that.  We have been looking for this for a very long time.  It is quite obvious that the income thresholds that are currently in place are extremely low.  There are three bands, with &euro;30,000 as the upper limit in a county like Mayo.  It goes up above &euro;40,000 in Dublin.  That is still extremely low by any standard.  It essentially precludes low-income working families and households from accessing social housing supports.  We need to change this.  We need to make sure social housing is available for many more people.  We know the demand and the need is there.  I do not think there is any public representative in this country who does not know about the need to expand the threshold and increase the income limits.  I look forward to the Minister of State's reply.  I know there is a review ongoing in the Department on this issue.  I would welcome an update that I might pass on to my colleagues on Mayo County Council.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1595" speakername="Peter Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#J00900"><p>I thank the Senator for tabling this matter.  I also thank her council colleagues for putting forward such a timely motion, which is very important to ensure that people have access to secure housing.</p> <p>A standard system for assessing applicants for social housing support was introduced in 2011.  The income bands and the authority area assigned to each band were based on an assessment of the income needed to provide for a household's basic needs, plus a comparative analysis of the local rental cost of housing accommodation across the country.  Housing for All was published in September 2021 and contained a commitment to reviewing income eligibility for social housing.  The review has been completed and the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage, Deputy Darragh O'Brien, has recently approved implementation of its recommendations.  The review is now available on the Department&rsquo;s website.</p> <p>On foot of the review, the Minister has approved proposals to scope and develop options for a revised or new social housing income eligibility model.  The exercise will assess the suitability of the current framework, having regard to the significantly changed landscape since it was introduced, and will make recommendations for an approach and income thresholds for Mayo and all other counties that reflect current and future needs.  This work will commence shortly under the aegis of the Housing Agency, which will be tasked with commissioning it.  It is expected that the work will be completed in the first quarter of 2023.</p> <p>Pending its completion, the Minister has also approved changes to the social housing income eligibility bands for five local authorities, namely, Carlow, Clare, Galway county, Laois and Westmeath.  These counties have been moved from band 3 to band 2 of the income eligibility framework.  Accordingly, the baseline income eligibility threshold for these areas has increased from &euro;25,000 to &euro;30,000.  The change reflects the significant movement in rents in these areas in recent years and ensures local authority areas with similar accommodation costs will continue to be grouped together in the respective bands.  The changes came into effect on 1 October last.  The Minister believes it is now appropriate to await completion of the substantive review before deciding on the revised income threshold levels for Mayo and other counties, given the potential impact of any changes that will arise.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#J01000"><p>The Senator was very concise in her request and the Minister of State was very concise in his reply, so they both have extra time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" speakername="Lisa Chambers" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#J01100"><p>I welcome the Minister of State's response.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Lisa Chambers:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2449"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2449&amp;amp;pid=LisaChambers&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is good to see that the Government is finally moving on this and that a review has been conducted.  There should be a greater level of urgency.  It is hoped to have it in quarter 1 in 2023, but we should be demanding to have it at that stage.  People are struggling to meet their housing needs and we know there are particular challenges in all counties.  I welcome that some counties have moved up from band 3 to band 2.  One could say that maybe other counties should have been moved also.  In Mayo, for example, the income eligibility threshold being down at &euro;25,000 and &euro;30,000 between a single person and a family is extremely low.  When looking for a three-bedroom property three or four years ago, a person could reasonably expect to get one to rent for in the region of &euro;700 or &euro;800.  Now it is about &euro;1,400.  This has just happened in the past three or four years.  The increase in rent in the last number of years in a county such as Mayo has been absolutely phenomenal.  If one checks <i>daft.ie</i>or other rental websites or local auctioneers on any given day, one will find in the region of 20 properties to rent in total for the entire county.<br/><br/>I completely support the call by councillors and the county councils to increase the income thresholds to a level that includes people who are working but are on lower incomes.  The fact that we have a housing support system in place that effectively precludes anybody who has a job and is working is not good for society, it is not good for mixed tenure development, and it is not good for the way local authorities operate.  We are getting this directly from local elected members who are on the ground and working in this space.  They know the housing need in their areas.  The councillors in Mayo know the housing need in the area and they have made a direct request to the Minister of State, the Minister and the Government to address that deficit.  I ask the Minister of State now that we would have a little bit more detail as to when the review and the recommendations will be implemented.  When will we see a direct correlation between that and the actual supports being available on the ground?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1595" speakername="Peter Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#K00200"><p>I thank Senator Chambers for raising this matter.  I will raise it with the Minister.  When speaking last night in the debate on RT&Eacute;1, the Minister committed to having the review before the end of the year.  I will communicate this to him and to the Housing Agency, which is under the aegis of the Department, to speed up that review.  I really do appreciate that so many citizens are caught in a trap of not being able to access housing and government supports, which are so vital for them to sustain a tenancy.  This is very important.  We really do need to ensure that this report is expedited insofar as possible.  We will work to do that.  I will talk to the Minister, on foot of what the Senators has said, in order to see if we can get it completed before the end of the year.  I really do appreciate the urgency.  As I travel around the country, this issue is raised by many councillors on a weekly basis.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.50" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar fionra&iacute; ar 3.18 p.m. agus cuireadh t&uacute;s leis ar&iacute;s ar 3.30 p.m.<br /><br />Sitting suspended at 3.18 p.m. and resumed at 3.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.51" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#N00100">An tOrd Gnó - Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#N00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, statements on the summer programme, to be taken at 4.45 p.m. and to conclude at 6.15 p.m., if not previously concluded, with the opening remarks of the Minister not to exceed ten minutes, group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes, all other Senators not to exceed five minutes, time can be shared, and the Minister to be given no less than eight minutes to reply to the debate; No. 2, Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na (Compensation) Bill 2021 [Seanad Bill amended by the D&aacute;il] &ndash; Report and Final Stages, to be taken at 6.15 p.m., and No. 3, Judicial Appointments Commission Bill 2022 [D&aacute;il] &ndash; Committee Stage, to be taken on the conclusion of No. 2, to adjourn at 8.30 p.m., if not previously concluded.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" speakername="Lisa Chambers" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#N00300"><p>Thank you, a Chathaoirligh.  I agree with the Order of Business, as outlined by the Leader of the House.  There are a number of issues to raise.  I express my concern at the apparent disappearance of Elnaz Rekabi, who then re-appeared on Instagram a number of days later.  She is the Iranian rock climber who was pictured competing in one of the rock climbing events without her hijab or headscarf and later could not be found.  Her passport had apparently been confiscated.  A number of days later, she appeared on Instagram apologising for the unintentional non-wearing of the headscarf.  It is deeply concerning, along with other young women continuing to lose their lives in the Iranian protests.  This happened to a young 33-year-old woman competing for and representing her country at an international competition.  After public outcry, thankfully, she appears to be alive and appears to be well.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Lisa Chambers:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2449"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2449&amp;amp;pid=LisaChambers&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We do not really know what happened in the intervening period, which is deeply concerning.<br/><br/>I reiterate my call that Ireland, as a member of the UN Security Council, and the Minister for Foreign Affairs, Deputy Coveney, who has direct contact with the Iranian ambassador to Ireland and the Iranian foreign minister, continue to call for full and transparent disclosure of all those who have lost their lives, for the Iranian authorities to desist in the use of force against peaceful protestors and, of course, for the full human rights of women in Iran to be enforced and protected as a given and that they not have to dress as per the demands of the dictatorship that is enforcing those rules.<br/><br/>On a more positive topic, I attended the opening of the specialist menopause clinic at the Rotunda Hospital this morning.  It is the fourth such clinic to open in the country in the past year.  By the end of this year, we will have gone from zero menopause clinics to six fully operational specialist clinics.  The country is unrecognisable today in how it treats women's healthcare compared even with five years ago.  We have made huge progress on this.  I commend the Minister for Health, Deputy Stephen Donnelly, the health service, the Rotunda Hospital and the healthcare professionals who are providing this much needed service.  It is long overdue and it is fantastic to see it in operation.  Women of my generation have access now to much more information than was the case in the past.<br/><br/>I acknowledge that Ireland launched the first ever national menopause awareness campaign on Friday last.  There is a brand-new Government website, <i>gov.ie/en/campaigns/menopause</i>, on which women can find all the information they need about symptoms and where they can get help and treatment.  That was not there for my mother's generation or the generations who went before.  I understand from speaking to menopause campaigners that we are the first country in the world to have a national menopause awareness campaign.  I have spoken to campaigners in the UK, US, New Zealand and Australia and they are asking how we did this because they want to replicate it.  It is great to see Ireland leading the way on this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#O00200"><p>I am changing the order of speakers to accommodate Senator Sherlock, whose mother is in the Gallery.  She is most welcome.  Also in the Gallery are members of the St. Luke's bridge club in Cork, whom I likewise welcome to Seanad &Eacute;ireann.  I invite the Senator to address the Order of Business and her mother.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1645" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#O00300"><p>May we heckle?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1683" speakername="Marie Sherlock" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#O00400"><p>I am delighted members of the St. Luke's bridge club are joining us.</p><p>I welcome the eviction ban that was announced earlier, which comes after many months of our being told that it would not be possible.  We were told about the possible constitutional challenges and the unseen legal advice and given warnings landlords would exit the sector.  Landlords are already exiting the sector.  The ban is being introduced now simply because there is no emergency accommodation left in this city or, indeed, in other parts of the country.  Why is the ban being delayed until November instead of being implemented now?  I ask that when the legislation is introduced, the ban be applied retrospectively.</p><p>I raise this issue because I am dealing with a family - I am sure all Senators are dealing with similar situations - made up of a mother and her four children aged seven, six and twins aged three.  They were due to be evicted at the end of September but were given an extra month to the end of October.  Their landlord died a number of months ago and the relatives want to sell the property.  This family will not benefit from the eviction that is being introduced in November because they must be gone by the end of this month.</p><p>We have asked Dublin City Council about availing of the tenant <i>in situ</i>scheme for the family.  There are all sorts of regulations and red tape associated with it.  Unfortunately, the council is of the view it cannot buy the house in question because it deems it substandard.  This means a mother and four children will, in effect, be homeless at the end of this month, notwithstanding that the eviction ban will start the following day.  My sincere plea is that the ban be brought forward.  It is long overdue and its introduction by the Minister is very welcome.  We need to see it brought into force without delay.</p><p>Some weeks ago, I raised the issue of security workers.  This was supposed to be a good news story, whereby 16,000 of them had negotiated a pay deal with the vast majority of employers in the sector and the Minister had signalled his willingness to sign off on the wage agreement.  However, an injunction was taken out on 24 August.  All these weeks later, the State has failed to enter any defence against that injunction.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Marie Sherlock:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=MarieSherlock&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We know a separate court matter is being taken in November regarding the constitutionality of the security employment regulation order.  When that goes to court, however, it will be put off for another six months or more.  All the while, we have very low-paid security workers in this country who are only getting a tiny pay increase and who the State is not standing up for.  There is a very serious issue involved.</p><p>We have been told by the Department of Enterprise, Trade and Employment and by the relevant Minister that confidential conversations are going on in the background.  For these security workers, nothing is happening.  Like everybody else, they are in a cost-of-living crisis.  For anybody talking about how we need to support low-paid workers, the State is not standing behind the pay deal on which it almost signed off.  We need to see some action from the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1665" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#P00200"><p>I am a great believer in process and allowing processes to run their course.  It was a great disappointment that last Friday in Galway, while at a very positive event with Genesys opening its new office at Bonham Quay in the heart of the city, word began to filter through that An Bord Plean&aacute;la had decided not to defend the legal action being taken against the Galway city ring road.  There are questions on a range of issues here, but particularly our planning laws and An Bord Plean&aacute;la itself.</p> <p>As Senators will have read in the newspapers, and this is hard to believe, the board admitted in its letter that it was not aware at its final meeting that a new climate action plan 2021 had been adopted four days previously on 4 November 2021.  How it could not be aware is one thing that is hard to fathom and believe.  The fact that a mistake or oversight, if that is what it was, by An Bord Plean&aacute;la could - but hopefully will not - scupper a project that has been worked on for years in Galway is another matter.</p> <p>This is only the latest incarnation of the road project.  Work commenced on the original project as far back as 1999.  Therefore, we are being left behind other cities like Cork, Limerick and Dublin where both road infrastructure and other infrastructure is powering ahead or has at least seen adequate development.</p> <p>The original bypass project was a road project only.  This incarnation of the Galway city ring road was part of the Galway transportation strategy.  A power of work had been done by the city and county councils combined with the democratic support of the local authorities and council members to progress this project as part of the transportation strategy.</p> <p>Only in the last number of weeks, the cross-city bus link project has gone to planning.  We see work going ahead on the new pedestrian cycle bridge at the salmon weir and other projects that are planned within the city.  We have also seen improvements in other areas and plans for a new greenway for Moycullen that will aid and reduce the pressure on the city.  However, we are still in limbo in terms of the next stages.  Thankfully, the county council on behalf of the city council and Transport Infrastructure Ireland stated that it is confident that the issues arising can be resolved and, as a result, intends to continue to progress the delivery of the Galway city ring road.</p> <p>The people of Galway cannot be treated in this manner.  Whether it was an oversight or a mistake by An Bord Plean&aacute;la, I hope it this does not scupper a vital project for Galway city.  I have said before that we need a debate on the whole area of planning.  The Government is looking at its planning laws but we have a situation where we cannot allow planning and decisions to be drawn out year after year and, indeed, for decades when it comes to infrastructure in Galway city.  Galway deserves better, and we need better.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1645" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#P00300"><p>On 31 August, I wrote to the Minister for Transport, Deputy Ryan, and the Minister of State, Deputy Naughton, following a request from a member of the public about tender documents that had been released by the Department of Transport for the procurement of consultancy services for search and rescue services.  My letter questioned why there were two very similar tenders in the marketplace.  The first detailed tender issued in June and closed on 31 August.  The second tender, which seemed to be for the same job, required less expertise and closed recently.</p> <p>In my letter, I questioned how these tenders would be adjudicated on given that we have no aviation expertise within the Department of Transport despite this being a key recommendation of the air accident investigation unit, AAIU.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Gerard P. Craughwell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2402"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2402&amp;amp;pid=GerardPCraughwell&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->By way of reply, I received a letter from the Secretary General of the Department of Transport in which he states the following:</p><blockquote>	That document is not in the public domain. It was provided only to entities who passed Stage 1 of the process ... Your possession of that document is a cause for serious concern. Consequently, officials from this Department, at my request, have consulted the Office of the Chief State Solicitor and the Office of the Attorney General.<br /><br />In order to protect the integrity of the procurement process I wish to ask you: how did you come into possession of this confidential R[equest] F[or] T[ender]?  I also request that you would not read, print, copy or circulate this document to any other third party.  Please delete from your email system any emails or attachments where the R[equest] F[or] T[ender] can be found electronically and destroy any hard copies if any have been made. </blockquote><p>As public representatives, all Members of this House will, from time to time, receive documents and possibly questions which are of concern to members of the public.  I believe we are obliged to bring the concerns of the public to the relevant Minister or Ministers.  That is exactly what I have done.  I have to say I was rather shocked by the intimidating reply from the Secretary General of the Department.<br/><br/>We are living in stressful times.  Nothing is more certain.  The report of the fatal crash of Rescue 116 provides indisputable evidence of a litany of reckless behaviour and failings on the part of the Department of Transport, the Irish Coast Guard and the operator of this vital service.  Changes were recommended.  Equally, our taxpayers need to be protected from decisions which lead to poor value for money.  The Department of Transport and the Irish Coast Guard have been shown to be lacking in their capacity to remain an intelligent customer for aviation in general and in search and rescue, SAR, in particular.  Yet, instead of complying with the recommendations of the AAIU, they still have no aviation expertise and instead rely on consultants.  The Department can tender for experts to minimise risk but it cannot tender out responsibility.  I am disturbed that any civil servant would be unaware of the Howlin <i>v.</i>Morris judgment on the private papers of Members and would feel he or she could use his or her position to intimidate a Member or a public representative-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#Q00200"><p>Senator, in relation to the language used in respect of the letter from the Secretary General, while of course you are entitled to bring up issues like that, describing it as intimidating-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1645" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#Q00300"><p>It was intimidating for me.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#Q00400"><p>Okay.  Just be careful about language.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1645" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#Q00500"><p>It was intimidating for me.  When a Member of this House is told that an email that was sent to Ministers is being referred to the Office of the Chief State Solicitor and the Office of the Attorney General, that is intimidating.</p><p>I would like the Minister for Transport to come to the House to reassure all Members that he does not support or subscribe to any form of intimidation.  I ask the Secretary General to comply with Article 83 of EU Directive 2014/24/EU and appear before the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Transport and Communications to deal with the substantive issues surrounding the SAR contract.  No Member of the House should be subjected to any form of intimidation.  I take the Cathaoirleach's point on the word &quot;intimidation&quot;, but this is not the first threatening letter I have received from the same Department.  The Secretary General must surely be aware of the Howlin <i>v.</i>Morris judgment and of the fact he cannot compel me to produce any document or to deliver the names of people who have contacted me.  There is a massive amount of concern, not just from me but from those who are interested in providing services to this country, that they are not being dealt with particularly well.  The Secretary General has an opportunity to come before the Joint Committee on Transport and Communications and answer the questions that need to be answered.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1693" speakername="Pauline O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#Q00600"><p>First, I highlight World Menopause Day, which Senator Chambers has already mentioned.  In May 2021 in the convention centre, I raised the issue of the menopause.  I felt a little bit nervous doing so.  We speak about all sorts of other issues, but we had not really spoken about the menopause.  I received a bit of a backlash following that, because certain members of the medical profession felt that perhaps I was blaming them for the experiences women had when they went to their GPs.  While I am certainly not blaming individuals, I am blaming a medical system that let down women for a long time.  We know that 50% of this population experience the menopause, which is nothing to be ashamed of, and 91% of women say they experience symptoms.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Pauline O'Reilly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=PaulineOreilly&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We need to talk about the menopause, and that includes the medical profession.  I am pleased to see that the first menopause clinic has opened and that the Minister for Health has taken on this issue.  It is welcome to see, under this Government, that we are prioritising women's health.  It is welcome we have menopause awareness week.  We must also look at the education system when it comes to any medical professional who has contact with women because the first port of call is the person that one goes to and explains one's symptoms as one actually does not know what is wrong.  Even today, I read a report where someone said their symptoms made them fear they had early onset Alzheimer's disease.  Therefore, the first person one encounters needs to understand fully what the menopause is, to be able to identify it and then say where one needs to go.  We have come a long way but we have not reached where we need to be when it comes to the menopause.  Lastly, people's careers and professions are deeply impacted by the menopause.</p><p>I welcome the decision by An Bord Plean&aacute;la to admit that it did not take into consideration the climate action plan.  Five months before the decision was made by An Bord Plean&aacute;la, it knew that the climate Act had passed and that it was a relevant body for the purposes of that Act.  Therefore, it was disingenuous for An Bord Plean&aacute;la to write in a letter that the climate action plan had only been published four days before when it knew its full obligations.</p><p>We must be honest with people that climate action requires us to take steps that are sometimes a little bit uncomfortable.  Many people do not realise that only 3% of the traffic in Galway city tries to get from one side of the city to the other side.  In particular around Galway city, there is no consensus that a road is the best solution and I believe a road would push people even further out of the city, thus increasing sprawl.  For all kinds of reasons a road is not the best approach.  The politicians have probably not been honest with people in Galway for a long time and that is why we are where we are.  Thankfully, progress is being made with public transport and cycling options, in particular for Galway city.  Let us celebrate that progress and advance these initiatives.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1688" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#R00200"><p>I wish to raise three items.  First, I, too, welcome the ban on evictions but, like my party leader said in the D&aacute;il today, we need action to be taken now or as soon as possible.  It is safe to say, and it is definitely safe to say on behalf of my party and, I am sure, on behalf of all of the groups on this side of the Chamber, that we stand ready to assist the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage and his Government colleagues to ensure the legislation is put through speedily, efficiently and effectively.  Families have come forward to speak about their experience of living in tents, and that shames us all.  We need to get this legislation through as soon as possible for all of the reasons we know.</p> <p>Second, the D&aacute;il will debate a Sinn F&eacute;in motion that seeks to ban energy disconnections and provide crucial protections for pay-as-you-go customers.  Much like my previous commentary, the Government proposal that such a ban would not come into effect until December simply is not good enough.  I ask colleagues to support tonight's motion in the D&aacute;il to ban energy disconnections, not in December, not in November but now when people need it most and when we know people are facing into an already difficult winter across a range of aspects of the cost-of-living crisis.  We know from last night and last week just how cold the nights are getting.</p> <p>Last, I wish to make it known that Belfast City Council has put out a public tender calling on artists to create two life-size or even larger sized statutes of Mary Ann McCracken and Winifred Carney to be located on the grounds of Belfast City Hall.  Anyone familiar with the grounds will know it is a lovely location at which to spend a sunny afternoon eating one's lunch but there are not many women depicted in the form of statues on the grounds.  There are not too many progressives or Irish republicans depicted on the grounds either.  I welcome the fact that a tender for both statues has been issued and artists from all across society are invited to submit a tender.  Many colleagues here regularly engage with artists and the cultural community so I ask them to make artists aware of the tender.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2477"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2477&amp;amp;pid=NiallODonnghaile&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Mary Ann McCracken is probably best known as being the sister of Henry Joy, but she was a hell of a lot more than that.  She was an abolitionist and a humanitarian.  Right up until she was in her 80s, she was down at Belfast docks handing out literature opposing the slave trade.  She is a very well-known figure in her own right.</p><p>Winifred Carney was James Connolly's aide-de-camp in the GPO.  She was known as the typist with the Webley.  She stood for Sinn F&eacute;in in the famous 1918 general election in my part of the world, east Belfast.  I have one very quick story if the Cathaoirleach will indulge me.  I remember listening to a talk on the life of Winifred Carney.  She was ordered to leave the GPO by Connolly when he was injured.  He told her to take off her Sam Browne belt in order that she would not be recognised and identified as having taken part as a member of the Citizen's Army.  Connolly ordered her to take off her belt.  Not only did she refuse to leave the GPO garrison and take off the badge, she actually removed the badge and carved her name, Winifred Carney, into it in order that she would definitely be known as having been in the garrison and involved in the Rising.</p><p>The deadline for submissions is 11 November.  I use this opportunity to encourage artists to put in their tender and I ask colleagues to do likewise.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1657" speakername="Eileen Flynn" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#S00200"><p>Over the past few weeks, I have called for the Minister, Deputy O'Gorman, to come to the House to debate ending direct provision.  I again thank the Leader for writing in and for supporting it.  Unfortunately, I will need to submit a Commencement matter for next two or three weeks until I can get him in the House.</p> <p>It has come to my attention and to the attention of many other Senators that people in direct provision who are employed, no matter how small their job might be, will be required to pay rent.  The Government can make it sound as nice as it wants, but it is still rent that people will have to pay.  Where did this idea come from?  Who is responsible for deciding that people living in direct provision will have to pay rent?  Would anyone here pay rent to live in a system that does not meet their needs?  From speaking to people living in direct provision, I know it is a cruel system.  Basically, all they have is a safe space.  Earlier I spoke to a woman who told me she has to share a bathroom with four other families.  Will we next ask women placed refuges to pay rent?  It is really getting serious when we are asking people living in direct provision to pay rent.  I know it is for those who have a job.</p> <p>It also came to my attention earlier that officials from the International Protection Accommodation Services are going into refugee centres and if people have their papers, they are being asked to move out.  How can people move out of these centres when they have no homes or anywhere else to go to?  We have a major problem that we need to deal with.  The Minister can hide away from it, but we need to get him to come to the House to ask him these questions.  At the end of the day, this is a humanitarian crisis and we should not be asking these people with little or no money to pay rent.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1630" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#S00300"><p>Today I am seeking leave to amend the Order of Business to introduce a Bill on behalf of the cross-party group on cancer care of which I am chair.  I refer to the Central Bank (Amendment) Bill 2022, which is colloquially known as the "right to be forgotten" Bill.  The aim of the Bill is to ensure that cancer survivors are not denied access to financial products, such as life insurance, due to their past medical history.  This is particularly pertinent for those who might be diagnosed with childhood cancer or cancer in their teenage years.  Research shows that nearly a quarter of cancer survivors have had difficulty accessing financial products in the past.  I hope this Bill will go some way to help reduce their difficulty and allow them go on to lead normal lives into the future.</p> <p>My colleague Senator Gavan will be seconding the Bill.  I propose an amendment that No. 21 on the Order Paper be taken before No. 1.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#S00400"><p>In the past few days, two pieces of news have caught my attention.  They are two linked items that give rise to some discrepancies.  The first is the seizing of a mansion in Saggart by the Criminal Assets Bureau from the Mansfields on account of it effectively being owned by Daniel Kinahan.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Sharon Keogan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=SharonKeogan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Second is the announcement yesterday by the Minister, Deputy McEntee, that &euro;2 million sourced from the proceeds of crime is to be invested into community projects.  The use of cash criminal proceeds in this way is to be lauded indeed.  It was from a motion by independent Louth councillors led by Councillor Paddy McQuillan that this brainchild was born.  It is our communities on the ground that suffer due to the selfish action of criminals and it is the people of those communities who should receive every support we can give them to build stronger and safer communities.  Just as we build up our police force to suppress crime, we must also build up our communities to prevent it.  Community projects which foster interconnectivity are an integral part of this.  As this use of liquid criminal proceeds is of obvious benefit, why are we so slow to liquidate other assets?  This seized mansion, which could fetch anywhere between &euro;1 to &euro;2 million, will instead languish on the books of the Criminal Assets Bureau, CAB, or its approved receiver for years, during which time it will be left vacant serving no one and moneys will have to be spent to maintain it and keep it secure.  During the housing crisis, the proceeds from this property could be used to house multiple families or even directly used itself as housing.  Why the delay in accomplishing this?  It is time to have a look at the Proceeds of Crime Act 1996 and allow the CAB to expedite the sale of criminal assets in order that those proceeds might speedily benefit our communities as well.  Will the Minister for Justice address the House with her opinions on this matter?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#T00200"><p>On education, there was some good and some not-so-good news in the past 24 hours.  The not-so-good news is the delay in publishing the junior certificate results.  Many students did not go into transition year but went on to start the leaving certificate cycle.  They will have been three to four months into the first year of a two-year cycle before they have the results of the junior certificate.  We have heard the excuses and the reasons but they are still not good enough.  For young people to do an exam in early June and not get the results until towards the end of November is really not acceptable and it should never happen again.  It is happening now and there is not a lot we can do about it but it should never happen again.</p> <p>On the good news, I have been campaigning for some time in this House and have met Ministers and spoken publically about the need for the leaving certificate papers to be accessible to people with print disabilities.  They need the papers to be digitally accessible.  It was announced yesterday that the papers would be digitally accessible to the blind and visually impaired community.  I want clarification as to whether this will be for all people with print disabilities, as it should be.  This country is an outlier when it comes to State examination papers being accessible to people with print disabilities.  For many years, they have been accessible in most other European countries so that people who use laptops, iPads and other forms of technology can access their examination papers and enlarge the print with their fingers or with whatever low-vision aids they need.  It is very positive that in June 2023, this facility will be available to people with vision impairments in this country.  It should have happened a long time ago but it is welcome that it has happened.  I commend the Minister for Education, Deputy Foley and the Minister for State, Deputy Madigan, on making it happen because I certainly annoyed them over the last number of months in particular to make this happen.  I want to commend F&eacute;ach, the organisation that represents parents of young people with vision impairments, on its campaigning on this issue and making it happen as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1638" speakername="Malcolm Byrne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#T00300"><p>I echo Senator Conway's comments on the disappointment at the delay in the junior certificate results.  It is quite unfair to those students, particularly for those who may be looking at an apprenticeship or at whatever subjects they might be choosing for senior cycle.  We have to ensure that delay does not happen again.</p> <p>I also call for a debate around the planned national research strategy.  While much of the focus will be around structures, there is a serious question regarding the level of support we are giving to our PhD candidates.  Some significant improvements were made in the budget but it did not go far enough.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Malcolm Byrne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;MemberID=1111"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1111&amp;amp;pid=MalcolmByrne&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->If we are to believe in investment in research in the long term, it is essential that we support those who are pursuing PhDs.  I would like the Leader to invite the Minister for Further and Higher Education, Research, Innovation and Science, Deputy Harris, to the House to discuss the research strategy.</p><p>I also want to raise the question of a global crisis that is in many ways often forgotten, given the focus of the news on other parts of the world, namely, the question of Venezuela.  The UN reported this week that since 2015, 7 million citizens have left Venezuela and after Ukraine, this is the biggest migrant crisis in the world.  Approximately 2.5 million people have ended up in Colombia.  They have been the victims of famine and of the economic collapse in that country.  Democracy has been repressed and we have seen political oppression.  It is important that Ireland at UN level does everything that we can in order to seek the restoration of democracy to Venezuela.  I welcome the fact that Venezuela lost its seat on the UN Human Rights Council in the last few weeks, although unfortunately we still see certain countries that have dodgy human rights records, such as China, Cuba and Qatar, sitting on that body.  However, it is important that we use our role at UN  and EU levels to try to ensure that we see democracy restored to Venezuela and that support is provided to those who are migrants from Venezuela, especially from the oppressive political regime that is in place there.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#U00200"><p>I would like to second the Central Bank Bill to which Senator Ardagh referred, which is also known as &ldquo;the right to be forgotten&rdquo; Bill.  I wish to commend everyone who is involved in relation to this matter.  I formally second that Bill.</p> <p>I want to raise the issue of my village of Castleconnell, because two serious aspects of life in Castleconnell have been highlighted in the last few days.  First, in a village of 2,500 people, we have 443 applicants on the housing waiting list.  That is 443 families and individuals.  The plan right now is to build five council houses between now and 2026.  It is absolutely shocking and what it means is that people really are bereft of hope.  They are paying exorbitant rents of &euro;1,400 per month for substandard three-bedroom accommodation.  A number of people had received eviction notices before the very welcome but belated announcement today.  They are, therefore, facing losing their homes at Christmas.  The fact is that there is so little planning by Governments and by the local authority - I  blame the Government in particular for the lack of funding here - shows just how overlooked the people of Castleconnell have been over the last number of years.</p> <p>To add further woe, we have been told just this afternoon that our local post office will close as of Friday.  People are being asked to travel 6 km to the next post office in Newport, County Tipperary.  The fact of the matter is that for a whole host of people, such as pensioners, people with disabilities and people who do not have their own transport, they will have no means of collecting their pension after this week.  It is an absolutely shocking indictment.  We hear so much about support for rural Ireland but here is the reality: our post office will close on Friday.  I have spoken to An Post and, in fairness, it is doing its best to try to get somebody else in to try to keep it open and running.  Yet, in the meantime, there is no aspect of life that will not be impacted in the village if the post office closes on Friday.  I want to appeal to all involved to try to keep this post office open until we can get a replacement service in place.  We cannot lose our post office.  It is the heart of our community and it is a shocking indictment that has been let get to this stage.</p> <p>I appeal for a debate on the role of rural life, in particular, and on the importance of post offices because I think we would all acknowledge it and yet we still see them close.  Urgent action should be taken.  Once again, I call for a debate on housing, particularly in terms of the appalling impact where I live in Limerick.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1656" speakername="Mary Fitzpatrick" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#U00300"><p>I would like to talk about public transport in Dublin Central.  Obviously, every senior citizen in Dublin Central can avail of free travel and young people up to the age of 24 are enjoying a 50% discount on public transport.  That is welcome.  Does the Leader know that feeling when one has been standing at a bus stop and has been waiting and waiting and the next thing three buses all come along at the one time?  It is infuriating, although one is delighted and wonders which bus to take.  What is happening in Dublin Central in terms of public transportation investment is similar to that.  Currently, in Dublin Central, we have a statutory planning application in train for the Blanchardstown bus corridor into town through the Navan Road.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Mary Fitzpatrick:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=MaryFitzpatrick&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The Leader knows the route well.  It runs down Old Cabra Road and through Stoneybatter.  An application has been made for a BusConnects route from Finglas and Ballymun, running down Mobhi Road and Botanic Road, through Phibsborough and Constitution Hill, and into town.  We also have the MetroLink, which is a massive infrastructural project.  The DART+ West upgrade is also progressing.  This is all welcome investment.  We all support more frequent, affordable and reliable public transport.  As the Leader knows, we have campaigned for safer public transport.  However, for residents and businesses in the area, this number of statutory planning applications running at the one time is an enormous burden.  It is a burden for any citizen to engage in a voluntary capacity.  It is a statutory process.  The engineering wizards and experts within the National Transport Authority, NTA, and other statutory bodies should have had the sequencing capacity to know that would put an unreasonable burden on residents.</p><p>I ask the Leader to write to the Minister for Transport on this issue.  I appreciate this falls within the remit of the NTA but the Minister for Transport needs to intervene and give direction that is going to galvanise support and engage people to support these massive infrastructural projects in order that we can have more reliable, efficient and affordable public transport.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1652" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#V00200"><p>I rise to raise a topic that has been raised by a number of Senators, that is, the stay on evictions and the greater and general topic of housing.  I agree with Senator Gavan that it would be no harm to have a discussion on housing in this House.  That would be informative for everyone.</p> <p>I welcome the Minister's decision to introduce a stay on evictions over the winter period.  It is a sincere and well thought-out provision by the Minister and the Government.  However, it will be important to follow on at the back end of that stay.  Landlords who have an enshrined right in this country to be in charge of their own properties and homes are having this law forced on them, for however a short a time.  If we are going to introduce a stay on evictions, we must work with landlords and property owners.  The detail seems to be sparse although I understand there may be further clarification later.  For argument's sake, I will say there are some tenants who are not playing ball at present and others who will not play ball because they know they are going to secure a house until next year.  That leaves landlords with very little or no recourse.  To go to the Residential Tenancies Board, RTB, to try to get a tenant out of a property if there is a problem takes a year at the best of times.  I am curious about what guarantees are available and what back-up we are going to give to landlords.</p> <p>Fianna F&aacute;il previously proposed a tax break for long-term leases.  I do not where that proposal has gone but it made a lot of sense.  I have spoken to my party colleagues about it.  I mentioned more than a year ago the tsunami of sales that were coming.  I mentioned that to my colleagues in the House approximately three months ago.  I can see it happening at first hand.  It is having a knock-on effect and causing a problem.  Each and every day, as the Leader will know from attending clinics, more people are presenting in cases where their houses are being sold and they are going to be left homeless, for want of a better word, or at least without their current home in a short timeframe.  That is something we need longer to consider.  We must engage and deal with landlords.  Putting our heads in the sand and running landlords out of the market is something we can do if we want to but we must have a proper strategy to do it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1695" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#W00100"><p>I also wish to raise the proposed closure of the post office in Castleconnell in Limerick.  Residents have contacted me.  It is not easy to get from Castleconnell to Newport.  Residents are reliant on getting lifts.  Many older people use the local post office for their banking facilities so I encourage the Minister for the Environment, Climate and Communications to come to the House for a debate on the future of post offices.</p> <p>I welcome the announcement by the Minister for Health regarding transforming four hospices from section 39 to section 38 organisations.  This is most welcome in Limerick, where Milford Care Centre is located.  It is joined by Marymount Care Centre, St. Francis Hospice and the hospice in Galway.  I compliment the CEOs, staff and the many volunteers who work in these hospices.  My family availed of the services in Milford Care Centre over the past number of years.  Compassionate work is carried out there.  The news today is welcome because it secures funding for the future of hospices in Ireland.  I thank the Minister for listening to us.  I spoke to him and the T&aacute;naiste about this matter and I think it was the right thing to do.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#W00200"><p>The Technological University of the Shannon opened a learning gate today.  One might ask what a learning gate is.  I learned this morning that it is a place where students can come and study.  Ballinasloe Area Community Development hosts a place for start-ups, enterprise and companies but it also has meeting room space and this is where students will now be able to come and learn, meet with other students or carry out research for the college they are attending.  This is the first of 11 that will be opened by the Technological University of the Shannon.  It is even opening one in Dublin.  It means there will be additional support for students.  I am delighted to see it because it again shows that there is third-level access in the Ballinasloe region and how we are developing these links with our third-level institutions which are driving excellence in the regions.</p> <p>As has been noted, there has been very good news on the education front, particularly further and higher education.  The Minister for Further and Higher Education, Research, Innovation and Science indicated that the extra SUSI payment for third-level students will be on 16 December.  We also know that &euro;1,000 has been taken off the student contribution fee so this will be a real boost for families and those who have paid in full.  I think they will have to submit their account details by mid-November.  For those who have not paid in full, it will be taken off their second payment.  This is really positive news for students and their families coming up to Christmas.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#W00300"><p>In response to Senator Dolan, it is a really exciting time when one gets such wonderful new educational institutions such as our technological universities.  It will be wonderful to watch them grow and develop from their inception.  It is really exciting for the areas that have them so I thank the Senator for raising that issue and for acknowledging the &euro;1,000 rebate that will be returned to students, or indeed their mammies and daddies who have paid their fees over the past couple of months.  It will be very welcome.</p> <p>Senator Maria Byrne spoke about Castleconnell post office, as did Senator Gavan.  I am not sure if it is of any benefit to either Senator if I contact the CEO of An Post but surely to God there must be somebody we can put in until we find somebody who will take over the post office.  I am assuming, although I do not know for sure, that somebody is retiring and they cannot find anybody else to take over the business.  There must be some interim arrangements that can be put in place for the 2,500 people referred to by Senators Gavan and Maria Byrne.  I will certainly make contact with the CEO and come back to the Senators.  </p> <p>Senator Maria Byrne also spoke about the very welcome announcement of the four hospices being redesignated from section 39 to section 38 organisations, which is very welcome.  Senators Davitt and Gavan both looked for a debate on housing.  While the eviction ban is very welcome for most people, I acknowledge their concerns about landlords.  We need to protect people.  The story on RT&Eacute; last night about the family living in a tent is not acceptable in this day and age.  There have been challenges regarding accommodation and building houses in the past number of years.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Regina Doherty:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2295"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2295&amp;amp;pid=ReginaDoherty&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is certainly not acceptable that two young children with autism and their parents are living in a car and a tent.  Nevertheless, we need to recognise that the more actions we take to discourage landlords from being in the business, the more that will result in people not having anywhere to rent, given that the State is not building the houses it needs to build in order to provide for those people.  It will be a welcome debate.  I will organise it as soon as the Minister is available to us.</p><p>Senator Fitzpatrick asked that I write to the Minister with regard to the three statutory consultations, which probably are a bit of an overload for the residents in the same area, even though we are all trying to improve the services of public transport for them, and I will certainly do that.</p><p>Senator Malcolm Byrne asked for a debate on research grants and the establishment of proper funding for PhD students and research candidates, which I will certainly organise.  He also touched on a global crisis that is not spoken about as much as other crises, namely, that in Venezuela, and spoke about attempting, through the UN and the EU, to restore democracy and look after the 7 million citizens who have been displaced over the past year or so.</p><p>Senator Conway spoke about the delay in getting the junior certificate results.  I have a little lady at home who is waiting, like all the other young ladies and lads in school, and it seems to be an unacceptable delay.  It certainly highlights the fact that there are not enough teachers to correct the papers, so we have to find the root of that problem and fix it.</p><p>Senator Keogan raised the welcome announcement that the fruits of the seizure of criminal assets will be redistributed to communities that have been most blighted by crime.  The announcement of the first &euro;2 million was made this week and Balbriggan was lucky enough to score &euro;150,000.  There was another announcement for Meath and there have been more for various places almost throughout the country.  I was flabbergasted to hear that we have to keep assets for six years before we can dispose of them and realise the cash.  That does not make sense.  I will certainly make inquiries, although it may require a tweak in legislation.  I would have thought that if we saw something and had the authority to seize it, we would not sit around for six years waiting to realise the value of the money, but I will revert to the Senator on that.</p><p>Senator Ardagh proposed an amendment to the Order of Business, which Senator Gavan seconded, and I am pleased to accept it.  I look forward to scheduling her Bill, as soon as I can, for a Thursday afternoon in order to try to get it progressed insofar as we can between now and Christmas.</p><p>Senator Flynn sought a debate on direct provision.  Every time she does so, I do ask about it but I have not yet been given a date.  I will ask again today and remind the Minister with responsibility.  I am concerned about the recent announcement that people in direct provision are being asked to pay for accommodation.  It is not acceptable that just because we have awarded them citizenship or remain to leave but they do not have anywhere else to go, we would then decide to charge them for what is substandard accommodation, so I support the Senator on that.</p><p>Senator &Oacute; Donnghaile welcomed the ban on evictions and raised both his party&rsquo;s motion that is to be taken in the Lower House tonight and the public tender for artists in respect of life-size statues.  I laughed when he spoke about Winifred Carney because not only was she an original Sinn F&eacute;in member but she was also a Fine Gaeler and then a Fianna F&aacute;iler before she got out of politics.  She was definitely a difficult woman who did not let any man push her around, which is very welcome, so I acknowledge that.</p><p>Senator Pauline O'Reilly the menopause experience, how good it is to talk about it, how often we have been talking about it and how welcome the major changes of the past year have been.</p><p>Senator Craughwell spoke about the SAR tenders, while Senator Kyne spoke about the ring road in Galway and the fact we are now back to the drawing board.</p><p>Senator Sherlock spoke about the injunction on the security industry, an issue she has raised a number of times.</p><p>Senator Chambers spoke not only about the welcome additions to the menopause clinics - we are now on the fourth one - but also about the worrying trend emerging in Iran of the disgusting treatment of women.  We really need to follow up with the Minister for Foreign Affairs to find out where that young woman is and ensure she is safe.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#X00200"><p>Senator Ardagh has proposed an amendment to the Order of Business: "That No. 21 be taken before No. 1."  The amendment was seconded by Senator Gavan.  The Leader has indicated that she is prepared to accept the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.86" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.87" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Order of Business, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.88" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#X00500">Central Bank (Amendment) Bill 2022: First Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1630" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#X00600"><p>I move:</p> <blockquote> 	That leave be granted to introduce a Bill entitled an Act to amend the Central Bank Act 1942 and prohibit financial service providers from discriminating against survivors of cancer from accessing financial services and to provide for related matters. </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.90" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#X00800"><p>When is it proposed to take Second Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#X00900"><p>Next Tuesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#X01000"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.94" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Second Stage ordered for Tuesday, 25 October 2022.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.95" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar fionra&iacute; ar 4.25 p.m. agus cuireadh t&uacute;s leis ar&iacute;s ar 4.49 p.m.<br /><br />Sitting suspended at 4.25 p.m. and resumed at 4.49 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.96" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#DD00100">Summer Programme: Statements</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1472" speakername="Josepha Madigan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#DD00200"><p>I thank Senators for the opportunity to be here to talk about the summer programme.  It has been a particular focus for me as Minister of State with responsibility for special education and inclusion.  I had the pleasure of visiting many of these summer programmes and I have seen first-hand the immeasurable difference this programme makes to children with special educational needs and those experiencing educational disadvantage.</p> <p>The provision of education for children with special educational needs is an ongoing priority for this Government, and my main focus as the first ever Minister of State with responsibility for special education and inclusion.  I am determined to ensure continuous development of special education provision and policy to allow all children achieve the best possible outcomes in their lives.  The summer programme is a very important scheme for pupils with complex special educational needs and those at greatest risk of educational disadvantage.  I want to see it supporting families and students with special educational needs during the summer months.</p> <p>Before we talk about what we are going to do for next year, I want to reflect on the significant progress we have made over the last number of years.  As Senators will know, until 2020, the programme was called July provision, and for many years catered for children in special schools and classes with autism.  When the provision was significantly expanded, it then became known as the summer programme.  Senators may recall this was just after the first school closures that occurred in 2020 due to Covid-19.</p> <p>The 2020 programme provided children with an opportunity to continue or re-engage with learning at school or, indeed, at home.  The eligibility criteria widened and significantly increased the number of primary-age children with complex special educational needs who were eligible for this scheme.  All special schools and primary schools with special classes could provide the school-based summer provision at this time.</p> <p>In 2021, the summer programme was expanded further so that mainstream schools could now provide a school-based inclusion programme.  This was introduced as a further Covid-19 measure to support children with complex needs and also those students at greatest risk of educational disadvantage.  For the summer programme in 2022, we matched the funding from last year of &euro;40 million.  This has helped well over 1,000 Ukrainian children integrate into their new learning environments through the inclusion programme.  It built upon the 2021 programme, which introduced the first ever inclusion programme and allowed all schools to offer a summer programme to pupils in primary and post primary, whether they are mainstream or special schools.</p> <p>I understand the importance of this crucial scheme for families and the children who participate in them.  The summer can be a really daunting time for families of children with additional needs and for some children who do not have enough interaction with friends or peers.  It is, therefore, really important that the Department engages and encourages schools to interact with the summer programme.</p> <p>The Department has listened to feedback and is striving to make the scheme as good as it can be, as am I, and that it is available to every eligible student who needs it.  The programme that was provided in 2022 was developed following extensive engagement with stakeholders, parents and disability advocacy groups.</p> <p>The current programme aims to support pupils to maintain their connection with education, build their confidence, promote well-being and increase their motivation.  For those who are at key transition stages, it helps to ensure they continue their education journey in September either in school or in further or higher education or training.</p> <p>The programmes on offer last summer included the inclusions programme in primary schools, which I spoke about earlier, a special classes and special schools programme in primary schools, Delivering Equality of Opportunity in Schools, DEIS, numeracy and literacy camps, or campa&iacute; samhraidh, in DEIS primary schools and inclusive programmes for all post-primary schools.  A home-based summer programme was also available for up to four weeks with ten hours per week for students with complex special educational needs where a place on a school-based programme was not available to them.</p> <p>A key objective of the 2022 scheme was to increase the number of schools offering the summer programme to their students.  Steps were taken to afford schools as much flexibility as possible and ease administrative requirements.  To support and facilitate schools and principals with organising and running the programme, the 2022 summer programme allowed principals delegate these functions to other members of staff through the provision of support roles of overseer and preparation hours.  The overseer and preparation roles provided an excellent opportunity for teachers to develop their leadership skills and experience with recognition at a whole-school level.</p> <p>Again, for the 2022 programme, the Teaching Council and Irish Primary Principals Network, IPPN, promoted the summer programmes with graduate teachers, professional masters of education, student teachers and undergraduate students registered under route 5 to increase the supply of available teachers.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Josepha Madigan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2424"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2424&amp;amp;pid=JosephaMadigan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Graduate teachers and student teachers could work on the summer programme where they had commenced their registration process with the Teaching Council and where certain conditions were fulfilled.  It is important to say schools were given the flexibility to engage staff not currently employed by them, including those in the early years or youth sector, to run their summer programme.  Other examples that schools have previously availed of successfully include students from therapy, nursing and other healthcare-related disciplines.  Other enhanced measures have been put in place to encourage participation of schools, including a centralised application process to reduce the administrative burden on schools, the earlier payment of school staff, an additional capitation to cover the running costs of the scheme, as well as enhanced capitation for special schools and classes.</p><p>In 2022, the Department had productive engagements with the National Association of Boards of Management in Special Education, NABMSE.  This led to positive initiatives to assist special schools, such as through the hosting of information webinars and the introduction of a new grant for these special schools.  I expect these engagements will lead to more positive measures for the 2023 programme and beyond.  Participation in the programme has grown over recent years, with 2022 seeing more schools and more students participate than ever before.  Final figures for this year's programme will be known later in the year, but based on the information available to date, it is anticipated that in excess of 45,000 pupils will have participated, with more than 1,000 schools running a programme.  That is an increase of approximately 18% on the 2021 numbers of participating students.</p><p>This year, for the first time, schools were able to submit the details of staff who worked on their programme through an online portal.  The first payments were issued in July and payments continued throughout the summer.  To date, more than 9,000 staff members have been paid for their participation in the school-based programme.  This represents almost all of staff who participated in the programme.  Feedback on the payments system has been generally positive, and the earlier payments for staff have also been welcomed.  Payments have been issued fortnightly for submitted claims since the first tranche of payments was issued in July.</p><p>Members will no doubt have seen the announcement the Minister for Education and I made about the 2023 programme.  I am delighted to confirm that funding has been approved under budget 2023 to continue the expanded summer programme for 2023.  I recognise the delay in announcing the summer programme in previous years meant some schools had insufficient time to prepare adequately and were not able commit to running the programme.  This early announcement for 2023 affords schools every opportunity and gives them several extra months to plan for a summer programme next year.  As Members will also be aware, I have asked my Department to review the programme so that for 2023, we can build further on all we have achieved so far to have the best possible programme available.  I am very conscious parents want this programme to be available in more schools in 2023.</p><p>As part of the planning that has already begun for next year, it is a priority of next year's development that children in special schools have access to a school-based programme.  It must be noted that while it is important to support a summer based programme in our special schools and special classes, it is also essential to ensure the children with complex special educational needs who are in our mainstream settings also have access to this critical support.  As our system has become more inclusive and many of these children with more complex needs now attend mainstream settings, it is recognised that they, too, will be impacted by school holidays and require that additional support to ensure they achieve their potential.</p><p>The Department is committed, and indeed it has already started intensively, through the review process, to engage with the management bodies, schools and the sector as a whole with a view to encouraging schools and supporting them to participate in next year's programme.  We want to support schools fully in terms of organisation, workforce availability, administration, resources and training to make it as successful as possible.  As part of the review, the Department is engaging with stakeholders, including the Special Education Consultative Forum, to ensure voices on the ground are being heard.  The Department has already met with officials from Malta to utilise some of the learnings from their system in terms of the planning and organisation, and it will be engaging directly with the National Parents Council.  The inspectorate in the Department has also visited schools, including special schools, as part of that process, and it is liaising with the staff, parents and children who participated to help ensure the review takes account of the lived experience.  The Department will also look at innovative ways to promote and publicise the programme for next summer to raise awareness of the scheme further and publicise the benefits of running a scheme.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Josepha Madigan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2424"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2424&amp;amp;pid=JosephaMadigan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> Alternative solutions for how schools can accommodate the summer programme will also form part of the approach to the programme in 2023.  Other aspects of the planning for next year include liaising with colleagues in other Departments and agencies with a view to expanding the potential workforce to support this essential programme.  Over the past two years, schools have been given the flexibility to engage staff who are not currently employed in the school, including those in the early years sector, to run their summer programme.  They have also been allowed to recruit final-year students graduating in the summer.  In 2022, this was further expanded to allow route 5 undergraduate student teachers to participate.  It makes sense to expand the workforce as this gives each school more access and support to run a programme.  For many workers in the early years sector, who work 38 weeks in the year and often are looking for work during the summer, the summer programme is a great option.  I will discuss how best to promote it with the Minister for Children, Equality, Disability, Integration and Youth, Deputy O'Gorman. </p><p>Following the review of this year's programme and finalisation of planning for next year, the details of the 2023 summer programme are intended to be published by the end of January next year.  I reiterate my commitment to ensuring children who need it most have access to this important educational initiative.  Both I and my Department will be working hard to make sure this is achieved.  I look forward to hearing statements from Members, which I am sure will be helpful to us in our endeavours.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#FF00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State, who is here in her capacity of having responsibility for special educational needs.  It is fantastic that we have this new programme.  The July provision was always one of those titles that was slightly confusing and it is great to see the name change to the "summer programme".  I spoke with a couple of school principals this morning to get some feedback.  The timing of the announcement is extremely welcome.  The late announcements around the programme in previous years were very challenging.  The timing of this announcement for 2023 will allow principals and schools to plan ahead and have people in place.  It is challenging when information is given at the last minute.  Schools are very positive about this change.</p> <p>The Minister of State mentioned in her press release this morning and in her speech that all schools will have an opportunity to run the programme.  This means more than 4,000 schools, including 3,200 or so primary schools and another 770 or so post-primary schools, can get involved.  All of those schools can take up the summer programme and benefit from it.  We need to look at how the Department can support that.  The Minister of State highlighted that, where possible, it should be a school-based programme and, where necessary, it will be provided in another shape or format.  It is crucial that the programme is being offered through the schools and in a school setting.  It will offer real support for students over the summer months.</p> <p>It is fantastic that more than 45,000 students participated this year, as the Minister of State indicated, which amounts to 1,000 schools, or nearly a quarter of the total, running a programme.  This is an increase of approximately 18% on the previous year.  I hope there will be targets for next year.  Will she comment on the targets she would like to see in terms of the number of schools that might complete the programme within the &euro;40 million in funding that is being given?</p> <p>The Minister of State noted there was an expanded summer programme in 2020 and she introduced the first inclusion summer programme in 2021.  That allowed for the accommodation of all the children in special classes, with the programme operating in primary, post-primary and special schools.  In Roscommon and Galway, which I represent, we have a number of band 1 DEIS schools.  One of the only primary schools included in the expansion of DEIS is in the Ballinasloe area.  There are challenges in that area around Pobal funding and issues for young families, particularly in the context of social backgrounds.  I was interested to hear the DEIS programme includes numeracy and literacy camps.  Supports for students at an early age are crucial, as are the supports for students from Ukraine, more than 1,000 of whom, as the Minister of State indicated, have attended some of these camps.</p> <p>I would like to explore, if not today then perhaps at another time, how we can develop the home-based programme.  One of the key issues for children is the transition from primary to secondary school and from secondary to third level.  It is known that this can be a very stressful time for students and their families as they make the transition and get used to new students.  All through the lockdowns, it was a huge issue for young children who were not able to socialise in ways that were possible before.  The summer camps are crucial for enabling children to engage in a positive way and to enter school having met some buddies beforehand and understanding what school is about and what is expected of students.  All of that is really helpful.  I would like to hear how we can develop well-being supports within the programme to facilitate these transitions.  I know it is hard to include everything within a set amount of time but supporting transition is one of the key benefits of these types of summer programmes.</p> <p>Staffing can be a challenge but I am delighted to hear there will be an administrator role for preparation of the summer programme.  That will be key for schools.  There will also be supports in place for the teachers, special needs assistants, SNAs, and support staff who will be running the programmes.  The Minister of State mentioned staff can come from different sectors.  Will she give more detail on the qualifications that might be needed for these types of roles?  It is great to encourage participation from other sectors, including the early years sector.  I am curious as to whether there might be any role for graduates coming out of the teaching training colleges, working with experienced teachers on these summer programmes.  Would such a role be confined to graduates or is there potentially a role for students during their earlier years of study?</p> <p>As the Minister of State noted, one of the interesting and effective measures that has been introduced is the earlier, centralised payment for teachers and SNAs.  It is probably a real challenge to encourage teachers and SNAs to come back in for two weeks after they reach the end of a packed year trying to manage students at whatever level.  Are any other incentives being considered?  The centralised early payment and the way schools can engage potentially from November or December in bringing people on board are important measures.</p> <p>I thank the Minister of State for her work on this issue.  Since she took on her role, we have seen a focus on special educational needs, but this programme is for all children.  That is what is really wonderful.  It is for all children and all schools.  Currently, 1,000 schools are benefiting from the programme and it will be wonderful to see it being rolled out for more schools.  Will she comment on her vision and targets for what this might look like?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#FF00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State for being in the House for this debate.  This is not my first time speaking on the issue of summer provision and I have no doubt it will not be the last.  It is really important to recognise progress when it happens.  Education is hugely important to people on this side of the House.  Senator Malcolm Byrne and I, as spokespersons on education, really value what the summer programme can bring to the many children who need it, as well as to their families and communities.</p> <p>I especially welcome the announcement by the Minister of State and the Minister, Deputy Foley, of a &euro;40 million summer programme for next year.  This is a timely intervention that gives schools an opportunity to prepare in earnest.  Once again, all schools will have the opportunity to run a programme for those children who need it the most.  It will allow us to support them in engaging with education in a meaningful way.  The benefits of the programme far outweigh what happens in the school building.  It benefits the children in the context of the community they live in and in terms of family interactions.  That support is hugely important.</p> <p>I acknowledge it is a priority that more children in special schools have access to a school-based programme.  That is very welcome.  In the past few years, it has been my experience that special schools did not want to run these programmes.  I recognise that for staff in special schools, it is complex and challenging.  For many, by the time the school term ends, there is a challenge in looking at running a summer programme.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Fiona O'Loughlin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2441"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2441&amp;amp;pid=FionaOLoughlin&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->They are exhausted and they feel that it is very difficult to engage in teaching.  That is why the new flexibility that has been introduced by bringing in teachers, graduate students and SNAs is helpful in this regard.  It is hugely important that every special school has this, because these are the children who need that support most.  For many parents and teachers who we speak to, when children are out of the routine that school has given them, they really do slip back.  The summer period is too wide a period to not be able to continue with education.</p><p>As we know, and as the Minister of State has mentioned, over 45,000 students participated in the summer programme this year with more than 1,000 different schools running a programme.  That increase of 18% is important and has to be celebrated and acknowledged.  The fact that the earlier payment scheme has been implemented is important, because I know from speaking to teachers and teaching unions that that was a big issue previously in terms of how long it took for teachers and SNAs to be paid.  The area of payment is important, as is the provision to recruit final-year student teachers and student teachers who are registered with the Teaching Council.  It gives young students an opportunity to learn and to earn at the same time.  </p><p>As I have said before, I believe we need to start down the road of universal access for children who need to avail of this provision.  It is not a luxury for families that have a child with complex additional needs; it is a necessity for how they manage and deal with their child.  I have previously criticised the scheme for not being extensive enough because we need to find a way of ensuring that all children with special educational needs have the option to continue attending school with school transport for the entire summer should they require it.  We are on the step to developing that.  I would also say that we need to move away from the opt-in and opt-out model for summer provision.  It should be mandatory and the Department should be flexible with how the summer provision is implemented but in special schools in particular, it needs to be mandatory.   </p><p>When we speak about providing services for special education and wider supports, we are not just talking about the four walls of the physical building.  We are talking about the resources, the special education assistants and the intervention therapies that are needed.  We all acknowledge that early intervention is important and that it makes such a difference in the lives of the young persons themselves of their families and of the people in their communities.  Everyone needs the opportunity to fulfil their potential in as meaningful a way as possible.  I also welcome the announcement of a review of the programme and that the Department of Education is engaging with relevant Departments, agencies and stakeholders in order that we can see more children participating in 2023.  It is important that schools are given the support they need to be able to run a programme during the summer and that the review will also take account of administration needs, workforce expansion and training requirements, which are vital components for the schools.  </p><p>Since 2021, the Government has invested in an enhanced summer programme to support students who are at risk of educational disadvantage and to help mitigate learning loss because of the Covid-19 pandemic and obviously, since the end of February last year, to support our displaced students such as the Ukrainian students.  That is all valuable work and adds to the educational experience of the young people.  I have been a long and genuine advocate for people who are living with disabilities and additional needs and I fundamentally believe that we should strive for a fully, truly inclusive education system, that is, one that meets all children where they are at and that coaches them to develop and reach their full potential.  Every child, regardless of his or her ability or societal background needs to be catered for and nurtured in his or her local school, within his or her community and alongside his or her peers.  Anything less is not acceptable.  The summer provision programme the Minister of State spoke about at the outset is a crucial part of that vision.  I commend the Minister of State on her work to date and thank her for her commitment to the whole school community.  There is still much work to do but we are on the right way.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#GG00200"><p>The Minister of State is very welcome.  It is good to have her in, particularly to talk about a subject as important as this.  I am standing in for my colleague, Senator Warfield, and I will do my best to address some of the key topics the Minister of State has raised.</p> <p>The summer programme is an opportunity to provide additional supports for children with complex special educational needs and for those who are at greatest risk of educational disadvantage.  The few weeks of the summer programme in school can really help students who need that extra bit of help and it can also prevent regression in children with additional needs during the long break in the summer.  Where it is available, it is a great support for parents and families as well.  Indeed, some families have come to rely on this support throughout the summer.  It can be a kind of respite for them during the break and can help them to cope.  It is therefore important that there is consistency on how it is delivered each year.  </p> <p>It has to be acknowledged that progress has been made in terms of the additional funding, which is very much welcomed.  In particular, I welcome the support given to the Ukrainian children, which was necessary.  It is great to see it happening and it is important to acknowledge that. </p> <p>The outstanding points where we express some concerns are in relation to seeing what else can be done to further improve the uptake from schools for the programme.  It is still relatively low in primary, secondary and special schools, despite the fact that we know there is a huge demand out there.  This aspect is worrying when you think of the risks of educational and behavioural regression for many children who need these reports.  One of the feedback issues that comes to us concerns the frustration that sometimes, the guidelines are issued a little late in the year.  That can sometimes be a disincentive for schools to run the programme.  Perhaps that is something the Minister of State could comment on or report back on in terms of progress in that regard.</p> <p>The other issue is that there are still concerns from schools about making sure they are properly equipped, both administratively and in terms of teaching resources.  Additional administrative supports were provided this year, which is something Sinn F&eacute;in has been calling for some time.  It has certainly helped but we probably would accept that there needs to be further upscaling in this regard.  The issue of early payment was a big stumbling block and again, it is welcome to see action on that as it was a huge disincentive.  As others have referenced quite correctly, sometimes teachers, in the very demanding role they have, are physically and mentally exhausted by the time the summer break comes.  Of course, we have to recognise that.  In that regard, the broader flexibility the Minister of State has introduced in looking to others to come in and do some of that work is welcome.  In that respect, I ask again for the Government to look at the issue of payment, particularly for SNAs, which does not reflect the quality of the work they do.  It is an ongoing issue and while I accept it is a broader issue, if we are looking to see how we can further incentivise some of the best people available to do that work, the issue of pay then must be acknowledged and further addressed.  </p> <p>As others have referenced, we are asking teachers to give up at least part of their summer and that is quite a big ask.  The Department continues to need to examine all possible incentives, whether they are pay-based or other forms of incentives, to ensure the schools have enough staff.  Otherwise, the uptake from schools will continue to be a challenge. </p> <p>I want to touch on home-based tuition.  While this is undoubtedly a preferable option for some children, there has been some feedback that home provision of the summer programme is not the right solution for everyone.  This was highlighted by the National Council for Special Education, which recently made the point that home-based summer programmes are probably the least effective way to deliver the scheme.  Obviously, it depends on the child and on the family situation.  There are obvious practical reasons it might not be suitable for some, as some families just do not have a space for that work to take place in the home.  There is also a lack of socialisation.  That is why it is important that in-school summer programmes are available.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paul Gavan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2469"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2469&amp;amp;pid=PaulGavan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->When they are not, parents are advised of the option of home tuition as a solution when it is not necessarily the right, best or most optimum solution for that child.  The various streams of the summer programme are a very valuable resource.  I know the Minister of State and her Department are working on making it more accessible.  I want to acknowledge that and say it is very welcome.</p><p>The most important thing to say, however, is that the summer programme needs to be resourced properly and consistently.  Continued increased resources are very much required.  Further thought also needs to be given to staffing issues to ensure what else we can do.  As I said, that issue of pay, particularly for special needs assistants, SNA, is one that all of us hopefully agree needs to be addressed.  Again, I acknowledge the work that has been done and very much welcome this opportunity to have a debate on the issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#HH00200"><p>I thank Minister Gavan.  I should say Senator Gavan; I nearly gave him a promotion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#HH00300"><p>I have been called worse.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1639" speakername="Miche&aacute;l Carrigy" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#HH00400"><p>The Minister of State is very welcome.  I also welcome Mr. Frank Hanlon from the Department.  I want to compliment the Minister of State on the work she has done in her role in special education.  I know from the numerous occasions we have spoken about it that this area of the summer programme is and has been a priority for the Minister of State.</p> <p>I am delighted with the announcement in the press release we received this morning that will give certainty to schools in 2023.  One issue that came up when we met with many of the teachers' unions and teachers' organisations at the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Autism last week was the certainty to plan for a programme and the fact that they did not know until very late last year.  I am, therefore, delighted that there is some certainty.  I would like to see more details before January.  We should aim or strive to have them put in place at least prior to Christmas.  The reality is that at this minute, and I have seen this myself, a significant number of schools have already decided they are not doing a school-based summer programme next year.  That is not acceptable.</p> <p>For somewhere in the region of 80% of children, in particular those who attend special schools, a school-based programme took place in only 34 out of the 136-odd special schools in the summer of 2022.  That meant those 80% of children with higher needs had no access to a programme.  The home-based programme was mentioned and, to be honest, that is not an option.  We have seen situations over the years where parents had to advertise online to get a tutor to take a child for July provision, as it was called, or the summer programme because there was not a school-based option for that.  The reality is that the vast majority of those parents could not get a person who would take their child for the programme.  That meant that child with the highest needs for whom we started the programme a number of years ago actually got no provision at all.  That has to change.  It is my opinion, and I have said this publicly before, that it should be mandatory for all special schools.  That message needs to go out.  I will get much criticism, which I got before, for saying that but it is the right thing to do.  The children should be our priority and we must make sure that programme can take place.</p> <p>I am also of the belief, and the Minister mentioned this in her speech, that we should expand the workforce that will be eligible to work within that programme to early childhood care and education, ECCE, workers.  I would like to see speech and language and occupational therapy students in our colleges employed during the summer, giving them work experience and enabling us to give children extra services within schools.  We met with HSE officials earlier today and put it to them that we should employ those students who are training, and, as has been said, children would then get a service.</p> <p>At the minute, as we know, a person must have a Teaching Council number to provide the school-based provision while if he or she is home-based, that person only has to be over 18 and Garda vetted.  As I said, we need a total review of the school-based programme.  I appeal to every principal in every special school to put it in his or her diary for summer 2023 and to look for the staff.  It is up to the Department to change the criteria on what staff are available, which I believe it will do.  Every principal should put it in his or her diary, but not like it has been done in the diaries I have seen.  We are 12 months out and they have already told parents there will be no provision next year.  Parents and families are in despair.  At a minimum, therefore, every single special school should be doing it.</p> <p>We should look at a situation similar to what happened in County Kildare where students in one particular town, which I think was Naas, although I stand to be corrected, came together to make sure that at least one school in the town provided the school-based programme per year.  That meant that every family within that community knew there was going to be a school-based programme.  As I said, we need to prioritise it for next year, which I know the Minister of State will do, and is doing, because of the announcement that came today.  I would appeal to the principals, however, in particular those in special schools, to mark in their diaries summer provision for 2023.  We do not want a situation like what happened.  A figure of 34 special schools out of 136 is not acceptable.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#HH00500"><p>I call Senator Pauline O'Reilly of the Green Party.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1693" speakername="Pauline O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#HH00600"><p>I thank the Minister of State very much for coming in today.  I very much welcome the announcement yesterday from both her and the Minister, Deputy Foley, on the &euro;40 million funding and the review of the programme.</p> <p>Many children with whom we speak are excited about summer provision.  It is a key part of their year.  We have two sets of people, namely, the students and the teachers.  We must resolve those two issues.  I know that is what the Minister of State is committed to doing.  Early payment is one of the issues that will hopefully resolve this issue around recruitment for the summer provision.</p> <p>I agree with much of what Senator Carrigy said, however.  The Minister of State can do so much but there is also an important part to be played by leadership within schools when it comes to summer provision.  This is an essential part of education; it is not an add-on.  It really gives people with special needs that continuity they so desperately need and want.  That is really important.</p> <p>Various groups appear before the Joint Committee on Education, Further and Higher Education, Research, Innovation and Science with regard to special needs, in particular.  The Minister of State has always been available to come into us as well.  One thing that has stood out for me about special needs teachers is that they really want to be part of leadership within schools. When I was chair of a board of management, we had an SNA who was there as a representative from the school.  Boards of management generally only have two representatives from the school.  Oftentimes, that is the principal and another teacher or deputy principal.  I was fortunate enough that it was a small school, so we had the principal and a special needs teacher.  It was, however, really key in ensuring that voice of special needs assistants was heard within our schools.  Given that we have this important Ministry now in this Government, I know that special needs assistants are seen as core to education.  Indeed, one quarter, or 25%, of the education budget goes into special needs education.  We have more special needs classes opening than ever before.  However, it is also now time to ensure that the leadership within schools includes those who are right in the middle of the teaching of special needs education.</p> <p>The other thing that was called for was that people would know a long time in advance that this summer provision was coming.  This is October; we are one month into the school year and already schools are being given notice that this is happening next year.  I was actually quite shocked to hear from Senator Carrigy about the number of schools that are actually providing it.  I know that number is low because I get so many emails about it.  It is a real difficulty in areas in which people only have one school and that school is not providing it.  It is also difficult because of transport issues around some parts of rural areas to ensure people get to where they need to be.</p> <p>We cannot say more than the Minister of State is now doing a review, she has addressed the issue of early payment and she has given advance notice.  I am very hopeful that next summer, we will see that most children who really need it will have access to this very important provision.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1638" speakername="Malcolm Byrne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#HH00700"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte freisin roimh an Aire St&aacute;it.  As colleagues said, it is important to thank the Minister of State for her work in this area over the last few years.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Malcolm Byrne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;MemberID=1111"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1111&amp;amp;pid=MalcolmByrne&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The major expansion of this programme is something that is positive.  It is also important that we thank the teachers, SNAs and schools that take part in summer provision and that we acknowledge the contribution they make.  I get Senator Carrigy's point about the difficulty of getting them but there are a lot of teachers who are willing and keen to do this and we need to recognise their work as well.  I agree with Senator Carrigy that we need to look at encouraging all schools to put it in their diaries, look at what provision will be needed for 2023 and plan it out.  In the majority of cases students are looked after and so on but there are always a couple of difficult cases and one does not want people to be under stress at the last minute.  A campaign from the Department to inform teachers, students and schools of the importance of this programme early on would be welcome.  I agree with Senator Gavan on the issue of pay for SNAs.  I appreciate it is a broader question but SNAs are often well qualified, they do important work and sometimes it is not sufficiently recognised.  I welcome the expansion of the programme to include Ukrainian students, which has also been positive.</p><p>I want to make a comment on the summer provision forum and the requirement in the statutory declaration that it should be witnessed by a peace commissioner, a commissioner of oaths or a practising solicitor.  As a peace commissioner I have often witnessed them and most peace commissioners will not charge.  Unfortunately it has been the case that some people bring them in through practising solicitors and they will charge.  I was not suggesting the Minister of State was being asked to fill in the forms but it is unfair that for a fairly simple form some teachers are expected to have the signing witnessed.  It may be down to communicating that they should go to a peace commissioner and he or she will not charge.  It is unfair if a charge is applied by any professional for signing the statutory declaration as it is a relatively simple form.</p><p>The second and broader question is on summer provision to help students with special needs who need assistance through the system in various ways.  One of my concerns is whether an examination has been done on the impact of Covid.  Some of that will not necessarily manifest itself immediately on a student's academic or social development but it may start to develop later on during the student's school career.  We know most students survived during Covid.  They were incredibly resilient and were able to adapt to home learning and so on but for others there is anecdotal evidence that they have fallen behind.  They have not been able to necessarily keep up from an academic perspective and they may not have had the home environment to sort it.  It is about that longer term question of dealing with the two-year period that was taken out of a child's education and if there is a need for a specific support down the line that should be available.  The summer programme may be necessary for that into the future.  I do not know the extent to which empirical studies have been done by the Department but I ask that the impact of Covid on children and young people's social and academic development would be looked at because it is important that if we can do so we would step in and provide those supports.  I fully get that for certain students and young people it may not fully manifest itself for a number of years down the line.</p><p>I thank the Minister of State for her commitment and work in this regard.  The Government's record on this issue is something we can be proud of.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#JJ00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House.  It is important to acknowledge that the Minister of State initiated the summer programme, which is something that needed to be done a long time ago but now is done.  I thank her for that.  It is a programme that is very important and one that is evolving and improving every year.</p> <p>Before I talk about the summer programme, I want to sincerely thank the Minister of State for the work she has done to make next year's leaving certificate papers digitally accessible to people with vision impairments, people who are blind and people with other print disabilities, although the Minister of State might clarify if that is the case.  We were an outlier from other European countries when it came to the examination papers being digitally accessible and every excuse under the sun was used, including the confidentiality and integrity of the paper, you name it.  The bottom line is that technology has moved on.  One has young people doing their education through their iPads and laptops, including the likes of myself and people who have similar conditions to me, who use the iPad and can scroll the print bigger with their fingers.  If I had that in my day it would have been so beneficial to me but it was not available and that is life.  Technology moves on and life moves on and as technology improves it is the great equaliser for people with such physical disabilities.  Next year we will see many more people with print disabilities getting the opportunity to go to third level education, simply because they will be able to read their examination papers in the format and on the equipment they are used to using and are familiar with.  That is a major achievement, driven by the Minister of State and which would not have happened but for the Minister of State.  I have had one-to-one meetings with the Minister of State in her office on this issue and I have also had meetings with F&eacute;ach, the organisation that represents parents of blind and visually impaired children in school.  The Minister of State listened, acted and delivered and that is all we can expect of her.  Well done to her.</p> <p>The Minister of State is delivering for the school programme as well.  It is not perfect by any means but it had to start somewhere and it has started somewhere.  We are in a situation where nearly 50,000 children benefit from the summer programme, which is great news.  I am also delighted that the Minister of State is reviewing it because the learnings from the programme, from people participating in it and from the teachers participating in it are what will make it even better.  The learnings from other countries such as Malta are also positive because if the wheel is there we do not need to reinvent it; we just need to learn from it, make sure it is well-oiled and properly resourced and make sure that it rolls on.  In summer programmes there should be more of a role for parents.  Parents of children with special needs are more involved in their children's education than any other parent but there is a central role that a parent can play in the summer programme because by its nature it is supposed to be more relaxed and fun.  We all know that if one is having fun one will learn and there could be a role for parents, or even older siblings.  I do not know how that might be factored in but it is something that is worth exploring in the engagement and review to see the best international practice.</p> <p>As always, it is important that it is pointed out that there are more resources put into special needs and special education in this country than in a lot of other countries.  We have 15,000 or 16,000 SNAs whereas back in the 1990s there were no SNAs.  I was probably among the first generations who had the opportunity to go to integrated education but had I been going to school in the 1970s I probably would have been going to the special school for the blind.  The reality is that the support I had was the visiting teacher for the visually impaired twice a year.  He was a nice man and he did a good job but the teachers in both of my schools acted as the SNAs and resource teachers because they took a personal interest, along with my community, neighbours and so on.  That created the opportunity for me but in modern Ireland there has to be a better structure and because of that only a tiny proportion of special needs students are going to special schools now.   I would like to think that some day we will be like Italy, where 99% of all students, including those with special needs and requirements, go to mainstream education.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Martin Conway:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2347"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2347&amp;amp;pid=MartinConway&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We are well on the way.  What has been achieved in the past two years in special education in this country is phenomenal and history will look back on this period.  In spite of Covid-19, a war in Europe, and challenges with the cost of living, the one thing that has got more resources year on year is special education.  That is something that the Minister of State and this Government can be proud of.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#KK00200"><p>I thank the Senator for his contribution.  He is a wonderful advocate in the House for the disability sector.  I call on Senator Murphy and I am sorry to have kept him waiting.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#KK00300"><p>Not at all, you are quite all right, a Chathaoirligh.  We will not worry about that.  I welcome the Minister of State to the House and pay tribute to all the work she has been doing in this area throughout her time in office.  She and her officials are to be complimented.  Like many others, I welcome the &euro;40 million for the 2023 summer programme.  As has been said, it is a priority for 2023 that more children in special schools have access to school-based programmes.  As others also have mentioned, in excess of 50,000 pupils have participated in the summer programme.  Up to 1,000 schools have been running a programme, and we hope this will increase year on year.  As has been stated, the review of the programme is very important and the Department is engaging with stakeholders and others and looking at other countries to take everything into account, from administration to workforce expansion to training requirements to vital components with the schools.  Like Senator Carrigy and others, I would like to see more schools taking up these programmes.  That is very important and I believe it will happen.  The review will sort out a lot of issues and concerns that may exist.</p> <p>I remember highlighting an issue in the House more than a year ago that I contacted one national school that was getting some support for special needs and I was clearly told they did not want it, which I thought was shocking at the time, and that the school did not want any publicity about it.  The support was needed in that locality.  That is the sort of thing that should not be happening.  I know at the time we were all shocked but it is to be hoped that type of attitude will go and the review will allow teachers and others to look at possible areas of concern or difficulty and iron those out.  As others have said, this type of programme is so important for students and to give everybody a chance.</p> <p>The continuation of the enhanced summer provision programme for 2022 was a response measure due to the impact of Covid-19 pandemic on education.  Prior to last year's expansion, summer programmes were only available to specialist schools and pupils in special classes in primary and DEIS schools.  It is important we look at the key strands of the programme, which are numeracy and literacy camps in DEIS primary schools; the school based summer programme in primary schools with special classes and in special schools; home-based provisions for children with complex needs where no school-based programme is available; and the opportunity for all primary DEIS and non-DEIS schools to provide a two week summer programme for mainstream pupils with complex needs and those at greater risk of educational disadvantage.</p> <p>There are people who cannot adapt to education as it is.  That was probably not recognised for a long time, but with all of this happening now, we recognise it now.  It is very important, whatever road we go down, that everybody gets the advantage of education.  Education is very advantageous, but sometimes some people cannot adapt to the systems that are in place.  The inclusion programme for primary and post-primary schools remains for 2023, and DEIS numeracy and literacy camps will continue to be available at all DEIS primary schools.  Regardless of whether we are politicians, parents and teachers, we have a responsibility for the young people coming up and we must give them every opportunity we can.  With what the Minister of State is doing here and the money coming again this year to prepare for 2023, we will have more people coming on stream and more young people availing of different opportunities of education.  That is what we need to do because if we do not do that for the future generations, we will not have served our country well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1472" speakername="Josepha Madigan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#KK00700"><p>I will address the Senators who are in the House as opposed to going through the contributions from the other Senators.  Senator Murphy raised some of the points already raised by other Senators.</p> <p>For Senator Dolan's information, there were 45 different summer schools in Galway looking after 726 children.  In Roscommon, there were 11 looking after 249 children.  We would love to see that number increased next year as well.  The Senator mentioned targets.  We have a large number of students who do home-based summer programmes and the target is to move these students to a school-based scheme.  The Senator also asked about my vision and it is a very simple one.  We want all children who need the programme to have access to a school-based programme.  That is critical.  On staffing, we have been engaging with the Department of Further and Higher Education, Research, Innovation and Science to see if we can engage students from other disciplines as well as students we have already opened it up to.  That could be beneficial for everyone taking part - for the student, the school and the children.  The bottom line from what all Senators said today is that we all want the same thing.  The Department, the Minister, Deputy Foley, and I all want the same thing.  It is just to make sure we deliver it.</p> <p>The review that was mentioned is critical.  It is the first time we have done a review and it gives us an opportunity to listen to every single person who is involved in special education - parents in particular but the voices of the children, the special education consultative forum and really everybody.  If there is something we are missing, we can try to change that and make sure we address it so we can get more participation into the future.</p> <p>It is interesting the Senators who are here, such as Senators Carrigy and Murphy, are all advocates for special needs, as has been mentioned.  It is no accident that the people speaking here today are people who are particularly and genuinely interested in this topic.  I know some of the other Senators have left the Chamber but they are all interested.</p> <p>I thank Senator Carrigy for his acknowledgement of the early announcement.  It has been an extremely good thing and a very positive development.  As the Senator said, schools can plan now and they have more certainty as to the funding.  I looked back on last year and we did not announce it until the beginning of May.  Having the announcement in October makes a radical difference.  I take the Senator's point about the details being provided in January, and if there is information that is needed, we can make it known earlier.  That would be a good thing to do.</p> <p>The Senator mentioned an important point which comes up on occasion about making school-based programmes mandatory.  Another Senator mentioned this as well, possibly Senator O'Loughlin.  The difficulty with that is the length of the school year is already set.  The terms and conditions are set and you cannot unilaterally or arbitrarily change that.  That would take much wider discussions across the school community.  I remember talking about it before and the primary schools have 183 days and the post-primary schools have 167 days, so we cannot just change that.  One of the things we did do was to offer double pay for them to extend the school year via the summer programme as an incentive to give them that assistance.  As the Senator knows, there is flexibility now and schools do not have to do it in July, it can be August or whenever.  I wanted to address that with the Senator.  He also mentioned occupational therapy or speech and language therapy students, and they would be very welcome to participate in the summer programme.  Some nurses can as well and they would be welcome, as would other students from healthcare backgrounds.  All of these things are being worked on and it is important to stress that.</p> <p>I thank Senator Conway for his words and he is a great advocate for this area.  He mentioned older siblings and a parental role in the summer provision, and I think that is good.  Senator Carrigy mentioned the innovation done in Kildare with different schools so that at least one of them was providing this.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Josepha Madigan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2424"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2424&amp;amp;pid=JosephaMadigan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Again, these sort of models and pilots can be initiated.  Why should older siblings and parents not have a role as well if it is something that they want?  We engage with the National Parents Council, which sits on the Special Education Consultative Forum, and others to make sure that we do everything we can.</p><p>Suffice to say, I very much welcome all of the Senators' comments.  In response to Senator Carrigy's point, there were 15 schemes in County Longford this summer, benefiting 467 children, and 19 in County Westmeath, benefiting 230 children.  I do not have the figures here for Senators Conway or Murphy , but I can get them to them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#LL00200"><p>No worries.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1472" speakername="Josepha Madigan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#LL00300"><p>We have all of that data.  There was an 18% increase in participation from last year.  As was mentioned, there were 1,000 schools involved in the programme, up from 945 last year.  That is one in four schools, but it is still not enough.  I was talking on the radio earlier and a school principal from County Carlow phoned in.  He said that schools should not be shamed into providing the summer programme.  It is certainly not my intention to shame any school.  Nor should the Department be shaming any school, and it does not.  It is actually about trying to encourage them.  It is about trying to address all of the feedback that we are getting from them as to why they are not providing it.  The main reason, from what we all can glean, is the fact that understandably, the teachers are exhausted by the end of they year, especially after Covid.  Senator Malcolm Byrne asked about that and about the risk of regression.  The Department inspectorate's report mentioned that the regression will continue for a period of time.  The teachers and the SNAs are exhausted too.  That is understandable.  There was also fear of a lack of oversight by bringing in external staff.  Now that the programme has been announced earlier, it allows schools time not just to recruit staff early, but to allow the staff into the school so that they can assimilate themselves, get used to the environment and get to know the children better.   We hope that will alleviate those fears.  There were also some concerns around pay and not being paid on time.  We have dealt with that.  There is an online portal now.  Some 9,000 staff have already been paid from the school-based programme.  The staff from the home-based programme will be paid by the end of this week.  There is a lot of good stuff being done.  We have appointed an overseer role and introduced preparation hours.  We are trying to take away the administrative burden for the schools.  It is not a question of telling schools that we do not want to leave them with any excuse not to do it; it is one of asking them why would they not do it when we are giving them all of these supports.  That is what we are really trying to do.  The teachers tell me themselves that they see the benefits when the children come back in September.  They have had that continuity of education from the time they left.  It has increased their well-being and promoted their positivity in the summer programme.  I thank the Senators for their contributions today.  I will bring them forward with me, and I will take them to the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.120" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar fionra&iacute; ar 5.53 p.m. agus cuireadh t&uacute;s leis ar&iacute;s ar 6.15 p.m.<br /><br />Sitting suspended at 5.53 p.m. and resumed at 6.15 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.121" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#NN00100">Garda Síochána (Compensation) Bill 2021: [Seanad Bill amended by the Dáil] Report and Final Stages</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#NN00200"><p>This is a Seanad Bill which has been amended by the D&aacute;il.  In accordance with Standing Order 148, it is deemed to have passed its First, Second and Third Stages in the Seanad and is placed on the Order Paper for Report Stage.  On the question "That the Bill be received for final consideration", the Minister may explain the purpose of the amendments made by the D&aacute;il.  This is looked upon as the report of the D&aacute;il amendments to the Seanad.    For the convenience of Senators, I have arranged for the printing and circulation to them of those two amendments.</p> <p>The Minister will deal with the subject matter of the amendments, which are grouped together for the purposes of debate.  I remind Senators that the only matters that may be discussed are the amendments made by the D&aacute;il.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.123" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That the Bill be received for final consideration."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1618" speakername="James Browne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#NN00400"><p>Before addressing the amendments, I will briefly address another issue raised in both Houses, namely, the reason this scheme was not extended to civilian staff of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  Civilian staff are not included under the current provisions of the Acts 1941 to 1945, nor were they included in the provisions of this Bill.  This was due to the fact that they are not engaged in front-line policing, which carries an increased risk of injury or death.  However, with the increased civilianisation of certain Garda functions comes the potential for them to be maliciously injured.</p><p>When the point was raised in this House, I agreed that I would discuss the matter with the Minister to see what could be done.  An extension of the scheme was discussed and examined with stakeholders, including the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform.  However, such an extension would not have been clear-cut due to the status of civilian staff as civil servants and the existing schemes and supports that already apply to them.  </p><p><i>Ex gratia</i>payments can be made to civil servants in the event of an assault.  Civil servants are also covered by the occupational injuries scheme and there are benefits in this context available to them.  One of the main concerns related to the interaction that would occur with these existing schemes.  This had the potential to delay the passage of the Bill quite significantly and I think we all agree reform is needed in Garda compensation claims.  As I mentioned on Committee Stage in the D&aacute;il, this can be re-examined in the context of another Bill once the new compensation scheme has commenced.  I thank Senators and Deputies for raising this question in both Houses.  </p><p>There are two technical amendments that relate to sections 11 and 16(2)(c).  The amendments will remove the requirement for the form of the application for initial assessment and the form for review to be prescribed by way of regulation, while retaining the need to publish the form electronically.  The application form to the Garda Commissioner and the application form to the Personal Injuries Assessment Board, PIAB, must align.  As the application form to PIAB may change slightly from time to time, the application form to the Garda Commissioner would then have to be adjusted.  It is, therefore, more straightforward to set out that the Garda Commissioner will determine the form of the application.  This change is also in line with the removal of the administration of the scheme from the Minister.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1669" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#NN00500"><p>There is just one point I would like to make.  We had a discussion about civilian employees of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and I do not know what happened with regard to that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1618" speakername="James Browne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#NN00600"><p>The view was taken that they would not be part of this scheme because they are not on the front line.  Nonetheless, considering the increased civilianisation, it will be looked at.  However, because of existing schemes for civil servants - the occupational injuries scheme and <i>ex gratia</i>payments scheme - it would be very complicated and would slow up this Bill significantly.  I give an undertaking to look at it but not in the context of this Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1669" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#NN00700"><p>The time will come when somebody throws a petrol bomb into a Garda station and a young Garda and two typists get injured.  The Garda will get compensation but the two typists will get nothing.  That is not right.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#NN00800"><p>The point is well made.  The Minister of State has committed to reflect on that situation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.129" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#NN00950"><p>When is it proposed to take Fifth Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" speakername="Barry Ward" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#NN00975"><p>Now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#NN00987"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.133" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question, "That the Bill do now pass", put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.134" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#OO00100">Judicial Appointments Commission Bill 2022: Committee Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.135" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>SECTION 1</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.136" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That section 1 stand part of the Bill."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1669" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#OO00300"><p>I wish to make a point about this section, if I may.  I got a ruling from the Chair today that three of my amendments were out of order, which came as a bit of a surprise given that one of them had previously been debated extensively in the House as part of the previous iteration of the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#OO00400"><p>It was the Cathaoirleach, not I, who ruled them out of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1669" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#OO00500"><p>I find it odd that the amendment is now found to be beyond the scope of this Bill.  I will take up the matter with the Cathaoirleach.  However, I will say that one of those amendments is very important.  The purpose of the Bill is to amend the Judicial Council Bill and there is a mistake in that legislation which needs urgent amendment.  I am more relaxed about my third amendment.  I want to make the point that these rulings are not in anybody's interests.  These are matters which should be dealt with soon.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1502" speakername="Helen McEntee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#OO00600"><p>We are amending it in the miscellaneous Bill.  I can speak to the matter later.  I was not sure what had been ruled in or out.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#OO00700"><p>Whatever section the Senator's amendments have been ruled out of order in-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1669" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#OO00800"><p>I just find it strange that on one of the few occasions that I was not here during Committee Stage of the previous Bill, one of the amendments I have tabled here today was debated and the then Minister, Deputy Flanagan, said it was an important issue which he might consider including on Report Stage, and I am now told the issue cannot even be discussed.  That is strange.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#OO00900"><p>The Senator can certainly speak to the section his proposed amendments would have dealt with when we get there.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1669" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#OO01000"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.145" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.146" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>NEW SECTION</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" speakername="Mark Wall" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#OO01300"><p>I move amendment No. 1:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 6, between lines 13 and 14, to insert the following:<br /><br />&ldquo;<b>Object of Act: judicial independence</b><br /><br /><b>2</b>. (1) With a view to upholding the independence of the judiciary as the foundation of public confidence in the administration of justice, the Oireachtas in passing this Act seeks to ensure that the recommendation and selection of persons to serve in judicial office is based on merit and is free from political patronage.<br /><br />(2) All persons concerned with the administration of this Act or who perform functions under it shall act in accordance with the object specified in subsection (1).<br /><br />(3) This Act shall so far as is practicable be construed in accordance with the Dublin Declaration on Standards for the Recruitment and Appointment of Members of the Judiciary, adopted by the General Assembly of the European Network of Councils for the Judiciary at its meeting in Dublin on 9 to 11 May 2012.&rdquo;. </blockquote> <p>The Minister is very welcome.  This amendment is based on upholding judicial independence.  In particular, our amendment seeks to incorporate as an interpretative aid the 2012 Dublin declaration on standards for the recruitment and appointment of members of the Judiciary, adopted by the General Assembly of the European Network of Councils for the Judiciary.  On that basis, we are asking the amendment to be adopted.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1669" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#OO01400"><p>This is an important amendment which I support.  It clearly sets out that the selection of persons to serve in judicial office is based on merit, which is in the Bill already, but also "is free from political patronage".  Two points occur to me.  I do not accept that, for instance, in deciding which of three people should be recommended for appointment to the Supreme Court, the Government of the day is debarred from making a political choice - with a small "p" in the word "political" - in the sense that it could decide it wants a liberal person and does not want a conservative person. That is a political choice which the Constitution confers on the Government.</p> <p>During the time I was Minister for Justice and the late Rory Brady, senior counsel, was Attorney General, the great majority of the appointees to the superior courts were people who we understood to be supporters of the Opposition parties at the time.  I want that point on the record.  It has not always been the case that political patronage has been the determinant or a major determinant of judicial appointments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" speakername="Barry Ward" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#OO01500"><p>I broadly agree with the statement Senator McDowell has made.  It is tremendously important to remember that there is a basis on which there should be a political involvement, a democratic involvement, if you will, in the appointment of judges.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Barry Ward:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=BarryWard&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->They are a branch of the Government in the Judiciary, as a whole, and it is appropriate that the people have some say through the Government.  That is the way it has worked and that is the way it should continue to work, which is why the Government still makes those appointments even under this legislation.</p><p>I wish to raise a point that is important to remember.  Once appointed, judges have no colour and no politics.  That has been the overwhelming experience of the Judiciary in this country for generations and continues to be the case.  There is a broad misconception that somehow, because a judge may have been politically active in the past, and many of them have been, that that politics continues into their judicial life.  In my experience, it does not.  They put that behind, separate themselves from it and it does not affect their decision-making on the bench.  That can be seen in countless examples of where judges who might be of one party have made decisions against that party when it was in government, for example.  The former political life of a person does not intersect with his or her judicial life, once appointed, in my experience.  It is very important to state that because to have it any other way would be to absolutely denigrate the good work that is done by the Judiciary.  As I have said in this Chamber on many occasions, we are lucky enough to have a Judiciary that is on the whole excellent.  That comes from the fact that those people divorce themselves from any political opinions they might have held before being appointed to judicial office and they take very seriously the independence that they need to exercise as a judge. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1502" speakername="Helen McEntee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#PP00200"><p>The Constitution provides for judicial independence and this Bill supports judicial independence.  I support the Senator's last comments that we have an independent Judiciary, one that we can be very proud of and one that is held up right across the world.</p><p>I thank the Senators for tabling this amendment.  The amendment provides for a new section.  It provides for an object of the Act being judicial independence and obviously there has been an explanation as to where this has come from.  The object of the proposed Act in itself is relatively straightforward; it seeks to establish a new commission to recommend persons for appointment.  Of course it does more than that.  It puts the entire system of appointments on a completely different level in terms of transparency and strengthens the procedures we have to safeguard the integrity that is already there in terms of the process of appointment.  I would say it is already manifesting, perceived and recognised at home and internationally as a very good, transparent and independent process.</p><p>The Bill is compliant with international standards.  The Court of Justice has taken the view that because national courts such as our courts in Ireland must implement and adjudicate on various fields of EU law, the process of appointment of judges to these courts must ensure the effective judicial protection of individual rights.  The Bill will achieve that and these provisions are also consistent with the Dublin Declaration, which was referred to in the amendment tabled by the Senators.</p><p>The method of appointing judges is seen as having a key impact on independence from an EU context.  The specific concern of the European Commission in the context of the rule of law report, and the Council of Europe's Group of States against Corruption, GRECO, is the level of discretion a member state government might have <i>vis-&agrave;-vis</i>an advisory or recommending body when it comes to appointments.  In particular, the European Court of Justice ruling has made it clear that an obligation under the rule of law it operates in the European Union is the maintenance and enhancing of the impartiality and independence of the courts.  The possibility that a Government would appoint a person who is not recommended by the independent body would be contrary to this rule of law in that context.  Also, it would be contrary to a merit-based approach.</p><p>Senator Ward referred to political patronage in the amendment and the requirement, under the amendment, is for a merit-based system and that is very clearly set out in the Act.  For the first time, this Bill will essentially provide that no appointment can be possible without the Government first receiving a recommendation from the commission.  Under section 39, they have to be merit-based.  Merit will have regard to a number of objectives set out in section 39, which we will mention later.  Government discretion to appoint will be from a limited choice of three candidates, while at the same time providing for the fact that our Constitution sets out clearly that a Government must appoint and so it still allows for that.</p><p>Senators will know that currently and historically when an appointment of a serving judge to a higher office is made that it will not have come through the Judicial Appointments Advisory Board, JAAB.  The remit of the board, under the Courts and Court Officers Act 1995, is restricted to people seeking appointment for the first time.  We will change that and make sure that everybody has to go through the judicial appointments commission.</p><p>More generally, I am confident that the new approach will enhance the reputation that we already have in terms of the independence of the Judiciary.  The Bill contributes to that.  As I have said, the Constitution provides for judicial independence and the Bill in itself supports that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1669" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#PP00300"><p>Briefly arising out of that, I am a bit mystified by some of the provisions of this Bill and I have studied it more carefully.  One of these provision is section 42.  Section 42(1) provides:</p> <blockquote> 	The Minister may request the Commission to make recommendations for appointment or for nomination for appointment to judicial office, as the case may be, where&mdash;  	(a) a judicial office stands vacant, or<br /><br />(b) he or she reasonably anticipates that there will be a vacancy in a judicial office.  </blockquote> <p>That seems to be discretionary in that the Minister &quot;may&quot; do so but is not obliged to do so.  I can see one circumstance in which the Minister might not make request the commission to make recommendations if it was intended to decrease the number of judges, say, in the High Court, the Court of Appeal or the Supreme Court.  He might say we are leaving that vacant so although there is a vacancy there, it stands vacant and not ask for recommendations.  I can see that that could happen but if one combines that with section 51----- </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#PP00400"><p>I remind the Senator we are on section 2, amendment No. 1.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1669" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#PP00500"><p>Yes, but I am talking about what the Labour Party amendment is about, which is the appointment of people.  I am not trying to waste time at all and I will be very brief.</p> <p>Section 51 seems to confine the Government to considering "recommended persons only" but section 42 seems to say that the Minister has a discretion as to whether he looks for recommendations in the first place.  I wonder how the word "may" gels with section 51 and what the Minister has just said.  Is it to be the case that the Government is to be prohibited from considering for appointment any person who has not been recommended?  Is that what this Bill is saying?  If so, why is it that section 42 does not make it mandatory rather than discretionary in terms of filling a vacancy?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1502" speakername="Helen McEntee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#PP00600"><p>What is very clear in this Bill is that a person cannot be and will not be appointed unless he or she has gone through the process.  As the Senator has outlined, there may be a situation, as is currently the case or had been previously the case, where vacancies are not filled.  For example, in the Supreme Court if a vacancy arises but it is not to be filled immediately, then it is not absolutely the case that the Minister of the day may ask for or should ask for a process to start.  The Bill is absolutely clear that no person will be appointed unless he or she has gone through the judicial appointments commission, unless he or she has gone through an interview process and unless the person is one of the three names that have been put forward to the Minister.  There is no other intention behind the provision.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1669" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#PP00700"><p>I can understand that is the purpose of the Bill.</p> <p>Section 51(1) seems on the face of it to say that a person could be appointed who had been recommended by the commission but was not recommended on this occasion.  The provision seems ambiguous and I am interested in that aspect.  Maybe we will come back to it later when we discuss the section. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#PP00800"><p>Yes, Senator.  When we reach the section we will come back to that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.158" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.159" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>SECTION 2</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#PP01000"><p>Amendments Nos. 2, 3, 5, 29 and 37 are related.  Amendment No. 37 is consequential on amendment No. 5.  Amendments Nos. 2, 3, 5, 29 and 37 may be discussed together, by agreement.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.  .</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1669" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#PP01100"><p>I move amendment No. 2:</p> <blockquote> 	In page  8, between lines 34 and 35, to insert the following:  	&ldquo; &ldquo;practitioner representative&rdquo; means a practising member of the solicitors or barristers profession nominated by the Law Society of Ireland or the General Council of the Bar of Ireland, as the case may be, and appointed by the Minister;&rdquo;.  </blockquote> <p>Amendment No. 2 is in the names of myself and my fellow Independent Senators.  Amendment No. 2 is part of a number of amendments, which are now grouped together for discussion.  Its purpose is to ensure that the judicial appointments commission should include among its members one practising barrister and one practising solicitor nominated by their respective professional bodies.  I know it is an objective of the Minister to keep the commission small.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Michael McDowell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=719"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=719&amp;amp;pid=MichaelMcDowellPD&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I regard it as close on ridiculous that in making judicial appointments both branches of the practising legal profession are given no input whatsoever into a consideration of the suitability of a candidate for appointment to the Bench at any level.  This seems to be a deliberate policy in this legislation and it is a change from the previous legislation promoted by the former Minister Deputy Flanagan.</p><p>To say that we do not want to hear what the representatives of either legal profession have to say at all on the suitability of candidates for the Judiciary and - worse than that - that the professions are effectively debarred from having any part in the process whatsoever because if they interfere, they will be accused of seeking to influence the outcome of the commission's activities seems to be completely indefensible.</p><p>Nobody is in a better position to judge the temperament of a solicitor or a barrister than his or her colleagues in either branch of the profession.  If they are ten years in practice, nobody is in a better position to say that while the person may appear squeaky-clean, there is a screw missing, there is an attitudinal problem, they are personally not given to being impartial or are unsuitable for 1,000 different reasons.  Nobody knows these things, but their colleagues do know these things.  Their colleagues on the Judicial Appointments Advisory Board have that function.</p><p>As Attorney General, I was a member of that board.  The judicial members of that board would ask if anybody knew much about the person being considered.  The legal practitioners would generally say that he or she is a good person.  However, sometimes they would say, "A big warning should be attached to that person.  They are really not suitable.  Their CV as handed in may look brilliant but we are warning that there could be question marks there."  There could be a conversation about why that was said about individuals.  I am not cooking up some crazy theory here.  I am talking about every court in the land.  There are solicitors and barristers who want to become District Court judges.  The people with whom they practise in their local county will have a view and their view may not be determinative if but at least it should be heard.  I find it difficult to understand why an ideological decision has been made here.</p><p>Regarding independence from the Government or political independence, the input of the legal practitioners heretofore has been absolutely neutral.  Nobody in the Judicial Appointments Advisory Board will point out that a candidate is a member of the Labour Party, Fine Gael or whatever and should or should not be appointed on that basis.  Nobody will say something like that on behalf of either of the professions.  Nobody who was appointed to the Judicial Appointments Advisory Board would for one minute consider discussing the politics of somebody who is under consideration.</p><p>We are left here with what I consider to be a brazen attempt to exclude a group of people who really have some practical experience of their colleagues.  They have some vague idea of their reputation, how they really conduct themselves and what kind of person they really.  If they are extremely touchy, short-tempered or whatever, this may not come out in a carefully schooled interview.  This may not come out if the decision is left to a number of judges and laypersons who have not heard of the person in question and know nothing about how they spent the ten years in practice that they are obliged to have spent in order to qualify for appointment.</p><p>I understand the Minister's desire to keep this body reasonably small and compact.  However, the extension from nine to 11 for the purpose incorporating two practitioner representatives in the manner suggested in the group of amendments we are discussing here would enhance the board, would make its decision safer and would eliminate risks which otherwise will not be adverted to.  People will present letters of recommendation or whatever.  People will present themselves for interview but will be interviewed by strangers who know nothing about them, know nothing about their weaknesses and have not been warned by anybody that this is not a good idea.</p><p>From my own participation in JAAB I know that the presence of practitioners did not affect the independence of the appointees, but brought this vital element of reality in possibly identifying someone as being seriously unsuitable because they did X, Y or Z.  They may have fired all their staff from the solicitor's office.  They have misled judges as a barrister and things like that.  That information is only available if there is some channel for it to come before the persons who are making a recommendation.  Unless the members of the Judiciary or the lay members are to go around and try to pick up gossip about people, that whole dimension of the candidate's personal standing in their professional community is completely left out.</p><p>In conjunction with this, because two extra lawyers were to be on the commission, I tabled an amendment proposing that the number of laypeople be increased by one.  That has been ruled out of order because it might impose a charge on the Exchequer, which frankly is weird, but there you are.  Another amendment, which was debated at length here under the Bill proposed by the former Minister Deputy Flanagan, is now said to be outside the scope of this legislation.</p><p>I am not trying to diminish the level of participation of laypeople or to switch the balance in any way.  We have something that works well with input from professional colleagues which can be extremely valuable in the consideration of a person's suitability.  Instead, we will have a group of people who have never met the person before they interview them, know nothing about them, and will not try to pick up intelligence as to whether they are good, bad or indifferent because that will not happen.  Neither the laypeople nor the members of the Judiciary will do that.  Appointments will be made on the blind.  People who present well at interviews and seem to have a squeaky-clean paper application will get appointed even though there were people who could have said it was a mistake.</p><p>We have not done much in our proposed amendment.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Michael McDowell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=719"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=719&amp;amp;pid=MichaelMcDowellPD&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We have merely said that one practising member of the solicitors' profession and one practising member of the barristers' profession, nominated by their professional bodies for appointment by the Minister for a term of three years and removable in the same way as a lay member if there is any problem with them, would bring significant added value to the commission and that their absence would make it seriously more likely that mistakes will be made by appointing people on temperamental and other grounds to the Bench.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#RR00200"><p>Before I call Senator Ward, I welcome Lucy Whelan and her dad to the Visitors' Gallery.  Lucy is here on an internship, I believe, in the Minister's office.  She will be able to put that on her CV when she is going for a job, perhaps in the Judiciary, but we will see how this Bill works out.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" speakername="Barry Ward" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#RR00300"><p>I will support the amendments, which make a great deal of sense.  The notion that the professions that know and understand the role a judge plays would be cut out of the decision-making process is, I think, flawed.  They should not have a veto.  I have a certain discomfort that the words as spoken by Senator McDowell, with the greatest of respect, sound a little like a boys' club supporting or endorsing one of their own.  That is not what it is about.  It is about people having an understanding of the individuals involved in a profession who might have a reputation among their colleagues.  It is less about a veto because there is no perfect system and any lawyer will agree there are colleagues who seem like perfectly reasonable people but who find themselves on the Bench and suddenly develop what we know as &quot;judgitis&quot; and can sometimes manifest traits they did not have in practice, and <i>vice versa</i>.  People who you might have thought would be wonderful members of the Bench do not always turn out to be that way.  There is no perfect system and no hard and fast way to assess who is or is not going to be a good judge.</p><p>Nevertheless, there is a benefit in having what a colleague of mine refers to as a smell test or a litmus test, which somebody might not pass for a good and justifiable reason, not because Joe does not like him or Mary thinks he is whatever.  It is about knowing the person in the context of his or her professional past, behaviour or reputation.  If a lot of laypeople who have no connection to the legal professions and no understanding of how they work are brought in to make that decision, that will divorce that professional experience from the decision-making process, and there will be a loss in that regard.</p><p>On Second Stage, I raised this issue and the Minister pointed out that there are provisions to ensure that some of the judges from the Judicial Council who are put onto this commission will include both those who formerly practised as solicitors and those who formerly practised as barristers and I applaud the attempt to recognise the professions in that respect, but I do not think it is adequate for a number of reasons.  As I said just a moment ago, when a person becomes a judge, he or she leaves behind in many respects his or her past experiences, albeit not all of them and they inform his or her judicial persona.  There are not judges who are former solicitors and judges who are former barristers.  We could certainly point out judges who previously practised as barristers and those who previously practised as solicitors, but that is not their persona on the Bench.  Their persona is as a judge and they change when they move from the role of poacher to that of gamekeeper, if I can put it in those terms.  They change and no longer occupy a position as a former solicitor or former barrister.  I think there is a fundamental flaw in trying to address the absence of the professions' input into the decision-making process by having that in the judicial corner.  I do not think that works.</p><p>The other difficulty with that is there will not necessarily be a balance of barristers and solicitors in any court.  For example, there will be far more solicitors in one court than another and far more barristers in one than another, and there will be no guarantee as we go through the process that there will be an adequate number of people from whom to select former solicitors and former barristers.  The notion of doing it that way is inadequate and far inferior to the notion of putting a representative of each of the professions on the commission who, as a representative of his or her respective profession, will have the ability to have that input at the point where the decision and the appointment are being made.  It is akin to a committee to appoint a consultant cardiac surgeon having no cardiologist or doctor on the committee.  We would not say that was reasonable because there would need to be somebody who has the expertise to understand the application coming before the committee.  Those two circumstances are comparable because the appointment of a judge requires a level of professional understanding of the individual but also of the role and where that person can fit into the role.</p><p>I support the notion that there would be professional representatives.  Where that has been the position in the past, in the case of JAAB, it has worked well.  I return to the comment I made earlier in respect of our Judiciary.  On the whole, our Judiciary works very well, diligently and impartially and does a very good job.  To an extent,, it is a case of &quot;If it ain't broke, don't fix it&quot;.  For that reason, these amendments make sense and are worthy of consideration if the Minister feels that is appropriate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1688" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#RR00400"><p>The illumination from Senator McDowell, particularly in regard to amendment No. 2, was helpful.  I am minded to support that amendment because of what he said.  Moreover, for all the reasons Senator Ward acknowledged, it would make sense to have practitioners who are not members of the Judiciary.  That would give a valuable insight and I recognise that.  I was not entirely convinced by Senator Ward's earlier contribution, given it may leave the matter open to accusations of a boys' club, a girls' club or whatever the case may be.   I am keen to hear what the Minister has to say about these amendments but in particular about amendment No. 2 because a strong argument has been made as to why it would be a sensible approach to have two practitioners on the commission who could give an insight.  I do not like the notion of every practitioner knowing every detail about every fellow practitioner in the State.  That would be worrying but from an experience perspective, it may prove helpful to the work of the commission.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#RR00500"><p>Strong cases have been made by Senators McDowell and Ward.  This area is not my focus, which tends to be on human rights representation and the very important layperson's perspective.  I have always been an advocate in general, in all areas of public service, for 360&deg; references, whereby not just those who have worked above a person but also those who have worked below and alongside him or her would give references.  I think that is a great idea and there is something to be said for those who have argued cases before judges and have that sense of how it works.  For me, the proposal to expand the numbers is the key in this context.  I do not think 11 is too onerous a number to allow the commission to perform its functions.  It is important we do not erode the lay persons' votes but some strong arguments have been made.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1502" speakername="Helen McEntee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#RR00600"><p>There are a number of elements to this, as the Senators pointed out.  One aspect I wanted to ensure was that there will not be a large commission whose number just continues to increase.  There are a number of later amendments regarding specific numbers of lay persons who should be appointed and how to reduce that.  I do not think the figure, therefore, would go from nine to 11 but rather to 13 because, as I have set out clearly, there need to be an equal number of legal persons as well as lay persons on the commission, working with the Attorney General but with the Chief Justice as chair.</p> <p>We are moving away from the use of peer impressions of individuals.  I do not necessarily agree it is the case that a nominee from the Bar Council and a nominee from the Law Society would know every person in the professions and be able to comment on every one of them.  It is just as likely that a person who has more recently been appointed to the District Court, having come from one of those legal professions, would have as much an understanding of an individual but also, as someone now sitting on the Bench, he or she would have an understanding of what is required of the candidate.</p> <p>Currently, there are no interviews, so perhaps it works better that people know, to a greater extent, whom they are talking about, although I reiterate I do not think any individual could know everybody.  We are now focusing on an interview, objective testing, skills and knowledge, all set out by the commission.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Helen McEntee:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2394"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2394&amp;amp;pid=HelenMcEntee&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->While interviews might not be perfect, for any job or role they are the best test to see who is suitable for a job.  People can always ask and inquire if there are questions or queries about an individual, but we are introducing a new system and structure whereby an interview will have to take place and a person will have to set out their competencies and skills.</p><p>I do not in any way want either profession to think that we do not respect the work done by the current Judicial Appointments Advisory Board, JAAB, or that its opinions are not worthy.  I have made clear that of the nine people, there will be the Chief Justice, the president of the court that will be appointing a person to the particular vacancy and two nominees by the Judicial Council ensuring that we have a man and woman, because we need to make sure we have that gender balance, and somebody with a background in practising as a solicitor or barrister and that these are taken into account, acknowledging that it is important to have a balance of both professions.</p><p>Overall, this is not to reflect badly on how the Judicial Appointments Advisory Board has worked to date, but we are moving to a new system.  We are moving away from this idea that it is based on impressions or on a peer-to-peer process.  It is very much focused on merit, it is independent and it is based on people's skills, knowledge and understanding.  Those sitting on the Bench would have a history and a past of practising on the other side of the Bench and would have a clear picture of what is required.  This would obviously be supported by the lay members as well.</p><p>I am not sure why Senator McDowell&rsquo;s second amendment has been ruled out of order because I think other colleagues will propose amendments that will balance it out.  I am not sure what the issue is there.  However, as I said, it would not be a case of moving from nine to 11 people, but it would be moving up to 13.  It is important that we have a stakeholder representative group that is small and coherent in size and not large and unwieldy.  Unfortunately, for those reasons, I cannot accept the amendments that have been tabled by Senators.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1669" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#SS00200"><p>I will raise two points.  First, the suggestion, as Senator Ward pointed out, that the Judicial Council members will somehow represent the diversity of the professions is just not statable as a proposition because the two nominees will be one male and one female nominee, one of whom, at the time of his or her appointment as a judge, will have come from the solicitor&rsquo;s profession while the other will have come from the barrister&rsquo;s profession.  The Judicial Council could be appointing somebody who has been out of the profession for 20 years and who has about as much connection to the solicitor&rsquo;s profession or to the Bar as anybody.</p> <p>I am talking about granular, real understanding of the kind of people who we will have seen writing letters as a solicitor.  We will have seen that a certain person is rude, offensive and all the rest of it and we will know that he or she has let down his or her partners on five different occasions.  Things like that go to one&rsquo;s reputation.  That reputation should be just completely thrown out it is foolish, especially when there is an easy means to have at least some chance that a person with a poor reputation does not wander through the system and get selected.</p> <p>The fact that a member of the Judicial Council has been elected by his or her colleagues and was a barrister or a solicitor 15 or 20 years ago will say nothing as to whether some young person who has been in practice for ten years is or is not suitable to be made a District Judge.  It just simply will not speak to that issue at all, and it is of no help whatsoever.</p> <p>It is a bit strange that my efforts to keep the lay and non-lay balance by reference to these amendments was ruled out of order on the basis that this might put a charge on the Exchequer.  I just cannot understand it at all.  It seems to be on the basis that they could get expenses and that there would be more expenses if there were one or two more people on the commission.  That shows how ludicrous the Standing Orders of this House have become, that you cannot suggest that you are going to balance something without being told, &ldquo;Oh they could claim expenses for turning up to a meeting so therefore you cannot make that balancing suggestion&rdquo;.   Therefore, it is effectively the Minister&rsquo;s position that nobody can increase the size of this commission because to do so requires a balancing exercise which could give rise to expenses.  This is something I find a bit difficult to swallow, but there you are.  The Chair has so ruled, and I am stuck with that.</p> <p>The difference between nine and 11 people is not all that important.  Will they all turn up on the day?  They may or they may not.  Some may be on holidays.  Some may be on maternity leave.  You can never know; they may not turn up on the day.  The difference between nine and 11 on this commission, therefore, is not some horrific difference in numbers.  I have to reject the argument that it would make it in anyway unmanageable to have 11 rather than nine people on it.</p> <p>While I am on that subject, I point that of the nine, the Bill as it stands at present states that the Attorney General cannot vote, so that is eight.  You have four judges and four lay people.  The Bill does not even give anybody a casting vote, which is even more remarkable.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" speakername="Barry Ward" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#SS00300"><p>My amendment will deal with that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1669" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#SS00400"><p>Senator Ward has tabled an amendment to do that.  It is amusing because the Bill, as it stands at present, means there will be a deadlock.  The four lay people will obviously listen carefully to the judges as a group.  They will not come in say, &ldquo;We are the lay people, and we have this candidate&rdquo; and the Judiciary will not say, &ldquo;Well this is our person&rdquo;.  I believe that the practitioner representatives would tend to assist the lay people rather than the establishment Judiciary in ensuring that there will be an openness to the whole thing.  If I were a layperson who was appointed through this system and if I were one of eight people who could vote on this issue, I would much prefer to have somebody else who was not a judge saying, &ldquo;I am with you on that person.  I agree with you on that&rdquo;.  The notion that somehow the practitioners would all align with the Judiciary is in my view mistaken.This is a point of fairly fundamental importance.  I did not table this amendment just to make a point or to hear the sound of my own voice.  It is a huge, fundamental error in this legislation that the professions are being railroaded out of it.  It is a big, fundamental mistake.</p><p>I heard what the Minister said by way of reply, but I do not accept the rationale of what she said.  She has not said that professional representatives or practitioners would be a bad thing.  She has not said that they would tend to be part of the <i>status quo</i>.  If we are talking about old boys&rsquo; clubs, the Judiciary is far more likely to be an old boys&rsquo; club together, than the Judiciary with two practitioner representatives looking at what they are doing.  I believe that it is a fundamental mistake not to accept this amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.173" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1502" speakername="Helen McEntee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#SS00500"><p>I have to stress what we are talking about here.  I appreciate that these amendments propose moving from nine to 11 people, but it would in fact become nine to 13, because I could not or would not accept that there would be a minority of lay persons.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Helen McEntee:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2394"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2394&amp;amp;pid=HelenMcEntee&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We have tried to strike a balance to ensure an equal number of laypeople and legal professionals on the commission.</p><p>The Senator mentioned the fact that the Chief Justice will not have a casting vote and that decisions will be made on the basis of consensus.  That is how JAAB has operated in effect.  I understand there has never been a vote at the JAAB.  It is important that names are put forward on the basis of consensus.  That is a good way to work and it is why I want to continue in that vein.  We are talking about a change from nine to 13, which would change the dynamic of any group.</p><p>In any other profession, people are appointed on the basis of an interview process in the vast majority of cases.  Appointments are not based on what a member of the profession thinks or does not think about a candidate, or may or may not have heard about him or her.  The Judicial Council must appoint people from the upper and lower courts.  A solicitor or barrister appointed to the District Court may only recently have left their profession and may have as much knowledge or information about current practising barristers or solicitors as anybody else.  We must get away from the idea of making appointments on the basis of knowing people's tics or lack thereof, or what they did or did not do in their previous roles.  We must focus only on a person's skills, expertise, knowledge of the courts, performance, personality and temperament.  Through an interview process, one can discover those things about a candidate.  It is not a perfect process in any profession but we are trying to make it as transparent as possible.  At the moment, the situation is that nobody is interviewed.  A substantial number of names come to the Minister and he or she then has to make a decision having, in the vast majority of cases, never met any of the candidates.  The Minister makes the decision on the basis of candidates' CVs, reputations and what they have put down.  I do not mean in any way to say that the opinions of those at the Bar Council of Ireland and the Law Society of Ireland are not valued or important.  What I have tried to do, albeit Senators do not agree, is to ensure we have representation of solicitors and barristers.  I agree that once someone becomes a judge there is no such thing as a solicitor-judge or barrister-judge, in the same way that a person is not from a political party if he or she was previously active.  There is still, however, that level of experience there and that can be reflected in decisions that are taken.  Unfortunately, for those reasons, I am not going to accept the amendments that have been put forward.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1669" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#TT00200"><p>The Minister has said that it is usual for people to interview for positions.  Take the position of a lecturer or professor in a university.  It is extremely unusual to say that the only groups of people who cannot be there at the interview board are lecturers or professors.  That is what we are doing here.  As Senator Ward said, if someone is to be appointed to a medical position, it is extremely unusual to say that the only people who cannot have any input into the decision at all are other medical practitioners.  That is what this Bill is achieving.  I accept the Minister's point that we would not have this legislation at all if JAAB was perfect.  However, to say this is an improvement on JAAB does not and cannot mean that it is the ideal solution.  I do not accept the proposition.</p> <p>I often wonder who these laypeople are going to be.  I am fairly certain they will face a cohort of judges and the judges are going to be in a position to discuss things beforehand and the laypeople will find themselves slightly on the outside.  The groups of people who could come to the aid of the process and with whom appointers could discuss the matter are other practitioners, who could be asked if particular candidates are really as good as they are making themselves out to be.  I would like the Minister's input on that point.</p> <p>The Minister also made the point that a young District Court judge may be on the Bench.  How likely is it that the Judicial Council is going to select the most recently appointed judge to go forward to this body?  If I know judges, the least likely outcome is that they would appoint the most junior judge to this body when there are others who have spent 15 or 20 years on the Bench.  Those judges are not going to prefer a barrister or solicitor who has recently been appointed a judge in order to find out what the professions think about the suitability of a candidate.</p> <p>The Minister is well aware that everything in the legal profession is changing.  The majority of practitioners on both sides are now women, or that is nearly the case.  We do not have to lean over backwards to achieve gender balance in the professions.  The professions are gender balanced at the moment.  As far as I can see, the Bar Council of Ireland is a gender-balanced entity.  We recently had two women chairpersons.  The notion that barristers or solicitors should be excluded because they are barristers or solicitors is indefensible.</p> <p>The point is that the definition of a layperson in section 2, which is the section we are dealing with, excludes barristers or solicitors, effectively, unless they are well out of practice.  In its totality, this Bill means that the only groups of people being excluded from becoming members of this commission in any shape or form are practising barristers or solicitors.  Of all the people who could be on the commission, this Bill goes to considerable trouble to state that a practising barrister or solicitor can never be part of this process.  For the Minister to come before this House and say she has great respect for the two professions is fair enough, and I take her at her word.  However, we are being asked to enact a Bill for the first time - and the former Minister, Deputy Flanagan, never tried this trick - to state that the only groups of people who cannot have any input whatsoever into the deliberation of this commission are practising barristers and solicitors.  They are somehow considered unsuitable to participate in this commission because they are practising.  That is the logic.  Section 2 states that these professionals do not qualify as laypeople and are not judges.  Therefore, the Bill is stating that veterinarians, advertising agents or medical doctors can be on this commission but a woman who is a practising solicitor or barrister is deemed unsuitable to serve on this commission.  I do not accept that.  I do not think there is any logic to it.  A frozen mind is being brought to this issue, based on the proposition that we want to keep the commission small and even between laypeople and people who have legal experience.  We are confining it, therefore, to judges versus laypeople, one block against another, when we could so easily have done what the former Minister, Deputy Flanagan, did, that is, to provide that the two professions could be represented on this commission.</p> <p>When the dust settles on the debate around this Bill, we are saying to practising barristers and solicitors of either gender that as a matter of law, they are the only people who cannot participate in this commission for some ideological reason.  That is wrong.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#TT00300"><p>A truism that is constantly put forward in the context of all boards is that we need boards to be much smaller.  It is a message that comes out again and again but without evidence.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Alice-Mary Higgins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2480"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2480&amp;amp;pid=AliceMaryHiggins&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->In general, with regard to "nothing about us without us" and all these other principles for which we argue in different ways, there should be an openness to moving to 13 if that is the case.  It is not so much to the Minister solely but I have noticed a pattern in State appointments.  There is a narrowing and I worry about the weighting of the importance of having a small board.  It is important there is at least an equivalent lay number of majority but I also think something can be added by those professions, so I think 13 is something that should be looked at.  We will come to it later but I note one thing that could free up a space.  The Minister will note that I suggest later that the Attorney General should be solely an observer and should not be a member in that context.  This could open space within the constraints placed upon us in terms of adding numbers.  </p><p>I also note that regarding the categorisation of lay persons, I am worried that there is some narrowness in terms of aspects of the lay experience and that we will end up with a very narrow contingent of the lay population who qualify because certain professions and expertise seem to be very strongly privileged over other very relevant areas of expertise but we will come to those amendments in due course.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1502" speakername="Helen McEntee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#UU00200"><p>We are not talking about the degree of connection to the profession here.  Regarding the two nominees from the Judicial Council, it is about an understanding of the role, how it operates, how people feel and an appreciation and understanding of what is required.  This is why we have the interview process as well.  It is not about the connection to the profession and removing that connection or suggesting it is not important.  It is about the role itself, and making sure the interview process focuses solely on the role and somebody's suitability for it.  That is why we have set this out.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.179" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#UU00300"><p>How stands the amendment?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1669" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#UU00400"><p>I am pressing the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.181/1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#UU00500"><p>Amendment put:</p><p>The Committee divided: Tá, 9; Níl, 20.</p><br/><br/><p>Tellers: Tá, Senators Michael McDowell and Gerard P. Craughwell; Níl, Senators Seán Kyne and Lisa Chambers..</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.181/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2022-10-18" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#UU00500">
            <divisioncount ayes="9" noes="20" abstain="0" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" vote="aye">Victor Boyhan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" vote="aye">Lynn Boylan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1645" vote="aye">Gerard Craughwell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" vote="aye">Paul Gavan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" vote="aye">Alice-Mary Higgins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" vote="aye">Sharon Keogan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1669" vote="aye">Michael McDowell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1688" vote="aye">Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" vote="aye">Mark Wall</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1629" vote="no">Garret Ahearn</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1633" vote="no">Niall Blaney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" vote="no">Jerry Buttimer</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1640" vote="no">Pat Casey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1641" vote="no">Shane Cassells</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" vote="no">Lisa Chambers</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" vote="no">Martin Conway</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1646" vote="no">Ollie Crowe</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1647" vote="no">John Cummins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1652" vote="no">Aidan Davitt</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1656" vote="no">Mary Fitzpatrick</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" vote="no">Gerry Horkan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1665" vote="no">Se&aacute;n Kyne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1666" vote="no">Tim Lombard</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" vote="no">Eugene Murphy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" vote="no">Fiona O'Loughlin</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" vote="no">Joe O'Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1693" vote="no">Pauline O'Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" vote="no">Barry Ward</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1687" vote="no">Diarmuid Wilson</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="abstain">
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.181/3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#UU00500"><p>Amendment declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.182" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Section 2 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.183" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Sections 3 to 8, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.184" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>SECTION 9</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.185" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1669" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#VV00400"><p>I move amendment No. 3:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 10, line 27, to delete &ldquo;9 members&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;11 members&rdquo;.  </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.186/1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#VV00500"><p>Amendment put:</p><p>The Committee divided: Tá, 9; Níl, 19.</p><br/><br/><p>Tellers: Tá, Senators Michael McDowell and Gerard P. Craughwell; Níl, Senators Seán Kyne and Lisa Chambers..</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.186/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2022-10-18" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#VV00500">
            <divisioncount ayes="9" noes="19" abstain="0" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" vote="aye">Victor Boyhan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" vote="aye">Lynn Boylan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1645" vote="aye">Gerard Craughwell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" vote="aye">Paul Gavan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" vote="aye">Alice-Mary Higgins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" vote="aye">Sharon Keogan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1669" vote="aye">Michael McDowell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1688" vote="aye">Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" vote="aye">Mark Wall</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1629" vote="no">Garret Ahearn</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1633" vote="no">Niall Blaney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" vote="no">Jerry Buttimer</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1695" vote="no">Maria Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1640" vote="no">Pat Casey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1641" vote="no">Shane Cassells</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" vote="no">Lisa Chambers</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" vote="no">Martin Conway</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1646" vote="no">Ollie Crowe</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1652" vote="no">Aidan Davitt</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1656" vote="no">Mary Fitzpatrick</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" vote="no">Gerry Horkan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1665" vote="no">Se&aacute;n Kyne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1666" vote="no">Tim Lombard</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" vote="no">Eugene Murphy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" vote="no">Joe O'Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1693" vote="no">Pauline O'Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" vote="no">Barry Ward</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1687" vote="no">Diarmuid Wilson</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="abstain">
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.186/3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#VV00500"><p>Amendment declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.187" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#XX00100"><p>Amendments Nos. 4, 6 and 11 to 13, inclusive, are related and may be discussed together, by agreement.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#XX00200"><p>I move amendment No. 4:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 10, line 30, to delete &ldquo;2&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;3&rdquo;. </blockquote> <p>I will speak to the grouping because amendment No. 4 is consequential on the other amendments in this grouping.  The core of this grouping is amendment No. 6, which would delete the provision in the Bill as stands that the Attorney General would sit on the judicial appointments commission.  During the pre-legislative scrutiny of this legislation by the Committee on Justice, the committee heard from a number of key stakeholders including the Law Society of Ireland, the Irish Council for Civil Liberties and academic experts including Dr. Laura Cahillane, Dr. Tom Hickey and Dr. David Kenny, that the Attorney General should not be a member of the commission.  For example, the Law Society of Ireland's submission to the committee noted:</p> <blockquote> 	If the new Commission is to be genuinely independent in its functions, there is no reason for the Attorney General, who also sits at the Cabinet table, to participate. ... To the contrary, it becomes more difficult to defend the independence of the process if a significant player has a dual role both prior to, and post, the Commission&rsquo;s recommendation. </blockquote> <p>On the issue of the dual role, it was also clear that as the chief legal adviser to the Government, the Attorney General would be taking part in Cabinet deliberations on the nomination of judges.  If this is something new and we are creating this independent judicial appointments commission, we should not have a scenario whereby you have somebody involved who is appointed solely as part of the Government and who answers solely to the Government.  We must bear in mind that none of us can see the Attorney General&rsquo;s advice on anything as he or she is solely in a relationship with the Government in that regard.  It is not an independent public role but one solely serving the Government.  We cannot have a scenario where such a person would be allowed to sit on the commission and potentially have an important role, on the one side sitting on the commission and on the other side in the Government&rsquo;s final decision on judicial appointments.  It muddies the process and compromises its independence.</p><p>My amendment No. 4 is a consequential amendment which recognises that were we to remove the Attorney General from the commission, the number of spaces would need to increase.  I had two amendments, one of which was to increase the number of laypersons accordingly and another one, which was to increase the number of other appointments.  I understand that my amendment on laypersons was ruled out of order, which I was surprised by because I was told about the charges on laypersons and increasing the number of laypersons.  I am surprised and that points to a wider problem whereby incidental costs are stopping us from making good legislative proposals.  I have given two different ways whereby the removal of the Attorney General could be replaced.  Some of the proposals put forward by Senator McDowell and others could be other potential substitutions following the removal of the Attorney General.</p><p>The other set of amendments in this grouping includes amendments Nos. 11 to 13, inclusive, and they go into a little bit more detail.  Amendment No. 11 is consequential on amendment No. 6.  Having removed the Attorney General from the commission, there would no longer be a need for the Attorney General to be removed from the voting because the Attorney General would not be a member of the commission.  What are more substantial and relevant are amendments Nos. 12 and 13.  Even if the Minister does not accept my proposal to remove the Attorney General, which would be wise and appropriate, amendments Nos. 12 and 13 seek to at least provide a greater degree of clarity and care around what role the Attorney General could play in the functioning of the judicial commission.  Amendment No. 12 would add a new subsection to section 9, providing that &quot;The Attorney General shall not, as a member of the Commission, play a role in the selection or recommendation of persons for appointment to judicial office in the Supreme Court&rdquo;.  So there is a provision stating that the Attorney General may not vote on a votable measure but there is no provision whereby, for example, the Attorney General could not end up playing the key role in the recommendation, nomination or selection of persons.  The Attorney General could play a significant role right up to the point of the vote.  That is a concern, especially given that dual role the Attorney General will then play in the Government&rsquo;s final decisions.</p><p>My amendment would ensure the Attorney General would not have a role in the selection or recommendation process for domestic judicial offices.  It is a compromise on my previous amendments, which removed the Attorney General entirely but it reflects recommendation 8 of the Committee on Justice&rsquo;s pre-legislative scrutiny report on this Bill, which was to carefully revise the role of the Attorney General on the commission.  The revision we are proposing would enhance the independent decision-making and independent operation of the commission when it comes to filling vacancies in our domestic courts.  Again I note that in its submission to the committee, the Law Society of Ireland expressed a need for a greater independence.  In addition, Dr. Cahillane, Dr. Tom Hickey and Dr. David Kenny noted that having the Attorney General also sit on the judicial appointments commission gives this law officer an outsized influence on the process.  Those experts noted that it has been common in the past for Attorneys General to take up positions as judges in the superior court upon leaving office, again making it a little bit of a concern if they are intimately involved in the selection process for judges.</p><p>Amendment No. 13 is an alternative to amendment No. 12.  Amendment No. 12 effectively removes the Attorney General from the selection and nomination process completely.  Amendment No. 13 is a compromise to the compromise.  It would simply remove the Attorney General from the key &ldquo;role in the selection or recommendation of persons for appointment to judicial office in the Supreme Court, Court of Appeal or High Court&quot;.  These are particularly sensitive roles.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Alice-Mary Higgins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2480"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2480&amp;amp;pid=AliceMaryHiggins&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->These are the courts that need to effectively hold the Government to account at times.  These are crucial roles.  We have had situations in the past where there has been something of a migration from Attorneys General into those courts.  At an absolute minimum, we should be looking to remove any question of the Attorney General being involved in the search or selection process leading to the appointment of members of those three senior judicial bodies.  I will be happy to hear the Minister's response.  I have further examples.  This issue came through from multiple stakeholders who spoke to the Joint Committee on Justice.  I urge that this anomaly be addressed because it will start us off on the wrong footing in terms of the independence of this new body.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.190" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" speakername="Barry Ward" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#YY00200"><p>I find myself in a difficult position on this.  Although I fundamentally and wholeheartedly disagree with Senator Higgins, I find my name on one of the amendments she has tabled.  For her it is consequential but for me it is primary.  What my amendment, No. 11, seeks to do is remove the restriction in section 9(3) on the Attorney General having a vote on the commission.  I do not think we should be removing the Attorney General from activity by him or her in any future decisions relating to our judges.  I spent a lot of time earlier this evening talking about the importance of the involvement of the professions.  As the leader of the legal professions in Ireland, the Attorney General is absolutely an appropriate person to be involved in that.  The very academics to whom Senator Higgins referred were people I listened to carefully at the Joint Committee on Justice.  They are seeking to substantially, if not completely, neuter any political activity in the context of judicial appointments.  On the face of it that sounds like a good thing.  There should be no politics in the Judiciary.  I agree with that but there should be democracy.  I have made this point already.  There has to be a democratic element in the appointment of judges in this State because they are a branch of government.  In a common law jurisdiction, they are particularly important one because they form part of a coterie of people who actually make the law.  It is perhaps not in the same formalised way that the Legislature and the Executive do but they nonetheless interpret the documents that come from these Houses and apply them to the law and tell us what they actually mean.  They are an important branch of the Judiciary.  It is for that reason that, constitutionally, they are a branch of government.  It is for that reason that the Government, as the delegate of the people, is involved in appointing those persons.  The academics who were referred to seem to totally disagree with that notion.  They want to absolutely remove the autonomy of politicians and the Cabinet in making those decisions, notwithstanding the fact that, over generations, those decisions have actually proven to be sound.  The people who have made up our Judiciary have proved to be excellent lawyers who have followed the law rather than their own opinions or preconceptions.  They have applied the law in an even way, which has benefited this whole country.  We have benefited much more than our nearest neighbour, another common law jurisdiction, from a Judiciary that applies the law without fear or favour.  I am not saying it is perfect by any stretch or that it has always got it right but we do not see the same level of interpretation in a particular vein in this jurisdiction as there might be in the other common law jurisdictions on either side of this country or the bodies of water either side of it.</p> <p>What I am trying to do in amendment No. 11 is give the  Attorney General a greater role in the process to allow him or her to have a proper voting role.  The proposal is that the Attorney General be a member of the commission in any event.  It stands to reason to me that he or she would have a voting role in that.  Another later amendment of mine would deal with the issue that has been raised in relation to possible tied votes and things like that.  There is a myopia to the decision that the Attorney General should not be part of this because the Attorney General is accountable to the Government.  The Attorney General is also the law officer of the State.  The Attorney General is a professional lawyer.  The Attorney General has an insight into what is required of judicial office in a way that very few people on this commission, including the judges themselves, will have.  To my mind, it is right and proper that he or she should have a more involved role, not a lesser one.  That is why I am bringing forward amendment No. 11.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.191" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1669" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#YY00300"><p>I find myself in the same position as Senator Ward.  I find myself put down as a co-sponsor of an amendment that has been proposed for a very different reason by Senator Higgins.  I am very happy to co-operate with her in any sensible way but I want to put on the record that my signature to this amendment, and those of my fellow Independent Senators, is for the precise opposite reason to hers.  There is a number of things I want to say on all of this.  First, the Attorney General is a constitutional officer.  The Attorney General is not some political hack put in by the Government simply to do its bidding.  The Attorney General, on the contrary, is a constitutional officer who has functions under the Constitution, such as nominating counsel in Article 26 references.  Much more than that, the Attorney General is the adviser to the Government on issues such as the constitutionality of proposals that come before the Cabinet for scrutiny or legislation.  The Attorney General is the person who advises the Government as to whether proposals for legislation are compatible with the Constitution, with EU law or with obligations under the EU treaties.  Having held the office, I know this to be the case.  The Attorney General is the person who, on occasion, may be asked to vindicate the rights of individuals where they stand to be infringed, such as people who are being denied their rights.  The Attorney General has a function to vindicate the rights in present circumstances, to uphold the laws of the State and to take injunctions against people who are infringing the laws of the State or the provisions of the Constitution.  It is unfair to take the view that the Attorney General is a highly political person whose function is to do the political bidding of the Government.  It is quite the reverse.  Any person who has served in Cabinet will find that the Attorney General is the person who, more than anybody else at the Cabinet table, tells them what they cannot do rather than what they should do.  There is a misconceived notion that the Attorney General is somehow a political figure whose judgment in relation to the appointment of judges is somehow suspect.  It is the contrary.</p> <p>I will go back to the point I made at the very outset of this debate.  When I was Minister for Justice and Rory Brady was the Attorney General, a great many judicial appointments were made.  We knew at the time that the great majority of them were people who did not come from the same political stable as did either he or I.  The appointments were made on merit.  They were made, first because the people involved were vetted in the great majority of cases by the Judicial Appointments Advisory Board and found to be worthy of appointment, and second, because they struck us as people who would improve the quality of the Judiciary.  I make the point because there seems to be some notion, and I agree completely with Senator Ward on this, that the Government has no function in determining who becomes a judge.  Even this Bill, however it is read, will put before the Government three names.  Why allow the Government to select from those three names?  What is the logic of that?  If people were to be totally purist it should just be one name and the Government should not be given any choice, if the anti-political and anti-democratic viewpoint is correct.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Michael McDowell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=719"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=719&amp;amp;pid=MichaelMcDowellPD&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I believe that view is wholly incorrect and that the appointment of judges is, as Senator Ward said, a democratic function envisaged by the Constitution to be carried out by one of the organs of government, namely, the Government itself, through advising the President.  What is the logic of allowing the Government to choose from a shortlist of three?  If one thinks about it, why should it have any say at all?  Is it in a better position than the judicial appointments commission to vet people's suitability on grounds of merit?  This is where I have a fundamental problem with some of the provisions of this Bill.  <br/><br/>If you concede the proposition that the Government has a constitutional right and duty to make appointments to the Judiciary in accordance with its judgment of the matter - and, constitutionally, you must - even if the Government is restricted to a shortlist of three, the principle is conceded that it is the Government, <i>qua</i>Ministers nominated and appointed by the will of the people through the D&aacute;il, that decides which of the three people is to become Chief Justice or a member of whatever court the shortlist refers to.  If that is right, certain things flow from it.  One is that the Government is entitled to know which of the three people before it is best qualified and to take the advice of the Attorney General on that issue.  If the Attorney General is the legal adviser to the Government, he or she is entitled and duty-bound to express a view as to the suitability or unsuitability of any of the three people on the shortlist before the Government if that view is relevant to the appointment which may follow.  <br/><br/>There seems to be a complete schizophrenia on this matter.  People think that the Government should somehow not have a role in determining who becomes a judge and yet we are enacting a Bill that states that it must have a role, although it must also be confined to three names put before it by another body.  What Senator Ward said is 100% true.  This democratic function envisaged by our Constitution is being heavily curtailed.  Whether that curtailment is constitutional itself is a matter on which I have some views.  It may be that the Attorney General now believes that the requirements of European law and our adherence to European law standards entitles the Legislature to confine the right of the Government to the appointment of persons recommended to it rather than to make appointments at large.  <br/><br/>I will now come back to my point about the function of the Attorney General.  If he or she is going to be on this commission at all, we cannot have the Attorney General sitting there like a eunuch in a harem, not allowed to say or do anything but just observing what is going on in the commission like some kind of constitutional voyeur.  It makes no sense to have a member of a commission, especially a small commission of reduced size, sitting there and watching what everybody else is doing while not participating in any shape or form in the discussion, in the debate or in the decision made by that commission.  It is interesting to note that the Minister's Bill allows the Attorney General to propose people for inclusion on the shortlist at the judicial appointments commission and to oppose people proposed by others.  He or she is entitled to do all of that but, under the Minister's text, he or she is not entitled to vote on the issue.  He or she is entitled to influence the debate and say whatever he or she thinks about the candidates.  The Attorney General is entitled to suggest that one candidate is better than another but, having made that contribution, is not entitled to be part of the decision should the matter come to a vote.  Where there is no vote, under the Minister's version of the Bill, the Attorney General is a full participant in the process.  If the commission is operating on consensus, the Attorney General is as entitled as any other member of the commission to play a full part in the deliberative process and, it must be presumed, in interviewing and setting out rules or procedures.<br/><br/>Where I come from on this question - and this is why it is ironic that Senator Ward and I find our names appended to an amendment put down by Senator Higgins for an entirely different purpose - is that the Attorney General is a very suitable person to participate in the activities of the commission, especially because, once the shortlist gets to Cabinet, he or she is perfectly entitled to strongly support a given candidate over others and to tell the Cabinet that, in his or her view, those other candidates are simply not suitable.  The Attorney General is perfectly entitled to do that.  If he or she is entitled to do that when the decision arrives at Cabinet, I see no reason for it to be somehow wrong for him or her to participate in the process leading up to that point.<br/><br/>I will make another point.  This is something that some of the critics who have committed themselves to paper, including the academics Senator Higgins mentioned, seem to have missed.  If the names of three different people come before the Cabinet for appointment to the Supreme Court, it is not some kind of chemical or mathematical formula that is used to decide which of them the Cabinet should put on the Supreme Court.  If the Cabinet wants a liberal Supreme Court, it will go for the person who appears most liberal.  If it wants a more diverse Supreme Court, it will look at the three candidates by reference to diversity in making its decision.  If the Cabinet wants a more conservative Supreme Court, it may appoint the person who appears the most conservative of the three people on the list.  There seems to be a notion that the Cabinet is somehow apolitical - I use that word in the democratic rather than the party political sense - in deciding that it wants another woman, a liberal woman or a conservative man on the Supreme Court or that the balance of the court requires a certain type of appointee but that is an entirely political decision being made by the people the Constitution entrusts with it.  Even if the Government has a shortlist to work from as a result of this legislation, the decision remains profoundly democratic, political and accountable.  The Government will choose which of the three persons is appointed to the Supreme Court.  <br/><br/>Who is appointed to the Supreme Court matters.  We do not need the wild American kind of political Supreme Court constituted along ideological lines for this to be the case.  Ideology with a small &quot;i&quot; and things like liberalism, conservatism and so on are entirely reasonable bases on which to choose between recommended candidates, especially when they come without any stated order of preference from the judicial appointments commission.  There is another point that has to be made about the role of the Attorney General.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Michael McDowell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=719"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=719&amp;amp;pid=MichaelMcDowellPD&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Supposing that after five years, the Judicial Council is found to have constantly come up with one type of person rather than another.  Suppose Senator Ward was a candidate and was constantly refused inclusion on the list going to the Government from the Judicial Council.  Is it wrong that the Cabinet knows that this is happening?  Is it wrong for members of the Cabinet to scratch their heads and say, "How come he's never on the preferred list?  People come and go on the preferred list but he's never there.  The four judicial people on the council seem to be vetoing that man for appointment to any of the superior courts or any court position."  Is it right that the Government should know this is happening?  Of course it is right.  That is a point about this legislation.  It is important that the Government should know who all the applicants were because it can then say, "Isn't it strange that Joe Bloggs or Josephine Bloggs never gets nominated by the judiciary.  Have they a downer on him or her?"  </p><p>I notice the Bill says that the commission can decide its own procedures but of the nine members of the Judicial Council, is there any right for three or four of them to insist that somebody's name at least gets to the Cabinet if five people say "No"?  Is there something akin to proportional representation?  Is there any right for a number of the members of this council to say, "We keep getting an application from Joe Bloggs or Josephine Bloggs.  We think that person is suitable and a yet a majority on this commission keep saying "No" to that person."  Is there no right for their nominee or the person they favour ever to be considered by Government just because they are in a minority?  I wonder about the correctness of it.  The Bill does not actually say that the composition of the list shall be determined by a majority vote in respect of each person.  Is it permitted for the commission to accord to a minority the right to select at least one person in three if there is a division of opinion regarding which people are suitable to go to Government or must everything be decided by a majority so that there are separate votes on candidates A, B and C?  </p><p>Section 51 states that in advising the President regarding the appointment of a person to judicial office in the State, the Government shall only consider for appointment those persons who have been recommended by the commission to the Minister under section 47.  If a person has been recommended three times and is not on the fourth shortlist, which comes before the Government in respect of a particular vacancy, is the Government by reference to what is in section 51(1) entitled to say that this person has been nominated before and it is surprised to see that person is now off the list and that other people are being put on instead?  Strictly speaking, that person is somebody whose name has been recommended by the commission in the past though not on this occasion.  If that is what the Bill is supposed to say, it should say so.  At the moment, it just seems to say that the Government can appoint any person whose name has been recommended, not is being recommended, for the particular vacancy.  I would like the Minister to clarify this question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.194" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#AAA00200"><p>Returning to my amendments, which relate to the Attorney General, if amendment No. 6 is not successful, I will not move amendment No. 11 so you will have it all to yourselves.  I will certainly be opposing it if amendment No. 6 is not successful.  The statements here have made the case for my amendments.  I have not opposed the political stage of the process.  My amendments do not seek to remove that discretion of the Cabinet between the three persons.  As has been described, it is very likely that there will be multiple considerations applied in the Cabinet selection process, some of which may involve eyes with whatever size of eye attached to it in terms of ideology.  This is why we are meant to be putting in place a process that has an independent stage previously and then a stage where the Cabinet looks and chooses which person it prefers from those deemed to be appropriate.</p> <p>The problem is that the Attorney General is in both parts of the process.  The Attorney General will be giving advice in respect of the deliberations of Cabinet between the three candidates put forward to it.  As a result, it is inappropriate for the Attorney General to also be in a position to propose or oppose those in the other independent part of the process.  There is a blurring of the lines between two processes where one is meant to feed into the other and the Attorney General is placed inside both of them.  It is a concern.</p> <p>We mentioned how candidates A, B and C might go forward and the Attorney General might say candidate B or C is a problem.  None of us will be privy to that information because the Attorney General's relationship when it comes to giving advice to the Cabinet is bound by Cabinet confidentiality.  There is a problem for all those engaging in the judicial appointments commission when one of its members says whatever.  It is fine for the Attorney General to give confidential advice to the Government but it is a concern if people come out of one process and give unknown input onwards.  There is almost a dual recommendation system where we will have the official three recommendations and then whatever the Attorney General says.  I am not saying the Attorney General should not have a role but his or her role rightly belongs around the Cabinet table giving input at that point.  To have the Attorney General in two different parts of the process is a problem and I am more convinced of that from today than ever before.</p> <p>I urge the Minister to consider moving the Attorney General from this part in the process.  If the Attorney General is to be there, and I agree it is frustrating to be solely in what is effectively an auditing role, I believe he or she must be in such an auditing role.  If the Attorney General was to have such an auditing role, an actual active role for people who could vote and do all the other parts of the process could be created even within the limitations of the nine members.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.195" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1502" speakername="Helen McEntee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#AAA00300"><p>I thank Senators for their amendments.  Amendment No. 4 very much relates to whether or not amendment No. 6 is passed and is to balance out the number.  I appreciate that.  I reiterate what many colleagues have outlined.  The Attorney General is a constitutional officeholder.  He or she is not there to represent the Government.  He or she is not on the commission to represent the Government.  He or she is independent of the Government.  That needs to be very clear.  The independence has been consistently recognised in decisions of the Irish courts.  The Attorney General also has a role in upholding the Constitution, including a duty to ensure the independence of the Judiciary.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.196" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Progress report: Committee to sit again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#AAA00500"><p>When is it proposed to sit again?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.198" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" speakername="Barry Ward" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101800002#AAA00600"><p>At 10.30 a.m. tomorrow.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-18a.199" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar athl&oacute; ar 8.30 p.m. go dt&iacute; 10.30 a.m., D&eacute; C&eacute;adaoin, 19 Deireadh F&oacute;mhair 2022.</p><p>The Seanad adjourned at 8.30 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Wednesday, 19 October 2022.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>