<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.2" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Leas-Chathaoirleach i gceannas ar 14:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.4" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.5" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#B00100"><p>I have received notice from Senator James Reilly that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Education and Skills to provide an update on the proposed new school facilities at Lusk Community College given that the construction works were due to commence in summer 2017. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Maura Hopkins of the following matter: </p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to provide and update on the provision of resources for home help and home care packages in County Roscommon; and the need for the further provision of funding for these services. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator John O'Mahony of the following matter: </p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to address the reason for the continued delay in restoring the motorised transport grant. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Victor Boyhan of the following matter:  </p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs to make a statement on the latest figures from Tusla which show that there are currently 25,387 cases of children with welfare or child protection concerns who have qualified for a social worker, but 5,720 of them are yet to be assigned a social worker.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Maria Byrne of the following matter: </p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to extend blood testing facilities to general practitioners on a Monday to Friday basis at University Hospital Limerick. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Tim Lombard of the following matter: </p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport to develop a strategy for increasing funding and recognition for, and participation in, women&rsquo;s sport. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Robbie Gallagher of the following matter: </p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Housing, Planning, Community and Local Government to outline when the terms and conditions for councillors will be improved and if he intends to address the current situation where city councillors receive less remuneration than their county counterparts.  </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Mark Daly of the following matter: </p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Housing, Planning, Community and Local Government to provide an update on the terms and conditions of local authority members.</blockquote> <p>I regard the matters raised by Senators Reilly, Hopkins, O&rsquo;Mahony, Boyhan, Byrne and Lombard as suitable for discussion.  I have selected the matters raised by Senators Reilly, Hopkins, O&rsquo;Mahony and Boyhan and they will be taken now.  I regret I have had to rule out of order the matters raised by Senators Gallagher and Daly on the grounds that they are a repeat of similar Commencement matters raised on 12 April 2017.  Senators Byrne and Lombard may give notice on another day of the matters they wish to raise.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.7" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#B00150">Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.8" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#B00175">Schools Building Projects</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#B00200"><p>I welcome the Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy Richard Bruton, to the House and indeed congratulate him on his re-appointment.  I thank him for taking the time to address this matter, which is of grave concern to the students, parents, teachers and the wider community of Lusk.  The population of Lusk was approximately 500 to 700 when I first started in practice back in 1983.  It was 7,000 in 2011, it is now 10,000 according to the last census of 2016, and it is due to grow further to 12,500 in the coming years.</p> <p>There are, as the Minister knows, active building sites all around Lusk.  Some of them involve the provision of new school and educational facilities and they are very welcome.  We have very good bus and rail links and we are very near Dublin city, Dublin Airport and Swords.  Lusk is an attractive place in which to live and start a home and a young family.  The demand, therefore, for all school facilities in Lusk will continue to grow.  Rush and Lusk Educate Together national school currently has 420 pupils.  Lusk national school has 850 pupils on its books and is growing.  The Round Towers GAA club has 600 members.  The soccer club, with 19 teams, has 325 playing members and rising.  We also have our athletics club, judo club, and many other clubs.</p> <p>As a Fine Gael Senator and local Lusk GP I am very proud to see three cranes on the skyline of Lusk building new primary schools and a new all-purpose PE hall, supported and implemented efficiently by the Minister's Department.  It surprises me and many others, therefore, that the same project group cannot seem to implement in a timely manner the building of the promised new facilities for Lusk Community College.  This involves a new build extension to cater for: an additional 650 pupils; a special needs unit; a physical education unit; a hall with a fitness suite and changing facilities; and ancillary accommodation, including a school library.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator James Reilly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2180"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2180&amp;amp;pid=DrJamesReilly&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->There have been multiple promises of start dates, tenders, etc.  I was delighted, as a Minister, when construction of phase 1 commenced in 2011 and completed on time in 2013, with phase 2 due to complete in 2014.  Everybody is surprised to learn that planning was not obtained until 2016.  We were given to understand that tenders would be awarded and construction would commence this summer but clearly that is not now going to happen because the tenders are not due in until July this year.  <br/><br/>The community is frustrated and annoyed.  People are losing faith.  I know from the meeting last Tuesday night, which was well attended, that several parents of children currently attending the school are considering sending younger children elsewhere because of the overcrowding, where children are required to eat lunch in their classrooms and the hall, which should be used for other functions, is now being used for teaching.  The parents cannot understand why this project is not proceeding.<br/><br/>I understand that the Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy Bruton, has been in communication with my office regarding a meeting I requested with him and his officials on behalf of the parents' group at Lusk Community College.  I would like the Minister to confirm today that he will meet with the parents' group from Lusk Community College so that they can explain their case directly to him and his officials.<br/><br/>Naturally, everybody is anxious to move this project forward and parents do not want any more delays.  The Minister will understand that many children commenced their education in this school in the belief that they would be able to complete their education there but because the school will not now be completed until, at the earliest, 2019 this may not be the case for many children.  There is a very strong community and committee involved, including Mr. Gabriel Kelly, Ms Caroline O'Malley, Mr. Josephine Lara, Mr. Michael Lenihan, Mr. Paul McNally and Ms Tricia Lynch.  <br/><br/>I would like to read into the record an email I received from a parent, Mr. Liam Cassidy, in Lusk:</p><blockquote>Following a meeting with local political representatives on Tuesday the 13th, I am writing to you to express my personal disappointment regarding the further delays in the completion of Lusk Community College.  We have now been given a best case completion date of the end of 2019.  To say that this is appalling is an understatement.  In its current state, the school is not fit for purpose and is already overcrowded, without even having the fully secondary cycle of children in attendance yet.  Imagine there is no PE hall, no library, no designated lunch areas.  Students are being facilitated in portacabins as there are not enough classrooms.  That might be okay when you were six or seven in primary school but not for growing teenage girls and boys.  Wouldn't fancy it, would you?</blockquote><p>As the Leas-Chathaoirleach is indicating that my time has expired, I will not read the remainder of the email.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#C00200"><p>The area about which the Senator is speaking is beautiful countryside.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#C00300"><p>I ask the Minister to do everything he can to remedy this situation given the impact it is having on the community.  This school was once a start-of-the-art facility with a great reputation but people are now starting to walk away from it.  This is the last thing we need when North County Dublin is bursting at the seams in terms of the number of children applying for school places from areas such as Rush, Lusk, Skerries, Balbriggan and Swords.  As a resident of Lusk, we do not want to have to send our secondary school children outside of their village, away from their friends and community, to complete their secondary school education.  This is having a detrimental effect on the community, families and local clubs which are critical to any community.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#C00400"><p>I thank Senator Reilly for raising this matter, which is about the second phase of accommodation for Lusk.  As stated by Senator Reilly, the first phase was completed some years ago.  This project will provide permanent accommodation to cater for the full projected enrolment of 1,000 pupils, including a special needs unit, a sports hall with a fitness suite and changing facilities and ancillary accommodation, and a school library.</p> <p>The project is included in the six-year programme announced by my predecessor on 17 November 2015 to go to tender, with construction scheduled to commence in 2018.  Notwithstanding that scheduled construction date, my Department approved the project to proceed to tender stage in October 2016, with the intention of completing the much-needed phase 2 accommodation as early as possible.  The pre-qualification of contractors for this project had first been conducted by the design team in April 2015.  Owing to the passage of time since then, the design team was concerned about the possibility of legal challenges at tender stage and sought advice from the Office of Government Procurement on the matter.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Richard Bruton:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=119"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=119&amp;amp;pid=RichardBruton&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The advice was that it would be prudent to run the pre-qualification process again.  My Department concurred with this advice and requested the design team to conduct a second pre-qualification process.</p><p>The Senator is correct in pointing out that I informed the D&aacute;il on 18 January that "Subject to no issues arising, it is anticipated that construction will commence in the summer of 2017 and the project is scheduled to take approximately 18 months to complete."  That was, however, based on the advice of my officials at the time and was, in turn, based on the information available on that date.  Issues did subsequently arise in the pre-qualification process but these have now been resolved.  I am pleased to inform the Senator that the pre-qualification process was concluded earlier this month and invitations to tender issued to six qualified contractors on 9 June 2017.  Subject to no further issues arising, it is anticipated that construction will commence in late 2017 and the project is, as previously advised, expected to take approximately 18 months to complete.</p><p>I can fully understand the frustration of parents but I am aware, from experience, that if prudent steps are not taken to ensure the supply chain is properly tested before one commits, then projects can go off the rails.  The prudence of the design team in taking these steps has prevented this project from being challenged further down the road.  A prudent approach was taken and I understand the frustration people experience when they see the potential opening date being pushed back as a result of this approach.  However, we must work on the best legal advice available to us.  If the Office of Government Procurement is indicating that this is the approach to take, then it is the correct approach.</p><p>I am open, of course, to meeting the Senator.  Other public representatives, including Deputy Farrell, have contacted me about the possibility of meeting.  If Deputies and Senators want such a meeting, I am happy to agree to that.  The project still must go through the process and tenders are now being invited.  I will not be influencing the selection of tenders or any of that.  It must be done in a wholly professional way by the Department.  I am content that although there was an interruption, which was unfortunate to the progress of the project from when we first sought to move it faster, I believe this difficulty has been overcome and that the project is back on track from our point of view.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#D00200"><p>It is my understanding that the website of the Department of Education and Skills originally said the project was to finish - or at least commence - in 2014.  I stand open to correction on that.  It is important that the Minister meets the parents of the children in the school.  It is more important than meeting all of us public representatives, although we would all be very keen to be there also.  There was a number of public representatives at the meeting last Tuesday night.  We all undertook to write to the Minister to again seek a meeting.  I appreciate his response to this request and the positive way in which he has stated it.  It is critical that there are no further delays.  Everybody accepts that we are where we are.  People would like an explanation as to why we are where we are and I believe they do not feel they have had that explanation yet.</p><p>I shall conclude by reading the two last paragraphs of the letter I read out earlier:</p><blockquote>As a parent of four young children, two already in primary cycle, I now have the worry of whether the school will be able to take my children in when their time comes or will I have to send them to a different school outside of our community.  It would be a crying shame if I had to do that.<br /><br />Our secondary school must be finished as soon as possible.  It is already nearly three years late being competed.  I understand why projects like this might run to some delay but at this stage there are no words for a delay of this length.</blockquote> <p>The end of 2019 is just not good enough but we understand that we are where we are.  I again appeal to the Minister to ensure that there will be no further delays.  The parents would appreciate an fact-to-face meeting with the Minister to allay their fears that there will not be further delays and that further damage to the school's reputation will not occur.  There is an excellent ethos in the school.  It has excellent teachers - many of whom I met the other night - who are really committed to the school and excited by the possibility of this new growing community that has sprung out of a very ancient village that has been in existence since the fifth century.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#E00100"><p>I will check the history of this.  I can only go back to November 2015 when this was announced as being on a building programme.  The Department has moved that ahead of the schedule that was then set out.</p> <p>No Senator knows better than Senator Reilly the difficulties we went through between 2010 and 2014 which was the planning date initially hoped for.  No doubt one of the reasons for the delay had to do with the economic crisis that prevailed in those times when schedules were disrupted.  I will check that history.  It is on a clear schedule.  Not only does the Department treat it as a priority, but by its action in bringing it forward ahead of its original schedule, it shows an appreciation of the difficulties for the school and for parents.</p> <p>Of course I am happy to meet and reassure parents but I am also sure the Department will facilitate the school in temporary accommodation should that be necessary given the pressure on the school in the short term.  I will do my very best to keep this on track but I do not directly control difficulties with tenders and construction.  They arise from sources I cannot always identify in advance.  I thank the Senator for raising the issue.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.17" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#E00200">Home Care Packages Provision</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1415" speakername="Maura Hopkins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#E00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State for coming to the House today.  I want to raise the need for increased supports for home care packages and home help supports in County Roscommon, which has one of the oldest populations in the country and one of the most rural.  We need to target areas with the greatest need and ensure adequate home care services are being provided to individuals who need them.  I am concerned.  I have received several calls from families regarding the provision of adequate home care support for their relatives.  I can point to several specific cases where, despite strong recommendations from health care professionals outlining a clear need for increased care at home, this has not been provided.  It is not good enough that the specific needs of individuals in respect of personal care, domestic tasks and other daily activities are not being met.  It is also particularly difficult to get weekend cover.  I have raised these issues numerous times with the Health Service Executive, HSE.</p> <p>I have also received calls from home helps and relatives about the length of visits.  Some have told me that visits have been reduced from 45 to 30 minutes.  It is impractical for many to help an individual get up, get dressed, have breakfast and be prepared for the day in 30 minutes.  It is extremely important that we support people to remain in their homes, but that requires proper home care packages and an adequate number of home help hours.</p> <p>Our focus needs to be on the individual receiving the care.  It is a question of delivering good quality care for the client, of the client&rsquo;s welfare and of supporting families and family carers to look after their loved ones at home.  Home care services are critical to allowing people stay in their own homes and communities for the longest time possible and to preventing early admission to long-term residential care.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Maura Hopkins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2478"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2478&amp;amp;pid=MauraHopkins&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I also want to point out concerns and difficulties that have been raised with me about not-for-profit home care providers.  If someone is receiving home help form a non-profit provider which is funded by the HSE but it is not currently possibly to get an additional number of hours privately from the same provider.  </p><p>The importance of the client-carer relationship cannot be underestimated.  These people are some of the most vulnerable within our society.  A new person coming into their home for the provision of home help or care can be a cause of unease and anxiety for many people.  When that relationship is built up, the value of it should not be underestimated.  It should be recognised and there should be a consistency in terms of care provision.  The arrangement with the non-profit organisations is a business one, with payment being made following the provision of home help hours.  There is a need to review the funding model with regard to the non-profit sector in order to allow for more flexibility in terms of care provision.  </p><p>I understand that work is under way on the consultation period for the development of a statutory home care scheme which would very much be focused and tailored towards meeting the needs of the individual. </p><p>I have plenty of experience in this sector, having worked as an occupational therapist and having seen the value of home care being provided.  I have also seen the challenges when not enough home care is provided.  That is why I am raising it today.  I have genuine, serious concerns about the adequacy of home care provision within County Roscommon.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#F00200"><p>I thank Senator Hopkins for raising this very important issue.  I know that she has a long held interest in the issue of services for home help and home care packages.</p> <p>The overarching policy of the Government is to support older people to live in dignity and independence in their own homes and communities for as long as possible.  Home care is an increasingly important part of the supports that we offer to older people, and will continue to increase in importance in the future.  The HSE has operational responsibility for planning, managing and delivering home and other community-based services for older people.  Service is provided on the basis of assessed health care need and there is currently no means testing.  </p> <p>The overall funding for services for older people in 2017 is &euro;765 million.  This included approximately &euro;373 million for the direct provision of home care and the HSE's national service plan provides for a target of 10.7 million home help hours, 16,750 home care packages and 190 intensive home care packages for clients with very complex needs.  </p> <p>All applicants for home care in the community health care organisation two, CHO 2, which includes Roscommon, Galway and Mayo, are assessed by a home care forum with clinical and social care professional representation.  Home care is allocated to those determined to be of the highest priority, having regard to the available budget.  With a budget of &euro;39.5 million, the HSE is providing a significant level of services for the area, and the projected monthly target is 1,254 people to receive a home care package, and that approximately 1.3 million home help hours will be provided by the end of the year.  By the end of April the HSE was providing 1,600 packages and 436,000 home help hours.  I am pleased to say that all new applicants on the waiting list across CHO 2 as of 31 March 2017 have 2.25 hours of home care per week approved for implementation.  The HSE has acknowledged that there are pockets - I accept Senator Hopkins's point - including the Monksland area of Roscommon, where a shortage of carers has impacted the implementation of approved care.  The Senator will be aware that arrangements for home care have developed over the years with a significant local focus, and there is considerable variation in accessing services in different parts of the country.  It is also accepted that there is a considerable demand for home support services over and above the existing service levels.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Finian McGrath:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1822"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1822&amp;amp;pid=FinianMcGrath&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The Department of Health is engaged in a detailed process to determine what type of home care scheme is best for Ireland.  This process will consider the future design of both the funding and regulation systems for these crucial services.  An important step in this process is public consultation which I will be launching shortly.  The purpose of the consultation is to allow all those who have views on this topic to have their say, including older people themselves, their families, and health care workers.  The Department wants to find out what people think about current home care services and would also like to hear the public's view on what the future scheme should look like.  I strongly urge all Senators, especially those in the Seanad with an interest in home care services, to make a submission to the consultation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1415" speakername="Maura Hopkins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#G00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his update on services within the community health care organisation, CHO, area 2, which covers Roscommon, Galway and Mayo.  However, I am still concerned about situations where health care professionals made recommendations on assessed need for personal care, domestic tasks and activities of daily life.  I can provide specific examples to the Minister of State in that regard.  The Government has continued to emphasise the importance of home care support to ensure people with disabilities and older people who need a little bit of extra support can live in their own homes and communities for the longest time possible.  The Minister of State outlined that access to services varies across the country.  I am concerned about that because no matter where one lives, one's financial situation, age or level of disability one should receive the same service based on an assessment of need.  I accept that the consultation process on the development of a statutory home care scheme is important in terms of trying to deal with those variations.</p><p>I have significant concerns about a number of cases where individuals have contacted me and I will provide details in regard to those cases to the Minister.  I have been in contact with the HSE on numerous occasions about them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#G00300"><p>I thank Senator Hopkins.  I will respond to the points she raised.  First, I will bring to the attention of the Minister, Deputy Harris, the point about non-profit providers to see if there is anything we can do about the hours.  I accept the point the Senator made about the importance of the client and the care relationship.  There must be stability and flow in such a relationship.  That is my experience as well, particularly in the disability sector.  If one chops and changes hours and carers that leads to instability, especially for older people and those with disabilities.  That is a very important point.</p><p>I urge people to get involved in the consultation process which is currently taking place.  Senator Hopkins also made points about other important issues such as the assessed need of people.  We need to ensure that if people are assessed and certain hours are recommended that they get them.  I am aware of problems with staffing in certain parts of the country but that is a management and human resources issue which we will have to deal with as well.  If there is anything we can do in terms of supporting those who are affected in the cases to which the Senator referred then it will be done.  If there are examples of significant stress experienced by families, especially involving senior citizens, we will do our best to see if we can plug the gaps.  I agree that it is not acceptable for either an individual in need of care or a carer for a person to be allocated 30 minutes or one hour and 40 minutes.  I will take the points that have been made and bring them to the attention of the Minister for Health, Deputy Harris.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.24" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#G00400">Motorised Transport Grant Closure</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#G00500"><p>I congratulate the Minister of State, Deputy Finian McGrath, on his reappointment.  The Minister of State might feel I am back to haunt him again.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator John O'Mahony:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2202"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2202&amp;amp;pid=JohnOMahony&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I suppose that is the case, but I want to raise an issue I have raised in a Commencement debate twice previously.  It relates to the motorised transport grant, which was removed in 2013 and has not been replaced.  I raised the matter with the Minister of State in September 2016 and February 2017.  It is now June 2017.  Each time I raised it, the Minister of State gave an undertaking that legislation on a new motorised transport grant was imminent.</p><p>I will highlight one particular case as an example of a number of cases I am dealing with, as I am sure are other Senators and Deputies.  I recall the issue being raised in the D&aacute;il on numerous occasions in recent months also.  It is the case of a wife looking after her husband 24 hours a day who is saving the State hundreds of thousands of euro, first in the sense that they did not make a claim against the hospital where the initial treatment was given, and, second, by caring for him in the family home.  Effectively, they have had to beg, steal and borrow, in the best sense, to continue to do that.  They got the motorised transport grant to buy a second-hand car on two or three occasions - this happened in 1995 - with a few thousand euro and they got the rest from credit unions.  That is what I am talking about - a woman taking her husband to hospital appointments and giving him a break out of the house to provide stimulation because he will only allow her to look after him.  It is a human case, and I am conscious of that.  I will not delay the House on the matter but the last time I raised it was in February and the Minister of State said at that time that legislation was imminent.  I am not holding my breath, but I implore the Minister of State to advance this in whatever way he can.  We talk about value for money but this family is saving money for the State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#H00200"><p>I thank Senator John O'Mahony for raising this very important issue.  I accept he has been campaigning on it and asking me about it for a long time.  I share his frustration about this issue.  It is important to outline again the current position in this matter.  There are blockages that we are trying to deal with but as the Senator will be aware already, the Government decided to close both the motorised transport grant and the mobility allowance schemes in February 2013.  This decision arose as a result of the reports of the Ombudsman regarding the legal status of both schemes.  I believe it is important to clarify that there are no plans to restore either of these schemes as they previously operated. However, the Government is aware of the continuing needs of people with a disability who rely on individual payments which support choice and independence.</p> <p>In that regard, it is important to know that monthly payments of up to &euro;208.50 have continued to be made by the Health Service Executive to 4,700 people who were in receipt of the mobility allowance.  The Government then decided that the detailed preparatory work required for a new transport support scheme and associated statutory provisions should be progressed by the Department of Health.  The Senator will be aware that A Programme for a Partnership Government acknowledges the ongoing drafting of primary legislation for a new transport support scheme.  The Government's legislative programme for 2017 includes the Health (Transport Support) Bill.  Both the Minister, Deputy Harris, and I are committed to its progression as soon as possible.  I can confirm that work on the policy proposals is at an advanced stage and I anticipate that this will be brought to Government shortly.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Finian McGrath:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1822"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1822&amp;amp;pid=FinianMcGrath&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The proposals will seek to ensure that there is a firm statutory basis for the scheme's operation, that there is transparency and equity in the eligibility criteria attaching to the scheme, that resources are targeted at those with the greatest needs and that the scheme is capable of being costed and affordable when introduced on an ongoing basis.  The Department is seeking a solution which best meets the aim of supporting people with severe disabilities who require additional income to contribute towards the cost of their mobility needs while keeping within the available budget and satisfying all legal and equality concerns.  The challenge for us all is to develop a new scheme on a statutory basis within a limited budget which is targeted at those with the greatest need.  I assure the Senator that the matter will be brought to the Government for consideration and a decision as soon as possible.  I look forward to a valuable and constructive debate when the Bill comes before the House in due course.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#J00200"><p>I accept what the Minister of State says but I know him long enough to see that there is some obstacle here which is not him.  I have seen in the D&aacute;il over the years how he has highlighted from the Opposition benches the need for people to be treated equally.  He said it will not be the old scheme, but when it comes in it must be equal.  The response to the example I gave him might be "Well, use public transport", but there is no public transport where these people live.  As such, this needs to be looked at carefully.  Whatever or whoever is the obstacle, I would love to bring the people whose example I have highlighted to the Minister of State or whoever is stopping him from getting this, because it is not about costing money but about saving it.  It is also about saving people's lives and caring for them in their own homes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#J00300"><p>I thank Senator O'Mahony again for raising this very important issue.  The particular case to which he referred is a very difficult one.  I wonder if that family is getting the &euro;208 mobility allowance currently.   Many families in rural Ireland are getting it in the meantime and as the legislation is being progressed.  Senator O'Mahony's point about value for money and not only saving money is an argument I am making very strongly myself.  The honest and direct answer to him is that there are some obstacles in there.  We have the legislation ready to roll and as recently as last week there has been communication between the Department of Health and the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform.  We hope to have some movement as soon as possible.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.31" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#J00400">Child Care Services Provision</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#J00500"><p>In the absence of time and because we have spent 45 minutes on three items, I will be brief and to the point.  I welcome the Minister of State to the House and congratulate him on his reappointment.  I am delighted for him.  He does an amazing job.  Despite all our challenges and talk on Commencement Matters, it is clearly a very difficult time and resources are a key factor in many of the responses the Minister of State has to give us.  We respect that as people who work in here.  We understand.</p> <p>To get to the point, we know from the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs, Deputy Katherine Zappone, that there are more than 5,000 people who have been approved for and should have a social worker.  They fall into the two categories of children at risk and children who are vulnerable.  This is a designated social worker as per best practice and Government policy, which is to say the policy of the Department of Children and Youth Affairs.  When the Minister was here recently, she told us there were 25,387 cases of children with welfare or child protection concerns of whom her Department was aware.  She also said there was a shortfall in need of over 5,000 in relation to social workers.  What is the latest update on that?  With the indulgence of the Leas-Chathaoirleach, I might take a moment in a supplementary to follow up on the response.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#J00600"><p>I thank the Senator.  The Government has made the reform of services to vulnerable children and families a very high priority.  Children about whom there are child protection concerns or who are awaiting the allocation of a dedicated social worker have their situations monitored by a social work duty intake team.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Finian McGrath:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1822"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1822&amp;amp;pid=FinianMcGrath&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Children about whom there is a child protection concern, but who are awaiting the allocation of a dedicated social worker, have their situation monitored by the social work duty intake team.  The monitoring may involve a visit to the child, telephone contact with, for instance, the school or preschool or other relevant information.  New information about possible risk increasing or decreasing to the child will inform the timeframe of the child being allocated his or her own named social worker.</p><p>All urgent and emergency cases notified to Tusla are dealt with immediately.  Urgent and emergency cases could involve cases of abandonment, allegations of physical and sexual abuse, parental ill health and the need to find an immediate placement, or threat to the safety or life of a child by a third party.</p><p>The number of referrals to the child welfare and protection services provided by Tusla continues to rise.  At the end of 2016, Tusla reported a total of 47,399 referrals for the year.  Up to 60% of these were child welfare concerns, which were up 12% on 2015.  The remaining 40% were child protection concerns, 5% up on 2015.  As the Senator correctly pointed out, there are delays in allocating social workers to some children who are the subject of child protection or welfare concerns.  It should be noted that cases waiting to be allocated to a social worker include new referrals, as well as children known to Tusla whose social worker is no longer available to them.  This could be due to a resignation, a career break or a retirement.</p><p>Unallocated cases are a matter of serious concern to the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs, Deputy Katherine Zappone, who has asked Tusla to provide her Department with regularly updated numbers of the unallocated cases with which it is dealing.  The Minister also meets regularly with the Tusla board and the chief executive officer, and has identified the reduction of this waiting list as a key priority in its business case in 2017.  The most recent figures supplied by Tusla indicate there were 25,384 open cases at the end of March 2017.  Of these, 19,226 had been allocated to a social worker and 6,158 cases remain to be allocated.  When Tusla was set up in 2014, there were almost 10,000 unallocated cases.  This has been reduced to 5,413 at the end of 2016, a 20% reduction in 2016 alone at a time when referrals were rising.</p><p>It should be noted the majority of referrals to Tusla do not result in a child protection assessment, with 60% of all referrals deemed to be welfare referrals.  Recent increases in family support programmes have been put in place to deal with welfare referrals and to ensure early intervention.  Regarding welfare concerns, the Department of Children and Youth Affairs provides strategic and policy direction for children and young people's services committees, CYPSC, whose role is to co-ordinate community and family supports to include families with child welfare concerns.  The abolition of unallocated cases remains a high priority, and recruitment and retention of social workers is linked to achieving targets in this area.</p><p>In the 12 months to February 2017, Tusla had a social work turnover rate of 8.4%.  This compares favourably with other jurisdictions such as England where the 2016 turnover rate was approximately 15%.  It remains a concern that despite Tusla&rsquo;s increased efforts during 2016, including an intensive graduate recruitment campaign in Ireland, including Northern Ireland, recruitment of social workers continued to be challenging, requiring significant recruitment activity to achieve a modest increase in whole-time equivalent staff and to compensate for normal worker attrition rates with which Tusla must contend.</p><p>The number of social worker graduates annually in Ireland is between 200 and 250.  Tusla is competing with social work services in mental health, hospital, disability, primary care and probation for this limited pool.  It is likely the recruitment of social workers will continue to be challenging.  For this reason Tusla launched an ongoing recruitment campaign for social workers on its website and it will also be expanding its 2017 graduate recruitment drive to England, Scotland and Wales.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Finian McGrath:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1822"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1822&amp;amp;pid=FinianMcGrath&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->In order to allow social workers to focus on their core duties, Tusla is altering the make-up of teams to draw on other grades, such as social care workers, family support practitioners and clerical administration staff, as appropriate.  The Government is committed to funding Tusla to drive forward the reforms and recruitment of the additional social worker complement.  The Department of Children and Youth Affairs will continue to monitor progress closely in this regard.  The Minister, Deputy Zappone, will continue to engage directly with the Tusla board and senior management team over the course of the year, to review the progress being made in reducing unacceptable numbers of cases that have not been allocated to a social worker.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#L00200"><p>The reality, which the Minister of State accepted, is that there are over 5,000 children involved.  The reply to a parliamentary question tabled in the D&aacute;il indicated that more than 5,000 children who have been brought to the attention of child welfare and protection services have not been allocated social workers.  That is totally unacceptable.  These are children who are at some level of risk.  The State is acting <i>in loco parentis</i>in respect of many of these children.  It has a duty and responsibility.  Have we not learned anything from the past about the protection, welfare and responsibility of the State when it is acting <i>in loco parentis</i>in respect of these children?  They are children who are vulnerable, some of whom have come through horrific circumstances, yet they do not have social workers.  I met a woman who had her young child in court in north County Dublin last week.  She has a very young child yet there was no social worker.  She has difficulty with language because she is non-European, although she is an Irish citizen.  These people are vulnerable and need assistance.  The State will be sued.  Legal action will be taken against the State in the future in respect of its failure to provide social workers for children for whom it acts <i>in loco parentis</i>.  The State has a constitutional obligation to protect and care for such children.</p><p>The Minister of State referred to own named social workers.  Social workers build relationships with children and children build relationships with social workers.  Children confide to them very sensitive, hurtful and personal experiences.  They need the continuity and consistency of an allocated social worker to advocate for them.  I rest my case.  It is an unsatisfactory response.  It is not the Minister of State's response but it is absolutely unsatisfactory.  It is something this House and the D&aacute;il will have to come together on to exert more pressure because they have to be found.  These are vulnerable children.  The Minister of State knows that more than anyone and I know he is committed to supporting them.  It is an unsatisfactory response and it is disappointing to say that.  It warrants a constant review; we should know every two weeks.  I will ask some of my colleagues in Leinster House to table parliamentary questions next week.  It is critical and crucial.  It is important and the situation is not acceptable.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#L00300"><p>I take the points raised by Senator Boyhan, particularly those on the number of children waiting for the allocation of dedicated social workers.  Nobody will argue against that but let us also look at the current situation and what is happening.  At the end of March 2017, Tusla had 1,486 whole-time equivalent social workers and it is at 42% of its 2017 recruitment target of 62 additional social workers.  Senator Boyhan asked if we had not learned.  We have to learn from life's experience and we have to learn that leaving these children in this situation is not acceptable.  We sat down and thought about it and came up with a business plan.  Tusla's 2017 business plan has identified a target of 369 additional staff which will include 62 social workers and 157 social care workers.  I want to use this opportunity to commend the staff I have dealt with a lot recently, namely, the social care workers in the services.  I commend the great work they do.  In addition, 103 family support workers and 35 clerical administration staff will be recruited.  That business plan is there and we are trying to implement it.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Finian McGrath:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1822"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1822&amp;amp;pid=FinianMcGrath&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Tusla, the Child and Family Agency, will be given a budget of &euro;713 million, an increase of &euro;37 million.  We have a problem with getting social workers and other staff, and that is something we have to deal with.  With an increase of &euro;37 million, it is not a question of money; it is a question of getting the staff.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.39" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 3.25 p.m. and resumed at 3.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.40" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#N00100">Appointment of Taoiseach, Members of Government, Minister of State and Attorney General</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#N00200"><p>Before I call the Leader on the Order of Business, I must inform the House that letters dated 3 and 14 June 2017 have been received from the Secretary to the Government regarding:</p><blockquote>(1) the resignation and appointment of the Minister of State at the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform with special responsibility for the Office of Public Works and flood relief;<br /><br />(2) the appointment of Deputy Leo Varadkar as Taoiseach;<br /><br />(3) the nomination of members of the Government;<br /><br />(4) the nomination of the Attorney General; and <br /><br />(5) the nomination of the T&aacute;naiste; and the allocation of Departments.  The letters will be set out in the Journal of the House.  Consequent on this announcement, they will also be printed in the Official Report.<br /><br />ROINN AN TAOISIGH<br /><br />Department of the Taoiseach<br /><br />BAILE &Aacute;THA CLIATH 2<br /><br />Dublin 2<br /><br />3 June, 2017<br /><br />Clerk of the Seanad,<br /><br />Leinster House.<br /><br />The Taoiseach accepted the resignation of Deputy Se&aacute;n Canney as Minister of State at the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform today, 3 June 2017.<br /><br />On the nomination of the Taoiseach and in exercise of the power conferred on them by the Ministers and Secretaries Acts 1924 to 2007, the Government appointed Kevin Boxer Moran, T.D to be Minister of State at the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform with special responsibility for the Office of Public Works and Flood Relief with effect from today, 3 June 2017.<br /><br />ROINN AN TAOISIGH<br /><br />Department of the Taoiseach<br /><br />BAILE &Aacute;THA CLIATH 2<br /><br />Dublin 2<br /><br />14 Meitheamh, 2017.<br /><br />Cl&eacute;ireach an tSeanaid<br /><br />T&aacute; orm a chur in i&uacute;l duit go bhfuil(1) an tUachtar&aacute;n, ar ainmni&uacute; Dh&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann, tar &eacute;is Leo Varadkar a cheapadh inniu, de bhun Airteagal 13.1.1&deg; den Bhunreacht, mar Thaoiseach;<br /><br />(2) an tUachtar&aacute;n, ag gn&iacute;omh&uacute; d&oacute; ar ainmni&uacute; an Taoisigh, le comhaont&uacute; Dh&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann roimh r&eacute;, tar &eacute;is na daoine seo a leanas a cheapadh inniu, de bhun Airteagal 13.1.2&deg; den Bhunreacht, mar chomhalta&iacute; den Rialtas agus bheith, i dteannta an Taoisigh, mar Rialtas:-<blockquote>Proins&eacute;as Nic Gearailt<br /><br />Pascal &Oacute; Donnch&uacute;<br /><br />Riste&aacute;rd de Briot&uacute;n<br /><br />S&iacute;om&oacute;n &Oacute; C&oacute;mhanaigh<br /><br />Cathal &Oacute; Flannag&aacute;in<br /><br />Heather Mhic Unfraidh<br /><br />S&iacute;om&oacute;n &Oacute; hEarcha&iacute;<br /><br />Miche&aacute;l &Oacute; Cr&iacute;od<br /><br />Donnacha &Oacute; Neachtain<br /><br />Se&aacute;n de Rossa<br /><br />Katherine Zappone<br /><br />Miche&aacute;l &Oacute; Rinn<br /><br />R&iacute;ona U&iacute; Dhochartaigh<br /><br />Eoghan &Oacute; Murch&uacute;</blockquote>(3) an tUachtar&aacute;n tar &eacute;is Seamus PhiIip Woulfe. S.C., a cheapadh, ar ainmni&uacute; an Taoisigh, mar Ard-Aighne de bhun Airteagal 30.2 den Bhunreacht.<br /><br />(4) an Taoiseach tar &eacute;is Proins&eacute;as Nic Gearailt a ainmni&uacute; inniu, de bhun Airteagal 28.6.1&deg; den Bhunreacht, chun beith ina T&aacute;naiste; agus<br /><br />(5) an Taoiseach, i bhfeidhmi&uacute; na cumhachta a thugtar d&oacute; le halt 4(1) den Acht Air&iacute; agus R&uacute;naithe (Leas&uacute;) 1946, inniu tar &eacute;is an Roinn Cosanta a shannadh d&oacute; fh&eacute;in agus na Ranna St&aacute;it seo a leanas a shannadh leis seo do na comhalta&iacute; faoi seach den Rialtas a luaitear a n-ainmneacha os coinne ainmneacha na Ranna:<blockquote>An Roinn Post, Fiontar agus Nu&aacute;la&iacute;ochta - Proins&eacute;as Nic Gerailt<br /><br />An Roinn Airgeadais agus An Roinn Caiteachais Phoibl&iacute; agus Athch&oacute;irithe - Pascal &Oacute; Donnch&uacute;<br /><br />An Roinn Oideachais agus Scileanna - Riste&aacute;rd de Briot&uacute;n<br /><br />An Roinn Gn&oacute;tha&iacute; Eachtracha agus Tr&aacute;d&aacute;la - S&iacute;om&oacute;n &Oacute; C&oacute;mhanaigh<br /><br />An Roinn Dl&iacute; agus Cirt agus Comhionannais - Cathal &Oacute; Flannag&aacute;in<br /><br />An Roinn Eala&iacute;on, Oidhreachta, Gn&oacute;tha&iacute; R&eacute;igi&uacute;nacha, Tuaithe agus Gaeltachta - Heather Mhic Unfraidh<br /><br />An Roinn Sl&aacute;inte - S&iacute;om&oacute;n &Oacute; hEarcha&iacute;<br /><br />An Roinn Talmha&iacute;ochta, Bia agus Mara - Miche&aacute;l &Oacute; Cr&iacute;od<br /><br />An Roinn Cumars&aacute;ide, Gn&iacute;omhaithe ar son na hAer&aacute;ide agus Comhshaoil - Donnacha &Oacute; Neachtain<br /><br />An Roinn Iompair, Turas&oacute;ireachta agus Sp&oacute;irt - Se&aacute;n de Rossa<br /><br />An Roinn Leana&iacute; agus Gn&oacute;tha&iacute; &Oacute;ige - Caitr&iacute;ona Zappone<br /><br />An Roinn Coimirce S&oacute;isiala&iacute; - R&iacute;ona U&iacute; Dhochartaigh<br /><br />An Roinn Tith&iacute;ochta, Plean&aacute;la, Pobail agus Rialtais &Aacute;iti&uacute;il - Eoghan &Oacute; Murch&uacute;</blockquote></blockquote></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.42" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#N00300">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#N00400"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, motion re Standing Order 70A, to be taken on the conclusion of the Order of Business without debate; No. 2, motion re amendment to the orders of reference of the Special Joint Committee on the Eighth Amendment of the Constitution, to be taken on the conclusion of No. 1 with the time allocated to group spokespersons not to exceed five minutes; No. 3, Inland Fisheries (Amendment) Bill 2017 - Second Stage, to be taken on the conclusion of No. 2 and to be adjourned at no later than 7 p.m., with the contribution of group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes and all other Senators not to exceed five minutes; No. 4, motion re Offences against the State (Amendment) Act 1998; and No. 5, motion re Criminal Justice (Amendment) Act 2009, to be taken on the conclusion of No. 3 and to conclude within 40 minutes, with the time allocated to the group spokespersons not to exceed five minutes and the Minister to be given five minutes to reply.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#O00200"><p>Today I would like to use my time to raise the issue of the appointment of M&aacute;ire Whelan to the Court of Appeal.  What we have seen in the past week is ducking and diving by the Taoiseach and members of the Cabinet.  All they seem to pivot back to is the line that M&aacute;ire Whelan is that eminently qualified for the post.  I am sure that the three High Court judges who formally expressed an interest in appointment to the Court of Appeal, whoever they are, were also eminently qualified for this post and clearly went about seeking the opportunity to serve on the Court of Appeal in accordance with the legislation.  The former Attorney General never expressed any interest in the post at the judicial appointments advisory board meeting she recently attended in May.</p> <p>What is being rightly questioned here is the process used by the Government to appoint M&aacute;ire Whelan.  Yesterday we saw the Taoiseach whisk M&aacute;ire Whelan to &Aacute;ras an Uachtar&aacute;in, a move clearly designed to quell the potential and public outcry over the barefaced croneyism on display here.  Not only is the Taoiseach showing contempt for the Parliament and members of the public, he is showing utter contempt towards those members of his own new Cabinet who sought a review of this decision at Cabinet today.  It is a shame that the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Shane Ross, did not raise serious questions at the Cabinet meeting last Tuesday.  Perhaps if the Minister had paid as much attention to M&aacute;ire Whelan's appointment by Fine Gael as he did to securing the re-opening of the Stepaside Garda station he might have been able to prevent such a flawed appointment.  He passed on this opportunity last Tuesday to ask tough questions about this appointment and everything that he says now is simply too little too late.  </p> <p>In order to fully understand how this debacle arose, we need honesty from those Government Ministers who were party to this decision.  I believe it is incumbent on the Taoiseach and on the T&aacute;naiste, Deputy Frances Fitzgerald, to provide an open and honest explanation as to how this appointment unfolded.  The following questions must be answered.  We now know from Leaders' Questions just an hour ago in the D&aacute;il that the incoming Taoiseach knew that M&aacute;ire Whelan's appointment was possible as he entered the Cabinet room last Thursday.  He had been informed the evening beforehand that it was a possibility.  The public needs to know who advised the incoming Taoiseach that it was a possibility and why, on the eve of the decision being put to the Cabinet, the Taoiseach says that he was only informed of it being a possibility.  For such an important appointment, why was the incoming Taoiseach only advised of it being a possibility?  Are we to believe that the decision was only made by the Minister between the Monday evening and the following morning? </p> <p>The T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Fitzgerald chose to make the recommendation of M&aacute;ire Whelan, ignoring the three High Court judges who had expressed an interest in this post.  Did the T&aacute;naiste come to this determination on her own?  The Taoiseach stated today that he was only informed that it was a possibility and that he had no part in drawing up this memo.  Did the Taoiseach confirm to the T&aacute;naiste that he would support M&aacute;ire Whelan's nomination?  Did the T&aacute;naiste discuss the matter with the outgoing Taoiseach, Deputy Enda Kenny?   We know that the T&aacute;naiste had a conversation with the incoming Taoiseach on Monday evening but who else did she discuss this matter with?  </p> <p>The T&aacute;naiste should set out exactly when the former Attorney General expressed an interest in the position on the Court of Appeal.  She did not express an interest in the post just a few weeks ago at the judicial appointments advisory board in May.  When exactly was the T&aacute;naiste made aware of the former Attorney General's interest in being nominated to the Court of Appeal?</p> <p>Finally, did the T&aacute;naiste discuss with M&aacute;ire Whelan in advance of the Cabinet meeting how she would nominate her?  Did she specifically agree with M&aacute;ire Whelan that she should remain in the room while the Cabinet determined her fate?  I believe it is in the public interest that the Government is held accountable for what we have witnessed in the past week.  It is for that reason I formally propose that the T&aacute;naiste be called to this House to provide answers to the questions people rightly want answered.     </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#P00100"><p>I welcome Deputy MacSharry back to his old House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#P00200"><p>I would like to raise three matters: the appointment to the Court of Appeal vacancy; Rebuilding Ireland and the shift or change in Government policy in that regard; and the new Government.  I will be brief.  I understand, from the media and my engagement with people, that at least three High Court judges had written to the Attorney General, M&aacute;ire Whelan, indicating that they wanted to be considered for the vacancy at the Court of Appeal.  I also understand that then Minister for Justice and Equality had sought a list of candidates from the Judicial Appointments Advisory Board and that the latter &quot;was not in a position to recommend anyone for appointment&quot;.  There has been much talk of the appointment being in accordance with previous convention and within the law.  I do not intend to spend much time raking over the coals of the appointment.  I do not doubt or question the integrity or capabilities of the appointee, Maire Whelan.  However, I do believe in learning from experiences.  Following on from this experience, there is a need for greater clarity regarding the appointment of judges.  Members will recall that I introduced a Private Members' motion on 15 September 2016 in respect of the appointment of judges and the establishment of a judicial council.  That motion was unanimously agreed by the House but, sadly, no progress whatsoever has been made.  Perhaps the Leader will follow up on that matter.</p><p>In regard to Rebuilding Ireland, the Taoiseach, on the appointment of Deputy Eoghan Murphy as Minister for Housing, Planning, Community and Local Government said:</p><blockquote>Rebuilding Ireland is working but it may not be enough and so I am tasking him to review it within three months and to consider what additional measures may be required, including consideration of a greater quantum of social housing build, a vacant home tax and measures to encourage landlords to remain in or enter the rental market.</blockquote> <p>Within 24 hours of that statement being made, the outgoing Minister, Deputy Coveney, issued an unusual statement on his website in which he set out his record in regard to Rebuilding Ireland and the rationale of moving on, which I think was brave and the correct thing to do because it set out his stall.  I invite people to take a look at both statements, one of which is available on Deputy Coveney's website and the other in the Official Report.  The Taoiseach has now indicated that there will be shift in policy in Rebuilding Ireland.  It is important to note this.  It would be timely and appropriate that the new Minister, once he has settled into his new office, would come to the House to discuss this issue in the context of the third review of the commitments provided for in Rebuilding Ireland.  </p><p>I take this opportunity to wish the Taoiseach well.  I also wish the new Ministers and Ministers of State well in what is a challenging job.  There are many people who are disappointed but that is the nature of politics.  In regard to the new appointees, I wish them well.  Leo's potent, political objective has taken him thus far but his toughest tests are yet to come.  I wish him well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#P00300"><p>I am sure Tom Gilmartin, wherever he is, is having a good laugh about Fianna F&aacute;il's commentary on cronyism and corruption.  Along with Frank Connolly, he wrote the book <i>Tom Gilmartin: The Man Who Brought Down a Taoiseach and Exposed the Greed and Corruption at the Heart of Irish Politics</i>.  Rather than comment further I will allow the people of this country to decide for themselves who are the masters of cronyism and corruption.</p><p>I wish to extend my sympathy to the victim of the events in Finsbury Park.  I worked near there for several years and I know the area very well.  What happened the other night was atrocious.</p><p>The main topic of my contribution today is Grenfell Tower.  We should all think about the silhouette in the window and what it means in terms of the people who have perished, why they have perished and the absolute inequality that the tragedy in Grenfell Tower exposes.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Rose Conway-Walsh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2462"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2462&amp;amp;pid=RoseConwayWalsh&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is the tragedy of people being treated as lesser citizens.  I am very familiar with the borough, having been born in King's College Hospital, which is close to Grenfell Tower, and I am very aware of the contrasts between the filthy rich and the wealthy of that borough and the hard-working residents of Grenfell Tower.  The way the latter were treated in terms of the refurbishment of the tower, the materials used and so on led to the loss of many lives.  In that context, it would be remiss of us not to examine the housing stock in this country.  I ask that the new Minister for Housing, Planning, Community and Local Government would come to the House to discuss the condition of our housing stock.  I know many tenants who have been paying rent for 30 to 40 years without ever having had any refurbishment work done on their homes.  These tenants must be listened to in terms of the work that needs to be done, particularly work that is required in the context of health and safety like rewiring and so forth.  The clerk of works system that operated previously in this country must be reintroduced in order that there are proper, independent inspections of properties.  We also need proper funding for local authorities to enable them to carry out essential works.  I also ask that our engagement with the Minister would also include a discussion on housing aid grants for older people.  The criteria for such grants have been restricted in recent years and people have been left with leaking roofs, bad wiring and so forth.  The third and final housing issue I would like the Minister to address is the need to lift the restrictions on the tenant purchase scheme.  These restrictions prevent people purchasing their council houses and doing them up themselves.  The councils do not have the money to carry out such work.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#Q00200"><p>I seek clarification with regard to the motion in respect of the special joint committee.  Am I correct in understanding that there will be five minutes for a debate on that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#Q00300"><p>Just to clarify for the Senator-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#Q00400"><p>The Leader will be called on to respond at the end.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#Q00500"><p>I asked for-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#Q00600"><p>I am sorry, but the Senator is not really entitled to do this.  I ask the Leader to be quick because this is out of order</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#Q00700"><p>Just to clarify for the benefit of Senator Higgins who, to be fair, was late coming in, I have allowed for debate given that the motion refers to an issue that was raised in this House.  I have allowed for a spokesperson from each group to contribute rather than having no debate at all.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#Q00800"><p>That is perfect.  I was actually here but I just wanted to clarify that to determine whether I needed to use my time on the Order of Business to speak to that issue.  I thank the Leader for that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#Q00900"><p>I am glad to be of help.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#Q01000"><p>I appreciate it.  As was mentioned, we will be speaking on the motion.  We have tabled an amendment in respect of the order that has come through from the Committee on Procedure and Privileges.  We are very concerned about the motion, especially with regard to its effective barring of substitution on a new committee, but we will have an opportunity to speak to that when the motion is being debated, as I understand it.</p> <p>I would like to echo the points made by Senator Conway-Walsh in respect of housing.  It would be very appropriate to have a debate in this House on that issue.  We also need to look at a question which, as I understand it, is being debated in the other House this week, namely, the concern in respect of developers who do not meet health and safety standards but who still proceed to be awarded public contracts.  That is something we need to look at more closely as part of ensuring we are far more rigorous in the way we do public procurement and enforce regulations.  We have seen the tragic consequences of an inadequate approach to regulation.  In that context, I appeal to everyone in this House to abandon a phrase which has been very toxic, that is, "the burden of regulation".  Maybe we could decide as a House never to use that phrase again.  Let us talk about regulation being effective and how it is streamlined, managed and so forth, but let us not talk about regulation as a burden.  That language was used in the UK and the former Prime Minister, Mr. Cameron, spoke about the need to attack the health and safety culture.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Alice-Mary Higgins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2480"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2480&amp;amp;pid=AliceMaryHiggins&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I believe that health and safety is of paramount importance for us in this State.</p><p>Today is World Refugee Day and Ireland still has not stepped up to its responsibilities.  I know this is an issue that has been strongly felt in this House and we have debated it back and forth.  We need to find ways to move the debate forward, and I appeal to the Leader to do so, and specifically to look at European strategy and the agreements which the EU continues to sign with Turkey, Libya, South Sudan and with many regimes that have extraordinarily questionable human rights standards in respect of the redirection of refugees and immigration control.  The EU holds moral responsibility for the experiences of those who seek refuge and who find themselves directed to these very questionable situations.</p><p>During the appropriate debate, I will have the opportunity to return to the key issue of the motion on the establishment of a committee on the eighth amendment to the Constitution.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#R00200"><p>I join Senator Conway-Walsh in expressing sympathy to all of those who were caught up in the appalling tragedy of the awful fire at the Grenfell Tower in London.  We are still seeing reports of increasing numbers of people having been killed.  I send sincere sympathies to all of those who are bereaved by the tragedy.  I agree that it would be useful to have a debate on the state of housing stock in respect of fire safety and especially on the practice of cladding blocks of apartments, which clearly has particular implications in the Grenfell Tower tragedy.  I understand we are still waiting to see what exactly was the cause of the fire and of it spreading so fast, but it seems that quite a number of experts have suggested that the cladding was a big factor.  I also wish to express sympathy to the family of the man who was killed in the Finsbury Park mosque attack.</p> <p>All of us in the House would also like to express sympathy to the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs, Deputy Katherine Zappone, on the sad loss of her wife, Dr. Ann Louise Gilligan.  The Minister was a colleague in this House prior to the last general election.</p> <p>I join Senator Catherine Ardagh and others in their comments on the process of the appointment of the outgoing Attorney General, M&aacute;ire Whelan, to the Court of Appeal.  It is rich to hear Fianna F&aacute;il criticising the practice of cronyism, but certainly the process of the appointment appears to have been deeply flawed.  I join my own party leader, Deputy Brendan Howlin, in calling for that decision to be reviewed, as he did last Friday.</p> <p>In the context of the announcements today by the Taoiseach, Deputy Leo Varadkar, I ask for a debate on women in politics.  I join others in wishing him well as Taoiseach but I was very disappointed to see the lack of commitment to ensuring we have a more balanced gender representation among Cabinet and Ministers of State.  Many of us thought the Taoiseach might use the Minister of State appointments today as a means of addressing the imbalance that exists in the Cabinet.  It is very disappointing that there was not more promotion of women in the Cabinet, but in the Minister of State appointments the Taoiseach has missed an opportunity by demoting one very able woman and not promoting any new women to the ranks of the Ministers of State.  For one who has very overtly and explicitly modelled himself on Emmanuel Macron and Justin Trudeau, I believe it is a terrible shame that the Taoiseach has missed this opportunity.  Those two leaders in France and Canada have explicitly moved to ensure better gender representation in their Cabinets by their choice of Ministers.  It is a real shame and a missed opportunity that the Taoiseach, Deputy Varadkar, has not done the same in Ireland.  I ask the Leader for a debate on the need to ensure the promotion of women in politics, to ensure enhanced gender balance among our political representatives, and to ensure support for the Women For Election group, an organisation that has done a significant amount to bring women forward and to support women in running for political office.  It is very important.</p> <p>Finally, I join Senator Higgins in wishing everyone a happy World Refugee Day.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" speakername="Gabrielle McFadden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#R00300"><p>As I was driving to Dublin today, I listened with interest and immense sadness to a report on RTE Radio 1 regarding people who were suicidal or who had attempted suicide having difficulty accessing appropriate psychiatric services, especially in out-of-hours times.  The programme outlined cases of people in these situations who had presented to emergency departments of their local hospital as recommended on the HSE website.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Gabrielle McFadden:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2399"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2399&amp;amp;pid=GabrielleMcFadden&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->They were triaged by a nurse on duty and in many cases had only a telephone conversation with a consultant psychiatrist before being discharged as medically fit.  Once discharged some of these people went on to commit suicide.  This is not a new issue and indeed it is one I raised here in February with the then Minister of State with responsibility for mental health, Deputy McEntee.  The discussion on the radio today was particularly timely because I received a call yesterday from a family in a similar situation.  A girl in her early 20s who attempted suicide several weeks ago, had a violent outburst towards her parents on Friday night and was taken by ambulance at 5 a.m. on Saturday morning to a local psychiatric hospital, spent the day there and was discharged and sent home in a taxi at 10 p.m. on Saturday, some 17 hours later.</p><p>If I or anybody else presented at the emergency department on a Friday evening with cardiac arrest, a brain haemorrhage, a stroke or any other severe physical illness and had been discharged and subsequently died, people would rightfully ask questions.  Why should it be any different for a person presenting with severe mental health issues? </p><p>We know that every community in Ireland is affected by suicide and self-harm and that the emotional turmoil associated with such ideation does not confine itself to out-of-hours' times.  Nobody suicidal should ever be turned away.  Will the Leader please ask the new Minister of State with responsibility for mental health to come to the Chamber and have a debate and hear comments from the Senators with regard to specific steps that can be taken to fix the problems associated with access to help, especially out-of-hours?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#S00200"><p>I second the amendment to the Order of Business proposed by my colleague, Senator Ardagh, to invite the Minister for Justice and Equality to come to the House to address the appointment of the Attorney General.  It is important that this issue is clarified and I support her call for that.</p> <p>Every year 2,500 people in Ireland are diagnosed with bowel cancer.  Of those, 1,000 lose their lives each year.  Bowel cancer is the second most deadly cancer after lung cancer.  It is striking, however, that up to 500 fewer of those people would lose their lives if two simple steps were taken, lifestyle changes and availing of a free bowel screen.  I encourage all those who are eligible, males and females between the ages of 60 and 69, to undergo this test.</p> <p>The Irish Cancer Society is very concerned that only 40% of those eligible are undergoing this much-needed test.  A leading expert in this field, residing in Scotland, has indicated that if all eligible people were to go for screening the number of deaths could be reduced by 30%.  That is a striking figure.  It is vital that the Minister for Health allocate sufficient funds to the promotion of this test and the age group of those eligible be extended to ages 55 to 74.  It is imperative that this be done without delay and I ask the Leader to ensure that the Minister provides sufficient funding to save these lives.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#S00300"><p>Several people have spoken about the appointment of the former Attorney General, Ms Whelan, to the Court of Appeal.  Everywhere the woman's name is mentioned we hear about her qualifications.  Her qualifications are not the issue.  The issue is the process.  If this happened in a public service job the employer would be before the Labour Court.  Was this woman sitting in on a meeting of the Judicial Appointments Advisory Board when the decision about the three High Court judges was made?<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Gerard P. Craughwell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2402"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2402&amp;amp;pid=GerardPCraughwell&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is something else to tell us that three High Court judges were not capable of promotion to the Court of Appeal.  Did the former Attorney General sit in on the Cabinet meeting that decided on her appointment?  We are told we cannot find that out because of Cabinet confidentiality.  This is the worst form of stroke politics ever, but as bad and all as that is, the political comment on it over the weekend, of huffing and puffing and getting as far as generating the wind to blow the house down and then deciding we would not blow the house down, really takes the biscuit.  Is it any wonder that the people of this country are totally cynical about politics and politicians?  What has gone on in this country over recent days with the appointment of this woman to a tainted position?  She has tainted the court by taking the role.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#T00200"><p>Would you stop?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#T00300"><p>Please, the lady is not here to answer for herself.  I am not going to allow that.  Please desist.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#T00400"><p>The Cathaoirleach has no choice.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#T00500"><p>I have a choice.  I am in the Chair, and the Senator will not challenge the Chair, with respect.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#T00600"><p>We should get the Minister for Justice and Equality in here this afternoon.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#T00700"><p>Please be orderly, Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#T00800"><p>What has happened here is disgraceful and it taints us all.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#T00900"><p>The Senator is entitled to his opinion.  His time is up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1423" speakername="Ray Butler" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#T01000"><p>I would like to send my condolences to the people of the tower block in London, and also to the Portuguese people as a result of the forest fires which have claimed the lives of up to 70 people.  There are going to be three days of national mourning in Portugal.</p> <p>I was delighted, along with everyone else, to hear about the deal done to get Irish beef back into the US market.  I have to say, however, that I am not very happy to see that the cartel, the beef factories, are slashing beef prices by up to &euro;50 per head this week.  The move comes despite a reported shortage of manufacturing beef across Europe.  There is a shortage of beef and so prices should be going up.  The cartel, however, is taking them down.  This is an attempt to panic farmers at a time when good grazing conditions and farmers busy at silage and hay are making cattle scarce.  The cartel, which has been allowed in this country, is putting the gun to farmer's head again, as it were, and cutting prices to get them to run into the factories.</p> <p>I read in the newspaper that good weather all across Europe is positive for farmers as the barbecue season looks like it will drive beef demand upwards.  It is not going up but coming down in this country.  It is a disgrace.  I would like to have the Minister into the House in order that we can see what he is going to do to ensure fair play for farmers.  This is not good enough.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#T01100"><p>It is World Refugee Day today.  There are millions of displaced people around the world with no home and no country.  I am organising a group of women and men from direct provision to come in tomorrow morning to do a presentation, and it would be great if as many people as possible, or their representatives, could make it to listen to the stories these people have to tell.</p> <p>I want to go back to the issue of Linn Dara in Cherry Orchard in Ballyfermot.  Half the beds there were closed three weeks ago.  We have been in negotiations with Minister of State at the Department of Health, Deputy McEntee.  I have been in constant contact with my union, the Psychiatric Nurses Association.  There are solutions but they have not been implemented.  I imagine that the reshuffle was more of a priority than our children, who have had to attend at accident and emergency departments and wait 24 hours.  They are at real risk.  My colleague, Deputy Louise O'Reilly, asked some political questions yesterday and received some responses.  The figures we received on child and adolescent mental health services are shocking and concerning.  Only 53% of the staff deemed necessary to implement a Vision for Change exists in child and adult mental health services.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator M&aacute;ire Devine:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2468"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2468&amp;amp;pid=MaireDevine&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->That means 47% of staff are missing and have not been appointed.  Adult services are slightly better, if one could say that, as 78% of staff have been appointed.  In Dublin South-Central only 52% of child and adolescent mental health staff positions are filled.  That cannot continue.  How many wake-up calls are needed?</p><p>UNICEF launched its report on children yesterday, including children in emotional distress and those with mental health issues.  Ireland came 34th out of 37 nations surveyed.  A total of 22.6% of children here, aged between 11 and 15, stated they had experienced two or more psychological symptoms in the past or more than once a week.  That is shocking and insupportable.  The closure of Linn Dara is insupportable and it is shameful.  I hope the new Minister of State with responsibility for mental health, Deputy Jim Daly, can be proactive and not sit back and rely on bogus reviews that sit and gather dust.  We need to act and there is no time like now.  We needed the services yesterday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1404" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#U00200"><p>This is the first sitting day since the passing of Ann Louise Gilligan and I wish to pay tribute to her in the Seanad not only for the impact she had on my life but the impact she has had on generations of lives across the community in Tallaght.  She cannot be faulted on the level of work and commitment she gave to working class communities as well as the LGBT community for many years.  A quote she used comes to mind and I will read it:</p><blockquote>The teacher is of course an artist, but being an artist does not mean that he or she can make the profile, can shape the students.  What the educator does in teaching is to make it possible for the students to become themselves.</blockquote> <p>I really feel that what Ann Louise gave to the women of Tallaght was space, and she facilitated the room for healing so that students and women could become themselves.  I wish to remember her here today and send my condolences to the Minister, Deputy Zappone.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#U00300"><p>Reference has already been made to the fact that today is UN World Refugee Day.  I congratulate the University of Limerick on becoming a university of sanctuary.  Yesterday, at the first Department of Justice and Equality citizenship event held at the University of Limerick, the president, Dr. Des Fitzgerald, made the announcement that the university would become a university of sanctuary.  There will be initiatives to welcome asylum seekers and refugees into the university community.  That is a very welcome initiative.  A total of 17 refugees and asylum seekers will be in receipt of scholarships from September 2017.  The university also stated there will be a three-year action plan to promote access and culture.  The university has said the knowledge and commitment of refugees and asylum seekers will be a key driver in the movement to designate not only Limerick but the mid-west region as a place of sanctuary.  That is very important, especially on UN World Refugee Day.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#U00400"><p>It is extremely fitting that Limerick has been mentioned in the previous contribution.  I do welcome the fact that the University of Limerick has announced it will be a sanctuary university.  It is UN World Refugee Day.  However, I wish to raise an issue which perhaps the Taoiseach himself could come into the Chamber to discuss, namely, the comments made by a Fine Gael councillor in Limerick, Stephen Keary, who is due to become the next Mayor of Limerick.  It is fantastic that the University of Limerick will become a sanctuary university and it is wonderful that we have laudable statements on UN World Refugee Day but that individual has made racist, anti-immigrant statements in recent weeks.  Our own Labour Party councillor in that part of the world, Elena Secas, who is of Moldovan extraction, is disgusted by what he said.  The new leader of Fine Gael does not seem to find the capacity within himself to censure the councillor, criticise him or perhaps even expel him from the Fine Gael Party, or at least make sure that his name does not go forward to be the first citizen of Limerick.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#U00500"><p>Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in is a long-standing Member and knows we should not refer to people outside the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#U00600"><p>Hold on, a Leas-Chathaoirligh.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#U00700"><p>Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in knows we should not refer to people outside the House who are not in a position to defend themselves.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#V00100"><p>This is the era of new politics.  We now have a new Taoiseach who, in the context of the person that he is and his background-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#V00200"><p>Does the Senator want the Taoiseach to address the House?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#V00300"><p>-----for many people represents a new opportunity for this country.  We have five appointees to positions as Ministers of State not one of whom is a woman.  We also have a councillor in Limerick making racist comments.  This individual is due to be Mayor of Limerick and there is absolutely no word from the Taoiseach on the matter.  I would like to discuss the-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#V00400"><p>The House is not actually aware of what it is the Senator-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#V00500"><p>-----comments made by this individual at a public forum in Limerick over which he is standing.  These were anti-immigrant and racist comments-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#V00600"><p>He is not here to defend himself, as the Senator well knows.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#V00700"><p>----and on this of all days we have to call him out.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#V00800"><p>The Senator's time is up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#V00900"><p>I want to know what the Leader believes the response of his party and the Taoiseach should be-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#V01000"><p>The Leader will respond, I have no doubt.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#V01100"><p>-----to a councillor who is making racist and anti-immigrant comments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#V01200"><p>That is the Senator's opinion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#V01300"><p>Is he welcome in Fine Gael and should he be Mayor of Limerick?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#V01400"><p>The person the Senator is referring to is not here to defend himself.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#V01500"><p>I agree with Deputy Ardagh on the comments she made.</p> <p>I raise the very sad loss of Mr. Thomas Power from Waterford, who, as I am sure all Members are aware, passed away at the weekend.  He went to Waterford hospital complaining of a pain in his chest but the cardiac unit was not open.  As we are all aware, for a long time the people of Waterford and the south east have been fighting for this unit to be opened.  It opens Monday to Friday from 9 a.m. to 5 p.m. and is closed at weekends.  Mr. Power was told he would be taken by ambulance to Cork but he died on the way.  That is a disaster.  It is tragic and so sad in terms of the loss of a young life.  The fact that the unit needs to be open 24 hours a day has been raised constantly with the Minister, Deputy Harris.  We do not have a 24-hour service in the south east.  It is unacceptable that people are expected to suffer heart attacks between 9 a.m. and 5 p.m on weekdays.  If they suffer heart attacks at any other time, there is no service available.  I call on the Minister to come before the House and provide an assurance that this cardiac unit will be open 24 hours a day.  Statistics show that 80% of heart attacks happen after 5 p.m.  I offer my sympathies to the Power family.  It is disgraceful that those of us living in Waterford and the south east do not have access to a proper service.  It is unacceptable.  We are being treated as second-class citizens and I am of the view that this is down to funding.  I ask that the Minister, Deputy Harris, come before the House and clarify this issue.  I also call for the unit in question to be open 24 hours a day.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#V01600"><p>I echo the words of sympathy to the Minister for Children, Deputy Zappone, on the death of her wife, Ann Louise Gilligan.  I did not know Ann Louise but I served with the Minister, Deputy Zappone, on a committee for five years and found her to be a great colleague and a very inspiring person.  Our hearts and our sympathy go out to her at this time.</p> <p>I support Senator Conway-Walsh on the need for a debate in the House - I appeal to the Leader to facilitate it - on the condition of Irish public buildings in terms of the cladding, sprinkler systems and alarms used and the fire safety measures in place.  We need an inventory of those, and we need to learn a lesson from the tragedy in the United Kingdom.  Along with other Senators, my heart goes out to the people of Grenfell Tower.</p> <p>I wish to raise the issue of young children who public health nurses and teachers notice need assessment for potential conditions, such as autism, dyspraxia and dyslexia, that will affect the kind of support they need in education, in life and in terms of their development.  The waiting list for those young children is too long.  Thank God, with the recession having passed, we are now in the process of building a normal society.  In order to build a normal society, we need to consider this question and reduce the number of children on the waiting list to zero.  In County Cavan, where I live, we have a wonderful Enable Ireland centre, which has great staff and beautiful facilities.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Joe O'Reilly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1610"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1610&amp;amp;pid=JoeOReilly&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I visited it recently and it is an excellent place, but there is, I am told, a two-year waiting list.  That cannot continue.  I ask the Leader of the House, Senator Jerry Buttimer, himself a former Chairman of the health committee and a former teacher, who has the sensitivity on this issue, to arrange this debate as a matter of urgency.  We must have a whole debate on it, bringing in the relevant Ministers of all Departments where it impacts.  These children cannot be left in limbo.  They must be the first to benefit from the fact that we are now in a different space economically.  In conclusion, I ask for a review of the waiting lists for children for psychological testing and assessment.  The current position is bizarre, wrong and, in fact, unconstitutional.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1431" speakername="P&aacute;draig &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#W00200"><p>Ba mhaith liom tac&uacute; le Senator Murnane O'Connor.  I understand where she is coming from.  I had a heart attack five years ago and was very lucky to be only a mile and a half from the hospital.  People in Waterford should not be second-class citizens in this regard, nor should anyone else.  What she is saying is fundamental.  Go raibh m&iacute;le maith agat as ucht a thabhairt os comhar an Teach seo.</p> <p>Speaking of second-class citizens, I congratulate the new Taoiseach, Ministers and Ministers of State on their appointments and wish them every success.  God knows, we need strength, leadership, depth and conviction to help Ireland get to where we need to be in this world of economics.  However, I express my disappointment, and that of many in the west of Ireland, that we do not have a Cabinet Minister from Galway.  It is the third largest city in Ireland with a population of 250,000 people.  However, in this and the previous Government, we have not had a senior Cabinet Minister.  I hear it on the streets in Galway and all over the place and I express my and other people's disappointment at the fact.</p> <p>I ask the Leader to invite the new Minister of State with responsibility for Gaeilge, Gaeltacht and the islands, Deputy Joe McHugh, to address the House on the Sc&eacute;im Gaeilge which is in place to promote Irish in the Gaeltacht and Ireland generally but which, frankly, is not working.  It has not worked during the term of the previous Government and it is not working under this one.  I was born, reared and live in the Gaeltacht.  Irish is my first language and English is my second.  One of the major reasons the scheme is not working is because we are not focused on the people.  We tell people, companies and communities to draw up a plan to promote Irish but it is purely academic and of no benefit whatsoever.  What people from the Gaeltacht want is the opportunity to get up and work.  We do not want handouts, we want the opportunity to have a job.  Ten jobs in a rural Gaeltacht in Kerry, Donegal or Galway or any other part of rural Ireland are worth perhaps 500 jobs in a place like Dublin.  I ask for us to focus on that and for the Leader to invite the Minister of State to come to the House to talk to us about his plean Gaeilge and his vision so that we can help him along that line.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#W00300"><p>It was interesting to hear the comments made on the appointment of the former Attorney General.  It is important to note that 16 of the 29 Attorneys General of Ireland have been appointed to the High Court.  A number of others were appointed to positions at European level.  I refer to Mr. Peter Sutherland SC and Mr. Justice John Murray.  In fairness to Ms M&aacute;ire Whelan, there is no question or doubt that she has the competence to serve on the Court of Appeal.  It is a prerogative of the Government constitutionally to make the appointment to any position on the Superior Courts.  People may complain about the procedures, but constitutionally it is the Government that makes the appointment.</p> <p>People criticise the Judiciary here from time to time, but over the last 80 or so years, it has served this country well.  Judges have pushed out the boundaries of the law when the Oireachtas, Ministers and taoisigh have refused to tackle the issues.  In quite a number of areas constitutionally, there are established rights for citizens on which the Oireachtas was not prepared to introduce legislation.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Colm Burke:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2353"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2353&amp;amp;pid=ColmBurke&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is important we have that separation of powers.  The Minister and the Government appointed M&aacute;ire Whelan to the Court of Appeal.  It must be remembered that the Court of Appeal was set up six years ago because we had a backlog in the Supreme Court and getting a hearing in that court could take four years.  We set up a proper procedure to ensure the backlog was dealt with.  It is important that access to the courts is within a reasonable time.  Over the past six years, we have changed some of the issues on that.  The criticism about M&aacute;ire Whelan's appointment is wrong.  She has the ability and experience to serve and to perform as a member of the Court of Appeal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#X00200"><p>She was also the nearest thing we had to having a Minister from Galway.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#X00300"><p>There are two Ministers from Galway now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#X00400"><p>There is a Minister next door too.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#X00500"><p>International research has indicated that the children of alcoholics and drug addicts are far more susceptible to mental and physical illness as a result of the experience they suffer at the hands of parents who engage in substance abuse.  The plight of these children is largely hidden from the public gaze.  The recent audit by the Government's special rapporteur on child protection, Dr. Geoffrey Shannon, is important.  His audit of the exercise by the Garda of the provisions of section 12 of the Child Care Act is important because it graphically lays bare the grim effects of alcohol and drug abuse on young people in the family home.  Dr. Shannon told RTE's &ldquo;Morning Ireland&rdquo; that insurmountable burdens are placed on the child protection system because of society's failure to address alcohol as a fundamental problem.  While the personal stories in the 318 page report were illustrated in the media, the poor quality of life endured by these children has since left the spotlight.</p> <p>Will the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs, Deputy Zappone, come to the House to tell us what supports are available for these children?  I acknowledge it as a time of grief for her and our sympathies go out to her.  As soon as appropriate scheduling permits, it would be good to hear from her.</p> <p>In February 2017, the all-party parliamentary group of MPs in Britain launched a manifesto calling for political support and funding for children whose parents misuse alcohol.  In April, the British health Minister announced that children living with alcohol-dependent parents were to be prioritised in the strategy to address their needs.</p> <p>Irish children living in such homes need to have their unique circumstances recognised by the State, given the harm they endure.  In light of Dr. Shannon's report, it is time for the Department to commission a new comprehensive survey to assess the extent of the risks faced by children whose parents abuse drink and drugs.  In the meantime, the Government could consider the provision of additional financing to advocacy groups to help support and counsel children living in homes where parental addiction is a constant presence.</p> <p>I add my voice and congratulations to the new Taoiseach, Deputy Varadkar.  It will be interesting and we all wish him well.  Some good things have already been said.  Following from what I said last week, however, I was disappointed the Taoiseach announced so baldly that there would be a referendum on the eighth amendment in 2018.  As I said in response to Senator Bacik last week, there is a committee which is supposed to be looking at the Citizens&rsquo; Assembly report.  If we are to have respect for the parliamentary process-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#X00600"><p>I am sure that will be debated further in the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#X00700"><p>I am making a fair point and I am not attacking the Taoiseach.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#X00800"><p>The Senator is.  The Senator is also one minute over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#X00900"><p>I understand that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#X01000"><p>Time is important.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#X01100"><p>This is simply a question of whether we respect committees of this House or not.  Is committee work to be mere window dressing or choreographing, or is there to be respect for it?  All I am asking is that there would be respect for a committee process.  Notwithstanding his ideological opposition to me, Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in would agree with me on the point of procedure.  The Taoiseach ought to have left that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#X01200"><p>It is about allowing people to have their say.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#X01300"><p>I would like to join Senators Ruane and O'Reilly in expressing my sympathies to the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs, Deputy Zappone, on her great personal loss at this time.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Michelle Mulherin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2309"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2309&amp;amp;pid=MichelleMulherin&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I wish to raise the issue of the pyrite and mica report that was published this day last week amidst the hurly-burly of changes in the Lower House and us getting a new Taoiseach.  At that stage, I requested that the report be debated in this House because it is very important.  I understand the Leader is proceeding to make that invitation to the Minister of State, Deputy English, who it has been confirmed will remain in his role and who has done a fine job.  The report is long awaited and very welcome.  It is the first official acknowledgment that the problem manifesting itself in blockwork in counties Mayo and Donegal is owing to pyrite and mica.  The report and the engineering solutions offered are stark.  With pyrite in blockwork, the most effective solution seems to be to remove the affected blockwork, which in some cases is the entire inner and outer sleeve of the walls of the house, and to rebuild.  This is both a daunting and traumatic prospect for many people in Mayo and Donegal and a very expensive one.  This brings me to asking the Leader to have the Minister for Finance in because apart from getting the solutions in place, they will also have to be paid for.  We need a remediation scheme in order that the affected distressed homeowners can be financially assisted in respect of these solutions.  We also need to debate how to get to a point whereby people who have carried out the works will get a certificate of structural soundness to enable them to sell and mortgage their houses.  If a house has pyrite it is pretty much blacklisted.  It is any homeowner's worst nightmare.  For most people, it is their main asset and it is truly traumatic.  As we look towards the next budget and the arrangements that will be made for how moneys available are divvied up, we need a scheme similar to that put in place on the east coast for people affected by pyrite heave.  I ask that this is given due urgency.  People are waiting in Mayo and Donegal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#Y00200"><p>I acknowledge the Leader is here to toe the party line and represent his party.  I am sure he is delighted to be still sitting where he is after a change of leader and so on and rightly so, because he has been a good and fair performer.  Without fear of contradiction, the biggest problem facing our country at present is Brexit and the fallout therefrom.  I would be very surprised if anybody could contradict that.  I was among the first people to call for a separate, specific Minister with responsibility for Brexit.  We debated it here on a number of occasions.  I do not think it was a big request; it was quite a good and logical idea.  I see the Leader shaking his head.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#Y00300"><p>I am not.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#Y00400"><p>I have given the Leader leeway by acknowledging he had to toe a certain party line but there was no man like Enda.  He was the man, he had to deal with it because he had the contacts and nobody else in this country could look after it by-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#Y00500"><p>It is nice to hear that from the Opposition.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#Y00600"><p>I am talking through the Chair and I would not interrupt anybody, particularly those in Fine Gael.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#Y00700"><p>The Senator is being complimented.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#Y00800"><p>I have to be honest about it.  The argument was that nobody but the ex-leader of our country could look after the Brexit portfolio because he had the connections in Europe.  It was rehashed here on three or four occasions as if it had to be written in stone.  When he departed as leader, I waited for the Cabinet reshuffle after which I thought we would have a Brexit Minister, Deputy Enda Kenny.  Consequently, I could not believe it when I heard the news that instead, the Minister, Deputy Coveney, who the Leader knows well, would be the Minister with responsibility for issues with the North.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#Y00900"><p>I hate to interrupt the Senator but this has no relevance to the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#Y01000"><p>It is fully relevant.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#Y01100"><p>Unfortunately, the Senator's time is up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#Y01200"><p>I am finishing.  I am getting there.  If I had not been interrupted I would be long finished.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#Z00100"><p>I will take-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#Z00200"><p>No.  Please, Senator Feighan, you will be next.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#Z00300"><p>I am only at the-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#Z00400"><p>With respect, I must ask Senator Davitt to wind up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#Z00500"><p>I will just continue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#Z00600"><p>I cannot let him continue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#Z00700"><p>Deputy Simon Coveney is now dealing with Northern issues, which is an extremely important portfolio.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#Z00800"><p>He is the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#Z00900"><p>One of the most important issues is Brexit.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#Z01000"><p>Nothing to do with the Seanad.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#Z01100"><p>There was a reshuffle.  We have now appointed a new Minister of State with responsibility for European affairs.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#Z01200"><p>Senator-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#Z01300"><p>I am extremely surprised that we could not have made one for Brexit.  It was a no-brainer, and it is a missed opportunity.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#Z01400"><p>The Senator has gone one minute over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#Z01500"><p>I ask the Leader to go back to his party leader and discuss it post-haste.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#Z01600"><p>I listened to Senator Murnane O'Connor discussing the very emotive topic of health.  We all agree that we would want state-of-the-art facilities to deal with accidents in our own areas.  She is absolutely right to raise it in this forum.  I left my office in Roscommon town this morning at 10 o'clock and an ambulance passed me on the way to Athlone.  At Knockcroghery, I saw the ambulance pull in and I saw the air ambulance arriving.  This was another sign of success and a different approach to medicine.</p> <p>Six years ago, 5,000 or 10,000 people protested, with about 3,000 outside the gates here.  Prophets of doom were saying that people would die, that it was awful and that the hospital would close.  More than 500 people work in Roscommon hospital.  Not one person that I know of has died in the past five years and hundreds of lives have been saved.  The air ambulance and its paramedics have brought hospital accident and emergency services to the people.  I am not saying the same applies in Waterford.</p> <p>Sometimes - I saw it in Roscommon - people have used health and other such issues as a political football, which can be unhelpful.  There are people whom we trust and they should be the people who make those decisions.  It should not be politicians making such decisions.  It is wrong that politicians make life and death decisions.  In my area, the best thing was done six years ago for the patients in County Roscommon and further afield.  The proof is in the pudding.  However, unfortunately it got political because the national and local media did not want to hear the truth, and they still do not want to hear the truth.  We will always have discussions on health and sometimes it may not be the right forum, but the Senator was right to raise it here as an issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#Z01700"><p>The doctors are looking for it to be kept open.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#Z01800"><p>Sorry, Senator-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#Z01900"><p>I am so happy that hundreds of people are alive today in County Roscommon six years later.  We had an accident and emergency department that only had ten people using it a day and most of the people said that it was spiralling out of control.  Unfortunately, the experts and HIQA were not listened to and the politicians at the time used it as a political football.  All of that is in the past and we should highlight that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#Z02000"><p>Before I call the Leader to reply, it would be helpful for me to deal with Senator Ardagh's amendment, which called for a debate with the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, Deputy Fitzgerald, on the appointment of the former Attorney General to the Court of Appeal to be taken today.  I regret that I must rule the amendment out of order on the grounds that it requires a Minister to answer in this House for a matter in respect of which she has no current official responsibility.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#Z02100"><p>I join other Senators in expressing sympathy with a former Senator and the current Minister, Deputy Katherine Zappone, on the very sad passing of her wife, Dr. Ann Louise Gilligan.  The tribute Senator Ruane paid in writing to her is one we should read and reflect on.  I pay tribute to Ann Louise on a life well lived as a fearless campaigner, advocate and educator, and as somebody who believed in giving to society.  In her own life, she was an ambassador for all things that are good about Ireland in terms of the power of education, the importance of campaigning and the strength of love.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I pay tribute to her and sympathise with the Minister on her very sad loss.  We are with her in spirit and stand in support with her.  I thank Senators for their remarks on what was a very sad day last week for the Minister, Deputy Katherine Zappone, and the family of Ann Louise Gilligan.  All of us will, in our own way, pay tribute quietly to the Minister, Deputy Zappone, as well.</p><p>I thank Senators for their congratulations to the new Taoiseach, Cabinet, Attorney General and Ministers of State, including Deputy Kevin Boxer Moran.  Senators Ardagh, Boyhan, Conway-Walsh, Bacik, Gallagher, Craughwell and Colm Burke raised the matter of the appointment of the former Attorney General.  I begin by joining Senator Colm Burke in outlining that 16 of the 29 previous Attorneys General of various types and hues have been appointed to judicial positions either here at home or in the European courts.  It is a question of competency.  The Government's prerogative is to appoint judges.  It is important that we not rush to populism.  When I hear members of Fianna F&aacute;il in particular speaking about stroke politics and cronyism, I wonder whether they are the same ones who were silent when their own people were appointed by their party leader while he was a Minister.  I ask Senators to reflect on the number and type of people who were appointed to boards and other positions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.148" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#AA00300"><p>The Taoiseach stated that the correct procedure was followed, the T&aacute;naiste recommended Ms M&aacute;ire Whelan to the Cabinet as the stand-out person for the vacancy and the Judicial Appointments Advisory Board did not have a recommendation for the post, so the Government came to the decision to appoint someone.  I do not know whether Senator Ardagh has heard me, but I want her to understand what happened.  The correct procedure was followed.  In addition, the Taoiseach did not instruct or ask the President to expedite the appointment.  As the Senator knows well from her legal background, the President can and does appoint members of the Judiciary within days of their nominations.</p> <p>The T&aacute;naiste, as the Cathaoirleach ruled, is no longer the line Minister and, therefore, is not the appropriate Minister to attend the House.  I am happy to ask the Minister, Deputy Flanagan, to attend.  I submitted a request to him in advance of today's Order of Business in the belief that there might be an amendment to it.  I hope that he will be here on Thursday, if the House is agreeable.  It is important that we allow for due process.  If we have a discussion on the appointment of Ms Whelan in itself, then we will stray into matters that are not necessarily connected with the import of the decision.</p> <p>The Business Committee has left to decide the D&aacute;il's business and I am unsure as to whether it has returned yet.  The appointment will stand no matter what happens.  It is up to us to ensure that the judicial appointments Bill is fast-tracked and passed by the House.  I am told that the Minister for Justice and Equality is available to come to the House on Thursday.  That would be important.</p> <p>Senators Conway-Walsh, O'Reilly, Colm Burke, Butler and Bacik raised the issue of Finsbury Park, Grenfell Tower and Portugal, where there were tragic deaths of innocent people.  I join Senator Conway-Walsh in paying tribute to those who died and hoping that there will not be such a socio-economic divide in our country.  It cannot be allowed to happen.  The Senator was right to highlight the matter on the Order of Business.  Given what Senator O'Reilly said about the type of cladding used, there is a need for building and fire safety regulations to be monitored, inspected and, if necessary, changed.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I agree that it is a matter of absolute importance.  Where I disagree with the Senator is that I do not know if the local authorities have the competency or personnel to do this.  It may need a different approach, which I think we all agree should be taken.  We cannot allow a tragic consequence to happen in this country like happened in London last week.  The Minister for Housing, Planning, Community and Local Government, Deputy Eoghan Murphy, has met with the Dublin fire chief and will meet with all other fire chiefs in the coming weeks.  He has also asked the National Directorate of Fire Emergency Management to meet and to assess this country's readiness for fire emergencies.  In addition to this, each local authority has been asked to review and come back with their plans for their multi-storey social housing units.  This also requires local authorities to ensure that early warning systems and alarm detection procedures and systems are in place.  Through the Private Residential Tenancies Board private landlords and the management companies of private apartment complexes are also able to ensure that there is an answer to the question the Senator raises.  </p><p>Fire safety precautions and readiness are extremely important.  Whether we follow what happened in England or not, the Senators are absolutely correct that awareness be raised and also that the fine line between being ready and prepared on the one hand and ensuring such a catastrophe never happens on the other, be put in place.  I hope that all of those involved in the management of our property units will respond to the Minister because it is imperative that we do not allow what happened in England to happen here.  I will ask the Minister for Housing, Planning, Community and Local Government to come to the House to discuss this matter as a matter of urgency.  It is critical.  Irrespective of where we are from or who we represent, what happened last week is a tragedy.  We must stand with the people and ensure that the monument left there today is one that we never see in this country.  All of us as public representatives at local and national level must work with those charged with responsibility at both private and public level to ensure that there are no fire traps or death traps in either our social or our private housing units.  We are lucky perhaps that we do not have the same height of building but we do have apartment blocks and management companies in this country.  We must ensure that no short cuts have been taken and that there is a rigorous inspection of these premises and units.</p><p>Senators Higgins, Bacik, &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in, Byrne and Devine pointed out that today is World Refugee Day.  I accept that more needs to be done and that we must continue to be a place of welcome and refuge.  We cannot be seen to be a cold house or a cold place for people seeking refuge here.  This is where we as a nation must ensure that the good work being done today continues.  It is also important that we pay tribute on this World Refugee Day to our Defence Forces, who have rescued and saved so many refugees in the Mediterranean.  President Higgins today asked us to pause and pay tribute to 65 million refugees and to ensure that we leave no-one behind.  That is our task, irrespective of our ideology, governments or political parties.  As citizens and as people we must ensure that no-one is left behind.  We have a moral duty to do that.  I welcome Senator Byrne's comment about the University of Limerick as a sanctuary university, where 17 people will have the opportunity to be educated on scholarships.  </p><p>I have not read the remarks attributed to Councillor Keary-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#BB00200"><p>"A major drain on the State."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#BB00300"><p>The Leader to respond, without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#BB00400"><p>If I may continue?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#BB00500"><p>The Leader may.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#BB00600"><p>The councillor has apologised for his remarks.  I do not in any way condone any inflammatory, racist or intolerant remarks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#BB00700"><p>"Stick a chain on them."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#BB00800"><p>Please, Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#BB00900"><p>That is the reality of it.  In my party he would have been kicked out.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#BB01000"><p>The Senator is out of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#BB01100"><p>I am out order?  This joker down in Limerick is out of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#BB01200"><p>I have to keep order here.  The Leader is responding.  Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in can find another opportunity to do that.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I understand that the councillor has apologised for his remarks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#CC00200"><p>I have read his remarks and I do not believe he has apologised.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#CC00300"><p>Allow the Leader to continue, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#CC00400"><p>Sometimes it is good to listen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#CC00500"><p>With the greatest respect, I hope nobody is listening to this man.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#CC00600"><p>I will not tolerate further discussion of this issue on the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#CC00700"><p>Do we take racism seriously, or not?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#CC00800"><p>The Senator is out of order.  Allow the Leader to respond, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#CC00900"><p>As Leader of the Seanad I was happy to allow Senator Alice-Mary Higgins to explain the rationale behind her-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#CC01000"><p>I ask the Leader not to encourage further debate on the issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#CC01100"><p>I am responding to the question regarding the Special Joint Committee on the Eighth Amendment of the Constitution.  I am explaining to Senator Higgins why I am allowing for debate on the matter.  It is important that we have this debate in the House.</p> <p>Senator McFadden raised the important issue of mental health and the need for implementation of A Vision for Change, which is the framework and blueprint for building positive mental health across all communities, in particular youth mental health and specialist services for people with mental illness.  I wish the new Minister of State, Deputy Jim Daly, every success in his new role.  Senator Devine raised the issue of Linn Dara today as well.  I agree with the points made by Senators Devine and McFadden.  I will ask the Minister of State, Deputy Daly, to come to the House to discuss the specific procedures around admittance of people to hospital outside of working hours, as raised by Senator McFadden, and the matters raised by Senator Devine, which matters she has raised previously.  We are all agreed that mental health services have been the Cinderella of the health services for far too long.  There is need for a real debate on how we can implement A Vision for Change.  Money has been ring-fenced for this area.  There is increased funding in the mental health budget and it is important that this is felt on the ground.  </p> <p>Senator Gallagher raised the important issue of bowel cancer screening.  There is a critical advertisement being run on radio in this regard, which I heard this morning in my car on the drive to Dublin.  We must encourage people, particularly men, to engage with this service.  I am happy to invite the Minister of State to the House for that debate.  The Senator's point that bowel cancer screening should be extended to all groups is an important one.  </p> <p>Senator Boyhan spoke about Rebuilding Ireland, which is the bedrock of Government policy on housing.  I wish the Minister, Deputy Eoghan Murphy, and the Ministers of State, Deputy Damien English and Deputy John Paul Phelan, well in their new roles.  I will be happy to ask the Minister to come to the House for a debate on Rebuilding Ireland.  Each Minister will try to add his own stamp to the Department.  </p> <p>Senator Butler raised the issue of Irish beef.  I congratulate the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine, Deputy Creed, on his mission with Bord Bia to Washington DC yesterday and today where he had important engagements in the White House and with the US Department of Agriculture and Food.  We welcome the opening up of the US beef market to Irish beef.  Senator Butler raised the important point of beef prices being cut by the factories.  The European Commission commodity price dashboard shows Irish beef prices have risen by 4.1%.  There is no reason factories should be cutting the price at this time.  I will be happy to have the Minister, Deputy Creed, come to the House on his return from the US. </p> <p>Senators Murnane O'Connor, &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh and Feighan spoke of the tragic death of Mr. Thomas Power in Waterford.  I extend my sympathies to his family.  To be fair, the issue raised by Senator Murnane O'Connor in regard to the cardiac unit has been well promulgated by Senator Coffey when he spoke in this House on the Order of Business and in the past by other Members from the south east.  There has been a huge debate on the issue.  The Minister for Health, Deputy Harris, has engaged with various stakeholders in that regard.  I am happy to ask the Minister to come to the House again on that matter.  Again, I sympathise with the Power family on their tragic loss.</p> <p>Senators Reilly and Devine raised the issue of child adolescent mental health services and the lengthy waiting lists for assessments for a range of conditions.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Senator O'Reilly correctly raised the tremendous Enable Ireland facility in Cavan.  Senator Reilly is correct that we need a debate.  These children cannot be left in limbo.  All of us understand the frustration of families with children who have a disability, families of children with autism, ASD or special educational needs, and that they require urgent intervention.  As we emerge from recession, as a Government and as a country we need to ensure that the benefit of the recovering economy is felt by people who most need it; in this case as articulated by Senators O'Reilly and Devine.</p><p>Senator &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh raised the matter of Roinn na Gaeltachta and daoine na Gaeltachta.  D&eacute;anaim mo chomhghairdeachas leis an Aire St&aacute;it, Teachta Seosamh McHugh, ar an bpost.  What the Taoiseach has done is quite innovative regarding the Irish language.  He has appointed a Minister for Irish and Irish affairs to sit at Cabinet, which is important.  It is not just about the Gaeltacht, it is about c&uacute;rsa&iacute; Gaeilge.  I wish the Minister of State, Deputy Joe McHugh, well.  I agree with Senator &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh that the plan did not work, notwithstanding the tremendous work done by former Minister of State, Deputy Se&aacute;n Kyne - and I pay tribute to him for his work in the role of Minister of State with responsibility for Gaeltacht affairs and natural resources.  We now need to see a focus on people and on the importance of jobs, employment and the creation of small indigenous industries in Gaeltacht areas.  Attracting industry to locate there is important.  I would be happy to have the Minister come to the House in respect of the matter raised by Senator &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh.</p><p>Senator Mullen raised the issue of children who are born to parents who suffer from substance abuse.  It is a very important issue and I would be happy to have the Minister come to the House.  The Senator also asked about the Special Joint Committee on the Eighth Amendment of the Constitution.  There will be a meeting tomorrow about the committee.  Senator Mullen is correct in that all Members of both Houses of the Oireachtas must respect the work of the committee system within the Oireachtas and that we do not pre-empt or prejudge any committee's work, not least the committee on the eighth amendment of the Constitution.  I wish all members of the committee, myself included, every success in their work.  Whatever the outcome that is presented to the Government, and whatever Government decides, it is important.</p><p>The issue of pyrite was raised by Senator Mulherin.  The Senator has been strong in the House in her articulation around the need for action for the people of Mayo and Donegal who are affected.  We very much welcome the report.  The Minister of State, Deputy Kyne, is thankfully retaining that position from the point of view of the issue in the report and I am happy that he has committed to coming before the House on the matter.</p><p>Senator Davitt raised the issue of a Minister for Brexit.  I wish to pay tribute to Deputy Dara Murphy for his work as Minister of State with responsibility for European affairs.  He was a very powerful ambassador for our country.  I wish the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade, with special responsibility for Brexit, Deputy Coveney, and the Minister of State, Deputy Helen McEntee, every success in their new posts.</p><p>I am not sure which Minister's post he would like to have been given but I believe that our former Taoiseach, Deputy Enda Kenny, has served our country in outstanding ways in Europe in positioning us in the Brexit negotiations.  The proof is, as we have seen, in the position paper outlined.  The Brexit negotiations commenced yesterday.  It is going to be two years of endeavour and I hope we will see a positive outcome.  I thank Senator Davitt for raising the matter.</p><p>Senator Feighan touched on the issue of the air ambulance in Roscommon, which is an important outcome for the people of Roscommon.</p><p>The amendment to the Order of Business proposed by Senator Ardagh has been ruled out of order by the Leas-Chathaoirleach, and I am happy to accept that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.174" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#DD00200"><p>I would like to address that matter and the Leas-Chathaoirleach's refusal in ruling it out of order and the Leader's offer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#DD00300"><p>The Leader has responded.  I am afraid the Senator cannot raise it.  As she probably understands, the Minister-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#DD00400"><p>I would like to put it on record that it is absolutely outrageous that the T&aacute;naiste-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.177" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#DD00500"><p>The Ministers do not have constitutional responsibility to this House, it is to the D&aacute;il.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#DD00600"><p>-----who was the T&aacute;naiste last week and who is the T&aacute;naiste today, and who is the lady who drafted the memo in Cabinet last week-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.179" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#DD00700"><p>I have made a ruling for the current time, and that is it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#DD00800"><p>-----and who is still a member of the Cabinet today, cannot come to this House and address-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.181" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#DD00900"><p>With respect to the Senator she is showing disobedience, which is unlike her.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.182" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#DD01000"><p>-----the House to tell us exactly what happened regarding the appointment of M&aacute;ire Whelan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.183" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#DD01100"><p>With respect, my ruling stands.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.184" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#DD01200"><p>It is absolutely outrageous.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.185" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#DD01300"><p>The Senator is out of order, I am sorry.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.186" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.187" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#EE00100">Report of Committee on Procedure and Privileges on Standing Order 70A: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#EE00200"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That the Report of the Committee on Procedure and Privileges on the amendment of Standing Order 70A be adopted, laid before the House and printed.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.189" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.190" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#EE00400">Special Joint Committee on the Eighth Amendment of the Constitution: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.191" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#EE00500"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That the Order of the Seanad of 13th April, 2017, relating to the Special Joint Committee on the Eighth Amendment of the Constitution be amended in paragraph (c) - (i) by the substitution of '6 members of Seanad &Eacute;ireann' for '7 members of Seanad &Eacute;ireann'; and<br /><br />(ii) after 'Seanad &Eacute;ireann' by the insertion of the following:<blockquote>'and the provisions of Standing Order 81 shall not apply to the Committee'.&quot;</blockquote></blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.192" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#EE00600"><p>I move amendment No. 1:</p><blockquote>In paragraph (ii), to delete &quot;the provisions of Standing Order 81 shall not apply to the Committee&quot; and substitute &quot;the provisions of Standing Order 81(1) shall apply to the Committee save that only one member and no other member may act as a substitute for an absent member: Provided that the name of such substitute be notified in writing by the relevant member of the Committee to the Committee clerk before the first meeting of the Committee&quot;.</blockquote> <p>I thank the Leader for giving me the opportunity to put forward this amendment.  The situations we have heard of in recent weeks, for example, the incarceration of young girls who have suicidal thoughts and who have sought access to abortion has again underscored the fact that the situation in Ireland today is unacceptable and dangerous and that the eighth amendment to the Constitution casts a shadow over many generations of women and needs to be addressed urgently.  In respect of implementing the recommendations of the Citizens' Assembly in full, it is regrettable that the establishment of the committee has been delayed by measures designed to restrict the participation of certain Senators and parliamentarians in the process.</p><p>I note the motion before us today mentions six rather than seven Senators participating and that substitution has been blocked.  In regard to the clause on non-substitution, as this is a special committee, Members will not have a right, as they do in other committees, to attend and speak if they have a concern about or interest in the area.  The only way to participate is through formal attendance and only those designated members of the committee will be able in any way to contribute to this process.  Blocking substitution is very unusual.  The only precedent for it was the banking inquiry, which operated in a quasi-judicial way, making findings against individuals and institutions and which was in no way similar.  We need to move past a judicial and criminalising approach to this issue and to debate it fully as a social issue.  The committee on the Protection of Life During Pregnancy Bill 2013, chaired by the Leader of this House, is a more relevant precedent.  Substitution was allowed on that committee and it did not impede its working.</p><p>The ban on substitution is against the spirit of new politics because it creates great difficulty for Independent groupings and small parties which have found constructive ways to work together to maximise and share their contribution.  Those who know our group in this House know we always endeavour to work constructively and contribute.  It is regrettable that it is being blocked in this case.  It is also notable that those in the D&aacute;il and Seanad affected by the ban on substitution are women who have well-known records, a history of acting on this issue, and expertise.  These are people such as Senator Bacik, those in my group, those in the Green Party, Deputy Coppinger and others.  They have a commitment which extends far beyond the three months of this committee and spans three decades of advocacy and work on this issue.  It is very unfortunate they will not be able to contribute to the work of the committee, but I have no doubt they will find, and I will endeavour to find, other ways to contribute to this debate, which is a debate in wider society.</p><p>Beyond that issue, non-substitution is a regressive practice and a step backwards in respect of inclusivity and participation in this House.  It means that if a committee member has a family or health emergency, he or she cannot be substituted for.  It creates a dangerous dynamic where people might be asked to choose between a family responsibility or a health concern and being present for a vital division.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Alice-Mary Higgins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2480"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2480&amp;amp;pid=AliceMaryHiggins&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is an extraordinarily poor practice and, if it became more commonly used, could prevent those who have care responsibilities, health concerns or a disability being able to fully participate and put themselves forward on special committees in the same way because it creates an unnecessary and inappropriate tension.  It denies us in the House the full body of expertise we should have.  I have put forward a compromise amendment.  It is not the constructive proposal for working we had hoped for before where, for example, Senator Kelleher and I would have substituted for Senator Ruane.  It is a basic safeguard which proposes a single, named substitute.  Every member of the committee could designate a substitute so that if an emergency or other consideration stops them attending, they can be substituted.  I am asking for support for this amendment.  I have great confidence in Senator Ruane, who will represent the Civil Engagement group on the committee.  Senator Kelleher and I and all the rest of us will continue to contribute to the wider debate we were having in society on this issue.  The most crucial thing is that we have a referendum in the spring to repeal the eighth amendment and fully implement the recommendations of the Citizens' Assembly.  We will all be working in every way we can for this.  I urge the House to think carefully about setting a precedent for non-substitution.  It is a regressive step for the House.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.194" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#FF00200"><p>Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in will second the amendment.  He has five minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.195" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#FF00300"><p>I second the amendment proposed by Senator Higgins.</p> <p>This is an issue from which politicians - not in my party but others - have run away for many years.  It took more than 20 years for the Supreme Court judgment of 1992 to be enacted and legislated for.  That legislation almost brought down the Government.  It forced the resignation of a number of members of that Government and a new political party was formed as a result.  Senator Higgins has proposed a substitution facility whereby if somebody is not in a position to attend a committee hearing, somebody else can stand in in his or her place.  It seems to be perfectly reasonable to have quite a number of people involved in the process.  I agree with Senator Higgins that the formation of this committee leaves a lot to be desired.  At the very least we are now talking about the eighth amendment and the potential for a referendum.  It is quite remarkable that a committee dealing with this most sensitive of Irish political subjects would not allow a substitution mechanism.  It is rumoured that the Leader will be the Chairman of the committee.  We will see what happens tomorrow.  I put him on notice that my party will not support any outcome that goes any way short of full repeal of the eighth amendment.  I look forward to hearing other political parties' view on that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.196" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#FF00400"><p>Does Senator Buttimer wish to speak?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#FF00500"><p>The Committee on Procedure and Privileges has discussed this and I do not disagree with the broad thrust of what Senator Higgins has expressed.  It is a very bad precedent because it changes the process for committees of the Houses of the Oireachtas.  I do not understand why the D&aacute;il Business Committee is pursuing this.  The Seanad Committee on Procedure and Privileges agreed the motion because we want to have Seanad representation on the committee.  I have taken the view as Leader that to forgo Seanad representation is too much to ask the House.  The D&aacute;il Business Committee proceeded without Members of this House in the Committee on the Future of Healthcare and in the establishment of a housing committee.  I did not want to be party to that.  It is with reluctance that I move the motion because I agree with what Senator Higgins is trying to achieve.  As the Senator is aware, I have facilitated a number of meetings to try to bridge that gap unfortunately we could not get peace in the matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.198" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#FF00600"><p>I acknowledge that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.199" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#FF00700"><p>We got a change in representation of the Seanad as well.  Regardless of who chairs the committee, it is important its work is carried out in a manner that is open to all possibilities and outcomes.  It is a matter for the committee to decide upon itself and ultimately for the Oireachtas to decide on what the committee recommends.  We are also awaiting the report of the Citizens' Assembly which, when published, will allow for the committee to sit in public and do its work.  It is in the spirit of ensuring Seanad representation that we do not allow for a situation in which we are left behind or excluded that I propose this motion.  I accept there is disappointment with the outcome of the deliberations but it is important we have Senators at the table debating, negotiating and engaging.  It is in that spirit that I have proposed the motion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.200" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#FF00800"><p>Is the amendment being pressed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.201" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#FF00900"><p>I am pressing it.  I want to acknowledge-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.202" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1404" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#FF01000"><p>Is nobody else speaking on it?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.203" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#FF01100"><p>Nobody else has spoken.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.204" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#FF01200"><p>Nobody else has spoken.  They should be allowed to speak.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.205" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#FF01300"><p>Yes, go on.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.206" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#FF01400"><p>I came in in the middle of it.  It had gone back to the Leader.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.207" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#FF01500"><p>I wrapped up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.208" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#FF01600"><p>No one else has offered.  I will put the question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.209" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#FF01700"><p>Do Sinn F&eacute;in Senators want to speak?  Sinn F&eacute;in Senators had indicated they wanted to speak.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.210" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#FF01800"><p>They did not indicate to speak but if they want to speak, I will let them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.211" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#FF01900"><p>I stand on principle because Fianna F&aacute;il Senators will not speak at all.  We spent a long time, took it seriously and deliberated on it upside down and inside out.  It is an extremely important issue.  I apologise but we have decided not to support the amendment.  We will not support it because it will result in the dilution of the presence of a named individual, in this case a Senator.  I say well done for getting Senators involved in it in the first place.  We ask that someone takes complete and utter responsibility for the attendance and for listening to contributions and presentations and bringing it back to us as a political party.  As a nurse working in psychiatry for a long time, I have worked with women and girls who have been refused terminations requested as a result of fatal foetal abnormality.  I have watched the fallout and heartbreak of women being sent back from England because one happens to mention Ireland's laws do not permit it.  That sort of stuff has gone on.  Women and girls are ending up in psychiatric institutions because of it.  My heart goes out to them.  I wish I could be on that committee; I think most of us wish that.  The repealing of the eighth amendment is a fundamental change to our Constitution and its repeal, as well as the enactment of legislation, constitute a fundamental change to the rights of women in this country.  Regretfully, Sinn F&eacute;in cannot support Senator Higgins's amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.212" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#FF02000"><p>I do not know what type of point Senator Devine is trying to make.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.213" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#FF02100"><p>It is very simple.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.214" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#FF02200"><p>I sat on the council and my views on the eighth amendment are very clear.  My colleagues in Fianna F&aacute;il and I all have differing views.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.215" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#FF02300"><p>I am not talking about that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.216" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#FF02400"><p>To what was Senator Devine referring?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.217" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#FF02500"><p>Senator Ardagh picked it up wrong.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.218" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#FF02600"><p>What exactly is Senator Devine inferring?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.219" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#FF02700"><p>Senators should speak through the Chair.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.220" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#FF02800"><p>What was Senator Devine inferring when she said we were trying to slip away?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.221" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#FF02900"><p>Senator Ardagh should speak through the Chair.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.222" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#FF03000"><p>This has been going on all day for no reason.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.223" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#FF03100"><p>Members of my party all have different views.  We are a broad church and everyone is welcome to have whatever opinion they like.  Unfortunately we will not be supporting the amendment.  We will be supporting the Government on this amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.224" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#FF03200"><p>Are there any other contributors?  Senator Murnane O'Connor will have to resume her seat.  The rule is one contribution per group and Senator Ardagh has made the contribution on behalf of the Fianna F&aacute;il group.  Is the amendment being pressed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.225" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#FF03300"><p>Yes, and I would like to acknowledge that we sought to negotiate a compromise.  I appreciate the Leader's recognition that this is not a good practice.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Alice-Mary Higgins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2480"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2480&amp;amp;pid=AliceMaryHiggins&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I hope we will robustly oppose any further use of this non-substitution clause in future.  In that spirit, I am pressing the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.227" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.228" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Motion put and declared carried.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.229" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#GG00400">Inland Fisheries (Amendment) Bill 2017: Second Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.230" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That the Bill be now read a Second Time".</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.231" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#GG00600"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Se&aacute;n Kyne, to the House.  This debate is to adjourn no later than 7 p.m., with the contributions of group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes and those of all other Senators not to exceed five minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.232" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1314" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#GG00700"><p>I am very pleased to present the Bill for the consideration of the House.  Its purpose is to confer an explicit power on Inland Fisheries Ireland, IFI, to bring and prosecute summary proceedings for inland fisheries offences.  It achieves this by amending Part 4 of the Inland Fisheries Act 2010 by the insertion of a specific provision providing IFI with the power to bring and prosecute summary proceedings under the specified Acts.  It will ensure that IFI can fully enforce the Inland Fisheries Acts.  The Bill also makes some additional corrections to the Inland Fisheries Act 2010 to ensure that minor omissions in the Act which might impact on IFI's prosecution powers are fully resolved.</p> <p>I will set out some background information on the Bill.  IFI is the State agency responsible for the protection, conservation, development and promotion of Ireland's inland fisheries and sea-angling resources.  IFI was formed on 1 July 2010 following the amalgamation of the Central Fisheries Board and the seven regional fisheries boards into a single agency.  Ireland has over 74,000 km of rivers and streams and 128,000 ha of lakes, all of which fall under the jurisdiction of IFI.  IFI's jurisdiction also extends to the 12-mile limit around the coast.</p> <p>The Department of Communications, Climate Action and Environment received advice from the Office of the Attorney General in February 2017 to the effect that IFI does not have a power to bring prosecutions under the Inland Fisheries Acts.  It was advised that an explicit power to prosecute should be inserted into Part 4 of the 2010 Act as a matter of priority.  The impact of the advice is that until the Inland Fisheries Act 2010 is amended, prosecutions brought by IFI for which proceedings have been initiated cannot proceed.  There are approximately 150 cases which fall into this category.  Cases which have already been finally disposed of by the courts are not affected.  In light of the advice, the amendments to the Inland Fisheries Act 2010 are being pursued as a matter of priority.  The Bill has passed all five Stages in the D&aacute;il without amendment.</p> <p>The Bill is important because it impacts on the capacity of IFI to bring prosecutions and fully enforce the Inland Fisheries Acts.  IFI needs these powers to effectively conserve and protect Ireland's inland fisheries and sea-angling resources.  My intention is that amendments to the 2010 Act will be in place well before the expiry of the statutory six-month time limit for the initiation of proceedings following the date of the alleged offences.  As the six-month period expires in early August, it is imperative to finalise the Bill as soon as possible to ensure that anyone who committing an offence will still be liable to prosecution.  It is intended that there should be no period during which offences can be committed with impunity.  All correct provisions and offences of the Inland Fisheries Acts continue in full force and effect.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.233" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#GG00800"><p>I congratulate the Minister of State on his reappointment.  I am sure he is delighted.  It is nice to be reappointed to an office and he has retained his portfolio in the Department of Communications, Climate Action and Environment.  It is a happy day for him and his family and a great honour.  I know what it is like myself having had the personal experience of being reappointed in different Departments.  I wish the Minister of State well in his office.</p> <p>Fianna F&aacute;il supports the Bill in principle.  It is a crucial and urgent amendment to confer an explicit power on Inland Fisheries Ireland to bring and prosecute summary proceedings for inland fisheries offences.  IFI is the main body with responsibility for protecting Ireland's inland waterways and up to 12 nautical miles off the coast and the fish that inhabit them from illegal poaching or overfishing and other illegal activity.  Prosecution is one of the main deterrents to illegal fishing activities in the long term but as of now the IFI's power to prosecute is open to challenge.  This has been confirmed by the Office of the Attorney General which has asserted that the 2010 Act should be amended to more clearly state and affirm the powers of IFI to prosecute all summary offences.  Clearly, we urgently need to address this situation.</p> <p>The Minister of State knows that I have made a very strong issue of the treatment of fisheries in our area.  I welcome his officials here today.  We had a presentation from IFI in Buswell's Hotel and I have received other communications since then.  However, nothing has really come from the Minister of State's Department as such.  The general line has been that IFI was waiting for the Department to communicate with me in this particular regard.  I have a letter from Dr. Ciaran Byrne, the chief executive officer, dated 3 February 2017.  In the letter, he thanked me for taking the time to attend the briefing day for Oireachtas Members held on 25 January.  He states that on the points I raised, he prepared a note for the Department and understood that it would communicate with me on it shortly.  He states that as my point was raised at the briefing day, the Department was anxious to respond to me directly and says he would be happy to engage directly with me on this and any other matter once the Department had the chance to respond formally to my concerns.  He trusts that I find that satisfactory and again thanks me for taking the time out of my busy schedule to come across to the open day.</p> <p>Areas are not being treated equally.  In his script, the Minister of State made it clear that there is one organisation now which comprises what were the Central Fisheries Board and several regional boards.  That is so.  What has happened is that the Government has discriminated against the midlands fisheries group where a permit is required.  Anglers in the Shannon region must have a permit, which incurs a charge, to fish for trout, pike or to engage in coarse angling in the midlands fisheries group of controlled waters.  This area comprises the River Suck and its tributaries, Lough O'Flynn, Lough Acalla, Hollygrove Lake, Stonehams Lake, which adjoins our land at Castlecoote in Roscommon,  Lough Lung, and Blacks Lake, also in the townland of Castlecoote.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Terry Leyden:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=636"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=636&amp;amp;pid=TerryLeyden&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The restriction is there too.  The area also comprises the River Inny and tributaries, the River Brosna and tributaries, the Little Brosna River and tributaries and the Camlin River and tributaries.  In that regard, it means that a fisherman who comes from England will have to pay &euro;45 for an adult annual permit.  A senior citizen has to pay &euro;25.  A juvenile annual permit costs &euro;20.  An adult one-day permit costs &euro;20.  A juvenile one-day permit costs &euro;10.  A 21-day permit from the Midland Fisheries Group is &euro;25 and a family day ticket is &euro;20.</p><p>I will support the Bill today but I will do everything I can on this side of the House to prevent the passage of the Bill through Committee and Report Stages unless there is equity and fairness.  I appeal to my colleagues in Sinn F&eacute;in, who I think would be very much in favour of fairness in this regard.  How can the Minister of State discriminate against one area of Ireland and say a permit is required?  This affects us and the jobs and tourism in our area.  If the Minister of State wants to bring in charges, that is another issue which he will have to get through Government and the Oireachtas.  I am not advocating it because, as the song goes, all our rivers run free, and that is the feeling.  The trout fishers Bill was brought in and practically brought down a Government some years ago.  Some of the same people who opposed it at the time seemingly slipped this in with regard to the Shannon fisheries area.</p><p>I am glad to get an opportunity today to make a good point for the people in the constituency of Roscommon-Galway who are affected by this situation.  I appeal to all Members of this House to go along with me in this particular regard.  I am making a request of the Minister of State and the Minister for Communications, Climate Action and Environment, Deputy Naughten.  I am putting pressure on the Minister in particular.  He cannot allow this discrimination.  It is just not on.  One cannot justify it.  It is inequitable.  In fact, I would consider that someone could not be pursued for not having these permits because this does not apply to the Republic of Ireland but to a specific area only.</p><p>I cannot understand how the Minister of State has not reacted already.  He is in the job and we spoke about this in January.  I want a response from him.  I also want to say that, whatever action I take, I will do everything in my power to stop this Bill going through.  Let me be quite clear about it.  Unless the Minister of State brings around fairness and equity, I will filibuster on Committee Stage, Report Stage and every other Stage.  We accept this in principle.  However, as an elected representative from Roscommon to D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann 40 years ago last Friday, I for one could never stand by a discrimination against an area.  This is affecting tourism, business and promotion.  </p><p>How can we promote in Britain fishing in our area, where they will have to pay &euro;45, while they can go down to parts of County Longford and pay nothing to fish on the River Shannon?</p><p>I make the case to the Minister of State to go back to Government to say that this situation must be rectified.  I will go the whole way on this.  I will pursue this in my party.  We accept it in principle, but I will be lobbying at a parliamentary party level and every other level.  The situation is simple.  The same rules should be applied for all fishing in Ireland.  It is as simple as that.  I will accept that with a heart and a half.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.235" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#HH00200"><p>I congratulate the Minister of State on his new post.  We welcome the Bill and understand the purpose and need behind these changes in legislation.  This is about giving effective and legally sound powers to protect against the pollution of our environment.  Of course, it is something that we need to consider in general and not just for our inland waters.  We have to consider the effect of powers for all regulatory bodies, not just in respect of the environment but also, for instance, in respect of consumer protection and white collar crime, which has seen its weaknesses exposed recently.</p> <p>The action we are currently debating only came about after a serious pollutant entered the River Tolka and in excess of 5,000 fish were killed.  It was only when this occurred that questions were raised in regard to the powers of Inland Fisheries Ireland.  The powers of regulatory bodies need to be sufficient to prevent pollution of our environment.  This means that sanctions need to be high enough to deter and must also be high enough to match the damages caused.  Alongside this, enforcement needs to be strong enough to ensure we take on those who pollute our environment.</p> <p>Giving powers is only the first step.  Regulating bodies may have powers in legislation but they are not worth the paper they are written on if they are never enforced.  Giving proper, effective and strong functions and enforcement powers to regulators shows that we are taking the problems that are there seriously.  We cannot deny that the problems exist.  Globally, freshwater species alone declined by more than 81% since 1970.  Once our environment is polluted, it is inflicted on aquatic environments.  Once these species are gone, there is no return and there is no second chance.  Such a decline in the numbers of these species is clear evidence that there is something radically wrong.  Plans, consultations and discussions are not needed but action in legislation must be taken.  Years of neglect by successive Governments have allowed for environmental protection to be seen as a threat rather than a great opportunity.</p> <p>I acknowledge the ongoing work by angling clubs, farmers and volunteers in keeping many of our rivers, canals and lakes clean.  They have picked up the slack on many occasions when Government and local authorities failed.  This is often done at their own expense.  The question of who is responsible for the upkeep and maintenance of rivers is one that urgently needs to be addressed.  Why are so many of our rivers in private ownership and who benefits from them?  This needs to be examined.  The song lyrics that only our rivers run free belie the reality in terms of who owns our rivers, who benefits from them and who is affected by the negative externalities that come about.  I am talking about farmers in particular.  They have land behind rivers that is privately owned.  They have to stand back and watch while their lands are flooded and ruined.  This is their main factor of production but nothing is done about it because it is not possible to establish whether Inland Fisheries Ireland, the local authority or central government is responsible or exactly who is responsible.</p> <p>An audit needs to be an carried out urgently of the ownership of and responsibility for rivers and how we get the community to maximise the benefits of our rivers and our natural resources.  If I was not in this job and had the time - I intend to do it some day - I would do a proper investigation into the handover of our rivers, how they were kept in private ownership, how we as a State now have to pay for the upkeep of many of these rivers and how the benefits are kept within a very select few within this country.  I ask that this be tackled in the lifetime of the Government.  The Minister of State would certainly get our co-operation in doing it.  In the meantime, we need to protect our environment and rivers and to ensure that the community benefits from our natural resources. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.236" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#HH00300"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to this House and congratulate him on his very worthy appointment.  I am sure that he will do an excellent job.</p> <p>Today we are discussing legislation that is urgent in so many ways.  We saw that last February the then Attorney General wanted to promote the legislation due to an anomaly she saw in the previous Bill.  It is important that we move ahead, if we possibly can, and pass this legislation.  There are roughly 150 cases pending and waiting on this legislation to be amended.  That would be a positive step.  I hope we move that step forward this evening in order that the good work being done by Inland Fisheries Ireland can be delivered on the ground.  We must consider the work it does on the ground.  It has an important role in ensuring that our rivers are protected.  </p> <p>We have had interesting contributions here today.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Tim Lombard:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2466"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2466&amp;amp;pid=TimLombard&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Senator Leyden mentioned something I was not aware of and I am sure the Minister of State will respond.  It was a very interesting remark.  We have also heard about the issue of the actual ownership of the rivers themselves.  The ownership of rivers has been an issue that has been around for an awfully long time.  I refer to my previous role in the local authorities where a former county engineer informed Cork County Council that most rivers in County Cork were owned by landowners and that the maintenance of those rivers was their responsibility.  This was a huge burden on the landowners.  The Cork local authority took the opportunity to inform them that the maintenance was their job.  This created unfortunate division between the local authority and the landowners over the potential knock-on effect on the expense of this.  There are issues surrounding the management of rivers that need to be clarified so that we know exactly when, where and how we are going with these issues.</p><p>Today's piece of legislation is important.  It is important that this House move swiftly to ensure that we pass it so that the 150 cases that need to be looked at can be suitably addressed by the courts.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.238" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1380" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#JJ00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House and congratulate him on his re-appointment.  I wish him well for the years ahead.  I welcome this piece of legislation that is in effect closing a loophole that was left open when the other powers were transferred several years ago from the Central Fisheries Board to Inland Fisheries Ireland.  I welcome the addressing of the issue of prosecutions as outlined by the Minister of State in his speech.</p> <p>I have some questions for the Minister of State.  A number of years ago we banned draft netting and drift net fishing because of the amount of salmon stock.  The ban was meant to increase these stocks throughout the catchment areas.  Has this ban been as effective as was hoped?  I would also like to ask the Minister of State about the restocking of lakes.  I know that Inland Fisheries Ireland has a restocking programme in place but it has been brought to my attention that some lakes that were restocked in the past were not restocked this year.  Loch Lannagh outside Castlebar is one example.  What will be the case in the future?  Will there be a restocking programme on a rotational basis or what is the mechanism for this?</p> <p>I would also like to congratulate the staff in Inland Fisheries Ireland for their great work in maintaining the rivers and lakes throughout the country.  I also commend landowners on giving access to people to fish.  We have a great product here but more could be done to promote Irish angling in Europe in particular because there is a clientele there for angling.  We have great angling lakes and rivers and we could promote the whole area of our inland fisheries much more.  Every fish that is caught on a rod, whether it is a salmon or a trout or whatever, is worth much more to the local economy than just the value of the fish, when we consider restaurants, bars, bed and breakfasts and hotels.  This is an area then that we should give some thought to and promote.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.239" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#JJ00300"><p>If no other members are indicating to speak I will call on the Minister of State to conclude.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.240" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1314" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#JJ00400"><p>I thank all of the Senators who contributed to the debate today.  As I have already stated, without a specific provision in the 2010 Act Inland Fisheries Ireland is hampered in effectively conserving and protecting the inland fisheries and sea angling resources and in fully enforcing the Inland Fisheries Acts.  This and the timely enactment of the amendment Bill will ensure that there is no period during which offences can be committed with impunity.  I reiterate that all current provisions on offences in the Inland Fisheries Acts continue in full force and effect and the powers of fisheries officers remain.</p> <p>I thank Senator Leyden for his support, on this Stage at the very least, and for Fianna F&aacute;il support in the D&aacute;il in the passage of the Bill through its various Stages.  The Senator raises questions that he has raised in the past about specific areas in his own constituency.  I know that when he raised these previously at the IFI open day in Buswells Hotel, the Department asked IFI to respond and to set out the position on the midland permit to the Senator.  I understand that this was completed.  The Senator's office emailed the fisheries division and the division then responded by email.  The big difference is that the waters in question are owned by the ESB.  They are managed by IFI under agreement with the ESB.  Part of the arrangement is that the funding of permits goes to the IFI in respect of management.  This is a different scenario to what one would find on many other lakes that are fully under the control of the State.  I would be happy to have senior officials engage with the Senator on this and I hope that this issue will not delay the passage of this very important Bill.  Delay of this Bill, the Senator's very valid concerns notwithstanding, will undermine the protection of rivers and lakes all across the State.  It is important that we acknowledge that.</p> <p>The case raised by Senator Conway-Walsh was settled by the court.  I am happy to report that, in addition to costs, reparation was also imposed by the court and the total cost to the defendant was approximately &euro;37,000.  The ownership and title of rivers is obviously a matter of property.  In the context of updating the legislation covering inland fisheries, a detailed examination has been undertaken of titled rivers and rates payable.  This is a very comprehensive piece of work.  The Fisheries Act 1959 was itself a consolidation of Acts going back to the 1800s.  The formation of the State and all that went with that must also be taken into account so there is a lot of work going on at the moment.  This work is ongoing and will hopefully be brought to fruition in this D&aacute;il and Seanad term.  </p> <p>Senators Lombard and Conway raised the issue of the management of our rivers and streams.  Senator Lombard is right about the requirements.  There are differences depending on private fisheries.  No works can be done first of all without the consent of the local authorities.  Where local authorities apply to Inland Fisheries Ireland work can then be consented to.  One often gets the situation where county councils may decide very late in the day to clean a lake under a drainage scheme or under emergency works.  They have to go through the process, however, of applying to IFI.  I understand that there has never been a case where IFI has refused permission to a local authority to clean under a drainage or emergency scheme where funding might be provided.  There are plenty of examples of this around the country.  </p> <p>Senator Burke mentioned the draft net fishing ban.  The ban did not achieve what it was hoped it would achieve.  It did in the first year, when there was an upsurge of returning numbers, but it has not had the desired impact since then.  That is not to say that it has not worked because we do not know what situation we would be in today if this ban had not been imposed.  We would be in a worse situation than we are now.  There are a number of different theories as to what exactly has caused the decline in salmon stocks, be it global warming, large super trawlers scooping up all before them, or sea lice.  We cannot exactly say.  We do know that there is a reduction in numbers across the southern half of Europe in particular.  As one goes further up, to the North of Scotland and up towards Norway, the level of decline is less serious.  Clearly then the ban has not worked to the extent that we had hoped.  That said, stocks in some rivers have increased or stabilised.  In other areas, unfortunately, decline has continued.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Se&aacute;n Kyne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2343"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2343&amp;amp;pid=SeanKyne&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> On the issue of the development of our natural assets, resources and rivers, &euro;2 million was invested under the national strategy for angling development in 50 community lead projects.  There will be a roll-out of further projects this year.  I agree with Senator Paddy Burke on the valuable work of the staff of Inland Fisheries Ireland, IFI.  I commend IFI on its very important work.  Like all front-line staff, they are under pressure in terms of numbers and resources.  I have continually raised that matter with the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform to ensure we get adequate resources to meet the staff requirements and capital investment in equipment to carry out conservation work.  The Senator is correct that angling and angling tourism is a valuable resource to many parts of the country.  We are continuing to try to develop this sector and the national angling development fund will aid accessibility by the replacement of stiles and the improvement of walkways to allow lakes and rivers to become accessible.  This ongoing work is community led in conjunction with Inland Fisheries Ireland and I want to see continued promotion of it.</p><p>I thank the Senators for their support of the Bill.  I look forward to its timely passage through the Oireachtas.  Let me repeat that I will engage with Senator Leyden on the issues he has raised.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.242" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#KK00200"><p>Chairman, the fishing rights on the River Shannon are owned by the ESB, and the electricity board does not charge for fishing rights.  The argument put forward by the Minister of State is very weak and does not hold water.  I believe that agreement has lapsed.  Somebody has been misinformed on this issue.  I hope it is resolved because the Minister has the power to resolve it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.243" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#KK00300"><p>I congratulate Deputy Kyne on his appointment as Minister of State at the new Department of Rural and Community Development and the Department of Communications, Climate Action and Environment.  Well done.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.244" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.245" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#KK00500"><p>When is it proposed to take Committee Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.246" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#KK00600"><p>Next Tuesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.247" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Committee Stage ordered for Tuesday, 27 June 2017.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.248" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#KK00800"><p>I propose that we suspend until 5.50 p.m. as the Minister is not available until that time.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.249" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 5.45 p.m. and resumed at 5.50 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.250" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#LL00100">Offences against the State (Amendment) Act 1998: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.251" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#LL00200"><p>Motions Nos. 4 and 5 will be debated together.  I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy David Stanton, and on the day that it is in it I congratulate him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.252" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#LL00300"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That Seanad &Eacute;ireann resolves that sections 2 to 4, 6 to 12, 14 and 17 of the Offences against the State (Amendment) Act 1998 (No. 39 of 1998) shall continue in operation for the period beginning on 30 June 2017 and ending on 29 June 2018.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.253" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1277" speakername="David Stanton" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#LL00400"><p>The proposals before the House this evening seek the approval of the Seanad to continue in force provisions of the Offences against the State (Amendment) Act 1998 aimed at tackling terrorism and the Criminal Justice (Amendment) Act 2009 in respect of organised crime.  Given the nature of these provisions, the House has decided that they should be routinely reconsidered.  The Minister for Justice and Equality is required to lay reports before the Oireachtas on the use of the relevant provisions in tho two Acts and reports covering the 12 months up to 31 May 2017 were placed in the Library on 9 June.  I am conscious that there has been reflection previously on the traditionally brief nature of the reports placed before the Houses.  They have been traditionally brief in order to be focused clearly on what is required by the Act.  I am sure the Minister will be open to consider suggestions Members might make as to how the report might be enhanced.  I must caution, however, that there would be clear constraints on the detail of what might be included in the context of ensuring there would be no danger of prejudice to the investigation or prosecution of crime or to the security of the State.</p> <p>The Offences against the State (Amendment) Act 1998 was enacted in the aftermath of the atrocity at Omagh in August 1998.  That act of depravity was an affront to humanity and to democracy, and it lingers long in our memory.  A robust response to the paramilitary group who carried it out and to its like was essential and these Houses put in place the 1998 Act with that aim in mind.  The 1998 Act targeted the Northern Ireland-related terrorist threat.  Regrettably, there remains to this day a real and persistent threat from those same paramilitary groups who have set their face against peace on this island.  Despite the progress made over years with respect to peace, they continue to seek a return to a bloody past.  We must continue to bear down on them and to put them out of business.  That remains a priority for the Government.  Of course, many provisions of the Offences against the State Acts could have equal application to the international terrorist threat, one that we have seen recently in the shocking attacks in London, Manchester and elsewhere.  Sadly, the very nature of that threat means that all open democracies now face it.</p> <p>In the time available to the House this evening, I will not go through all of the relevant sections in detail.  The report laid before the House does so and it also details the instances in which the various sections in question have been used in the reporting period.  I note that sections 6, 12 and 17 were not used during the period.  It is the case that not every section is used every year.  However, that does not undermine the rationale for the powers being available as part of the legal framework for combating terrorist groups.  The report also notes the clear view of the Garda Commissioner that the Act continues to be an important tool in ongoing efforts in the fight against terrorism.  The Garda authorities have stated that the provisions of the Act are used regularly and that is evident from the report laid before the House.  On that basis, I must conclude that these provisions continue to be required and that they should remain in operation for a further 12 months.</p> <p>Section 8 of the Criminal Justice (Amendment) Act 2009 is also the subject of a motion before the House.  It refers to a small number of serious, organised crime offences that are set out in Part 7 of the Criminal Justice Act 2006.  Section 8 of the 2009 Act makes those offences scheduled offences for the purposes of Part V of the Offences Against the State Act 1939 - that is to say, trials for those offences are to be heard in the Special Criminal Court subject to the power of the Director of Public Prosecutions to direct that the offences be tried in the ordinary courts.  The purpose of this provision was to guard against the possibility of interference with jury trial by ruthless criminal gangs.  As the report laid before the House shows, no trials in respect of the offences have taken place in the Special Criminal Court.  That does not, to my mind, invalidate the reasoning for having this provision in place and available for use when appropriate, rather this, in fact, serves to highlight the very considered approach taken by the DPP in exercising discretion to direct that cases be tried in the ordinary courts where that is possible.  We greatly value trial by jury but we cannot ignore the threat posed to the criminal process by ruthless criminal gangs.  The view of the Garda Commissioner is set out clearly in the report and it is that this provision will be required for some time to come.</p> <p>The Minister for Justice and Equality must have full regard for the views of the Garda authorities.  Nobody here could be in any doubt about the pernicious nature of the activities of serious organised criminals in the State.  They have no regard for the damage they cause in communities.  They have nothing but disdain for the rule of law and they show no hesitation whatsoever in the use of extreme violence and murder in pursuit of their aims.  It is my view, therefore, that section 8 should be continued in operation for a further 12 months.  A Chathaoirligh, I commend these motions to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.254" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#LL00500"><p>I congratulate the Minister of State on his reappointment as Minister of State.  It was well earned.  As a neighbour in Cork, I am delighted for him.</p> <p>Fianna F&aacute;il will support the measures because they are necessary and because we still have the threat of dissident republicanism, organised crime and organised terror all over this island and throughout Europe.  It is important to note that we as an Oireachtas have an overriding safeguard on these measures because they have to come before us on an ongoing basis for renewal, and that is an important protection.</p> <p>There are criminal gangs in this city, which we all know about.  Every day we read in the evening newspapers about a murder, drug trafficking, firearms offences, explosives offences and kidnappings, among other crimes.  Ordinary citizens in the capital and throughout rural Ireland are living in fear of organised crime.</p> <p>Jury intimidation is a real threat.  There is no question or doubt about it.  I know all about it, living not too far from Limerick.  It would be very unfair for ordinary citizens who happen to be on the register of electors if they were to be selected for jury service in cases where there could be interference from organised crime and where they would be in fear of their lives.  It would be very difficult for them to dispense justice in a calm and reasonable way.  We have a safeguard in so far as the DPP can override that if he or she so wishes.</p> <p>Global terrorism is common and it is coming closer to home all the time.  We have seen the atrocities in London, Paris, Berlin, America, all over the Middle East and the rest of the world.  Society has to be able to stand up to it.  Organised terror always tests a civilised government or institution because it will keep making it essential for the state to protect itself.  There is always a fine line between the protection of the state and the rights of the individual.  There is no shortage of people in this country or elsewhere who will make a stand for civil liberties.  It is good that happens, but the greatest civil liberty of all is life.  I am sure the Minister of State would agree.</p> <p>I ask anyone to point to cases where the Acts before us have been counterproductive or where they should not have been introduced.  If people have any doubts about that they should ask the relations of Veronica Guerin or Jerry McCabe.  They will tell us in a resounding manner what they would think of that.  Unfortunately, there is still a minority in this country who think, as Deputy Jim O'Callaghan said in the D&aacute;il, that they can bomb their way into the political world they desire.  There are very few of them left.  We have seen that there are other ways to make progress.  That is evident in our own country when one looks at the example of people such as John Hume, Seamus Mallon, David Trimble and also Sinn Fein when it came into the peace process.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Ned O'Sullivan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2233"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2233&amp;amp;pid=NedOSullivan&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->There will always be the right to protest, the man with the megaphone who is entitled to go out, once he behaves reasonably, to get his message across to the people, but that kind of violence and intimidation has no place in a proper society.</p><p>I am old enough to remember the days when a very young Minister, a neighbour of mine in Limerick, Dessie O'Malley, as Minister for Justice had to introduce a special powers Act in the early 1970s because of the atrocities by so called republicans in the North and in the South.  He and his late wife were verbally and physically abused.  He was only a gars&uacute;n, a young man in government, but he did not flinch.  My near neighbour, Gerard Collins, was a Minister for Justice and had to live with round the clock protection from these individuals, but he did not flinch.  Paddy Cooney of the Minister of State's party did not flinch.  We must never flinch and must be prepared to take on these measures.  It is regrettable that the rights of an individual may be straitened or limited in some way, but for the greater good of society, my party will be four-square behind the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.256" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#MM00200"><p>I echo Senator O'Sullivan's congratulations to the Minister of State on his reappointment.  The continuing spate of gang related murders in Dublin and the fear within communities most directly affected by the activities of violent organised criminals requires a sustained and focused response.  Sinn F&eacute;in stands 100% with citizens, Garda and the courts against the unprecedented threat of organised crime.</p><p>To confront this threat properly and the wider corrosive impact it is having on our society, the Garda and the criminal justice system require the tools to do their job effectively.  In this regard, a comprehensive review of the Offences Against the State legislation in advance of its renewal next year is required.  It should focus on how to modernise the criminal justice system to make it responsive to the needs of Ireland in 2017.  Sinn F&eacute;in believes we need new legislation repealing the outdated emergency Acts currently in place and replacing them with strengthened legislation providing for new courts to deal with these cases.  The Garda and the criminal justice system need to be equipped to target organised crime bosses, their operations and their assets effectively and relentlessly.  Sophisticated, organised, well-resourced and murderous threats to citizens require a focused and rigorous response.  Any strategy to counter the threat posed by crime gangs with a huge international reach needs to be intelligent and multi-layered.</p><p>One of those layers must be at community level.  We need targeted and substantial investment in community development, education and employment, particularly in areas where organised crime gangs are recruiting members and where their malign influence is having a devastating effect on social cohesion.  A level of investment in local community policing greater than anything we have witnessed so far is required.  This must include an end to the reckless and irresponsible policy of closing Garda stations.</p><p>Those in the upper echelons of the crime syndicates are well known to the authorities and are deploying the huge resources at their disposal to avoid prosecution.  This requires the State to prioritise adequately resourced intelligence gathering and intelligence-led operations against key criminal organisations.  It also requires full co-operation between the Garda and the police services abroad, especially in countries where crime syndicates directing organised crime in Ireland are based.  The Garda must have the ability to respond rapidly to violent incidents and threats and to deploy highly trained armed units.</p><p>We also need the courts to be resourced in order that they can expedite criminal trials effectively and demonstrate that justice can be delivered fairly and swiftly.  We need to examine whether we need special prosecutors specifically dealing with the new threat of organised crime.  While always supporting, defending and promoting the judicial norm of the right to a jury trial, only in very special circumstances should we deviate from this to protect the judicial process.  Currently, hearings in the family court are held <i>in camera</i>while the drug treatment court is a specialised court operating within the legal system.  Sinn F&eacute;in's position on the use of special courts in dealing with organised crime has been seriously misrepresented by our political opponents and elements of the media.  The Garda and the courts are facing 21st century challenges with 20th century legislation.  This needs to change.  The current outdated criminal justice system does not act as a deterrent to organised crime.  It is in fact exploited by organised criminals.  The Special Criminal Court was first established under the Offences Against State Act 1939 during the Second World War to counter what the Government at the time claimed was a threat to the State's neutrality from the IRA.  Its current incarnation dates from May 1972 following Bloody Sunday in Derry and the escalating political conflict in the North.  The Offences against the State (Amendment) Act 1998 and the Special Criminal Court are ineffective relics of a conflict era which have failed to deal with the new threats posed by organised crime in the here and now.  Under the terms of the Good Friday Agreement, the Irish and British Governments have a responsibility to work towards the normalisation of policing and security matters.  That means ending the state of emergency under which the Offences against the State (Amendment) Act 1998 operates.  An academic debate about the merits or otherwise of the Special Criminal Court during the political conflict will not make communities in 2017 any safer in the face of organised crime.  This needs to be our focus now.</p><p>The current threat to the administration of justice, including jury intimidation, emanates from the rise of ruthless organised criminal gangs principally involved in drug related and violent crime.  Sinn F&eacute;in recognises that there are certain criminal cases which are more difficult to prosecute given the nature of organised crime today.  The opportunity for well-organised and well-funded criminal enterprises to influence juries, tamper with evidence or intimidate witnesses is greater than in most criminal cases.  Therefore, Sinn F&eacute;in does not oppose special courts to deal with the very specific circumstances of violent, organised criminal gangs which present serious threats to the security of the State and communities when the ordinary courts are prevented from securing the effective administration of justice.  The Constitution provides for this.  The objective is to minimise the capacity for those on trial to interfere with or influence the outcome of such cases by engaging in jury or witness intimidation.  Sinn F&eacute;in has also called for a proper examination of the option of juror anonymity and other special arrangements to protect those involved in court cases dealing with organised crime.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.257" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#MM00300"><p>I join Senators in congratulating the Minister of State on his reappointment.  It is obviously a great relief to him to continue the good work he is doing.  It is also a great relief to many of us here who have a deep interest in the Department of Justice and Equality because he has been doing phenomenal work in that area.  Unfortunately, 12 months is not enough and a significant portion of that involves getting to know the structures, the system and reading into the briefs and so forth.  I look forward to substantial progress in the Department as I know it is about to happen.  I wish him well.  I think I speak for all my colleagues in saying we will co-operate with him in any legislation he feels is necessary to deal with issues such as direct provision and the migrant crisis.</p> <p>This is this third or fourth year in which I have supported the provisions of the Offences against the State (Amendment) Act 1998.  I do so against the backdrop of what is happening in London almost weekly.  There is a new type of terrorism, and unfortunately this country has had its fair share of activities that were unbecoming.  The provisions of this Act are necessary.  It is unfortunate, as previous speakers have said, that it is necessary, but I commend the Taoiseach, Deputy Varadkar, on initiating a COBRA style emergency response Cabinet committee to examine the threats posed in this country and how we would react to such threats.  This country, North and South, has experience of terrorism and we have to be ready for the new type of terrorism.  If we need to strengthen the provisions of the 1998 Act, so be it.  We are better off being prepared than not.  I support this provision and recognise the unfortunate necessity for it.  I thank colleagues for supporting it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.258" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1277" speakername="David Stanton" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#MM00400"><p>I am grateful to the House for its consideration of these two motions this evening and thank Members for their contributions.  Naturally, I welcome the support expressed for continuing these provisions in force.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy David Stanton:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1053"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1053&amp;amp;pid=DavidStanton&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=20"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I appreciate the shared commitment that exists in the House to ensure that a robust legal framework is in place for the Garda and courts to deal with the most serious of offences that may threaten the State and the operation of the criminal justice system.  As we know, the Garda deploys very considerable operational resources to tackle terrorism and serious organised crime in the State.  We, as legislators, must provide it with the necessary means in law to do so.</p><p>I am sure we all wish the circumstances were otherwise and laws such as these were not needed.  However, the sad reality is that until conditions allow, these provisions are a necessary addition to the general criminal law.  I again commend the motion to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.260" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#NN00200"><p>Is the motion agreed to?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.261" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#NN00250"><p>It is not agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.262" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.263" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#NN00400">Criminal Justice (Amendment) Act 2009: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.264" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#NN00500"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That Seanad &Eacute;ireann resolves that section 8 of the Criminal Justice (Amendment) Act 2009 (No. 32 of 2009) shall continue in operation for the period beginning on 30 June 2017 and ending on 29 June 2018.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.265/1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#NN00700"><p>Question put:</p><p>The Seanad divided: T, 20; Nl, 5.</p><br/><br/><p>Tellers: T, Senators Michelle Mulherin and John O'Mahony; Nl, Senators Mire Devine and Niall  Donnghaile.</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.265/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2017-06-20" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#NN00700">
            <divisioncount ayes="20" noes="5" abstain="0" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" vote="aye">Victor Boyhan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" vote="aye">Colm Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1380" vote="aye">Paddy Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1423" vote="aye">Ray Butler</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" vote="aye">Jerry Buttimer</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" vote="aye">Maria Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" vote="aye">Martin Conway</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" vote="aye">Frank Feighan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1415" vote="aye">Maura Hopkins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" vote="aye">Gerry Horkan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" vote="aye">Tim Lombard</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" vote="aye">Michelle Mulherin</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" vote="aye">R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1374" vote="aye">Kieran O'Donnell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" vote="aye">John O'Mahony</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" vote="aye">Joe O'Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1385" vote="aye">Grace O'Sullivan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" vote="aye">Ned O'Sullivan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1431" vote="aye">P&aacute;draig &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1399" vote="aye">Neale Richmond</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" vote="no">Rose Conway Walsh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" vote="no">Maire Devine</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" vote="no">Paul Gavan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" vote="no">P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" vote="no">Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="abstain">
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.265/3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#NN00700"><p>Question declared carried.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.266" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#NN00800"><p>When is it proposed to sit again?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.267" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017062000002#NN00850"><p>At 10.30 a.m. tomorrow.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-06-20a.268" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>The Seanad adjourned at 6.27 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Wednesday, 21 June 2017.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>