<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.2" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00"><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 14:30</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00"><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.4" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00"><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.5" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Colm Burke that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:<blockquote><br />The need for the Minister for Education and Skills to provide the funding for the construction of a general purpose hall in Scoil Íosagáin, Farranree, County Cork, in accordance with the planning permission granted for same on 21 April 2011.</blockquote>I have also received notice from Senator Trevor Ó Clochartaigh of the following matter:<blockquote>Go dtabharfaidh an tAire Iompar, Turasóireachta agus Spóirt soiléiriú faoin tacaíocht atá dhá dheimhniú ag Fáilte Éireann d'fhorbairt ionad mínithe ag Teach an Phiarsaigh, Ros Muc, Contae na Gaillimhe agus má tá on ionad le bheith oscailte in am do chomórach déad bliain Eirí Amach na Cásca i 2016.</blockquote>I regard the matter raised by Senator Burke as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment and it will be taken on the conclusion of business.  I regret I have to rule out of order the matter raised by Senator Ó Clochartaigh as the Minister has no official responsibility in the matter.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.7" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000003#B00100">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.8" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000003#B00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, motion regarding proposal for a regulation of the European Parliament and of the Council amending Council Regulation No. 1346/2000 on insolvency proceedings, to be referred to the committee, without debate, at the conclusion of the Order of Business; No. 2, motion regarding Teagasc pig research, to be taken at the conclusion of No. 1, without debate; No. 3, Finance Bill 2012 - Second Stage, to be taken at the conclusion of No. 2 and to conclude not later than 6.30 p.m., with the contributions of group spokespersons not to exceed ten minutes and those of all other Senators not to exceed six minutes and the Minister to be called on to reply not later than 6.20 p.m.; and No. 30, Private Members' business, motion No. 10, to be taken at 6.30 p.m. and conclude not later than 8.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000003#B00300"><p>We will not oppose the Order the Business.  I wish to raise two issues.  I understand the Minister will be present for the debate on the Finance Bill and as there are very important measures in that Bill which all of us wish to discuss I do not want to use up the time.  Notwithstanding that, it is important that the Minister come to the House to speak specifically on the implications of the deal in Cyprus which is worrying and sets a very dangerous precedent.  One wonders about the talk of Labour's way or Frankfurt's way historically, when under the chairmanship of the Labour Party-Fine Gael Government we were happy for a European deal to be done which does not even burn bondholders, it burns depositors.  What are the implications for Irish depositors in the future if this is the case?</p> <p>This sets a precedent for Europe.  What are the implications for the Italians, the Spanish and the Portuguese?  What we have now is a further ramping up of the eurozone crisis in which there are implications for Russian investors and Cypriots are having to look east rather than west for a solution.  Surely, that is not something we want set as a precedent during our Presidency of the EU.  It is more akin to the works of Chavez, the Argentinians or other default nations than those of this country.</p><p>Another dangerous precedent being set is that under the Irish Presidency, there has been an insistence in these talks that corporation tax be increased from 10% to 12.5%.  What are the implications of that for Ireland where the corporation tax is supposed to be ring-fenced?  Can we have some clarity on these issues?  A very concerning impression has been created about the eurozone crisis following a botched Cypriot deal which had more to do with placating the election-focused Angela Merkel than on finding an overall solution to the banking troubles of the European Union.</p><p>I ask that the Minister for Health be made available to the House at the earliest possible juncture.  In the north west we have seen over the last week a senior consultant dermatologist break ranks to admit that he is dealing with waiting lists under which appointments for routine matters cannot be scheduled within three years in one instance and five years in Donegal.  This is unacceptable at a time when moneys are supposed to have been made available to provide for consultants.  The rebalancing exercise to help hospitals to break even towards the end of last year saw some moneys taken from larger hospitals and given to smaller ones.  In Castlebar in the constituency of the Taoiseach and the Cathaoirleach, €10 million was provided.  Among five hospitals in the north west this issue is at a critical juncture.  The consultant in question has said that basic referrals from GPs and the prioritisation of same are now a lottery.  I ask the Minister for Health to look to the north west and the financing of these hospitals where critical appointments to consultant posts for acute services have not been made.  A consultant is now coming out to admit that the service is unsafe and cannot be managed because he will not be given the necessary resources.  This is a very important issue and we will revisit it in the coming days if there is no response.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000004#C00200"><p>The Minister for Finance will come to the House this afternoon on Second Stage of the Finance Bill.  Colleagues will raise the very worrying situation in Cyprus.  The decision by the Cypriot Parliament sets down a marker that the people of Cyprus will not stand for the levy on depositors which was proposed.  Senator MacSharry has placed undue emphasis on the Government.  While it chairs the European Presidency, the Dutch finance Minister chairs the eurozone group of finance Ministers.  I agree with Senator MacSharry, however, that a large part of the impetus for this particular deal and the levy on depositors originates in the concerns of the German electorate and Chancellor Angela Merkel's concerns about the forthcoming German election.  It is the wrong way to plan any resolution to the eurozone crisis.  Clearly, the deal must be renegotiated and better terms offered to Cyprus.  The Cypriot finance Minister has travelled to Russia and there is a lack of clarity about the extent of investment from Russian depositors.  Very different reports have emerged ranging from 20% to 50%.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000004#C00300"><p>Less than 18%.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000004#C00400"><p>Senator Norris says it is less than 18% which is what I had heard too, contrary to reports which suggest that half of deposits were from Russian investors.  In fact, it is less than 20%.  In any case, the idea of a levy on depositors was a step too far and the risk of contagion too great.  I hope we will see a renegotiation of the deal.</p><p>I welcome the publication yesterday of a Bill to reform the courts by the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Alan Shatter.  It aims to provide for greater transparency in the way family law cases are decided.  There has been far too much anecdotal evidence and speculation on the outcomes of family law cases.  It will be useful to see some pattern or statistics on the outcomes of family law cases while preserving the anonymities of the parties.</p> <p>I also welcome the publication yesterday of the Courts Bill by the Minister for Justice, Equality and Defence, Deputy Alan Shatter.  This aims to provide for greater transparency in the way in which family cases are decided in the courts.  There has been far too much anecdotal evidence and speculation about the outcomes of decisions in family law cases.  While preserving the anonymity of parties to family law cases, it will be useful for us to see at least some pattern or statistics on the outcomes of these cases.</p><p>I will be asking for permission to publish a Civil Registration (Marriage Equality) Bill that I launched yesterday in Ashbourne in County Meath with Counsellor Eoin Holmes, the Labour Party candidate for the by-election.  We would like to see that Bill on the Seanad Order Paper.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1169" speakername="Mary Ann O'Brien" time="14:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000005#D00200"><p>The death of our town centres is a continuing nightmare and it is happening before our eyes.  Last week I spoke about retailers who represent 90,000 jobs in 4,000 family-run businesses.  There are inconsistencies around the country in local authority business rates, parking rates, parking fines and the threat of clamping in town centres.  This poses a real problem for these businesses because consumers drive to large out-of-town shopping malls where they can park for free and shop in giant multinational stores.  After five austerity budgets our businesses are under threat.  Will the Senators here today who come from different parts of the country think about their local authorities and come up with some solutions to create consistency, such as guidelines, free parking days, or a levy on parking in the out-of-town shopping malls.</p><p>I use the American word 'mall' because this trend started in America.  Almost all of the Senators have visited America; they have certainly visited England and have seen the death of town centres and high streets there.  That is what we are presiding over here.  Most of the Senators will hopefully visit some part of Ireland over the Easter holiday.  I was in Claremorris over the weekend, and drove through Roscommon.  Our town centres are dying.  I would like the Leader to include this subject in our upcoming debate on action for jobs and advise us when that will happen.  Will he also advise us which Minister is responsible for this problem?  Is it the Minister with responsibility for tourism?  What will tourists see in Ireland if there are no town centres left?  Will they see shopping malls outside towns and towns with tumbleweed rolling up and down the street and a few charity shops and bookies' premises?  That is all that will be left in town centres but people have to pay to park there and place their bets.  Should we invite in the Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government, Deputy Hogan, or the Taoiseach?  That may sound over-dramatic but these towns are the life and breath of Ireland. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="14:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000005#D00300"><p>As an honorary Cypriot I send a message of praise, congratulations and support to the courageous people of Cyprus.  Brave little Cyprus, small as it is, is unique in standing up to the thugs and bully boys of the Eurocracy.  We lay down and let them bulldoze all over us.  Not one member of the Cypriot Parliament voted for this disgraceful thing.  Our abolitionist Taoiseach, Deputy Enda Kenny, could not wait to get out and say that this was good for Europe, good for Cyprus, good for all of us.</p> <p>That is rubbish.  It is rotten and the morons in Europe do not have the wit to realise they have no strategy.  They stagger from crisis to crisis, in dribs and drabs.  They are responsible for the crisis in Cyprus because what they did to Greece, at the behest of those involved in international finance, triggered the crisis in Cyprus.  We should address this issue with honesty.  I could not believe my ears when I heard the Minister of State, Deputy Lucinda Creighton, on the wireless last night.  She had the sheer effrontery to say the bank guarantee in Ireland had been introduced to protect small investors.  That is an insult to people here and it is an outrage to have it said by a responsible person.  We were told by the European Union, the IMF and the ECB that we could not name the bondholders, but I am glad I did so in this House.  We certainly could not burn them because they were protected.  In the same breath we were told the investors, the people who had put their savings into the bank, who were not gamblers, were supposed to be protected even more.  Of course, the contagion will spread all over Europe.  The penny still has not dropped.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000006#E00200"><p>Is the Senator looking for a debate on the issue?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000006#E00300"><p>Yes, I am.  The system has cracked from top to bottom.  Five years ago - please God someone will start to listen now - I started saying this and will now put it as simply as I can.  The mistake being made is that all over Europe half-baked politicians, analysts and economists are saying we must preserve the system.  Good governance starts with the welfare of the people and one then adjusts the system to the requirements-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000006#E00400"><p>Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000006#E00500"><p>Will he accept that in raiding the National Pensions Reserve Fund, through the pension levy and the property tax they have their fingers in our pockets, just as they have in Cyprus?  Do Members remember the advertisement in which someone was pickpocketing------</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000006#E00600"><p>The Senator is way over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000006#E00700"><p>That is what they are doing.  We lay down, but thank God for the Cypriots.  They are courageous and a great little people and I am proud to have a house in that country.  We have one person in this country of whom we can be proud, Mrs. Mary Robinson, in terms of what she has been elected to do.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1124" speakername="Michael Comiskey" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000006#E01000"><p>I welcome the news about the CAP reform deal agreed last night.  It is good news for all farmers.  It has been in progress for two years or more and I congratulate the Minister on it.  There will be a redistribution of funds from farmers in receipt of very high payments to those with lower payments.  This is welcome because we all know farmers who are struggling as in recent years they have been in receipt of low or no payments.  I also welcome the news for younger farmers who will be able to receive a top-up payment.  That will encourage more of the young people in agri-colleges to enter the business of farming.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000006#E01100"><p>Like previous speakers, I welcome the news about the CAP deal entered into by the Minister, Deputy Simon Coveney, whom I congratulate, although the CAP budget is to be reduced.  It is the first time that the budget has been reduced.  Having said that, I am concerned about the divergent statements on what the new CAP proposals will mean from the president of the IFA, Mr. John Bryan, and the Minister.  If my colleague, Senator Michael Comiskey, is correct, I welcome the redistribution of CAP funding to prevent the continuation of the <i>status quo</i>, whereby 2,000 farmers receive the same amount of money as 52,000 others on the lowest payments.</p> <p>There are deep concerns about how the flexibility issue will be dealt with within this country.  I, therefore, call on the Minister to come to the House for a debate on what has been agreed to date.  There are mixed messages coming from the farming organisations and, contrary to what my learned colleague, Senator Michael Comiskey, said, Macra na Feirme representatives stated earlier that they were concerned about the way they might benefit from the new deal.  The devil is in the detail, but it is an important day for Ireland.  The future of Irish farming is at stake and an urgent debate is warranted sooner rather than later.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1144" speakername="Jimmy Harte" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000007#F00200"><p>I welcome Senator Mary Ann O'Brien's contribution and fully support her call for a debate on the death of town centres.  I am sure everyone has noticed how they are dying.  I have a business in Letterkenny and in the past six or seven years many shops have closed.  Car parking has become expensive on main streets, whereas free parking is available outside shopping centres.  Multinationals which benefited from lax planning by previous Administrations that decided to expand towns the wrong way and destroyed town centres by granting planning permission to multinationals to set up on the outskirts of towns have a role to play.  Those that set up in town centres were beneficial.  We should have a special debate on how we can address the death of town centres.  Every Member knows main streets are being populated by bookmakers and businesses that close on Friday evening and do not open until Monday morning, which does not benefit tourism.  I encourage shopkeepers to put signs outside their premises written in both Irish and English.  I have done this and it has proved to be an attraction, as it implies there is a different culture and the main street is not the same as Main Street, Manchester.  We should also debate how rates are worked out.  They should be to the benefit of a business rather than to its detriment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000007#F00300"><p>I welcome the meeting between President Obama and the Taoiseach.  In addition to maintaining warm relations between Ireland and the United States, some serious business was carried out.  Yesterday's international aircraft order was the largest in history.  The Ryanair model of doing business is based on that of Southwest Airlines.  President Obama will be most welcome to Ireland next summer.  Some of those involved in the media seem to think Fermanagh is not in Ireland, but it is.  I hope the free trade project between the Taoiseach, the President of Europe, and the US President will not be slowed by bureaucrats.</p><p>I support Senator David Norris's comments on the Cypriot crisis.  Will the Leader bring up with the Minister for Finance - we may do so ourselves later - the issue of deposit insurance?  Professor Christopher Pissarides, the Nobel Prize winner for economics in 2010, who has addressed the House asked a number of relevant questions on &quot;Bloomberg Businessweek&quot;.  If deposits of less than €100,000 were insured, what happened to that insurance?  How could the Eurogroup agree to tax deposits as small as €1?  What is the meaning of deposit insurance in the eurozone?  Megan Greene who attended a major international conference on finance in Ireland last year and whom I introduced to the Minister for Finance stated, &quot;The Cyprus bailout deal makes a mockery of deposit insurance in Europe.  This doesn't bode well for the credibility of a European Union-wide deposit guarantee, one of the basic tenets of a banking union.&quot;  Will the Leader stress to the Minister the importance of deposit insurance and the need to call it in as soon as possible?</p> <p>Had that been done, the present crisis might not have occurred.  There is deposit insurance but what has happened to it?  Is it the umbrella that does not work when it is raining?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" speakername="Eamonn Coghlan" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000008#G00200"><p>This year's St. Patrick's Day celebrations have come and gone.  I was proud of the images of Ireland beamed across the world, as well as seeing many iconic buildings throughout the world, including the White House, being lit up in green.  It was a marketer's dream to promote such a positive image of Ireland.</p><p>St. Patrick's Day this year was also a great celebration for mná na hÉireann.  We already have had Katie Taylor and Fionnuala Britton being wonderful in winning Olympic gold medals and European championships.  The ladies rugby team on St. Patrick's Day provided a wonderful image for women's sport in Ireland.  I congratulate the Irish women's rugby team on their grand slam win.  It was not until they defeated England for the first time that they came into the wider public domain.  I was pleased RTE decided to broadcast the game against Italy live.  The women's rugby team outstripped the men's rugby team, if one will excuse the pun.</p><p>The first Irish rugby team to win a grand slam was captained by Karl Mullen and the second by Brian O'Driscoll.  It was mine and Senator Paul Coghlan's namesake, Fiona Coghlan, who captains the women's team.  Yesterday, in an interview I heard her say how she was inspired by the likes of Sonia O'Sullivan, Katie Taylor and Fionnuala Britton.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000008#G00300"><p>Not to mention Eamonn Coghlan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" speakername="Eamonn Coghlan" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000008#G00400"><p>She was inspired by these wonderful women.  The message the women's rugby team brought back is really good for all women's sports in Ireland.  I congratulate the Irish Rugby Football Union, IRFU, for its announcement yesterday of a €1.1 million annual investment in women's rugby with the view to qualifying for the 2016 women's rugby sevens at the Rio Olympic Games.  I would encourage the Irish Sports Council to continue its investment in women's sport in Ireland which has proved to be successful with the investments made to date.  Well done to the Irish women's rugby team.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000008#G00500"><p>I support the call made by Senator Darragh O'Brien for a debate on town and village centres.  A pop-up policy has been put in place in Carlow which looks at encouraging enterprises to take up opportunities in vacant properties.  It is a pilot scheme and is worthy of debate.</p><p>I call for a debate on the whole issue of public and private debt, the significant issue which has not been sorted out in Europe.  Our European and this State's leaders simply have not learned the lessons of the real reason why this country is in crisis.  We have a huge mountain of banking debt that was taken on by this State.  We also have significant levels of personal debt with families in mortgage arrears and having other loans they cannot service.  Since the Government came into office, we now have twice as many people, some 185,000, in mortgage distress with 1,000 families every month falling into mortgage arrears.  Of that 185,000, according to the Central Bank, up to 145,000 will not be able to pay their mortgages now or into the future unless their circumstances change.  The bottom line is that as long as a family or an individual is servicing debts they cannot repay, then the economy will not be able to grow and the family's or individual's circumstances will not change.  Unless we have a write-down of the private banking debt, taking it off the shoulders of the taxpayers and a restructuring of domestic mortgages to include a suite of interventions including mortgage write-downs, families will not be able to get out of the dire circumstances in which they find themselves and, accordingly, spend.  So far the Government has not put in place any tangible proposals to help people in mortgage distress.  The Government's latest initiative is to set targets for the banks to deal with mortgage resolution but the banks will retain a veto and can simply disregard the targets as they have done in the past.</p><p>I am calling for a debate on the whole issue of debt.</p> <p>There is a need for the Government and the European Union to get serious about the real problems which are bearing down on ordinary working people, including the unsustainable levels of private and personal debt.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" speakername="John Kelly" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000009#H00200"><p>I take the opportunity to congratulate St. Brigid's GAA club in County Roscommon on going down in history as the first team from the county to win the all-Ireland club final.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" speakername="John Kelly" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000009#H00400"><p><i>En route</i> in the Connacht final they beat my home team of Ballaghaderreen.  It is great that there are two teams in County Roscommon playing at such a high level in all-Ireland leagues.  Fair play to Shane Curran, Frankie Dolan, Senan Kilbride and the rest of the lads.  I am delighted for them and we are all proud of them.</p><p>  I support the call made by Senator Mary Ann O'Brien on the regeneration of town centres.  I raised this issue with the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government, Deputy Phil Hogan, at the Joint Committee on Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation three weeks ago when I suggested we needed to provide incentives, as town centres were dying.  Senator Mary Ann O'Brien has rightly pointed out that all we see are bookmakers and charity shops, with the greatest of respect to them, opening in town centres.  The reason town centres are dying is purely the bad planning of the past.</p><p>  I listened to the media coverage during the weekend and on the way here in the car today about the chief executive of Bank of Ireland who is on &#8364;900,000 a year.  Have we not learned anything at this stage?  It was absolutely outrageous to listen to the debate and hear that he was on that kind of money.  When I switched to another channel, I had to listen to a girl who had gone to see to a community welfare officer this morning.  She is a qualified health professional who, because of illness, has had to give up work.  Her husband was self-employed, but his business went to the wall.  They have lost their home and are surviving on social welfare payments.  They do not have the price of a pair of shoes for their children.  It is chalk and cheese.  There is no problem in looking after those who are running the banks with losses of &#8364;2 billion a year, but we are doing nothing for people at the lower end of the scale who have absolutely nothing.  It is time the Ministers in question looked up and smelled the coffee.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1142" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000009#H00500"><p>On several occasions I have commended the ICTU and the trade union movement in general for the mature manner in which they have responded to the fierce challenges that they have faced in recent years. I have said before that when we eventually get out of the hole we are in, it will be noted that the trade union movement played a serious, important and positive role in that regard.  Everyone on both sides of the House accepts this point. The unions are balloting on the tough and difficult deal negotiated recently.  In that context, I express my horror and dismay at the unprecedented intervention of the Catholic Primary School Management Association yesterday which communicated by letter with national school principals effectively, advising them to oppose the deal.  This is placing the INTO in a difficult position.  That union had the courage to stay in the talks and negotiate.  It declared that the deal it had received was not the one it wanted.  Is the Catholic Primary School Management Association suggesting national school teachers should now take further pay cuts and work even longer hours?  This is an unprecedented intervention in the democratic process and should be condemned.  I declare an interest.  I am a former national INTO activist and had the honour to be nominated by the INTO to the Labour Panel to contest the Seanad elections on the last two occasions, but apart from this, this is unprecedented.  I call on the Leader to join me in agreeing that the trade union movement has behaved responsibly and that we should ask people with no say or hand, act or part to play in the actual ballot process not to get involved.  Certainly, the organisation mentioned has a valid interest in education, which I do not deny, as itt has done tremendous work, but it was not a party to the deal and, therefore, should keep out of it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000009#H00600"><p>The CAP agreement was referred to.  I congratulate the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine, Deputy Simon Coveney, on it.  It is an honour for Ireland because we have held the Presidency of the European Council since January and will hold it until June.  That the agreement was reached under the Minister's stewardship is unique and I congratulate him on it because I do not believe the deal would have been driven through without his energy.</p> <p>I ask the Leader to arrange for a debate on the CAP agreement.  This is important, because the CAP agreement is not about redistributing funds, but about supporting active farmers, young farmers and new entrants into farming.  It is also about providing flexibility and I believe the Minister has managed to get flexibility with regard to how funds are distributed.  Senator Comiskey said it would be about redistributing funds from larger farmers to smaller farmers on small payments, but that is not what it is about.  It is about active farmers, young farmers and new entrants.</p><p>I congratulate the Minister with regard to the agreement reached on sugar quotas.  We exited the sugar regime in Europe a few years ago and it was a sorry day for Ireland when that happened.  Agreement has been reached now that sugar quotas will disappear in September 2017.  We have companies, such as Beet Ireland, which are actively trying to encourage the growing of beet here again and perhaps we will announce the site for a new factory within the next two months.  Sugar beet was a very important industry for agriculture in Ireland and I believe it will fit in well with the new CAP regime.  That is part of the reason I asked for a debate on CAP.</p><p>I asked for this debate previously in the context of the policies of the parties in the Opposition, Sinn Féin and Fianna Fáil, and their position on the CAP payments.  It is important to have a debate in the House on CAP reform so that we can hear the policies of the Opposition.  They cannot play both sides all the time. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor Ó Clochartaigh" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000010#J00200"><p>Aontaím go hiomlán le mo chomhleacaí go bhfuil géarghá le díospóireacht maidir le cúrsaí CAP agus mar sin de.  Ach ar dtús, ba mhaith liom comhghairdeas a ghabháil le peileadóirí Chumann Peile Naomh Bríd, Roscomáin, as ucht an chraobh a thabhairt siar, thar An tSionann leo.  Ba mhaith liom freisin comhghairdeas a ghabháil le iománaithe Chumann Naomh Thomáis a thug leo an chraobh iománaíochta siar go Gaillimh.  Gabhaim comhghairdeas le foireann rugbaí ban na hÉireann as an éacht a rinne siadsan chomh maith.</p><p>I would certainly welcome a good robust debate on CAP in the Seanad.  We would have a good debate on the proposals here because we welcome and accept the need to redistribute the CAP funding more equitably among farmers.  Sinn Féin supports more equitable support of the smaller, rural farmers.  We also hope that during that debate the Minister would be able to honour his commitment to limiting CAP payments to €100,000, with a view to lowering those payments to €50,000 by 2019.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000010#J00300"><p>We never said that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor Ó Clochartaigh" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000010#J00400"><p>We will be calling for that during the debate.</p><p>I commend the Cypriot parliamentarians who stood up for their citizens last night in a very robust manner.  I hope our Government will support them at European level to negotiate a fairer deal for Cypriot citizens.  I add to the calls for the Minister for Finance to come in and debate the EU decision to impose the proposed deal.  Did he agree with the smash and grab tactics employed by the troika, which the Cypriots wholeheartedly turned down?  Fair play to them for having the gumption to do that.  It is a shame we did not have a much stronger, resolute way of dealing with the troika when it came to dealing with our financial crisis and that we did not make it go back to look at the European nature of the crisis and the real debt issues, rather than impose all of the burden on our citizens.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1162" speakername="Denis Landy" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000010#J00500"><p>A number of speakers have supported Senator Mary Ann O'Brien on the issue of town centres and the retail sector.  I would like to support that, but I believe town centres have not died yet and that there are tangible and real ways we can help.  I wish to raise one of these ways this afternoon, one I raised about three months ago, namely, the proposal by Government to centralise the issuing of new credit card style driving licences.  The effects of this could be the loss of up to 4,000 jobs in small towns among pharmacists and professional photographers.</p><p>The Road Safety Authority was charged with rolling out the new system, which will come into play in September.  It went to tender on the system and a Swiss based company, SGS, won the tender.  Initially, this company agreed photographs could be taken at local level, in chemist shops and by local photographers, and sent to the company with the driving licence applications.  However, now confusion reigns on the issue, but everybody seems to have gone to ground, including the chief executive of the Road Safety Authority.  This is not good enough.  This same system was tried in France and the SGS centralised system was scrapped because of public opinion.  </p> <p>We have a real and tangible opportunity to save jobs in small towns in rural Ireland by allowing photographs for the purposes of the new service to continue to be taken locally.  I am asking the Leader to call on the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Leo Varadkar, to provide clarity and direction for the Road Safety Authority on this issue.  This is an example of something we could do to ensure small towns in rural Ireland do not die.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" speakername="Terry Brennan" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000011#K00200"><p>Coimeádtar an fíon maith go dtí an deireadh.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Caít Keane" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000011#K00300"><p>Tá sé ann fós.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" speakername="Terry Brennan" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000011#K00400"><p>An dtuigeann an Seanadóir é sin?  I intend to speak about two matters that have already been mentioned.  I congratulate the ladies international rugby team on their achievement at the weekend in Milan in unbelievable and abominable conditions when they added the grand slam to the Triple Crown they had won last month.</p><p>There is no way any man or woman could justify the payment of a salary of €900,000 per annum to a CEO or any boss.  We have discussed these obnoxious salaries on many occasions in the House and I wonder whether there is anything we could about them.  I was annoyed to read in a newspaper today that the man about whom I am speaking had signed an agreement in 2009 whereby he would receive a salary of €623,000.  I cannot believe how it increased from €623,000 to more than €800,000 in just three years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000011#K00500"><p>Is the Senator looking for a debate on this issue?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" speakername="Terry Brennan" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000011#K00600"><p>We will have to do something about it.  We should debate the issue of salaries.  Nobody can deny that there are men and women in this country and Irish men and women in foreign fields who might be willing to come back who are capable of running the banks or working as the CEOs of various companies for less than the outrageous salaries being paid.  No man or woman could justify being paid €2,000 a day.  I am calling for a debate on why certain salaries in banks that have failed the people and taxpayers have increased by 33% in the times that are in it.  We urgently need a debate on the payment of such outrageous salaries to CEOs.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000011#K00700"><p>Last week I mentioned Senator Eamonn Coghlan's famous ancestor, the Kerry-born engineer John Coghlan, when I was saluting some of his achievements in another context.  I join the Senator in warmly congratulating another of our namesakes, Fiona Coghlan, on her team's tremendous victory at the weekend.  As Senator Terry Brennan said, to win the Triple Crown and the grand slam is a tremendous achievement.</p><p>I fully support what Senator Mary Ann O'Brien and others have said about town centres.  Retailers in towns throughout the country have suffered and are suffering.  To a large extent, vibrancy and vitality have been robbed from town centres.  I hope Senator Denis Landy is right when he says everything is not yet lost.  The planning departments of town councils wreaked havoc in many towns when they allowed out-of-town developments to be built.</p><p>I am concerned about our much sought after wild venison.  There should be a ban in this regard.  I am, therefore, calling on the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine, Deputy Simon Coveney, whom I salute for what he has achieved with regard to the Common Agricultural Policy, and the Minister for Arts, Heritage and the Gaeltacht, Deputy Jimmy Deenihan, who is in charge of the National Parks and Wildlife Service, to take action in this respect.  Sadly, the poaching and night shooting of stags, in particular, are on the increase.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000011#K00800"><p>It might be more suitable to raise this issue on the Adjournment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000011#K00900"><p>I have no doubt that the Cathaoirleach is probably right, as ever, because he is a wise old owl.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" speakername="Terry Brennan" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000012#L00100"><p>He is wiser than half a dozen owls.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000012#L00200"><p>If the Senator tables it, I could take it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000012#L00300"><p>Sadly, this poaching is on the increase.  I must declare, if one likes, a non-declarable interest.  I am a lifelong member of the Kerry Deer Society, which is concerned with conservation.  We were never poachers or were never into culling.  Whatever about management issues, we would not want to see the native Irish red deer - the Kerry red deer -  seriously under threat, and I am not talking about the deer in Glenveagh and other parts because they are different strains.  Members are very welcome to visit the national park with me.  There is a threat in that people are hunting the stags for their antlers and for the meat.  Although we talk about traceability and so on, wild venison should not be bought by any restaurant or hotel.  The Ministers, Deputy Coveney and Deputy Deenihan, have to come together to devise a system to ensure this is stopped.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" speakername="Susan O'Keeffe" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000012#L00400"><p>Like others, I welcome the initial movement on the CAP negotiations.  I am sure the Minister, Deputy Coveney, has been working extremely hard to try to get countries to agree to anything at all.  I would like to join with others to say "Well done" on that front, particularly in regard to the ending of the quota for sugar beet, which raises a very real opportunity for the Irish sugar industry.  Obviously, this CAP negotiation will have to go through the European Parliament, and it is the first big test for the European Parliament in terms of its responsibility on this negotiation.  I join with others in asking for the Minister to come to the House so we could have a debate on CAP, particularly the greening aspect, which is still causing concern and will undoubtedly be reorganised through the European Parliament.</p><p>If the Minister is coming in to discuss CAP, I make the point that we see more reports today of tonnes of desinewed lamb being found in France, having been imported from the UK.  Desinewed meat has been illegal in Europe for some ten years since the BSE scandal, so for it to be discovered in the human food chain is quite a concern.  While I hope the Minister will be able to draw breath following the CAP negotiations, I ask that we would have him come to the House to discuss the whole horsemeat and now lamb difficulties.  There are still big concerns with regard to what is happening in the food industry, the meat industry in particular.  In short, I am asking for two debates, one on the meat industry and one on CAP.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000012#L00500"><p>We have proven again we are the best in the world on the sporting field.  The ladies' wonderful victory in achieving the rugby grand slam has been referred to and we cannot forget the 14 winners at Cheltenham last week, which highlights the strength of Irish racing and how important the Irish horse industry is to our country.</p><p>On the economic and business front, Ryanair has proven what a fantastic business it is, given the huge order it has placed with Boeing for new aircraft.  Its plans will see an additional 3,000 jobs created, which will bring its workforce worldwide to 14,000.  It is to be congratulated.  It is a major Irish company and this is a major achievement.  I hope the visits of the Taoiseach and Ministers throughout the world over the St. Patrick's weekend will result in many jobs being created in this country in the years ahead.</p><p>I support the call from Senator Mary Ann O'Brien and others for a debate on the problems facing town centre businesses.  We are all acutely aware of this, and coming from a small rural town in the west, Ballinasloe, I can see my own town being decimated.  We need innovation and we need to think outside the box in regard to how we might revive town centres.  This Chamber has a lot of knowledge and expertise, and can contribute to a very constructive debate.  I ask the Leader to put that on the agenda.  It has been discussed at the Oireachtas committee dealing with jobs but this House should have an opportunity for all Members to contribute to helping to revive our town centres.</p> <p> I cannot let the opportunity go without referring to two great sporting achievements by west of Ireland teams - St. Thomas's hurling club from County Galway and St. Brigid's from Roscommon who brought the two senior club championships across the Shannon over the weekend.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Caít Keane" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000013#M00200"><p>Like the other Senators, I congratulate the ladies team.  Maybe the men could learn something from them in that sphere, as in every other sphere.  I support Senator Brennan's comments on bankers' salaries.  The only bank in Iceland that did not fail was governed by a lady.  We should widen the debate to gender experience worldwide and how it is a valuable asset not only in sport but in every sphere.  It is a lesson well learned and well taken.</p><p>There must be something in the Coghlan gene but we are about to throw away and destroy 1,000 samples in the national archive of the heel prick test taken from every baby born in every hospital.  Iceland, Norway and Sweden preserve these samples for 1,000 years.  Why do they do this?  They do so because of the valuable genetic material stored in that system.  It has been used in the past to confirm that Ireland has the highest frequency of haemochromatosis.  It has been used for various other things, including identifying vulnerability to sudden adult death syndrome.  All of this will be lost.  I am asking for a debate on this issue before it is too late.  The samples have not been destroyed yet.  Professor John Crowe, president of the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland, has called for the samples to be saved from destruction because they are a valuable and precious resource for future genetic studies on the Irish population.  Why are we doing it?  It is not just being done for fun, obviously.  In 2011, implied consent was agreed-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000013#M00300"><p>Is the Senator looking for a debate on the matter?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Caít Keane" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000013#M00400"><p>I am looking for a debate.  It is a serious issue.  I am looking for an immediate debate because I do not want it to happen after the event.  I want to try and stop it before it goes through.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000013#M00500"><p>I join with my colleagues in congratulating fellow Corkman, the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine, Deputy Simon Coveney, for the work he has done on CAP reform.  It also goes back to his own experience of working in the European Parliament and the mechanism that works in Europe about negotiation and compromise.  In achieving that compromise, he has done a good deal for Ireland.</p><p>Senator Keane just referred to the proposed destruction of the Guthrie cards which record the result of the heel prick test.  Senator Bacik raised this issue last week.  Some medical consultants contacted me this morning.  They are looking for an immediate meeting with the Minister.  I ask that this meeting be arranged.  The people in question are Professor John Crowe, the president of the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland, and other key people who were not consulted when this decision was arrived at by the Department, the HSE and the Data Protection Commissioner.  I ask that this meeting be held within the next seven days because 31 March 2013 is the deadline.  I have already had an Adjournment debate in this House on the matter.  There has been no compromise from the Department.  The destruction of these cards will be very significant.  We will not be able to get this information back again in 12 months' time if these cards are destroyed.  The minimum I am asking for is a meeting within the next seven days between the key players in this area - the Department and HSE and the medical consultants who are very upset that they were not consulted when this decision was arrived at.  </p> <p>I support my colleague, Senator Keane, in again seeking a debate on this matter.  She is correct in stating that Denmark, Norway, Sweden and New Zealand have made legislative provision to the effect that these cards cannot be destroyed in their jurisdictions.  There is no reason we cannot do likewise or why the Data Protection Commissioner's decision in this regard should be taken as gospel.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000014#N00200"><p>I also wish to share in the positive vibes wafting through the House in respect of what occurred during the St. Patrick's Day Festival and in subsequent days.  I am pleased to report from County Clare that The Gathering is working.  I was out and about in Lahinch last evening and the restaurants there were full of Americans who were openly discussing The Gathering.  The latter is currently our major tourism initiative and it is going to be our most successful ever.  Bright and early this morning eight busloads of Americans departed a beautifully sunny Lahinch to visit the Cliffs of Moher.  That is a very positive sign that we are seeing more than just green shoots in terms of tourism.  Coupled with our sporting achievements and the phenomenal parades which took place throughout the country, this shows that the fighting Irish spirit is alive and well and that we are being successful in fighting back and regaining control over our country and over the pride that exists in the hearts of its citizens.  I am very uplifted and joyful about that.</p><p>Everything I have just said relates very well to the discussion on town centres.  When tourists visit any city or town, they like to see what is at its centre.  Countries throughout Europe are famous for their beautiful plazas and, as we refer to them as Gaeilge, sráideanna.  It is awful to see &quot;For Sale&quot; and &quot;To Let&quot; signs on empty buildings in beautiful towns throughout the country that are famous for their history and architecture.  What is required in respect of our town centres is action.  There is a need for a properly constituted, constructed and targeted tax incentive scheme for our town centres.  I refer here to the centres of small and large towns and also those of our cities.  We followed the British example of moving shopping centres, etc., out of our towns, which was a mistake.  We need to reconsider the position in this regard and take appropriate action.</p><p>I understand that a concert is due to be held in the Phoenix Park.  In the aftermath of the tragedies which occurred during one of last year's events there, I am surprised this is happening.  I am sure proper procedures and precautions have been taken and that there are new health and safety guidelines in place.  Will the Leader make time available, if possible, for the Minister of State with responsibility for the OPW to come before the House to outline what has been done to ensure that there will be no repeat of what occurred last year?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000014#N00300"><p>Senators MacSharry, Norris, Ó Clochartaigh and others raised the issue of the proposed Cypriot bailout.  Despite any irresponsible innuendo to the contrary, I wish to make it clear that there will be absolutely no impact on Ireland, on Irish depositors or on our corporation tax rate as a result of this proposed bailout.  There are no signs of contagion in respect of Ireland.  In that context, Irish bonds continue to trade at their lowest yields in many years.  Unfortunately, and as a result of the catastrophic policies pursued by previous Fianna Fáil Governments, Irish people are far too familiar with the cost of rescuing banks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000014#N00400"><p>We were responsible for it happening in Cyprus, Portugal, Spain and Italy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000014#N00500"><p>The Leader, without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000014#N00600"><p>The Taoiseach can take the spoils over in the White House but he will not accept the fact that this is a worldwide crisis.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000014#N00700"><p>We are all aware of Fianna Fáil's light regulatory approach to the banking sector in the past.  Ireland is certainly in a completely different position to Cyprus.  We have already recapitalised our banks, unfortunately at great expense to taxpayers and the people in general.  We have moved from the crisis mode which obtained in 2008 to one of stability in the past couple of years.  We are now in a position where we are recouping as much money as possible by selling financial sector assets such as Bank of Ireland contingent capital notes and Irish Life.</p> <p>In addition to the promissory note agreement which has improved our deficit and our debt position it is very important for the people of Cyprus that a sustainable programme of assistance is agreed and implemented in order to bring economic and financial stability to Cyprus.  I am sure we all hope that a proper bailout for Cyprus will be agreed soon. </p><p>Senator MacSharry also raised the question of the delays in the waiting lists for consultants in the north west.  He referred to a statement by a consultant in the north west.  I will raise that matter with the Minister for Health.  He has been dealing with waiting lists.  Significant progress has been made by the new special delivery unit in reducing waiting lists, as evidenced by the performance in 2012.  If there are problems in the north west I am sure they will be addressed by the special delivery unit.  It is obvious that this is a cause for concern for the consultant.  I am sure his concerns will be addressed by the Minister and the HSE.</p><p>Senator Bacik advises me she will be introducing a Bill soon.  I will certainly allow it to be published on the Order Paper.  She welcomed the Courts Bill which will be before the House soon.</p><p>Senators Mary Ann O'Brien, Harte, Conway, Landy and others, referred to the decline in town centres.  This matter was raised last week by Senator Quinn and other Senators and it was dealt with at length.  The question of parking fees is a matter for local authorities.  I am sure that chambers of commerce, business associations and traders throughout the country make representations about parking fees to their local authorities.  It is in the interests of all towns and local authorities to be competitive where parking fees are concerned.</p><p>Senator Kelly also raised the question of incentives for town centres.  The Finance Bill will be in the House today.  I am sure Senator Kelly will raise the matter with the Minister.  </p><p>Senator Comiskey and several Senators welcomed the agreement on CAP reform.  Senators Comiskey and O'Donovan said it is a good deal for young farmers.  There will be some who will lose out because the budget has been reduced.  Senators O'Neill, O'Keeffe and others mentioned the flexibility of the payments.  They welcomed the disappearance of the sugar quotas in 2017.  They complimented Beet Ireland.  Hopefully we will be in a position in 2017 to renew and restore our beet industry which has been a great loss to the country and to farmers.  Other Members called for a debate on the CAP reforms.  The Minister had agreed to come to the House after Easter to discuss the horsemeat and food labelling situations.  I suggest that rather than having the debate on those issues, we could have the debate on reform of the CAP when the Minister comes to the House after the Easter recess.</p><p>Senator Barrett asked for a debate on the free trade negotiations.  Last week, Members raised the issues of the EU-US trade agreement, the undocumented Irish and job creation.  Those negotiations and visits are continuing this week.  An Taoiseach and other Ministers are in the United States.  </p> <p>I hope that the negotiations will bring much needed jobs to our citizens here.  </p><p>Both Senator Coghlans saluted the Coghlan clan-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" speakername="Eamonn Coghlan" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000016#P00200"><p>They do it themselves.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000016#P00300"><p>-----on their women.  Ms Fiona Coghlan captained the successful Irish women's rugby team.  We all salute their efforts.  It is a wonderful team and they did the country proud.</p><p>Senator Cullinane again called for a debate on public and private debt and mortgage arrears.  We have had numerous debates here on the subject and I am sure that we will have more with the relevant Minister in attendance.  The Government has directed banks to address the mortgage arrears problem and targets have been set that must be met.  The Central Bank and the Government will ensure that they are met in order to address the important issue. </p><p>Senators Kelly, Mullins and others complimented the success of club teams from west of the River Shannon, St. Brigid's and St. Thomas's, on winning their respective All-Ireland trophies over the weekend.</p><p>Senators Kelly and Brennan raised the issue of the Bank of Ireland's remuneration for its CEO and his terms and conditions of employment.  Those matters were decided in 2009.  As part of his appointment, the previous Government approved his salary of €623,000 as an exemption to the Covered Institution Remuneration Oversight Committee.  Since the Government came to office restrictions on remuneration levels at covered institutions have been tightened.  No appointee may receive an aggregate all-inclusive remuneration, excluding pension contributions, of €500,000 per annum.  The Government has been seen to act in that regard with the appointment of new CEOs in AIB and PTSB.  It should also be noted that the State is a minority shareholder in Bank of Ireland at 15%.</p><p>Senator O'Sullivan raised the item of the Irish Catholic schools managers association's, as he stated, unprecedented intervention.  I agree with him that it was an unprecedented intervention.  I compliment the INTO and the trade union movement for playing a responsible role in the talks on Croke Park II.</p><p>Senator Landy referred to the new driving licence and the proposed centralised system.  He sought clarity on same from the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport.  I will try to discover the up-to-date position on the new driving licences.  </p><p>Senator Paul Coghlan referred to the conservation of red deer which is an important item for Killarney and the country.  We all believe in conservation and condemn the increase in poaching and night shooting of stags and deer.  </p><p>Senator Mullins complimented everybody involved in the success of the 14 Irish winners at the Cheltenham race festival.  Their success is a great advertisement for Horse Racing Ireland.  </p><p>Senators Colm Burke, Keane and others referred to the Guthrie cards.  Again, the matter was debated last week when it was raised by Senator Bacik.  I am sure that the Minister for Health will facilitate a meeting with the consultants if they have sought same.  It is an important issue so if we can do anything to arrange the meeting then we will do so.  The matter has been raised here by Senators on a number of occasions. </p> <p> Senator Martin Conway spoke about the positivity of the St. Patrick's Day parades throughout the world and stated The Gathering was working.  Obviously, it is working in County Clare, with many tourists flocking to the Cliffs of Moher and many other destinations the length and breadth of the county.  It is good to end on such a positive note.  We will check with the Minister of State with responsibility for the Office of Public Works on the question of concerts in the Phoenix Park and the increased health and safety measures that will be taken in that regard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.76" nospeaker="true" time="15:50:00"><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.77" nospeaker="true" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000017#Q00300">Council Regulation on Insolvency Proceedings: Referral to Joint Committee</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000017#Q00400"><p>I move:<blockquote><br />That the proposal that Seanad Éireann approves the exercise by the State of the option or discretion under Protocol No. 21 on the position of the United Kingdom and Ireland in respect of the area of freedom, security and justice annexed to the Treaty on European Union and to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, to take part in the adoption and application of the following proposed measure:Proposal for a Regulation of the European Parliament and of the Council amending Council Regulation (EC) No. 1346/2000 on insolvency proceedings,a copy of which was laid before Seanad Éireann on 9th January 2013, be referred to the Joint Committee on Justice, Defence and Equality, in accordance with Standing Order 70A(3), which, not later than 28th March 2013, shall send a message to the Seanad in the manner prescribed in Standing Order 73, and Standing Order 75(2) shall accordingly apply.</blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.79" nospeaker="true" time="15:50:00"><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.80" nospeaker="true" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000017#Q00600">An Bord Bia Act 1994 (Levy on Slaughtered or Exported Livestock) Order 2013: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000017#Q00700"><p>I move:<blockquote><br />That Seanad Éireann approves the following Order in draft:An Bord Bia Act 1994 (Levy on Slaughtered or Exported Livestock) Order 2013,a copy of which Order in draft was laid before Seanad Éireann on 14th March 2013.&#8217;&#8217;</blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.82" nospeaker="true" time="15:50:00"><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.83" nospeaker="true" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000017#Q00900">Finance Bill 2013 (Certified Money Bill): Second Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000017#Q01000"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Brian Hayes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.85" nospeaker="true" time="15:50:00"><p>Question proposed: &quot;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&quot;</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000017#Q01200"><p>I thank the Leas-Chathaoirleach for giving me the opportunity to come to the Seanad once again to take Second Stage of the Finance Bill 2013.  When he introduced the Bill to the Dáil, the Minister for Finance, Deputy Michael Noonan, noted that he was pleased to do so at a time when we could be more optimistic.  That was just one month ago, but even since we have seen further signs of economic recovery, of which I am sure Senators are aware.  We all know that the State has been through the most severe downturn in its history, but I believe, as does the Minister, that we can say with confidence that we have begun to turn things around, due in no small measure to the sacrifices of the people.  As a Government, we have made many difficult and sometimes unpopular decisions, but we are beginning to see that these decisions have been worthwhile.  We are on track to bring the budget deficit below the target of 3% of GDP by 2015.  The banks have been recapitalised and regained access to borrowing markets.  The economy is expected to record growth in 2013 for the third straight year.  For last year as a whole, a GDP growth rate of 0.9% is projected, with the Department of Finance expecting the rate of growth to increase this year to 1.5% and further strengthen in the medium term.  The strong performance of net exports also means that the current account for the balance of payments is back in surplus.  In fact, a current account surplus of just over 3% of GDP is projected for 2012, rising to over 4% in 2013.</p><p>Our progress is reflected in investors' confidence in our ability to successfully tackle our economic and budgetary problems.  The yield on the 2020 Irish Government bond has fallen from a level of 14.9% over 18 months ago to under 4% at the start of February and we are all aware that the National Treasury Management Agency, NTMA, was able to successfully re-enter borrowing markets last week and issue a benchmark ten year bond at very favourable rates of just over 4%.</p><p>On the fiscal side, the public finances have stabilised and the budget deficit has started to decline.  This year the general Government deficit will be reduced further to 7.5% of GDP.  In order to meet this target, budget 2013 introduced a package of adjustment measures, totalling €3.5 billion, and the Government is well aware that these measures will impact on citizens on both the tax and expenditure sides.</p> <p>However, sustainable public finances are a prerequisite for sustainable growth and job creation.  That is why, as Senators are aware, the Government has worked so hard at a European level to ensure that we achieved a deal in relation to the promissory notes and the progress announced recently in terms of lengthening the maturities of our European loans.</p><p>As we now turn to the Finance Bill itself, I will restate the point, already made by Minister, Deputy Michael Noonan, that despite the progress that we are making in relation to fiscal and banking matters, the Government still considers unemployment to be unacceptably high and the biggest and most important challenge that we must address. The Bill should be viewed as one element of a wider strategy to support economic activity that is complemented by the Action Plan for Jobs 2013 which the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation published recently.</p><p>The Bill begins to implement the ten-point tax reform plan announced in the budget.  This plan includes measures such as reforming the three-year corporation tax relief for start-up companies, increasing the cash receipts basis threshold for VAT, amending the close company surcharge to improve cash flow for SMEs and extending the foreign earnings deduction for work-related travel to certain additional countries.</p><p>Senators may be interested to note that the public consultation on taxation of micro enterprises which was also a part of this plan has closed. The submissions received are currently being assessed and analysed by officials of the Department of Finance and the Revenue Commissioners with a view to helping to cut compliance costs and make starting a business less daunting for ordinary people.</p><p>I would add that the introduction of the new JobsPlus scheme later this year will provide grants to employers to encourage them to employ individuals who have been on the live register for longer than 12 months.  Two more pro-employment measures which I might highlight for the House are the amendment of the key employee provision of the research and development tax credit regime and the extension of the employment and investment incentive and the seed capital scheme.</p><p>I now turn to the Bill but of course I cannot cover every individual measure in the time available.  The Bill comprises 108 sections, two Schedules and 177 pages.  We will have an opportunity tomorrow to go through some of it, if Senators wish.  It is a significant piece of work and not only by officials and legislators.  Measures are not simply devised in Merrion Street.  Rather, they represent the product of much discussion and dialogue across all Departments, with representative organisations and with individual citizens.  I have chosen to highlight some measures which I think may be of particular interest to Senators.</p><p>Part 1 of the Bill deals with the income levy, universal social charge, income tax, corporation tax and capital gains tax.  Section 3 provides for the changes to the universal social charge announced in budget 2013, which applies the standard rates of USC to those aged 70 years and over, as well as to medical card holders, both PAYE and self-employed income earners, who have income in excess of €60,000 per annum.</p><p>Section 5 relates to the key employee provision of the research and development tax credit, the amount of time an employee must spend on research and development in order to qualify is being reduced from 75% to 50%.  Sections 6 and 45 amend sections 71 and 29, respectively, of the Taxes Consolidation Act 1997.  These amendments counter potential avoidance mechanisms in relation to non-domiciled individuals.</p><p>Section 8 gives effect to the budget day announcement that maternity benefit payments will be treated as taxable income with effect from 1 July 2013.  As is the case with all social welfare payments, maternity benefit payments will continue to be exempt from the USC and PRSI.  Section 9, which was inserted on Committee Stage in the Dáil, extends mortgage interest relief for additional tranches of loans that are drawn down in 2013 for building or improving a principal private residence, where the first part of such a loan was drawn down in 2012.</p><p>Section 10 provides for an extension of the foreign earnings deduction for work related travel to a number of African countries.  We introduced this last year and it has been a novel commonsense proposal in terms of encouraging the export industry but specifically agrifood exports into parts of the world where we had not previously gone.</p> <p>Section 13 makes a number of changes to provisions on benefits in kind while section 14 deals with various issues related to <i>ex gratia</i>payments including the abolition of top slicing relief which the Minister also announced on budget day.  Section 16 makes changes to the basis of assessment for rental income or profits sourced from outside the State.</p><p> Section 17 provides for pre-retirement access to funded additional voluntary contributions.  Section 17 relates to a concern that was raised in the House last year to which the Minister has responded to allow the withdrawal on a once-off basis of 30% of the value of additional voluntary contributions.  Section 18 includes two new provisions which apply to individuals dealing in or developing land.  Section 19 provides for changes to the scheme of tax relief for donations to approved bodies as announced by the Minister in the budget.  Section 12 relates to stock relief and extends the general 25% rate and the 100% young trained farmer rate of stock relief to 31 December 2015.  The Bill also extends the definition of registered farm partnerships.</p><p> Section 21 relates to film relief.  Following a review by the Department of Finance, film relief will no longer be available to investors in qualifying firms.  Instead, a payable tax credit will be paid directly to a producer company which will benefit significantly and support the industry.  The Minister is setting the rate for the credit at 32%.  The extension of and changes to the employment and investment incentive seed capital schemes are set out in section 22 of the Bill.  Section 23 increases deposit interest retention tax, or DIRT, by 3% as announced in the budget.  Section 24 reduces the tax credit available for donations of heritage property to the State from 80% of the market value to 50%.  Section 28 increases the amount of group expenditure and research and development activity excluded from the incremental basis of calculation from &#8364;100,000 to &#8364;200,000.</p><p> Section 30 relates to the living-city initiative.  This is a pilot scheme and it will be confined to certain designated areas for the moment.  On foot of the requirement to obtain EU state-aid approval, the provision will be subject to a commencement order.  Amendments to the Taxes Consolidation Act 1997 are made in section 31 to establish an accelerated capital allowances scheme pertaining to the aviation sector.  Section 33 amends the close company surcharge rules and increases the <i>de minimis</i>amount of undistributed investment and rental income which may be retained by a close company without giving rise to a surcharge from &#8364;635 to &#8364;2,000.  The same increase will apply in respect of the surcharge on the undistributed trading or professional income of certain service companies.  Section 34 extends the three-year corporation tax exemption for start-up companies which has been a key feature of what we have attempted to do in this and previous budgets.  Section 39, introduced on Committee Stage in the Dáil, contains a technical amendment to provisions on the exit tax rate for payments to companies from life insurance products and investment funds.</p><p> Section 40 increases the rates of tax applying to life assurance policies and investment funds by three percentage points with effect from 1 January 2013.  Section 41 provides for the introduction of a tax regime for real estate investment trusts, or REITs.  The Minister for Finance, Deputy Michael Noonan, took into account concerns expressed by Deputies on Second Stage and introduced on Committee Stage two new investor protection measures to the REITs regime.  These measures will provide additional safeguards for REIT investors without adding cost or complexity to the regime.  They provide for a debt-equity ratio which restricts the level of borrowings within REITs and for a good-asset test which requires that a minimum of 75% of the assets of a REIT are assets of a property rental business.</p><p> Section 43 provides for a capital gains tax, or CGT, rate increase from 30% to 33% as announced on budget day.  All capital taxes went up in the budget from 30% to 33%.  Section 47 relates to changes in CGT relief introduced in last year's Finance Act for individuals who dispose of agricultural assets to their children and certain other individuals.  Section 48 provides for the relief from CGT for farm restructuring which measure was announced in the budget.</p> <p> Section 49 gives effect to the increase in the rates of tobacco products tax which, when VAT is included, amount to 10% on a pack of 20 cigarettes, with <i>pro rata</i>increases on other tobacco products.  The section also provides for a further increase of 50 cent per packet of roll-your-own tobacco.</p><p> Section 51 introduces a new section in mineral oil tax law to provide for partial relief by way of requirement for auto diesel used in the course of business by qualifying road haulage and bus operators.  This was an important issue on which road hauliers campaigned had hard for the past 12 months and which the Minister conceded in the budget.  He extended it to bus operators, which was an important additional relief for that sector of tourism and transport.</p><p> Section 52 amends the general provisions of excise law, including provisions to ensure repayment of overpaid excise duty does not result in unjust enrichment.  Section 56 provides for the indictable offence of the illicit production of tobacco products, as well as the offence of selling or the delivery of unstamped tobacco products.  Section 58 gives effect to the increase in the excise rate of alcohol products tax, inclusive of VAT, which amounts to approximately 10% on a pint of beer or cider and a standard measure of spirits and a &#8364;1 increase on the standard bottle of wine.</p><p> Section 61 provides for a number of amendments in preparation for the commencement of the solid fuel carbon tax with effect from 1 May this year as the Minister announced in the budget.  Section 63 gives effect to the revised system of VRT which was also announced and is effective from 1 January this year.</p><p> Part 3 of the Bill deals with VAT.  I will not go through the individual sections because they are straightforward.  Part 4 of the Bill deals with stamp duties in sections 79, 80, 82 and 83 which Senators can read.  Part 5 of the Bill deals with capital acquisition taxes, in line with the measures the Minister announced in the budget, whereby all of the capital taxes have moved up three points from 30% to 33%.  That is dealt with in sections 85 and 90.  Part 6 of the Bill deals with miscellaneous provisions in sections 94, 96, 100, 102, 103 and 105.  We can deal with these provisions in greater detail tomorrow.</p><p> The Bill forms an important part of the parliamentary and legislative year.  It will bring us closer to achieving our deficit targets by the end of 2013.  The Government is adamant that we must be below a budget deficit target of under 3% by 2015 and the adjustment required in the context of the budget is a key requirement for Ireland's come-back.  We are doing very well in what is required, but that is a difficult story to tell the people because while at the macro level things are improving significantly, at a micro level people do not see it in their daily lives, as we know from the lives of our constituents.</p><p> The task we face in the Bill and other measures the Government will announce is how to provoke the domestic economy.  How do we have growth-friendly fiscal consolidation as the Europeans call it?  Some might describe that as a contradiction in terms.  On the contrary, we have shown that since 2008 the previous Government and this Administration have effectively taken out &#8364;28.5 billion in that period, yet we have seen growth in the past three years at twice the rate across the European zone.  If one looks at the matrices of the 27 member states and even of the 17 eurozone countries, growth is flat-lining in Spain, France and Italy.  Some shocking examples of the tragedy of the recession are unemployment rates of between 24% and 26% in some member states.  There are quite a few crumbs of comfort and one is in the data for unemployment in the State.  Having been stubbornly high for so long, at 15%, it has been on the way down in recent months and now stands at 14.2%, which is far too high for this economy.</p> <p>It is far too high for this economy.  The No. 1 task of this Government for the rest of this year and beyond is to give an opportunity to people, at the micro level, to get back to work, get the economy working and provoke domestic demand.  By doing that, we can return to the kind of growth rates we all want to see.  Budget 2013 is an essential part of that and we present it in confidence to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="16:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000021#U00200"><p>I must apologise for having a cold.  I welcome the Minister of State to the House.  Notwithstanding the difficulties, having someone with the experience of Deputy Michael Noonan as Minister for Finance, ably assisted by the Minister of State, is something I welcome.  As a nation, we are lucky to have him.  Naturally, the targets remain the same for both sides of the House and what divides us politically is how the ends are achieved.</p><p>  There were choices available in the Finance Bill.  The standard banter in both Houses refers to how the troika insisted on this or the memorandum of understanding dictated the other.  I have attended our delegation's meetings with the troika on numerous occasions.  In each meeting, the troika is specific on the fact that the bottom line must stay the same and how one arrives at the bottom line is up to the Government of the day.  In addition, the previous Government is in the past and our job is to hold the current Government to account.  Notwithstanding that, and taking us back to the Order of Business, we cannot have the Taoiseach and the Tánaiste taking the spoils, receiving awards and appearing on <i>Time</i> magazine and taking the credit for bringing Ireland under control when the Minister for Finance, Deputy Noonan, described the late Brian Lenihan as a brilliant fiscal manager who had taken some bad decisions on banking.  However, he did not blame him for that on the basis that he was provided with poor data at the time.  We must acknowledge these things.  We cannot celebrate the so-called deal for the Cypriots.  How did Fianna Fáil manage to create a crisis in Ireland, Britain, France, Spain, Portugal, Cyprus, the United States, France, part of Germany and Japan?  We have really left behind the GAA and the Catholic Church if our focus------</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1160" speakername="Michael D'Arcy" time="16:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000021#U00300"><p>There is a Fianna Fáil cumann in Japan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="16:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000021#U00400"><p>-----has managed to dictate the pace in all of those countries.  Whatever about the results in last year's season, this is about this year's season.  We must adjudicate on the games, tactics and resources that player managers are using at this moment.  In that context, there were choices to be made on the Finance Bill.  We put forward budget proposals.  Some were the same, some provided alternatives.  Some decisions are unavoidable but in other cases there were clear choices.</p><p>Regarding the universal social charge, 3% or more was expected on incomes over €100,000.  Far from being a measure that would bring down the house, people in that income bracket were ready for the increase.  They expected it to happen.  The Labour Party was pressing for the measure and it did not materialise, which clearly led to some banter behind closed doors.  It was a missed opportunity.  Additional funds could have been provided to offset some of the more difficult measures for families.  Rather than hitting the families, we could have brought in income otherwise.</p><p>The Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Varadkar, seems to agree with, and has put to Cabinet, the idea of a levy on off-licence sales of alcohol.  Nothing has materialised since he did so.  I have a personal view on suicide prevention and a policy paper I wrote suggests the money should be spent specifically on that area of mental health.  An amount of money, €120 million, is available in that area.</p> <p>I refer to the application of the property tax.  There could have been a fairer way and this has been outlined in previous debates.  The principle underpinning the tax is not the issue.  In 1977, the people were done an injustice by Fianna Fáil in government, although the manifesto of every political party in that general election proposed something similar.  That Government did not do us a good service.  We needed to reform how the tax was applied and calculated rather than abolish it but we did not and Governments have been paying for it since.  The regions have suffered because they were unable to finance their own development.  They have been dependent on the proximity of a Minister to bag a capital project in their area, no matter which party is in government.  I do not mean that as a criticism of this Government specifically or to absolve previous Governments regarding their management.</p><p>I refer to mortgage arrears.  I have pushed this issue, even when I sat on the Government benches.  The Minister of State will acknowledge there was much behind the scenes support for my Family Home Bill in 2011 but when we debated it in the House, it was rejected by only three votes.  The Minister of State said during the debate that there was no issue, the code of conduct was going exceptionally well and there was no cause for alarm.  However, the issue has seriously worsened.  We have had the Cooney and Keane reports and any amount of commentary nationally in the House and on the airwaves as interest groups and so on called for measures to be introduced.  The reality is in recent weeks the Government has handed full control to the banks.  Senator Barrett, myself and others have joked in the House over the past few years about the mythical back stairs that seems to be for the exclusive use of developers and bankers.  One wonders whether there has been a virtual seat for the banks at the Cabinet table.</p><p>Given what was announced last week, all that needs to be done is to appoint a banker to the Cabinet because the proposals put them in full control.  I am sure Members are receiving representations throughout the country about this.  Today, acting as an intermediary, I was asked by people in mortgage arrears with a particular bank to be considered for its mortgage-to-let product against my advice.  However, that is the only product they feel they can afford.  I said I would ask for this on their behalf.  The bank came back and said it was not prepared to consider the proposal but that it would allow for a reduced payment for a further three months during which time it expected the people to pay down secondary debt and then be in position to meet full repayments on the mortgage.  That is a fantasy.  This was superficial and not a real engagement to tick the boxes for the regulator or the Government and whoever else oversees the sector.  This interaction will be repeated but now the code of conduct has been amended and the good protections regarding contact by financial institutions and so on have been removed.  Those in distress can effectively be plagued to agree a solution designed by the bank.  How many people have been offered a solution whereby 40% of the loan will be warehoused for 20 years?  Most people in difficulty are aged between their late 20s and late 40s.  Not many of them have been told that having paid off ten years of a 25-year mortgage, they are a good bet because they or their partners will get a job again and the mortgage can be extended to 25 years.  It would help the banks because it would be more profitable for them at the end of day but it would be a major help to the people in difficulty with the knowledge that they can keep their home.  Senator Hayden has been correctly vocal about the rights of people renting in the buy-to-let sector where there will be a focus on repossessions.  A receiver will immediately move to get tenants out in order that the property can be sold because investors want to buy with vacant possession.</p><p>I acknowledge that macroeconomic indicators are coming into line but at what cost?  There were, and are, choices but the Government does not seem to be grabbing them.  There is banter in the House during debates as well as justified criticism and constructive criticism.</p> <p>The Minister and the Minister of State enjoy the support of everyone in reaching the targets set.  However, can we start pushing people out front in the solutions we ought to use?  The precedent set in Cyprus is not a good sign for this country's corporation tax rate or burning depositors, with senior bondholders, rather than protecting them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1160" speakername="Michael D'Arcy" time="16:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000023#W00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to conclude the debate on the Finance Bill 2013 between today and tomorrow.  It is the crucial legislation in raising revenue for the State.</p><p>On Senator Marc MacSharry's points on the 2008 Irish bailout package, Cyprus's deal was deemed so unacceptable that there was not one single vote in its parliament in favour of the package.  That should have happened here when the troika came knocking on our door.  The deal done at the time of our bailout was so harsh and unacceptable that the Government which has taken up the mantle from the previous Government has tried to reorganise many of the conditions imposed.  It has been successful in having the repayment period lengthened and the interest rates reduced.  The conditions of the deal were so bad that both Houses of the Oireachtas at the time could have legitimately voted “No”.  We also see it in the ways the troika has allowed certain terms to be changed such as the arrangement for the promissory notes.  We have also been told there may be further deals in the offing.</p><p>In 2008 €34 billion in revenue was raised through taxes.  This year it is projected that €43 billion, with €1 billion in rates, will be raised.  In five years there has been a significant increase of €10 billion in the tax take coming out of individuals' pockets, corporations, retailers and many other businesses.  The public spend in 2008 was €49 billion, while this year it will be €48 billion.  All of the adjustments are being made on the side of the tax take.  Some may not be pleased about where we stand with expenditure on social welfare, owing to the fact that there are so many more out of work, or in servicing the national debt.  While we are making cuts in Departments, we are spending more in these two specific areas.  Individual spending is also tight.  Even those who always had money to spend now find it tight.  This, in turn, impacts on economic growth and without growth, the show will be over.  This also goes for Europe and member states.  In the United Kingdom the budget projected economic growth of 0.6% this year, which makes one wonder.</p><p>The big salaries in the public sector, as well as those in the private sector, are unjust.  There was much discussion earlier about the pay of the chief executive of Bank of Ireland, Mr. Richie Boucher.  I am not referring to him, but to the pay of the 1.8 million workers in the private and public sectors.  We are told about their gross pay, but there is no discussion whatsoever of their net pay.  We keep hearing about fat cats and greedy civil servants.  After they pay their taxes, however, there are not that many who are in receipt of €450 and €850 in take-home pay.  I accept that take-home pay of €850 is large.</p> <p>I am saying that take-home pay of €850 is in the region of €100,000 per annum but when taxed the figure is reduced and a person on that income would not take home 50% of it.  That is the reality.  I am keen to see a discussion and debate about the real moneys that are going into people's pockets, that is, net pay.  I have made this point on several occasions and I am bored repeating it but I believe I must continue to make it.  There is a gap between people who are working and those who are not working but the reward for those working is not enough to bridge the gap.  I am not referring to impoverishing people who are not working but I am suggesting that people must be rewarded if they get up and go to work.  A significant quantity of people do not take home €500.  Such people go to work but it costs money to put a car on the road and to tax, insure, fuel and service it and so on.  There are no tax breaks or anything else in this Bill for people who must commute.</p><p>The Pobal HP deprivation index published some time ago shows that the area of most deprivation now is the commuter zone.  I am keen to see some target based on those who commute.  I live in Gorey, some 61 or 62 miles from here.  The number of people on the N11 travelling north every morning is remarkable.  I would go so far as to say that many of those people are in the territory to which I am referring, that is, with a take home pay of €500.  To put a car on the road and get here and home every evening costs a great deal of money.</p><p>Everyone should be focused on this issue because these are the 1.8 million people, the worker bees, who are keeping the economy going.  They will bring in €15 billion in income taxes in this calendar year as well as paying their share in VAT, excise and other payments.  People who work contribute perhaps in the region of 60% to 65% of the total but it is difficult to put a finger on the exact figure.  I am not discounting others who are paying taxes but I am saying these people are at their limits and there is no more left in terms of taxing these people or increasing excise for the fuel for the cars they drive to and from work.  The people in the country who are being most ignored in the debate on taxes are the workers and at some stage we need to refocus on them.</p><p>Many people refer to the fact that there is no wealth tax.  We are getting close to a rate of 40% for capital gains tax and 40% for capital acquisitions tax and other taxes dating back to the pre-McCreevy era, when it was at 40%.  The figure has increased from 30% to 33%.</p><p>Section 30 includes the living city initiative.  I welcome this section as a pilot initiative but we need to broaden it.  I have commented on the commuter zone.  Some areas in the commuter zone are larger than some cities.  The population of Waterford is 40,000 but some of the commuter zone towns are almost as big.  However, for historical reasons we chose to ignore these commuter towns.  The Pobal HP deprivation index has indicated that the commuter zone is the most deprived and we should focus on it.  I am referring to crucial sites that will be of real benefit in the regeneration of certain areas, sites that represent a huge negative.  I am not referring to going crazy as we did in the past with property-based tax incentive schemes but there are areas that need something.  I do not suggest I know for certain exactly what that something is but we cannot continue to ignore it or allow those areas to stagnate or stay as they are, because within a period they will begin to reverse or go backwards.  It is even more difficult to stop an area declining when it start to decline, and some already have.</p> <p> I welcome the retention of the position whereby social welfare payments will be exempt from the USC and PRSI.  I made the point about the gap between those who are working and those who are not.  I believe we should not impoverish people who are not working.  However, we cannot ignore the fact that at the peak of the boom there were 140,000 people who did not work.  We were bringing in tens of thousands of people from outside the European Union to work here.  We choose to ignore this because it is an unpleasant fact.  I made the point that there are not 440,00 people unemployed in the State - just 300,000 - because the 140,000 who were not working then are still not working, but they get the same payment as the person who has worked for the past 30 or 35 years and who has paid contributions and paid income tax, health levy and other levies that existed before being combined in the universal social charge.  How can it be legitimate and just that those people who never worked are in receipt of the same payments as people who have worked for decades?  Under the old stamp system, the more one paid in, the longer one got paid, but the regulations have changed.</p><p>It is important that Fianna Fáil does not go &quot;Dallas&quot; on us.  Deputy Micheál Martin cannot be like Bobby Ewing and step out of the shower and ask if what happened over the past five years was just a dream.  It was no dream.  Some people are living a nightmare because of the actions of Fianna Fáil and a senior Minister in that Government.  Deputy Martin cannot just choose to ignore that.  This is not &quot;Dallas&quot; for many people.  These are difficult times and not much fun. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1176" speakername="Katherine Zappone" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000025#Y00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House.  I agree with how Senator MacSharry started and acknowledge the fine work done by Deputy Noonan, assisted by the Minister of State, Deputy Hayes.  As Deputy Hayes said, the Government has made many positive changes at macro level.  What we are hoping now is that people will be able to feel that in their day to day lives.</p><p>Senator D'Arcy spoke about the gap between those who are working and those who are not and suggested that work needs to pay off for people.  As the Minister of State knows, many of my concerns for the next year or so relate to the need to see the impact of the changes at macro level.  How will they impact on the working poor and their children?  Will we need more changes in order to increase the gap between the income at which decisions are made in order to protect people and the income people make from their work?  That may be what we need to do.  I wonder how many days or months should go by before such changes are felt at the micro level.  What are the targets, particularly in the context of poverty, to which we need to attend?  I acknowledge the work that has been done and hope the change the Department hopes for will follow. </p><p>I wish to focus the rest of my remarks on the miscellaneous section towards the end of the Bill.  Part 6 deals with issues that are critical for a significant minority of our people.  I note that significant work has been done for this minority over the past couple of years.  My comments, therefore, will look both backwards and forward.  This all started when we debated the final Stages of the Finance Bill in 2011, when I put forward a number of recommendations seeking to achieve parity between same sex and opposite sex couples in the tax code. </p> <p>The Minister, Deputy Noonan, graciously agreed that I had identified a disparity with regard to tax relief on maintenance payments.  The tax relief on maintenance was available to a spouse in marriage at the time of a deed of separation or a judicial separation.  In the case of civil partners, tax relief on maintenance payments was not a possibility until annulment or statutory dissolution.  That meant there was a significant time differential between the time married couples and civil partners had to wait before tax relief kicked in.  The Finance Bill 2012 subsequently provided that when a civil partnership breaks down and a legally binding agreement between the parties is drawn up, this agreement can be recognised for tax purposes.  It was a creative resolution.  The Finance Act 2012 placed civil partnerships on the same footing as married couples in so far as it accepted that following the break-up of a relationship, people may continue to live under the same roof while being considered separately for income tax purposes.</p><p>While these changes sound quite technical, they are very significant for a huge minority of our people.  Almost a year after I pointed out the inequalities that led to these changes, I identified further areas of inequality between civil partnership and civil marriage during the debate on the Finance Bill 2012.  The Minister, Deputy Noonan, kindly gave an undertaking that the remaining gaps would be addressed in as far as constitutionally possible.  The welcome changes necessary to fill these gaps are contained in the Bill before the House.  They resulted from an exchange between the Department of Finance, the Revenue Commissioners, the Office of the Attorney General and me.  I want to express my sincere gratitude to the Minister, his Department, the Revenue Commissioners and the Office of the Attorney General for examining my recommendations and for meeting me and the taxation expert and barrister, Dearbhla Cunningham, who has assisted me in bringing about these changes.  When the Minister of State spoke, he did not mention the three significant changes that are involved in section 103, which is in Part 6 of the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="16:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000026#Z00200"><p>I was trying to leave time for everyone else.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1176" speakername="Katherine Zappone" time="16:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000026#Z00300"><p>I will note one or two of them if that is okay.  Maintenance payments made to a former civil partner for the support of a child after a separation will not be treated as income and therefore will not be subject to tax.  That is a very good thing.  It is one of the big changes.  The second change amends the Taxes Consolidation Act to ensure that in a break-up situation, the transfer of property between civil partners under a deed of separation will no longer be subject to capital gains tax.  The same thing applies to married couples under a deed of separation.  The third change amends the Capital Acquisitions Tax Consolidation Act 2003, under which there is a tax benefit when assets are moved between people who are related to each other.  The 2003 Act sets out what types of relationships can avail of these benefits.  The amendments being made in this legislation will ensure that the civil partner of a person's child will be included for these purposes.  If a person wishes to gift assets to the civil partner of his or her child, the civil partner would receive the gift at a more favourable rate as a result of this measure.  This is currently the case for the spouse of a child.  When all of these changes kick in, they will enable parity of treatment between civil partners and married couples.  I welcome the changes being made in this Bill, which constitute a major achievement on the part of the Government.</p><p>  When I first raised these issues a couple of years ago, I expressed concern that the children of civil partners were not receiving tax treatment equivalent to that received by the children of married couples.  The civil partnership Act does not recognise a legal relationship between a civil partner who is a parent and the non-biological child he or she is raising.  The Act does not extend to civil partners and their children the same legal rights or responsibilities that are automatically accorded to married couples.  It is interesting to note that the Finance Act 2012 and the proposed Finance Bill both acknowledge the relationship between a non-biological child and the parent who is raising him or her by providing for parity of tax treatment between such a child and the child of a married couple.  The Revenue Commissioners have indicated, in effect, that the tax treatment of the children of civil partners should in all circumstances reflect the treatment of the children, stepchildren and adopted children of spouses.  I welcome this progressive development.</p> <p> On the issue of constitutionality, given we had to work within the parameters of constitutionality in terms of these changes, we do not yet know if marriage equality is prohibited under our Constitution as the Supreme Court has not yet interpreted on this question.  It may be the case that marriage equality could be provided for by the introduction of legislation, and I note that a Bill recently launched by Senator Bacik would certainly help this process.  In a matter of weeks, as the Minister of State knows, the Constitutional Convention will examine and vote on the question of marriage equality.  For the moment, we do not currently have parity between opposite-sex couples and same-sex couples in our laws, although I know that one day we will.  In the meantime, nearly 1,000 couples have entered into civil partnership since it was introduced in 2011.  These changes will have a very real impact on the day-to-day lives of these couples and their families, for which I am very grateful.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000027#AA00200"><p>It is important to remember that this Government is not presiding over a giveaway budget in the way previous Governments were fortunate enough to do.  Indeed, it is also fair to recognise there has been criticism of this budget, in particular criticism around the taxing of maternity benefit, extending the universal social charge and so forth.  It would be wrong of us to sit here in a self-congratulatory way and not acknowledge there is discontent out there in regard to some of the provisions of the budget.  At the same time, it is also important, particularly during a Second Stage debate, to highlight some of the important things that are contained in this budget.  I believe quite strongly that this budget does pave the way for improvement in our economy.  In particular, I believe it is a pro-business budget designed to stimulate job creation.  Some of the measures in this Bill will be of particular benefit to Ireland's SME sector, which is a welcome departure given the SME sector is responsible for 70% of all of the jobs in this country.  While we will be discussing this in more detail tomorrow, the Bill does set out quite clearly the details of the ten-point tax reform plan and the two additional measures in the Bill which the Minister of State outlined and which have been particularly welcomed by SME sector representatives.  It can be said that this budget is positive for business.  It clearly shows this Government is willing to take innovative measures to stimulate business and encourage job creation.</p><p>As I said, there are aspects of this budget that people do not like.  This is not unusual when a Government has to make savings in the way this Government does.  However, I believe the measures that have been imposed in the budget have been fair and the measures that have been included in the Bill are, as a result, also fair.  This is evidenced by the breadth of the attacks that have been made by the Opposition on the Bill, particularly in the focus among some of the Opposition groups on the so-called tax on childbirth.  As a woman and a mother myself, I would like to make a brief comment on this.  The current arrangement gives - I want to emphasise this - additional benefit to working women.  There is no denying that having a child is an expensive time and that people incur additional costs, but those costs are no extra on a working woman than they are on an unemployed woman or on a woman who stays at home and whose husband is at work.  The situation is that we have an anomaly in our tax code and what we are doing in this Bill is removing that anomaly.  I would like to see benefits extended to all women in some form in recognition of the additional costs that are incurred on the birth of a child.  I would ask that this be made a priority when this country is put back on its feet.  At the same time, I will not stand over an anomaly just because it benefits one particular group of women when other women are excluded from a similar benefit.</p><p>It is important that, irrespective of the financial condition a country is in, budgets have to be about reform, and as a corollary, therefore, Finance Bills also have to be about reform.  I believe there are positive steps in this budget.  In particular, I would like to highlight, as I did last year, the increases in capital taxes.  I believe it is fair to say this country has for too long been dependent on personal income tax as the chief form of personal taxation.  We have had the local property tax as a way to remedy this, although I must say it would have been better if the current Opposition had introduced this at a time when we had the money to replace the tax on earnings from work at the same time, so it would have had a neutral effect on its introduction.</p> <p>However, we are not fortunate enough to be in that position.  </p><p>Aside from taxes on property, there are other forms of taxation that are also very important in spreading the tax burden.  The measures contained in this Bill, which raise capital gains tax and capital acquisitions tax by 3% and continue the trend of last year's budget of bringing taxes on unearned income into line with taxes on earned income, are to be welcomed for a number of reasons.  It is important to restate this because there seems to be a level of amnesia about what went on in this country.  The halving of capital taxes by a previous Fianna Fáil Government played a significant part in the promotion of a &quot;get rich quick&quot; culture which dogged the Celtic tiger economy and encouraged speculation in property over investment in real job creation.  Why would anyone spend years developing a patent when one could buy an apartment off the plans and sell the benefit of the contract without ever doing a day's work?  </p><p>More importantly, it is important that the tax system be fair.  A tax system that requires those who have the resources to earn through investment by purchasing shares or who inherit wealth to pay less than those who earn their living through employment is not a fair system.  This Government must continue to equalise the manner in which tax is levied on income, regardless of whether that income is gained through investment, inheritance or employment.  It is not right to tax someone who works an extra hour in a factory or in a front-line job such as a garda more for every extra hour worked than someone who makes money trading in shares.  </p><p>The Minister has indicated in respect of the property tax and the Finance Bill that he is willing to take on board the comments made.  I congratulate Senator Zappone because I know from previous debates on this matter that she has fought and campaigned long and hard on the issue of the tax status of same-sex couples and has worked extremely hard to promote through every available opportunity the constitutional rights of same-sex couples.  I very much support her and congratulate her on her achievements.  </p><p>I also welcome measures in this Bill that are very progressive.  I wish to highlight the introduction of real estate investment trusts, REITs.  Effectively, REITs allow investment in property to be owned collectively in a company structure.  Individual shareholders are liable for income tax on income distributions from the REIT and must pay capital gains tax on share disposals.  This is a very welcome development in which I have been very interested for many years.  There is no doubt that the Irish property market has taken a severe hit in the past few years.  There is little or no appetite at the moment among individuals to invest even at a time when values are very good.  REITs have worked well in other countries, particularly in the US and the UK, because there is capacity to invest collectively in property which spreads the risk over a portfolio and arguably - the evidence supports this - improves property management.  While most of the commentary on REITs since the budget has focused on them in the context of commercial properties, there is even larger potential in the residential area.  </p><p>As we know, the Governor of the Central Bank and the Minister have indicated that there should be repossessions in the buy-to-let market given the levels of arrears in this sector.  I have raised concerns on many occasions in this Chamber as to what impact repossessions will have on tenants living in these repossessed properties, bearing in mind that one in every five families now lives in a rented property and risks severe disruption if these repossessions are not handled properly.  There is incredible opportunity for the buy-to-let properties to be bought by a REIT which would bring professional property management to bear on these situations, providing a clear benefit to the country.  REITs should be encouraged in this context.  </p> <p> I also welcome the living city initiative which makes provision for new urban renewal schemes for the refurbishment of Georgian buildings in our cities.  These schemes are to be introduced on a pilot basis in Limerick and Waterford, but I agree with Senator Michael D'Arcy that they should be expanded into the wider construction sector.  The position in that sector is extremely difficult.  The sector is running at a figure of approximately 3%, but in any normal developed economy, it should be in the region of 10%.  I accept that urban renewal schemes attracted a bad name during the 1980s and I am well aware that some of the buildings constructed in Dublin, for example, are the slums of tomorrow, if not today.  On previous occasions I referred to the plight of town centres.  It is truly shocking and depressing to witness their degradation.  In the context of the willingness to enter into further consideration of schemes such as those to which I refer, I ask the Minister of State to examine the possibility of including town centres.  Perhaps we might establish a living town initiative before the level of degradation becomes so severe it cannot be countered.</p><p>I am a great believer in the tax code being used for community gain.  Rents are rising and those on low incomes are finding it very difficult to access certain properties.  In the same way that we use tax incentives - I refer, for example, to section 50 initiatives - to provide student accommodation, I strongly request that consideration be given to using similar incentives to make rental properties available to those on very low incomes.  A great deal could be done if tax incentives were used for the benefit of society.  There are many legitimate ways in which the tax code can be used.</p><p>I will end on a somewhat negative note.  The Minister for Finance, Deputy Michael Noonan, indicated in the Dáil that he could not consider poverty-proofing budgetary measures on an extensive scale because of the number of staff that would be required to achieve this.  It is extremely important that we work to poverty-proof the measures that will be contained in future budgets.  If it proves necessary to redeploy staff in this regard, that should be done.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="17:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000029#CC00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State.  On the Order of Business the Leader was asked to emphasise to him and the Minister for Finance, Deputy Michael Noonan, the importance of deposit insurance.  Both Megan Greene who we introduced to the Minister when she attended an international conference last year and Professor Christopher Pissarides, the Nobel prize winner from Cyprus, have stressed the importance of such insurance.  This is part of the crisis management in which the Minister of State, the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, Deputy Brendan Howlin, and the Minister for Finance have been engaged for the past two years.  We have been trying to stop the rain coming in through the roof, but we must also look at some of the remaining architecture.  We must ask what happened to the deposit insurance which was supposed to have been in place throughout the European Union and also why it is necessary to repeatedly engage in carrying out emergency repairs.</p><p>By way of explanation and apology, I point out to the Minister of State that the final draft of the Bill reached Senators after the deadline for recommendations.  As a result of the fact that the numbers of some of the recommendations may change, we may appear to be at even greater cross purposes than usual in our discussions.  This is explained by the fact that we have just had a long weekend and no one can be blamed for what has occurred.  I certainly do not wish to lay the blame at anyone's door.  I much prefer the use of the word &quot;recommendation&quot; as opposed to &quot;amendment&quot; when it comes to discussing the Finance Bill.  Recommendations give rise to a much more reasoned debate and do not simply involve trying to put the Government out of office or whatever else we might attempt to do in the context of how we normally operate.</p><p>In the context of the difficulties in which the country found itself and from which the Government, with the support of the House, has been trying to extricate it, there was a certain amount of groupthink involved.  It was groupthink in favour of construction.  On reading through the Bill, I became concerned by the fact that a certain level of groupthink continued to obtain.  There are certain sections which we will discuss in detail on Committee Stage in which the Government is continuing to seek to bolster the construction industry.  We must be extremely cautious because we did this previously and it did not work.  In fact, it wrecked the country.  Why are concessions included in respect of shops established adjacent to the Georgian areas contemplated in the living city initiative?  As Senator Michael D'Arcy indicated, the reason there are no shops is an additional €10 billion has been levied in taxation.  Providing subsidies in order that people might establish shops next to buildings which happen to be old does not appear to make sense.</p> <p> Why is there a subsidy for a building in which to hold aircraft?  The aircraft sector in Ireland is booming.  How did it manage to get this concession in the Bill?  It makes me fear that a feature of the Finance Bill, as Senator MacSharry and others have observed, is that lobbyists prevail.  We need the promised legislation on lobbyists who were previously far too influential and after reading the Bill I fear they have been at it again.  Why is film relief still provided?  </p><p>I appreciate what the Minister of State and the Minister did on issues such as the promissory notes in an effort to shore up the creaking European edifice.  We had a domestic problem which needed attention and to which several Senators have referred.  I note that the Minister of State is nodding in agreement.  The Culliton review pointed out that Ireland had far too many tax lawyers and accountants who had been too influential.  There is a defensive note in the Minister of State's contribution that indicates that it was not all written on Merrion Street.  I think those involved on Merrion Street should get out more and meet people.  I was delighted to hear the Secretary General of the sister Department, Mr. Robert Watt, say at the Statistical and Social Inquiry Society of Ireland last week that he intended to get involved more with economists.  He is leading by example.</p><p>The old property-based economy did not work.  The system allowed people with more tax lawyers and accountants to obtain special tax breaks for themselves.  As the Minister of State knows, we never quantified them.  We did not conduct a regulatory impact assessment or a cost-benefit analysis.  That has to end.  We cannot have a system which benefits a handful of individuals and imposes huge costs on the rest of us when we are trying to balance the books.  There is a need for a lot more regulatory impact assessments of proposals. </p><p>The Bill has two sections dealing with research and development.  An bord snip nua tried to find out the results of Ireland's massive investment in research and development, but it could not get an answer.  An report on innovation was published in 2010 in which Mr. Colm McCarthy again asked when we would we see a return.  The amount of money poured in is unknown to us because it is done by way of tax breaks, rather than by direct expenditure.  Society needs to know whether these schemes are worthwhile.</p><p>I question any attempt to push up the price of land or property.  I am worried about the old sections 17 and 19.  Section 21 in the old numbering provides for tax breaks for hotels, guesthouses and self-catering accommodation and we bankrupted the country building empty hotels.  I, therefore, beg the Minister not to start again.  I ask him to ensure some new thinking in the Department.  These measures start small and are very difficult to correct.  We are then back into bubble territory in which so much damage was done in the past.</p><p>Section 30 provides relief for industrial buildings for commercial aircraft.  I do not know why this relief is provided for, although I appreciate what Senator Aideen Hayden said.  Why should the Government become involved again in giving tax breaks for property?  We have to get the economy, as well as the banking system, away from this.  It is still a system based on property.  We made that mistake with disastrous consequences for the country.  Let us not go there again.  I look forward to a full and comprehensive debate on Committee Stage tomorrow.</p><p>The ideal characteristic of the tax system is that it should be equitable.  As Senator D'Arcy said, it should not distort the position on work.  I was worried to see in the Mangan report the models for various forms of child benefit schemes.  The benefit proposed for those on family income supplement would have left two thirds of the working poor worse off.  This issue must be examined immediately.  I am concerned that Mr. Dan O'Brien has noted that during the boom we reclassified many unemployed persons as recipients of disability and invalidity payments, thereby precipitating the increase, more than in any other country in Europe, in the number of houses in which nobody worked, even in a time of full employment.</p> <p>Did we massage the figures?  I do not think so.  Perhaps generously we increased the number of people receiving disability and invalidity allowances but that had horrendous consequences later on.  Senator Michael D'Arcy made the point that we need a gap between those people who work and those who do not take home pay.</p><p>The Mangan report is really weak in the way that it evaluated the family income supplement.  As Senators will know, IMF studies show that Ireland spends more on social welfare, public pay and capital expenditure than other OECD countries.  In order to refocus the economy we should examine those provisions in order to redress the balance.  It is important that the tax system is not used to repeat the mistakes that harmed the country so much.</p><p>A former director general of the IMF now works in the University of Cambridge, Mr. Vito Tanzi.  He is no relation to the much missed Mr. Paul Tansey who reported so eloquently and whom I wish was alive to comment on the Irish economy.  Mr. Tanzi outlined why most countries are in trouble with their public finances and gave solutions.  He quoted a former chief executive of Solomon Brothers as stating &quot;laissez-faire is all well and good until something goes wrong.&quot;  Perhaps we should make allowances and make the decision that if businesses are too large to fail then they are too expensive to rescue.  The Department and the Government should say that the businesses have failed a market test and are at an end.</p><p>Mr. Tanzi was also concerned about the growth in lobbying.  A lobbyist can prove that a handful of people will benefit so proper cost benefit analysis is never carried out now.  We should ask ourselves whether the remaining 4.5 million people in the country will be worse off?  We need legislation because it is too easy for lobby groups to succeed in this country.  The casino banks did us no favours.  The complexity of the tax system also means that the arm of the tax lawyer and accountant is completely unproductive.  Therefore, we need some simplifying measures.</p><p>Mr. Tanzi expressed his concern at the growth in the number of lobbyists at the end of his book.  We need a new beginning for this aspect of finances.  I appreciate that the Government has been distracted by having to hold the entire system together.  However, I am disappointed that the Finance Bill is so old hat and does not evaluate the outcomes.  The country is short of money so we must ensure that the people who have been given tax breaks in the Bill are worthy recipients.  It is impossible to tell unless we conduct more analysis and that is why we asked for the regulatory impact assessment.  </p><p>The Bill should be referred, as the IMF intended, to the Irish Fiscal Advisory Council because we need to hear more views and guard against repeating mistakes.  Some of the provisions in the Bill were contained in Finance Bills from ten years ago and look where they led us.  I thank the Leas Chathaoirleach for allowing me extra time and I also thank the Minister of State.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="17:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000031#EE00200"><p>I thank the Senator and I call Senator Paul Coghlan who has six minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="17:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000031#EE00300"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House and thank him for his overview of the Bill and explanation of the various sections.  I appreciate that we will have more time to deal with them individually tomorrow.</p><p>  I welcome the Living City Initiative.  It will be a successful project for urban regeneration.  It is a constructive and targeted intervention that has the potential to make a real and substantial difference to an area that requires regeneration of which there are many, particularly in Waterford and Limerick where the pilot projects will commence.  The impetus behind the initiative is to provide a tax incentive to people who are brave enough to restore an old church or property in an area designated part of the Living City Initiative.  Incentives will only be available if the person intends to live in the restored property as an owner-occupier and as such is not suitable for speculative development.  I welcome the initiative.  </p><p>  Ireland has a significant stock of Georgian houses and many are in areas that have seen a high level of dereliction, decay and deprivation.  The cities of Limerick and Waterford have suffered greatly in recent years and merit inclusion in the scheme.  I want the pilot scheme extended to some of the core areas in Dublin which have a substantial stock of vulnerable Georgian housing in areas of intense deprivation, in particular the north Georgian core area around Mountjoy Square and Parnell Square.  The residential area has suffered significantly from urban decay and would benefit from targeted regeneration. </p> <p>I understand that a range of local and national groups are supportive of the extension of the pilot scheme to this area, including the Mountjoy Square Society, the Irish Georgian Society, the Dublin Civic Trust, and our own colleague, Senator David Norris.</p><p>I understand from the Minister's comments in the select committee and in the Dáil that he fears an extension of the pilot scheme at this stage to this area of Dublin could jeopardise the State aid payments for the entire scheme.  I am not sure I follow that logic.  If the scheme is targeted properly by reference to defined criteria, it should be possible to submit the scheme for approval, with some area of the capital included, provided the objective criteria for inclusion of the areas by reference to levels of deprivation are clear.  I urge the Minster to engage with the relevant groups in the area to determine whether progress can be made rather than allow another period of dereliction and decay to endure.  A scheme such as this could be a real impetus for regeneration in areas requiring renewal and, as we are aware, these areas certainly fall into that category.</p><p>On the question of the appointment of receivers, I am concerned about the trigger-happy tendency on the part of some banks that is prevalent in some instances to appoint receivers to businesses in circumstances in which there are viable alternatives.  I do not wish to comment on high-profile cases currently before the courts, but it strikes me that a new approach in this area is needed.  For example, is there a role for the Credit Review Office to hear a submission from a business owner who believes that the decision to appoint a receiver is premature?  Mounting a legal challenge to a well-resourced bank can be a daunting task for most distressed businesses, and I suggest some alternative mechanism is urgently needed to put a check on banks that behave unreasonably in that regard.</p><p>In this climate, nobody deserves to be taken to court without any notice.  That is happening to many people, and it is wrong.  I know of one case where the business owner thought he was getting on very well with his bank but, without any notice, the bank took that person to court.  That should not happen.  That is the reason the Credit Review Office could be useful in putting a break on those matters.  It is about protecting the jobs.  When that precipitative action happens, it jeopardises jobs.  I know of another case in which more than 100 people were employed but three of them took fright and left immediately when this happened.  Unnecessary damage is being done to businesses.  It upsets staff, which is understandable.  In the case of hotels and so on, it has an effect on bookings and even weddings, which are very good business.  Those losses must be curtailed by avoiding such precipitative action because when it happens, it further limits credit.  We should take this issue very seriously.</p><p>We spoke earlier about the frightful damage being done to our town centres throughout the country in the way planning departments have allowed projects to go out of towns to the disadvantage of town centres.  The Living City initiative is bringing this to my mind.  That is an area we must examine also if we are to have vibrant towns, to which we pay so much lip service.  Perhaps there could be a focused approach in that regard also.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" speakername="John Gilroy" time="17:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000032#FF00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State.  The Finance Bill is the single most important item of legislation in the legislative year, along with the Social Welfare Bill, and we would do well to carefully consider its contents.  Things are looking a little bit brighter, but we need not overstate what is happening.  It is our third year of growth.  Exports are doing well.  Our reputation is much enhanced and investor confidence has returned.  We have had deals on our promissory notes and our other euro debt.  We sold CoCo bonds and sovereign bonds recently.  We returned to the markets successfully, and we are about to get rid of the bank guarantee.  Those are good developments but, in addition, we need a deal on legacy bank debt, which I believe we will get after the German elections in September.  All of those developments are irrelevant, however, when we consider that unemployment is the main crisis facing us.  If the high level of unemployment is not reduced, the benefits we are trying to achieve in this Bill - and every other Bill we bring to the House - will not be felt by real people, so to speak, which is the reason we are here.</p><p>An hour and 25 minutes ago I had a conversation with a young man who is unemployed.  He was self-employed during the boom years.  He has a wife and a four-year-old daughter.  He told me he cannot afford to buy clothes for his four-year-old girl.  That is shocking, and it is a terrible thing to happen to anyone.  That is the reality facing him and many other people in our society.  When we debate the Finance Bill we must not forget the real stories and the real people.  If that young man is listening to me he would ask whether the Bill we are discussing here will make a difference to him and his family, including his little girl.  We must acknowledge - the Minister acknowledged it in his opening statement - that while the macro-indicators are positive, and I have outlined how positive they are, the micro-indicators are not being felt in our communities.  We must keep that in mind and do everything we can to focus on that.</p><p>The answer I would have to give this young man is that unless we can close a €13 billion deficit, which is a shocking figure considering we have already taken over €20 billion out of the economy, nothing will make any difference to us.  I have heard suggestions that we could introduce a higher rate of tax for higher earners or even a higher level of universal social charge for higher earners.  I have some sympathy for that argument, and there may be some scope to do that.  However, if we were to try to close the deficit by taxation measures alone, we could put 20% onto all tax heads in the next budget, if we were happy to do that, but it would destroy the economy.  We must find a balance between cuts and revenue-raising measures.  That is a dreadful decision to have to make.  Dreadful decisions have been made, and further dreadful decisions will be made, but we can avoid making those decisions.  The Labour Party and Fine Gael have a history in that regard.  The Minister will recall being told about the time in the 1980s when we, as a Fine Gael-Labour Party Government, failed the people of this country by postponing those decisions, and the result of that was ten years of stagnation.</p><p>In terms of what we need to do now, we need to make the decisions.  If I were to say anything to that young man, his wife and his little girl it would be that we must make the decisions now.  The worst is probably behind us, but a considerable effort will be needed to achieve the benefits of the recovery that is ahead of us.  I welcome the senior Minister, Deputy Noonan, to the House.  He said some time ago that if we do things right the economy is ready to spring forward and the benefits from that will accrue to everyone.</p><p>This young man told me he would do anything for his wife and family.  We would all do that.  He also said he wanted to make a difference.  I had prepared a great speech for this debate that would touch on all the wonderful topics of our time but having spoken to this young man I tore it up and asked myself if there is a real possibility that we, as politicians, are forgetting the reason we are in these Houses.  Do we really understand the decisions we make and the impact of those decisions on the lives or ordinary people?  That young man might make a difference - he probably has - but when we are arguing over the detail of this Bill on Committee Stage tomorrow we should remember that none of us in this Chamber has ever been faced with the prospect of being unable to buy clothes for his or her four-year-old.  That is a shocking indictment.  We should remember that.  This is not the usual Second Stage speech, but it is no harm to remind ourselves of the reason we are in this House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" speakername="Feargal Quinn" time="17:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000032#FF00300"><p>The Minister is very welcome.</p> <p>I was very taken by Senator Gilroy's words in respect of the young man and his four-year old daughter for whom he could buy clothes.  His question was what will this do to help that situation.  I appreciate the Minister has taken a number of steps to ensure that we move in that direction.  </p><p> I have been advocating for the release of some pension funds to allow citizens some relief and to get cash flow in the economy.  I welcome the move to allow people access to 30% of their additional voluntary contributions. This will help thousands of people who are in trouble.  It is a forward-thinking move which will be of benefit to people who need cash now.  </p><p> I draw attention to a recent article by Mr. Richard Curran in the <i>Sunday Business Post, </i>entitled &quot;How Noonan can encourage spending&quot;.  In it, he said that if you cannot pay your mortgage or your credit card loan or you simply do not have any money to spend, what good are your pension savings to you?  Pensions may be useful for the future but many people are trying to deal with the financial challenges of the present.  He also said that. &quot;Such a measure will create an economic stimulus as people would probably spend the money they receive.&quot;  I am glad the Minister has heeded those views.  However, I would like him to allow people to take a certain amount of their AVCs tax free, say, the first &#8364;10,000 and pay the 41% on the rest.  This would encourage more people to access the cash they need.  Will the Minister consider an amendment to reflect a small amount, say, &#8364;2,500?  He must realise that people are being crippled by household debt.  If a person or an SME could access &#8364;2,500 tax free tomorrow, they would, perhaps, pay off a credit card debt and several overdue bills and get back on their feet.  The possibility of a person starting all over again is very exciting.  If a person can do that, then we have set the conditions for them to start their own business, which is what we are all hoping we can encourage.  That is what government should be all about, not giving them a job or providing for them, but setting the right conditions for them to make their own way.  That is why I urge the Minister to consider an amendment whereby a small port of the AVCs can be accessed tax free. </p><p> We should also consider a measure to allow businesses tax free access to pension funds linked to expansion of their businesses or taking on new employees.  This could be considered a Government nudge in that it would allow businesses to access cash if they wish to expand.  As a business person and what every businesses person will say is that cash is king.  Businesses need to get going.  If they could access a little more cash it would open up many possibilities.  There are savings and there are pensions.  I have been involved in Link Finance Limited, in which I declare my interest, because it aims to facilitate peer to peer lending.  That is an example of what the private sector is doing to help SMEs.  I think the Government can permit businesses to access cash by allowing them some access to pension funds.  </p><p> People argue that we should not allow any access to pensions but the point I would argue is that the Government has already dipped into people's pension funds with the pension levy.  Even the Government's National Pensions Reserve Fund has been used for the short term.  Why can an individual or business not access some small portion of them as the Government has done?  I stress now is the rainy day.  There is no point in opening up pension funds in five years time.  We need to allow businesses to survive now by allowing them access to much-needed cash.  This could also provide a massive stimulus to our economy.</p><p> In 2009, Denmark allowed people to take a portion of their pension funds to cover immediate expenses rather than wait for retirement.  Approximately 94% of those who had pensions took out some of their money and the economy was stimulated to the extent that GDP increased by 1.4%.  Imagine the benefits if our GDP had a similar rise and the benefit to the SMEs who were able to access cash and expand, or even to survive.  The Irish Brokers Association said that allowing people early access to their pensions has the potential to unleash &#8364;1.5 billion and to get 50,000 distressed borrowers out of financial trouble and it could support 7,300 jobs for a period of three years.  If we introduce a similar measure we might free up a portion of the estimated &#8364;100 million held in voluntary Irish savings to create confidence in the economy.  It would have a flow-down effect, not just for persons getting access to some of their pension but it would get people spending again and benefit large parts of the community.</p><p> We need to get people spending again.  This release of money would be a way to do it.  Will the Minister consider this idea in the context of the Bill and even an amendment to it.  If we do so, we could support the SME sector even further.  I am sure the Minister can see the inherent sense of this simple idea.  While I welcome the limited access to the AVCs we could go further by simply allowing SME access to a small portion of cash locked up in pensions.  Given that the Bill improves the conditions for research and development tax credit, there are other things we can do.  Sweden introduced what is known as the earned income tax credit in 2007.  The measure offered strong incentives for lower skilled people to work and marked a fundamental change for Sweden.  The so-called earned income tax credit was reinforced in 2008, 2009 and 2010.  The stated motive of the reform was to boost employment, in particular, to provide incentives for individuals to go from unemployment to at least part-time work.  It has given some lower paid workers the equivalent of a month's extra salary every year.  Even the Swedish Finance Minister, Anders Borg, did not expect that his tax cut for the lower paid would increase economic growth so much that it has almost entirely paid for itself.  It would be worth the Minister's while having a chat with the Swedish Minister for Fiance.  It appears to be a real success story.  He did it in 2007 and repeated it in 2008, 2009 and 2010.  It is a success story of putting money back into the economy and creating jobs.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" speakername="Terry Brennan" time="17:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000033#GG00200"><p>Ar dtús cuirim fáilte roimh an Aire ar ais go dtí an Seanad.  While there are six Parts to the Bill and 108 sections, I can assure him I do not wish to speak on the 108 sections.  He will be pleased to note that I wish to refer to three, in particular, the sections dealing with SMEs, the local property tax and the rebate to HGVs and bus operators.</p><p>The Bill builds upon the SME supports introduced in the budget and includes a number of new measures to support SMEs.  These are welcome.  The SME sector is close to my heart.  I believe it will be the driver of economic recovery in every county across the country and the Government is committed to supporting this key sector.  I am delighted to acknowledge this fact.  The SMEs are the key provider of jobs across the country and with more than 250,000 private sector jobs lost between 2008 and 2011, it is this sector that will lead the recovery in the domestic economy and will create the jobs to make the serious inroads into our all too high unemployment levels.  Our unemployment figures are still far too high as I have stated on a few occasions.  </p><p>Each of the measures included in the Bill is designed to help this critical sector to trade, to grow in new products and in new markets, to sustain existing and, most important, to create new jobs.  If each of the SMEs was to create one job - I am not sure of the total number of SMEs in the country but it is in the region of 200,000 - that would be 200,000 or if 50% was to create one job, it would be in the region of 100,000, one can imagine what that would mean to the economy.</p> <p>These initiatives will build on the supports that are available through Departments, agencies and the measures introduced to support credit flow into the SME sector.  The Minister's initiatives to improve credit flow are to be applauded.  It is fitting that the Government should do everything in its power to support small and medium enterprises to grow and develop.  The Minister is doing so.  The ten-point tax reform plan introduced and announced in the budget includes measures to make a real difference to the SME sector such as reforming the three-year corporation tax relief for start-up companies, increasing the cash receipts basis threshold for VAT, amending the close company surcharge to improve SME cashflow and extending the foreign earnings deduction for work-related travel to certain additional countries, including countries in Africa.  The key employee provision of the research and development tax credit regime is amended to reduce from 75% to 50% the proportion of time such an employee must spend solely on research and development activity to qualify for the credit.  The amendment should assist small and medium enterprises to avail of the provision.</p><p>The Bill includes a small number of amendments to local property tax.  The changes apply in specific circumstances.  The local property tax as it applies to the vast majority of taxpayers is unchanged.  An amendment to provide an exemption for properties affected by pyritic heave is being finalised.  It is proposed that where a property has been certified to standards specified by the National Standards Authority of Ireland as having been affected by pyritic heave, an exemption from local property tax can be claimed.  That is rightly so.  The deferral of local property taxes will be permitted in circumstances in which the personal representative of a deceased person's estate is responsible for payment.  The deferral is for up to three years to allow for the administration of an estate without causing cash flow issues for personal representatives.  The deferral is for a limited period to avoid creating an incentive to deliberately delay the administration of an estate to avoid the payment of local property tax.  Any increase in the chargeable value of the property arising from expenditure on modifications to accommodate a disabled person may be disregarded, which is welcome.  Properties owned by local authorities and approved housing bodies will be deemed to be valued in the lowest valuation band for the first valuation period.</p><p>The Bill also gives effect to the auto diesel excise duty relief for licensed and tax compliant hauliers which was announced by the Minister in his Budget Statement.  Following further consideration, the relief will be extended to bus and private tour operators.  Will it apply to the national carrier, Bus Éireann, from 1 July 2013?  To be parochial, I come from the most scenic part of the country, the Cooley Peninsula, where there are a number of HGV and private bus operators.  Having made several representations and been on delegations, I commend the Minister for listening to us at an early stage.  The provision is of great significance to HGV and bus operators.  More than 300 people in my part of the world work in heavy goods and bus operations.  The provision will be a great boost and create jobs for HGV and bus drivers and bring more tourists to the most scenic peninsula in the country.</p><p>I acknowledge the significant contributions the Minister for Finance, Deputy Michael Noonan, the Minister of State, Deputy Brian Hayes, and their departmental officials have made to the compilation of the Bill.  Cúpla mí ó shin, dúirt an tAire liom go mbeimíd &quot;all right&quot; agus sin mar atá sé.  Go raibh maith aige.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1155" speakername="Kathryn Reilly" time="17:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000034#HH00200"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House and acknowledge the comments by Senator Gilroy about the importance of listening to real stories about the real experiences of people in the real world.  As legislators and elected representatives, it is important that we are able to listen to people and relay and record their stories in the Oireachtas to ensure their plight is known.</p><p>There are 11 specific references to the principle of fairness in the Fine Gael and Labour Party programme for Government.  On the formation of the Government, we were told it was committed to forging a new Ireland built on fairness.  We were promised that by the end of the Government's term, Ireland would be recognised as a modern, fair, socially-inclusive and equal society supported by a productive and prosperous economy.  We were told that the Government was committed to tackling the economic crisis in a way that was fair, balanced and which recognised the need for social solidarity.  Despite these clear commitments, the Bill presented to us today is anything but fair.  The Minister's second Finance Bill embeds his second budget and, like its predecessor, its impact will be to increase poverty and inequality in Irish society.  Recently released statistics show that child poverty in Ireland is among the worst in the EU and is increasing.  This is not just my view.  The Economic and Social Research Institute produced reports on each of the Government's budgets which demonstrated that more income is being taken from the less well-off in society while the upper echelons are being protected.  Even in the worst days of its Government, Fianna Fáil did not have the brass neck to so brazenly hit the poor while protecting the wealthy.</p><p>While some people will have doubted Fine Gael's commitment to fairness, many believed that a Government including the Labour Party would ensure that whatever pain was introduced would be focused on those most able to pay.  ESRI reports have shown that the most regressive budgets introduced since the start of the economic crisis in 2008 have been those crafted by Fine Gael and Labour Party Ministers.  There were alternatives.  Senator MacSharry mentioned earlier that there were choices.  A long list of organisations presented fully-costed alternative budget proposals.  Sinn Féin produced an alternative budget and parliamentary questions record our costed proposals, bar the wealth tax.  The proposals crafted by Sinn Féin and other organisations representing the people about whom Senator Gilroy spoke earlier were ignored.  Senator D'Arcy mentioned earlier that there are some positives in the Bill and it would be remiss of me to ignore them.  The increase in capital gains and acquisition tax is to be welcomed, notwithstanding that it is too modest.  The additional restrictions on some tax avoidance schemes are also positive although much more could have been done.  The excise duty relief for hauliers and transport providers is a very necessary support for a very important sector of the economy which is genuinely struggling.  However, these measures cannot outweigh the overwhelmingly negative impact the budget will have on ordinary people.</p><p>Before the Minister entered the Chamber, Deputy Brian Hayes spoke about the macro versus the micro picture and said that things were looking better in terms of the former.  The effect is just not trickling down to the micro level and people's ordinary lives.  Members, including myself, will have been out knocking on doors in the Meath by-election.  Elections give one the chance to connect on a more personal level with the people one represents.  Just this morning, I knocked on a door and the woman who answered told me that her belt was getting tighter while the wealthy seem to be getting fatter.  People are suffering and it is having a knock-on effect in terms of confidence in public representatives and institutions, including the Oireachtas.  Significant increases in indirect taxation through excise duties and certain tax treatments are going to take much-needed spending power out of the pockets of low and middle-income families.</p> <p>This will take much-needed spending power out of the pockets of low and middle income families.  It will make their lives harder, as we all hear from ordinary people, and will damage the businesses that rely on them for trade.  Although there are measures in the Bill aimed at SMEs we have to consider what taking money out of people's pockets does to the domestic economy and the spill-over effect on small businesses and trade.</p><p>Taxing maternity benefit for new mothers, adoptive benefit and the health and safety benefit are clear indications of this Government's priorities.  It will push many struggling families further into financial hardship while protecting wealthier people.  There is no third rate of income tax for high earners.  There is no real wealth tax, not even the moderate increase in the universal social charge for high earners as proposed by the Labour Party.  This Bill does not demonstrate the fairness mentioned 11 times in the programme for Government.  This legislation is unfair.  Poverty and equality proofing of future budgets would go a long way to address many of the inequalities so far brought forward.  Families and the domestic economy are hurting which hampers our social and economic recovery.  That is why we will be opposing this Bill.</p><p>I have one question for my own information, if the budgetary process is being brought forward to October this year will there be another Finance Bill by the end of the year or will it be introduced next January?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/955" speakername="Michael Noonan" time="18:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000035#JJ00200"><p>It will be this year.</p><p>I thank the Senators for their comments during what has been an interesting and informed debate today.  I am sorry that I was not here for the whole debate but the Minister of State from my Department, Deputy Brian Hayes, substituted and left me some notes.</p><p>This Finance Bill marks another step on our journey to economic recovery.  As the Minister of State noted earlier we continue to see signs of economic recovery.  Things have begun to turn around.  It is worth looking again at some of the statistics: we are on track to bring the deficit below 3% of GDP by 2015, our banks have been recapitalised and regained access to borrowing markets.  The economy is expected to record its third straight year of growth in 2013.  For last year as a whole GDP growth of 0.9% was projected and my Department expects growth to increase this year to 1.5% and to strengthen further over the medium term.  The signs are positive.  We know, however, that there are no quick fix solutions.  Our progress to date has been hard won and we still have some way to go.  As the Minister of State remarked, it is difficult for people to see this progress yet at the micro level.  As we continue to resource the sustainability of the public finances this Government has also been mindful of protecting the emerging economy.  We outlined several steps in budget 2013, including the ten-point plan for SMEs but we must acknowledge that for the moment Ireland is in a programme of financial assistance.  We have made firm commitments to bring down our deficits to sustainable levels by 2015.  These we have consistently achieved.</p><p>We are endeavouring to be fair, to ensure that the burden is spread.  We know that when marginal rates of tax are very high jobs are lost.  Indirect and capital taxes have a less adverse impact on employment.  That does not mean that the wealthy should not carry the principal burden of the tax.  I remind Senators that the OECD has consistently assessed Ireland highly for its progressive taxation system.  It is estimated that in 2013 the top 5% of income earners will pay 44% of the total income tax with those earning €50,000 or less, as 78% of income earners, paying 19% of the total.  Furthermore, it is estimated that 841,000 individuals, some 40% of the income tax base, will be exempt from income tax.</p><p>Unemployment remains our biggest challenge and that is why so many of the measures in the Finance Bill 2013 are aimed at maintaining and creating employment, particularly in the SME sector which is one of the key drivers of the economy.  This is why it is important that the Bill begins to implement the ten point tax reform plan announced in the budget.  This plan includes measures such as reforming the three year corporation tax relief for start-up companies, increasing the cash receipts basis threshold for VAT, amending the close company surcharge to improve cash flow for SMEs and extending the foreign earnings deduction for work-related travel to certain additional countries.</p><p>The Bill should also be viewed as just one element of a wider strategy to support economic activity.  It is complemented by the action plan for jobs 2013 which the Minister for Enterprise, Jobs and Innovation, Deputy Richard Bruton, recently published.</p><p>I will now address the points raised by Senators today.  As always on these occasions the debate was wide-ranging and matters were raised which go well beyond the Finance Bill and its contents.  I am sure Senators will understand if in the very limited time available to me I will concentrate on addressing issues which relate directly to the Bill and to the policies it reflects.  I thank Senators MacSharry and Zappone for their words of encouragement and I agree that we all seek to achieve the same outcomes but perhaps in different ways.  Senator MacSharry implied that the Government had missed an opportunity to raise revenue by increasing the USC rate by 3% to 10% on those earning in excess of €100,000 per annum.  The position is, however, that there is already a 10% rate of USC which applies to the income of the self-employed in excess of €100,000 per annum.  To increase the USC rate of charge by 3% to 10% for PAYE income earners with incomes in excess of €100,000 would have the effect of increasing the top marginal rate of tax for such individuals to 55%.  This relates to the points raised by Senators D’Arcy and Zappone regarding the need to ensure that there is some reward for work.  Marginal tax rates are very important because they influence individual decisions to work more or indeed to work at all.  The OECD working paper, Tax and Economic Growth, indicates that there is also &quot;the possibility that high top marginal rates will increase the average rates paid by high-skilled and high-income earners so much that they will migrate to countries with lower tax rates resulting in a brain drain which may lower innovative activity and productivity&quot;.  High marginal tax rates may also incentivise a greater level of tax evasion and contribute to the development of a shadow economy.</p><p>Senator MacSharry also suggested that we have a choice with regard to being apply a levy on certain alcohol sales.  Legal advice was received on the proposal which found that it would be likely to breach EU directives on alcohol taxation.  I thank Senator Zappone for her welcome for the changes set out in section 103 and in particular for drawing my attention and that of my officials to the omissions.  I welcome Senator Hayden's comments supporting the introduction of REITs to the Irish market, the two particular issues the Senator highlighted, the risk spread benefits of collective investment and the potential for improved professional standards in the rental property market are two of several significant benefits which it is hoped that the REITs will bring to the Irish market.  I thank Senator Hayden also for her comments clarifying the equity principles behind the taxation of maternity benefit.  The description of this measure as a tax on childbirth by certain Members of the Opposition is disingenuous in the extreme.  Income tax can of course be applied only to income and only those individuals or couples who have sufficient incomes to attract a liability to income tax will be affected.  I note also her support, and that of Senator D’Arcy, for the living city initiative.</p><p>In response to Senator Barrett's concerns I emphasise that the REITs regime is not a tax relief.  It can be better understood as a structural reform of property investment structures allowing for lower risk sustainable long-term investment.  In fact the overarching objective of the REITs regime is to remove a tax bias caused by a double layer of taxation which has typically discouraged collective investment in the property through a company.  Senator Barrett asked why the aviation sector measures are included in the Bill.  These measures were included in order to encourage employment intensive companies engaged in the maintenance, repair, overhaul and dismantling of commercial aircraft to set up here.  Ireland is already a major global centre for aircraft leasing.  This provision will further enhance its attractiveness.</p> <p>With regard to the employment and investment incentive, EII, the hotel sector currently employs 51,000 individuals.  Since the downturn in the economy, approximately 100 hotels have been placed in receivership or have ceased trading.  Access to funding will permit hotels to invest in refurbishment and enhancement.  In order to qualify for EII, hotels must be considered to be tourist traffic undertakings and, as such, will be required to have three-year development and marketing plans approved by Fáilte Ireland.</p><p>Senator Barrett also raised the issue of cost benefit analysis in respect of the research and development tax credit.  The Senator may be interested to know that the Department of Finance has already announced a comprehensive review of the tax credit, which will take place throughout 2013.  The terms of reference of the review have been published on the Department's website.  One of the central purposes of the review is to ensure the research and development tax credit gives value for money to the Irish taxpayer and, accordingly, a cost benefit analysis will be included.</p><p>I appreciate the views of Senator Quinn in respect of tax-exempt access to additional voluntary contributions, AVCs, and access to the main pension fund.  However, contributions to AVCs benefitted from marginal tax relief when invested.  We must also strike a balance between access to funds and ensuring people are encouraged to make adequate provision for their retirement income.</p><p>Senator Gilroy referred to the case of a self-employed person with a four-year-old child whose business failed, leading to severe problems.  These cases are extremely difficult.  In seeking to remediate them through the tax system, we need to make sure we do not widen the problem and create a bigger problem for other families.  We are in a programme and trying to work our way out of a bankrupt situation.  In that respect, we are still running a major deficit and so every concession made on tax must be made at the expense of another set of taxpayers.  Any concession made, whether the measures suggested today or others, can only be achieved if I tax somewhere else.  Senators must remember that.</p><p>The debate here and in the other House tends always to highlight the very difficult cases of individuals.  There are some very difficult cases for individuals but by highlighting these one tends to forget the generality of cases, which one cannot personalise in the same way.  In trying to correct the hard case, one damages the general situation and that is one of the dilemmas.  It is a question of judgment whether one taxes this or does not tax that.  At present, we are in a position of very difficult choices but as the economy continues to grow and as we work our way out of this, I hope we will be positioned to give relief to those most in need where we will not need to raise taxes elsewhere so that we can use the fruits of growth to relieve the difficult situation of our poorest families and to move on.  I hope the economy will grow and continue to grow.  It is growing this year, it grew last year and the year before.  If we could get greater growth rates, many of our problems would be solved at a quicker pace.</p><p>We will return on Committee Stage and I look forward to a debate on the detail of the Bill.  I thank the Senators who contributed to the debate and we will deal with the specifics later.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.122/1" nospeaker="true" time="18:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000036#KK00200"><p>Question put:</p><p>The Seanad divided: Tá, 23; Níl, 13.</p><p>Tellers: Tá, Senators Paul Coghlan and Aideen Hayden; Níl, Senators Ned O'Sullivan and Diarmuid Wilson.</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.122/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2013-03-20" time="18:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000036#KK00200">
            <divisioncount ayes="23" noes="13" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" vote="aye">Ivana Bacik</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" vote="aye">Terry Brennan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" vote="aye">Colm Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1114" vote="aye">Deirdre Clune</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" vote="aye">Eamonn Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" vote="aye">Paul Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1124" vote="aye">Michael Comiskey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" vote="aye">Martin Conway</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" vote="aye">Maurice Cummins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1160" vote="aye">Michael D'Arcy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" vote="aye">John Gilroy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" vote="aye">Aideen Hayden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1152" vote="aye">Imelda Henry</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" vote="aye">Caít Keane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" vote="aye">Marie Maloney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" vote="aye">Mary Moran</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1134" vote="aye">Tony Mulcahy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" vote="aye">Michael Mullins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" vote="aye">Susan O'Keeffe</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" vote="aye">Pat O'Neill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1163" vote="aye">Tom Shehan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" vote="aye">Jillian van Turnhout</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1176" vote="aye">Katherine Zappone</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" vote="no">Sean Barrett</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1147" vote="no">John Crown</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" vote="no">David Cullinane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1119" vote="no">James Heffernan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" vote="no">Marc MacSharry</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" vote="no">Rónán Mullen</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" vote="no">Denis O'Donovan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1142" vote="no">Ned O'Sullivan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" vote="no">Trevor Ó Clochartaigh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1115" vote="no">Labhrás Ó Murchú</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1154" vote="no">Averil Power</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1155" vote="no">Kathryn Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" vote="no">Diarmuid Wilson</mpname>
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.122/3" nospeaker="true" time="18:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000036#KK00200"><p>Question declared carried.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="18:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000036#KK00300"><p>When is it proposed to take Committee Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="18:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000036#KK00400"><p>Tomorrow.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.125" nospeaker="true" time="18:10:00"><p>Committee Stage ordered for Thursday, 21 March 2013.

Sitting suspended at 5.55 p.m. and resumed at 6.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.126" nospeaker="true" time="18:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000037#MM00100">Restorative Justice Process: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="18:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000037#MM00200"><p>I move:<blockquote><br />That Seanad Éireann:acknowledges the Government's commitment to further develop and expand the restorative justice process throughout the State;<br />reiterates the rights of victims of crime to receive appropriate information, support and protection and to participate in criminal proceedings, where appropriate;<br />acknowledges and affirms the work of the National Commission on Restorative Justice;<br />notes that the Probation Service, in partnership with community based organisations, is engaged in the promotion, development and delivery of restorative justice initiatives and that the extension of restorative justice programmes is a strategic priority for the Probation Service;<br />recognises the experience and positive outcomes associated with the application of restorative justice in Northern Ireland;<br />recognises the work of the Nenagh Community Reparation Project, the Restorative Justice Service and Le Chéile Restorative Justice Project in the provision of restorative justice pilot programmes in their respective areas;and calls on the Government:to support the Minister for Justice in the development and extension of restorative justice to the greatest possible extent, as a nationwide non-custodial option available to the criminal justice system; and<br />to commit to the implementation of EU Directive 2012/29/EU of the European Parliament and Council of 25th October 2012 establishing minimum standards on the rights, supports and protection of victims of crime.</blockquote>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Kathleen Lynch, for the debate on this important motion.  When I was first elected to Seanad Éireann, I was appointed to the Oireachtas committee on justice.  As part of my work on this committee, I was a member of the penal reform sub-committee which was researching and reporting on better ways of dealing with penal reform.  Part of that process involved visits to Mountjoy Prison and Cork Prison, as well as St. Patrick's Institution.  I was struck by the number of people who should really not have been in prison.  Being there was going to do nothing for them or society.  Unfortunately, prison life does not augur well in preparing people for life after incarceration.  Despite the best efforts of prison governors and staff, prison life is harsh and can make inmates angry.</p><p>  Do the victims of crime want this?  Do they understand prison life does nothing to rehabilitate the offender, the person who committed a crime against them?  We are leaders in our own right and here to improve society, to make it a better place.  I do not understand how society benefits from having young men, in many cases possibly for their second or third offence, in prison.  I have been trying to identify a better way to deal with this.  Going through my work programme for the year with my parliamentary assistant, I was explaining my frustration following these prison visits.  My assistant asked me if I had ever heard of the restorative justice process, which I had not.  After tabling this motion, I have found that many of my colleagues have not heard of it either.  This debate is, accordingly, timely.</p><p>  The National Commission on Restorative Justice produced a valuable report in 2009 which outlined the benefits of such a system.  For those who are not aware of it, it is a means by which the victim and the offender are brought together through a restorative conference process.  The victim has a central role in ensuring the perpetrator of the crime against him or her understands the impact the crime has had on him or her.  It appeals to the good nature of the majority, even criminals.  The process does not have any legal status for adults, but it does for children.  The 2001 Children Act provides the juvenile courts process with a restorative justice framework and speaking to those who have used it, they regard it as successful.</p><p>  The Probation Service and An Garda Síochána have done their best to embrace the principles of restorative justice through several successful pilot projects in south County Dublin and north Tipperary.  The latter was extended from covering Nenagh specifically to include the whole of north Tipperary.  There is also programme in place in parts of Limerick city.  I welcome Ms Nadette Foley from Facing Forward and some of her colleagues to the Visitors Gallery who are gently pushing the principles and philosophy of restorative justice.  The reality is that the Irish Prison Service is not working.  Incarceration costs &#8364;65,000 per year per prisoner, while the cost of the restorative justice process is &#8364;3,500.  The victims of crime in society deserve a better deal, as do offenders.  Restorative justice clearly offers a better deal for the victim, the offender, the public interest and society.  It is a process for which the country can set best practice internationally, as we have done through our peacekeepers and missionaries.</p> <p>We have set best practice in areas such as the smoking ban and in myriad areas throughout the short period of our democracy.  Our neighbours in Northern Ireland have set best practice in restorative justice but I believe this country has the wherewithal to create a new thinking, a new way of dealing with crime, a new way of ensuring that the victims of crime and their needs become centre stage and that the communities in this society which have been the victims of crime, of which there are many, take centre stage.</p><p>The figures speak for themselves.  The pilot programmes have shown that 78% of offenders who engaged in the restorative justice process have not re-offended.  Can we say that 78% of prisoners who have served their sentences and gone back out have not re-offended?  Absolutely not.  This is a win, win, win situation.  It is a case of &quot;Yes&quot;, &quot;Yes&quot;, &quot;Yes&quot;.  The reality is that this approach is cheap, cost-effective, it treats people as human beings, it respects the dignity of all people, it respects the dignity not only of the victim but also of the offender and it respects the dignity of their families.</p><p>In the course of being introduced to this process I attended some very worthwhile lectures which took place throughout the city.  I heard from genuine volunteers who are working under the radar trying to deliver a message of difference and hope, a message that we can do things differently, that we can do things more cost effectively and that we can do things while respecting the human dignity of everyone.  We have a great society.  This will not cost money; in fact it will save money.  This is something that must happen; there is no alternative.  The Irish Prison Service is bursting at the seams and it is not working.  This is clear if one goes to any of the prisons.  I have been there as have members of the Joint Committee on Justice, Defence and Equality.  It is proven beyond doubt that they are overcrowded, primarily with people who should not be there in the first place.</p><p>The pilot programmes in existence in south Dublin, north Tipperary, Limerick and within the youth services should be extended nationally.  The Government should make the resources available to run a properly-funded national restorative justice programme.  We have the expertise in terms of the restorative justice community, who are doing great work.  We have the expertise within the Probation Service, which is a partner in this process.  We have the expertise within An Garda Síochána, which is embracing this in the various areas.  I have attended lectures at which members of the Garda have spoken about their pride in the programmes of restorative justice.  We need to take this and run with it.</p><p>I am pleased that no counter motion has been tabled.  I hope this motion will receive the unanimous support of Seanad Éireann.  It is probably the first time that a restorative justice motion has been put forward in the House and received unanimous support and that is useful.  The Joint Committee on Justice, Defence and Equality, through my work, has agreed to a module on restorative justice.  I hope we will invite in some of the participants to give evidence and then produce a report for Government on how a national programme could be run effectively.  The results speak for themselves.  I commend the motion to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Maloney" time="18:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000038#NN00200"><p>Before I call on Senator Burke to second the motion I welcome the Minister of State at the Department of Justice and Equality, Deputy Kathleen Lynch, to the House.  I neglected to do so at the start of the debate.  You are always a welcome face here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="18:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000038#NN00300"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House.  I thank my colleague, Senator Conway, for bringing forward this motion.  I fully support and second the motion.  This issue is something we need to address in this country.  That is something we have not done in real terms.  There has been little if any major reform of the criminal justice system and little has been done to see if there is a better way of dealing with the criminal and assisting the victim.  This is something we need to do.  It was Gandhi who said that an eye for an eye will leave the whole world blind.  While victims seek to ensure that perpetrators are identified and brought to account for their actions, the vast majority are keen to ensure that the person who has perpetrated a crime does not repeat it.</p><p>Unfortunately, the criminal justice system we currently have is like a revolving door.  One need only go to any of the courts to find that the people before the courts were there six months ago, 12 months ago, 18 months ago or two years before that.  In other words, this is not their first time in the courts.</p><p>The motion refers to a directive from the European Parliament dated 2012.  The purpose of the directive is to establish minimum standards on the rights, support and protection of victims of crime.  The articles refer to the need for the victim to understand and be understood, receive information, be heard, have access to victim support services, enjoy safeguards in the context of restorative justice services, be protected and enjoy privacy and be individually assessed to identify specific protection needs.  The directive states that practitioners likely to come into contact with victims should be trained and that member states should provide data and statistics to the European Commission.  The directive is focused on the issue of victims because until recently victims were excluded from the process.  This motion includes victims in a way such that we can have the person involved in the crime and the victim working together with the local community with regard to looking at a better way forward, rather than what we have done in the past.</p><p>It is interesting to consider the report of the National Commission on Restorative Justice.  It presents restorative justice as a forward-looking, problem-solving approach to crime which involves the parties and the community generally in an active relationship with various agencies.  It argues that restorative justice brings victims and offenders into contact with each other and gives victims an opportunity to get answers to questions that are of direct concern to them.  It also gives victims a chance to explain to offenders the real impact and consequences of their wrongdoing.  Accordingly, it can be a significant experience which may provide the victim with a degree of closure, a point singularly important following any crime; it is crucial to ensure that the victim feels that there is closure at some stage in the process.  Far too often victims see no closure.</p><p>Earlier I referred to reform in the criminal justice system.  The Minister of State will probably be aware of a project dating from 1996 in Cork.  The project was led by Colm O'Herlihy who works in the Irish Prison Service.  It was an important project.  We have a revolving door prison system but we are not proactive enough in trying to steer people in a different direction.  The project was done in Cork Prison.  He got approximately 20 people who were in prison to go on an education programme.  At the same time he got their partners, who were not in prison but who were giving support to the prisoners, to go on an education programme as well.  When they came out of prison approximately 12 of the 20 went back to full-time education.  This goes to show what real reform is about.  That was one project which was very successful and it is a pity that we have not done more like it.  While we have done some work, we need to do a good deal more.  This process of restorative justice must be developed, encouraged and put in place far more extensively, rather than then simply relying on two pilot projects.</p> <p>Compared to the 1996 project, it was a success, but unfortunately we have not done enough of a follow-up to ensure that success will benefit others.  I welcome this motion and fully support it.  It is a case of all of us working together to try to bring about the change required.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="18:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000039#OO00200"><p>I support this important motion and thank Senator Conway for making the effort and going to the trouble of putting the motion before the Seanad.  I compliment him on the diligent and effective work he does as a member of the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Justice, Defence and Equality.  As a member of that committee, I am acutely aware of the tremendous interest and effort he has put into it.</p><p>It was the Fianna Fáil Party which introduced the pilot projects on restorative justice and initiated the National Commission on Restorative Justice in 2007 to set out the potential for restorative justice in Ireland.  It is imperative that victims are placed at the heart of the justice system and that offenders face the full rigour of the law, with a view to curbing recidivism and making amends for the wrongdoing that has been done.  We have inherited the British common law system of penal justice, which is outdated and in need of reform.  We recognise that the principal stakeholders in the restorative justice system are the victims, the offenders, the community and the State and it is important we consider all these aspects of our system.  I am convinced of the Hegelian notion propagated by Trotsky or someone like him that we have a thesis, antithesis and synthesis, but unfortunately our society has never gone the full hog to a state where we have no crime.  I wish that was the case.</p><p>The report of the National Commission on Restorative Justice describes restorative justice as an &quot;invaluable cost effective option&quot; for the criminal justice system.  The report states that the cost of running such a programme or pilot project is approximately €3,250 per adult, compared to the €97,700 required annually for a prisoner in detention.  The report also suggests and estimates that annual savings of up to €8.3 million can be made by replacing prison placement with the use of restorative justice and suggests expansion nationwide of the two trial projects currently in place in Tallaght in Dublin and Nenagh in County Tipperary.  It should also be noted that court referred conferences are mandated under the Children Act 2001, to explore ways in which young persons can take responsibility for their behaviour and its consequences and, where possible, make amends to victims.  It is important we tackle crime by young offenders as closely as possible in this manner because once people become habitual criminals, it is more difficult to get through to them, particularly if they have passed the age of 18 or 21.</p><p>I made the point here previously that the relationship between our system and society is somewhat like that between Pontius Pilate and Our Lord and their society.  The demand of society is to &quot;crucify&quot; the criminal.  As a solicitor and politician, I have often come across the attitude that we should just lock up these young criminals and throw away the key.  While that might be a short-term solution, it is not right.  We should always seek a better solution.  I have visited Cork, Mountjoy and Portlaoise prisons and in those prisons I have come across many prisoners who have mental illness problems.  These could be the result of the abuse of drink or drugs and some people may have been abused growing up.  Professional counsellors and psychotherapists should be available to prisoners.</p><p>When I visited Cork Prison many years ago, I found that while there were approximately 350 prisoners, they only had one psychotherapist available to  them and he visited only one day a week.  I met the man involved and he told me he could do with visiting every day and could do with two or three assistants, because of the number of prisoners there who needed help.  If a person is given a six or 12-month sentence and is then released without having received any assistance of this nature, the easiest thing for that person to do is to fall back into the same trap, thereby creating the revolving justice system mentioned by Senator Burke and others.  Whether we like it or not, that is what we have.  </p><p>Fianna Fáil believes that the justice process should be as inclusive as possible and that the outcome should be lead and shaped by local people.  Local solutions for local issues should be the shared goal for both the community and the criminal justice system.  We understand that the system needs to deal with serious crime, but in the case of low-level crime, it is vital we involve the community in so far as we can.  We need to be responsive to the needs of victims and we need to use the criminal justice resources effectively to provide protection, redress and rehabilitation.  Ultimately, whatever route we travel, we must ensure that those who offend face the full rigours of the law and that victims remain at the forefront of the justice system.</p><p>The experience elsewhere and from the two pilot projects indicates that restorative justice serves as a real alternative to locking up offenders, reduces re-offending and gives victims a sense that they are at the centre of the justice system.  I wait anxiously to hear the Minister of State's response and I thank Senator Conway for raising this issue.  I am not always so decent to the Government side, but I thank all of them for exploring this important initiative across the political boundary because it is above and beyond politics.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="18:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000039#OO00300"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Kathleen Lynch, to the House and look forward to hearing her response to this debate.  I commend Senator Martin Conway on his initiative in putting this important motion to the House.  I also welcome the groups represented in the Visitors Gallery, who agree it is very important we debate this issue, particularly in the wake of the report of the National Commission on Restorative Justice.</p><p>I have a strong interest in this area.  Along with Senators Conway and O'Donovan, I have shared in the work being done by the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Justice, Defence and Equality in the area of penal reform.  Next Wednesday, we will publish a report on the issue which will complement this debate because it focuses on the back door strategies or end of sentence strategies and on issues such as remission and the community return programme.  The committee has been looking at addressing overcrowding and appalling conditions in prisons and at addressing the high rates of recidivism or re-offending through dealing with end of sentence and sentence management within prisons.  Therefore, it is useful that tonight we are debating issues around the pre-sentence and how we can divert offenders away from custody in the first place.</p><p>Restorative justice has a long history in Ireland.  In our indigenous legal system, the Brehon law system which predated the introduction of the common law system, there was a very well-established restorative justice model, whereby the families of a victim were paid an honour price by the offender by way of reparation for the wrong done to the victim's family.  This is a traditional model we share with other indigenous systems.  However, this system has been overwhelmingly replaced in our modern criminal justice system by retributive principles, whereby people are given a sentence proportionate to the seriousness of the crime they have committed, on a sort of &quot;just desserts&quot; or proportionate basis.  While this is a standard model of criminal justice, there are many problems and flaws within it, as mentioned by Senators Conway, Burke and O'Donovan.  We have rejected other models such as deterrents and incapacitation.  I believe we should emphasise rehabilitation as a model more in our sentencing system, but I also believe restitutive or restorative justice has a very important role to play and I would fully endorse the recommendations of the commission in terms of implementing these on a national basis.</p><p>We have some existing models in statute.  We have a provision in our criminal law whereby judges can order compensation be paid by an offender to a victim.  Although this is not used as extensively as it could be, it could be built into a more structured restorative justice system on a national basis.  Under the Children Act 2001, we also have a provision, at the juvenile stage, for victim offender mediation.  It is worth noting that the interest in restorative justice has taken off in modern Ireland since the second have of the 1990s.  Therefore, this is all fairly new.</p> <p>The pilot projects mentioned by Senator Conway began in 1999, when approval was received for the payment of grants through the probation service.  Those projects in Nenagh and Tallaght were analysed at some length when the National Commission on Restorative Justice, which was established in 2007, issued its final report in 2009.  Importantly, this work was predated by the Oireachtas oral hearings on the benefits of restorative justice methods in Ireland, which took place at the Joint Committee on Justice, Equality, Defence and Women's Rights in 2006.  The committee's report, which was launched in January 2007, contained ten recommendations proposing that restorative justice be developed as a more regular feature of the Irish criminal justice system.  A good deal of work has been done.  Later in 2007, following the publication of the joint committee's report, the then Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform launched the National Commission on Restorative Justice.  Our distinguished predecessor in this House, Dr. Mary Henry, who has a long-standing interest in restorative justice, was among the members of the commission, which was chaired by Judge Mary Martin.</p><p>The report of the National Commission on Restorative Justice contained some exciting and clear recommendations relating to the potential of restorative justice with regard to diversion from prison.  It suggested that &quot;between 290 and 579 persons due to be sanctioned before the courts could be diverted from being given a custodial sentence&quot; and that this could bring about &quot;a reduction of between 42 and 85 prison spaces per annum&quot;.  That would be an important part of an overall programme of penal reform or decarceration.  In any of these models, there is always a danger of &quot;net widening&quot;, as it is called in criminology, whereby people who might not otherwise have been sent to prison are brought into the net.  In other words, we need to be mindful that judges tend to impose restorative justice orders on people they might not otherwise have sent to prison.  The commission has recommended that the restorative justice model should be confined to people who would otherwise be serving sentences of up to three years.</p><p>As I have said, the commission's recommendations are very important.  Most notably, it recommended that the models of restorative justice should be rolled out with nationwide application by 2015 at the very latest, that restorative justice should be grounded in legislation and that the probation service should continue to take the lead as part of a multi-agency approach.  All of us would endorse those important recommendations and would concur with what Senator Conway said when he welcomed the somewhat limited extension of the pilot projects.  We all want the 2009 report to be followed up.  We want a national strategy, building on the great work that is still being done in Nenagh and Tallaght, to be developed.  Senator Conway mentioned the work that is being done in this regard by Le Chéile in Limerick.  There is a need for further monitoring and for an up-to-date review of the way restorative justice programmes are operating.  There is no doubt that these programmes will be of huge benefit to our criminal justice system when they are rolled out nationally.  I commend Senator Conway for taking this initiative.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/982" speakername="Kathleen Lynch" time="18:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000040#PP00200"><p>I wish to mention at the outset that the previous Government put in place the first project of this kind.  We need to acknowledge that Máire Hoctor, who served as a Minister of State in one of the areas for which I am now responsible, was instrumental in putting the project in place.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="18:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000040#PP00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/982" speakername="Kathleen Lynch" time="18:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000040#PP00400"><p>When the victims of crime and their families are interviewed on their way out of court - this generally happens in cases of far more serious crimes - one seldom hears them expressing satisfaction with the end process.  Regardless of how well-intentioned the court process is, in most cases neither the perpetrator nor the victim is terribly satisfied with how justice is administered.  I join others in congratulating Senator Conway for tabling this interesting motion, which I am addressing on behalf of my colleague, the Minister, Deputy Shatter.  He cannot be here this evening, unfortunately, because he is in Brussels this week in his capacity as Minister for Justice and Equality.  He sends his best regards.  He has a deep interest in this area.</p><p>Restorative justice is a system of criminal justice that focuses on the rehabilitation of offenders through reconciliation with victims and the community at large.  It uses processes that bring those harmed by crime or conflict, and those responsible for the harm, into communication with one another.  It enables everyone who is affected by an incident to play a part in repairing the harm and finding a positive way forward.  In welcoming the opportunity to discuss the motion and listen to the contributions being made, I particularly thank the Senator who tabled this motion for his support of important victim-sensitive measures within the criminal justice system.  There have been differing interpretations of the evolving concept of restorative justice.  We do not always find perfect consensus with regard to it.  We should base our development of this form of criminal justice on the definition arrived at by the National Commission on Restorative Justice, which operated between 2007 and 2009.  The definition provides that &quot;restorative justice is a victim-sensitive response to criminal offending, which, through engagement with those affected by crime, aims to make amends for the harm that has been caused to victims and communities and which facilitates offender rehabilitation and integration into society&quot;.</p><p>The Minister intends to develop and extend restorative justice practices to the greatest extent possible and offer them as a nationwide non-custodial option in the criminal justice system.  The provision of restorative justice practices is a priority for the Probation Service.  The restorative principles of admitting and repairing the harm done to the victim and to society by offending behaviour are central to the concept of community service, with which we are already familiar and which the Probation Service delivers so well.  They also form a key part of the community return initiative, which was established more recently.  Both schemes operate primarily from a reparative model.  They require offenders to address the indirect harm to the community caused by their offences by performing unpaid supervised work benefiting that community.  Under the community return initiative, prisoners who have already served a custodial sentence are given the structure and the opportunity to engage in restorative practices and avail of the rehabilitative effect of repairing some of the harm they have done and reintegrating into society.</p><p>The Probation Service is drafting an integrated restorative justice strategy which will set out a series of actions to be driven by the service in collaboration with its partners.  The aim of the strategy is to bring about greater availability and integration of restorative practices at various stages of the criminal justice process in respect of adult offenders.  The strategy is intended to include actions that will facilitate the expanding and strengthening of capacity to ensure high-quality restorative justice projects and services are provided.  It will also provide for the greater use of restorative practices in the overall assessment and supervision of offenders referred to the Probation Service and partner agencies.  If restorative justice practices are to be more widely used, the Probation Service will build awareness and confidence among criminal justice professionals and the general public, helping them to understand that a restorative justice intervention is a viable sanction which can provide benefits for all stakeholders.  It is also the intention of the Probation Service to ensure the quality of service provided by restorative justice interventions is consistently high and is in line with agreed restorative practice standards.</p><p>In all of its interventions, the Probation Service intends to provide for more inclusive victim-sensitive services, thereby extending the reach of restorative methods.  Community members and volunteers will need to have an increased role if this is to happen.  The Probation Service works with and within communities to provide services to offenders.  Despite our difficult economic circumstances and the ever-increasing pressures on limited resources, the Minister continues to ensure a large proportion of the Probation Service's overall budget is available to fund community-based organisations that are dedicated to the delivery of these services and help them in achieving their strategic objectives.  In working with adult offenders, restorative justice has the potential to break the destructive pattern of behaviour of those who offend by challenging them to confront the full extent of the emotional and physical harm they have caused to their victims.  As a way of responding to offending behaviour, it balances the needs of the victim, the offender and the community by providing a real and meaningful opportunity to engage in a process where the victims' perspective is considered and represented.</p> <p>Restorative justice also offers a process whereby offenders take responsibility for their actions and the harm caused by their behaviour to the victim and to society, and commit to making some reparation.  This allows the circumstances and factors leading to the offending to be addressed and, very important, allows the community an opportunity to bring its constituent members together for purposeful, solution-focused intervention.</p><p>The probation and welfare service, in partnership with community-based organisations and some of its statutory partners, currently delivers a number of restorative justice programmes and interventions.  This includes restorative justice projects available to a number of the District Courts in Dublin and the midlands, as well as dedicated restorative justice responses to youth offending through delivery of family conferencing, under the Children Act 2001, and the recently established restorative justice pilot project in Limerick.</p><p>Restorative justice practices are in place for juvenile offenders through the provisions of the Children Act 2001, and the Minister is committed to extending such practices to work with adults.  It is also worth recalling that restorative justice practices in Northern Ireland are well established, having been formally developed between 1995 and 2004.  Flexibility of practice is perceived by Northern Ireland practitioners as the best manner by which to achieve the aims of restorative justice, which are as follows: &quot;to reflect best practice&quot;, &quot;[ensure] that victimisation does not occur&quot; and &quot;[ensure]that all parties (victim, offender and community) come away as satisfied as possible with the outcome&quot;.  In that regard, both the probation and welfare service and the Irish Prison Service are involved with the Restorative Justice Forum of Northern Ireland in planning an all-island event on restorative practices to coincide with international restorative justice week in November 2013.  This is yet another welcome example of North-South co-operation, where learning, expertise and experience is shared by key practitioners.</p><p>Turning to the directive of the European Parliament and European Council establishing minimum standards on the rights, support and protection of victims of crime, Ireland took a positive approach to the draft directive in the negotiations in the Council working party, at the JHA Council and during the trilogues with the European Parliament.  For his part, the Minister, Deputy Shatter, ensured that the enactment of legislation giving rights to victims was a key commitment in the programme for Government.</p><p>The victims directive includes a range of provisions for victims to protect them from secondary victimisation and intimidation in the event that restorative justice services are offered.  These protections include the requirement that any victim involvement in restorative processes is subject to free and informed consent, which may be withdrawn at any time.  The victim should also be provided with full information about the process, possible outcomes and the methods used to supervise the implementation of any agreement reached.  In addition, the victims directive requires that any agreement which involves the victim is concluded on a voluntary basis.  The directive ensures that the legitimate concerns of the victim are taken into account, where the victim is included in the restorative process.  These victim concerns must be addressed, while acknowledging the equally legitimate efforts to rehabilitate offenders.</p><p>The Minister, Deputy Shatter, has long held a deep interest in the needs of victims in the Irish criminal justice system.  In 2002 and again in 2008, he tabled a Victims' Rights Bill while in opposition.  As further evidence of his commitment to protecting those who find themselves to be the victim of a crime, the Minister has ensured the budget for 2013 for the Commission for the Support of Victims of Crime was maintained.  The Minister has already instructed officials to begin preparatory work with a view to transposing the directive into Irish law.  The final date for transposition of the directive is 16 November 2015.</p><p>The House can be assured that the Government is resolute in its commitment to further develop and expand the restorative justice process throughout the State.  We must and will continue to do everything we can to ensure its potential as a non-custodial option available to the criminal justice system is explored to the fullest extent possible.  Similarly, the Government is committed to ensuring that provision is made for victims to receive appropriate information, supports and protection, where they are called on to engage in restorative processes.</p><p>I commend the motion to the House and thank the Senators for putting it forward.  It is an example of the freedom that is available in this setting, which is not available in others.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor Ó Clochartaigh" time="18:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000041#QQ00200"><p>Cuirim fáilte roimh an Aire Stáit.  Is cosúil nach bhfuair sí mórán deis ar an Guinness glas ag an deireadh seachtaine.  Tá míle fáilte roimpi agus í linn arís.  Ba mhaith liom tréaslú leis an Seanadóir Conway a chur an rún seo síos.  Cuireann sé croí agus anam i ngach rud a dhéanann sé sa Teach seo.  Is maith an aghaidh air an obair atá déanta ar an rún seo aige.</p><p>  I am happy to take this opportunity to speak in the debate and I commend the Fine Gael motion and Senator Conway on putting it forward.  I and the Sinn Féin Party are happy to support the motion.  Sinn Féin has long been an advocate of the restorative justice approach.  It is my view that the benefits of this approach, as it has been applied in the North, remain clear for all to see.  I am very pleased this is an idea which is gaining more and more political support throughout the island.</p><p>  I understand that last October saw a presentation given by the two main umbrella groups that are responsible for restorative justice in the North - Community Restorative Justice Ireland and Northern Ireland Alternatives - to the Committee on the Implementation of the Good Friday Agreement, and that they gave an insightful and evidence-based account of the effects of such an approach.  These are organisations which are heavily embedded in their communities and also partner with housing, health and social affairs authorities in their work.</p><p>  The key point of the approach and the philosophy is that the focus is on rehabilitation of offenders and ensuring justice is done while, at the same time, not being punitive and ensuring that the offender can be in a position to add to their community and repay their debt to the same community.  According to Community Restorative Justice Ireland, the practice is based on eight key principles which underpin its whole philosophy and approach, namely, participation, interconnectedness, honesty, humility, respect, accountability, hope and empowerment.  Where such an approach can be used, we should seek to make use of such a humane approach.</p><p>  I noticed with interest the Minister, Deputy Shatter's response to a question tabled by my colleague, Deputy Pádraig Mac Lochlainn, on 24 October last.  Indicating his support for the scheme, he made an interesting point regarding the place of victims within such a system.  He said:<blockquote>...it is interesting that restorative justice essentially requires offenders to speak for themselves from start to finish whereas if one brings them into a court system, apart from saying &quot;guilty&quot; or &quot;got guilty&quot;, the offender may say nothing at all in court, and certainly is not emotionally engaged necessarily in an exchange where he perceives the person against whom the offence was committed as truly a victim of that offence.  No doubt offenders find the restorative justice process emotionally demanding and tough and it gives them an opportunity to see the victim as a person and to say &quot;Sorry&quot; to him.  There is really no chance of doing that in a court process.  It happens only occasionally.</blockquote>This is an important point and I agree there is a clear philosophy there which encourages seeking forgiveness and so on.</p><p>  As for its efficacy, the facts speak for themselves.  The recidivism rates with programme participants were 8% to 9% within a year of completion of the programme compared to 50% to 60% for those offenders incarcerated in mainstream prisons.  In many ways, this is not surprising as putting people in prisons, particularly where they are overcrowded and the conditions are poor, can be damaging and can even add to the possibility of recidivism.  This is particularly the case among younger people.</p><p>  This is an also an approach which makes economic sense.  As we all know, incarceration is extremely expensive, so there are obvious savings which will accrue if the scheme is successful.  Simply put, if we can invest in prevention rather than cure, we would save a great deal of money for the taxpayer over the medium to long term.  Of course, there are also positive stories for the South and, as the motion notes, the work of the Nenagh Community Reparation Project, the Restorative Justice Services and Le Chéile Restorative Justice Project deserve great commendation.</p><p>  I might further make the point that schemes such as these should form part of a wider, more community-focused reorientation of justice.  Clearly, a scheme such as community restorative justice can only work in partnership with the local community.  However, I believe that idea of partnership should be applied right across the board.  Local authorities and local gardaí, in conjunction with tenants committees, residents associations and other community stakeholders, are all responsible.  Issues concerning justice and safety in a community should be responded to with public meetings on an estate by estate, development by development or even street by street basis.  We also believe there would be a value in the drawing up of a collective &quot;good community&quot; agreement.</p><p>  The Minister will know we have long called for the full roll-out of the joint policing committees, JPCs, across the State and for greater resourcing of designated community gardaí, who are among the most effective tools available to the force in tackling antisocial behaviour, particularly locally.  This was brought home to me last Friday at a meeting in Galway about the issue of the increase in burglaries, about which people are very concerned.  The main issue coming from the people in the audience was that they want to see gardaí on the streets.</p> <p>It is a very small thing.  It is community policing.  Great praise was given to the community police on the streets in Galway city.  </p><p>Such an approach would fit well with the approach we are discussing with restorative justice.  The philosophy inherent in that approach is that not only are there rights that accrue to victims and communities but consequently there are obligations on the victim and community.  The offender has an obligation, as the CRJI puts it, to make things right as much as possible and to be an active participant in addressing their own needs and their obligations to victims as restitution takes priority over other sanctions and obligations to the community.  Likewise, the community has a responsibility to support and help victims of crime and antisocial behaviour to meet their needs.  It has a responsibility for the welfare of its members and the social conditions and relationships which promote crime and antisocial behaviour and community peace and other obligations in a similar vein such as reintegration.  Clearly, this philosophy applies to a wider context and we should consider how this can be rolled out across the board and include statutory authorities and the gardaí.  </p><p>Something like this is not just an issue for the Department of Justice and Equality but is an issue for all Government Departments.  Something that would have come forward again on Friday was that the general economic climate is encouraging crime in a number of areas.  We have also seen societal disadvantage in areas that would have been measured under the Trutz Haase deprivation index.  The areas were still deprived relatively speaking even though money was put into them over the years.  Equality of access to services and education was an issue there.  It is important for all Departments to put the community first and keep the levels of funding available to community projects, drugs task forces, family resource centres and drug rehabilitation as high as possible.  </p><p>Even though the Minister for Justice and Equality did much work in opposition on these issues, the date of November 2015 seems a long way off - two and a half years.  Could that date be brought forward because this is the type of Bill we would all welcome sooner rather than later?  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1114" speakername="Deirdre Clune" time="19:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000042#RR00200"><p>I thank the Minister and Senator Conway in his absence for putting down this motion and for giving me the opportunity to engage in the debate and to learn more about the issue.  Restorative justice has a role to play in the justice system.  Very strong arguments have been made by previous speakers.  The Prison Service is very important but the cost is €65,000 for an individual prisoner for one year, while the cost of restorative justice is €3,500.  That is an important element but it is not the "be all and end all".  Senator Conway stated that 78% of those who engaged in the restorative justice process did not re-offend, which is extremely important.  Up to 50% or more of prisoners do re-offend.</p><p>Obviously, this has a very important role to play in the justice system.  I welcome the comments of the Minister of State with responsibility for disability, equality and mental health when she said that the Minister is engaging and ensuring that the directive will be put into place.  I do not know whether that can be brought forward or not but the Minister's previous comments demonstrate his commitment to victims' rights and to ensuring their voice is heard.  The directive, which was published in November 2012 and has been put in train, focuses on victims' rights.  It states in this summary that restorative justice services should only be used if they are in the victim's interests.  It is important that the victim be supported in every way.  Information should be made available to them, for example, about how they can make complaints, as well as legal advice, information about compensation and contact details for communication about their cases and supports should be provided to them.  It is important for the victim, it an individual or community, to be put at the centre.  The directive is very supportive of victims, which is what one would expect.  </p><p>Reading about restorative justice systems, which are available in many countries, I am struck by the type of issues that can be addressed from minor antisocial behaviour to serious crimes like assault and robbery.  I am aware of a graffiti programme in Cork where Cork City Council and Cork County Council engage with the Probation Service.  Dealing with graffiti under the Litter Pollution Act was very difficult for a long time.  Local authorities did not have the resources but the Probation Service now works with local authorities in Cork very productively.  It gives offenders an opportunity to make amends to their victims, among which in many cases is the community.  </p><p>I have huge admiration for the Probation Service.  The way it engages with prisoners and ensures they can be supported in re-establishing themselves in society is very important.  Rehabilitation services within our prisons have also been mentioned.  I had occasion to visit Cork Prison, which is a very bleak place.  I am not questioning the fact that individuals are incarcerated in prison but the prison is bleak.  It is an old grey building.  One does not see any daylight, one cannot find one blade of grass or plant and a huge net covers the yard.  It is not a very encouraging place to be and is not the best place in terms of rehabilitation.  We need to do more in that area.  </p><p>I compliment the gardaí on the work they do, particularly the community gardaí.  I know previous speakers referred to them.  We have a very successful programme in Cork involving the JPCs and from them have come community fora in different locations whereby gardaí are present and the community, public representatives and a range of officials from the local authority get together.  It has been extremely successful.  I attend three of them on a regular basis.  The issues that have been dealt with by the local community, the gardaí and the local authority are wide-ranging.  It has been very effective and has the support and confidence of the community.  My opening point was that there is much that can be done in the area.  One size does not fit all.  I again commend Senator Conway and commend the motion to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Maloney" time="19:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000042#RR00300"><p>I welcome the Minister of State with responsibility for Gaeltacht affairs to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" speakername="Susan O'Keeffe" time="19:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000042#RR00400"><p>I welcome the opportunity to agree with this motion and to thank Senator Conway for bringing it to the House.  It was not my intention to speak but when others were speaking about restorative justice, I was minded about two visits I made to two young offenders' institutions in the UK when I was working as a journalist.  I always remember the lingering sadness of those places where people were locked away and almost forgotten about.  Whenever they came out, people were working with them but already the managers were very clear in saying to me and others that this does not work.  It is very difficult for the managers of a prison to be working with young offenders in the knowledge that they know it is not working and to try to bring something real to that situation so that those young people might have some hope as they leave.  That stuck with me because I had not expected to find it.  While we were sitting here talking about restorative justice, it occurred to me that here is a system that allows those young people in particular to take responsibility in a very different way.</p> <p>Under this system, young people are confronted with what they have done and are given the opportunity to accept responsibility for it.  They are obliged to face those whom they have offended and for whom they have caused difficulties.  They are also encouraged to look at what they have done in a different way.</p><p>We have developed a system through the courts which involves the use of paid interlocutors.  I intend no offence to the many legal people present in the Chamber but it must be recognised that we pay other individuals to do the talking and to remove all of the responsibility from those who commit crimes.  One of the great aspects of restorative justice is that it restores that responsibility to offenders.  It also offers victims the opportunity to have the wrongs done to them acknowledged in a way that is very personal and completely different from that which obtains in the courts.</p><p>I welcome those in the Gallery who work in this area and I commend those various communities in Tallaght, Limerick and Nenagh that are involved in restorative justice.  I welcome the commitment given by the Minister of State, Deputy Kathleen Lynch, to the effect that the restorative justice system will be not only maintained but expanded.  The latter is really important because it provides a signal to those who work in the area that what they do is valued and recognised in the context of the good it has achieved.  It is also an acknowledgement that we are on the right path.</p><p>The challenge that arises in the context of the restorative justice system lies in ensuring that the dignity of victims is upheld.  I am aware that people are concerned by the fact that at present everything seems to revolve around the rights of the offender.  It is the rights of victims which should always be taken into account.  I am sure this is a very familiar theme and good restorative justice systems obviously take account of it.  It must be remembered that offenders also have their dignity and their rights.  I am of the view that moving to a system such as this, where their dignity is recognised, is important.  Once people are thrown into an adversarial system such as the courts system, from the outset they will be treated as individuals for whom there is less consideration.  In such circumstances, it is not surprising that people reoffend.  Those who are convicted go straight from the courts to one of our many overcrowded prisons - Senator Clune mentioned visiting the prison in Cork and I have been to Mountjoy - and these are not great places to be.  It is no surprise, therefore, that when people are released after serving prison terms, they reoffend.  This is because they have been offered very little to assist them in restoring their dignity or availing of opportunities into the future.</p><p>Part of the problem with society is that it very much recognises the system that has been put in place.  How many films have dealt with what happens in courtrooms, the great drama of somebody being found guilty and being sent to jail and the loud clang as the door to the latter closes?  These are very resonant themes that we recognise.  Restorative justice is a very brave approach because it attempts, not least, to turn this on its head and state that there is another way of proceeding.  It is quite difficult to swim against the tide in terms of the ways of punishing people which we acknowledge and which are rooted in our system.  As Senator O'Donovan noted, our need to punish people is very strong.  To begin to discuss something which is different from that and to acknowledge that we do not need to punish people in what has become the accepted way is a step forward.</p><p>I suggest that not only must we expand the system of restorative justice but we must also begin educating children in school about the way in which responsibility must be taken by offenders and those who engage in wrongdoing.  We must also educate them to believe that victims have a right to engage in the process.  When many of those present in the Chamber went to school, they may have undergone the public humiliation of being told to stand in the corner if they had done something wrong.  The position in schools has, of course, changed but I am of the view that we should begin to educate young people about this matter in order that we might start to overturn the very deep-rooted idea of punishment to which I refer.</p><p>The motion calls on the Government to commit to the implementation of EU Directive 2012/29/EU of the European Parliament and Council.  I am of the opinion that implementing the directive would be of assistance in respect of this matter.  I do not know if there are lessons to be learned from those who are involved in early intervention programmes with parents and young children.  We are aware that there is very much to be done in terms of trying to get through to such parents and young children by giving them good advice and assistance at an early stage.  There must be lessons that can be learned from the programmes to which I refer and perhaps what is learned can be applied to restorative justice programmes.  This is an area which may be worthy of consideration.</p><p>The findings of the National Commission on Restorative Justice indicates that young men are very much involved in crime and that alcohol is a major problem.  In the context of the joined-up thinking I continually advocate, it is clear that action in respect of the consumption and cost of alcohol and the way in which young men, in particular, consume it must be part of any solution at which we arrive with regard to restorative justice.  We cannot afford to ignore this problem.  The report of the commission also indicates that in Finland and Norway, trained volunteers and lay mediators are very much part of the restorative justice process.  Given that we live in a country in which there are many volunteers, perhaps the Government might consider establishing a training programme for lay volunteers in order that they might become involved in the area of restorative justice.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="19:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000043#SS00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy McGinley.  I compliment Senator Conway on his tabling of this most important motion.  I am one of those Members to which the Senator Conway referred, namely, those who previously knew very little about the restorative justice process.  This debate has given us the opportunity to learn a great deal about the matter.  I was encouraged by the very positive contribution made by the Minister of State at the Department of Justice and Equality, Deputy Kathleen Lynch.</p><p>  Earlier this afternoon, I searched for a definition of restorative justice.  I wish to read into the record one of the definitions I found, which I like.  It states:<blockquote>Restorative justice is a process where all the stakeholders affected by an injustice have an opportunity to discuss how they have been affected by the injustice and to decide what should be done to repair the harm.  With crime, restorative justice is about the idea that because crime hurts, justice should heal.  It follows that conversations with those who have been hurt and with those who have afflicted the harm must be central to the process.</blockquote>If someone can discuss with the perpetrator of a crime the hurt that has been caused and if the latter is given the opportunity to express regret, it would certainly be a move in the right direction.</p><p>  The victims of crime must be at the centre of our justice system.  We all know people whose lives have been damaged and changed for ever as a result of their being the victims of crime.  I refer to those whose homes were burgled, who were assaulted or who were the victims of anti-social behaviour of any kind.  We must ensure, in the first instance, that the Garda Síochána is properly resourced in order that it might prevent the commission of crime.  When a crime occurs, however, in the aftermath the victim must be in a position to be satisfied that justice has been done and has been seen to be done.  As the Minister of State, Deputy Kathleen Lynch, acknowledged, this is not always the case.  Victims often do not have the opportunity to have their say in court.  Likewise, perpetrators are not given the opportunity to apologise to victims in court.</p><p>  With the exception of serious crimes, I am firmly of the view that - particularly in the case of young offenders - alternatives to prison should be considered.  The prison system is completely unsuitable for vulnerable young people.  There is a real chance that bad influences within that system may result in such individuals becoming repeat offenders and, in many instances, living a life of crime.  It was stated that the cost of keeping someone in prison is &#8364;65,000 per year.  That money is being spent on keeping a system which does not work in operation.  A restorative justice system could cost as little as &#8364;3,500 per offender and could possibly give rise to much more satisfactory outcomes.</p><p>  In the context of the debate in which we are currently engaging, we must ask why young people find themselves acting outside the law on so many occasions.  Is it because they did not engage with the education system, or do factors such as family circumstances, social deprivation and a lack of employment opportunities come into play?  I am of the view that the lack of employment opportunities is a real issue.</p> <p>The key to reducing crime among young people is the provision of opportunities to work and to do something meaningful with their lives.  I welcome the youth guarantee scheme initiative which will ensure that when finishing secondary school young people will have an opportunity for further education, training or work experience.  Over the years when I worked in industry I had the opportunity to give employment - long-term employment in some cases - or work experience to young people who found themselves outside the law and who had committed crimes.  When they engaged with people in a work environment and where people looked out for them and cared for them, their lives were turned around.  This is the outcome we want from a restorative justice system.</p><p>The Ballinasloe Training Workshop, or Canal House, as it is also known, is in my home town of Ballinasloe.  It is operated by the Probation Service in conjunction with the Department of Justice and Equality, FÁS, County Galway VEC, the local community and the Courts Service.  Its aim is to enable offenders to re-integrate into society through the provision of training and employment opportunities, to reduce re-offending through the provision of alcohol and substance misuse awareness programmes, supplemented by appropriate workshops and one-to-one sessions, and to develop restorative community projects with organisations such as the Tidy Towns committee and sporting organisations.  The programme is working.  It is not as extensively used as we would like but I am reliably informed that as much as two thirds of the people who engage with the process at Ballinasloe Training Workshop do not re-offend.  </p><p>The restorative justice process presents real opportunities to consider alternatives to prison.  As a previous speaker said, it needs to be established in legislation.  I welcome the Minister's commitment to further this process.  We need a national debate on the issue in order to have engagement from the public.  Like ourselves, the majority of people do not know what is involved.  We need to take the victims' concerns on board because they must be central to the process.  Restorative justice offers significant opportunities at a much reduced cost.</p><p>I commend Senator Conway for introducing this motion.  I hope it will be the first of many discussions in this House on the matter.  I urge the Minister to expedite legislation that will provide real alternatives to the prison system and to a penal system that has failed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="Rónán Mullen" time="19:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000044#TT00200"><p>Cuirim fáilte roimh an Aire Stáit.  I congratulate Senator Conway and Senator Burke for proposing and seconding this motion and other speakers whose contributions I found very interesting.  I have long been a believer in the importance of advancing restorative justice processes in our prison system and as an alternative to prison.  I urge all present to give consideration to restorative justice as a serious and effective alternative to imprisonment in many cases.  Currently the justice system is failing to deliver.  It continues to lock up the poor and the vulnerable but it does not prevent crime or deter offenders.  It does not address the root causes of crime and it does not manage to rehabilitate offenders very much either.  Evidence of this can be found in the high rate of recidivism.  The truth is that nobody benefits from crime, neither victims nor the community and under the current justice system the offender does not benefit especially if he or she continues to re-offend.</p><p>  We have been talking about this for a long time but so much more needs to be done.  Back in 2004 the annual report of the prison chaplains contained the combined reflections and experiences of those chaplains.  They questioned the current system where people are imprisoned and a method of rehabilitation is attempted.  However, it is questioned whether this can have a positive effect when people are removed from their family and society, when all responsibility is removed from them, such as the responsibility to earn a living, to care for their families and to become contributing members of society.  I am not denying, of course, that there are situations where the custodial dimension is essential.  However, we need to be realistic about what occurs under the current system where prisoners are confined to their cells for more than 17 hours a day with nothing to occupy them only television and computer games.  As many who enter prison are not even able to read, that luxury is denied them.  How can this be called rehabilitation when perhaps only four or five hours a day are devoted to education and work experience and only two hours a day devoted to recreation?  The practical needs such as food and shelter are provided for but other basic human needs are denied to them.  For example, young people of 16 and 17 are removed and isolated from their families and mothers and fathers are removed from their children.  This will surely have a negative effect on future generations.  Wives and children become social welfare recipients while at the same time husbands and fathers walk prison yards or lie in beds.  The chaplains' report queried how productive from an economic point of view is the minimal training available in workshops when the same walls are constructed, painted over, knocked down and then the whole process repeated constantly.  Prisoners often become institutionalised and marginalised.  They lack social skills and they certainly do not develop the normal skills for everyday living.</p><p>  Society needs to question whether imprisonment reforms, deters or discourages offenders.  The high rates of recidivism must mean that the answer is clear; imprisonment does not reform or deter and it does not discourage crime.  When offenders are sent to prison they are cut off from the consequences of their crimes and their responsibility to victims, families and society at large.</p><p>  Restorative justice tries to set up a situation where offenders are confronted, among other things, with the consequences of their actions and the effects of their actions on others.  It would involve, in my view, a brand new approach to the treatment of sex offenders.  This is a very difficult and sensitive area but many such offences are perpetrated within the family so, therefore, where possible, the solution and healing might best, in some cases, be found within a family setting.  Community-based programmes can offer an alternative to prison.  The particular needs of some young sex offenders might best be met within community while undergoing treatment.  Certainly, locking them away in an all-male prison, where minimal if any help is available to them, cannot sensibly be seen as a solution.  Older men, especially those who have not offended in years, could benefit more from treatment in some cases than from imprisonment.  Of course I am not saying that there must not be a prosecutorial and sometimes a custodial dimension.  That will, of course, always depend on the seriousness of the crime and the other surrounding circumstances.  However, it is about society thinking smarter instead of working harder.  Society can become a safer place, for example, when sex offenders receive proper treatment.  Child protection is enhanced and there is less disruption to the lives of many families.  There is an important balance to be struck.</p><p>  The process of restorative justice can also better serve the needs of those suffering from addiction.  Prison becomes a fertile ground for drugs of all kinds as a consequence of the lack of any meaningful employment.  Drug use arises when existence becomes sheer boredom and a lack of meaningful contact with family and friends makes the situation worse.  The underlying problems that originally led to drug use are rarely dealt with.  The absence of counsellors, apart from those who provide the service on a voluntary basis, means that for the most part, prison is a complete waste of time and of taxpayers' money.  Addictions such as alcohol call for treatment first. </p><p>  I will conclude by making a few brief points.  Examples of where restorative justice has been put into use successfully can be found in Germany, New Zealand and Japan.  Atlantic Philanthropies has done good work in Northern Ireland in promoting initiatives across the community which are designed to support reconciliation, to address the problems of the past and to assist communities in moving away from violence.  </p><p>  I believe that if a system of restorative justice, building on the initiatives referred to by other speakers, were to be seriously embraced, it would reduce recidivism and as a result, there would be a decrease in the total prison population.  I am certain that everyone in society would support it.  </p><p>  I refer to an article published in the <i>Irish Probation Journal</i> in 2011 by Shane McCarthy.  A limited survey among defence solicitors, designed to measure their knowledge and understanding of the principles of restorative justice, found that in many cases there were limitations and gaps in the understanding even among legal personnel about the potential of restorative justice.  Much work remains to be done.  It is a major challenge because of long-established practice and embedded systems that have to be questioned all over again.  We need to raise the profile of restorative justice among the key people in criminal justice.  We need an education strategy to inform people and to assure them that it works, that there can be benefits.  The implementation of the key recommendations of the national commission should be prioritised and expanded as part of mainstream practice.</p> <p>There is a need for ongoing evaluation of its efficacy and effectiveness as an alternative sanction.  The implementation of any alternative sanction should be monitored.  This is not just some idealistic left-wing fantasy, rather it is something that has been seen to work and can work for us as a society.  I again express my thanks and congratulations to my colleagues.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="19:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000045#UU00300"><p>I welcome my good friend, the Minister of State, Deputy Dinny McGinley.  The debate has been inspiring and interesting.  I inform Senator Denis O'Donovan that it was remiss of me in my earlier remarks not to commend the previous Government for taking the brave initiative to establish the restorative justice commission, the establishment of which led to the pilot projects.  It was also remiss of me not to mention the work of the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Justice, Defence and Equality.  The next stage for the committee is to recommend the legislation required to make restorative justice part of the mainstream.</p><p>Everyone has said the prison system is not working.  Let us think of the image of a rotten apple in a barrel of apples, but what if the barrel is also rotten?  That the prison system does not work is not fault of the many good personnel who work within it.  The reality is that too many are in prison who should not be there.  The only interest in victims is shown through the victim impact statement, a measure which many believe does not work either.  The victim needs to play a far more central role in the process.  Restorative justice is a very nice way to ensure a victim's voice is heard in a true and meaningful manner.  It makes a difference to society, serves the public interest and improves society.  It can help young people who have fallen or are about to into a life of crime to identify a better and more successful path in life.</p><p>The contributions made across the House prove that restorative justice is a political issue.  Thankfully, it is not a party political issue or football.  I have great hope that we will see in future years a very well defined mainstream national restorative justice programme that will achieve great results.  I have been given hope by the fact that the initiative has received unanimous support.  Effectively, a restorative justice programme is in train; it will not stop and will transcend future Administrations and generations.  </p><p>The debate has been informative and the speech by the Minister of State, Deputy Kathleen Lynch, was very inspiring and encouraging.  A clear commitment was given that it would be a national initiative, including pilot projects.  That development  is very encouraging, but I would like to hear a proposed timeframe.  I am surprised that the IMF has not made a restorative justice programme a priority, given that such a programme has been proved to save costs.  I am sure the troika will be happy with the Minister of State's speech in which she gave a commitment to make it part of the mainstream.  </p><p>We have had a good debate.  It may be just a drop in an overall context, but drops in the ocean, if penetrated properly, can produce a significant ripple effect.  The Oireachtas Joint Committee on Justice, Defence and Equality will hold hearings later in the term and I hope we will return to the topic during Primate Members' time to report progress.  I would love to see suitable legislation being brought before the Houses of the Oireachtas in the not too distant future, I hope during the term of office of the Government.  I want the right legislation.  I want proper research to be carried out, even if it means launching a national pilot project initially, to allow us to take baby steps that will lead to a more defined programme.  I would like a national programme to be initiated in the very near future which would lead to proper structures being put in place through legislation.  Unfortunately, the victims of crime have not been legislated for, while offenders have not been given the opportunities they deserve.  </p><p>I have been convinced about the benefits of a restorative justice programme by the examples given by practitioners, the people working on the ground, when they spoke at lectures and seminars I have attended in recent months.  They passionately believe restorative justice is the right way to proceed and can attest to the success stories.  They have witnessed the futures of some people being enhanced, while opportunities have been given to others who perhaps would not have had opportunities in life but for this process.  All of the evidence has convinced me that there is no alternative.</p><p>I thank all of the Senators who contributed for their informative and enlightened contributions.  Let us hope we will see a bright future for the victims of crime and offenders.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.150" nospeaker="true" time="19:35:00"><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Maloney" time="19:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000045#UU00500"><p>When is it proposed to sit again?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="19:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000045#UU00600"><p>Ar 10.30 maidin amárach.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.153" nospeaker="true" time="19:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000045#UU00700">Adjournment Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.154" nospeaker="true" time="19:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000045#UU00800">Schools Building Projects</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="19:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000045#UU01000"><p>I thank the Minister of State for taking this matter at short notice.  This is the third or fourth night on which we are the last people in the House.  I hope we have not set a precedent for the rest of the year.</p><p>My Adjournment matters relates to Scoil Íosagáin, Farranree, County Cork which has over 400 primary school students but does not have a facility for any activity other than its classrooms.  The school was granted full planning permission in 2011 for the construction of a general purpose hall at the rear and within its boundary.  However, the project has been included in the Department's building programme for over ten years.  The school has a large number of young pupils, but it does not have the necessary resources.  In the past six months there have been a number of debates in the House on the need for young people to exercise and attend school to study.  If one does not have the facilities, however, it is impossible to be active.  The school does have outdoor facilities, but they can only be used in good weather.  During the winter months recreational activities are confined; therefore, a general purpose hall is urgently needed.  I seek clarification on where the project is ranked in the building programme of the Department.  When will the facilities be constructed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1000" speakername="Dinny McGinley" time="19:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000045#UU01100"><p>I am taking this Adjournment matter on behalf of my colleague, the Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy Ruairí Quinn.</p><p>I thank the Senator for raising the matter of the proposed building project for Scoil Íosagáin, Farranree, County Cork, as it provides me with an opportunity to outline to the Seanad the Government's strategy for capital investment in education projects in the next five years and clarify the position on the project referred to.</p> <p>I would first like to set out the context within which decisions relating to meeting the accommodation needs of schools must be considered over the coming years.  Overall enrolment figures are expected to grow by approximately 70,000 students between 2012 and 2018 - by more than 25,000 at post-primary and 45,000 at primary level.  Indeed, post-primary level enrolment is expected to continue to rise until at least the year 2024.</p><p>In order to meet the needs of our growing population of schoolgoing children, the Department must establish new schools as well as extending or replacing a number of existing schools in areas where demographic growth has been identified.  The delivery of these new schools, together with extension projects to meet future demand, will be the main focus of the Department's capital budget for the coming years.  The five-year programme announced in March 2012 will provide more than 100,000 permanent school places, of which more than 80,000 will be new school places.  The remainder will involve the replacement of temporary or unsatisfactory accommodation.</p><p>The proposed project for Scoil Iosagain, Farranree, entails the construction of a general purpose room and two mainstream classrooms.  The school is staffed by a principal, 22 mainstream teachers and ancillary teaching staff with 416 pupils enrolled in the current school year.  The project is currently at an advanced stage of architectural planning.  In the stage 2b approval letter which issued on 12 November 2012, the board of management was informed that the project was not authorised to proceed to tender at that time.  Due to competing demands on the Department's capital budget, imposed by the need to prioritise the limited funding available for the provision of additional school accommodation to meet increasing demographic requirements, it was not possible to include this project in the five-year construction programme announced in March 2012.</p><p>Schools which have not been included in the five-year construction programme but which had previously been announced for initial inclusion in the building programme will continue to be progressed to final planning stages in anticipation of the possibility of further funds being available to the Department in future years.  The project at Scoil Íosagáin, Farranree, remains available to be considered for progression in that context.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="19:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000046#VV00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his response.  I am disappointed the school has not been included in the five-year programme.  As I said, we have full planning permission, so there is no further waiting time in that regard.  In view of the fact we have full planning permission, it should be taken up as a project which is ready to roll.  We have full planning permission, have a site which is within the school boundary and have the student numbers which will be maintained into the foreseeable future and may even grow.  I ask that the school be included in the programme or if another school drops out, that it be included in it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1000" speakername="Dinny McGinley" time="19:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013032000046#VV00300"><p>As a former teacher, I recognise the importance of the facility for a school of this size, with 460 pupils, 22 teachers and ancillary staff.  There is inclement weather, even in Cork in the sunny south.  I got my secondary education in a scoil Íosagáin in the same county, namely, Coláiste Íosagáin in Ballyvourney.  I realise the importance of the project and appreciate the Senator's efforts on the school's behalf.  I will certainly convey his views and recommendations to the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-03-20a.160" nospeaker="true" time="19:45:00"><p>The Seanad adjourned at 8.05 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Thursday, 21 March 2013.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>