<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Leas-Chathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.4" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#A00100">Gnó an tSeanaid - Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Se&aacute;n Kyne that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine to make a statement on the potential of an offshore wind development at Ros an Mh&iacute;l pier, County Galway. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Joe O&rsquo;Reilly of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Health to make a statement on the supports and services provided for gambling addiction and problem gambling. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Pat Casey of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage to make a statement on the Arklow Bank Wind Park phase 2 project. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Eugene Murphy of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Social Protection to make a statement on the future of the job club service and job club staff in the context of the new regional employment service. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Barry Ward of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Education to address the lack of parity between traditional and simplified Chinese characters in leaving certificate Mandarin Chinese. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Fiona O&rsquo;Loughlin of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Health to make a statement on plans for the development of a hospice in the midlands. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Malcolm Byrne of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Further and Higher Education, Research, Innovation and Science to make a statement on the plans, if any, he has to separate the office of director general of Science Foundation Ireland from the office of the Government&rsquo;s chief scientific adviser. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Maria Byrne of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Health to make a statement on the disbursement of funding to address waiting lists, particularly at University Hospital Limerick. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Garret Ahearn of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Health to make a statement on the BreastCheck screening delays in Nenagh, County Tipperary. </blockquote> <p>The matters raised by the Senators are suitable for discussion.  I have selected the matters raised by Senators Kyne, O&rsquo;Reilly, Casey and Murphy and they will be taken now.  The other Senators may give notice on another day of the matters they wish to raise.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.7" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#A00300">Nithe i dtosach suíonna - Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.8" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#A00400">Wind Energy Generation</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#A00500"><p>I am delighted to welcome my friend and colleague, the Minister of State, Senator Hackett, to her own Chamber.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1665" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#A00600"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach's office for selecting this Commencement debate and I welcome the Minister of State to the Chamber.  I had a choice of which Minister to put this matter to.  I could have put it to the Minister for Environment, Climate and Communications, the Minister of State with responsibility for the Gaeltacht, &Uacute;dar&aacute;s na Gaeltachta and Gaeltacht regions, which includes Ros an Mh&iacute;l, or to the Minister of State's own Department, the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine.  That shows the cross-departmental role this development has.</p> <p>I acknowledge the visit by the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine, Deputy McConalogue, to Ros an Mh&iacute;l last Friday.  He launched a report that recognises the suitability of Ros an Mh&iacute;l in the Galway or Connemara Gaeltacht as a prime location for the development of a strategic hub to support the floating offshore wind sector, with the potential to create 900 jobs.  Having 900 potential jobs in a region such as Ros an Mh&iacute;l, sa cheantar sin, would be huge.  The report by Dublin Offshore Consultants, DOC, was launched by the Minister last Friday.  Planning permission was granted to the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine in 2018 for a 200 m deepwater quay to provide an opportunity to develop the necessary onshore infrastructure at Ros an Mh&iacute;l.  The port currently supports ferry, fishing and leisure activities within the existing harbour.  I acknowledge the support of the Department in the development of the marina at Ros an Mh&iacute;l and the pontoon development for the Aran Islands ferries as well.</p> <p>Rinne &Uacute;dar&aacute;s na Gaeltachta cur i l&aacute;thair don Aire, an Teachta McConalogue, an tseachtain seo caite maidir le calafort Ros an Mh&iacute;l, agus sheol an tAire tuarasc&aacute;il faoi na deiseanna at&aacute; i Ros an Mh&iacute;l maidir le fuinneamh in-athnuaite.  T&aacute; &Uacute;dar&aacute;s na Gaeltachta ag tac&uacute; le Coiste Taca&iacute;ochta Chalafort Ros an Mh&iacute;l chun an togra seo a bhr&uacute; chun cinn.  Teasta&iacute;onn &oacute; na Ranna seo, s&eacute; sin, an Roinn Talmha&iacute;ochta, Bia agus Mara, an Roinn Comhshaoil, Aer&aacute;ide agus Cumars&aacute;ide, agus an Roinn Turas&oacute;ireachta, Cult&uacute;ir, Eala&iacute;on, Gaeltachta, Sp&oacute;irt agus Me&aacute;n, teacht le ch&eacute;ile chun an togra seo a bhr&uacute; chun cinn agus a chur i bhfeidhm, ar mhaithe leis an gceantar agus don earn&aacute;il fuinnimh agus mara.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Se&aacute;n Kyne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2343"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2343&amp;amp;pid=SeanKyne&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=21"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> Three Departments are involved in this project, namely, the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine, the Department of Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sport and Media - which has a particular relevance to &Uacute;dar&aacute;s na Gaeltachta - and the Department of the Environment, Climate and Communications.  We need officials in all three Departments to come together, sit around a table and thrash this out.  I do not believe that the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine, on its own, wants to push this project forward for fisheries purposes.  However, there is more to it than that; we are talking about a broad approach here, including, in particular, the potential for offshore renewable energy.  There is a need for a whole-of-government approach.</p><p>Development of the fisheries harbours is included in the national development plan, as it was in previous plans, and the relevant planning permission is in place for Ros an Mh&iacute;l.  It is important now for all stakeholders to come together and I am asking the Minister of State to spearhead that.  As I said, the Minister was very gracious in coming down to launch the report and hear the presentation from the group.  We need him to sit down at the table with the Minister for the Environment, Climate and Communications, Deputy Eamon Ryan, and the Minister of State at the Department of Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sport and Media, Deputy Jack Chambers, and push forward this project with the support of the Government.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1661" speakername="Pippa Hackett" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#B00200"><p>I thank Senator Kyne for the opportunity to speak on this matter.  The Department owns, operates and maintains, under statute, six designated State-owned fishery harbour centres.  These are located at Ros an Mh&iacute;l, Castletownbere, Dingle, Dunmore East, Howth and Killybegs.  As the Senator stated, the Minister visited Ros an Mh&iacute;l fishery harbour centre last week and had the opportunity to meet with key stakeholders and see for himself the location of the proposed deepwater berthing project.</p> <p>I understand from the Minister that the possibility of developing this project at Ros an Mh&iacute;l has been under consideration for some time.  The Department currently has planning permission for that purpose, which runs until April 2023.  A phased programme for the infrastructural development of Ros an Mh&iacute;l has been progressed in recent years, which has seen investment of approximately &euro;31.6 million from 2010 to 2020.  Earlier this year, the Minister allocated &euro;1.09 million for capital works in Ros an Mh&iacute;l.  Of this, &euro;100,000 is to fund two studies concerning the deepwater project.  One is a review of the wave-modelling studies previously carried out in 2002 to ensure the analysis takes account of both the revised quay development layout and the influence of climate change on wave models affecting the harbour.  Separately, the Department has commissioned a review of the cost-benefit analysis report previously carried out by DKM Economic Consultants Limited in 2017, again incorporating the revised quay development layout.  Both studies are interlinked in that the wave-modelling outcome will likely influence the cost-benefit analysis.  The final reports are expected in November or December.</p> <p>The influence of climate change, particularly sea level rises and changes in storm intensity and duration, has always been an important consideration in marine infrastructure projects.  More recently, this has been formalised via the agriculture, forest and seafood climate change sectoral adaptation plan, which is part of the suite of measures being implemented under the Government's climate action plan.  It is important that the current studies should be concluded and can contribute to any future decisions on funding such projects.</p> <p>During his visit to Ros an Mh&iacute;l, the Minister received a copy of a report commissioned by &Uacute;dar&aacute;s Na Gaeltachta that identifies Ros an Mh&iacute;l as a prime location for the development of a strategic hub to support the floating offshore wind sector on the west coast.  There is a broad context here of cross-cutting Government policies, as the Senator highlighted.  I understand &Uacute;dar&aacute;s na Gaeltachta will be taking this report forward with the Minister for Rural and Community Development, Deputy Humphreys, to ensure there is a rounded consideration of the policy issues and investment needs raised.</p> <p>Last week, the Minister, Deputy McConalogue, received the report of the seafood sector task force, which firmly places an emphasis on creating opportunities for Ireland's fishing communities to offset the impact of the loss of access to UK waters through the trade and co-operation agreement between the UK and the European Union.</p> <p>That said, the primary role and function of the fishery harbour centres is to support the seafood industry, and the provision of any other services or facilities in the centres must be considered in that context.  This is a legal obligation set out in the Fishery Harbour Centres Acts.  Any future decision formally to initiate the deepwater quay project in Ros an Mh&iacute;l will have to reflect available Exchequer funding and competing national priorities.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1665" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#B00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State for her reply.  The last part of it, where she said that the function of fishery harbour centres is to support the seafood industry, cuts to the core of this issue.  The fact, however, is that we need to look at this in a broader way.  We must be ambitious for Ros an Mh&iacute;l and for this project.  That is why we need a cross-departmental approach to develop and push it forward.  My view is that officials in the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine do not want to progress it.  I have sufficient evidence over a long period that they will try not to support it.  They are quite happy with Castletownbere and Killybegs and are not interested in progressing the project in Ros an Mh&iacute;l.</p> <p>The potential is there for offshore development.  I ask that the Minister of State engage with the Ministers, Deputies Eamon Ryan, McConalogue and Humphreys, the Minister of State, Deputy Jack Chambers, and all the local representatives in the area to push forward this project.  I appreciate her response and support and I look forward to further engagement on this matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1661" speakername="Pippa Hackett" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#B00400"><p>The cross-departmental nature of this project requires that there be cohesion between Departments in how we address it.  Clearly, offshore wind generation is a priority for our country in meeting our renewable and decarbonisation targets.  That must be kept front and centre in all decisions that are made.  I am not aware of the specific details of the project but I will engage with the Minister with a view to progressing it.  I do not know whether the officials are supportive of it, but I certainly will look into that, even for my own knowledge.  The possibilities are good and it is always important to support job creation in areas like Ros an Mh&iacute;l and elsewhere in the west of Ireland.  I am happy to engage further with the Senator if I get any more information.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.15" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#B00500">Gambling Sector</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#B00600"><p>I welcome my good friend and colleague, the Minister of State, Deputy Feighan, to the House, of which he is a former Member.  I am delighted he is back here in his ministerial capacity at the Department of Health.  I was happy to have heard in recent days the good tidings that a gambling regulation Bill and the establishment of a gambling regulator may be imminent.  I have advocated very strongly, with others, for such measures for a long time.  It is good news and it will deal with an important facet of the gambling problem in Ireland.</p> <p>I want to address a distinct part of that problem today, namely, the situation of those who suffer from a gambling addiction and those who engage in problem gambling.  The two groups are very closely related.  First, I would like to hear from the Minister of State that he accepts that addiction to gambling is an illness and, as such, is a matter for, and the clear responsibility of, the Department of Health.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Joe O'Reilly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=1610"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1610&amp;amp;pid=JoeOReilly&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=21"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The Department of Justice has responsibility for the gambling Bill and the gambling regulator, but addiction to gambling is a distinct Department of Health issue and I would like the Minister of State to accept that.  What specific services are available from the Department of Health and the HSE for persons with addiction to gambling, including counselling, residential care or care wherever is required?  What services are ring-fenced for gambling addiction?  How many people were treated in the past year for an addiction to gambling by the health services?  Critically, what are the future plans in this sphere?  I know the Minister of State is ambitious to achieve in the Department.  What does he see the Department doing in the future to expand and develop services?</p><p>Addiction to gambling has to be dealt with as a separate and tragic reality and something outside of all law and regulation and everything else one deals with to prevent it in the future or minimise it.  The condition has to be dealt with separately.  We have to have evidence that the Department of Health and the HSE recognise that and that there are specific services, as we know there are for other similar difficulties, which are all functioning.  Not only that, money must be ring-fenced specifically for addiction to gambling and a strategy must be put in place to dealt with this in the future.  It is no different from any other addiction.  It is an illness and has to be defined and treated as such.  Every estimate from various sources of the number with the problem in Ireland is not less than 30,000.  It is a sad and living reality all around us.  I look forward to the Minister of State's response.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1608" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#C00200"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this important issue and welcome the opportunity to update the House on the support and services provided to persons who experience gambling addiction.  I am aware problem gambling affects a significant number of individuals and the Senator is correct in that research conducted by Ipsos on behalf of the Department of Justice estimates approximately 1% of the population is affected by problem gambling.  I would have thought it would have been a little higher.</p> <p>The Department has overall responsibility for gambling regulation and it published the interdepartmental working group report on future licensing and regulation of gambling in 2019.  The report addresses the social impact of gambling, including the issue of problem gambling and it notes the social and health impacts of gambling.  I acknowledge problem gambling can lead to social breakdown with devastating financial losses and alienation of family and friends.  Problem gambling can be associated with a range of harms, including higher risk of psychiatric disorders; alcohol and drug misuse; physical and mental health issues; separation and divorce; and unemployment and insolvency.  The interdepartmental working group recommended funding be made available for research, training and community interventions into treatment of problem gambling and gambling addiction, public education and awareness-raising programmes and the production of relevant information materials be supported and assistance be given in the provision of additional services to treat gambling addiction.  To meet these objectives, the group recommended a social fund, managed by the gambling regulatory authority, should be established.  I fully support this recommendation.</p> <p>Significant work is being undertaken in the Department of Justice to progress the general scheme for the gambling regulation Bill.  This will include the establishment of a social impact fund that will support funding services to treat gambling addiction.  The Government approved the general scheme this week and it will be published shortly.  The Department of Health does not have a remit for problem gambling.  It does not provide funding to support organisations that deal with gambling addiction or problem gamblers.  The Department is responsible for providing services for people affected by drug and alcohol addiction.  HSE and section-39-funded addiction services have, in some case of gambling addiction, provided treatment within existing resources.  Interventions currently provided to those presenting with gambling addiction include one-to-one counselling, financial advice and onward referral to other services.  However, for the Department and the HSE to provide specific services or centres for gambling addiction without additional funding would result in significant capacity issues and the lengthening of waiting lists for drug and alcohol addiction.</p> <p>The Senator asked how many people were treated last year.  I do not have the figure but I will try to get it for him.  I agree that gambling addiction is a serious issue.  I go into bookmakers and online gambling and many times, one has to self-regulate.  There are so many angles there with gambling available online, including on one's mobile phone.  It is an issue to which we need to wake up and address.  I thank him for raising this important issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#C00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  I agree with his assessment of the problem and all its human repercussions.  My basic point, which I would like the Minister of State to bring back to the Minister for consideration, is the Department of Health should accept addiction to gambling is an issue for it and there should be ring-fenced money and delineated services, as for other illnesses.  I appeal to the Minister of State to look at that.  I appreciate his response and acceptance of the great problem and the need to deal with it.  I know well that is where he is on the issue, but I appeal to him to look at it as a specific issue for the Department of Health, rather than for the Department of Justice, and to look at ring-fenced funding, direct services and support for charities.  We are on the one page.  It is a question of approach and resources and such.  I hope this debate will advance the issue and further progress will result.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1608" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#C00400"><p>I again thank the Senator for raising the issues of gambling addiction and problem gambling.  There is, without doubt, an issue with problem gambling in Ireland.  Many actions can be taken by gambling companies to minimise problem gambling, including restrictions on advertising, the ending of free bet promotions and limits on how much people can bet through online accounts.  However, there are people who will still develop problem gambling habits.  That is why we need a social fund on the gambling industry to provide supports and counselling for those affected.  The Department of Health is willing to play its role in providing additional services for those affected by gambling addiction and it is my view that the resources for these services should come from the gambling industry.  I again thank the Senator for raising this important issue, of which I have anecdotal evidence throughout the country from young men and women and many others.  It is much easier to gamble, especially online.  It is an issue we certainly need to address.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.21" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#C00450">Planning Issues</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1640" speakername="Pat Casey" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#C00500"><p>I welcome the Minister of State who has responsibility for public health, well-being and the national drugs strategy but I had hoped a Minister from the Department of Housing, Local Government and Heritage would take this matter.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Pat Casey:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2431"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2431&amp;amp;pid=PatCasey&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=21"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->In recent months and even before that, we have both seen the following headlines: "Energy blackouts this winter 'can never be ruled out'"; "European energy crisis a wake-up call for Irish policymakers"; "EirGrid warns of electricity supply shortfalls over next five winters"; "Ireland could be facing energy blackouts this winter"; "Dark days lie ahead if we fail to tackle energy crisis"; "New report paints stark picture of climate change impact in Ireland"; "Global warming to hit 'critical zone' within 20 years".</p><p>I will outline to the Minister of State what the Arklow Bank project will deliver to address two of these critical interlocking international challenges, namely, the climate crisis and the need to decarbonise our electricity system and deal with the immediate, significant energy generation capacity shortage.  This project will reduce Ireland's carbon emissions by approximately 1% and will offset more than 500,000 tonnes of harmful CO2 annually.  Wicklow currently has a housing stock of more than 56,000 homes.  This project will generate eight times the electricity required for these homes.  That is 520 MW of electricity, which is enough to power more than 450,000 homes with green energy, contributing to Ireland's action plan target of 1 GW of offshore energy by 2025.</p><p>In March, a report was presented to the Department to facilitate the extension of the long-stop dates within the lease and ensure that the project is delivered in line with the most up-to-date environmental standards.  This will allow the project to deliver the positive change in line with Ireland's ambitious climate action targets and mitigate the current electricity generation capacity crisis the country is now facing by 2025.  While I appreciate that this application requires examination, I do not consider that a delay in excess of seven months without any apparent advancement is acceptable.  This is the core of the problem, not just in the Department but with all Departments and arms of the State.  They just do not seem to understand the implications of processes and applications that are not time-bound.  The uncertainties caused by the lack of decision-making will have a significant effect on Ireland delivering solutions and addressing the challenges we face.</p><p>Arklow suffered from serious decline in the late 1990s and early 2000s when thousands of jobs were lost, including in the IFI plant, which at its peak employed more than 1,200.  These industries left behind hundreds of acres of industrial wasteland.  I have supported this project in Wicklow.  I was delighted when SSE Renewables decided to locate the operation and maintenance facility in Arklow in 2020.  This will mean 80 full-time jobs and thousands of indirect jobs in Arklow and Wicklow during the construction phase and over the project's lifetime.  It will contribute millions of euro annually to benefit communities and commercial rates.  It is a capital investment of up to &euro;2 billion to power the green recovery.  I am annoyed and frustrated at the time being taken by the Department to progress this application, which would allow it to proceed to the next stage, namely, a transboundary environmental public consultation.  If that is not achieved, we can throw our 2025 targets out the window.</p><p>Thanks to the likes of SSE Renewables, and others showing confidence in Arklow and Wicklow, Arklow is now moving to a new era of green technology, embracing new industries and new technologies.  Arklow is at a turning point in its history.  Let us not risk losing these opportunities to revitalise Arklow due to a process that is not time-bound and that is not progressing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1608" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#D00200"><p>I thank Senator Casey for raising this issue, which I am taking on behalf of the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage.</p> <p>The programme for Government contains a commitment to achieving 5 GW capacity in offshore wind off Ireland's eastern and southern coasts by 2030.  It also commits to production of a longer-term plan setting out how the State will harness the potential of at least 30 GW of offshore floating wind power in our deeper waters in the Atlantic.  This pace of development is vital to achieve a reliable supply of safe, secure and clean energy.</p> <p>Ireland's ambitions for the offshore renewable energy, ORE, sector require an up-to-date regulatory regime to provide certainty to project promoters and deliver a pathway to realising the necessary investment.  The Maritime Area Planning, MAP, Bill, currently on Committee Stage in the D&aacute;il, will enable the realisation of these ambitions for ORE by providing the necessary legislative toolkit for forward planning, well-regulated development, streamlined consenting, and comprehensive environmental assessment of proposals.</p> <p>Under the Bill, a new development management system for the maritime area has been introduced to replace the current regime, as operated under the Foreshore Act, which dates back to 1933, and was designed to manage a completely different type of marine use to that currently envisaged.  This new marine planning system will incorporate consenting for the occupation of the maritime area by means of maritime area consents, MACs, by a new agency, the maritime area regulatory authority, MARA, and a new planning consenting regime to be implemented by coastal local authorities and An Bord Plean&aacute;la.</p> <p>The Bill also sets out special provisions for ORE projects satisfying the definition of "relevant maritime usage".  The special provisions for ORE are in recognition of the need to have a pipeline of projects progressing under the new regime in order to meet our 2030 climate and energy targets.  Recognising that it will take time to establish the new agency, MARA, it was decided by the Government that the Minister for the Environment, Climate and Communications should be granted limited powers to invite MAC applications for specific ORE projects for a specified period in advance of establishment.  However, in the case of SSE Renewables and the Arklow Bank wind park phase 2 project, the company has an existing lease in place under the Foreshore Act and has now applied for an extension of the long-stop dates specified in that lease.  While it is not appropriate to comment in detail on an application that will come before the Minister for determination, it is important to note that the application by SSE Renewables is unprecedented in the level of change from the existing lease arrangements, and, accordingly, it is necessary to review the application carefully so as to ensure that any decision made upon it is as robust as possible and will stand up to any challenge that may be brought forward.</p> <p>I again thank the Senator for raising the issue.  He referred to the 80 jobs that will be provided in Arklow in the future.  He also referred to thousands of jobs in construction sector and in other areas.  I hope the various stakeholders can come to an arrangement that gets matters progressed as quickly as possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1640" speakername="Pat Casey" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#D00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his reply.  I had to wait until the very end to get exactly what I needed.  When he referred to the MAP Bill, I was concerned that he was going to suggest this project should go through that process, but it is clear that he is not.</p> <p>My issue does not just relate to the Department of Housing, Local Government and Heritage; it is all Departments.  How can a project progress if it does not know when it is going to get an answer or when it can move to the next phase?  Realistically and honestly, we will not deliver on what the Government and we, as a people, want to deliver on climate change unless the Departments make the decisions.  All decisions should be time-bound now and in the future to give certainty.</p> <p>I do not want to interfere in the process.  All I ask is when the decision will be made.  Could the Minister of State indicate when the Department will make the decision on the extension of the long-stop lease for SSE Renewables?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1608" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#D00400"><p>We want to meet our 2030 climate and energy targets.  SSE Renewables has a lease in place for the Arklow wind project, which is, fortunately, under the Foreshore Act.  Senator Casey asked when a decision will be made.  I do not have the information, but I will bring the question back to the Minister to see if we can expedite the matter as quickly as possible.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Frankie Feighan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2014"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2014&amp;amp;pid=FrankFeighan&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=21"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> It is good that an Oireachtas Member has chosen to raise this issue.  There can sometimes be blockages so it is no harm to keep an eye on things and progress matters.  I thank the Senator again.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.28" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#E00250">Employment Support Services</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#E00300"><p>I know that the Acting Chairperson and the Minister of State, who hails from the same county as me, will have an interest in this matter.  In recent times, this issue has been raised in the Seanad but it is important that we continue to fight the case on behalf of the particular group of people involved.</p><p>I will read from a letter that I received recently.  I will not mention any names or the part of the country involved, but it is a town in rural Ireland.  The letter is from somebody who is involved in a jobs club and it states:</p> <blockquote> 	As a staff member currently working a certain centre I have had no direct communication from department officials to inform me of what my future holds.  They repeatedly insist that extensive engagement has been held, but I can categorically state that <i>contracted, on the ground staff members</i>have not been engaged with at all.  While meetings have been held with independent job clubs, the letters have been sent to service providers for RFT 2, but we have been forgotten about.<br /><br />At this moment, we don&rsquo;t know whether we should be job-seeking or holding on ourselves for redundancy; a redundancy that we will probably have to jump through hoops for.  The undue stress this is causing my colleagues and I is unacceptable and unbelievably unprofessional.  We have worked alongside and collaboratively with staff in our local Department of Social Protection for over 20 years.<br /><br />When the Indecon reviews were completed, our understanding was that the new service would appear more like the existing LES services, with adaptions to incorporate the Job Club service.  Indeed, the Department have stated that the new Regional Employment Service is to &ldquo;consolidate existing LES and Job Clubs service and to extend it nationwide&rdquo;, but the opposite seems to be happening.  Disappointingly the tender appeared very similar to the JobPath service already in existence.  Why was the service model changed?  I can say that having read the tender, absolutely no part of the Job Club service has been incorporated in this new service.  The Department of Social Protection repeatedly mention that there is no LES service in the regions in Lot 1, and while that is true, it completely discounts the work the Job Club in those regions have completed over the past 2 decades. </blockquote> <p>Over 20 years, jobs clubs have played a significant role.  The letter continues:</p> <blockquote> 	It&rsquo;s like we don&rsquo;t exist!  There is also the matter of the &ldquo;tweak&rdquo; and &ldquo;learnings&rdquo; that is undergoing in the tender for RFT2.  What are these tweaks/learnings and how can it be fair that providers in Lot 1 had to tender for something potentially different?<br /><br />While we are of course worried, stressed and concerned about our own jobs, we are also greatly concerned about the future for unemployed people locally and wondering where these people are going to avail of such a service going forward.  Having heard first hand from a vast amount of clients throughout the past few years, the JobPath model does not work.  It is not popular.  It is certainly not cost-effective.  It has a large turnover of staff.  The CVs produced are questionable, often adopting the copy and paste option from job descriptions found online, with no personalization.  The jobs sent out from case workers to individuals, at times, have no connection to the persons past employment experience.  It is not person centered and it is not open to anyone who needs assistance.<br /><br />This is the wrap around service that is so vital, that will not be available for job seekers in the future.  The walk in and wrap around service we provide is extremely valuable and the new tendered service, as per JobPath does not make allowances for the people who need this. </blockquote> <p>The case has been very well made by the person who wrote the letter.  That person is very worried not just about their job future but about the people who are badly in need of this service.  We must realise that there are people out there who need support and help.  The people who work in jobs clubs do very good work.  I look forward to hearing the Minister of State's reply.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1608" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#E00400"><p>I thank my colleague, Senator Murphy, for reading that letter into the record.  I will bring the issues of concern to the attention of the Minister.</p> <p>Earlier this year, the Government published its employment services strategy, Pathways to Work 2021-2025, which contains commitments to expand the capacity of our public employment service.  The strategy also provides for an increase in resources that will deliver the regional employment service across the entire State.</p> <p>In late 2019, the Department of Social Protection commenced a review of the public employment service delivered by it and its service partners.  Following on from this review, and in line with the commitments in the Pathways to Work strategy and the Indecon reviews, the Department is making changes to how it contracts external services, including those currently provided by the local employment service, jobs clubs and JobPath.  The Department has engaged extensively with the sector about these changes.</p> <p>The existing arrangements for the LES and jobs club services extend back over 20 years without any formal procurement taking place.  This is in contravention of good governance and public procurement practice.  The Attorney General has advised that these services must be procured in line with EU and national public procurement rules by means of open and competitive tendering processes.  The Department has, therefore, commenced a two-phased procurement process, which will see the delivery of a new national employment service and a regional employment service to replace the employment services delivered by the Department's current service partners.</p> <p>The new regional employment service will deliver tailored employment services for those furthest from the labour market and for the first time these services will be available across the entire State.  The regional employment service will deliver enhanced governance oversight and ensure that those individuals who need access to employment supports and services will receive tailored high-quality services irrespective of where they live in the State.  The Indecon Review of Jobs Clubs published in 2018 recommended the integration of jobs clubs and local employment services into one service provision.  Therefore, it is not intended to contract for jobs clubs beyond 2021 in areas covered under phase 1 of the procurement process.  These areas will be covered by the new regional employment service from the start of 2022.</p> <p>Existing jobs clubs in phase 2 areas - such areas cover 19 counties - are being given a new contract for six months - from January to June 2022 - for the specific purpose of providing them with additional time to work collaboratively with other organisations on submitting a joint bid under phase 2.  The Department intends that the request for tenders for the regional employment services, under phase 2, will be published before the end of this year.</p> <p>Organisations that submitted tenders under the phase 1 procurement were notified of the outcome of the process earlier this month.  A standstill period is currently in operation and the Department cannot comment further until that has concluded.</p> <p>This process of procuring a regional employment service places a premium on ensuring a quality service that is delivered by capable and experienced practitioners who focus on accession local supports for their clients.  In areas where jobs clubs may be unsuccessful in competing for the new services, new service providers would do well to avail of the existing skill sets already available in their areas and look to employ these individuals.</p> <p>The Department's objective is to expand the provision of employment service capacity.  Another objective is to deliver high-quality employment services that are designed to meet individual's employment assistance and support requirements.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#E00500"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his answer, even though I do not agree with a great deal of it.  He knows, from the experience in our part of the country, that the jobs club is a free service which helps people with job applications and which provides formal training, walk-in support clinics, job interview preparation and information in respect of employment supports.  The clubs also arrange the provision of the latter.  The list goes on and includes information on employment rights.  These supports and services are all very important to a group of people who find it difficult to do interviews.</p> <p>I am afraid that with all of this privatised system, because that is what is going to happen in most cases, those people will fall through the cracks.  We are going to get rid of a system that is, in many parts of the country, really good, effective and free of charge looks out for people who find it difficult to find employment.  I believe that the cessation of this service is not a good step and will continue to argue that case.  However, I accept that the Minister of State will convey my comments back to the Department.  I know that he gave a response on behalf of the Department and I ask him to convey my concerns to the Minister and the officials.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1608" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#E00600"><p>I thank Senator Murphy for both of his contributions.  In the drive to enhance and deliver State-wide employment services for the long-term unemployed, and other cohorts, we cannot forget about the welfare of the people who provide those services, as the Senator rightly said.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Frankie Feighan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2014"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2014&amp;amp;pid=FrankFeighan&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=21"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->In the consultation phase of this process, I understand Department officials visited every single job club in the State and saw for themselves the quality service provided by many of them.  They have provided a great service on the ground and, as a local politician, it was great to introduce people to these services.  I thank the Senator for raising this issue.</p><p>The key message delivered then, and that I reiterate now, is that job clubs must now work with partners in their areas to ensure they have the capacity to deliver services under the new models.  As with every procurement process, existing providers may not be successful in their tender.  Where this occurs, every effort should be made by their current employer and the new service provider to come to an arrangement that ensures clients can engage with quality, experienced staff as they seek to return to employment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.34" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 11.22 a.m. and resumed at 11.30 a.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.35" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#G00100">Death of Sir David Amess MP: Expressions of Sympathy</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#G00200"><p>I did not have an opportunity to join with the Cathaoirleach in expressing my personal sympathy, and I know I speak for all Members, with the wife and family of the Sir David Amess MP in the UK.  It was a horrendous crime against a wonderful family and against democracy.  It is a crime against good values and everything that is right in humanity.  It is a horror.  We are conscious that today at 12.45 p.m. we are having a mass in his honour and for his family at St. Teresa's Church, Clarendon Street.  I hope Members can both attend where appropriate to them, and also it be borne in mind with the level of alacrity we display as we go through the business.  I call on our Leader to announce the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.37" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#G00300">An tOrd Gnó - Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#G00400"><p>The Order of Business today is No. 1, motion regarding the arrangements for the address to Seanad &Eacute;ireann by MEPs representing the European Parliament, Dublin constituency on Tuesday, 2 November, to be taken on conclusion of the Order of Business, without debate; and No. 2, the Finance (European Stability Mechanism and Single Resolution Fund) Bill 2021 &ndash; Committee Stage, to be taken at 1 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#G00500"><p>I thank the Leader.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#G00600"><p>I support the Order of Business as outlined by the Leader.  Before today's Order of Business we received news that the restrictions in regard to partners attending maternity appointments and labour will be lifted from 1 November within the hours of 8 a.m. and 9 p.m. every day.  This is welcome news.  We all acknowledge that babies are born between the hours of 9 p.m. and 8 a.m. At the same time we must be cognisant of the public health restrictions and reduced staff on duty during those hours.  I pay tribute to all the women and their partners who campaigned for this, such as Emma Cross, who gave voice to the deep frustration and sadness they had experienced.  I also thank the Leader for the role she played and the Irish women's parliamentary caucus in terms of fighting for this.</p> <p>Last week I spoke to the Minister for Health, Deputy Stephen Donnelly, in regard to this issue.  He reminded me, and it is important to remember, that six babies have died of Covid-19 in maternity hospitals and that on any given day, seven pregnant women were in ICU.  It is important to think of those lost souls and to remember them and their parents, and to wish every pregnant woman well.  It is really good news. </p> <p>It is go slow day today to remind everybody about the danger of speeding and compliance with speed limits.  There have been 113 people killed so far this year in fatal road accidents and many others injured and maimed.  It is important that we re-emphasise road safety in our schools, both primary and secondary.  We should have an education policy about cyclists, e-scooters and pedestrians.  Every school student in the country should be given a yellow vest to wear at all times.  This is very important.  </p> <p>The half-price public transport for 19 to 23-year-olds is an important and significant step.  It is important that it is for all young people, not just for students.  If I could make a call out in regard to mature students who are over the age of 23, it should be extended to them.  It should also be extended to private vehicle owners.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#G00700"><p>I thank Senator O'Loughlin.  I am going to be strict on time out of deference to the ceremonies later.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1665" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#G00800"><p>I wish to comment on the Passport Office and passport services.  I acknowledge the pressure the services and staff are under who are liaising with ourselves and the general public with regard to pressures within the system.  There is of course pent-up demand for passports, and delays due to Covid-19.  Covid-19 meant people were not travelling but they are now.  We always support Ireland as the venue of choice and people to staycation.  We have to acknowledge as well that people wish to go abroad for a break with family or with mates.  Sometimes it is planned for months, sometimes it might be a spur of the moment, and sometimes it is an emergency, it might be for a funeral or to support a loved one abroad who has illness or whatever.  The passport is so necessary, and there must be a better way than what we have at the moment in terms of the pressures, the frustration and upset, and the postponements and costs that families are incurring.  If ever there was a misnomer it is "Passport Express" because eight to ten weeks is not express.  Using that word might give people the view that that is the best way to go.  It is not.  Online is the best way to go.  Online is the quickest and most efficient way to apply.  That is not to say that there are not sometimes delays but they can be more quickly sorted online.</p> <p>The Department of Foreign Affairs needs to introduce a system of notification of time-to-renew one's passport say six months or a year in advance, by text or email.  Elderly people who may not be tech-savvy could nominate a family member to receive such a notification.  It should not be outside the bounds of modern technology to be able to do that.  Airlines could step up also.  It might not be in their interests but there should be somewhere when one is booking a flight to tick one has checked one's passport or what the expiry date of one's passport is.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Se&aacute;n Kyne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2343"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2343&amp;amp;pid=SeanKyne&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=21"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Reminders should be provided because, unfortunately, too many people only remember to check the expiry date a few days or maybe a week before their flight, only to find it has passed.  Then panic sets in, phone calls are made and blood pressure rises.  The consequences of that are huge.  There needs to be a better system in place.  Yes, Covid has caused the backlog we have at the moment, but we must also move away from the paper system and provide supports, possibly in the form of sub-offices, for those elderly people who may not be tech savvy.  There needs to be a better system.  I urge the Minister for Foreign Affairs and the Government to look at those alternatives.  We could also look at additional passport offices, including in the west, such as in Galway, for example, and in Northern Ireland.  There are actions that can be taken to expedite the process and solve some of the delays we are having.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#H00200"><p>I agree with what Senator Kyne has said.  Perhaps Passport Express should be renamed "Passport stopping at all stations".</p> <p>I thank the Leas-Chathaoirleach for mentioning the mass for the late Sir David Amess today, to which people of all faiths and none are welcome.  It is no harm at this point to thank all those who made this possible, including the British ambassador, who will address the congregation after communion today, and the Australian ambassador, who I believe will be present as well.</p> <p>The Leader will forgive me for not being here to hear her response because of arrangements I must make in respect of that ceremony, but I will be paying close attention to what she says.  As I think everybody knows, an issue has arisen with commercial rates, stemming from a decision of the High Court last week.  It deserves some focus and attention and, potentially, action from Government and the Oireachtas.  As we know, registered charities are ordinarily exempt from paying rates, but last week the High Court ruled charities which include the advancement of religion as one of their charitable objects are not exempt from rates under the Valuation Act.  This was in a case concerning Tearfund Ireland, a Christian group that does development work in impoverished parts of the Third World, which is a registered charity.  The High Court found that because one of the objects of the organisation was the advancement of religion, a phrase well-known to people who know about charity law, it could not qualify as a charitable organisation under the 2001 Act and therefore was not eligible for a rates exemption.</p> <p>It seems strange a registered charity doing work among the poor and the hungry anywhere in the world would not be considered a charitable organisation for the purposes of any legislation.  I do not think that could have been the intention of the Oireachtas when it passed the Valuation Act.  You could literally have two registered charities in adjacent premises, both dedicated to the cause of helping the homeless, with one being entirely secular and the other, because it has a religious ethos or affiliation, not being eligible under the valuation legislation.</p> <p>If the two definitions of charitable organisation in the Valuation Act 2001 and the Charities Act 2009 are not properly or fully merged by section 3 of the Valuation Act 2001, as amended, then that means there are charitable organisations that are charitable by the law on charities but are not by the law on valuation.  That contradiction cannot be let stand.  It is not my job to blame either the original legislation or the courts that interpret it.  There is a problem here that must be fixed.  The purpose of section 2(a) of the Valuation (Amendment) Act 2015 was clearly to adopt for valuation purposes the definition of "charitable organisation" in section 2 of the Charities Act 2009.  Thus, we have the faintly ludicrous, or maybe extremely ludicrous, position that the definition of "charitable purpose" is sufficient to secure exemptions from income tax, corporation tax, capital gains tax, deposit interest retention tax, capital acquisitions tax, dividend withholding tax and professional services withholding tax but insufficient to secure an exemption from the payment of rates.  That cannot have been the intention of the legislator.  I even wonder about the constitutionality of the exclusion of an organisation on the basis its charitable purpose was religion.</p> <p>This is a matter for us as legislators to attend to and I hope it is something the Government can take an interest in.  I would certainly like to be involved in the process of remedying this contradiction, which seems to have no just reason for its existence.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1688" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#H00300"><p>I join colleagues in thanking those who are making the arrangements for today's service for the late Sir David Amess.  Unfortunately, I will not be able to attend but I take this opportunity to put on record my sympathies to his family after the tragic and unbelievable events last week.</p><p>I also endorse the remarks of Senator Kyne on the Passport Office.  Any opportunity we have to engage and convey our experience of what we are dealing with is a welcome one.  It is to be hoped it will assist the valiant efforts of staff there.  I do not diminish what the workers are doing in the office.  I just think they need to be better supported to be able to do their job and expand upon the already impressive work they put in.</p><p>&Aacute;ras U&iacute; Chonghaile, the James Connolly visitor centre in west Belfast, is a fantastic tourism, community and educational facility.  It seeks to tell the story of the life of James Connolly and of his family, to give people the opportunity to engage with his story and, indeed, with his politics, writings and philosophies.  This weekend the centre will organise a sponsored walk to the historic Cave Hill, which overlooks Belfast and which was the inspiration for Jonathan Swift's <i>Gulliver's Travels</i>.  It was known also as an historic meeting place for the Society of United Irishmen, where they could meet in secret above the city.  The centre is doing a sponsored walk in solidarity with the Moore Street Preservation Trust to support the trust's plans for the regeneration, redevelopment and preservation of the Moore Street historic area.  I know there was a Commencement matter on this during the week but I would welcome the opportunity to have an update on Moore Street from the Minister responsible so we can all engage on this important issue.  I welcome and support that solidarity being expressed between both cities, going forward.</p><p>I also want to reflect on the launch yesterday by my party colleagues, Deputy First Minister, Michelle O'Neill MLA, and Caoimhe Archibald MLA, of our own tourism strategy which outlines our vision for connecting the Wild Atlantic Way and Ireland's Ancient East.  The Leader will know this is something I have raised before.  As we emerge from the restrictions and seek to bolster a safe return of tourists and visitors to Ireland, it is a timely opportunity for the Minister responsible to address us about our international work in promoting Ireland as a tourism destination and how we can all engage to ensure that destination and those services are even better for the many visitors we hope will be able to safely come and see us.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1683" speakername="Marie Sherlock" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#H00400"><p>I too extend my condolences to the Amess family and thank those involved in the service today.  Unfortunately, I cannot be there myself but Senator Wall will be.  It is important we in the Houses mark Sir David Amess's passing.</p> <p>I propose an amendment to the Order of Business such that No. 15 be taken before No. 1.  No. 15 is First Stage of the Social Welfare (Surviving Cohabitant&rsquo;s Pension) Bill 2021.  It is incredible in 21st century Ireland that cohabiting couples are assessed jointly for housing purposes, jobseeker's benefit, care benefit, medical cards and accessing college grants as mature students, yet when a partner passes away, that couple is not recognised in the eyes of the law and the remaining partner does not qualify for either a widow or widower's pension.  We believe that law needs to be changed urgently.</p> <p>The issue I wish to raise is that we are seeing an increasingly difficult situation in children's hospitals at the moment because of the sharp rise in respiratory illnesses.  Worryingly, we had reports this week of one pediatric ICU bed being available.  We have heard also the stories of parents.  Of course, only one parent is allowed in with the baby.  They are having to hold their young child for up to nine hours with no access to buggies or to support other than from the staff.  As anybody with young children knows, there is only a certain amount we can do to protect and prevent young children from acquiring viruses but what we can do is ensure speedy intervention when a temperature, a cough or whatever else arises.  It is unacceptable we have a situation where some GPs are refusing to see babies until they have a negative Covid result.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Marie Sherlock:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=MarieSherlock&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=21"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->While we can access Covid tests relatively speedily, of which I am well aware having had to do so a number of times over the past two weeks because there was Covid in my household, it can take between 25 to 29 hours, sometimes longer, to get the results.  That might be fine for an older child or an adult, but for a small baby that is simply way too long.  When infections get out of control, parents rightly become worried and they need to bring their babies to Temple Street hospital, Crumlin hospital or to any of the other paediatric wards throughout the country.  While there is free GP care, attending an accident and emergency department without a doctor's letter costs &euro;100, which is a significant cost.</p><p>I ask that the Leader would contact the Minister for Health with regard to the putting in place of a fast-track process for Covid tests for young babies because the current process is too lengthy.  We also need direction from the Irish College of General Practitioners to the effect that all GPs should be triaging babies, at least, in the car park, when they present with potential infections.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1632" speakername="Frances Black" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#J00200"><p>Today, I would like to discuss the recent announcement on the easement of restrictions with particular reference to the music and entertainment industry and the confusion, uncertainty and anomalies delivered on Tuesday afternoon.  On 31 August last, 22 October was hailed as the date for the full reopening of this sector.  Since then, preparations have been under way, rehearsals have been taking place and tickets were sold in anticipation of a return to full capacity after 587 days of closure.  Unfortunately, instead, we were delivered a plan of total confusion, contradiction and anomaly.  This plan had the appearance of an unrehearsed or thought-out performance, one that seemed more like an improvisation than a carefully composed piece.  The uncertainty and confusion is bewildering among industry professionals.  Some parts of the industry are still not free from capacity restrictions, which means work is not guaranteed or viable.  This uncertainty is accompanied by phased out pandemic unemployment payments for many in the sector who rely on the pub gigs to earn their living.  Pub gigs are under restrictions, as is dancing.  There is a considerable dancing culture in this country.  Dancing is permitted in a nightclub and at a wedding.  The confusion around Tuesday's announcement has led to absurd circumstances and the question whether people dancing is permitted at a dance.  This is a genuine question.  It is crazy.  Tuesday's announcement is another example of how the music and entertainment industry has again been disregarded and given the 11th hour and 59th minute treatment throughout this pandemic.</p> <p>In the budget, the independent sector was awarded &euro;25 million, which is a 50% cut on the necessary support in budget 2021, yet the Arts Council budget at &euro;130 million remained the same.  A pilot basic income scheme was announced to support 2,000 artists with &euro;325 per week and budgeted at &euro;25 million when the actual cost is &euro;33.8 million.  Independent musicians and entertainers, who are traditionally not funded, work extremely hard to make a living at their art.  They have to survive.  They perform, write, teach, record, manage and organise.  These people are my family members.  They tour and do anything and everything to earn a living.  When one or more achieves fame and success on the world stage, the powers that be are quick to acknowledge and associate themselves with them and praise them for their valued contribution to Irish culture, heritage and identity, yet in their 14,088 hours of need over the past 587 days, they have had to fight hard for recognition for understanding and support.</p> <p>I would like to know from the Taoiseach how much consultation took place with stakeholders in the industry prior to Tuesday's announcement.  I would also like to know what engagement the Minister for Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sport and Media , Deputy Martin, and her Department had in the week prior to Tuesday's announcement with the industry stakeholders and other Departments such that she was able to relay the industry's concerns.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1638" speakername="Malcolm Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#J00300"><p>Ba mhaith liom c&uacute;pla rud a ard&uacute;.  I share colleagues' frustrations around the delays in the Passport Office, but it is at least processing applications.  I want to again raise the fact that the registration of foreign births is listed as paused due to Covid-19.  While we are seeing a reopening of every other sector, the Department of Foreign Affairs continues this paused registration of foreign births.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1688" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#J00400"><p>That is a good point.  Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1638" speakername="Malcolm Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#J00500"><p>When things were normal, this process took 12 to 18 months.  Now, people have been waiting for well over two years.  There has been no progress.  Quite frankly, given that every other aspect of public life has opened, it makes no sense that the Department of Foreign Affairs continues to pause this service.  I am raising the matter again in the hope the Leader will raise it with the Minister and the Department.</p> <p>I welcome the appointment this week of Professor Philip Nolan, the former President of Maynooth University, as the incoming director general of Science Foundation Ireland.  He has provided great leadership during this difficult period,  This appointment presents an opportunity for us to separate the role of director general of Science Foundation Ireland and that of the chief scientific adviser.  This is something many in the science and research community, including the Royal Irish Academy, have called for for some time.  It is important that this is done.  As I said, this appointment provides that opportunity.  I intended to table a Commencement matter on this issue, but I ask that the Leader would raise it with the Minister.</p> <p>Yesterday was the 14th anniversary of the murder of Paul Quinn, who was beaten to death in County Monaghan by a provisional IRA gang.  His parents, Breege and Stephen, have long sought justice for their son, an innocent man.  The Garda have said that they now have fresh information.  Could we, through this House, appeal that anybody with information about this savage killing would come forward to give some level of peace to his family? </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" speakername="Mary Seery Kearney" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#J00600"><p>I echo Senator Byrne's remarks with regard to the Quinn family and their need for justice.</p><p>I want to read into the record a small part of an email that I received this morning.  It is similar to many emails I get all of the time.  I will read just a couple of lines:</p> <blockquote> 	My son has low vision and is registered with the NCBI.  I have fought so hard over the last eight weeks and yesterday got the call that we won and the school had been allocated, the hours needed to SNA hours. They needed eight hours a week. The stress, anxiety and upset for my son over the last eight weeks in trying to manage the school ... [that is in a wider context]. </blockquote> <p>Further on the email references that the following information was sent to this woman:</p> <blockquote> 	The NCSE has responsibility for planning and coordinating the school supports for children with special education needs, including the allocation of SNA's and reviews. The department doesn't have a role in making those determinations because we have a bespoke body who are supposed to be doing this and it's not happening.  <br /><br />The methodology that's applied by the NCSE is not effective or on time. It's not timely in its delivery of the needs for children who very clearly need SNA support. So here we have a budget that was fantastic in its allocation, that we have a government that provides for an additional and eleven hundred and sixty five SNA's for the coming year. <br /><br />That's on top of the record numbers that we've ever had employed at the state. So we have political will for the delivery of SNA's and for ensuring the children are supported in their schools and the system itself in the administration, if that breaks down. </blockquote> <p>One of the last big public meetings I attended in February 2020 was hosted by Involve Autism in Dublin 6.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Mary Seery Kearney:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=MarySeeryKearney&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=21"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->They were talking about the lack of places in schools, the type of system and the relationships with special educational needs organisers.  They are merely given lists of schools to apply for and they have to apply for 20 or 30 schools.  The system does not work.  We need an update.  We need a debate.  I am at a loss to know what else we need, but we definitely need to ensure that on the boards of these organisations, which are set up to serve the citizens of the State, we have people who represent the needs of distressed parents who are pushed to the limit emotionally in trying to fight tooth and nail for their children.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#K00200"><p>Today, I want to raise something that is very difficult to talk about but must be talked about.  My town of Duleek had the darkest of days in 2018 and 2019 when we suffered five young deaths by suicide.  This morning, I am highlighting my birth parish of Denn in County Cavan, which has experienced three young deaths by suicide this past year, all of whom were neighbours.  On Tuesday, I listened to Joe Finnegan of Northern Sound talking to the Heaslip family of Carrickaboy - Raymond, Maggie, Chloe and Finn.  I heard about a young man, their son and brother, Eden Heaslip, a bright witty fellow with a great gr&aacute; for music and cars.  I heard about his Joe Canning Galway GAA jersey, his family farm and his willingness to stand up for others.  I also heard about how he was kicked to the ground every day and how he was shouted at, "Go home to your own country", on account of his Protestant background.  I heard about his head being physically held down soiled toilets, of him being pinched at lunch tables and boxed, and how the threats from his abusers were so great that he would not even enter his own town.  I heard how the abuse followed him online, how he could not put a single thing up on social media without vile vicious comments being hurled at him and how his abusers would create new accounts to continue to harass him even after he had blocked them.  I heard about how, after carrying a pain of the heart, a pain of his mind, that it left scars deep where no one could see.  Eden came to think, "This is it, I have to put up with it.  This is the way it is going to be."  No one can live their life that way and, on 20 September, Eden Heaslip took his own life at the age of 18.  No parent should have to bury their child.  We have laws to protect employers from bullying in the workplace.  Where are the laws to protect Eden?  I ask us to hear the Heaslip family today.  Can we do our duty as legislators and put a stop to this senseless suffering?  Can we, please?</p> <p>I heard Fr. Jason, the parish priest, talking this morning on Northern Sound about this particular child.  Like so many parish priests in the country, including my own priest, Fr. John, he is instrumental in providing counselling for these young people.  God bless them in their work.  We really need to put wraparound services in local areas that are suffering such as my home parish of Denn and Duleek.  Otherwise, it will be left to us community leaders to step in where the Government has failed.  Let us not fail the Heaslip family.  Let us not fail all those families who have suffered death by suicide in this country.  There are too many.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#K00300"><p>I thank Senator Keogan.  I am conscious that we have to move on today because of the mass but I will say this: I am from that community and I know the exact case.  I know that, tragically and sadly, everything Senator Keogan has said is true.  It is a horror.  It is an unspeakable event and the events leading to it are unspeakable.  I thank Senator Keogan for raising it.  I look forward to the Leader's response on that.  This is the most serious matter raised here for a long time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#K00400"><p>I support Senator Keogan.  I just came in from the Joint Committee on Transport and Communications.  It is a harrowing story.  I had seen it online.  It is so tragic.  If anything can come out of it, it is that people might try to be that bit kinder to each other and try not to engage in this activity.  It is horrific.  Perhaps they do not appreciate what they are doing but they are really doing enormous harm.</p> <p>I rise today in relation to the final reopening of hospitality - the reopening of the late-night entertainment sector after 585 or 586 days at this stage.  It has been an enormously long time.  The previous Seanad was still sitting when the lockdown was introduced in March of last year.  At the time, we did not know what was coming.  It was all very new.  I want to wish everyone who works in or is involved with the hospitality industry, including those who avail of late bars and nightclubs, particularly young people but also those young at heart who are maybe not as young, all the very best.  I encourage everybody to do their best to try and stick to whatever guidelines are there.  We all want to open up in a reasonable way but we are cognisant that this week there are many more people in hospital than last week and many more people in ICU than last week.  This House should send a message to everyone in that industry that it is valuable and important and we appreciate the work they do.  I wish all of those who have turned 18 and will be able to go to these places for the first time, with their legal-age ID card as proof of the fact, many evenings of enjoyment.  They have never been there before.  I hope they stay safe and they mind each other.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#K00500"><p>I will begin with something I meant to say yesterday.  I wish to put on record my own support for the Leader in relation to the nonsensical emails that we have received over the past few days.  Some of those people will be outside the building today.  We do not believe in any of that nonsense and are in full solidarity with the Leader in that regard.</p> <p>The issue I want to raise today is the plight of the people of Yemen.  There was an awful landmark reached yesterday.  Ten thousand children have now been killed or maimed since fighting started in March 2015.  That is the equivalent of four children every day.  According to a UNICEF report, four out of every five children need humanitarian assistance.  That is more than 11 million children.  The plight of the people of Yemen is horrendous and the elephant in the room is that our neighbours in Britain have sold &euro;20 billion worth of arms to the Saudi authorities to help them to continue to wage their war - aircraft, helicopters, drones, grenades, bombs, missiles and various other countermeasures.  The Minister for Foreign Affairs has spoken out about the humanitarian consequences but we have a seat on the United Nations Security Council.  I would ask what are we using that seat for if we do not speak out against the horrendous policies of the British Government in relation to that war.  They are profiting to the tune of &euro;20 billion worth of equipment.  If we are to be on the UN Security Council we must be prepared to use our voice and that does not merely mean stating that the situation is awful and something must be done.  I acknowledge that we have contributed valuable aid to alleviate the plight of the people there but, surely to God, if we are on the Security Council, we need to speak out for human rights.  I am sorry to say it is another further abject failure of the Government to speak out about what is happening in Yemen, in particular Britain's role in &euro;20 billion worth of weapons to keep the crisis going and to keep children being bombed and suffering and dying, day after day.  Surely, when we are on that council, we can do better.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1656" speakername="Mary Fitzpatrick" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#K00600"><p>I urge the Leader to contact the Minister for Finance before he publishes the finance Bill and ask him to extend, in budget 2022, the provision that exists for commercial residential landlords to claim tax relief to address fire defects in apartments to owner-occupiers and social landlords.  This is an issue that has been aired on many occasions.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Mary Fitzpatrick:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=MaryFitzpatrick&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=21"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage has established an independent working group, which is evaluating the cost of these works and their extent.  The Department of Finance, to be fair, is engaged on that working group.  In the meantime the owner-occupiers are living in what can only be described as ticking time bombs.  They are living in apartments that have inadequate fire protection.  They cannot sleep at night for fear of smelling smoke or the sound of a fire.  It is unnerving for them.  On top of that, the home insurance they had is due to run out by the end of this year.  The insurance companies will not extend it beyond next year.  There is an urgency now for an intervention.  We were all horrified by Grenfell and when Priory Hall was discovered, Dublin City Council moved promptly to address that.  I urge the Leader to write to the Minister for Finance and urge him to even make a time-bound limited intervention in budget 2022 to extend the same provisions to owner-occupiers of apartments and social landlords that exist for commercial landlords.</p><p>I also thank Senator Keogan for raising that issue.  It is really heartbreaking to hear that story.  It is unbelievable for that individual and family and for all of our community.  We all need to recognise that there are a lot of toxic and very ill people in our communities and in our society.  We must all do what we can to address that and support those who are being victimised.  It is really wrong.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#L00200"><p>To make it clear to colleagues who have arrived, I am taking the prearranged list first and then will move to give the vacant slots.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1695" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#L00300"><p>I raise an issue that affects many of us around the country, namely ice rinks.  In many towns and cities, ice rinks appear at Christmas.  Many people visit them from schools and from families who get great joy.  They usually last six to eight weeks.  This year, they are finding it difficult to get the insurance.  Normally their insurance comes through London where ice rinks are able to get it.  It is usually between &euro;10,000 and &euro;25,000 for the period.  One ice rink operator from Limerick told me he has had no claims over the past 17 years, yet many companies have been quoted &euro;300,000 to operate for the six-week period while some have received quotes that are even greater.  When ice rinks are lit up it is very festive.  It is associated with the Christmas period.  It would be a shame if ice rinks did not operate in Ireland this year.  I do not know where we can raise this but it is something that needs to be raised to see if it can be resolved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1671" speakername="Erin McGreehan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#L00400"><p>I raise matters relating to the HSE.  First, I welcome the full reopening of maternity services.  I congratulate the Oireachtas women's caucus, Senator Fiona O'Loughlin and the Leader for all their work on this.  It is really important and it is way beyond time.  The situation was ridiculous.</p> <p>Second, this morning the Joint Committee on Disability Matters heard incredible testimony from advocates of the personal assistant services.  It would do us all well to look back on their testimony, as it was incredibly powerful.</p> <p>Third, now that maternity services are moving towards a full reopening, I want to raise something that I am personally affected by.  We are not doing adequate child development checks.  This country has a significant backlog.  Children are not being checked.  Mothers are getting a booklet in the post outlining where their child should be on the general development scale.  No child is general.  This is an important issue that we have to start looking at.  I have had contact over and back with the HSE.  There seems to be no plan to get through the backlog of child development checks.  In CHO 8, almost 20,000 children have not been checked.  My son is one of those.  Thankfully, I do not have any worries about my children.  Hearing, sight, clicky hips and many other issues can be seen by parents every day but they might not notice.  These development checks are important.  This morning's committee meeting was a reminder that when children are left behind, we open a bigger can of worms.  I ask the Leader contact the HSE on behalf of the House to ask for the resumption of child development checks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#L00500"><p>I thank the Senator.  I certainly relate to that matter because my wife does those checks every day.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1666" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#L00600"><p>To follow that theme, I went through a process of speech therapy with a four-year-old on Zoom during lockdown.  It was the most bizarre experience of my life.  There is a real need to look at the waiting lists that have arisen because of lockdown.  There are issues with timelines, particularly for speech therapy, and they will be grossly affected unless we get movement.</p> <p>I would like to raise amenities in State ownership, specifically the only publicly-owned swimming pool in west Cork.  It an amazing amenity that we put nearly &euro;6 million into four years ago.  It is state-of-the-art.  Unfortunately, we cannot get it open seven days a week.  It is closed every Sunday and Monday.  If money is put into amenities and we have a public swimming pool in west Cork, the most practical thing would be to put a plan in place that it would be open seven days.  The lack of such a business plan is creating chaos, particularly for swimming lessons for people who want the opportunity to learn to swim, young and old.  This is a state-of-the-art amenity and it is a disgrace that we do not have the opportunity to use it seven days.  We need an explanation for why that is happening.  The Government must also step in.  It has put money in through sports capital grants for these projects.  There must be criteria in place.  Local authorities cannot step back and say we can only open five days a week.  If they cannot keep it open seven days a week, they should not get the funding.  We will have to come down hard to make sure that the local authorities step up to make sure these public amenities can be accessed on a seven-day-a-week model. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1645" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#L00700"><p>I second Senator Sherlock's amendment to the Order of Business.  The Rescue 116 families are confronted with the possibility of massive legal costs.  I have raised the Rescue 116 incident several times here and the failure to deliver a report.  It is outrageous that these families are being called upon to pay for their legal costs.  I do not believe they were the people who initiated the review; that was the operator who has, according to the Comptroller and Auditor General, benefited from as much as &euro;7 million in State money to upgrade their aircraft and bring them in compliance for night vision.  That was in 2013 and to this day they have not fully implemented that, which is horrendous.  The House should call on the Minister for Transport to stand by the families in this case and protect them and protect their assets.</p> <p>On a related matter, a new air regulator has been appointed.  I am deeply disturbed that the regulator has moved from one of the major airlines directly into the regulator's job.  There has been no cooling-off period that I am aware of.  It is just bad business.  I would like the Minister for Transport to come to the House to debate that.  We should also have the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform before the House too.  We need to reform how people in senior positions on State boards are interviewed by various Oireachtas committees after they have been appointed, with no real methodology for us to say we do not want this person.  We must look at these senior appointments urgently.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1651" speakername="Paul Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#M00100"><p>I join with Senator Gavan in lending my support to the Leader on the email we have been receiving.  I stress the singular "email", although we may have been receiving multiple copies of it.  Where would we be without the convenience of being able to copy and paste in the world we live in?</p> <p>I wish to raise an issue that has no doubt been raised here previously, regarding scam calls and text messages.  At this stage, it is time for the Minister for the Environment, Climate and Communications or the Minister for Justice to come in here to discuss it.  I was in my parent's house recently for a very short time and during my visit my mother answered three calls on the landline that were all scam related.  I know of somebody who fell for a text message scam in a moment of weakness and lost a small amount of money from a Bank of Ireland account.  The transaction showed up on the banking 365 statement as going to another Bank of Ireland account.  Today, if we are a suspect in any case, the Garda is able to tell us our every move in the Big-Brother-is-watching world we live in.  Every activity on our phone is available and where it emanated from.  I have no doubt the telecommunications companies can stop this if they have the wherewithal to do so.  The saying is, where there is a will, there is a way.  The question is if the will is there.  Are the telecommunications companies and service providers making big money from these numbers?  Are the numbers what is known as premium numbers?  Is there a win for the companies in regard to them?  We need to get the Minister for the Environment, Climate and Communications and perhaps also the Minister for Justice to come in here.  We must get to the bottom of it.  People are wise to it and are probably not falling into the trap as often, but it is not even about falling into the trap and being caught for money.  For elderly people living alone, whose landline is their only outlet to the wider world, there can be a sense of joy and almost excitement when it rings and there is a conversation, but when they answer the phone and it is a recorded message or telling them about an Amazon package that is on its way, the only Amazon they know is the river in Brazil.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#M00200"><p>In response to the issue Senator Daly describes, it is probably far greater than that.  I know people of a certain age look at the numbers coming up on their phone and they think, "not again" and just ignore it.  However, I also know from experience that as we get older &ndash; we all have parents and older people that we represent &ndash; people worry an awful lot more about things that Senator Daly and I would not even think about.  They do genuinely start to question, for example, whether they owe &euro;18 to somebody.  They go down that little rabbit hole and they get caught for considerable amounts of money.  The Minister for Justice issued a statement in recent months advising citizens not to follow through, but it does not work in a lot of cases because older people do worry.  It is important that we have such a debate.  I will ask both the Minister for Justice and the Minister for the Environment, Climate and Communications to respond to us with a date after the recess.</p> <p>I anticipated Senator Craughwell standing up this morning when I heard on the news yesterday evening the outrageous suggestion that the families of the people who lost their lives in Rescue 116 would have to pay any legal fees just to represent their loved ones in a case and a review that was taken by the operator.  I noted with interest that the Taoiseach said in the D&aacute;il yesterday evening that no family should have to incur legal costs, but for that to be borne out and for it to be made true, somebody has to step in.  I will write today to the Minister for Transport to make sure that those families do not have to pay.  All of their assets must be protected from this review.  I thank Senator Craughwell for raising it this morning.</p> <p>I also take note of the comments Senator Craughwell made with regard to the appointment of the new regulator.  The Public Appointments Service is the body that acts on behalf of the State to ensure that there is no conflict of interest and that there is a cooling off period if it is required.  I have to assume it happened in this case, but let us find out.  I will write a letter today to the Minister and I will make sure to come back to the Senator.</p> <p>Senators Lombard and McGreehan spoke about the service to provide development checks for children with extra special needs and how they have been severely interrupted in the past 18 months.  I do not find it acceptable that the HSE says it has no plans to find a way to resolve the backlog.  We will send a letter to the HSE today asking for its detailed plan in all CHOs to ensure that development checks happen as they are incredibly important, especially for newer parents.  Like me, the Senators have a few children so perhaps one grows in confidence as one has more babies, but it is vital in particular that first-time parents get the support.  There are also parents whose children have special needs and require extra help and assistance such as occupational therapy.  In normal times, we talk about the delays that families experience and I cannot even begin to imagine the extra delays and difficulties they have experienced in the past 18 months.  We must get through that and start living our new lives and making sure that we catch up on the services that matter.</p> <p>Senator Maria Byrne spoke about ice rinks and the fact that they cannot get insurance.  I will send a letter to the Minister of State, Deputy Fleming, today to ask him if he will intervene because it is certainly something that people look forward to, and it is an outdoor event, which we are encouraging people to engage in during the winter.</p> <p>Senator Fitzpatrick called for an extension of the tax relief provision for commercial landlords to owner-occupiers to address the fire defects that many thousands of residents who are living in apartments face.  I will send a note to the Minister for Finance today and ask him to respond to that.</p> <p>Senator Gavan spoke this morning about the continuing awfulness experienced by the people in Yemen.  He raises a vital point, that we cannot continue to blindly ignore those countries that are profiteering off the back of these people's misery.  I will send a note to the Minister for Foreign Affairs and ask him to come back to us or for us to have a debate here in the coming weeks on the role we play on the Security Council and how it can benefit from an Irish perspective all the people with whom we stand in solidarity.</p> <p>Senators Horkan and Black raised very eloquently the real frustration that is being felt by the industry they represent.  I cannot even begin to understand or imagine how people must have felt this week listening to the mixed messages.  I do not blame anybody for that, as the information was only related to the Cabinet on Monday.  Ministers tried their very best to give as much information as they could, albeit confusing, on Tuesday.  Yesterday, the Minister for the Environment, Climate and Communications said that there was engagement with the industry.  I do not know how much or how little there was, but those involved tried to engage in the last couple of days, so as to come up, I hope, with a new set of recommendations today.  It is difficult.  It has even been the source of mirth in recent weeks about leaving space for the holy spirit when we go dancing.  How can one have drinks in a nightclub and not be standing beside someone?  It is difficult, but the unenviable position of the Cabinet is that it has to find a way that these industries can reopen safely.  That is nearly an oxymoron, but we must and will reopen all our industries and learn to live in the new world of trying to mind ourselves, while we make sure that people can earn their living and provide us with great entertainment.  One of my colleagues from Skerries, Councillor Tom O'Leary, sent me a video last night of him in Nealon's Bar in Skerries with the fire lighting and the live music in the corner.  We all just want to get back to there and to enjoy the talent Senator Black and many members of her family provide.  I support her and I hope how we will deal with the restrictions is announced today.</p> <p>Senator Sherlock moved an amendment to the Order of Business.  I am very happy to accept the amendment.  I wish her well with her Bill.  I hope it brings change.  I often thought when I was Minister that it was very odd that when somebody receives a widow's pension, that if she manages to find love again the widow's pension is taken off her.  I do not know when one stops being a widow if one has lost one's first partner.  There are lots of anomalies.  I wish the Senator well.</p> <p>Senator &Oacute; Donnghaile asked me to send a letter to the Minister seeking an update on Moore Street.  I will do that and send him a copy today.</p> <p>Senator Mullen raised a very odd anomaly that arose from a High Court case during the week.  I accept that the only way to resolve the issue is for us to amend the Bill and I will work with the Senator to see if we can find a way to do it.</p> <p>Senator Kyne started the day off by talking about the passport system.  We are all incredibly frustrated, and that is not even coming close to the frustration of parents whose children are getting passports and the parents are not.  I do not know how we expect families to go away together if we do not look after them as a unit, but we need to come up with a better system.  Something has happened with the wonderful online system that we all lauded last year, whereby people said they applied on a Monday and got their passport on a Wednesday, because it is not working either.  The Minister for Foreign Affairs sent us all an email yesterday outlining his plans.  I hope they work.</p> <p>Senator O'Loughlin opened today's proceedings talking about the announcement from the HSE this morning that it is now going to change the visiting hours in maternity hospitals to pre-pandemic visiting hours.  Anybody can go and visit from 8 a.m. to 9 p.m.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Regina Doherty:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2295"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2295&amp;amp;pid=ReginaDoherty&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=21"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This means that any daddies who are lucky enough that their partners have their babies between 8 a.m. and 9 p.m. will get to be there for the entire labour journey.  It is a step forward, but it is not enough.  I commend the women from the Better Maternity Care group because at least we know that their voices are being heard.  They are making good strides in providing what should be the best maternity journeys for all women and their partners.  I commend them again because this is certainly is a step in the right direction.</p><p>I thank Senator Keogan for raising what is the most awful of tragedies.  I heard details of it on the radio in the past couple of days.  Indeed, I saw the beautiful photograph that the family released of young Eden with his birthday cake on his 18th birthday.  I extend my deepest condolences to his family and his community on what is an absolute tragedy.  What is also a tragedy is that the kind of bullying to which that young boy was subjected for the last number of years in his life is not uncommon and is probably happening in every single town and school in this country in which we all live.  The problem is that nobody talks about it.  People keep it quiet, try to deal with it in their family and support their loved ones as best as they can.  We reach a point, however, where young people cannot cope any more because there is no other way for them to deal with the pain and trauma that they are going through.  For young Eden to make the choice and take the route he did was an absolute tragedy.</p><p>What we need to start talking about is not just prevention in the context of people who are in crisis, we also need to make sure that the services are in place, that the interventions start far earlier than when somebody actually presents to Pieta House or Jigsaw because they are harming themselves or looking for ways out of the pain they are in.  Prevention needs to start far earlier for people who are subjected to bullying, violence and even intimidation on social media platforms, which affects our children, on the basis of their resilience, in entirely different ways.  We need to start really talking to and educating the young people who are perpetrating the harassment, violence and bullying.  I know from experience that they do not really realise the harm that they are doing until it is too late, and then they have to live with the harm they have caused.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1645" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#N00200"><p>We might organise a specific debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#N00300"><p>Unfortunately, there is no legislation relating to minors when it comes to this issue.  Perhaps, as legislators, we could examine the matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#N00400"><p>Maybe the Senator is right.  After the recess, I will see how we can have a debate on how best we can formulate a policy or programme in schools and homes to support families and children in order to ensure that tragedies such as that involving Eden do not happen again.  I thank Senator Keogan for raising the matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#N00500"><p>I thank the Leader for her responses, particularly the last one.  I also thank Senator Keogan.  I hope, please God, that we can discuss the matter again because it is beyond serious.</p> <p>Senator Marie Sherlock has moved an amendment to the Order of Business: "That No. 15 be taken before No. 1."  Senator Craughwell seconded the amendment.  The Leader has indicated that she is prepared to accept the amendment.  Is the amendment agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.73" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Order of Business, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.74" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#N00800">Social Welfare (Surviving Cohabitant’s Pension) Bill 2021: First Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1683" speakername="Marie Sherlock" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#N00900"><p>I move:</p> <blockquote> 	That leave be given to introduce a Bill entitled an Act to amend the Social Welfare Consolidation Act 2005 to entitle surviving cohabitants to a contributory pension; and to provide for related matters. </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.76" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#N01000"><p>When is it proposed to take Second Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1683" speakername="Marie Sherlock" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#N01100"><p>Next Tuesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#N01200"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.80" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Second Stage ordered for Tuesday, 26 October 2021.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.81" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#N01400">Address to Seanad Éireann by Members of the European Parliament: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#N01500"><p>I move:</p> <blockquote> 	That, in accordance with Standing Order 57(1) and the approval of the Committee on Parliamentary Privileges and Oversight, Seanad &Eacute;ireann agrees that, in respect of the European Parliament Dublin Constituency, Mr. Barry Andrews MEP, Mr. Ciar&aacute;n Cuffe MEP, Ms. Clare Daly MEP, and Ms. Frances Fitzgerald MEP, may attend and be heard in Seanad &Eacute;ireann on Tuesday, 2nd November, 2021, and that the following arrangements shall apply:<br /><br />The proceedings shall commence at 5 p.m., shall not exceed two hours, and shall consist of&mdash;  	 <blockquote> 	(<i>a</i>) a speech of welcome by the Cathaoirleach;<br /><br />(<i>b</i>) an opening address by each MEP which shall not exceed six minutes in each case;<br /><br />(<i>c</i>) a contribution not exceeding five minutes by a spokesperson from each Group;<br /><br />(<i>d</i>) a single response not exceeding two minutes by each MEP to the combined issues raised by the Group;<br /><br />(<i>e</i>) questions from all other Senators in accordance with the sequence set out in the Schedule to this resolution, which shall not exceed one minute in each case, and a reply not exceeding two minutes from each MEP;<br /><br />(<i>f</i>) a final concluding statement of not less than four minutes by each MEP;<br /><br />(<i>g</i>) a speech of thanks by the Leader of the House; </blockquote>and the members of the European Parliament may take seats on the floor of the Seanad Chamber.<div>Schedule</div>Fianna F&aacute;il Group<br /><br />Fine Gael Group<br /><br />Independent Group<br /><br />Green Party<br /><br />Sinn F&eacute;in Group<br /><br />Labour Group<br /><br />Civil Engagement Group.  </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.83" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.84" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 12.35 p.m. and resumed at 1 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.85" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#Q00100">Finance (European Stability Mechanism and Single Resolution Fund) Bill 2021: Committee Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#Q00200"><p>I welcome the Minister for Finance, Deputy Paschal Donohoe, back to the House, exactly a week since he was last here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.87" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Section 1 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.88" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>SECTION 2</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.89" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That section 2 stand part of the Bill."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#Q00600"><p>The Minister is very welcome.  I would like to speak to the section.  I have a number of questions for the Minister regarding the amending agreement.  My colleague, Senator Higgins, engaged with the Minister on this legislation on Second Stage.  She is at the Conference on the Future of Europe today and could not attend the Seanad but looks forward to engaging again with the Minister on these issues on Report Stage.</p> <p>The amending agreement in the legislation allows that, as part of a memorandum of understanding relating to a financial assistance agreement, the sale of public assets can be attached as a conditionality.  We know, for example, that the Greek Government is in the process of selling its stake in a number of the country's largest ports.  This is part of a much larger process of privatisation of state assets that was a key condition of Greece's bailout from the International Monetary Fund, IMF, following the recession.  The selling off of state assets should not form part of any financial assistance agreements.  We know from areas such as housing and climate that the selling off of public assets and infrastructure often means countries cannot deliver key public services to their citizens.  Does the Minister think it is appropriate for the selling off of public assets to be allowed within financial assistance agreements such as this when we have a large volume of evidence showing that such actions undermine social cohesion and the long-term public finances?</p> <p>I have a number of questions on the eligibility criteria contained in the amending agreement.  The amending agreement is purporting to change the precautionary conditional credit line because it did not work and only nine countries qualified, but it is making the same mistake again.  When Senator Higgins engaged with the Minister, he pointed out that many of the fiscal criteria had been suspended in regard to the credit line and the credit that had to be provided during Covid.  However, that too shows that the precautionary credit line and the tools we had were inadequate and that additional and different approaches needed to be taken in respect of the Covid crisis.  This does not represent a different approach.  We are facing more global crises such as the climate and biodiversity crisis and we will need functioning tools for financial assistance.  Has there been any assessment of how the eligibility criteria for this agreement will be able to support countries in respect of climate or strategic social infrastructure, for example?  Eligibility criteria and complying with the terms of any agreement should never be placed at odds with aspects of EU law, with human rights or with the environment.  Has the Minister engaged with his EU counterparts on how complying with the European Stability Mechanism, ESM, might force countries into a situation where, in order to get financial assistance, they have to undermine themselves with regard to the extremely important issues I just mentioned?</p> <p>The amending agreement grants extensive powers to the board of directors in respect of the eligibility criteria.  The agreement provides that the board will notify the depository once ESM members have completed their applicable national procedures.  Does this include engagement with national parliamentarians?  We need to have the space to debate how changes to the eligibility criteria might affect our ability to access financial assistance and how that would intersect with the other public policy goals we have in our parliaments.  We cannot have a situation where national parliaments of ESM members, some of which may be majorly disadvantaged by changes in the criteria, are not consulted.  Will the Minister commit to a review, to be published, of the precautionary conditioned credit line mechanism and the eligibility criteria set out in annex III?  That annex offers a modelling of risk scenarios, including risk regarding climate, and the readiness or appropriateness of the precautionary conditioned credit line, the relationship between the ESM eligibility criteria, or memorandums of understanding, MOUs, where applicable, and EU law and policy, including law and policy in respect of human rights, environment and social cohesion.</p> <p>I would also add that the provisions of this section and this legislation seem premature as the Conference on the Future of Europe, where MEPs, national parliamentarians and citizens are debating and discussing our collective future in the EU, is ongoing and the output of that process may well result in changes to EU policy in respect of this area.  Will the Minister and his counterparts be looking at how the conference's outputs intersect with things like the ESM?  I look forward to the Minister's response and I may bring forward amendments relating to these issues on Report Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1558" speakername="Paschal Donohoe" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#Q00700"><p>I thank the Senator for the issues he has raised on behalf of Senator Higgins.  I look forward to debating these matters with her directly on Report Stage.  I will go through the different issues the Senator raised.  The first relates to the eligibility criteria and whether it is appropriate that any government be in the position of selling off its share in an asset it currently publicly owns.  That did not happen here in Ireland.  Our ports, airports and infrastructure went into the global financial crisis publicly owned and they exited publicly owned.  Our important semi-State bodies continued to be in a position where they were either entirely or mostly publicly owned.  It can be the case for some governments that that is a decision they decide to make, in conjunction with the engagement they have with the ESM.  It is a decision that we mostly avoided having to make here in Ireland but I respect the fact that other governments may decide that it is an appropriate decision for them, as opposed to other decisions that they would otherwise take.</p> <p>My broad point on what the Senator has said, which goes back to an issue I touched on during our debate last week, is that the issue of conditionality must be seen in light of the fact that other taxpayers are ultimately paying into this fund.  As Ireland becomes a bigger and bigger net contributor in the years to come, this Parliament will be asking the Government of the day if these funds are used and under what criteria they are accessed.  That is a question taxpayers who are contributing into these funds ask of their governments and it will increasingly be asked of an Irish Government too.  That is why I believe that while conditionality is a difficult question and one that raises difficult matters, the principle is nonetheless one that should be preserved.  If funds are being accessed, whether through lending or even grants, as is the case now with EU recovery fund, they should be accessed on the basis of clear criteria.</p> <p>As to whether this is in any way at odds with the law of the European Union, the answer to that question is that it is not.  One of the reasons this legislation is so complex is that it has to be consistent with the law of the European Union on all matters, whether that be the preservation of the Single Market or the balance that is in the law of the EU between the roles of European central institutions and national governments.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Paschal Donohoe:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2244"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2244&amp;amp;pid=PaschalDonohoe&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=21"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The answer to the question of whether we will consider the output of the Conference on the Future of Europe in relation to these and other matters in the future is "Yes".  We will do so because the process that is under way is a good one.  It will be helpful in making the decisions we need to make on the future of the EU to have a forum within which the views of a wide range of parliamentarians throughout Europe can be considered.</p><p>I am not committing to the publishing of a review on this because it is ultimately something that will be about a potential relationship between another national government and the ESM, which I hope never happens.  It is not appropriate for me to commit to a review of a relationship that could be taking place elsewhere between an EU institution and another national government.  Of course, I will always be available for debates and discussions on these issues, both in this House and the D&aacute;il, because it is an issue that will be important to parliaments.</p><p>This leads on to the question raised on the role of national parliaments.  Again, while I disagree with the Senator, I acknowledge his point.  The relationship is fundamentally one between the ESM and the governments of the EU, which in turn are accountable to their parliaments, as opposed to the ESM operating directly to national parliaments.  The appropriate area of accountability should be between the ESM and national governments, while governments are accountable to their parliaments.  If we were to give a further role to national parliaments, first, it would undermine that important balance of accountability and, second, it is very conceivable that the ESM could operate in an atmosphere in which time and a display of urgency really matters.  With that in mind, practically, the best and most appropriate relationship to preserve is that between governments and the ESM, given all the further issues that could be involved if we were to elongate or change the process to directly involve the role of national parliaments as well.</p><p>On the final set of questions about whether it is premature to move ahead with something like this, Senator Higgins is probably referring to the work that is under way on the future of the Stability and Growth Pact.  If any discussion or change takes place regarding the criteria for the pact or how it operates, we will need to consider the implications of that for other parts of the architecture of the EU.  That being said, it is very much up to the ESM, within which countries are represented, to reach an agreement with countries on how funds should be made available to them.  It will always be mindful of where the view of the EU is, in the round, on these issues.  We need to accept that the ESM needs to have the capacity and ability to do that work itself, especially if we are in a situation where a matter is urgent or where we could even be in a crisis-like atmosphere in which time matters when responding to these issues.</p><p>On whether issues of social cohesion are taken into account, again, this a matter that national governments tend to be highly aware of when they are trying to reach agreement with the ESM on funding issues.  These issues are recognised.  To be truthful about the matter, in a crisis situation there are differing views on how that social cohesion can be recognised and maintained in a process like this.  From my experience of how these issues evolve, this is an issue the national government that is engaging with the ESM is always highly aware of. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#R00200"><p>I appreciate the Minister's comments and I look forward to Report Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.94" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.95" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sections 3 to 7, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.96" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>NEW SECTIONS</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#R00600"><p>Amendment No. 1 is in the name of Senator Higgins who is not present.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#R00700"><p>I move amendment No. 1:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 7, between lines 17 and 18, to insert the following: <br /><br /><b>&ldquo;Report </b><br /><br /><b>8.</b>The Minister shall, within 12 months of the passing of this Act, publish a report setting out the measures taken to ensure appropriate safeguards and separation between ESM cooperation with the EU Commission on any area of policy and ESM engagement with private investors.&rdquo;. </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1688" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#R00800"><p>I second the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#R00900"><p>This amendment seeks "a report setting out...measures...[for] appropriate safeguards and separation between ESM cooperation [and] the EU Commission on any area of policy and ESM engagement with private investors."  On Second Stage, my colleague, Senator Higgins, outlined how it is unclear what the firewalls will be regarding engagement with private investors in terms of the ESM.  I would be concerned if, on the one hand, the Minister is seeking to play an active role within the European Commission in the implementation of its policy functions - there is a policy ambition that is concerning in this refrain - and, on the other hand, there are plans to segue in respect of private investors.  How will we firewall these two parts of the process?  How will we be clear on what exactly the Commission is doing in comparison with what the ESM is doing?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1558" speakername="Paschal Donohoe" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#R01000"><p>I do not propose to accept this amendment to add a new section 8 to the Bill.  This amendment provides for the publication of a report outlining details on two separate matters: first, measures taken to ensure appropriate safeguards and separation between ESM co-operation with the EU Commission in the area of policy; and second, ESM engagement with private citizens.  I will say a word about each in turn.</p> <p>On the first matter, my understanding of the objective of the proposed amendment is to gain assurances via the proposed report that the new enhanced co-operation between the ESM and the Commission will comply and be consistent with EU law, in particular with measures adopted in the field of EU economic policy co-ordination.  A key concern expressed by the Senator in her previous engagement on the Bill relates to the future role of the ESM.  I appreciate her concerns and recognise it is clear that the content of conditionalities is directly linked to the measure of economic policy co-ordination under the SGP.  As such, the space for autonomy of the ESM in this area is limited and its role must be predominantly related to its function as lender.  </p> <p>In defining the new role for the ESM, the euro area member states recognise there are limitations to the role of the ESM.  In practice, the Commission's liaison with the ECB and the ESM would collaborate on the design and negotiation of policy conditionality.  The ESM would contribute, from its perspective as a lender, to areas that are directly relevant to the beneficiary member states' financing needs and ability to repay the ESM, as well as the organisational and operational aspects of the funding of the member state to help to restore its financial situation.  The latter task pertains to the operational organisation of the debt office, its management strategy and technical assistance.  </p> <p>In addition, it is important to note that the compatibility of the existing ESM treaty with the exercise of competencies of economic policy under the EU treaties has already been checked by the European Court of Justice, ECJ, in the Pringle case.  In this judgment, the ECJ underlined the role of the Commission as the institution called to ensure consistency with EU law in the course of ESM operations.  The new arrangements regarding the enhanced co-operation between the ESM and the Commission in the ESM treaty amending agreement have been carefully crafted to respect the parameters laid down by the Court of Justice.  Given the ECJ recognises the Commission as the institution with responsibility for ensuring consistency, it is not appropriate for the Minister for Finance to publish a report regarding matters that are the responsibility of the European Commission.</p> <p>On the second matter, the Senator proposes that I publish a report on ESM engagement with private citizens and investors within 12 months of the passing of the Act.  However, in its annual report, the ESM details its funding and investor relations activities for the previous 12 months.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Paschal Donohoe:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2244"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2244&amp;amp;pid=PaschalDonohoe&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=21"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I made this report accessible to the Oireachtas in accordance with my obligations under Article 30(5) of the ESM treaty.  I am therefore satisfied the information the centre is seeking is available and will continue to do so each year in the ESM annual report.  While I will not be accepting the amendment, I am happy to engage further with the Senator on the matter, especially on Report Stage.</p><p>If the Senator is specifically concerned about the new role of the ESM, I can assure her that in accordance with recital 11(a) of the amending agreement, the ESM's involvement in such negotiations can only be at the request of the member state in question.  In addition, the ESM's involvement will be on an informal, non-binding, temporary and confidential basis.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#S00200"><p>I will withdraw the amendment with a view to further engagement on Report Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.104" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#S00350"><p>Amendment No. 2 is also in the name of Senator Higgins.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#S00400"><p>I move amendment No. 2:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 7, between lines 17 and 18, to insert the following:   	<b>&quot;Report </b><br /><br /><b>8. </b>The Minister shall, within 12 months of the passing of this Act, conduct and publish a report outlining where compliance with EU fiscal criteria has precluded public strategic investment or required public services or infrastructure to be delivered &quot;off balance sheet&quot; and the additional costs associated with such short term expenditure versus long term investment.&quot;.  </blockquote> <p>This amendment asks the Minister to publish a report outlining where compliance with EU fiscal criteria has precluded public strategic investment or required public services or infrastructure to be delivered off balance sheet and the additional costs associated with such short-term expenditure versus long-term investment.  As my colleague, Senator Higgins, has highlighted, the EU fiscal rules have been used as an excuse not to invest in public services or deliver services off balance sheet.  We know with the suspension of EU fiscal rules that this is no longer an excuse and we need a proper examination of how those rules have impacted our public expenditure.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1558" speakername="Paschal Donohoe" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#S00500"><p>This amendment will provide for the publication of a report outlining where compliance with EU fiscal criteria has precluded public investment or required public services or infrastructure to be delivered off balance sheet with the additional costs associated with such short-term expenditure versus long-term investment.  It is important to recognise the EU fiscal rules do not limit the level of Government expenditure, nor do they require infrastructure to be delivered off balance sheet.  Additional public investment is always possible if it is matched by revenue-raising measures or offsetting expenditure adjustments elsewhere or both.  In addition, to avoid penalising spikes in Government investment, the framework allows investment to be smoothed over a four-year period.</p> <p>I take the opportunity to bring the Senator's attention to the review of EU economic governance which the Commission relaunched.  This review provides an opportunity for stakeholders to engage in this public debate to build a consensus on the future of the governance framework.  I encourage the Senator to engage in the debate through various forums and will be happy to engage with her further, but I am not in a position to accept the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#S00600"><p>I will withdraw this amendment with a right to resubmit and further engagement on Report Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.109" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.110" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Section 8 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#S01100"><p>Amendments Nos. 3 to 12, inclusive, have been ruled out of order as they are in conflict with the principle of the Bill as read a Second Time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.112" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendments Nos. 3 to 12, inclusive, not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.113" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Schedule 1 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.114" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Schedules 2 and 3 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.115" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Title agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.116" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Bill reported without amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#S01600"><p>When is it proposed to take Report Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1695" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#S01700"><p>Next Tuesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#S01750"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.120" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Report Stage ordered for Tuesday, 26 October 2021.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#S01900"><p>When is it proposed to sit again?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1695" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021102100002#S02000"><p>At 2.30 p.m. on Tuesday, 2 November 2021.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-21a.123" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>The Seanad adjourned at 2.25 p.m. until 2.30 p.m. on Tuesday, 2 November 2021.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>