<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.4" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#A00100">Gnó an tSeanaid - Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Eugene Murphy that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister with responsibility for mental health and older people to make a statement on the development of later life psychiatry services at the former Rosalie Unit in Castlerea, County Roscommon. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Garret Ahearn of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Health to provide an update on increased uptake of the Covid-19 vaccine since the Government announcement on 19 October of the continuation with the requirement to show the EU digital Covid certificate. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Tim Lombard of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Health to make a statement on the disposal of baby organs by incineration at Cork University Maternity Hospital.  </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Erin McGreehan of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine to make a statement on plans to ensure the viability of the sheep sector, including the status of the wool feasibility study. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Malcolm Byrne of the following matter: </p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sport and Media to make a statement on the introduction of a universal basic income for artists and art workers. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Barry Ward of the following matter: </p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Education to make a statement on the lack of parity between the use of traditional and simplified Chinese characters in leaving certificate Mandarin Chinese. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Ollie Crowe of the following matter: </p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Justice to make a statement on her Department&rsquo;s plans to address the growing issue of antisocial behaviour in Eyre Square, Galway city. </blockquote> <p>Of the matters raised by the Senators suitable for discussion, I have selected those raised by Senators Murphy, Ahearn, Lombard and McGreehan and they will be taken now.  I regret that I had to rule out of order the matter raised by Senator Crowe on the ground that the Minister has no direct responsibility in this area.  The other Senators may give notice on another day of the matters they wish to raise.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.7" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#A00300">Nithe i dtosach suíonna - Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.8" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#A00500">Psychiatry Services</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#A00600"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it, mo chomhghleaca&iacute; agus mo chara.  I thank the Cathaoirleach for considering this matter and allowing us to debate it.  I thank the Minister of State, Deputy Butler, for coming to the House to deal with this Commencement matter.  The Minister of State's commitment to mental health and to older people is well recognised throughout the country.  To be honest, communities continuously tell me about the great work being done by her.  I want to acknowledge that here this morning.</p> <p>It would be fair to say that it was during my time as a Deputy, that the Minister of State would have heard more about the old Rosalie Unit, as we discussed it over and over again.  The centre was a home for several people who suffered from dementia.  There was controversy when it was closed.  That is water under the bridge at this stage, but a new centre was promised, which was announced in June 2020 by the then Minister of State with responsibility for mental health, Jim Daly.  I believe the head of the HSE was there and, if I am not mistaken, then Taoiseach, Deputy Varadkar, was also online as was the Minister for Health.</p> <p>This new centre was to be a day care centre for CAMHS and for psychiatry in later life, which is vital and important.  There have been some developments there, and I welcome the commitment of the Minister of State, Deputy Butler, to the centre.  I am informed that CAMHS' work is up and running on certain days in the week, which is very welcome.  I am aware it is the Minister of State's desire to see everything that was promised is done.  I am aware the Minister of State is committed, and that when she has something she wants to achieve that she will achieve it.</p> <p>I am looking for an update as to where we stand with the new e-health centre in Castlerea, County Roscommon.  There seem to be issues around psychiatry of later life services.  Is it a staffing issue?  I am aware that the Minister of State has provided the money.  I do not know if there are issues around getting staff.  It is important and crucial that once and for all we ensure this centre gets up and running as quickly as possible.</p> <p>The Minister of State will also have heard me speak previously about the unspent money from 2012 to 2015, which was &euro;18 million for mental health services for our county.  That money was not returned.  The money should have been put into mental health services at the time.  It is still a big bone of contention with people and it is highly regrettable that this has happened.  When the system needed that support it did not get it.  This is an issue for the people who deal with mental health and with the public in our own county.</p> <p>I will not delay any longer and I look forward to the Minister of State's reply.  I hope that we can get some clarification this morning.  I am sure the Minister of State will appreciate the absolute importance of the centre.  It is great that it was promised.  It is great that part of it is up and running, but we need to get the whole matter sorted now.  I look forward to the Minister of State's reply.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1614" speakername="Mary Butler" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#A00700"><p>It is good to see Senator O'Sullivan in the Chair.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1694" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#A00800"><p>It is lovely to see the Minister of State, Deputy Butler, in the House.  It would be remiss of me not to welcome you.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1614" speakername="Mary Butler" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#A00900"><p>I thank Senator Murphy for raising this issue in Seanad &Eacute;ireann.  I can safely say that this is not the first time I have heard about this from the Senator.  As Senator Murphy has said, we have spent a lot of time discussing the previous Rosalie Unit.</p> <p>The project was announced by then Minister of State, Jim Daly, in June 2020, comprising a new CAMHS Connect day hospital and a psychiatry of later life day hospital.  In 2020, &euro;800,000 was provided for establishment works and staffing recruitment by the HSE.  In 2021, 14 posts were approved with an allocation of &euro;1.4 million.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Mary Butler:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2445"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2445&amp;amp;pid=MaryButler&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Staffing for the CAMHS Connect day hospital includes a consultant psychiatrist, a non-consultant hospital doctor, an advanced nurse practitioner, a senior social worker, a clinical nurse specialist, a senior psychologist and an occupational therapist.  We are trying to put in place multidisciplinary teams around the country that will be able to support people with mental illnesses across all disciplines.  The consultant, the non-consultant hospital doctor, the advanced nurse practitioner and the senior social worker for this team have been recruited.  The remaining three posts are at an advanced stage of the recruitment process.</p><p>The following services are now available from the CAMHS Connect team: CAMHS multidisciplinary clinics, including a monthly mental health intellectual disability clinic; diagnostic assessments; cognitive behavioural therapy, CBT, and family therapy, which is important in supporting the families of loved ones with mental illness; outreach support; and CAMHS group work, which is being run to deliver therapy to young people.  There is an existing psychiatry of later life service at Castlerea.  Staffing for the new psychiatry of later life day hospital includes a consultant psychiatrist, a non-consultant hospital doctor, an advanced nurse practitioner, a social worker, a clinical nurse specialist, a senior psychologist and a senior occupational therapist.  The non-consultant hospital doctor has recently taken up the duties of the position, and the remaining posts are going through the recruitment process and will be filled as soon as possible.  Funding is allocated to the local mental health service as staff are appointed.</p><p>One of the real challenges being experienced is in recruiting staff.  It can take up to 50 weeks to recruit and successfully put a person in place in a role, especially if the post must be backfilled.  We are seeing this challenge with recruitment throughout the country and I have had many discussions about this issue.  I met the CAMHS team in north county Dublin yesterday.  When we are recruiting for staff, whether in the public, private or voluntary areas, and regardless of whether the recruitment is undertaken by NGOs or the HSE, we are all dipping into the same pool of personnel.  It is difficult, but suffice it to say the will is there, the funding is there and recruitment for posts is under way.</p><p>The new psychiatry of later life day hospital on site will meet evolving mental health needs across a wide catchment area.  A major component of the new services is outreach to emergency and inpatient units through telepsychiatry.  This approach will continue to be developed by mental health professionals.  The new psychiatry of later life day hospital reflects a new and improved approach to meeting the mental health needs of older people in the region, compared with the old Rosalie unit which was based on the same site in Castlerea.  The day hospital will provide a real alternative to inpatient mental health care in Roscommon and will facilitate older people living in their own homes or in nursing homes.  Specific programmes will be delivered for older people with severe mental health difficulties and individuals with dementia, including a new memory clinic.  The service will provide another option in addition to acute hospital care, delay admission to continuing care and provide carer respite capacity.  Services also include cognitive behavioural therapy and other therapies, anxiety management, recovery programmes, as well as art, music and healthy living skills.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#B00200"><p>I welcome the statement from the Minister of State.  Commitments were given regarding CAMHS and they have been fully looked after with these developments.  I welcome that the Minister of State addressed the subject of the psychiatry of later life, but it is now clear that some issues remain concerning staffing.  The Minister of State explained the situation very well in respect of how long it is taking to get staff into certain areas.  The good thing I take from what the Minister of State said is that good progress is being made in this area.</p> <p>It is also interesting to note what was said about telepsychiatry.  Things change and this is something new and it will be part of how we deal with issues such as this in future.  It is clear from what was said that this service will be up and running fully and that new ideas and approaches are emerging.  I would love if the Minister of State would come to visit County Roscommon and this centre and have a discussion on these issues, including going through what is happening there.  It would be well worthwhile.  The invitation has been issued now, and I hope the Minister of State does not think I am being cheeky in pushing it on her like this.  We would love to have her down there with us soon to discuss this matter further.  I thank her for being here this morning and for her clear answers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1614" speakername="Mary Butler" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#B00300"><p>I thank the Senator for his positive approach.  The Castlerea mental health hub represents a new approach to developing options in mental health services delivery, including the psychiatry of later life.  It is my intention, and that of the HSE, that the Castlerea hub will help to inform this objective nationally.  I will take up the Senator's offer to visit his county to see the centre.  As I said, this is a new approach to developing options in mental health services and it is so important.  One of the things I was most pleased to secure funding for in the budget for next year is in the context of the integrated care programme for older persons.  Everyone will be aware of what the programme does, but it does not deal with the psychiatry of later life.  I secured funding for three pilot teams so that we will not be duplicating services in this area.  If an older person presents with frailty, a broken hip or related issues, any issues concerning the psychiatry of later life can be addressed then as well.  I am pleased about that.</p> <p>Mention was made of the &euro;18 million.  When I came into my post last year, there was a deficit of &euro;53 million in the area of mental health services in the Department of Health.  I have managed to clear that and we are going into next year with no deficit.  Working with the Department and the HSE, we went back as far as 2012 and we were able to see where some savings were made.  One relevant aspect from my previous life is that I was good at figures.  What we have been able to do is to secure the budget for the future.  None of the &euro;1.149 billion funding allocation for mental health services is owed or will have to be spent on something that happened previously.  I am very pleased about that aspect because it is so important in light of Covid-19 and all the other challenges that people face that we have a good and robust mental health system.  I look forward to visiting Roscommon and my office will talk to the Senator about it.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.16" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#B00400">Vaccination Programme</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1629" speakername="Garret Ahearn" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#B00500"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the Chamber.  She is always welcome and I thank her and the Cathaoirleach for facilitating this debate.  I am raising this issue because the Minister of State will remember that a couple of weeks ago there was a lot of controversy about the continuation of the Covid digital certificate and the recommendations being brought in by the Government.  The issue that seemed to upset some people was the continuation of the Covid digital certificate.</p> <p>My question is how successful that digital certificate has been in recent weeks.  I ask that because I was supportive of this initiative and I have seen the advantage of it in recent months.  I refer to how people have embraced it, how it has encouraged people to get vaccinated and, most importantly, and this is the part people frequently forget, how the Covid digital certificate is there to support businesses.  It is not impeding businesses in any way.  It is a little bit of an inconvenience for people to have to check it when people come in, but the whole point of the digital certificate is to allow businesses to remain open.</p> <p>Some weeks ago, about 370,000 people over the age of 12 were not fully vaccinated.  My question is where are we now in respect of those 370,000 people, and I am asking because the impression I get is that there seems to have been an increase in the uptake of the vaccines.  If Clonmel is anything to go by, and we are very lucky to have a vaccination centre there, as well as one in Nenagh in Tipperary, there has been an increase in the number of people receiving vaccinations.  I have seen that myself.  There was a sense before 22 October that if people who had not been vaccinated - for whatever reason, some people have genuine reasons and some people just do not want it or do not want to do what the Government is asking them to do, and it is always going be the case that we will have a percentage of people like that - just got to 22 October, they would then have got over the end line and that would have been it.</p> <p>I get the sense now, though, that people realise the Covid digital certificate is not going to be gone any time soon.  One of the major and positive decisions we made in respect of the Covid digital certificate is that there is no end date for it.  There is talk that there might be such a date in future, but I strongly encourage the Department not to have an end date for when the Covid digital certificate will be phased out, because a date, such as 1 January 2022, would give people the ability to decide to wait until that end date arrives and try to get past it that way.  If we have learned anything from our experience over the past 18 months, it is that we cannot predict anything and therefore we should not have an end date because it just causes us more problems.</p> <p>One suggestion I have concerns what is happening in other countries, such as Spain, where it has been successful.  I refer to the fact there seems to be a lower uptake of vaccinations among non-English speaking residents in Ireland.  If we could start a campaign to encourage those people to get vaccinated, that would be very helpful.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Garret Ahearn:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=GarretAhearn&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We know many people are either sceptical of this or come from countries where there is a scepticism about vaccines even in their governments over years.  We could set up a campaign within the Department of Health to encourage such people to get vaccinated.</p><p>I welcome the discussions between the Taoiseach and representatives of the hospitality sector, such as the Restaurants Association of Ireland, the Vintners' Federation of Ireland and all the other groups that participated in yesterday's process.  Now is the time to encourage all businesses to use digital Covid certificates.  It is the mechanism to keep the industry open over Christmas but we need everybody on board.  I am sure the Minister of State knows businesses that have not been checking the certificates and I have gone to bars and restaurants where it does not happen.  It is different everywhere.  Some places are very positive and engaging while others are not.  Even the businesses that are quite good may not look for photo identification, and I might refer to that in my concluding remarks.  Now is the time for businesses in the hospitality sector to ensure as many bars and restaurants as possible can continue checking the digital Covid certificate over the next two months.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1614" speakername="Mary Butler" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#C00200"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this matter, which is important.  He has set out the position clearly.  On 19 October, the Government approved the reopening of the remaining aspects of the hospitality, entertainment and night-time economy.  The hospitality sector has been permitted to reopen only with a full range of protective measures in place and the wide and robust implementation of the EU digital Covid certificate.  Thinking back to the debate on the digital Covid certificate in the D&aacute;il - I read the transcript a couple of weeks ago - I recall it being very emotive.  Only the Government parties and one Independent supported it at the time.  The digital Covid certificate being implemented to allow hospitality to fully reopen was likened to a pig in a poke and an Irish solution to Irish problem.  It was labelled discriminatory.  I can now see how all parties have engaged with the digital Covid certificate as a solution.</p> <p>I was in a premises on Sunday morning when I did a bit of shopping.  I do not mind mentioning I was in a Starbucks and I was so impressed when I entered the premises.  A person is first asked for a digital Covid certificate when sitting down and identification to complement it.  After sitting, a person can scan a code at the table to indicate the time and date when he or she is there.  Some places are implementing the process well.  Unfortunately, as we have heard, 37% of establishments are not up to speed and it is important that they participate fully in the process.</p> <p>More than 7.6 million doses of the Covid-19 vaccine have now been administered since the programme began last December.  This figure encompasses both primary vaccination and the administration of booster doses.  Vaccination of those not yet inoculated remains an immediate focus of the programme.  In recognition of this priority, the HSE has established an uptake improvement group, which has deployed initiatives that include pop-up clinics and targeted media campaigns.</p> <p>In addition to the full reopening of the hospitality sector on 19 October, the Minister for Health announced an update to Ireland's Covid-19 vaccination programme in extending the booster vaccination to those aged between 60 and 79.  The change was made on foot of a recommendation from the national immunisation advisory committee that a booster dose of the Pfizer BioNTech vaccine should be offered to all those aged 60 to 79 who have completed their primary vaccination course.  The recommendation has subsequently been updated to include provision of a half dose of Moderna's Spikevax vaccine to be offered to those aged 60 to 79.  Persons aged over 60 will be offered an mRNA vaccine regardless of the type of vaccine used for their primary vaccination course.  The booster dose should be given after an interval of six months, or at least five months, following the previous dose of any authorised Covid-19 vaccine.</p> <p>I am pleased to report to the House that significant progress has been made in the weeks since the announcement.  An estimated 336,000 persons aged over 70 are in scope for booster vaccination and nearly 33,000 doses have been administered to date.  GPs are responsible for the administration of booster doses to this cohort and I express my sincere thanks for their ongoing contribution to the success of the vaccination programme.</p> <p>The HSE anticipates that the booster vaccination of those aged over 70 and residing in the community will be completed by the end of November.  Those aged 60 to 69 are being vaccinated through community vaccination centres and 13,000 doses have been administered to date.  It is expected that the roll-out of booster doses for those aged between 60 and 69 will be substantially completed by the end of December.  The roll-out of booster doses to those aged 60 to 79 is occurring in parallel with the vaccination of those aged 80 and living in the community and to healthcare workers, with the process for those in long-term care facilities having been substantially completed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1629" speakername="Garret Ahearn" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#C00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  The question is fairly simple and the Department might be able to respond to it.  The key figure I am seeking is how many first doses have been administered since 19 October, as this would give an indication of how many people have been vaccinated since the announcement.  How many people took a first dose in the two weeks prior to 19 October, as it would indicate the percentage increase of people who have taken a first dose?  This could strengthen the Government's case for how it takes decisions to protect people's lives and people could see the long-term strategy.</p> <p>The Minister of State is correct in her comments on the opposition to this.  She knows where I am from and I must listen to utter rubbish quite a lot in Tipperary from people who go whichever way the wind blows.  Some of the comments relate to the decisions we make as a Government to protect people's lives and they are just outrageous.  The majority of people do not listen to that rubbish.</p> <p>I have another suggestion that the Department might consider.  We all know places where the process of asking for a digital Covid certificate is done well but identification may not be requested.  These certificates may remain for a long time.  Has the Department considered the option of photo identification being part of the digital Covid certificate?  The majority of pubs and restaurants are seeking these certificates.  We encourage those that are not doing so to do it.  The photo identification element is important.  It would make no difference to the restaurant or bar that must check a certificate in any case but it would discourage people from using fake Covid certificates or certificates from somebody else.  More powers should be given to the Garda to fine people rather than bars or restaurants, as this is about discouraging people from using other people's Covid certificates.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1614" speakername="Mary Butler" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#C00400"><p>I do not disagree with anything the Senator said.  Every decision taken by this and the previous Government was to protect people's health and to ensure they could be kept as safe as possible.  I know the Government had to make tough decisions.  The difference is we have vaccination and booster programmes now, along with the digital Covid certificates.</p> <p>I will try to get data on first doses given since 19 October and I am sure it will be easy enough to get.  I take on board the Senator's point relating to photo identification being part of the certificate and I will pass it on.  It is only by coming into the D&aacute;il and Seanad that we hear suggestions and that is a good one.</p> <p>We started the booster roll-out four weeks ago for those aged over 80 and in long-term residential care facilities.  Already in the past two weeks we have seen a fall in the number of people in nursing homes contracting Covid-19 because of the booster shot.  It is certainly working.  Of all breakouts in nursing homes in the past four months, 83% have comprised five people or fewer.  That is heartening as previously they could have involved up to 40 staff and members of the community.  There is no doubt the data indicate the booster shot is working.  I am glad the decision was made that our front-line workers will also receive it now.  As far as I am concerned, that cannot happen fast enough.  I thank the Senator for his constructive approach.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.22" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#C00500">Hospital Investigations</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1666" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#C00600"><p>I want the Minister for the Health to make a statement on the disposal of baby organs in Cork University Hospital.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Tim Lombard:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2466"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2466&amp;amp;pid=TimLombard&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This is probably one of the most troubling cases I have come across in my workload in recent weeks.</p><p>On 28 September, an "RT&Eacute; Investigates" programme showed an unfortunate incident in the maternity hospital in Cork, where 18 families were told the news that their children's organs had been disposed of.  Subsequent to that, one of those families contacted my office and they were very irate about how this was dealt with.  I have had two meetings with them about this issue.  Seventeen families were informed of the news; the 18th family found out on the eve of the programme's broadcast.  On 28 September, one family got a phone call to inform them that an "RT&Eacute; Investigates" programme would be aired that night with evidence relating to this issue outlined.  They were told their poor baby's organs were cremated, but they were actually incinerated.  They were not aware of all the evidence until they watched the "RT&Eacute; Investigates" programme.  It was a shocking programme in many ways.  It involved 18 families and a breach of faith in respect of the organs of their loved ones who died.  The 18th family had hoped and agreed that the organs of their child would be buried in the angels' plot in CUH, which was appropriate.  They had the child baptised according to their religious beliefs.  They wanted the child to be part of their family.  That was all shattered when they got the news, literally on "RT&Eacute; Investigates", that the organs of their deceased child had been incinerated in Belgium alongside waste.  There has been a breach of faith here that will take an awful lot of work to rebuild.  We need an urgent review of how this happened and, more importantly, an urgent review of this case in particular.  One family was not informed.  One family found out only on the eve of the programme's broadcast.  One family had to sit down, watch the programme and learn that way where their child's organs ended up.  That was inappropriate.</p><p>There needs to be a better way to do business.  I have been involved in public life since 2003.  Never have I seen a case such as this.  We have no real line of communication put in place that would have ensured that these families were appropriately informed of the evidence of what had happened and how the breach of trust had happened.</p><p>We have a body of work to do.  I will forward the Minister of State the information on this family after this session.  The family needs to be contacted not by liaison people from CUH but by the senior staff of CUH and the HSE to explain who was involved and how it transpired that they were not made aware of this incident until hours before information on it was aired on RT&Eacute;.  There also needs to be a major change in the law.  My understanding is that there is only a guideline for how these loved ones' organs are dealt with in a morgue.  That is not appropriate.  We now need legislation brought before the Houses of the Oireachtas to ensure that people are empowered such that when it comes to these issues they have the law on their side, they have the right to make sure justice will be done and their loved ones' organs will be taken care of appropriately.</p><p>This is a frightening case.  It is beyond belief.  It is a betrayal of human life and a betrayal of so many families.  We need to come clean here.  We need to deal with this family.  We also need to deal with the law and we all need to put in place an assurance that never, ever again will we have a scenario in which organs are shipped to Belgium as waste and incinerated without the approval of the family.  It is a sin and a crime, and I hope the Department will take heed and do something about these issues.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1614" speakername="Mary Butler" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#D00200"><p>The Senator has used the words "shocking", "heartbreaking" and "a breach of faith".  There is not one word he has said that I disagree with.  I feel so much for the 18 families.  I did not realise that one family found out on the eve of the "RT&Eacute; Investigates" programme and that the other 17 families were informed before then.  There are no excuses for that, and nothing I can say here will give comfort to the 18 families, not least the one family that was not included.  It is absolutely heartbreaking.  I was very upset when I heard about these much-wanted, loved babies' organs.</p> <p>My colleagues and I are aware of the hurt this incident has caused to the families affected by the incident in Cork University Hospital.  These families have been through the tragedy of having lost a beloved child, and it is absolutely unacceptable to me and to the Minister, Deputy Stephen Donnelly, that the organs of their children were disposed of in such a manner.  There are no words that will ever give these families comfort.  While it is not appropriate to comment on individual cases, I wish to accept and acknowledge the bravery of the couple who spoke about their experience and heartbreak on the "RT&Eacute; Investigates" programme on 28 September and the other families who shared their experiences on 19 October.  These are parents who have suffered the loss of a child, and this extremely distressing situation should not have happened as it has only added to their distress and grief.  Not only did they lose their loved, wanted babies, but to learn in such a way how their babies were disposed of - there are no words to describe it.</p> <p>The Department of Health is advised that the HSE, the South/South West Hospital Group, CUH and Cork University Maternity Hospital have apologised to the bereaved families and very much regret the incident.  The Minister for Health and the HSE are committed to ensuring there is learning across the health services to prevent such events happening again.  This can never happen again.  The Senator spoke about changing the law.  The HSE has advised that a systems analysis review is being undertaken by the South/South West Hospital Group.  The purpose of that review is to find answers as to what happened, why and what can be done to reduce the risk of it happening again.  However, reducing the risk is enough.  It cannot happen again.  I would have zero tolerance for it.  We cannot only reduce the risk of this happening again; it cannot happen again.</p> <p>The HSE advises that the review team met last week to review queries raised by families and to plan meetings with families who wish to engage with the review.  Family meetings will be offered on 22 November and 24 November.  The timeline for completion of the review will depend on whether there is a requirement to reinterview any staff regarding any new issues raised by families.  The review team will further consider the issues after those meetings.  The South/South West Hospital Group advises that it will act on any recommendations emerging from the review.  Open disclosure with the families involved is an ongoing process and continues for a considerable time in the aftermath of an incident.  This includes engagement in the review process and in sharing the review with the families.</p> <p>As for legislation, which the Senator raised, the human tissue (transplantation, post-mortem, anatomical examination, and public display) Bill will implement the key recommendation of the Madden report that no hospital post-mortem examination should be carried out and no tissue retained for any purpose whatsoever without the informed consent of the family or next of kin.  That would have prevented this incident if it had been in place.  The Bill will ensure that the principles of protection of the bodily integrity of the individual before and after death, respect for the autonomy of the individual, and the rights of the bereaved are enshrined in legislation.</p> <p>I stand here as Minister of State with responsibility for older people and mental health in the Department of Health.  I can only apologise to these families.  I am heartbroken for them.  It is an absolutely awful tragedy, it is shocking and it is an awful breach of trust for these families and their beloved babies.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1666" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#D00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State for her response and her compassion regarding this incident.  Yes, it really was a breach of trust.  The lack of communication, or the breakdown in communication, needs to be looked at directly by the HSE.  The communication lines were not appropriate, they did not work and they failed this family in particular.  The review team needs to look at that when it meets.  The meetings of 22 November and 24 November should be held both physically and online.  Some of the families will want to attend online, and that needs to be accommodated.  I hope the Minister of State will make sure that at some stage, sooner rather than later, senior members of the maternity services in Cork will meet these families.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Tim Lombard:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2466"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2466&amp;amp;pid=TimLombard&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->They are meeting a liaison officer at the moment.  She is doing her best, but that is not appropriate.  Senior consultants and senior staff in CUH have never spoken to these families.  That is not the game.  Responsibility needs to be taken at the very top.  We must prioritise this legislation.  It cannot be put on the long finger.  Guidelines have previously been breached.  This is not the first time it has happened; we have seen breaches in guidelines before.  This legislation needs to be prioritised by our parties in government during the next session of sittings in the D&aacute;il and the Seanad.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1614" speakername="Mary Butler" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#E00200"><p>I do not disagree with anything the Senator has said about the breakdown in communication.  I will ensure that both options are available if some families want to meet in person and others want to meet online.  How they engage will depend on how those families want to address the matter.</p> <p>The Senator is right about the legislation.  It is hugely important that we do not lose any more time on it.</p> <p>The South/Southwest Hospital Group has confirmed that the capacity issue around cemetery places has now been addressed with a new plot in St. Mary's Cemetery in Curraghkippane, just outside Cork city.  I will certainly bring back to Government the Senator's comments.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.29" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#E00300">Agriculture Industry</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1671" speakername="Erin McGreehan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#E00400"><p>The Minister of State is welcome.  I have a question for him and his Department.  I am seeking an update on the Department's plan for the viability of the sheep sector, along with an update on the wool feasibility study.  As the Minister of State knows, sheep farming is a sustainable sector.  I hope the Department will pay more attention to it and see it is a strong, sustainable sector.  It has demonstrated time and again that it plays an integral role in protecting and enhancing the diverse habitats that are commonly found on marginalised farmland and lowland farms.  With the correct supports, this livestock can coexist with fragile conservation sites, areas of scientific research and breeding sites for endangered wildlife.</p> <p>I welcome many of the proposals in the Common Agricultural Policy, CAP, but many in the sheep sector are disappointed with the new sheep scheme.  The next CAP will only deliver &euro;2 for the sheep welfare scheme.  I have generations of sheep farmers behind me.  I am a sheep farmer's daughter so I know the importance of the sheep sector and the importance of this funding to farming families.  I come from north Louth and I remember the devastation in the farming and sheep sectors that we love when we lost all our stock to foot-and-mouth disease many years ago.</p> <p>Like every market, the sheep sector experiences fluctuations.  We saw some very high prices this year, although they have now dipped.  The cost of production has gone up dramatically.  Sheep farming is labour intensive and sheep require a lot of attention.  The age cohort of farmers is increasing and due to the work involved, older farmers are finding it difficult.  Herding sheep, dipping, clipping, feet maintenance and dagging to prevent maggots are all required.  Much work needs to be done to look after sheep.  The Government and the Department must support the sheep sector to make it more attractive to young farmers.</p> <p>Despite the intensity of the work required, the sheep sector delivers a low income for those involved in it.  From talking to sheep farmers, many of whom are elderly, I know that this new sheep improvement scheme is important.  I wish to highlight a matriculation when it comes to payments on livestock.  One livestock unit equates to one cow or 6.6 ewes.  Cattle farmers will receive &euro;150 for their first ten cows and &euro;120 for each cow thereafter.  Sheep farmers are paid &euro;79.20 per livestock unit.  That is a sizeable discrepancy.  Sheep farmers have a significant role to play in the agricultural sector and industry.</p> <p>There is an issue around the lack of movement from the Department on creating markets for our wool.  A sheep must be clipped every year.  It costs &euro;3 to clip a sheep and a farmer gets a return of 25 cent.  Many farmers are putting their wool into storage and holding it.  There is so much that the Government can do.  I am asking for a research fund and I encourage the Government to put that out to tender.  It should facilitate companies.  There is much that companies and the Government can do to facilitate an increase in the size of the market for traditional wool for clothing and new products for insulation.  Far better and brighter people than me can find creative ways to use our wool and to give farmers a proper payment for it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1586" speakername="Martin Heydon" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#E00500"><p>I thank the Senator for raising the important issue of the viability of the sheep sector and its importance to our overall agricultural and rural economies, and our food production and exports.</p> <p>I am pleased to see that the strong performance of the sheep sector in 2020 has continued into 2021 in terms of overall prices.  It is good to see the market providing returns which goes some way to rewarding farmers for their hard work, commitment and dedication to producing a world-class product, as the Senator has outlined.  Global production patterns and increased demand are expected to support this continued strong performance.  The current average price is &euro;6.54 per kg, which is 33% above the same period last year.  This is impressive, given that the year-to-date figure for sheep slaughtering is only slightly behind that for the same period last year.</p> <p>Bord Bia analysis suggests that retail demand for sheep meat increased over the last year, as consumers invested more time in preparing home-cooked meals.  In addition, data from the Central Statistics Office shows that 2020 was a strong year for Ireland's overseas sheep meat trade, with 64,000 tonnes exported to 38 international markets at a value of nearly &euro;356 million.  This represents an increase of 12% in value terms on 2019.  In 2020, 73% of sheep meat products in value terms were exported to the EU, 12% to the UK and 15% to other third-country markets.  France remains the single most important export destination, accounting for a third of Irish sheep meat exports in 2020.  The future prospects for Irish sheep meat exports remain positive.</p> <p>As Minister of State with responsibility in the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine for new market development, I and my officials continue to work on seeking new outlets for sheep meat, as well as enhancing existing access to as many markets as possible.  The sheep meat protocol with China was signed recently.  There are a number of steps still to be taken in that regard, but it is another sign of progress in the work the Department is carrying out.  We are well positioned to benefit from the opportunities presented by an expanding global demand for high-quality Irish lamb.</p> <p>Notwithstanding the strong market prices, I am acutely aware of the need to provide support to sheep farmers who are the cornerstone of the sector.  Provision for over &euro;1.8 billion of funding was made in budget 2022 for the overall agriculture sector.  This is in addition to almost &euro;1.2 billion in EU-funded direct payments received annually to support farm incomes and reward good agricultural and environmental practices.  This year's budget provision included funding to allow continuation of the sheep welfare scheme in the transition period until the new CAP.  The scheme is an important support for sheep farmers, as it assists them to undertake important management practices such as scanning or mineral supplementation.</p> <p>The Minister, Deputy McConalogue, has, subject to approval from the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform, updated the reference year for the scheme to 2017 from 2014-2015, as the Senator will know.  That will allow for a greater number of ewes to be made eligible for the scheme.</p> <p>When considering the overall scheme and the new CAP, we cannot look at each scheme in isolation.  We must also look at all of the other measures in place.  The new CAP will include the agri-environmental scheme, which will build on the green, low-carbon,agri-environment scheme, GLAS, but pay more.  Those supports are important.</p> <p>I can expand on the general points about the sheep welfare scheme in my supplementary reply but I wish to move to the Senator's point about wool, the production of which is an important component of the agricultural industry.  Unfortunately, as the Senator outlined, I am aware that the wool industry has been under pressure for some time.  I have met with merchants, farmers' representative organisations and directly with sheep farmers.  Wool is a sustainable, organic, renewable and natural material that can be used in a wide range of products, such as textiles, fertilizers, insulation and packaging. It fits closely with the goals of the climate action plan to develop a circular and bio-economy.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Martin Heydon:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2286"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2286&amp;amp;pid=MartinHeydon&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->One of the actions in the programme for Government is to undertake a review of the potential demand in domestic and international markets for wool-based products such as insulation and fertilizers.  We allocated &euro;100,000 in the budget for this review.  A public consultation process was initiated to determine the terms of reference.  I can outline the terms of reference in my supplementary reply.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1671" speakername="Erin McGreehan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#F00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his response.  The Government has been doing a lot of work on finding markets for sheepmeat.  With regard to the sheep improvement scheme and the &euro;2 increase, agricultural schemes are open to every farmer but the sheep improvement scheme is specifically for sheep farmers.  I am glad to hear that there will be some movement on the wool feasibility study.  Instead of studies, pilots and reviews I would rather see some action very soon.  Because it is so far back, the reference year often penalises and restricts younger farmers and ambitious farmers trying to get into the sector.  On behalf of young farmers I ask that the reference year be looked at.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1586" speakername="Martin Heydon" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#F00300"><p>The Senator is right.  The role of the Government is to support sheep farmers in the very important work they do.  With every reference year there are hard cases and challenges.  It is definitely to the benefit of farmers that we move the reference year from 2014-15 to 2017 because it will bring in more ewes.</p> <p>The terms of reference for the wool feasibility study involve the identification of market opportunities domestically and internationally for wool-based products, carrying out economic feasibility and cost-benefit analysis on proposed market opportunities, determining mechanisms that can be used to support industry initiatives and the identification of potential research projects available to support the identified market opportunities.  This is important work and it will be followed through.</p> <p>We are building on the dedicated work of the country's sheep farmers through a number of avenues, which I have already outlined.  We continue to support farmers through the new CAP transition period.  There will be further support in the new CAP to build on these schemes.  While market prices are strong at present we will continue efforts to open up new markets for sheepmeat as well as to enhance the value of existing markets.  We are seeking to restore the value of wool as a byproduct.  Our work is ongoing and we recognise the very important role played by sheep farmers.  We will continue to support them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.35" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 11.23 a.m. and resumed at 11.38 a.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.36" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#G00050">An tOrd Gnó - Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#G00100"><p>I want to pay tribute to Austin Currie, former Deputy and Minister of State, who sadly passed away yesterday.  He was born in Dungannon in 1921 and educated in Queen's University Belfast.  He was a leading light of the civil rights movement.  He was one of the founders of the Social and Democratic Labour Party, SDLP, alongside the late John Hume.  He was a dedicated and committed politician who made an important contribution to the lives of many throughout the island, North and South.  He served as a Minister of State at the Departments of Education, Justice and Health during the 1990s.  I send my sincere sympathies, along with those of all Senators, to his wife, Annita, and his children, especially our colleague, Senator Emer Currie.  Ar dheis D&eacute; go raibh a anam d&iacute;lis.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" speakername="Lisa Chambers" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#G00200"><p>I join the Cathaoirleach in his words of sympathy and condolence to the Currie family, our colleague, Emer, all of his community and his colleagues and friends in the SDLP, Fine Gael and the Parliaments on this island.  He led an extremely interesting life and made a significant contribution to public life.  He has left a fantastic legacy.  May he rest in peace.</p> <p>The Order of Business today is No. 1, Criminal Justice (Amendment) Bill 2020 - Committee Stage, to be taken at 1 p.m. and to adjourn at 2.15 p.m., if not previously concluded; No. 2, Official Languages (Amendment) Bill 2019 - Second Stage, to be taken at 2.30 p.m. or 15 minutes after the adjournment of No. 1, whichever is the later, and to conclude after 105 minutes, if not previously concluded, with the time allocated to the opening remarks of the Minister not to exceed ten minutes, group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes and all other Senators not to exceed five minutes and the Minister to be given no less than ten minutes to reply to the debate; No. 3, Planning and Development (Amendment) Large-scale Residential Development) Bill 2021 - Order for Second Stage and Second Stage to be taken at 4.30 p.m. or 15 minutes after the conclusion of No. 2, whichever is the later, and to conclude after 135 minutes, if not previously concluded, with the time allocated to the opening remarks of the Minister not to exceed ten minutes, group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes and all other Senators not to exceed five minutes and Minister to be given no less than ten minutes to reply to the debate; and No. 4, Private Members' business, Safe Access to Termination of Pregnancy Services Bill 2021 - Second Stage, to be taken at 7.15 p.m. or 15 minutes after the conclusion of No. 3, whichever is the later, with the time allocated to the debate not to exceed two hours.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1651" speakername="Paul Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#H00100"><p>On my behalf and that of the Fianna F&aacute;il group, I wish to be associated with the Cathaoirleach and the Deputy Leader in sending our condolences to our colleague, Senator Currie, on the sad passing of her father, Austin.  As the Cathaoirleach rightly said, his decision to squat a house in Caledon, County Tyrone in 1968 was widely seen and historically recorded as the beginning of the civil rights movement.  He was one of the co-founders of the SDLP and, in political terms, successfully traversed the Border by later becoming a Deputy representing Dublin West.  His legacy is great and I extend our sympathies and condolences to Emer and her mother, Annita, as well as her four siblings, the extended Currie family and the large circle of friends Austin accumulated during his distinguished career.</p> <p>I wish to raise an issue that has been raised on several occasions in the House.  I refer to the backlog of passport applications.  It is the passport issue again.  I welcome the moves that have been made by the Minister to provide Members with an Oireachtas contact line.  Although it has had some teething problems and may not be the silver bullet we were all hoping for, it certainly has helped in many situations.  All Members know why the backlog exists.  Covid has been blamed, with people having to work from home and so on.  However, Covid or the other aforementioned reason cannot be blamed for the lack of a little bit of common sense and a personal touch.</p> <p>On two occasions recently, I thought I had been successful in getting a passport for people at closer to the 12th than the 11th hour.  In both cases, I was trying to get the passport on a Friday.  One of them was on the Friday of a bank holiday weekend.  When we got confirmation that the passport had been printed, the confirmation also stated the passport had been posted.  The passports were needed for flights that were on a Sunday and a bank holiday Monday, respectively, but the facility to collect them or even to organise a courier to collect them was not made available.  There was no common sense shown.  There has to be a personal touch and some common sense used.  I know the staff are under pressure trying to get through the backlog but it is very simple to recognise that a passport posted at 5 p.m. on a Friday evening to a person who desperately needs it for a flight on the Sunday of a bank holiday weekend will not reach the person in time and may as well not have been printed.  The staff would have been as well served to put the effort into processing a passport for a person flying on the Tuesday.</p> <p>It has been brought to my attention that in cases where further information is required, there is some fault in the application or the photograph is not up to standard, this is not being highlighted to the customers or clients until the due date for printing of the passport.  These issues can be highlighted sooner to give people the opportunity to submit the extra information or an updated photograph or whatever the case may be in ample time.  These are simple things.  I do not wish to sound flippant but all it needs is a little common sense and a personal human touch.  I ask the Deputy Leader to highlight these issues to the Minister such that he can bring them to the attention of supervisors or others in the Passport Office.  I am not being critical of the staff.  I know there is a backlog and they are working hard but it is nonsensical to post a passport on a Friday evening when it is evident and obvious it will not arrive in time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1665" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#H00200"><p>I too wish to be associated, on my behalf and that of the Fine Gael group, with the remarks on the sad passing of Austin Currie.  I offer condolences to his wife, Annita, who herself suffered greatly at the hands of loyalist paramilitaries, and to our colleague, Senator Emer Currie.  Austin was a man of peace and decency who, with John Hume, Gerry Fitt, Seamus Mallon and others, kick-started the civil rights movement in Derry and across the North.  Ar dheis D&eacute; go raibh a anam d&iacute;lis.</p> <p>There was an exciting and at times difficult public meeting in Athenry mart on Monday in respect of Common Agricultural Policy, CAP, proposals.  Politicians representing east and west Galway were in the ring of the mart.  There was a good crowd.  The meeting was organised by the Irish Farmers Association and there was a significant turnout of very productive and active farmers from the east Galway area, as well as some from west Galway.  I understand from the Leader that the Minister, Deputy McConalogue, will be appearing before the House as part of the climate change debates.  The Minister of State, Senator Hackett, is due to appear in the Chamber on Thursday to discuss forestry.  I am sure the Minister, Deputy Ryan, will come to the House in the coming weeks to discuss transport.</p> <p>The majority of farmers understand that climate change is real and they accept that agriculture has to play its part.  Indeed, it has been doing so for several years.  However, it is a difficult area and there is some confusion regarding what is being announced.  Farmers are experiencing several things that are happening at the same time.  Obviously, there is the new CAP, which is enough to deal with on its own.  There are also the climate change issues on top of that and, of course, the price of commodities such as fertiliser is very high due to the current input price of gas.  All of those issues are coming at the same time for farmers, so it is a difficult period for them.  Those at the meeting on Monday certainly expressed their concern about it.</p> <p>It is acknowledged that Irish farming and food production is among the most sustainable, if not the most sustainable, in the world in terms of a grass-based system and long grazing periods compared with other countries.  We have a responsibility internationally to be part of the movement, to acknowledge the reality of climate change and to be part of the COP26 proposals to limit the impact across the system, and farmers understand that.  I look forward to the debate with the Minister, Deputy McConalogue, in the coming months.  There are several points and questions raised by farmers that I will put to the Minister in that debate.  I am sure he will be able to provide answers in respect of the minute details of the proposals outlined in the climate action plan.  I look forward to a debate on that issue as soon as possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#H00300"><p>I thank the Deputy Leader for outlining the proposed Order of Business.  My apologies for being delayed coming to the House.  I know the Cathaoirleach, too, ran up the stairs.  I do not think any Senator has delayed the start of the Seanad by ten minutes.  I have just come from an amazing event.  I thank the Cathaoirleach, the Ceann Comhairle and the Leader of the Seanad for presiding over the joyous and exciting unveiling of a portrait of Senator David Norris, our esteemed colleague.  The Senator was very gracious and there were great speeches, as well as a significant press and photographer presence.  The unveiling will be followed by further celebrations later in the day.</p> <p>I wish to acknowledge David and his unique style, individualism, eloquence and energy but, more important, in this House I want to acknowledge the significance of David's remarkable crusade in respect of the decriminalisation of homosexuality, his crusade for marriage equality and his trips to the High Court, the Supreme Court and, eventually, the European Court of Human Rights.  What an achievement by a man who is a Member of this House.  It proves the importance of Independent politics, but also his ability to collaborate.  While he may have had difficulties with some people, he always remained in good personal friendships with them and that is the mark of the man.  In summary, he is a lover of life, humanities and antiquities, and an amazing mentor to young people coming into political life.  I hope we will have many more days of David being a Member of this House.</p> <p>I join colleagues in offering condolences to Senator Currie of Fine Gael and her family.  These are sad times for them.  Her father was a remarkable man who made a remarkable contribution to the political life of this island, and that needs to be acknowledged.</p> <p>I raise the issue of local government funding.  I know Senator Kyne has been very much to the fore in calling for this action on this issue in the context of Galway.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Victor Boyhan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2463"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2463&amp;amp;pid=VictorBoyhan&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Five municipal districts in Galway - Loughrea, Tuam, Ballinasloe, Athenry and Connemara - have rejected the municipal district budgets to take a stand about the lack of adequate funding.  We need a debate in this House on local government funding.  We need a debate on how the local property tax, LPT, is being administered.  We need a debate about the major reduction in commercial rates.  We certainly need to debate when we hear that local authorities are seeking commercial rates from private individuals who have small offices in their homes.  Particularly post Covid, the scenario has changed.  I join others in calling for an extensive debate on local government financing, especially focused on the problems in Galway County Council.  The people in the Galway County Council area, the staff of the council and the councillors deserve our support.  I would welcome an early debate in the House on that issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#J00200"><p>I apologise to the House for starting the Order of Business ten minutes late, but as the Leader of the Opposition has outlined, it was in the course of unveiling a portrait of the great Senator Norris.  His contribution to this House in the longest unbroken record of service was marked by the unveiling of a portrait of him.  As Senator Boyhan outlined, he championed minority causes when nobody else would speak on them.  Often forgotten as we go through this pandemic is the previous pandemic of the AIDS virus, which was a silent killer in Ireland.  Nobody in the establishment or society in general wanted to talk about it, but Senator Norris raised it here time and again until he ensured there was a change in public policy.  That shows the power of him as an Independent and the power of the Seanad in its role of raising issues that were uncomfortable for society.  He forced change by his presence in this House.  It was great to be there this morning to honour his great service to the country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1667" speakername="Vincent P Martin" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#J00300"><p>On behalf of the Green Party, An Comhaontas Glas, we closely associate ourselves with the remarks of the Cathaoirleach and previous speakers in conveying our deepest sympathy to Senator Currie and her family on the sad passing of Austin Currie.  Austin was a fearless voice and an advocate of equality.  Articulating those views at that time meant putting one's life in peril.  It is only a short few decades ago, but it is worth noting that he was not silenced nor were others in the SDLP, despite coming under attack from extremes in loyalism and republicanism.</p> <p>There are different shades of green.  Austin Currie may not have been the deepest shade of green, but perhaps the deepest shade of green is a galloping green that strives to achieve and realise a legitimate dream, but in the efforts of striving so harshly, at times it can prove counterproductive.  Austin Currie did not believe in rushing.  He came from a place whose only crime, which caused the SDLP trouble at the time, was a consent principle and to espouse the dream of a united Ireland exclusively by peaceful means.</p> <p>It is also worth noting that another member of the SDLP, Gerry Fitt, was hounded out of his constituency in west Belfast.  They shouted at him, "Fitt the Brit".  What did he ever do?  I accept he took a peerage and many people here might not like to take a peerage.  While it is not something I would do, perhaps in taking the peerage he reached out to the other community.  Margaret Ritchie also took a peerage and people from the nationalist community might find it hard to accept that.  In a sense, from a different prism, that may be a form of reconciliation.</p> <p>Austin Currie was also involved in what many would regard as the most bruising presidential election campaign.  The father of the House might disagree.  He would like the bragging rights of having been involved in a far more bruising presidential election campaign.  I close my remarks by mentioning the father of this House.  I commend the Independent grouping's beautiful and appropriate initiative to acknowledge the ongoing and selfless work of a public representative who has made his mark nationally and internationally.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#J00400"><p>On behalf of the Sinn F&eacute;in group, I offer our condolences to our colleague, Senator Currie, and her family on the passing of Austin Currie.  May he rest in peace.</p> <p>The latest Daft rental report confirms what anybody who is trying to rent in this country already knows, which is that rents are continuing to rise.  Munster, Connacht and Ulster are facing hikes of between 15% and 18% and, incredibly, the average monthly rent in Ireland is now &euro;1,516.  There is no doubt the rental crisis is continuing and the Minister continues to be four steps behind with every measure he takes.  For years we have said rent pressure zones were not working and yet the Minister thinks simply tweaking around the edges will fix it.  Seventeen counties have double-digit rental increases and some counties have had increases of as much as 20%.  What does the Minister propose to deal with it?  He proposes to allow landlords to hike rents by a further 2%.</p> <p>Sinn F&eacute;in has detailed proposals to support tenants, including a ban on rental increases, money back in renters' pockets through a refundable tax credit, and the prioritisation of genuinely affordable homes, including affordable purchase and cost rental.  People waking up today will not be surprised with the Daft report because anybody who is trying to rent in this country knows how broken the system is.  Tragically, they have a Government which gives them no hope of any change in the short term.</p> <p>The recent budget offered nothing for renters and the policies coming from the office of the Minister, Deputy O'Brien, continue to be developer, investor and landlord driven.  The Minister said he would ban co-living but left a long enough lead-in time to allow the developers to get their applications in before the change came into effect.  The Minister said he would curb investors' bulk-buying homes, but the Government is now embarking on a roadshow to calm the investors and to assure them to stick with us, as the T&aacute;naiste said.</p> <p>Later today we will debate a Bill to abolish strategic housing developments, SHDs, a developer-led planning process designed to bypass democratic oversight.  We warned it would fail and now, unfortunately, we have been proven right.  However, just like co-living, the proposal in the Bill to be debated today has such a long lead-in time that the SHDs will be with us until 2022.  Throughout next year developers will be able to use planning processes to delay the system of getting houses onto the market.  The housing system in Ireland is broken.  Despite nine years of rent inflation, the Minister is repeating the same mistakes of his predecessor.  Tinkering will not cut it.  Housing is like climate change and transport.  It will only be fixed by State-led capital investment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1672" speakername="Rebecca Moynihan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#J00500"><p>I propose an amendment to the Order of Business, that No. 86, motion 3 be taken before No. 1.  It is moving the writ for the by-election on the University of Dublin panel, further to the election of Deputy Bacik to the D&aacute;il.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#J00600"><p>I second that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1672" speakername="Rebecca Moynihan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#J00700"><p>On behalf of the Labour Party, I reiterate the kind words about Austin Currie.  I pass on our condolences to our colleague Senator Currie.  Austin Currie was one of the pioneers on housing and in the civil rights movement in the North.  The housing situation was blatantly discriminatory against Catholics.  We have lost a giant of Irish politics.  Along with John Hume and Seamus Mallon, he was the last of the big three to pass away.  On behalf of the Labour Party, I want to be associated with the words that have been spoken about him.</p> <p>One of the things about speaking later on the Order of Business is that sometimes Senator Boylan raises the issues that I had planned on raising.  I also want to speak on the Daft report.  That has happened a few times.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Rebecca Moynihan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=RebeccaMoynihan&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The Daft report that was published today is interesting.  It reiterates the points made in the Residential Tenancies Board, RTB, report, and states that rental increases are going up 7% nationwide.  In some counties, particularly in the midlands and on the western seaboard rents are increasing in double digits.  There is a supply issue, but I also believe that the investor-led approach is not working.  Investors cannot, and will not, deliver affordable rents.  Only direct State intervention through the Land Development Agency, LDA, and the Government will do this.  In the context of a market with unprecedented scarcity, I am reiterating the Labour Party's call on the Government to increase renters' rights and put some power back in the hands of renters.  As part of this, the Government must ask that build-to-rent standards be reviewed to include balconies and facilities for more long-term living.  We need a commitment from the Government that the apartments that will be built by the LDA and the Government under cost rental schemes will have long-term standards that are better than build-to-rent, and will include balconies and storage space.</p><p>I have heard some worrying reports that some proposed schemes will be built to build-to-rent standards.  They are not good for long-term living for people who are living in cost rental.  Building poor quality housing does not allow people to live there comfortably in the long term, either as renters or owners.  We need to empower renters to make them feel that their house is their home.  It is clear, from the RTB report that was published two weeks ago and the Daft report that was published today, that there is clear non-compliance with rental inflation caps.  The balance between renters and landlords is the cause of this.  Renters are terrified to go to the RTB or challenge landlords because there is such a scarcity of rental accommodation.</p><p>We need a culture change in how we approach rent in this country and our rental laws need to be rebalanced in favour of tenants.  Labour has long called for a three-year rent freeze to give renters a break while new housing comes on the market.  This is hugely important to try to stymie the crisis in the market, but it also must be done in tandem with the State building of cost rental schemes.  This needs to be increased beyond the 2,000 units per year that have already been proposed if we are going to make a dent in housing and rental affordability.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1632" speakername="Frances Black" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#K00200"><p>On behalf of the Civil Engagement Group, I, too, would like to pass on my deepest condolences to our Seanad colleague, Senator Currie, and her family on the passing of her Dad, Austin Currie.  Ar dheis D&eacute; go raibh a anam d&iacute;lis.  I also want to commend the Independent Group on the wonderful tribute it made today to the father of the House, Senator Norris, who is a wonderful man and an inspiration to us all.</p> <p>I want to speak briefly about a report that was published earlier in the week by the Tallaght Drug and Alcohol Task Force regarding the landscape of drug misuse in the Tallaght and Whitechurch areas of Dublin.  The report was launched by my colleague, Senator Ruane, who has done really important work in the area and brought attention to the realities of life for people in her community and others like it.  The Tallaght Drug and Alcohol Task Force commissioned a piece of research earlier this year in light of concerns about the deterioration of what was already a seriously challenging drug problem in the area.  The relevant community health area has one of the highest rates of drug use nationally, the second highest rate of people seeking treatment for drug addiction and the second highest rate of new presentations to drug treatment services.  While heroin is the main problem drug, the task force was increasingly concerned about the number of people seeking support for addiction to cocaine and crack cocaine in the area.  The research supported this conclusion, with the levels of crack cocaine use found to be among the highest in this country.</p> <p>When you combine an expanding young population, a high level demand on local services and high levels of poverty, you are left with a really challenging landscape in which drug misuse can become rampant.  It is clear that this is what has happened in Tallaght and Whitechurch, but unfortunately, the area is not an outlier in this way.  There are too many communities around the country that have been let down by the State and that are marked by high levels of drug and alcohol misuse.  These two things go hand in hand but, for whatever reason, we choose not to acknowledge it.  Services like the Tallaght Drug and Alcohol Task Force do exceptional work in supporting people in addiction to lead happier and healthier lives, but they do so in an increasingly challenging landscape with limited resources.</p> <p>The Tallaght Drug and Alcohol Task Force has seen a decrease in funding made available to support its work since 2010, in spite of the increasing levels of demand for its service.  When compared with other task forces in Dublin, the Tallaght Drug and Alcohol Task Force receives less funding than some areas that have smaller populations and lower numbers of people accessing drug treatment services.  How can we stand over this in good faith?  The answer is that we simply cannot.  As my colleague, Senator Ruane, has previously stated, the cost of inaction on this issue is far greater than the cost of action.  First and foremost, we need to ensure that services like the Tallaght Drug and Alcohol Task Force receive the funding they require to continue their work.  I encourage the Department of Health to review this matter specifically as a matter of urgency.  We also have to consider the broader role that the State can play in intervening in problem drug use early to ensure that fewer people, families and communities are touched by drug and alcohol addiction.  It is an issue we need to give greater attention to.  I would welcome the opportunity to discuss it with my colleagues in the House in the coming weeks and months.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1638" speakername="Malcolm Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#K00300"><p>Like my colleagues, I would like to join in the expressions of sympathy for the late Austin Currie, to his family and particularly to our colleague, Senator Currie.  He was a giant in Irish politics and showed the power of peaceful protest.  His legacy will live on.</p> <p>I wish to join Senator Daly in raising again the issue of the Passport Office and the delays in processing applications, but I want to add the question of the registration of foreign births, which is an issue that I have raised in the House on a number of occasions.  As we heard, the marts and nightclubs are open, but if you visit the Department of Foreign Affairs website, you are told that the section that deals with the registration of foreign births is still closed due to Covid.  There is currently a backlog of around 31,000 applications.  Part of the difficulty is that documents are sent into the Department and they are sitting there.  People cannot access a lot of those documents because of the delays.  This issue has been raised on several occasions.  I ask that the Minister of Foreign Affairs is invited to the House to respond specifically on the issues of the registration of foreign births and the Passport Office, in respect of which, as stated by Senator Daly, we all still have complaints.</p> <p>The Deputy Leader and I took part in a very useful engagement this morning of the Seanad Special Select Committee on the Withdrawal of the UK from the EU, the Joint Oireachtas Committee on European Union Affairs and the Joint Oireachtas Committee on the Implementation of the Good Friday Agreement with the House of Lords European Affairs Sub-Committee on the Protocol on Ireland/Northern Ireland.  It is important that this Chamber looks at engaging with other chambers.  One of the key aspects that was found to be useful around that was the message that we all need to keep talking.  If we can arrange for more engagement between this Chamber and other chambers around the issue, it should be encouraged.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" speakername="Mary Seery Kearney" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#K00400"><p>I want to begin by paying tribute to the courage, commitment and dedication to peaceful protest exhibited by Austin Currie, and to express my deepest sympathy to Senator Currie and the entire family.</p> <p>Last night, the "Prime Time Investigates" documentary on wardship was aired.  I wish to begin by renewing my call that the Assisted Decision-Making (Capacity) Act is commenced and that we bring forward the launch of everything that needs to flow from that.  The Minister has assured me on several occasions that it will be next June, but that is a long way away for people who are being made wards of court in the meantime and who are labouring under the current regime that presumes them not to have capacity.  We need to move to a place of respect and capacity as quickly as possible.  This has gone on long enough.</p> <p>I also ask that we have statements in the House relating to what was shown in the documentary last night that I found really quite appalling, namely, the idea that the State obliges a regime of fiduciary duty taken up by the Courts Service, and the circumstances where the investments under that fiduciary duty have led to the absolute loss of the amount of money that was there for a person's full life.  These people were given awards that were supposed to last their lifetimes and in some instances, when they are still in their 40s, that money has expired because of the manner in which it was invested over the past ten years to 15 years. That is not okay.  If they had left it in a bank account and not invested it in anything, they would still at least have it.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Mary Seery Kearney:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=MarySeeryKearney&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We need a debate or statements in the House and we need to hear the view of the Minister.  I call for that to be arranged.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1658" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#L00200"><p>I would like to say a few words about the participation of women and girls in sport.  It is important, where possible, that we encourage all young people, both boys and girls, to get involved in sport whatever that might be.  Volunteers do great work the length and breadth of this country to promote sport, and encourage both young boys and girls to get involved.  Last weekend, there was a shining example of such great work in my constituency where history was made.  The under-13 and under-15 girls' teams represented the Cavan-Monaghan Underage League in a football match that took place in Donegal.  It is a very positive thing to happen and was the first time this ever happened.  For the two squads involved, their coaches and mentors and everybody involved it was a super day and an historic day.  For the coaches involved whose idea it was to get a team to participate was a very positive thing.</p> <p>For women in sport the motto seems to be if one can see it then one can be it.  Again, there are two prime examples and shining role models in the Cavan-Monaghan constituency.  First, there is Leanne Kiernan from Killinkere, County Cavan.  She is an Irish soccer international and now she is a striker with Liverpool Football Club.  Second, there is the Cavan referee, Margaret Farrelly.  Next Sunday, she will be the first woman to take charge of a men's senior football final when Gowna and Ramor United will play a replay match in Kingspan Breffni Park.  Her appointment is the first of its kind and is an historic occasion.  I was greatly impressed with her saying that she looks forward to the day when it will not make headlines when a woman is asked to referee a football match and I echo her sentiment.  I urge girls to look up to these two young ladies and aspire to be just like them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#L00300"><p>As the Senator has said, if one can see it then one can be it and I congratulate Ms Farrelly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1666" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#L00400"><p>I wish to express my condolences to Senator Currie and her family on the tragic loss of her dad.  Obviously this is a very traumatic time for her and her family, and I would like to be associated with the kind tributes that have been uttered about him here in this House.</p> <p>I wish to refer to the significant proposal to stage a major yacht race, as part of the America's Cup, that is hoped to come to the southern half of Ireland in 2024.  It would be the third biggest sporting event in Ireland in 2024 and would have a huge knock-on effect on the tourism industry as it would bring anything up to 2.5 million visitors to Ireland who would have a proposed spend of anything up to &euro;750 million.  The event has the potential to be the biggest event ever to take place here and the knock-on effects for Ireland would be huge.  The event would safeguard the tourism industry for 2024.  We do not know how the world economy is going to go and this event will act as an insurance policy by creating a boom in our tourism industry in 2024.</p> <p>The clock is ticking and we need to make a decision.  We need to make sure that we are in the race to host the event but for that to happen the Government will need to make a decision.  I ask the Deputy Leader, in particular, to contact the office of the Minister for Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sport and Media, Deputy Catherine Martin, about the event as it has the potential to change lives and the economy.  As the event would ensure that the southern side of Ireland would have a very prosperous 2024 we must make sure that the Government gets on board with the idea and makes a decision in the  appropriate timeline.  I believe from now until the end of the year is the appropriate time to make the decision and we should avail of the opportunity.  Ireland has moved from being one of 30 contenders to one of three contenders to host the event .  We need to make sure that we finish the race but for that to happen the Government needs to step up and deliver.  I ask the Deputy Leader to contact the Minister about the issue in good time.  It is appropriate for us to debate the issue and I ask that the Deputy Leader invites the Minister to come here, in the next few weeks, to discuss her view of the proposal to stage a leg of the America's Cup and whether she will put the full support of the Government behind the proposal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1671" speakername="Erin McGreehan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#L00500"><p>I, too, wish to pass on my condolences to the family and friends of Austin Currie and, indeed, to our colleague, Senator Currie.  It must be remembered that in the face of so much adversity and strife in the North, Austin Currie stood against bullies.  People on both sides went against him yet he stood up for what was right and never faltered.  He always positively disrupted the <i>status quo</i>of injustice and inequality.</p><p>In terms of the legacy of real activists from Northern Ireland, I wish to emphasise that this is an important time in history due to the Northern Ireland protocol.  We have the scenario of &quot;will we, won't we&quot; or &quot;will they, won't they&quot; trigger Article 16 on this island.  I hope that the British Government decides to pull back on the protocol.  Earlier we had a great engagement with the representatives of the House of Lords.  We are in stasis where we need to get Brexit done.  We need to move on with the next stages of Brexit and deal with the consequences of same.  This State remains in stasis as the British Government does not know what sort of Brexit it wants and has not planned for anything.  Let us hope that there is a fruitful and proper outcome in the next couple of weeks so that all of the people on this island can move forward with peace and prosperity.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1695" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#L00600"><p>I wish to be associated with the condolences extended to our colleague, Senator Currie, her mother, Annita, and the extended Currie family on the passing of Austin.  I had the pleasure of working with him when he ran in the presidential campaign back in the 1980s.  I knew him to be a thorough gentleman.  He brought so much to the office of the Minister of State but also in terms of his work as a Deputy, and his work on the North in the past.  I am thinking of all of his family at this sad time.</p> <p>I welcome the motion that was passed recently in the D&aacute;il.  The motion was proposed by Deputy Carroll MacNeill and concerned the establishment of a committee on gender equality.  The figures are stark and are as follows: women only accounted for 22.5% of Deputies - there is a better percentage in the Seanad; women in Ireland effectively work for free for the last 14.4% of the year; women accounted for  22.4% of board members; and 19% of Irish companies have no female directors.  Those statistics are frightening.  A committee would be a step in the right direction and I would like it established as soon as possible.  I seek the support of this House on the establishment of a committee in terms of securing gender equality and equality for all.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#L00700"><p>That issue will be on the agenda of the Committee on Parliamentary Privileges and Oversight today and if it is agreed there then it will be on the agenda tomorrow in the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1694" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#L00800"><p>I would like to be associated with the kind remarks that Members have expressed for our old colleague, Senator David Norris.  I have had the privilege of serving in this House with him for 14 years and I have been most impressed by him at all times.  It is nice to see him being recognised in his own lifetime.</p> <p>I came into the Chamber especially to join in the condolences to the great Austin Currie.  When I was growing up I considered Austin Currie a hero.  He was a man of great courage who was prepared to take on the system in a democratic and non-violent way.  He and his SDLP colleagues are the people who affected profound change in the North.  We are at a time when, unfortunately, there are people in these Houses who will still try to justify the murder campaign of the Provisional IRA.  Indeed, the leader of one of the largest parties in these Houses continues to justify the murder campaign of the IRA.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Ned O'Sullivan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2233"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2233&amp;amp;pid=NedOSullivan&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is important to reflect on the fact that people like Austin Currie showed that you can effect change without shooting people, putting bombs on buses or murdering innocent women and children.  He needs to be recognised for that.  I send my heartfelt condolences to his daughter, Emer, and the rest of his family, and to his parliamentary colleagues in the SDLP and Fine Gael.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1629" speakername="Garret Ahearn" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#M00200"><p>Following on from the contributions of others, I also wish to mark the sad passing of Austin Currie.  I pass on my condolences, as others have done, to Emer and the whole Currie family on their sad and sudden loss.  I spoke to Emer this morning and she asked me to pass on her appreciation to everyone who has contacted her and the family.  It is a great source of strength to them at this time.  Mr. Currie was elected in 1989, the same day as my mother.  They were very good friends and Emer and I often joke about how we, too, entered this building and the irony involved in that.  It is a sad time for the Currie family.</p> <p>I ask the Deputy Leader for an update on the Government's commitment to provide funding for IVF treatment for women and couples.  Ireland, along with Lithuania, is one of only two countries that still do not provide State funding for assisted reproduction, even though the World Health Organization recognises infertility as a medical condition.  The legislation was supposed to have passed last year and then Minister for Health, Deputy Harris, worked on the matter.  It was thought the legislation would have gone through by now and IVF would be available.  Some &euro;2 million was designated for the procurement of IVF doctors in the public sector.  IVF patients typically have many expenses beyond the procedure itself that can add significantly to the overall costs involved.  Those costs include medications, blood tests and ultrasound monitoring.  Government in general, and this Government in particular, has done an awful lot to support families and women through maternity and paternity leave.  Everything we do is intended to try to support the family network but IVF treatment is one area that has been left out.  Many people across the country want to have a child and the expense of it, especially if they have to attend more than once or twice, is astronomical and the State needs to support those families.  They only have a certain period within which they can get that treatment and the longer we leave it, the more likely it is that people will be left out.  I urge the Deputy Leader to get an update on that issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#M00300"><p>I join with my colleagues in extending our sympathies to the Currie family and to our colleague and friend, Emer, on the sad passing of Austin Currie.  He was a colossus and a leader.  When it was unpopular to do so, he took the need for human rights to be upheld to a new level.  He built his life around peace and building bridges.  He never recoiled from what he stood for but never supported violence.  For the sake of his legacy and memory, we should all work to achieve his vision every day of our lives.  Ar dheis D&eacute; go raibh an anam.</p> <p>I join with Senator Lombard in asking for an urgent debate on the America's Cup.  This is a generational opportunity not only for Cork but also for the south west and the whole of our country.  We have had the Ryder Cup and the world championships in showjumping and athletics.  We have had all types of sporting and cultural events in our country, including the Eurovision Song Contest, and they have been held successfully to a high level.  The Ryder Cup showed we can do it in a sporting context.  We should embrace the America's Cup and ensure it is delivered to Cork and Ireland.  It is important for us to do that.  Senator Lombard was right to raise the matter.  The Minister should come before us.  It is not a matter of money or cost, it is about the opportunity and what the event can bring to us.  I do not own a boat and I do not have sea legs.  I do, however, have an appreciation of what this event is and of its scale, size and potential.</p> <p>We should remember Austin Currie this morning, a man who led, delivered, upheld and spoke about peace in everything he did.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1645" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#M00400"><p>I am grateful to the Cathaoirleach for allowing me in even though I was not scheduled to speak.  The death of Austin Currie, as many of my colleagues have said, is a tremendous loss to Ireland.  My sympathies go to his family.  It is a pity we do not have more people like Austin Currie now working in Northern Ireland, people with nothing but peace in their minds, hearts and everything they do.  As Senator Ned O'Sullivan said, Mr. Currie did not need guns or bullets.  He did it with language and talk.  We need those kinds of voices now, louder than ever, in the North.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#M00500"><p>I, too, would like to be associated with the tributes to Austin Currie.  He is a huge loss to his wife, Annita, to our friend and colleague, Senator Emer Currie, and to her siblings.  Austin Currie is also a huge loss to the island of Ireland.  We saw and know what he did when he was a Minister of State and representative of Dublin West.  He worked tirelessly for the people south of the Border but what he did in the North was inspirational.  In the darkest days of violence and when his own family were violently attacked on many occasions, he never once contemplated picking up a gun or engaging in violence.  That is real leadership.  Those are the types of people who I respect in Northern Ireland.  Mr. Currie was a leader.  Never did he contemplate violence.  I know he would abhor anyone justifying the 30 years of violence we had in this country.  That is his legacy and we should all be proud of it.</p> <p>On another issue, I notice there is going to be legislation for e-scooters in this country.  I have been at traffic lights when e-scooters have flown past me.  As somebody with impaired vision, it is quite frightening, as it is for older people and others with impairments and disabilities, to see e-scooters flying by.  I do not think the Houses of the Oireachtas should pass any legislation allowing the use of e-scooters until we are completely satisfied that protection measures are in place for the vulnerable people who also have a right to use the roads.  We must remember that the blind and visually-impaired community in particular are the original greens.  They use public transport and walk to get from A to B.  We should be leaders in this country in terms of e-scooters.  We should not legislate for them or legalise them until protections are in place.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#M00600"><p>I join with the words others have said about the late Austin Currie, leader of the civil rights movement.  His occupation of a house in Caledon was a seminal moment, born of his burning desire for justice.  He was elected to Stormont at 24 years of age, became leader of the SDLP, was elected to the D&aacute;il in 1989, served as a Minister of State from 1994 until 1997 and was a presidential election candidate.  He was courageous, brilliant and completely giving of himself.  As has been well said by others, he was a man of peace.  He fulfilled the Christian ideal to the letter of the law.</p> <p>I had a personal connection with Mr. Currie.  The first time I was elected to this House, he came to my local community to make a little presentation of a piece of crystal to me.  He came with Anita.  It meant we came to know each other.  I always remember that, the warmth he brought with him and the affection he was held in by the people.  His spirit lives on in our colleague, Emer.  I offer my sympathies to Anita, Emer and their family.  Go bhfana s&eacute; ar thaobh na l&aacute;imhe deise &oacute; Dhia.</p> <p>I will briefly join in the words that have been said about Senator Norris.  He has been a pioneering social reformer and was one of the greatest parliamentarians of the 20th century.  He is man who has broken moulds.  We badly needed him in this country.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Joe O'Reilly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=1610"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1610&amp;amp;pid=JoeOReilly&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> I have raised my last issue with the Leader previously.  It relates to the waiting list for child and adolescent mental health services, CAMHS.  I asked the Leader whether something can be done to shorten it?   Where is this at now?  It is a horror to leave children in this state.  I cannot see a greater social priority than to deal with the CAMHS list.  My understanding is that it is too long and I would like a comment on it, and action on it. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1646" speakername="Ollie Crowe" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#N00200"><p>I offer my sincere sympathies to Anita, Emer and the Currie family on the death of a statesman.  I want to raise the construction sector.  It is an area, thankfully, that is rebounding strongly following lockdown with business having increased in each of the past seven months.  The sector seems poised for further growth and with the new sectoral employment order likely to be implemented - I attended a joint committee on this earlier - that is very welcome.  However, there are issues facing the sector in regard to recruitment, apprenticeships and, in particular, the soaring costs of construction materials, which is having a significant impact on the cost of housing, especially in my own city of Galway.  This is an area of great concern.  Price inflation in the construction sector hit a record last month largely due to supply chain issues and Brexit.  To give an example, a couple contacted me recently who initially agreed to purchase a property for &euro;450,000 but due to significant costs, the price increased to &euro;525,000 for first-time buyers, which was to their detriment.  They are unable to proceed now, naturally, as the price has gone up by &euro;75,000 but they have also lost the &euro;30,000 help-to-buy grant.  This issue needs to be addressed.  The costs are being passed on in all cases.  Whether building homes or infrastructure, this is a significant issue facing all our people.  I ask the Leader to invite the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage to the House to have a discussion and find a solution to the matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" speakername="Barry Ward" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#N00300"><p>I also wish to be associated with those Members who have expressed condolences to the Currie family.  Austin Currie was a giant of Irish politics and the only person to have served on the Executive on both sides of the Border.  I extend my condolences to our colleague, Senator Emer Currie, as well.</p> <p>I also wish to be associated with those who have expressed support for the America's Cup coming to Ireland.  I am a sailor, not at that level, but I can recognise the massive benefit inherent in that project coming to Ireland and I support that.</p> <p>I want to mention driver's licences.  Members will be aware that driver's licences are divided into different categories according to what kind of vehicle is being driven.  A is for motorbikes, AM is for mopeds, W is for work vehicles and tractors, and B is the standard car licence.  Until 2006, those who got a B licence automatically got an AM and a W category licence.  The W is still given but the AM has ceased since October 2006.  Any people who got licences for the standard car over the past 15 years are not given the right also to drive mopeds.  I simply do not see the sense in that.  We are unique in the EU in that regard.  Every other country accords that extension to people who have an ordinary car licence.  An AM is a moped of a certain size and capacity, which can only do a certain speed and can only travel with a certain power.  It makes absolute sense that we should allow people to use mopeds from an environmental, traffic and common-sense point of view.  Can we make time for a debate on that, or call for the Minister for Transport to revise that policy and bring us in line with our colleagues in the EU?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1639" speakername="Miche&aacute;l Carrigy" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#N00400"><p>I pass on my sympathies to our colleague and the Currie family on the death of Austin Currie.  They can be very proud of the immense contribution he made to Irish life both North and South.</p> <p>Members will be able to see the badge I am wearing to support the Irish Heart Foundation promotional month, FAST, to highlight the signs of stroke: face, arms, speech and time.  It is important we recognise that.  I also highlight that it is four years since the HSE was asked to produce a national stroke strategy and it has not been published yet.  When will that be published?</p> <p>An issue relating to Gaelic games within our diaspora in the US has come up in the media.  We should be proud of how we promote our games throughout the world, and the numbers of people who play them.  The GAA is a magnet to our diaspora.  I lived in the US for a short while and the first thing people do is join the local GAA club.  They do immense in promoting Irish culture and keeping that sense of Irishness throughout America.  During 2020 a significant number of clubs did not travel to games in Boston due to Covid-19.  The GAA in the US is suspending and fining clubs for not travelling more than 3,000 miles from the west coast of America to Boston to take part in games and giving them no right of appeal.  I was heavily involved at national level in the GAA.  It is a very democratic organisation with appeals processes for every issue, yet this does not seem to pertain to US GAA.  I would ask the GAA at Croke Park level to intervene.  We are very proud of keeping our culture alive and this does set a good example.  People who prioritised the health of their communities by not travelling, which we also asked our citizens not to do, are now suspended.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" speakername="Lisa Chambers" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#N00600"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach.  Given that every colleague who contributed paid their respects and expressed sympathy to the Currie family on the passing of Austin Currie, I propose that have a minute's silence to honour his passing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.72" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Members rose.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" speakername="Lisa Chambers" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#N00800"><p>I thank everybody for their contributions to the Order of Business.  Senator Daly started by raising the issue of the Passport Office and the continuing backlog while acknowledging that some improvements have been made with the direct line but also highlighting the ridiculous situation that a person was posted their passport when it was not possible to reach them.  Generally when people come to anyone in public life looking for help with a passport, it is always at the eleventh hour, if not beyond that.  That is why the office needs to have a system in place to deal with those emergencies.  It is not a favour or a gift; it is an entitlement as a citizen.  </p> <p>Senator Kyne raised the issue of the ongoing Common Agricultural Policy, CAP, negotiations and the meeting in Athenry mart.  I acknowledge the fantastic work done by Minister, Charlie McConalogue, who has done a tour of marts throughout the country to engage with all farming organisations on the CAP.  There are some difficult decisions to be taken.  There is not, unfortunately, a unified position among those in the farming community, which others have highlighted.  There will be significant decisions to be taken on that, but it is important to ensure there is fairness at the heart of the next CAP. </p> <p>Senator Boyhan raised the outstanding record, legacy and contribution of Senator David Norris, who is the longest serving Member of the House or the father of the House as he is so often called, and referenced the unveiling of a portrait of the Senator, which was unveiled earlier today by the Cathaoirleach and the House Leader and other Members to honour his contribution to this House and to Irish public life.  There will be continued celebrations later today and we join by congratulating the Senator on his fantastic achievements as one individual who has done so much for people in this country.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Lisa Chambers:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2449"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2449&amp;amp;pid=LisaChambers&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Senator Boyhan also raised the matter of local government funding, which has been mentioned by many other Members over the past few weeks in particular, asking for a debate on the matter.  He also mentioned the local property tax and rates issue.  We should seek that debate at the earliest opportunity.<br/><br/>Senator Martin concurred with the remarks about Senator Norris and spoke on the passing of Austin Currie as well.  Senator Boylan spoke about the <i>daft.ie</i>report, as did Senator Moynihan, and in particular the increase in rents.  It is a concern for all of us that rents are increasing at such an alarming rate.  The Government has recently launched its Housing for All plan, underpinned by &euro;4 billion of investment.  This is the largest ever investment by the State in housing.  There will be significant investment in public, affordable and cost rental housing to ensure we can tackle this housing crisis once and for all.<br/><br/>Senator Black raised the matter of drug use, referencing Tallaght in particular and the lack of addiction support services in helping people get better.  It is a chronic issue not just in that area but in many areas of the country.  Senator Malcolm Byrne raised the matter of the backlog in the issuing of foreign birth registrations, as he has before, and concurred with Senator Paul Daly's comments about the passport backlog.  It may be worth putting down a matter on the Commencement on that very specific issue in order to get an update on why there is such a delay in the issuing of those birth registrations.<br/><br/>The Senator also mentioned we had a very productive meeting of the Seanad Brexit committee in a joint meeting with the EU affairs and Good Friday Agreement committees, where we had a virtual discussion with Members of the House of Lords.  It was a really good engagement and I am sure people agree it is very timely, given what has been happening in the Brexit process.  Senator McGreehan was also at the meeting and raised the matter again on the Order of Business this morning.  It is really important we have continued dialogue and continue speaking with one another.  That message was delivered loud and clear from the House of Lords as well and those Members want to continue speaking as well while keeping the door open to ensure discussion is maintained.  It was a very interesting meeting with many solutions being proposed as to how we might get around the current impasse.  We will continue to work towards a solution.<br/><br/>Senator Seery Kearney raised the question of wards of court and issues around investment.  It is a serious question and there should be accountability around who was managing those funds.  Ultimately, a very vulnerable person was left in a very poor position.  Perhaps she could put down a matter on the Commencement and if that is not sufficient, we should seek a further debate in the House to give all Senators an opportunity to discuss the matter.<br/><br/>Senator Gallagher spoke about young girls in sport.  It is a major issue that there is a huge drop-off rate in girls participating in sports, particularly in second level education.  There is no doubt that when there are positive role models such as Leanne Kiernan and Maggie Farrelly, referenced by the Senator, who are leading the way in their fields, it will encourage other young girls to stay in sport for the benefit of themselves and their communities.  I congratulate the two teams involved in that historic moment and it is great to see.<br/><br/>Senators Lombard, Buttimer and Ward raised the matter of the America's Cup and the importance of the event.  I will not pretend to be an expert in sailing but I understand how important that event would be to so many people.  I hope it will be looked upon favourably and any event of that magnitude would be beneficial for the country I am sure.  We have much sailing expertise in the country and many sports men and women, as well as young people, in the area.<br/><br/>Senator McGreehan spoke very eloquently about the need to get the Brexit matters sorted and the real impact it is having on people's lives.  We speak about this often at a high level but this is affecting businesses and citizens, particularly those living in Border areas like Louth, where the Senator lives.  It has an impact right across the Border region so it is really important we get this right.<br/><br/>Senator Maria Byrne commended Deputy Carroll MacNeill on her proposal to set up a committee on gender equality.  It is something with which I would have no difficulty.  It would be very worthwhile and I look forward to hearing more information on what that committee might do or how we might get it up and running.  We want to work with the Deputy and Senator on that matter.<br/><br/>Senator O'Sullivan spoke very eloquently, as he so often does when he gets to his feet, and we can see the depth of experience in him when he speaks.  He delivered a very strong message that change can be affected in a peaceful way.  That is the legacy Austin Currie left for his family and all of us.  I concur with the Senator's remarks.<br/><br/>Senator Ahearn sought an update on the funding for IVF treatment, which is a very important matter because so many couples and families experience infertility.  It is long overdue.  My most up-to-date information is a Bill is being worked on to try to get this over the line as quickly as possible and provide State financial support to couples experiencing infertility, as is evident in so many other countries.  We are lagging behind in that regard.<br/><br/>Senator Craughwell got to his feet to pay his respects to Austin Currie, as did Senator Conway.  Senator Conway also raised an interesting question around electric scooters.  I had not heard the term &quot;original greens&quot; before in reference to those who are visually impaired and have been using public transport for a very long time.  It is a very important point that when we make these policy and legislative changes, we must ensure it is in the interests of everybody to do that.  Legislation pertaining to these vehicles must be explored further.<br/><br/>Senator Joe O'Reilly raised the question of the child and adolescent mental health services waiting list, and we are all getting representations about that.  As the Senator said, we are leaving very vulnerable people in a very dire position.  It is a waiting list that should be cleared with urgency.<br/><br/>Senator Crowe raised the matter of the construction sector and the cost of building materials, which we are all very keenly aware of now.  It is affecting the building of family homes and public housing so it is a major concern.  A debate in the House with the Minister would be welcome.  The Minister will be before the House at some point anyway and this is a very important point to raise with him.<br/><br/>Senator Ward raised the question of driving licences and I was not aware of what he mentioned.  That probably indicates how long it has been since I got my licence.  It is a sensible solution and would offer people the opportunity to drive a moped when they have been tested in a car.  It might be a useful Commencement matter as it is quite specific.<br/><br/>Senator Carrigy mentioned the work of the Irish Heart Foundation.  Perhaps a Commencement matter would give an answer on his question about the national stroke strategy, as again it is quite specific.  It is important work that should be concluded.  The Senator also spoke about the GAA and he has made it clear to people at senior levels in the association that the matter should be addressed.  I hope they will respond positively to the Senator's request.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#O00200"><p>Senator Rebecca Moynihan proposed an amendment to the Order of Business, "That No. 86, motion 3, on the Order Paper be taken before No. 1."  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.76" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Order of Business, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.77" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#O00400">Vacancy in Membership of Seanad Éireann: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1672" speakername="Rebecca Moynihan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#O00500"><p>I move:</p> <blockquote> 	That the Clerk of Seanad &Eacute;ireann do send to the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage notice of a vacancy in the membership of Seanad &Eacute;ireann occasioned by the election to D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann of Senator Ivana Bacik, a member elected for the University of Dublin constituency at the General Election for Seanad &Eacute;ireann, April, 2020. </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1645" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#O00600"><p>I second the motion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.80" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.81" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 12.50 p.m. and resumed at 1 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.82" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#Q00100">Criminal Justice (Amendment) Bill 2021: Committee Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.83" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Section 1 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.84" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>SECTION 2</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.85" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That section 2 stand part of the Bill."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#Q00400"><p>Is the section agreed to?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1669" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#Q00500"><p>It is not agreed.  I was unfortunately not able to participate in the Second Stage debate on the Bill.  I would have liked to have said a few words about its general principle.  I will take this opportunity on the section to make a few remarks about the Bill.</p><p>First, in light of the judgment of the Supreme Court in Wayne Ellis <i>v</i>. the Minister for Justice and Equality, I believe the present Government and the present Attorney General have no option but to introduce legislation along these lines.  Therefore, I make no criticism whatsoever of the Department of Justice or the Government for sponsoring this legislation.</p><p>Second, the judgment of Ms Justice Finlay Geoghegan in the Supreme Court on 15 May 2019 broke new ground insofar as it effectively said the Oireachtas, in determining by statute penalties that can be imposed for offences, may not provide for penalties - or mandatory penalties at any rate - for second and subsequent offenders that are greater than those for first offences.  I wish to put on the record a couple of points in that regard.</p><p>When the Criminal Justice Act 2006 amended section 27A of the Firearms Act 1964, it provided as follows: &quot;It is an offence for a person to possess or control a firearm or ammunition in circumstances that give rise to a reasonable inference that the person does not possess or control it for a lawful purpose, unless the person possesses or controls it for such a purpose.&quot;  In other words, it is an offence to have a weapon for an unlawful purpose unless one has a lawful purpose, which is obvious.  That section continues:</p> <blockquote> 	A person guilty of an offence under this section is liable ... on indictment&mdash;  	(a) to imprisonment for a term not exceeding 14 years or such shorter term as the court may determine, subject to subsections (4) to (6) of this section or, where subsection (8) of this section applies, to that subsection, and<br /><br />(b) at the court's discretion, to a fine of such amount as the court considers appropriate.  </blockquote> <p>This is possession of a firearm with an intent to commit a serious offence.  Section 27A(3) states: &quot;The court, in imposing sentence on a person for an offence under this section, may, in particular, have regard to whether the person has a previous conviction for an offence under the Firearms Acts ..., the Offences against the State Acts ... or the Criminal Justice (Terrorist Offences) Act 2005.&quot;  Thus far there is no problem with that.  In imposing a sentence up to a maximum, the court may have regard to the fact that the person has previously committed a fairly serious firearms offence.  Section 27A(4) states: &quot;Where a person (other than a person under the age of 18 years) is convicted of an offence under this section, the court shall, in imposing sentence, specify a term of imprisonment of not less than 5 years as the minimum term of imprisonment to be served by the person.&quot;  That is simple too.  It is a minimum tariff of five years for all offenders.  However, following amendments made by the Criminal Justice Act 2007, the Act went on to state, in section 27A(4A), &quot;The purpose of subsections (5) and (6) of this section is to provide that in view of the harm caused to society by the unlawful possession and use of firearms, a court, in imposing sentence on a person (except a person under the age of 18 years) for an offence under this section, shall specify as the minimum term of imprisonment to be served by the person a term of not less than 10 years, unless the court determines that by reason of exceptional and specific circumstances relating to the offence, or the person convicted of it, it would be unjust in all the circumstances to do so.&quot;  I was the Minister at the time of the drafting of that legislation, and that section was crafted in close consultation with the then Attorney General, Rory Brady SC.  It provided that the minimum sentence for a repeat offender was to apply unless, having regard to the exceptional circumstances of the offence, or specific circumstances relating to the offence or the person convicted of it, it would be &quot;unjust in all circumstances to do so&quot;.  Section 27A(5) provides that subsection (4)</p> <blockquote> 	&quot;does not apply where the court is satisfied that there are exceptional and specific circumstances relating to the offence, or the person convicted of it ... [which would make the minimum term] unjust in all the circumstances, and for this purpose the court may [subject to subsection (6)] have regard to any matters it considers appropriate, including&mdash;  	(a) whether the person pleaded guilty to the offence and, if so&mdash; <blockquote> 	(i) the stage at which the intention to plead guilty was indicated,<br /><br />(ii) the circumstances in which the indication was given </blockquote>and<br /><br />(b) whether the person materially assisted in the investigation of the offence.  </blockquote> <p>Section 27A(6) states:</p> <blockquote> 	The court, in considering for the purposes of subsection (5) of this section whether a sentence of not less than 10 years imprisonment is unjust in all the circumstances, may have regard, in particular, to  	(a) whether the person convicted of the offence has a previous conviction for an offence under the Firearms Acts ..., the Offences Against the State Acts ... or the Criminal Justice (Terrorist Offences) Act 2005, and<br /><br />(b) whether the public interest in preventing the unlawful possession or use of firearms would be served by the imposition of a lesser sentence.  </blockquote> <p>This was a second way out for a court.  This was the essence of what was provided by the then Attorney General, in consultation with the Department of Justice.  First, the Judiciary was not required in any case where it would be unjust to apply a minimum sentence.  Second, the criteria that were set out were not exhaustive but purely indicative, and it was left to the court to take a very broad view of whether a minimum sentence should be imposed under the section.  The Supreme Court in the Wayne Ellis case came to consider the issue as to whether a minimum sentence imposed was in fact unlawful or, as the Supreme Court was later to find, an unlawful invasion of the sole prerogative of the Judiciary to administer justice and to impose sentences as part of the judicial function of the State.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Michael McDowell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=719"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=719&amp;amp;pid=MichaelMcDowellPD&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->In other words, those provisions that I have just read out were regarded by the Supreme Court's judgment as an impermissible invasion of the courts' jurisdiction.  In so finding, the court relied on previous jurisprudence to the effect that minimum sentences could be legitimate if they apply to everyone, but they could not be regarded as legitimate if they did not apply to everyone who committed an offence of the type in question.<br/><br/>This is the first occasion on which I have had any opportunity to discuss this decision.  When a person is a Minister, an Attorney General or in government, it is suicide to even query the correctness of a Supreme Court decision.  One just cannot do it.  The media would devour you and say you are arrogant, stupid and all the rest of it for querying it.  Therefore, the Constitution means what the Supreme Court says it means, and I fully accept this proposition.  Even though a person may in good faith disagree with the Supreme Court, if he or she holds executive office, either as Attorney General or as a Minister, then he or she is bound to comply with the jurisprudence of the Supreme Court and bound to comply with their view of what the Constitution does or does not permit.  I fully accept all of that.  It is obvious.  I make no criticism whatsoever of this Bill.  It interests me to point out that it was not simply the section in question that had to be amended, but that a variety of other sections also had to be amended to take account of this new determination by the Supreme Court as to where the boundaries lie between the legislative powers of the State, on the one hand, and scope of the judicial function, on the other.<br/><br/>The <i>ratio decidendi</i>of the Supreme Court was that it was, in effect, bound by previous court decisions that if there was to be a minimum sentence or a general sentence of a minimum kind for an offence, it had to apply to everybody who committed that offence and not just to some classes of people who might have committed it.  The Bill before us deals with a series of offences under previous statutes where differentiation was made in sentencing of a minimum kind between people who had previous convictions for that offence and people who had not.  Of course, it is very commonplace to say in legislation that in the case of a first offence the maximum is two years and in the case of a second or subsequent offence it is seven years.  This is nothing to do with the Supreme Court decision that we are dealing with here.<br/><br/>I am tentative on this next point, but I do want to make it.  Having been the Minister involved, having consulted with the Attorney General and having carefully considered that there was an issue that a minimum sentence law had to respect, in the ultimate, the right of the Judiciary to depart from it where it considered that its result would be unjust, it was strange indeed that we would find ourselves in the position that the legislation should be struck down.  Very few people have been in the position that I am in now of having introduced legislation on the advice of the Attorney General and saying that it was legitimate and kosher in the context of the Constitution, only to find afterwards that the Supreme Court, having addressed the issue, took a radically different view to the effect that the provisions that had been included in order to ensure that no court would be forced to impose a minimum sentence where it would be unjust to do so, and in throwing out categories of issues which the court could look at to see whether it would be unjust, not do so exhaustively and allow the court a wider discretion not to impose it on the grounds that it would be unjust to do so.  I am long enough in the tooth, as a Member of the Houses of the Oireachtas, as a person who has held ministerial office and served as Attorney General, and as someone who has practised law, including criminal law, and who has appeared in many constitutional cases, to afford myself the opportunity to say that I believe that in this respect the approach of the Supreme Court was wrong.  I just want to record that fact.<br/><br/>I am not saying that my view is preferable to the court's view, or that my view should dissuade the Minister of State from going ahead with the legislation or that my view has any real weight in this matter.  I do, however, make the point - it is worthwhile making it but nowhere is it referred to in a satisfactory way in the majority judgment of the Supreme Court - that there is, in my view, a very clear rule of double construction to the effect that any statute which comes before the Supreme Court should be looked at and if it contains a constitutional interpretation, it should be accorded that meaning.  Looking at the judgment of the Supreme Court, I find that it failed completely to address that issue.  I just want to put this on the record - very few people are in a position to be able to say this - I find that it failed completely to address that issue.  It simply looked at the judicial function and the legislative function and, without determining the legality of it - and it expressly prescinds from that of generalised minimum sentences - and stated that this provision offends the distinction between the competence of the Oireachtas to provide minimum sentences and the rule, which the court found in earlier case law, that if there are to be minimum or mandatory sentences, they should apply to everybody in the category and not just to classes of offenders.<br/><br/>I believe that the late Attorney General Rory Brady got it right.  I also believe that the Supreme Court did not apply its own jurisprudence on the question of the constitutional interpretation of statutes in a satisfactory way.  I have the greatest of respect for the judges who are mentioned in the case report.  I have huge respect for all of them.  I felt that simply to acquiesce in the judgment and not point out that the whole constitutional dimension had been very carefully considered by the Attorney General at the time in the context of the advice he gave to the Department of Justice and that the Supreme Court seems to have departed from the rule of double construction in that if the Act were in every case and if it is indeed the case that there is something wrong with distinguishing between different categories of persons who commit the same offence, then the statute was capable of being given a constitutional interpretation and ought not have been struck down.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Michael McDowell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=719"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=719&amp;amp;pid=MichaelMcDowellPD&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Respectfully and humbly, therefore, I consider that the reasoning of the Supreme Court in this case was wrong.  I put that on the record humbly, accepting that we live in a constitutional democracy and that the Constitution, by way of how we have enshrined the judicial function in the Constitution, means what the Supreme Court says it means.  However, I feel it is important to put on the record that this statute did not require any court to impose the minimum sentence where it found that it was unjust to do so.  The consequence of that must be that it was advisory at the most and was not mandatory.  Although its language approaches mandatory language, it has this escape valve of non-application where it would result in an injustice.</p><p>It may be a bit self-indulgent to dispute the correctness of a Supreme Court judgment in the Houses of the Oireachtas and perhaps very few people would dare to do so.  While accepting that the Supreme Court judgment is the binding judgment, and that my view of the matter is not in any sense a reason Ministers should not act on their judgment and implement the substance of their view, it occurs to me that sometimes the Judiciary takes a view of its province which is, and properly so, jealous of invasion by the Oireachtas.  Where the Oireachtas, however, enacts a law which on the face of it respects the right of the Judiciary regarding a minimum sentence for a repeat offender and expressly provides that it shall not have effect if in the opinion of the sentencing court it would be unjust to do so, which is the cardinal principle of what the Attorney General advised the Department to put into the statute at the time, it is hard, applying the double construction rule, to come to the view that the underlying effect of the provision in question was permissive and advisory and not mandatory in respect of any particular outcome in any particular case.</p><p>We rarely have situations like this, because at the end of a Supreme Court decision as to what the Constitution means, that is it and that is what the Constitution means.  Nobody can argue with it.  The Supreme Court has held that whatever was in question means X or Y, and there is no opportunity for anybody to ask if that decision was right.  We live in a democracy and legal academics can challenge decisions on areas such as, for instance, the admissibility of evidence and all that type of jurisprudence.  People can take sides in a particular case on something of that kind.  I must say, however, in respect of applying the double construction rule, which was undoubtedly in the mind of the then Attorney General, Mr. Rory Brady SC, and applying the absolute principle which was set out in this section that the minimum sentence for a repeat offender would not apply where in the view of the court it was unjust, full stop, and considering that the provisions giving examples of reasons for injustice were not exhaustive but purely exemplary, that it seems to me that the double construction rule was not properly applied in this case.  </p><p>To make one further point on this subject, I believe this was a warning shot across the bows of the Oireachtas to signal that the judicial function in imposing sentences should not be the subject of a legislative policy as regards the circumstances in which any particular punishment is given.  I fully accept that the Judiciary is entitled to fire such a shot across the bows of the Oireachtas, but I consider that the enthusiasm of the Supreme Court in arriving at this judgment and this outcome in the Wayne Ellis case was coloured more by a desire to fire that warning shot than to pay adequate respect to the principle of double construction which should have saved the statute.</p><p>I will not say more than that.  I thank the Acting Chairperson for indulging me in saying that.  I feel that sometimes these things should be said and this House is one where these kinds of issues can be discussed.  I do not want to trespass on the patience of Members, but I do want to provide some explanation as to what happened and to put a serious question mark over the correctness of the decision eventually arrived at.  </p><p>The Supreme Court prayed in aid of its decision a prior decision about offences applying to all offenders committing an offence rather than just some or specifying a class of offenders.  That was not, however, dispositive of the issue in question, because the kernel of the issue in the Wayne Ellis case in my view, and that of the Minister of Justice, was new territory previously uncharted and therefore it should have attracted the double construction rule.  I have made my contribution, and I am thankful to the Acting Chairperson and the House for allowing me to do so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#S00200"><p>We gave the Senator a little bit of leeway.  We will move to the next speaker and try to stick to the amendment.  I call Senator Ward.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" speakername="Barry Ward" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#S00300"><p>Following on from what Senator McDowell said, I have no difficulty with criticism of the judgment, conscious that Senator McDowell from the outset acknowledged the supremacy of the Supreme Court and the reality of the fact that the Minister, the Executive and, ultimately, the law must follow what the Supreme Court has said.  I do not necessarily dispute what the Senator has said.  Undoubtedly, the Wayne Ellis case was a complex one.  I am not sure how much the parsing of arguments in this House advances the matter before us today, but I absolutely agree with the Senator when he says that one of the purposes of the decision made in the Wayne Ellis case was to put a shot across the bows of the Oireachtas to mark out the importance of judicial discretion.</p> <p>As it happens, I agree 100% with the Supreme Court on that front.  There is a habit sometimes in politics for us to want to push the penal provisions in legislation in a particular direction and to say that we are going to clamp down on a particular kind of offence and hit this kind of offender.  That is okay for politicians, but it fails to recognise that judges are highly qualified and highly experienced people who know what they are at.  As a Legislature, we should have faith in their ability to hit on the right sentence for any given offender.  I frequently get comments from people who contact me about something they have read about in the newspaper concerning a criminal case where somebody has got a sentence that they feel is unjust for whatever reason.  I am not necessarily saying that those people are always wrong, but what I always say to them is that the case was in the newspaper because it was an outlier, controversial and exceptional.  </p> <p>What is not in contained in the newspapers in respect of such cases is the detail of everything that was said in court, everything that was before the court and everything that the judge saw, heard, read and understood about the offender, as much as about the offence, and the effect on the victim, if there was an identifiable victim in a case.  I always caution people against deciding that a sentence is not hard enough for a person because of X, when in fact they cannot possibly have a full understanding of the factors that contributed to the final decision regarding a sentence.  The person who does have a full understanding in such instances is of course the sentencing judge who sat in court on the day, and who saw and heard the people concerned.  In accordance with the law and the procedures laid down in court, which are there to protect all of us, the judge will have heard exactly what factors come to bear on the sentence.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Barry Ward:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=BarryWard&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->When handing down sentences, judges invariably set out in some detail the factors they took into account, including mitigating factors that lowered sentences and aggregating factors that increased them.  They are now required by dint of decisions of the Court of Appeal in particular to set out where on the range of sentences available to them the offence should lie, where their starting point is and what they are applying in respect of aggravation or mitigation, for example.  Much more so than even ten, 15 or 20 years ago, there is now considerable clarity as to the exact factors that have a bearing on judges' decisions when they hand down sentences.  This is obviously for defendants and persons who are convicted but it is particularly for the victims of offences.  We have made great leaps forward in that regard such that a victim sitting in court or learning after the fact has much greater insight today than a decade ago as to the exact reason the sentence was arrived at.</p><p>In addition, there is a provision for the DPP to appeal against the undue leniency of a sentence.  If she feels that is inappropriate, there is jurisprudence set out in this regard.  We, as Members of the Legislature, should be marking the importance of judicial discretion and of having trust in our Judiciary.  In Ireland, perhaps more than in any other common law jurisdiction in the world, we have a Judiciary that has served us incredibly well.  We do not see a litany of miscarriages of justice in this country.  We do not see people being convicted unfairly in the way that can occur in other jurisdictions, and that is because the rule of law stands.  It is because judges respect the law and apply it as it is handed down from these Houses or interpreted by the superior courts, as the case may be.</p><p>I do not disagree specifically with Senator McDowell.  I recognise his right to say what he has to say, but I do believe it is important for us to acknowledge what the court has said about the Ellis case.</p><p>I want to raise another issue.  I wish to raise it under section 2 although I could raise it under any section.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#T00200"><p>It is not particularly related to section 2 either.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" speakername="Barry Ward" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#T00300"><p>Are we not on section 2?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#T00400"><p>I am saying that what the Senator is going to say is not particularly relevant to section 2.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" speakername="Barry Ward" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#T00500"><p>This Bill, as has been pointed out, seeks to amend a number legislative measures arising from the decision in the Ellis case.  As I said on Second Stage, I do not have a difficulty with the changes.  Many of them reflect what was in my Private Members' Bill, the Criminal Procedure and Related Matters Bill 2021, or go beyond it.  The one question I have, on which I have not tabled an amendment but which arises from the Road Traffic Acts, concerns the fact that this Bill, arising from the Ellis judgment, deals primarily with mandatory sentences arising from second offences.  Section 26(5)(b) of the Road Traffic Act relates to consequential disqualifications regarding offences under sections 52, 53 and 56.  For someone convicted of a second offence of having no insurance, there is a mandatory consequential disqualification.  Not having considered this matter until I was reading the amendments tabled for today, I must ask whether there is any issue transgressing what the Supreme Court said in respect of the Ellis case?  It is not a custodial sentence, obviously.  The approaches to disqualifications from driving are quite different because one does not have a right to drive.  It is a privilege to be granted a licence to drive in this country, as it should be, and therefore that privilege can be removed as the law and courts see fit.  Nonetheless, there is in section 26(5)(b), which was inserted by the Road Traffic Act 2010, mandatory disqualification on a second insurance offence.  I am wondering whether the Minister of State or Department has a view on whether that also transgresses the ratio handed down in the Ellis decision.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1669" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021111000002#T00600"><p>There is nothing that Senator Ward said with which I disagree at all.  I know, from having been where he is now and from having served as an Opposition Deputy, a Minister and Attorney General, that there is always a clamour for minimum sentences.  It is said that if you hit a Garda, you must go to jail for a year, for example.  Minimum sentences go down well with some parts of the media.  At the time we were trying to address this matter, we were trying to deal with gangland crime.  That was what we were worried about.  Fellows who produced sawn-off shotguns on day one could do three years and, lo and behold, appear again with a Kalashnikov or whatever.  We wanted to send a message to them that if they wanted to carry out firearms-related offences on an ongoing basis, they faced a very serious sentence of the kind in question.  That was the motivation.  It was not about appealing to the newspapers or unthinking bar stool critics.  The purpose was to send a message to those who had one brush with the use of firearms.  It was a very serious matter when I was Minister for Justice.  I was the guy who mistakenly talked about the dying wasp in respect of gangland offences.  The offences were a very serious matter.  Bearing in mind facts of the circumstances that gave rise to the sentence that was challenged, it is pretty alarming that somebody in those circumstances should not feel the full weight of the law on them.</p><p>I want to make one comment on what Senator Ward said about the progressive disqualification provisions.  I believe the Supreme Court would probably apply the double construction rule and say the disqualification of a driver is not a penalty or punishment in itself but a consequential decision by a court.  Let us be honest about it among ourselves: it is a punishment.  It is undoubtedly a punishment to put somebody off the road for five years, especially when it wipes out his or her capacity to drive a lorry or taxi, or to work as a travelling salesman or otherwise.  It is codology to say it is not intended to be punitive.  It is the consequence that is held out in front of drink drivers.  They do not care about the crime and do not really believe they will end up in Mountjoy unless they are completely drunk and kill somebody or injure somebody badly, but disqualification is the primary factor.  I have no doubt, however, that the court system would come to the view that this does not fall foul of the arrangement in question because it is not a judicial punishment <i>per se</i>.</p><p>I cannot remember the time of the change regarding the right of appeal against a sentence but I believe it existed at the time in question.  In legislation we passed in this House subsequently in respect of the Judicial Council, provision was made for sentencing guidelines.  Presumably, they are supposed to be mandatory in respect of the lower courts provided they have some flexibility in them.  They comprise guidance to judges as to what should happen.  Let me outline what interests me in that respect: supposing the judicial guidelines provided something that we all said was a bit rich or too light, or supposing it was said that for a second offence of rape there should be a sentence of eight years, at a minimum, we might say the sentence should be far longer and that it should be 14 years, at a minimum.  In such circumstances, can the Oireachtas do nothing and must it remain absolutely silent when it considers judicial guidelines on sentencing adopted by the Judicial Council whenever they are, in fact, promulgated?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-10a.98" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Additional debate to follow.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>