<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.2" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 14:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.4" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.5" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#A00100">An tOrd Gnó - Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#B00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Annie Hoey that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, she proposes to raise the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Health to outline when the monthly stipend to student nurses, approved by the Cabinet in 2021, will be paid. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Martin Conway of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Health to provide an update on resourcing at the adult metabolic service in the Mater Hospital and resourcing for response testing to new innovative therapies for phenylketonuria, PKU, treatment. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Maria Byrne of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Health to make a statement on progress in the roll-out of the programme on women's health announced in budget 2022. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Aidan Davitt of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for the Environment, Climate and Communications to make a statement on the exclusion of wood pellet stoves from the national retrofitting scheme. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Garret Ahearn of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage to outline his vision for HR shared services in local government. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Fiona O'Loughlin of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minster for Defence to make a statement on the affiliation of representative organisations within the Defence Forces with the Irish Congress of Trade Unions. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Malcolm Byrne of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister of State with responsibility for the Office of Public Works to provide an update on the planned new Coast Guard station at Courtown Harbour, County Wexford. </blockquote> <p>Of the matters raised by the Senators suitable for discussion, I have selected Senators Hoey, Conway, Maria Byrne and Davitt and they will be taken now.  I regret that I had to rule out of order the matter raised by Senator Fiona O'Loughlin on the ground that it is <i>sub judice</i>.  The other Senators may give notice on another day of the matters that they wish to raise.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.7" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#B00250">Nithe i dtosach suíonna - Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.8" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#B00300">Nursing Education</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1663" speakername="Annie Hoey" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#B00400"><p>I welcome the Minister of State.  I cannot believe that I am once again here talking about paying student nurses and midwives.  I ask the Minister of State to take my pleading back to the Minister for Health to sort out the pandemic payment for student nurses and midwives.  It is unbelievable that this is still going on.  A year ago, I introduced a piece of legislation that would allow student nurses and midwives to be paid.  The Government, cynically, did not oppose the Bill.  In fact, it let it proceed to Second Stage and be sent off into the ether rather than face a bad headline of once again simply refusing to acknowledge it or to commit to paying student nurses and midwives.  Whatever about the argument that student nurses and midwives are not working and, accordingly, whether they should therefore be paid, that is a little bit beyond the scope of what I am here to speak about today.</p> <p>I ask the Minister of State why student nurses and midwives have still not been paid the promised pandemic payment.  I have spoken to a number of student nurses and midwives around the country, and they want the Government to put its money where its mouth is and instead of clapping for them, to pay them the promised pandemic payment.  Students were deployed to fight this virus and while the Government did pay them the rate during the first wave, they ended up working during the much more aggressive second and third waves free of charge.  Student nurses and midwives took on the same workload as nurses while still balancing learning the skills required as part of their college training placement.</p> <p>I will not lie.  After two years of this pandemic, with all that we asked of student nurses and midwives and all that they did on the Covid-19 front line, I was almost apoplectic when I learned that the reason their payment, for which they have been fighting tooth and nail, was not yet paid was because a memorandum had not yet been written.  It is a very hard pill for student nurses and midwives to swallow that they are not getting a payment they had been promised from September, one I was told had been approved by the Cabinet before Christmas, although it is now February, nearly March, because a memorandum has not been written.  That is beyond unseemly.  It is extremely frustrating for student nurses and midwives.</p> <p>It is unbelievable that we have left struggling student nurses and midwives, and have not paid them this meagre contribution given that they held the hands of dying patients at the height of the pandemic when their family could not be there for them.  They cared for elderly patients on wards and played a crucial role in keeping the lights on and the doors open while Covid consumed the health service, all while they were students and supposed to be learning and on placement, upskilling and training to get the technical skills that are so desperately needed on their part.  The pandemic payment is not a whopper.  I believe it is &euro;100 a week, which is not insignificant.  It is incredible that it has not yet been paid.</p> <p>I would contest that student nurses and midwives are currently working for free, but the Government has the power to change that.  The Minister of State will probably tell me that the reason they have not been paid is because a memorandum has not gone out and that someone else has not done the work.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Annie Hoey:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=AnnieHoey&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Ultimately the Minister for Health is in charge of ensuring that student nurses and midwives are being paid.  That memo went to Cabinet and my understanding is that it was agreed by Cabinet.  As I said, it is unbelievable that we are in this situation.  It is February, nearly March, and student nurses and midwives are going to be coming to the end of their academic year very soon and they still have not been paid.  Why has this happened and, most important, when is it going to be rectified?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1614" speakername="Mary Butler" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#C00200"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this very important issue.  It is not the first time she has taken to her feet to raise this.  A key Government priority is to protect the education of all students,  including student nurses and midwives.  Clinical placements account for 50% of the overall education programme requirements for student nurses and midwives and supporting students to undertake clinical placement remains a key priority for the Government.  In early 2021 the Minister, Deputy Donnelly, directed a longer term review of matters relating to student nurses and midwives to be undertaken.  He appointed Mr. Se&aacute;n McHugh to carry out this important work.  In November 2021 following consideration of the recommendations within the McHugh report, Government approved the Minister's interim proposals to provide significant additional supports, worth &euro;12 million, to student nurses and midwives while attending their clinical placements.</p> <p>For supernumerary students these proposals extended the pandemic placement grant, PPG, of &euro;100 per week to all eligible nursing and midwifery students on placement for this academic year backdated to September 2021.  In addition, the McHugh report sets out recommendations to enhance the current travel and subsistence scheme for students in attending their supernumerary clinical placements.  The Minister will consider these further so that a permanent enhanced scheme can be developed that will provide a targeted and more equitable approach to supporting students in undertaking supernumerary clinical placements, to be in place from September 2022.</p> <p>In the meantime the Minister has doubled the weekly cap on vouched accommodation allowance to &euro;100 per week of placement for supernumerary students needing overnight accommodation away from their normal place of residence in order to attend some of their clinical placements, which is also backdated to September 2021.</p> <p>In regard to internship students on rostered placement, work is ongoing to progress other recommendations within the McHugh report, including increasing the salary of intern students to 80% of the staff nurse salary.  In the meantime we are providing student nurses and midwives on paid internship placement with additional support of &euro;50 per week of placement, amounting to &euro;1,800 in total.  This is for the duration of their internship and is with effect from January 2022, the same date as paid internships for the current academic year began.  </p> <p>To go to the nub of the Senator's question, on 22 January 2022 the Department issued sanction to the HSE regarding these additional supports and requested that payment be prioritised.  Yesterday the Department was informed by the HSE that it is finalising a memo to be issued to services to provide for payment.  As part of this process the draft communication has been shared with representative groups.  After the memo is finalised and issued, the HSE has confirmed payment will follow the normal lead in time for routine payment cycles which I believe is fortnightly.  The Department has once again emphasised to the HSE the importance of expediting these payments.</p> <p>In conclusion the Department has also commenced its work on the recommendations from the McHugh report that are applicable to the next academic year, and in this regard the Minister intends to bring a detailed proposal to Government in due course.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1663" speakername="Annie Hoey" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#C00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State for her reply.  We understood the memo had very recently gone out.  The review is extremely welcome and I urge the Minister to enact these recommendations with haste.  It is all well and good that this is going to be sorted out soon.  I note there is no set date yet.  It is still somewhat in the hopefully not-too-distant future, which will bring student nurses and midwives some comfort but it will not help them backdate anything.  Backdated payments are all well and good if you can afford to have a backdated payment.  However, landlords are not going to take backdated rent, Vodafone will not take a backdated bill, and Tesco is not going to take a backdated payment for groceries.  I am sure the Minister of State understands how deeply frustrating this is for students nurses and midwives.  They go in every single day and do their absolute best and they are exhausted.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Annie Hoey:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=AnnieHoey&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->They are wrecked.  The pandemic payment is a small payment and it immensely frustrating for those student nurses and midwives.  My phone is literally hopping in front of me with people asking when they are getting this, on which date and what is happening.  We cannot have stuff backdated all the time.  I hope that this can be sorted very quickly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1614" speakername="Mary Butler" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#D00200"><p>To reiterate, on 26 January 2022, just under a month ago, the Department issued the sanction to the HSE regarding these additional supports and requested that payment be prioritised.  Yesterday the Department was informed by the HSE that it is finalising a memo to be issued to services to provide for payment.  The Department has, once again, emphasised to the HSE the importance of expediting these payments.  The Senator is quite right.  It is exactly as she said.  They are student nurses and they have been guaranteed this payment.  It needs to happen very quickly.</p> <p>In conclusion, I just want to make some additional remarks.  I want to inform the House that the overwhelming majority of student nurses and midwives have availed of the Covid vaccination, which has been a significant contributing factor to ensuring that clinical placements have continued with minimal disruption.  I want to commend all student nurses and midwives in this regard. </p> <p>Second, to ensure that appropriate oversight of support is in place for students, the clinical placement oversight group has remained in place and reports to the chief nursing officer in the Department.  </p> <p>I will again raise the Senator's issue.  We are nearly there but nearly is not good enough.  They need their back money and I do appreciate that.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.15" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#D00250">Hospital Services</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#D00300"><p>It is always a pleasure to have the Minister of State, Deputy Butler in the House.  I am raising this matter about the adult metabolic services at the Mater hospital in Dublin.  I am sure the Minister of State is aware of the importance of the work that this unit does.</p> <p>However, it is, unfortunately, significantly under-resourced.  There are much-needed resources required for this unit to operate at a reasonable capacity.  At the moment, it is not operating to its capacity at all.  It certainly is not reaching its potential and, sadly, it is not reaching the potential that it could achieve for the patients who are suffering.  I am thinking particularly of the patients who are diagnosed with phenylketonuria, PKU.  I am sure the Minister of State is aware of how debilitating PKU can be.</p> <p>From birth, many children who are diagnosed with PKU find that their eating habits have to be completely altered.  They are isolated from their peers even when they go away on school tours, trips away and so on.  They have to have a special diet because of their condition.  This continues into adulthood.  A friend of mine has it and it is a daily struggle in terms of just putting together a diet that one would feel satisfied with and one would feel they are fulfilling the best they can in life.  That is a huge strain on people.  It is a huge strain on people&rsquo;s mental and physical health.</p> <p>We have, as a society, a responsibility to do all that we can to support these people who are a small minority of our population.  Yet, Ireland has double the European average of people who suffer from PKU.  Many medicines are being trialled but, unfortunately, they are not being trialled on adults because the resources are not there and the expertise is not in place at the Mater to do so.  I am thinking, particularly, of a drug called Kuvan.  Perhaps the Minister of State is aware of this drug.  It is a new drug and it is believed it can revolutionise the lives of people who have PKU.  However, it is no good to people in Ireland who are suffering from PKU because the drug is not being trialled at the Mater hospital.</p> <p>Kuvan is just one drug.  I believe there is much research internationally being done on PKU.  There are many drugs at pretrial and trial stage in other countries.  However, we are a long way down the line from ever being able to trial those drugs in this country.  </p> <p>PKU sufferers are citizens of this country as well.  They pay their taxes the same as the rest of us.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Martin Conway:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2347"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2347&amp;amp;pid=MartinConway&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->They are citizens and they have the same right to access to proper, decent healthcare and the potential to have access to new medicines that can and would transform their lives.  We have spent a great deal of money on health over the past number of years for the good reason that we were in a pandemic.  The spend on health in this country has increased year-on-year dating back over the past ten years.  The health budget is &euro;24 billion.  When &euro;24 billion is being spent on health, all citizens should have a reasonable expectation that they are going to benefit from it.  This unit in the Mater hospital needs investment.  It needs to be tooled up and resourced so that people who are suffering from PKU will have the same access as their European counterparts to ground-breaking medicines that will change their lives.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1614" speakername="Mary Butler" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#E00200"><p>I thank the Senator for the opportunity to address the House on this important matter, which I am taking on behalf of Minister for Health, Deputy Stephen Donnelly.</p> <p>As the Senator will be aware, the Mater Misericordiae University Hospital is the designated site for the National Centre for Inherited Metabolic Disorders for adults.  This centre provides assessment and treatment to adults with inherited metabolic disorders.  It is also responsible for the diagnosis and management of these patients.  Inherited metabolic disorders include a diverse group of rare conditions that can result in significant morbidity and mortality.  Presentation may occur at any age.  With advances in healthcare delivery and new therapeutic interventions an increasing number of affected children whose lifespan previously would have been severely curtailed are now reaching adulthood.</p> <p>The adult metabolic service in the Mater hospital provides multidisciplinary care for patients with metabolic disorders.  These disorders include phenylketonuria, PKU, which the Senator has spoken about, galactosemia and lysosomal disease.  This important service helps patients to manage their conditions with optimal diets that match their metabolic needs.  The HSE has informed me that current staffing in this important service at the Mater hospital is 12.5 whole-time equivalents.  This team includes consultants, non-consultant hospital doctors, nursing staff, dieticians, a medical social worker, a psychologist and administration staff.  Currently, approximately 900 adult patients attend the metabolic service at the Mater hospital.  It is anticipated that will increase by at least 100 additional patients per annum over the next five years.  These additional patients will include transition patients from the paediatric services located in Children's Health Ireland, CHI, at Temple Street.  In addition to the above, the centre tests patients' responses to therapies for PKU treatment.</p> <p>Since August 2019, newborns diagnosed with PKU have been tested in CHI at Temple Street and treated, when responsive, with Kuvan.  There are also a number of patients with known dietary requirements who have been trialled on this medication.  Once a child is placed on Kuvan, this treatment is expected to be lifelong.  To date, access to Kuvan has not been available for PKU adults attending the centre at the Mater hospital, other than for three patients who received ongoing approval following an earlier phase 3 clinical trial extension. </p> <p>I have some good news for the Senator.  I have been informed that the HSE and the Mater hospital have now agreed appropriate funding levels for 15.6 whole-time equivalent staff and the Mater hospital is commencing this recruitment process.  With this resource in place, the centre at the Mater hospital will begin to expand the service to meet current and future requirements.  This resource will also support provision of Kuvan trialling and monitoring for appropriate patients with PKU.  I am assured that the HSE and the Ireland East Hospital Group remain committed to the progressive development of metabolic services at the Mater hospital and to improving this service for patients of the Ireland east region.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#E00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State for the comprehensive update.  It is very positive news.  I sincerely hope that the recruitment of the additional three or four whole-time equivalents happens and that it does not fall into the HSE ambitious plans for recruitment that does not happen.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Martin Conway:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2347"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2347&amp;amp;pid=MartinConway&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This is specialised and critical and I imagine it will have to be an international recruitment process.  The reason people want adults to avail of Kuvan, in particular, relates to the fact they have seen its success with children and the difference it makes.  The adults the Minister of State mentioned who are continuing to use it in their lives following the trial have benefited from it.</p><p>Given there are clear benefits and the results speak for themselves, it is essential that this happens.  I sincerely hope the recruitment will happen in 2022, with Kuvan rolled out this year also.  The Minister of State might stress to the HSE, perhaps even in writing to the chief executive, the need to put this on the priority recruitment radar, even above and beyond other recruitment, in order that it will be made a top priority of the HSE.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1614" speakername="Mary Butler" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#F00200"><p>The Senator is absolutely correct.  As he will have heard in my earlier response, it is anticipated the number of patients presenting will increase by at least 100 per annum over the next five years, so we have to build capacity.  There are currently 12.5 whole-time equivalents in the adult metabolic service at the Mater hospital and that figure will increase to 15.6, or an additional three posts.  That is welcome and recruitment should be commenced as a matter of priority.</p> <p>The recruitment of the additional staff agreed between the hospital and the HSE will enable the service to expand to meet future requirements, including the provision of Kuvan trialling and monitoring for appropriate patients with PKU.  As I said earlier, children who are put on the drug remain on it, but it is not as accessible for some adults.  I will certainly convey the Senator's concerns to the Minister for Health and I thank him for raising the issue.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.22" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#F00300">Health Services</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1695" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#F00400"><p>I thank the Minister of State for appearing before the House to discuss this important topic.  I seek an update on the progress of the roll-out of the programme on women's health announced in budget 2022.  Budget 2022 included a number of announcements relating to women's health, one of which involved the provision of free contraceptives for 18 to 25-year-olds.  It is my understanding this is due to happen from August.  A survey carried out by Plan International Ireland has found that many females have decided they are going to avail of the offer.  Will it begin in August?  Will someone who is almost 26 years old be cut off when they turn 26 or can they continue for a year or two?</p> <p>A total of &euro;10 million of the funding will be used to address period poverty.  One survey has found that many females aged between 12 and 19 have found the cost of sanitary products to be very difficult.  Some public buildings have started to provide free sanitary products, as have some local authorities.  Similarly, in Scotland and New Zealand, free period products are offered to all those who need them.  Who will be in charge of the programme in Ireland and will we be able to match what is being done in Scotland and New Zealand, for example?  What will be the nature of the roll-out in schools, universities and colleges?</p> <p>There was also an announcement relating to the funding of four menopause clinics, a really important area.  The first one has opened, in Dublin.  Will the other three be spread out among the regions or will they all be Dublin based?<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Maria Byrne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2465"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2465&amp;amp;pid=MariaByrne&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->For example, will there be one in Munster and another in Connacht?  It is important that there be a regional spread.</p><p>Will the Minister of State update the House on the gynaecological model of care?  It ties in with the menopause clinics and is part of the maternity strategy.</p><p>Significant emphasis was placed on endometriosis.  Will the Minister of State provide an update in that regard?  I look forward to hearing from her.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1614" speakername="Mary Butler" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#G00200"><p>I thank the Senator for the opportunity to speak to the House on the important topic of building a more positive outlook for women's health.  That this Oireachtas has finally placed such an emphasis on women's health is a positive outcome.  It is great to hear the different voices in both Houses all supporting one another.</p> <p>My Department is committed to improving women's health.  Since the establishment of the women's health task force in 2019, we have engaged with women all over Ireland.  We have listened to what they want from their health service and we have taken a number of positive steps to improve women's experiences of healthcare and health outcomes.  We are building supports for tackling period poverty.  The Government has supported the Free Provision of Period Products Bill 2021, taking into account the recommendations of the period poverty in Ireland discussion paper.  A cross-governmental period poverty implementation group is co-ordinating the development of interventions recommended in the programme for Government, the discussion paper and the Bill.  More than &euro;700,000 has been allocated to my Department in 2022 for initial period poverty measures.  I hope to have more detail on the Senator's question about schools and universities soon.  I would be happy to return to the House and update it on the matter.  We are currently working on HSE-led initiatives for members of the Traveller and Roma communities in the south east as well as projects in collaboration with local authorities, for which the majority have already submitted expressions of interest.  We are reaching out to the voluntary sector, including food banks, to support as many people as possible.</p> <p>Following up on the programme for Government commitment, we are preparing to introduce free contraception for women, starting with 17-to-25-year-olds.  Funding of &euro;9 million has been allocated for 2022.  The scheme will provide the cost of prescription contraception, two GP consultations per year and fitting, removal and check-ups for long-acting reversible contraceptives; and additional training and certification for medical professionals to fit and remove long-acting reversible contraceptives.  Contraceptive options will include contraceptive injections, implants, coils, the patch and ring, and various forms of oral contraceptive pill, including emergency contraception.  As such, it will not be limited to oral contraceptives only.  Expanding the scheme to further age cohorts can be considered once we have had a chance to monitor and evaluate the 17-to-25-year-old scheme and ensure that it is working smoothly.</p> <p>We anticipate significant progress with the roll-out of a number of specialist menopause clinics this year.  In 2021, a specialist menopause clinic was established under the governance of the National Maternity Hospital, the first publicly funded clinic of its kind.  Budget 2022 provided the necessary funding to enable the roll-out of an additional three specialist menopause clinics.  As to the Senator's question on whether they will all be Dublin based, she will be delighted to learn that they will not be.  There will be one in Galway, one in Cork and one in Limerick.  The three new menopause clinics being established in 2022 will be part of the maternity networks in the South/South West, University Limerick and Saolta hospital groups.  This provides a good catchment area around the country.  As I understand it, the operationalisation of the new clinics will be dependent on resourcing the necessary staff.  In this regard, the HSE's national women and infants health programme has advised that the engagement with the relevant hospital groups is progressing as planned.</p> <p>Across each of the issues raised under this Commencement matter - period poverty, contraception and menopause - we are committed to progressing the agenda and advancing women's health experiences and outcomes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1695" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#G00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State for that positive response.  It is great to know that the programme is on course to deliver within the timeframe.</p> <p>Regarding my first question, I am still unsure as to whether the free contraception programme will start in August.  I assume from the Minister of State's answer that it will.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Maria Byrne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2465"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2465&amp;amp;pid=MariaByrne&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The fact that it is to be reviewed for an older cohort once it is up and running is very welcome.</p><p>I am delighted that University Maternity Hospital Limerick has also been included in the clinics.  This is very welcome news.  I thank the Minister of State and the Department for their commitment to women's health.  It is an area that has been forgotten for a long time so it is very welcome news.</p><p>The Minister of State also spoke about the inclusion of food banks.  There are people in poverty who go to the Society of St. Vincent de Paul and such places.  It is important that there is engagement with those places regarding the provision of products.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1614" speakername="Mary Butler" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#H00200"><p>I thank the Senator very much.  I agree with her; that is why the food banks were mentioned.  Like she said, the likes of the Society of St. Vincent de Paul are important.</p> <p>My understanding is that free contraception will commence in August as planned.</p> <p>I will touch on one point that was not raised but that comes under my remit, which is perinatal mental health supports.  We currently have six main hubs across the country.  All 13 spoke sites now have mental health midwives in place under the model of care for specialist perinatal mental health services for women before, during and after their pregnancy.  Sometimes people can have mental health difficulties and to have those 19 perinatal mental health midwives in place throughout whole country is really positive.</p> <p>We have been have been actively progressing a commitment for &euro;31 million in additional funding for women's health in budget 2022.  In the coming weeks, we will launch the women's health action plan for 2022-23 setting out the actions that will realise the investment.</p> <p>I thank the Senator and other women Members of both Houses for raising their voices on women's health.  It is very timely and great to see.  It is great to have the Minister, Deputy Donnelly, support all our calls and have our voices heard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#H00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  We certainly echo that.  It is wonderful to see such investment in women's health.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.30" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#H00400">Environmental Schemes</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1652" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#H00500"><p>I just met the Minister of State outside the Chamber.  It is a benefit of arriving early, which does not happen too often.  I had a good conversation with him and he was very informative and helpful in providing information regarding this Commencement matter.  He has probably alleviated most of my concerns or at least answered many of them.</p> <p>A massive scheme was announced last week.  The headlines can be misleading at times and there are different issues to be explained with regard to the grants available.  I ask the Minister of State to refresh me on a few of the points we discussed outside the Chamber.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#H00600"><p>That was a very short contribution.  The Senator does not mince his words.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1652" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#H00700"><p>The Minister of State has given me a personalised answer already, in fairness to him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1479" speakername="Ossian Smyth" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#H00800"><p>It is important that I put everything on the record as well having a chat.</p> <p>I thank Senator Davitt very much for raising this issue and giving me a timely opportunity to give an update on the Government's support for home retrofit.  The programme for Government and climate action plan set targets to reduce greenhouse gas emissions from the residential sector from 7 megatons of carbon dioxide in 2018 to between 3.5 megatons and 4.5 megatons in 2030.  A comprehensive retrofit programme will be a key measure to support the achievement of this target.</p> <p>We will need to retrofit the equivalent of 500,000 homes to a building energy rating of B2 and undertake the installation of 400,000 heat pumps in existing homes to replace older, less efficient heating systems by the end of 2030.  This represents approximately 30% of the housing stock and is among the most ambitious retrofitting programmes in the world.</p> <p>The national retrofit plan was published last November as part of the climate action plan 2021 and sets out how the Government will deliver these targets.  The plan is designed to address barriers to retrofit across four key pillars.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Ossian Smyth:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=OssianSmyth&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->First is driving demand and activity, second is financing and funding, third is supply chain skills and standards and fourth is governance.</p><p>Recognising that the achievement of our climate action plan targets will require a step change in the pace and scale of delivery of Ireland&rsquo;s residential retrofit programme, the Government has approved a package of supports to make it easier and more affordable for homeowners to undertake home energy upgrades to create warmer, healthier and more comfortable homes, with lower energy bills.  The key measures include: first, a new national home energy upgrade scheme, providing increased grant levels of up to 50% of the cost of a typical deep retrofit to a B2 building energy rating, BER, standard.  That is up from 30% to 35% of grants that were available.  There are a significantly increased number of free energy upgrades for those who are at risk of energy poverty.  That is up to &euro;400 per month, from an average of &euro;177 per month in 2021.  There is a special enhanced grant rate, which is equivalent to 80% of the typical cost for attic and cavity wall insulation for all households.  That is to urgently reduce energy use as part of the Government's response to current exceptionally high energy prices.</p><p>The new initiatives will be funded by the unprecedented national development plan financial allocation for residential retrofit.  That is &euro;8 billion available up to 2030.  More than 60% of this funding, &euro;5 billion, will be sourced from carbon tax revenue.  A total of &euro;267 million has been allocated for the Sustainable Energy Authority of Ireland's residential and community schemes and the solar photovoltaic scheme in 2022.  This is the highest ever allocation for the schemes.  The investment this year would support almost 27,000 home energy upgrades, including over 8,600 homes, to a building energy rating of B2.  This is a near doubling of the number of homes delivered to B2 in 2021.  In addition, &euro;85 million funding has been provided by the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage, Deputy Darragh O&rsquo;Brien, for the local authority energy efficiency retrofit programme.  This means that of the total Government retrofit budget of &euro;352 million, 58%, or &euro;203 million, will be spent on dedicated energy poverty schemes and local authority retrofits.</p><p>Regarding wood pellet burners, a marginal abatement cost curve was developed as part of the climate action plan.  That was to provide a solid, analytical foundation on the most cost-effective pathway to reduce emissions in line with Ireland&rsquo;s decarbonisation targets.  In using Ireland&rsquo;s 2018 greenhouse gas emissions projections to 2035, associated projections of economic activity and assessments across 300 business cases for technology, the analysis identifies the technologies, including fuel switches and the associated levels of adoption that are required to meet our 2030 targets in the most economical way.  Our national target of 400,000 heat pumps was derived from this analysis, and Government funding and incentives are aligned with this policy objective, as opposed to other heating systems, such as wood pellet burners, which do not have national targets.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1652" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#J00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  The rising cost of electricity is probably the biggest concern, especially with some of the retrofit innovation.  Heat pumps are probably our largest concern.  They are so tied to the ESB.  This is particularly the case when we cannot feed power back onto the grid.  We are doing so in a very minimal way at present.  That is really an issue.  The sooner that link with ESB is tidied up to be able to feed power back in through the grid, it will be a massive help.  The cost of power when it comes to heat pumps is probably the greatest concern I have in relation to this matter.  I appreciate the Minister of State&rsquo;s answer.  He has been very helpful.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1479" speakername="Ossian Smyth" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#J00300"><p>The Senator rightly identifies that electricity has a key role to play in decarbonisation.  He is right to ask about the refit tariff.  This is the money that is paid to people for selling their electricity back to the grid.  That process is in train as fast as it can be done.  It will be ready within a small number of months.</p> <p>Regarding the deep retrofits, our analysis says that approximately 50% of homes need their attic insulation redone and  that they would get a great return on investment by doing that.  Attic and cavity wall insulation are the two most cost-effective measures.  For somebody who spends &euro;500 on getting their cavity walls and their attic insulated, the Government will pay &euro;2,500 on top of that &euro;500.  That means that they will make back about &euro;300 a year.  It means that their return on investment of &euro;500 down will be made within less than two years.  It is a very good way to save money on electricity bills.  It is worth more per year than the &euro;200 that we are putting in people's accounts on one-off basis.  They will get &euro;300 every year thereafter.  We are very keen that as many people as possible take that up.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Ossian Smyth:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=OssianSmyth&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is a very affordable scheme for people who are not on welfare but are on low pay.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1652" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#K00200"><p>The Minister of State pointed out something to me outside the Chamber that I had not realised from listening to the media which is that this can be done bit by bit.  That can be done without doing other parts of the retrofit.  That is very good.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#K00300"><p>Yes.  When the one-stop-shops are in place it will bring a lot of clarity.  I have suggested that post offices in our communities would be very much involved both in helping with finance and in doing some of the one-stop-shop business as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1479" speakername="Ossian Smyth" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#K00400"><p>An Post has offered a one-stop-shop service.  Electric Ireland is also doing so.  Its service is called Electric Ireland Superhomes.  The credit unions will also offer one.  They are three trustworthy bodies across Ireland and I expect to see others.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.42" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p></p><p></p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.43" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#N00050">An tOrd Gnó - Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#N00100"><p>Before I ask the Leader to outline the Order of Business, I welcome to the Distinguished Visitors' Gallery the Lord Mayor of Cork, Mr. Colm Kelleher, and his son.  We are delighted to have them here today.  Mr. Kelleher informed me that the chain of office he holds is just one year younger than the United States of America, at 245 years old.  I welcome him to the Chamber and am delighted he is with us.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#O00100"><p>The Order of Business is No.1, Online Safety and Media Regulation Bill 2022 - Order for Second Stage and Second Stage, to be taken at 4.45 p.m. and to adjourn at 7 p.m., if not previously concluded, with the opening contribution of the Minister not to exceed ten minutes, group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes and all other Senators not to exceed five minutes, and the Minister to be given no less than ten minutes to reply to the debate; and No. 2, Electricity Costs (Domestic Electricity Accounts) Emergency Measures Bill 2022 - Committee and Remaining Stages, to be taken at 7 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#O00200"><p>I add my voice to the welcome for my esteemed colleague and friend, the Lord Mayor of Cork, Colm Kelleher, and his son.  It is a great pleasure to have them in the Chamber for today's business.</p> <p>Stoyu z ukrayinoyu: stand with Ukraine.  I was on the phone this morning to my esteemed friend and colleague, Yevheniya Kravchuk, who is a Ukrainian parliamentarian, speaking about the current situation in Ukraine.  It is imperative that we condemn the actions of the Russian President, we stand with Ukraine and we demand sanctions.</p> <p>On a lighter note, I thank the Cathaoirleach for his very warm welcome to Athy Sing and Sign Club.  They are an incredible group of young people, led by the inspirational Maggie Owens, who has a super choir that signs everything they sing.  They came to Leinster House this morning and signed the national anthem for the Cathaoirleach.  It is wonderful when we see innovative people and communities like this throughout country and we need to celebrate them.  It just happens this group is from Kildare, but they are very appreciative of the Irish Sign Language Act that was brought through the House.</p> <p>I will also raise the issue of affiliation to the Irish Congress of Trade Unions, ICTU, for the Defence Forces.  I understand the reason my Commencement matter on the issue was ruled out of order, but I will very briefly raise it now.  In essence, we know public pay policy is set by the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform and the public services committee of ICTU, but PDFORRA and other Defence Forces personnel cannot influence this because they are not members of ICTU.  It is simply wrong that while members of the Defence Forces are currently beneficiaries of the public sector pay determination process, they are, in fact, precluded from participating in any meaningful way because their representative bodies are not permitted to affiliate with ICTU.  It is vital they are offered the support of ICTU prior to the commencement of any pay review and this should happen within the next four weeks.</p> <p>Yesterday, I met Caoimhe O'Connor from Newbridge, who is graduating from the special needs assistant, SNA, course in University College Dublin on Thursday.  She reminded me of the meeting I attended of the north Leinster branch of F&oacute;rsa union representatives, who were very clear in their demands for respect for the SNA campaign.  It is very important that SNAs, especially those who have done this particular course, receive the appropriate accreditation and that they have a more professional qualification at Quality and Qualifications Ireland level 6, which would increase the standing of SNAs in the school system and secure proper recognition for their work.  I am happy to say I will have a meeting with the Minister for Education, Deputy Foley, on this and other educational issues tomorrow, but this has to be a priority.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#O00300"><p>On behalf of the Fine Gael group, I accept the Order of Business.  I also join with colleagues in welcoming Lord Mayor Kelleher and his son to the Chamber.  It is a very prestigious position to be Lord Mayor of Cork, our second city.  I wish him well during his trip to Dublin and for the course of this very important year.</p> <p>The Cabinet is today approving the disbandment of the National Public Health Emergency Team, NPHET, and the removal of most remaining public health measures, including the wearing of masks.  It is appropriate this House sends a very clear "Thank you" to NPHET, Dr. Tony Holohan and Dr. Ronan Glynn for the outstanding work they did during this pandemic.  From the very start and the very first press conference, right through to now, their communication skills have been outstanding.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Martin Conway:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2347"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2347&amp;amp;pid=MartinConway&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->They were conservative in their approach but that approach saved many thousands of lives.  It is also appropriate to thank the people who support them.  We think of Paul Reid and Damien McCallion and the team at the HSE.</p><p>They did not get everything right but nobody gets everything right.  In the fullness of time, lessons will be learned for future pandemics from what we achieved and did not achieve during this pandemic.  The critical point is that everybody proceeded with the best of intentions and the ultimate goal of protecting public health and saving the lives of our citizens.  They did a damn good job.  On behalf of this House, I propose that the Leader send a letter to Dr. Glynn, Dr. Holohan and the HSE and its management team.</p><p>I pay particular tribute to public health mid-west in my area.  One looks at Dr. Favier and people like her and the manner in which they went on local and national radio.  They were very clear, distinct and articulate in selling the necessity to abide by the public health measures.  At a local level, I acknowledge the great work done by public health mid-west, not just during the pandemic but prior to it.  I know that work will continue post pandemic.</p><p>It has come to my attention that the blind and visually-impaired students who are doing the leaving certificate this year will not have access to digital examination papers.  Modern technology - iPads, computers and sign readers - has done such wonders for visually-impaired young people in terms of being able to communicate, do their business and study for their examinations.  I remember when I, as a visually-impaired person, did my leaving certificate 30 years ago.  Despite what is available now and the opportunity technology provides, the Department of Education is still so antiquated that it does not provide examination papers in digital form.  I would like the Leader to bring this matter to the attention of the Minister for Health.  Perhaps the House will have a discussion on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1645" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#P00200"><p>I first want to remark on the fact that representatives of the Uyghur community were in Leinster House today.  It is a testament to the Seanad that we are not afraid to recognise and bring into the House people from any community anywhere in the world who are being subjected to horrendous treatment.  I also welcome the Lord Mayor of Cork.  It is always a pleasure to see him in the House.</p> <p>I know the Leader has an interest in issues relating to aviation.  She must be aware of the change in the law that took effect on 1 January as a result of a European directive on security clearance for people working at airports.  The Garda vetting system is breaking down.  Employers do not know who to contact.  They do not know how to expedite for clearance people who are brought in to work.  We presume, although we do not know, that the clearance procedure involves investigating the backgrounds of family members, as well as the individual concerned.  There is some suggestion that people coming from overseas can be Garda vetted much faster than indigenous Irish people.  We need to look into this fairly urgently.</p> <p>There is much talk about Ireland's seat on the United Nations Security Council and how we won it.  According to an article in one of today's newspapers, we won it with 945 pairs of socks and with umbrellas, badges and notebooks.  Some &euro;125,000 of our hard-earned taxes were used to bring on side the diplomats who would be voting.  It is repugnant to everything the United Nations stands for that these annual competitions should take place for a seat that rotates every 20 years in any event.  There is something terribly wrong, in a world that is full of inequality and hungry, about us throwing out socks, umbrellas and fancy notebooks in order to win a seat on the United Nations Security Council.  It is horrendous.</p> <p>I will move swiftly along to Ukraine and what is happening there today.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Gerard P. Craughwell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2402"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2402&amp;amp;pid=GerardPCraughwell&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->On Mr. Putin's suggestion that he would move into eastern Ukraine in a peacekeeping role, there is only one organisation in this world that can decide on peacekeeping and that is the United Nations.  If Mr. Putin is that afraid of the possibilities of problems in eastern Ukraine, what he needs to do is to bring it to the United Nations Security Council and let it pick a peacekeeping nation that will look after the needs of the people in eastern Ukraine.</p><p>I have been engaging with the Ukrainian ambassador and her staff over the past few days.  My heart goes out to them today.  They are miles from home and at the end of the day, they have no idea what will happen over the next 24 or 48 hours.  We saw that in the incursions into Georgia, there was absolutely no support.  We cannot allow that to happen in Ukraine.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1667" speakername="Vincent P Martin" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#Q00200"><p>Since the Seanad last sat, we learned the sad news of the passing of a fellow parliamentarian on the island.  On behalf of the Green Party-Comhaontas Glas, I convey my deepest sympathies to the family, friends and the DUP on the sudden loss of Christopher Stalford, who represented the people of South Belfast since 2016 and had been the Assembly's Principal Deputy Speaker since 2020.  Ar dheis D&eacute; go raibh a anam.</p> <p>Like previous speakers, the Green Party is appalled by the developments in Ukraine, and the aggression.  The Russians are not only recognising but are occupying the two eastern provinces in Ukraine.  It is in flagrant breach of international law and the Minsk agreements and is a wholesale assault on the sovereign integrity and the territory of Ukraine.  It is a matter to which this House perhaps should devote a separate debate.  Last week, we celebrated 100 years and one thing that was said is that we can play an advisory role to the Government.  We can think differently.</p> <p>Maybe in a debate, Ireland, which has a good solid reputation, could in a most difficult situation pave some small way forward.  At such a debate, I would why Ireland is not one of the following eight EU member states which have signed a declaration on the EU membership perspective for Ukraine, namely, Lithuania, Estonia, Latvia, the Slovak Republic, Poland, Croatia, Slovenia and Bulgaria.  I believe the Czech Republic and Romania are due to give that support.  It is a complex and challenging matter applying to be a member of the EU.  I would like an explanation.  There may be a reason for it.  There are other countries conspicuous by their absence from that support.  We talk the talk but when Ukraine wanted to come into the EU, which is such a difficult task, Ireland with its credibility was not leading the way.</p> <p>Also, we have learned from the peace process here.  Despite a long-term occupation on the island, it did not stop peace.  It did not stop the silencing of the guns.  Have we something to offer our fellow European neighbours here as we face the worst outbreak potentially of bloodshed and war since the Second World War?  Could we nudge some great peacemakers, like them or not, such as former Taoiseach, Bertie Ahern, Gerry Adams, Lord David Trimble, a Nobel Peace Prize winner, Ms Monica McWilliams, and Liz O'Donnell?  If they were asked, they would bring our credibility and experiences.  It is a precious peace, albeit not a perfect peace, on the island of Ireland but maybe we can bring something to at least trigger bilateral talks, which, according to what I am reading, do not seem to even be happening at present.  There is no sign of bilateral talks.  I note both parties might be reluctant to enter bilateral talks but as a catalyst, even if it is behind the scenes, Ireland, as a credible country, has something to offer on its own peace journey.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1688" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#Q00300"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh Ardmh&eacute;ara Chorcaigh agus a mhac at&aacute; linn inniu fosta.  I welcome the lord mayor to the Chamber.</p> <p>I echo the sentiments of Senator Martin in relation to the very sudden and very sad death of Christopher Stalford, MLA.  I have known Christopher for a long time.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2477"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2477&amp;amp;pid=NiallODonnghaile&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We were on Belfast City Council together.  We travelled on a number of international delegations to the United States, in his role as chair of the development committee and my role as ardmh&eacute;ara in Belfast.  I knew Christopher before that, perhaps not in the same personal sense but certainly in a political sense, as he would often turn up at events wearing Union Jack socks and a pinstripe suit.  One thing you could never take away from Christopher was his commitment to his unionist and, he would say, conservative views and the very articulate and passionate way that he advocated them.  He and I had many disagreements on political issues relating to Ireland but also more broadly.  I have to say, however, that I always found him a great character and a great wit.  After a robust debate, I could join him for a cup of coffee or, dare I say it, even the odd pint, to have a really respectful conversation.</p><p>One thing that struck me in later years with Christopher was the real love and commitment he had for his wife Laura and their four children.  They are first and foremost in all of our thoughts.  Christopher's death is a big loss to them, his broader family, his DUP family and his constituents in south Belfast.  On my behalf and on behalf of the Sinn F&eacute;in group and, I am sure, colleagues across the House, I extend deepest sympathies to Laura and Christopher's children.</p><p>I might return to this matter given the limited time I have available to me but the Leader will have seen coverage of our neighbour, the National Gallery, whose staff and a number of artists have taken issue with the award of a particular contract.  I sense your eyes on me, a Chathaoirligh, so I will not go into the specifics around contractual and procurement issues.  Nevertheless, the best artists are those who hold a mirror up to society and challenge some of its worst elements.  Direct provision remains a real issue and a problem and concern for many people across society.  I hope to return to the issue, but in light of what has been said in the public domain in recent weeks about the National Gallery, it is timely for the Minister for Children, Equality, Disability, Integration and Youth, Deputy O'Gorman, to come to the House to discuss the programme for Government commitment to end direct provision and to give an update on that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1683" speakername="Marie Sherlock" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#R00200"><p>I very much welcome Lord Mayor Kelleher and his son to the Chamber.  I also extend deepest sympathies, on behalf of the Labour Party Senators, to the Stalford family on the loss of Christopher.  It is a shocking time for the DUP and the wider unionist family but there was shock right across the island of Ireland in recent days when people learned of his passing.</p> <p>The Continent of Europe has entered a very dark period with the events in Ukraine in recent days.  I express my solidarity with all the people of Ukraine.  While the news of the package of sanctions is very welcome and the detail is eagerly awaited, we need to hear a very strong message from the Government about supporting the sanctions.  Ireland is a net exporter to Russia, but we rely hugely on fossil fuel imports from Russia.  We must be seen to be very strong in backing the sanctions against Russia at this point following its acts of aggression against its neighbour, Ukraine.</p> <p>The main issue I wish to raise today relates to the announcement yesterday of the postponement of the citizens' assembly on drug use until 2023.  This flies directly in the face of the Taoiseach's commitment on the floor of the D&aacute;il just two weeks ago.  It runs contrary also to what he said in the Fergus McCabe lecture last year.  We must have an open, honest and detailed conversation about drug addiction and drug use in this country.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Marie Sherlock:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=MarieSherlock&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->People's lives, their communities and their families depend on that conversation.  As my colleague, Deputy Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in, who spent many years campaigning on these issues, said, lives are going to be lost.  Ireland has one of the highest rates of lives lost to drug overdoses when compared to every other EU member state.  In 2017 alone <b>377</b>people lost their lives due to a drug overdose.  Many were concentrated in some of the most deprived and disadvantaged parts of this country.  It is, however, important to say this is an issue affecting all of Ireland.  It is not just confined to Dublin, Cork or Limerick or the main urban centres.<br/><br/>There is much anger and frustration at the Minister of State, Deputy Feighan.  We had tried to work constructively with the Minister of State, Deputy Feighan, on the drugs issue since he took up his position but we now need to hear from people more senior than him, namely, the Taoiseach and the Minister for Health, what they are going to do about drugs policy in this country.  If there is going to be a citizens' assembly on drugs in 2023 - we are told it is going to happen then but it may not - it will be 2024 before the Government can even begin to consider the recommendations.  Are we really going to have a Government make sensitive and difficult decisions a year or months out from a general election?  There is a very serious question mark over all that but the key issue is that we need to hear from the Taoiseach and the Minister for Health what their plans are with regard to drugs policy in this country because lives depend on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1657" speakername="Eileen Flynn" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#S00200"><p>We support the call for the Minister, Deputy O'Gorman, to come into the House to have a debate about where we are on ending direct provision.  Too often I come into this House and speak about the people we are leaving behind.  On 28 February we are leaving behind our most vulnerable people.  We are leaving behind people in our society with long-term health issues and who will now be living in fear, without the protection of mask wearing.  It is something we need to look at.  We are forgetting about people who have COPD.  I have COPD and I am anxious about people sitting beside me not wearing a mask.  I was on the bus yesterday coming from Donegal and I put my bags beside me because I was not comfortable.  There are many people in the world, especially in Ireland, who are not comfortable, including wheelchair users, people who have cystic fibrosis or other major underlying health issues already.  Unfortunately, this Government has failed to listen to those people and to our elderly people.  It is extremely sad.</p> <p>Last week I met with people from the Respect for SNAs campaign.  The scheme for qualification has not been changed since 1979.  That was more than 43 years ago and we have not looked at changing the scheme.  The Department wants to look at the contracts of SNAs before it looks at the qualifications of SNAs.  I am a qualified SNA and I have a FETAC level 5 qualification.  We might say it is only an SNA.  That is a load of crap.  I am sorry, a Chathaoirligh, but an SNA is more than just an SNA.  We go into classrooms and we are caregivers and educators.  That needs to be respected and recognised and, most important, it needs to be valued.  If we are all serious about giving every child equality of opportunity to be successful within our education system, we need to be serious in supporting that success by supporting our SNAs.</p> <p>The review group is looking at having an expert group to look at the qualifications of an SNA.  I support the setting up of that group as soon as possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1638" speakername="Malcolm Byrne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#S00300"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach for welcoming the representatives of the Uyghur World Congress and colleagues who attended the meeting to hear about the ongoing abuse of human rights in China.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Martin Conway:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2347"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2347&amp;amp;pid=MartinConway&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> Since we last met and with the storms, we in Wexford lost a very valued employee of Wexford County Council, Mr. Billy Kinsella, who sadly died while out serving his community.  He was working hard on behalf of the people his community.  I hope Members would join with me in extending sympathy to his wife Rita, their son Conor and, indeed, his family, friends and Wexford County Council, generally, on that loss. </p><p>I, too, want to raise the question of what is happening in Ukraine.  We have previously talked in this House about an increasingly authoritarian Russia and the approach that it has taken.  Russia has now violated the sovereignty of an independent state.  This is a defining moment now for Europe.  Colleagues have spoken as well about how the sanctions we need to see at European level need to be strong.  I believe that every Russian oligarch and their family should be stripped of any EU visa in order to send the message very clearly home to Vladimir Putin.  Certainly, there have been calls that UEFA should withdraw the Champions League final from St. Petersburg.  We should in no way allow the Russians to host such an event.  </p><p>A message needs to go out very strongly from these Houses, that we stand very much in solidarity with the people of Ukraine.  Also, I believe that there are a number of political parties and representatives from this island who have been ambivalent in their attitudes towards Russian aggression and we need to call those out.  It has to be very clear that we will no longer tolerate this.  We have seen two of our MEPs, Mick Wallace, MEP, and Clare Daly, MEP, who, quite frankly, are nothing more than Putin&rsquo;s sock puppets parroting the line of the Kremlin.  Those political representatives who have supported Russia over this time need to be called out.  I would hope that our Government would continue to do so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1648" speakername="Emer Currie" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#T00200"><p>I, too, want to extend my sincere condolences to the family of Christopher Stalford, MLA.  It is an incredibly sad time for his family - his wife Laura and their four children, the DUP family and the entire political family in the North.  Our thoughts and sympathies are with them today and this week.</p> <p>I want to reflect on the announcement yesterday about the connected hubs in relation to the launch of a mobile app where people can locate a local hub that they can work from.  There is a network of more than 200 hubs that they can choose to work from, a campaign to generate awareness of that and &euro;5 million to enhance the services.  This is about making remote working a more realistic proposition into the long term and providing the community infrastructure to support it.  Some &euro;100 million has been put into making that happen in communities.  We are addressing the barriers along the way.  This is change in motion.  One of the things the Minister for Rural and Community Development, Deputy Humphreys rightly pointed out yesterday was the need for this to be affordable for people.  She is looking at ways to do that.  Anchor tenancies are a way to do that as well, in terms of bringing in an employee to work on a long-term basis and multiple employees and employers setting up those arrangements.</p> <p>It is not just the Department that can help, it is also Revenue.  We have a remote working tax relief, but that tax relief seems to be only for employers, which can pay their employees &euro;3.20 per day tax-free to work from home.  That should immediately be available for people to work in hubs.  The community gets more from people who will be working as well as spending in the community.  We should be looking at reduced VAT rate for people who are paying it for themselves.  We need to invest in hubs in general to make them affordable and accessible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#T00300"><p>Ireland has always been at the forefront of speaking up for those who have been oppressed.  We recognise the interconnectivity of the countries of Europe and the world at large and that injustice anywhere is a threat to justice everywhere.  We have had calls in this House to address serious human rights abuses occurring in all places over the world, from China in the East, to here in the West, and addressing the issues in our own country as well.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Sharon Keogan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=SharonKeogan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I find it odd that we have heard nothing of the well publicised, high profile, peaceful protest that is being violently suppressed and dispersed by armed government forces.  Ranks of uniformed and armoured military figures, stripped of their badges and identification tags, converged on protestors, an officer on horseback trampled over a disabled woman, approximately 200 arrests were made and over 60 vehicles were seized by the state.  This sounds like something we would hear about in regard to Russia or actions which we would condemn in Hungary or Poland but instead this is happening in the supposedly liberal democracy of Canada and no condemnation has been forthcoming.  </p><p>To legally permit the level of force, Prime Minister Trudeau invoked the Emergencies Act 1988, the first time this Act has been evoked since it replaced the War Measures Act 1914.  Not being satisfied with merely dispersing protestors, the state froze the finances associated with certain individuals and companies believed to be involved in the protests.  These are people who committed no crime and have not been convicted lawfully in court but who the Government decided to punish because they might have been connected with a protest that was inconvenient to the government.  It was an unprecedented act by the state against its citizens, which should be roundly condemned. </p><p>I call on the Leader to write to the Canadian ambassador, H.E. Ms Nancy Smyth, condemning the excessive force used by the government on the overreach that is happening there to its citizens.  Authoritarianism is a threat to democracy no matter whose foot the boot is on.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#U00200"><p>Senator Currie spoke about the remote working hubs, how important they are and the recent Government announcement regarding extra funding for those hubs, which is very welcome.  They are going to be very important to all parts of the country, particularly rural Ireland.  There are approximately 200 hubs in place, with a plan to increase that number to over 400 within the next two years.  That is really good news.</p> <p>The other good news is the announcement today by the Government of &euro;7 million in support for the pig industry.  There are 8,500 people employed in that industry.  Not that long ago, pig farmers were doing very well but now they have hit on hard times.  I welcome that the Minister and the Government have stepped in again.  There are 1.6 million pigs, 300 pig farmers and 8,500 people employed in this industry.  I hope the funding announced by Government will be of assistance to all of those people.  </p> <p>I want now to return to an issue that is discussed here year in, year out, that is, flooding along the River Shannon.  I have been speaking to people who live in the Callows area.  I am told that at this stage thousands of acres are flooded, some of the side roads are blocked such that people have to make round trips or cannot get out and that water levels have risen by almost five inches in the past 48 hours.  We are heading into a crisis there.  I hope that the weather is going to improve somewhat.  It has been horrible over the past number of days, particularly in the west and the midlands.  In that regard, I ask that the Leader would ask the Minister of State, Deputy O'Donovan, who has responsibility for this area to come to the House to update Members on progress made.  This Government and previous Governments have been very committed to flood relief.  A significant amount of money is there but we need an update in regard to where we are going.  I am aware that improvements are being made but this is a really bad time for farmers along the River Shannon.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#U00300"><p>I ask that the Leader and the House would consider issuing an invitation to the Chief Medical Officer, Dr. Tony Holohan, to address Seanad &Eacute;ireann on the occasion of the wind-up of NPHET.  It would be a fitting end to a pandemic that on behalf of the nation, we would afford Dr. Holohan an opportunity to address the Seanad on the handling and management of the pandemic.  As a nation, we owe NPHET a debt of gratitude.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We may not have agreed with everything it said, prescribed or did, but, collectively, we stood up to Covid-19.  The actions of NPHET, its management and its honesty saved thousands of lives.  The state owes the members of NPHET a significant debt of gratitude.  I thank them all most sincerely for the work they did, the sacrifices they made, the decisions they took and, most importantly, the professionalism they showed in their handling and management of the pandemic.</p><p>I join with other Senators in asking for a debate on working from home.  The issue of work hubs is a new dimension and they are important and welcome.  Working from home has brought a new dimension to thousands of people's lives that is to be commended, but it is not for everybody and we cannot lose sight of that fact.  There is an obligation on employers, unions, employees and workers, families, children and all stakeholders in society to have a debate on what working from home should look like, what it will mean and what will be the obligations and responsibilities of employers and other important stakeholders, an issue I will return to another day.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#V00200"><p>I passed by the Ivy restaurant on my way to the House today in order to have a look at its quite extensive menu, which mentions a 12.5% service charge.  It did not mention the price of being a member of a trade union but, thanks to the Labour Court, we now know that price in light of the fact that two very brave young women lost their jobs as a direct result of joining a trade union and of trade union activism.  The 32-page judgment is well worth reading.  It outlines how the case against these two workers was completely fabricated, how cameras in their changing rooms provided footage that was sent directly to management and the appalling victimisation of people just seeking the right to join and be represented by a trade union.</p> <p>It was a good day for workers' rights when the two women got justice got in the court, but the elephant in the room, of course, is that the Ivy restaurant was just implementing accepted policy.  The Restaurants Association of Ireland and the Irish Hotels Federation are absolutely clear that they do not recognise trade unions nor engage in collective bargaining, which is why there is no joint labour committee for hotels that could put a floor of decency back into the sector.  I again reference Dr. Deirdre Curran and the powerful report she compiled just prior to Covid in which she detailed a series of levels of abuse throughout the sector.  They relate not just to breaches of employment rights but also to verbal, psychological and physical abuse of workers.</p> <p>Let us face it: the hospitality sector enjoys considerable lobbying in this Chamber and in the D&aacute;il.  When will this House call on the sector, very simply, to recognise the right to collective bargaining, engage in a joint labour committee process and ensure standards of decency are put back into the sector?  There cannot be more victims like those two brave young women, who just wanted to join a trade union and be represented.  All of us need to stand up.  I ask for an urgent debate on the matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1655" speakername="Timmy Dooley" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#V00300"><p>I might get some clarity from the Cathaoirleach before I make the point I wish to raise.  Our colleague raised the issue of the unrest in Canada and requested he write to the Canadian ambassador.  Before he does that, we should have a full debate in the House and let all sides of that issue be discussed.  My reading of what is going on in Canada is that it is really an extension of Trumpism, whereby a certain group of far-right protestors, using Covid-19 to further a separate agenda, have intimidated journalists and residents of Ottawa.  I have looked on in amazement.  Everyone in the House is entitled to his or her opinion, but I have every faith the Cathaoirleach will not write such a letter on behalf of one particular side.  If a motion is tabled in this House, where we will all have an opportunity to express our opinions, that is fine, and if it is passed, I will accept the will of the House.  Nevertheless, I would like to have a say, if possible, before such a position is reached.</p> <p>The main issue I raise is one I have been aware of for some time but it was brought into stark focus for me this morning, when I received communication from a resident of Clare.  It relates to the delays in certain medical treatments, particularly hormone replacement therapy, HRT.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Timmy Dooley:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2015"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2015&amp;amp;pid=TimDooley&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I have had direct contact with someone who spent seven years just trying to get a diagnosis in the first instance.  After going through all the cost and trauma associated with that, she eventually reached the point where it was accepted that the menopause was the core of the issue.  Now, though, there is an issue with getting the prescribed medicine.  Approximately 32,000 women have faced difficulties in sourcing their HRT medication.  It has been put to me by the woman who contacted me as well as by many others that changing from one medicine to another does not work and has profound impacts on their mental health, given the physical and emotional consequences of same.</p><p>We need to understand why the delays are happening.  Perhaps we need to bring the Minister to the House.  It has been put to me that such delays are not evident in other countries, particularly European ones.  Perhaps the Leader could invite the Minister or a Minister of State from the Department of Health to speak to the House about when the supply chain issue might be resolved for those women who are going through a difficult time as a result of these delays.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#W00200"><p>I believe the Senator was referring to the Leader, who asked about the letter going to the Canadian ambassador.  It is open to any Senator to write to anyone he or she feels appropriate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1670" speakername="John McGahon" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#W00300"><p>Last week, the EU proposed and approved new targets for renewable energy.  We want to hit 40% in the EU by 2030.  That is very ambitious.  Two elements stand out to me where Ireland is concerned.  First, the EU wants to increase the number of cross-border energy connections.  Second, it wants to accelerate the approval process for renewable energy projects like wind farms.  This will be beneficial to Ireland.  The European legislative process has just started and Ireland should use it to look for further funding from the EU to supercharge our wind farm efforts, including offshore.  There is a funding pot for this.  It is called the Trans-European Network for Energy, TEN-E.  Under it, approximately &euro;5 billion can be availed of by EU member states.  It recently updated its criteria.  One criterion is offshore wind.  Recently, the EU placed Ireland in the North Sea offshore grid, NSOG, priority corridor.  Given that the EU is looking at Ireland as a potential wind champion and other member states like Germany and France do not have the same capacity to produce offshore wind energy as we do, this is a good opportunity for Ireland to apply for funding from the EU to supercharge our wind farm plans and concepts.  This might not only allow us to hit our own wind energy targets by 2030, but also to sell excess wind energy to member states that need it.  The Minister for the Environment, Climate and Communications, Deputy Eamon Ryan, has been good in coming to this House multiple times to discuss the range of climate action initiatives that are being worked on.  I am calling for a debate on Ireland's wind strategy at some stage, in particular as it relates to offshore wind energy.  That would be helpful for all Senators.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" speakername="Mark Wall" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#W00400"><p>I will start by thanking the Cathaoirleach for facilitating today's visit by Athy Sing and Sign.  He has been to the fore as regards the Irish Sign Language, ISL.  Athy Sing and Sign has always put it first.  It is a great group led by Ms Maggie Owens along with Ms Linda Dobbyn, Ms Mary Byrne, Ms Breda Moore Flynn and Ms Majella Harris.  Of course, who could forget Mr. Aiden McHugh?  The group promotes ISL at every opportunity and it was great to meet it today.  The Cathaoirleach and the group discussed a number of interesting proposals on progressing ISL <i>vis-&agrave;-vis</i>other sign languages around the world.  I look forward to assisting him in that as it is worked through.  Today's visit was good and appreciated, and I wish to put on the record how proud we in the town of Athy are to have such a group among us.  I congratulate it on the great work it is doing in our community.</p><p>I wish to raise the issue of the lack of GPs.  This is a particular problem in the commuting counties.  I am sure the Leader will have encountered it as well.  I have had representations from Louth, Laois, Carlow, Wicklow and my own county of Kildare.  We have provided housing in certain places and people have come to live and join the communities there, but they cannot find GPs.  It is a major problem in south Kildare in particular.  I have written to the Minister and the HSE.  In its latest reply to me, the HSE stated that it had no role or authority in assigning a GP to a private patient.  Where do we go from here?<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Mark Wall:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=MarkWall&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->These people have young children and are raising young families, and they are driving to Dublin to where their previous GP practices were to avail of services for their sick children.  One can just imagine putting a sick child into a car or whatever in order to get them to a GP in Dublin an hour or an hour and a half away.  It is just not acceptable.</p><p>As I have asked before, we need to have an urgent conversation in that regard and bring the Minister for Health into the Chamber.  With the retirements, etc., of GPs into the future, it is a huge problem for commuting counties and for rural Ireland.  We need a debate on it urgently.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1661" speakername="Pippa Hackett" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#X00200"><p>Yesterday, Offaly County Council was pushed to provide safe houses for victims of domestic violence.  It was asked to do so out of its housing allocation as a matter of urgency but the council's response was that it needed more time.  I understand anyone's plea for more time but when we face a crisis, time is often something of which we have little.</p> <p>Recently, I met with Offaly Domestic Violence Support Services and it is obvious that victims do not have any more time.  They cannot wait; this cannot wait.  People in these areas need help now and I urge Offaly County Council to act now.</p> <p>Last week, Tusla published its review of accommodation services for victims of domestic, sexual and gender-based violence.  It highlighted major gaps in services across the country but particularly in the midlands.  Some 62% of people living in County Offaly, 37% of those living in County Laois and a truly shocking 93% of those living in County Longford live more than a 30-minute drive from emergency accommodation.  We need to fix this.  Lack of services for victims is not only a moral failing; it is a failing of our international obligations and we need an immediate solution.</p> <p>Following the publication of the Tusla review, the Minister for Justice, Deputy McEntee, and Minister for Children, Equality, Disability, Integration and Youth, Deputy O'Gorman, listed counties Laois, Westmeath and Longford for prioritisation for the urgent provision of family units.  Laois Domestic Abuse Service has been campaigning for many years for a refuge and Portlaoise has been prioritised for eight family places.  Laois County Council is collaborating to identify a suitable site, hopefully as soon as possible.  We need to see the same level of prioritisation for County Offaly.</p> <p>The Minister, Deputy McEntee, will outline timelines and structures for the delivery of safe accommodation and refuge places as part of the third national strategy on domestic, sexual and gender-based violence.  I understand this strategy will be published in April and I look forward to reviewing it with a midlands lens.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#X00300"><p>I will follow up on my colleague, Senator Flynn's points in terms of public transport.  Research from the UK has found that bus drivers have higher levels of Covid-19 deaths than other occupations.  We also have research that found that 41% of people polled said they were less likely to use public transport after the pandemic.</p><p>I am really concerned that removal of masks as a requirement on public transport will, in fact, damage the safety of those working and those who have to travel by public transport and, indeed, as we have seen, discourage others from using public transport when that needs to be a priority in terms of our wider safety and in respect of climate.  I really urge the Government to rethink its policy public transport.</p><p>What I will speak about today, however, is something even wider and more important in terms of the pandemic.  It is premature to talk about it being over because we know people are dying all around the world.  Last week, the 6th European Union-African Union Summit: A Joint Vision for 2030 took place.  As we anticipated, the Trade-Related Aspects of Intellectual Property Rights, TRIPS, waiver was a huge issue of trust and damaged trust.  The South African President, Cyril Ramaphosa, tweeted that:</p> <blockquote> 	An agreement on the #TRIPSWaiver would strengthen and consolidate our relations with Europe.  If we are not able to reach a solution, this will mean we were not able to find each other on a matter of life and death. </blockquote> <p>This House passed a motion before Christmas on the TRIPS waiver.  We sent a very strong signal that we recognised the urgency of a TRIPS waiver on life and death.  We wrote to the Department of Enterprise, Trade and Employment, which responded by saying it did have lead responsibility and that the proposal is primarily one of health policy rather than a general trade or intellectual property issue.</p><p>Yet the T&aacute;naiste, Deputy Varadkar, was at that EU summit and he did not speak about it as a life or death issue or as a health issue.  He said at this EU-African summit that we want to avoid the pandemic being used to &quot;undermine innovation or undermine intellectual property.&quot;  I am really concerned that the T&aacute;naiste on one hand tells us it is a health issue, and he acknowledges that, and then speaks on all our behalf in a way that is out of spirit with the statement from this House and with what the Minister for Health said.  He is representing us at a key forum of Europe's conversation with African nations and telling them that he regards intellectual property as a bigger priority than health or life and death.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Alice-Mary Higgins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2480"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2480&amp;amp;pid=AliceMaryHiggins&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Again, I hope we can move forward on this.  I will pass this to the Leader because she herself has been very good on this issue.  Can we convey in some way our concern in relation to this matter?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#Y00200"><p>I call on Seanad&oacute;ir Erin McGreehan.  I believe she has some distinguished visitors in the Gallery today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1671" speakername="Erin McGreehan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#Y00300"><p>I have very distinguished members with me today.  I have three of my sons, Conor, D&oacute;nal &Oacute;g and Eoin.  It is great pleasure to be here as a Senator and to have three of my boys here with me today.  It is lovely to see their faces.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#Y00400"><p>Make sure you wave to mam, while she is here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1671" speakername="Erin McGreehan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#Y00500"><p>It is appropriate that we are talking about children.  The Certain Institutional Burials (Authorised Interventions) Bill was published today.  It is a really important Bill.  It is critical that we get this through our Houses, passed, put into legislation, enacted and put into place as quickly as possible.  If I was born, and if those boys over there were born in a different time, I would be in a mother and baby home.  I am an unmarried mother.  When I look at those wee faces, I think of the burials in Tuam.  It is very emotional, even to have them here today.  We need to have this Bill.  I congratulate the Minister for Children, Equality, Disability, Integration and Youth, Deputy O'Gorman, on the work that he, his Department and his officials did.  They took on many of the recommendations that were in the pre-legislative scrutiny report.  They have included coronial and scientific expertise in the new Bill, which was not there before.  That is a big move from what it was.  We really needed this and was part of what the children&rsquo;s committee recommended.</p> <p>I really welcome this.  I hope that we do not have lots of delaying tactics on this Bill.  It is a really good Bill.  I congratulate all the officials and the outside expertise that helped the Minister with this Bill.  I congratulate them on it.  I look forward to seeing the Bill pass through all Stages in this House. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#Y00600"><p>Could I say to the junior Senators from County Louth, you should be very proud of your mother.  She does great work in the Seanad.  We are sorry that she has to be away from home so often, but she is working very hard on behalf of everybody.  I now call on Senator Maria Byrne.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1695" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#Y00700"><p>I rise today to welcome last Friday&rsquo;s news that the T&aacute;naiste, the Minister of State, Deputy Troy, and the Minister of State, Deputy English, launched the recent development plan in Nenagh, with &euro;18 million in investments for businesses to expand, as well as to avail of services such as Innovate Limerick and to work with different projects.  As Local Enterprise Week is coming up, and will take place from 7 March onwards, it is good to get the message out to businesses that there are supporting services out there and that they should apply for them.</p> <p>The other issue I want to raise is my concerns regarding University Hospital Limerick.  I am like a wound-up record at this stage.  I know that the Minister for Health, Deputy Stephen Donnelly, visited the hospital recently.  There are talks of HIQA carrying out an independent investigation.  Yet, University Hospital Limerick is topping the charts in terms of trolley numbers.  It has been doing so consistently for a long time and certainly, something has to happen.  I acknowledge the Minister met staff and senior management but I believe we need to have a fresh pair of eyes looking at University Hospital Limerick to alleviate the plight of both the staff who are working there and of the patients.  It is about safety as well and that patients feel safe when they visit University Hospital Limerick.  Trolley numbers are definitely very high and have been consistently so for a while.  Something has to happen about it.  I believe it requires somebody independent to review it.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1629" speakername="Garret Ahearn" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#Y00800"><p>I welcome the three young McGreehans to Seanad &Eacute;ireann today.  They should be very proud of their mother.  From looking at them and how well behaved they are, I think Fianna F&aacute;il will be well represented in Louth for the years to come.</p> <p>The town and village renewal scheme is an important scheme for towns and villages in my county of Tipperary.  It is part of a number of schemes in the Department of Rural and Community Development, which is a Department that was set up by the Fine Gael Party in 2016.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Garret Ahearn:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=GarretAhearn&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It benefits rural areas, which is really important.  Hopefully, there will be an announcement soon on the town and village renewal scheme.  An awful lot of projects in Tipperary have submitted applications.  Will the Leader contact the Minister find out when the announcement will be made?</p><p>It is really important that these schemes get up and running as quickly as possible.  We see the rising cost of construction almost on a weekly basis.  I think there are ten applications from Tipperary alone.  Some are from Tipperary town, including one to do up a recreational amenity.</p><p>There is a really good application from Ballyporeen for the upgrade of an old school house into a enterprise hub with broadband and a community centre.  These are really important things for rural areas and towns.  There is an application from Golden which my colleague, Councillor Michael FitzGerald, has been working on to do up the area at the kind of island where the bridge is.  There is a range of other ones.  It is really important that the announcement is made as quickly as possible.  I ask the Leader to find out when it will be.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1636" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#Z00200"><p>It is important that we have an early debate on tourism.  Two years ago the name for tourism was "staycation".  It worked very well for the country.  Such a debate should be a priority because so many areas in the sector are under severe pressure.  The hospitality sector is under pressure in terms of staff and in many cases it is looking for permits.  That is something that crosses over to other Departments.  There is a shortage of chefs and a whole range of staff in catering.  Then there is the matter of sterling which is getting stronger.  That could help our tourism sector.  We should be encouraging people from the UK to holiday here.</p> <p>In high-profile tourism areas, we should have very good Wi-Fi so that people visiting can use it for business as well as for pleasure.  This is the time of the year to have such a debate.  The hospitality sector needs a lift.  It is experiencing massive increases in the cost of energy and other things.  There are great challenges and if the House could be of any assistance in highlighting these matters, that would be very welcome.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" speakername="Barry Ward" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#Z00300"><p>Like others, I join in welcoming Dolkun Isa, president of the World Uyghur Congress, to Ireland.  Some of us had a chance to meet him today and to acknowledge what he said.  It is important to speak to people like him and to hear what they have to say.</p> <p>The European directive for transparent and predictable working conditions, which is due to be transposed in this jurisdiction by 1 August, according to article 21 of the directive.  It is a very important piece of employment legislation that will particularly protect people in insecure or low-paid employment.  It will have important provisions on maximum probation periods and the minimum wage.   Another important provision is that an employer will not be able to advertise a job without setting out clearly a salary scale.  That is something that not only addresses certainty for the applicant but it will also go a long way towards addressing the gender pay gap.  There will be clarity on what pay will be available to people and it give people an opportunity to submit a job application with their eyes open.</p> <p>I do not know what steps have been taken to transpose this legislation.  I do not have that information.  I hope this House will have an opportunity to speak about it because the details of how that is done will be tremendously important.  The way that it is worded and takes effect in Irish legislation will dictate whether it is a strong measure for the employees who need it or not.  I hope we will have a debate on that and have a clear opportunity to look at the legislative provisions that transpose the directive.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#AA00100"><p>Before I call the Leader to respond to the Order of Business, I join colleagues in expressing my sympathies on the death of Christopher Stalford to his wife and all his colleagues across the community in Northern Ireland.  I met him at an event in Queen's University on the future of unionism and he was most gracious afterwards when we had a cup of tea and a chat.  He put across his point of view in a very forthright manner but in a way that brought the best out in every part of our conversation.  We extend to his family our regret on his sad loss.  Ar dheis D&eacute; go raibh a h-anam.</p> <p>I call the Leader to respond to the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#AA00200"><p>I join the Cathaoirleach in expressing my sympathy on the loss of Christopher Stalford.  When I heard the news at the weekend, I genuinely realised how fragile life is.  A 39 year old gentleman with an incredibly promising political future ahead of him has died.  We all have no doubt he would have been leadership material in probably the not too distant future.  It is an awful tragedy.  On my behalf, and on behalf of all the Members, I extend condolences to Laura and his four children, to all his constituents, to party colleagues and to all his colleagues in the North.</p> <p>Senator Ward asked how the current EU employment legislation will be transposed.  From my experience of being a Minister with responsibility with employment, unfortunately I have to tell him that it will probably take years to happen.  It took us a long time to get the last miscellaneous provisions Bill passed in 2018 but I will make inquiries with the Minister today and find out.</p> <p>Senator Burke asked for a debate on tourism, which I have scheduled in the diary, but I will see if I can bring it forward now that the days are getting longer and we all have had a spring in our step in the past few days.</p> <p>Senator Ahearn asked when the announcement on the town and village renewal scheme will be made.  I do not know but I will make inquiries today and come back to him on it.</p> <p>Senator Maria Byrne raised, and not for the first time as she has done so nearly on a weekly basis, as have others, the inefficiencies in University Hospital Limerick that are nearly unique to Limerick.  I am surprised by what she said and that is why I texted her.  I was under the impression that the Taoiseach in the D&aacute;il a number of weeks ago had agreed to an independent review and now the Senator has been told the Minister on a visit to the hospital this week has said they are only considering it.  That is not good enough.  I will certainly make known the Senator&rsquo;s views to the Taoiseach, the T&aacute;naiste and the Leader of the Green Party today.  We have a commitment to make sure we improve those services.  Hundreds of thousands of euro have been given to University Hospital Limerick in recent years but there has been no comparable improvement in services for the people of that region.  It is not good enough.</p> <p>It is lovely to see people back in the Chamber and around the Houses and normal life returning.  I wish Senator McGreehan and her three little boys well.  It is lovely to see them with their squeaky clean little faces and lovely hairdos and great to see them here.  The Senator raised a really important issue.  I heard the Minister, Deputy Roderic O&rsquo;Gorman, interviewed on radio this morning on my drive to the Houses.  He is one of the most thoughtful Ministers we have had in a long time.  I am not being disrespectful to anybody in saying we all have to be a Minister on our first day in office without having been one prior to that.  The Minister, Deputy O'Gorman, has taken this issue to heart and has put Trojan effort into making sure this Bill takes into account all of the issues that have been raised with him during the past 18 months.  I have no doubt when it is published this week some people will say it is missing this or that, but he had done an enormous body of work to bring forward the institutional burials Bill.  I reassure the Senator that I spoke to the Minister&rsquo;s private secretary yesterday and there is no doubt we will have this Bill passed by both Houses hopefully by the end of May or the beginning of June.  That should be a priority for all of us.  There are 796 little bodies buried that need to find a connection with their family members.  It is incumbent upon all of us to make sure that happens as smoothly as it possibly can.</p> <p>Senator Higgins talked about the Trade-Relates Aspects of Intellectual Property Rights, TRIPS, waiver and the T&aacute;naiste&rsquo;s perception of what we discussed here before Christmas.  I will certainly convey the Senator&rsquo;s message to the T&aacute;naiste and come back to her on it.</p> <p>The Minister of State, Deputy Hackett, talked about Tulsa's recent review of accommodation services presented to Ministers last week and the need for timelines, which I think we will get in a few weeks when the Minister, Deputy McEntee, has finished her three-week public consultation review. </p> <p>Senator Wall talked about the urgent debate that is required for GPs and I will organise that as quickly as I can.</p> <p>Senator McGahon talked about having a debate on renewable energy targets that have now been set at 40%. </p> <p>To answer the question raised by Senator Dooley, I certainly will try to arrange a debate on the topic of the request Senator Keogan raised this morning because it would be very apt to hear wider views on it.  As to why there are delays with the supply chain, having listened to delays of diagnoses of whether women were depressed or menopausal, which they have had to put up with for donkey's years, is beyond belief.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Regina Doherty:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2295"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2295&amp;amp;pid=ReginaDoherty&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I will see what I can find out and come back to the Senator.</p><p>I thank Senator Gavan for raising the issue he did because I was trying to figure out how I would bring it up nobody else did so I am glad he brought it up.  I had the privilege of meeting Julia and Lenka.  Deputy Joan Collins brought them to me a number of years ago.  They are two remarkable women, but they were incredibly vulnerable when I met them because of how badly they were being treated by their employer, the Ivy, the salubrious restaurant down the road.  They were treated despicably by that organisation, and it gave me great pleasure to see the judgment that was handed down.  The only thing that gave me a little bit of sadness was that they did not get four times the amount of money that was awarded to them.  They had been treated despicably.  We should name and shame every organisation that mistreats the people who go in and provide a service on its behalf on a daily basis and who give the best impression of that organisation.  In the back rooms of such companies' premises, these staff are treated so poorly.</p><p>I have been in contact with the two ladies since.  I want to let them know they are the reason we have the new legislation on tips.  They are the reason we started that ball rolling a couple of weeks ago and we had the T&aacute;naiste here a couple of weeks ago.  They are the reason that will make me fight to make sure the service charge is included in the legislation and I have done a bit of research in recent weeks which I did not do when I was in the Department.  The original agreement between the unions and the industry at the time, 48 years ago when service charges were introduced, there was no legislation covering it because it was an agreement between unions and the industry that the service charge would be introduced to make sure the people who were giving you the service got looked after and got paid well.  That was because the wages were always considered too low to earn a living.  There is no reason why any employer should take that to pay for knives, forks, their own bottom line, broken plates or whatever they are having themselves.  It is for the people who serve us and that is where it should be going.  I will work hard with Senator Gavan and others to make sure it goes that way and stays that way.</p><p>Senator Buttimer and others talked about NPHET in view of the fact that it was disbanded suddenly this morning.  Colleagues have raised acceptance and delight at the fact that this time next week we will not have masks and the visible signs of Covid.  Others, such as Senators Flynn and Higgins, have talked about the fact that there still is an air of cautiousness among some people.  As a society, we need to make sure that we recognise both.  There are people who will be gleeful next week and there are people who will still be scared and vulnerable.  We need to make sure we look after those who are scared and vulnerable but also try to genuinely get down to whatever the new normal will be as quickly as we possibly can.</p><p>Senators Murphy and Currie talked about the work hub.  Senator Currie spoke about the connected hubs and the extra 200 we are getting over the coming years, which will be great.  Senator Murphy also sought a debate on the flooding of the River Shannon, which I will organise as quickly as I can.</p><p>Senator Keogan brought up the protests in Canada and I will try to organise that debate on a Thursday afternoon in the coming weeks because it would be interesting to do that.  The Senator is right and she mentioned last week that there was little coverage of its so maybe it is a good time to bring it up.</p><p>Senator Malcolm Byrne talked about the Uyghur World Congress visit this morning.  I note with interest the lovely email we got and I thank the Senator for his reply, which was well drafted.  There is no reason not to shine a light when human rights violations are being made and to sing about them insofar as they should not be done in the quiet or in close corners.</p><p>Senator Flynn asked for a debate on direct provision, which we will organise.</p><p>Senators Sherlock, Martin and Craughwell, among others, talked about Ukraine and the sanctions I hope will be announced at some point in the afternoon.  Each of them are right that the sanctions need to be as loud and reactive to the intolerable actions of the Russians last night as possible.  They should not be tolerated by any part of a functional, normal and democratic society.</p><p>Senator Craughwell showed his dismay at the cost of the 945 pairs of socks.  That sounds silly but you do not get to have a seat on the UN Security Council without lobbying all the people who make a decision.  However, he has a point and he made it well.</p><p>Senator Conway talked about sending a letter to NPHET and looked for a debate on disability and digital papers for students of this year&rsquo;s leaving certificate.</p><p>Senator O&rsquo;Loughlin started the debate by condemning the Russian attacks and she again talked about the lack of ICTU affiliation for our Defence Forces and their powerlessness in talks on their pay.  The Senator also referred to the Respect for SNAs campaign and Caoimhe O&rsquo;Connor in her area, who will graduate as an SNA next week but who will not get the respect she deserves.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Regina Doherty:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2295"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2295&amp;amp;pid=ReginaDoherty&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->As I said here before, the Respect for SNAs campaign deserves all our support in any way, shape or form we can offer it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#CC00200"><p>Senators might invite Ms Julia Marciniak and Ms Lenka Laiermanova when that legislation is coming through because of what they had to endure to highlight that particular issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.90" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.91" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#CC00400">Online Safety and Media Regulation Bill 2022: Order for Second Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.92" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p></p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#CC00500"><p>I move: "That Second Stage be taken now."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.94" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.95" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#CC00700">Online Safety and Media Regulation Bill 2022: Second Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.96" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That the Bill be now read a Second Time."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1471" speakername="Catherine Martin" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#CC00900"><p>Dl&iacute; ceannr&oacute;da&iacute;och is ea &eacute; an Bille um Rial&aacute;il Sabh&aacute;ilteachta ar L&iacute;ne agus na Me&aacute;n, 2022 agus t&aacute; &aacute;thas orm &eacute; a chur faoi bhr&aacute;id an T&iacute;.</p> <p>The main aim of this legislation is to jump-start modernisation of Ireland's approach to the regulation of content, both for traditional editorial media and the landscape of newer online services fuelled by user-generated content.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Catherine Martin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2425"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2425&amp;amp;pid=CatherineMartin&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This is driven by changes in the way we consume media and the growth of the online world.  Streaming services are now a key feature of everyday life.  They are on our phones, laptops and televisions.  However, regulation of these editorially controlled services has not kept pace with the regulation of broadcasting services.  This Bill will change that and ensure that streaming services are subject to up-to-date rules.</p><p>While the fact the Internet is a key part of our lives has become increasingly apparent, the Covid-19 pandemic has brought sharp focus to this reality.  From working from home to schooling from home, the Internet has enabled us to weather this pandemic in ways that have surprised us all.  While the Internet has had a broadly positive impact, there are risks, however, especially to children.  Some of these risks are online extensions of existing problems, such as bullying.  Others represent new challenges in our digital age, such as image-based abuse.  While we have updated our criminal law for the online age, there has not yet been a way to hold online services to account.  These are key matters this Bill will begin to tackle for the first time.  As such, the Bill's scope is ambitious and includes updates to the regulation of broadcasting services, including radio, television and streaming services.  It also provides for the creation of a new regulatory framework for online safety to tackle the availability of the most serious forms of harmful online content.  This will be done by providing for risk-based regulation of services that facilitate access to user-generated content.  In doing this, the Bill also provides for the implementation of the revised audiovisual media services directive into Irish law.</p><p>The foundations for achieving this ambition are those elements of the Bill that provide for the creation of a new regulatory body, coimisi&uacute;n na me&aacute;n, the media commission, which will implement and enforce these new and updated rules.  In order to do so, an coimisi&uacute;n will have a robust and modern suite of regulatory functions and powers and, in line with EU law and best practice, will be wholly independent in its exercise of those functions and powers.  Regulatory independence is key to effective regulation, especially for content regulation, where fundamental rights are so important.  In some parts of Europe, this independence is being eroded.  It is vital that Ireland leads on this issue.</p><p>The powers of an coimisi&uacute;n include the power to fund its operations by levying the services it regulates; to create legally binding regulatory codes; to gather information and appoint authorised officers to conduct investigations; and to seek the imposition of sanctions for failures of compliance, including financial sanctions of up to &euro;20 million or 10% of turnover, whichever is higher.  In the most serious cases, an coimisi&uacute;n may seek criminal prosecution of senior executives of non-compliant services and seek court orders to block access to a service in Ireland.  In respect of broadcasters, an coimisi&uacute;n will retain the power to revoke broadcasting contracts for serious breaches.</p><p>An coimisi&uacute;n will also take over the current functions of the Broadcasting Authority of Ireland, BAI.  The staff of the BAI, approximately 40 people, will transfer to an coimisi&uacute;n.  I envisage that an coimisi&uacute;n will need to scale quickly up to a staffing level of at least 160 and in the longer term may require staffing of up to 300.  The Government has approved the establishment of an coimisi&uacute;n on an administrative basis, including recruitment of key personnel, prior to the enactment of this Bill.  Work on this is ongoing between my officials, the Public Appointments Service and the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform.</p><p>While the functions of an coimisi&uacute;n primarily relate to the regulation of services, it will also have wider roles relating to the protection of children, research, education, media literacy, and journalistic and creative supports.  In carrying out these roles, an coimisi&uacute;n will support and promote an open, trusted and pluralistic media and online environment.  There is a widespread problem with the availability of harmful and criminal content on widely used online services.  It is clear that self-regulation in online safety is not working and that oversight and accountability is required.  As regards online safety, the Bill requires an coimisi&uacute;n to regulate video-sharing platform services in line with the directive.  In addition, the Bill provides an coimisi&uacute;n with the power to designate further online services for regulation from a pool of relevant online services.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Catherine Martin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2425"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2425&amp;amp;pid=CatherineMartin&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->In this context, an online service is relevant if it facilitates access to user-generated content.  This covers a very wide range of services, including social media services, many gaming services and online messaging and storage services.  In order to designate an online service, an coimisi&uacute;n is required to conduct a risk assessment of the service, including regarding the prevalence of harmful online content available through the service and the nature and scale of the service.  This approach will enable an coimisi&uacute;n to direct its energies to the areas where they are most needed.</p><p>Once an online service is designated, an coimisi&uacute;n can require it to comply with binding online safety codes.  These codes can require online services to adapt their systems and processes in three key areas which are rules for content moderation and complaints handling; rules regarding the design of the service and how and why it displays certain content to users; and rules about advertising.</p><p>With regard to video-sharing platform services, an coimisi&uacute;n is required to apply the provisions of the directive to those services through these codes. The main aim of the online safety codes is to tackle and progressively reduce the availability of harmful online content on designated online services.  In this regard, the Bill clearly defines harmful online content.  Online content is harmful where it either relates to one of 40 criminal offences listed in the Bill, or is cyberbullying, the promotion or encouragement of eating disorders, self-harm or suicide, or makes available knowledge of methods of self-harm or suicide.</p><p>The schedule of criminal offences includes the offences under Coco's Law, or the Harassment, Harmful Communications and Related Offences Act 2020, with regard to image-based abuse, abusive communications and harassment.  For harmful online content which is not criminal in nature, a risk test must be met for it to be considered harmful.  This includes whether the online content gives rise to any risk to a person's life or a reasonably-foreseeable risk to a person's mental or physical health.  The Bill also provides for a mechanism for future categories of harmful online content, both criminal and non-criminal, to be added to this list, subject to Oireachtas oversight.</p><p>The Bill also requires an coimisi&uacute;n to create a super-complaints scheme, under which nominated bodies such as expert NGOs can formally notify an coimisi&uacute;n of a range of online safety issues.  In addition, the Bill empowers an coimisi&uacute;n to audit the handling of complaints by designated online services.</p><p>In summary, the online safety elements of this Bill will ensure that an individual person will be exposed to far less harmful online content and that online services will be required by law to respond to and robustly deal with complaints when they are made.  In this regard, an coimisi&uacute;n will have significant powers of compliance and sanction to hold these services to account.</p><p>As the Members will be aware, I have established an expert group to examine providing for an individual complaints mechanism in the Bill.  The role of the expert group is to examine whether it is practicable to do this and, if so, how it may be done.  The group has 90 days from the date of its first meeting, which was on 31 January 2022, to examine this matter and to report back to me with its recommendations.  Following this, I will then consider tabling an amendment as the Bill passes through the Oireachtas.  If an individual complaints mechanism can be provided for, I would like to ensure that it is.  In this regard, any proposals that I bring forward must be workable and legally robust.</p><p>In terms of the regulation of broadcasting and streaming services, this will for the most part be done through media codes and rules.  Media codes are mostly about the content of programming, including rules for programme standards and advertising.  Media rules, on the other hand, are mostly about the presentation and structure of the service, including rules regarding the time given to advertising, accessibility requirements for persons with disabilities and quotas for European works.  In order to ensure the uninterrupted regulation of broadcasters, provision is made for the existing broadcasting codes and rules to be carried over and become media codes and rules.</p><p>The Bill also provides for the mandatory registration of streaming services to ensure that, in line with the directive, all streaming services established in Ireland are subject to appropriate regulation.  Broadcasters will remain regulated on a contractual basis.  The Bill also provides for the transposition of an optional provision in the directive to empower an coimisi&uacute;n to levy broadcasters and streaming services, including those established elsewhere in the EU, in respect of any revenues that they may make in Ireland in order to fund the production of European works, including Irish-produced works.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Catherine Martin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2425"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2425&amp;amp;pid=CatherineMartin&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Provision is made so that the money collected could be dispersed by an coimisi&uacute;n through a content production scheme.</p><p>The Bill does not set the amounts of any such levy as this would be inflexible but enables an coimisi&uacute;n to design and implement a levy having regard to relevant economic factors.  There are potential risks and benefits to a levy, including for consumers, and it is intended that an coimisi&uacute;n would thoroughly examine these matters before these provisions are commenced.</p><p>Turning to a more detailed overview of the provisions of the Bill, it is first important to note that it amends the Broadcasting Act 2009.</p><p>Part 1 addresses preliminary and general matters.</p><p>Part 2 amends the 2009 Act to insert and amend a number of definitions, including key definitions such as the definition of a "relevant online service".  Furthermore, sections 4 and 5 under this part provide for the relevant jurisdiction rules from the directive.</p><p>Part 3 amends Part 2 of the 2009 Act to provide for the establishment of coimisi&uacute;n na me&aacute;n.  Key provisions under this part include provision for the independence of an coimisi&uacute;n, the appointment of commissioners, including a chairperson, an coimisi&uacute;n to impose levies on regulated services - not including community broadcasters - to fund its operations, an coimisi&uacute;n to report on its operations and the accountability of the chairperson to the Committee of Public Accounts and the chairperson and other commissioners to relevant Oireachtas committees.</p><p>Part 3 also provides for the general powers and functions of an coimisi&uacute;n.  It is important to note that this provision does not contain every power and function to be exercised by an coimisi&uacute;n but does set out, at a high-level, certain powers and functions that an coimisi&uacute;n shall exercise and matters that it shall take into account when exercising its powers.  This includes upholding Ireland's democratic values, protecting the interests of the public, in particular children, ensuring the diverse needs of the people of this island are served by our media, stimulating content production, particularly in respect of the Irish language and climate matters and sustaining independent and impartial journalism.  In particular, an coimisi&uacute;n  is provided with a strong education and research role.</p><p>Part 4 provides for matters related to the registration of providers of streaming services through the insertion of a new Part 3A into the 2009 Act.</p><p>Part 5 concerns the duties, codes and rules applicable to radio and television broadcasters and streaming services and provides for these through the insertion of a new part 3B into the 2009 Act.  Chapter 2 of this new Part concerns duties, including in relation to privacy, news and current affairs and advertising.  Chapters 3 and 5 of this new part concern media codes and rules.  Chapter 3 of this Part also provides that existing broadcasting codes and rules made by the Broadcasting Authority of Ireland, BAI, such as access rules, will continue in force following the enactment of the Bill.</p><p>Part 6 amends Part 4 of the 2009 Act and primarily concerns changes to take into account the establishment of an coimisi&uacute;n and the statutory regulation of streaming services in respect of redress mechanisms.</p><p>Part 9 amends Part 7 of the 2009 Act to take into account the establishment of an coimisi&uacute;n in regard to public service broadcasting, allow for the part-funding of the broadcasting functions of an coimisi&uacute;n from television licence receipts, provide for changes to the calculation of total advertising time for broadcasters and insert a new chapter 7 regarding the availability and prominence of public service programmes and services.</p><p>Part 11 inserts a new Part 8A into the 2009 Act concerning online safety regulation.  Chapter 1 of this new part concerns the definitions of harmful online content and age-inappropriate online content, which I have already detailed.  Chapter 2 concerns the process for designating relevant online services for regulation.  Chapter 3 concerns the making of online safety codes, the matters which they can address and matters which need to be taken into account when the codes are being drawn up, including the protection of children, fundamental rights, the nature and scale of online services and the impact of automated decision-making or algorithms.  Chapter 4 concerns the making of online safety guidance materials and advisory notices.  Chapter 5 concerns an obligation on an coimisi&uacute;n to establish a super-complaints scheme for nominated bodies, and a number of other matters.  Part 11 also inserts a new Schedule 3 into the 2009 Act containing the list of offence specific categories of harmful online content.</p><p>Part 12 inserts a new Part 8B into the 2009 Act concerning investigations and sanctions.  Chapter 2 and of this new Part provides an coimisi&uacute;n with the power to appoint authorised officers and concerns the procedure for investigations by those officers and decisions by an coimisi&uacute;n following investigations.  Chapter 4 concerns the imposition of administrative financial sanctions.  Chapter 5 of this new Part provides an coimisi&uacute;n with the power to issue notices to end a contravention and provides for secondary criminal liability for senior executives linked to these.  Chapter 6 provides an coimisi&uacute;n with the power to seek court orders to block access to non-compliant online services in Ireland.  Chapter 7 provides an coimisi&uacute;n with the power to issue content limitation notices in respect of individual items of harmful online content.  Chapter 8 provides for three categories of summary offences under the Bill and provides an coimisi&uacute;n with the power to prosecute these offences.  This part also inserts a new Schedule 4 into the 2009 Act concerning oral hearings.</p><p>Parts 7, 8, 10, 13, 15 and 17 amend various Parts of the 2009 Act and other relevant Acts to take into account the dissolution of the BAI and the establishment of an coimisi&uacute;n.</p><p>Part 14 inserts a new Part 10A in the 2009 Act concerning European works.  This Part provides for the requirements of the directive for European works quotas and prominence and provides an coimisi&uacute;n with the power to introduce a European works levy and European works scheme.</p><p>Lastly, Part 16 provides for transitional matters.</p><p>As can be seen, given its subject matter, this Bill is necessarily complex and far-reaching.  It deals with a wide range of important issues from modernising media regulation to introducing, for the first time, online safety regulation to tackle the availability of serious forms of harmful online content.</p><p>I would like to conclude by acknowledging the work undertaken by the members of the Joint Committee on Tourism, Culture, Arts, Sport and Media on the general scheme of the Bill as part of the pre-legislative scrutiny process.  The report of the committee demonstrated the importance of pre-legislative scrutiny to the democratic process.  I was pleased to address a significant number of the recommendations made by the joint committee through the Bill.  As we now progress through the next phase of parliamentary scrutiny of the Bill, I look forward to the Senators' contributions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#FF00200"><p>Gabhaim bu&iacute;ochas leis an Aire.  She deserves a good deoch uisce after that wonderful presentation to us.  I deliberately left her an extra few minutes because I think all of us here in the Chamber and those of us listening in or watching realise how important this legislation is.  It will be a very hard act for Senator Martin to follow his sister.  The next eight minutes are his.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1667" speakername="Vincent P Martin" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#FF00300"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire agus roimh an Bille seo.  The legislation proposed must be one of the most complex and hugely important to come to the Houses.  Today marks a milestone in its progress..  We are now another step closer to finalising this groundbreaking legislation.</p> <p>The full establishment of Coimisi&uacute;n na Me&aacute;n, setting up a new regulatory body that will oversee a more streamlined and effective regulation of audiovisual media content, in addition to the important appointment of the online safety commissioner, will bring an end to the era of self-regulation of the social media giants that have established headquarters in Ireland under our jurisdiction.</p> <p>The eyes of Europe and, indeed, the rest of the world are upon us as legislators.  There is much at stake and the Minister and her officials must be commended on the prioritised emphasis she and they have placed on drafting a Bill that is so far-reaching in its scale and ambition.  The Government of this day ought to be commended too on supporting the need for this initiative.</p> <p>Undoubtedly, once enacted, the Bill will be very impactful.  I welcome the extent of the pre-legislative scrutiny that colleagues undertook at the Oireachtas committee.  I welcome the Minister's acceptance of the majority of their recommendations within the report.  It is a good example of the vital work Members of the Oireachtas do; often away from the glare of publicity.  They go through legislation word for word, line by line.  At times, I regret that it can be used as a box-ticking exercise but one cannot say that in respect of this Bill, the Climate Action and Low Carbon Development (Amendment) Bill 2021 and many others.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Vincent P. Martin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=VincentPMartin&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I hope in the months and years to come we will fully value the role of pre-legislative scrutiny.  I acknowledge some areas are still under consideration by the Minister, in particular the establishment of the working group on an individual complaints mechanism.  Public confidence and trust, which are hugely lacking in the current self-regulatory framework will be essential within this consideration.  Many concerned stakeholders are waiting for years, more than a decade.  I am delighted the Minister, the Department and the Government are moving ahead, as they are today.<br/><br/>The technical and operational challenges to individual complaints should be acknowledged.  A potential reach of more than 450 million people across Europe is a vast user base.  It is difficult to comprehend how the Irish regulator might handle such a structure and potential workload, but if there is a way to allow for a process whereby individual complaints can be reviewed, then it would be prudent of the Minister to take time for further analysis of this issue.  I welcome her decision to expedite the work of the group to just 90 days.  I acknowledge that any solutions presented must be legally robust.  I look forward to hearing the recommendations in the coming weeks.<br/><br/>Our children and their safety are the driving force and momentum for all of us when considering the Bill.  Evidence, both data-driven and anecdotal, tell us that children are at daily risk of exposure to many types of harmful online material, from criminal harms to other harms such as bullying, harassment, exploitation and content that promotes suicide or eating disorders.  The tech companies make vast sums of money through their products and parents cannot be expected to be singlehandedly responsible and accountable for supervising their children at all times from accessing these platforms whose tentacles reach into almost every aspect of our everyday lives.<br/><br/>I welcome the online safety code framework established by the coimisi&uacute;n.  It will ensure that services take appropriate systemic measures to reduce the availability of harmful online content, including cyberbullying.  At long last, the tech companies will be held to tangible account.  The online services will be forced to respond to and robustly deal with complaints when they are made.<br/><br/>I recognise that both society and business welcome the important development of this Bill.  Technology companies, many of whom are established in Ireland and have had great positive impact on our lives and have made a contribution to the economy, and employ thousands, will also play their part in putting the legislation into action in its implementation or, if they do not, face unprecedented, tough sanctions from the coimisi&uacute;n.<br/><br/>It should be acknowledged that there is a widespread problem with the availability of illegal and harmful content on widely used online services and it is clear that self-regulation is not working.  Today heralds the start of the journey to end the era of self-regulation.  The days of self-regulation are numbered.  They have failed us and our children.<br/><br/>I welcome the Minister's work on the Bill in transposing the audiovisual media service directive, which places the focus of media regulation on both broadcasters and streaming services.  How audiences consume content at home and on mobile devices has changed dramatically.  I welcome this legislation which moves to adopt structures to recognise the need for expanded oversight.<br/><br/>As a firm believer in the power of democracy, disinformation is one of the defining issues of our time.  The spread and amplification of disinformation by social media in global politics is creating a demand for alternative narratives.  The influence of fake news has become an acute threat to democratic societies.  Why has the Bill not addressed this key issue?  Does the Minister have a process in place to tackle this once the online safety commissioner is <i>in situ</i>?  The impact of this legislation is to be felt right across the spectrum of society which interacts so frequently with audiovisual content and social media.  It is recognised that further legislation will be required in order to keep pace with the changing landscape of media and technology, but it is vitally important for us to get the foundation right.  The development of this Bill has, understandably, been complex and challenging.  It is evident from the physical weight of the Bill that it is a mammoth project.  It contains much detail.  It should be recognised that Ireland is paving the way for the rest of the world.  The Bill will benefit from its journey through both Houses of the Oireachtas.  I look forward to actively partaking in the journey in the Upper House.  The days of self-regulation are numbered and I unequivocally welcome that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#GG00200"><p>I thank Senator Martin.  That was not a bad follow-up act after the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#GG00300"><p>The Minister is very welcome to the Chamber.  The Bill has been in the works for some time and will bring about drastic change for people and companies working in broadcasting and streaming.  It will affect everyone in the country in some way.  It is a large Bill and at times a technical one, but its main effects are laid out in an accessible manner.  It will result in the replacement of the Broadcasting Authority of Ireland with the new Coimisi&uacute;n na Me&aacute;n, whose remit will extend beyond that of the BAI into the realm of audiovisual on-demand media services or streaming to the layman, and also into social media, which the Bill calls a relevant online service for the time being.</p> <p>I am going to stick to some of the terms that everybody knows.  This Bill comes about because of a debate that has happened in the western hemisphere in recent years.  It was largely kick-started in 2016 by the cultural fallout from Brexit and the presidential election in the United States, the crux of which was that people behaved poorly online and what was to be done about it.  This primarily is a moral issue; someone with no love of neighbour does not care what harm they bring to others, but since we cannot legislate that everyone be moral, then here we are.</p> <p>I will take some aspects of the Bill in order of appearance.  Section 35, which amends section 123 of the principal Act, allows the commission to receive funding from the television licence fee, joining RT&Eacute; and TG4 as the recipients of such.  I do not know how TG4 feels about sharing the pie, but RT&Eacute; has spent recent years having a good moan about how the &euro;200 million a year that gets spent from the fee is simply not enough.  It has continually held out the begging bowl to successive Governments.  Most companies, families and individuals might have to look at costs and expenses and engage in a bit of budgeting to make ends meet when times are tough, but then for most companies, it is not illegal to not pay for the service that you did not ask for and do not use.  There was some talk of a broadcasting levy which would be applied to every household, rather than only those with a television.  Let us all be glad that was not the route taken.  Instead, we are going to put a levy on Netflix, Hulu, Prime Video and Disney Plus - the companies that make the content that people want to pay for - and radio stations and social media companies, which they will pay to the commission for the privilege of being regulated in the hope that some money will be put in their coffers.</p> <p>Part 2 of the Bill is where things get more worrying than ridiculous.  It relates to online safety.  Before I talk about harmful online content, I want to mention section 139D, which relates to age-inappropriate online content.  I am so glad that it is in the Bill.  Very few parents have any idea of what children see online.  Children are given a phone, sometimes as young as six or seven, and they are left alone with it day and night with unrestricted Internet access.  That is not okay.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Sharon Keogan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=SharonKeogan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I am so sick and tired of the blind eye being turned when it comes to the harm this is doing to the children the length and breadth of this country.  From constant exposure to cyberbullying, to unrealistic body imagery for young girls leading to low self-esteem and eating disorders, to one-click access to hard-core pornography which desensitises, to the oversexualisation of young people, to direct messages from anonymous accounts on TikTok, Instagram and Discord, asking them for photos.  The list goes on and on.  Parents are not doing their job at protecting their children from the Internet.  That is a fact.  This will not be a very popular statement, because we do not like to criticise parents, but this is too important, and we must call it out.  That, of course, is the role of the parent; to raise, nurture and protect their child.  It is less so the relationship between the Government and its citizens and yet, that is what the Government is seeking to do with this Bill.  It is to make the media commission the saviour of grown adults nationwide by saving them from offence.</p><p>Alongside the serious issues of self-harm, suicide and eating disorders is the definition of "harmful online content" as online content which "humiliates another person".  Under this Bill, if someone tweets something which I feel humiliates me, I can ask Twitter to take it down.  If it does not do so, I can go to the media commission, tell the commission that it is negatively impacting my mental health and the commission will order it to be taken down.  This is the teacher making sure that the kids play nice in the yard, scaled up to the entire online presence of everyone in the country.</p><p>Bullying is a different story.  It carries with it the idea of behaviour that is targeted and repeated.  There is no such provision in this Bill.  There can be a once-off occasion and, just like that, this organ of the State will swoop in and make sure that no one&rsquo;s feelings ever get hurt.  The role of the State is to protect our rights, not our feelings.  We are in the very early Stages of this Bill.  I welcome the provisions of this Bill, particularly those that protect our children.  However, I also have serious concerns on the possible overreach of the commission in restricting freedom of speech online.  I look forward to working with the proposers on Committee Stage, when I will table amendments to ensure the continued existence of freedom of speech in this country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1641" speakername="Shane Cassells" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#HH00200"><p>The Minister is very welcome and all the more so because she is bringing forward one of the most far-reaching and significant pieces of legislation ever seen in these Houses.  It is much needed for the regulation of media in this modern age.  As a member of the Joint Committee on Tourism, Culture, Arts, Sport and Media, I was delighted over the last year to have been working on that pre-legislative scrutiny of the general scheme of the Bill, along with my colleagues, Senator Malcolm Byrne, and the Chair, Deputy Niamh Smyth.  We addressed the dozens of witnesses from many spheres of society that came before us, from media experts, to health experts, to young students who had been subjected to vile sexual abuse and sexual exploitation online.</p> <p>Now, we have a Bill to deal with the robust regulatory framework.  That is so welcome and I commend the Minister.  We now see the benefits of having a Minister with responsibility for the media, as well as of having a Department with responsibility for the media, in bringing forward legislation that is required.  However, here is the rub, which is bit like when Governments in the past took on the big, vested interests in the world, such as the tobacco industry.  We are facing, just like we did with tobacco in the past, tech giants which make profits that would make one's eyes water.  Facebook&rsquo;s profits are &euro;40 billion.  The ball is very much in these companies' court.  They are looking at this Bill very carefully, as we have seen from their appearance before us at the media committee.  The warnings by Facebook whistleblower, Frances Haugen, at the weekend, when she spoke on RT&Eacute;, were that the world is depending on Ireland for a level of robustness that keeps people safe.  This is stark.</p> <p>Equally stark is her warning about what an online safety commissioner will need in terms of staff and expertise.  She said that it would need at least 20 algorithm experts with deep product expertise, who understand how small choices make parts of the system interact with each other.  If we do not have these experts, then we do not have a chance of holding these systems accountable.  Here is the problem.  Remember that there is no undergraduate course from which we can obtain these experts.  They exist and are trained only by the very tech giants that we are seeking to regulate.  In effect, we will have to break into Willy Wonka&rsquo;s chocolate factory and steal a couple of Oompa Loompas so that we can get the magic formula and take these guys on at their own game.  If we do not, we will get outflanked at every turn.  Just like Augustus Gloop, we will be stuck in the pipe, only ours will be a huge, high-speed fibre cable one.</p> <p>I am very positive about this Bill.  More so, I have been heartened by all those who came before us and spoke to us at the committee.  Not all of the voices were those that predicted doom and gloom.  Many young people and students spoke to us about the dangers of over-regulation.  They said that a process of education and support is needed in our education system.  They nearly half-scolded us.  They said that teachers and parents need to understand the world as it is, as opposed to the world in which we grew up.  This should not be an over-regulated world.</p> <p>We also had students before the committee.  One in particular case, Alicia O&rsquo;Sullivan, the law student from UCC, had her image used on a fake Instagram account.  Several of the posts were nude images of girls, without their faces visible.  The account&rsquo;s creators falsely purported that these images were of Alicia.  One of the most frustrating things was her interaction with An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na when she reported it.  Garda&iacute; were kind of looking at her as if to say, &ldquo;What are you doing here?&rdquo; and they were asking her about what kinds of images she posted herself.  They did not have the expertise.  They were not trained in this whole area and sphere to be able to deal with her complaint properly.  Hence the need for the individual complaints mechanism in the Online Safety and Media Regulation Bill, so that we have a proper area whereby complaints can be dealt with.  </p> <p>On the issue of health - and this is such a broad-ranging Bill - we had the Irish Heart Foundation before the committee.  Its representatives described as worrying the absence of a ban on junk food advertisements aimed at children.  Professor Conor O&rsquo;Mahony, the special rapporteur on child protection, spoke of the dangers of targeted gambling advertisements, which is quite frankly one of the biggest threats in our society today.  They are one of the biggest advertisers in the online world.  Trust me, they have their own batch of Oompa Loompas working in the back offices who are targeting susceptible people and are creating case files on their big clients and big gamblers so that they can keep them hooked.  These people have unlimited resources to make sure that they are using the online world for financial gain. </p> <p>We met with Facebook, Twitter, TikTok and Instagram at our hearings.  They were terse exchanges.  They did not come skipping to the table to meet us.  We subsequently met with representatives from Facebook privately online to discuss community standards.  We came away even more despairing after that, given our differences in interpretation of what was regarded as acceptable content, versus what was not.  Hence, it reinforced my backing for, and my belief in, the need for regulation, as well as for a complaints mechanism.  Only 3% to 5% of hate speech on Facebook is picked up through its artificial intelligence filters, and only 1% of violent inciting content.  What was most worrying about comments by Frances Haugen, who will be before the media committee tomorrow, is her claim that Facebook now rewards hate content.  It will target and promote content that elicits reaction when people are thrashing each other, when they are fighting back and forth, when they are getting that engagement and when people are pressing "like".  That is very depressing.  </p> <p>This Bill obviously has broader implications for the total world of media, because it will dissolve the existing regulator and will provide the commission with the powers and functions to an appropriate apply and enforce review framework.  The issue of the content levy, of which the Minister spoke, under section 157 has, as the Minister says, pros and cons.  However, ensuring that we have a fund for original Irish content is essential, as we discussed at the committee.  I would echo the comments of Screen Producers Ireland which is looking at a definitive start date for that content levy.  We have been discussing this for a very long time.  We need to see progress and a date for that. </p> <p>We also had the traditional media providers before us, because their future is under threat.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Shane Cassells:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2448"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2448&amp;amp;pid=ShaneCassells&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Content from newsrooms is being used for free online.  Just as Johannes Gutenberg put the monks out of business in 1440 when he invented the printing press, I am not trying to hold back the tide.  I worked in the print industry for 20 years and I can see that the game is changing.  The press needs to try to make people buy newspapers again, but we need to address the future of the media.  Hence, we need the report of the Future of Media Commission so that we can have that debate in tandem with this Bill.  They have a complementary aspect.</p><p>I wish the Minister well and look forward to the Bill progressing to Committee Stage.  Today is a major step, on which I commend the Minister.  It is important for the future of the media.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1670" speakername="John McGahon" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#JJ00200"><p>I offer my apologies on behalf of Senator Carrigy.  Over the past year and a half, he has worked hard on the committee with colleagues.  Unfortunately, he cannot make it today.  I am happy to fill in for him because this is an issue in which I have taken a personal interest for the past 18 months in terms of big tech and the algorithms that are being used.  I watched Ms Frances Haugen's testimony to the US Congress, the European Parliament and the House of Commons.  Given how big tech has been so beneficial, Ms Haugen going around the world and giving personal testimony to parliaments shows how important this matter is.</p><p>I wish to set out the context for why we are introducing legislation like this.  It has to do with the US and section 230 of its Communications Decency Act of 1996.  It was one of the world's first Internet Acts and came about to provide news websites that had comment sections with immunity against libellous comments.  It made sense at the time because we were in a new era and did not know what it was.  Now, big tech companies like Twitter, Facebook and YouTube hide behind that section because they can define themselves as platforms as opposed to publishers.  When they are not treated as publishers, they are not responsible for the content - much of the time, it is hateful content - that is posted on their sites.  The loophole they use is to say that they are only hosting the content and are not responsible for it.  The minute that social media and big tech companies become responsible for the content on their platforms, the sooner they will take greater care towards it.</p><p>We have needed to introduce legislation like this because they have failed to self-regulate regardless of all the times they have said they are doing this or that.  It would not make sense for them to self-regulate because doing so would fundamentally alter their business model.  Like any business, their business model is to try to make a profit.  Why on Earth would Mark Zuckerberg or other people in big tech turn around and alter their algorithms to make them safer for people and, in the process, lose money?  It will not happen.  That is why it is so important for governments to step in and legislate.  That is what the Irish Government is doing today and what the EU is doing with the Digital Services Act.  In the US, trying to repeal section 230 was the one thing that the former President, Donald Trump, and Democrats could agree on.  There are moves in the US Congress to do that now.  It would be a decent approach.  That is the context for where we find ourselves today.</p><p>Something else that we have to understand and acknowledge is that big tech moves at lightning speed and is changing every week.  It is difficult for the government in any democracy to try to keep pace with that.  We are trying to do so with this Bill, but it is important that we build mechanisms into the legislation so that we can review it every year.  There is no point in just passing it, putting it on the Statute Book and forgetting about it for four or five years.  Since big tech is an ever-evolving system, it will have to be monitored rigorously and continuously.  As my colleague, Senator Cassells, said when referencing Ms Haugen on RT&Eacute; over the weekend, we must have people in the commission who are experts in algorithms and in how big tech works.  We need to pursue big tech employees to work for us and help us shine a light on what these companies are doing.  The commission needs the highest quality personnel.  Otherwise, I fear that it will not be as successful as it could be.</p><p>I will turn to a few other aspects.  I welcome the Minister's comments on an individual complaints mechanism and that she will revert to us 90 days after 31 January.  I understand why some people may baulk at the concept of an individual complaints mechanism.  For example, if I fell out with Senator Warfield or Senator Keogan, anyone could report a comment on this and that.  The mechanism will not work if it is being abused by people who are using it just because they do not like what so and so said.  However, it allows for action to be taken where someone has clear evidence of sustained harassment or abuse over a distinct period.  At the moment, what can an individual who is being harangued, abused or harassed online do?  He or she can go to the Garda or take the offenders through a costly, time-consuming and laborious legal process.  However, if someone is able to make a direct complaint to the commission about an individual who is clearly targeting a certain section of society or so on, then that individual can be blocked from a platform or sanctions of some sort can be applied.  Importantly, this would provide people with reassurance that there is an avenue to make such complaints and that they would be backed up in doing so.</p><p>We have discussed misinformation.  Last week, I read a good article in <i>The Economist</i>about big tech and misinformation.  It had a really good cartoon depicting the Four Horsemen of the Apocalypse, who are traditionally Famine, Death, War and Conquest.  Three of those are matters that previous societies had to contend it, but perhaps the 21st century has to contend with a fifth horseman, namely, misinformation.  Misinformation is being used around the world to try to destabilise economies and democracies and undermine vaccines and Covid responses.  It is being allowed to run amok online.  This was shown a couple of years ago when Facebook's algorithms took people down rabbit holes.  If people searched for a certain thing, it would produce another level of that content and then another level, and they would go further and further down the rabbit hole.  There is an excellent podcast from <i>The New York Times</i>called &quot;Rabbit Hole&quot;.  It details exactly how these algorithms worked.  After the lid was blown on the story, Facebook all of a sudden said it needed to do something about it.  This is why we cannot trust big tech companies whatsoever.</p><p>I went off on a slight tangent there, so I will return to my point on misinformation.  The Department of Education and the commission could examine a good approach that Finland has been taking since 2014.  That year, Finland came under a large cyberattack from Russia over perceived grievances.  As a result, Finland's department of education introduced misinformation classes in which it showed primary school children what online misinformation was, how to identify it and how to react to it.  If we did something like that to prepare Irish children for the online world, which is different than when some of us were younger, it would go a long way.</p><p>The reason we must introduce this legislation is because it would be insane for us to rely on big tech companies to regulate themselves.  It will never happen.  They have tried to do it.  Actually, to be honest, I do not really think that they have tried to do it.  They have only tried after the lid was blown on some of their practices.  They then give mealy-mouthed responses about what they are trying to do.  Until the business model of big tech changes &ndash; the companies will never change it themselves &ndash; governments will have to step in and regulate.  This Bill will be the first such legislation to be introduced and will be followed by other democracies around the world.</p><p>It is important that we review the legislation every year.  If we do not, we will not be able to keep up with the lightning speed of big tech.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#JJ00300"><p>Senator Cassells will shortly take over for me in the Chair.  I look forward to making my own presentation.  I have been impressed by everything that has been said so far.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#JJ00400"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House.  It is a source of significant frustration that she has yet to publish the Future of Media Commission's report.  The co-operation and synergy between the commission and the new regulator were core issues for the joint committee when debating this Bill.  Here we are discussing the dissolution of the Broadcasting Authority of Ireland, yet the Parliament does not have to hand a report from the commission, which was set up by the Government at a cost to taxpayers in the State of &euro;400,000.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Fintan Warfield:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2458"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2458&amp;amp;pid=FintanWarfield&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I asked RT&Eacute; representatives when they were before the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Tourism, Culture, Arts, Sport and Media recently how they felt.  They said they were beyond frustrated that the report has not been published yet.  The Press Ombudsman was before the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Public Petitions, of which I am a member, and he expressed his concern that it had not been published yet.  The committee pre-legislative scrutiny report noted the notable overlap between the Future of Media Commission and the new regulator.  I urge the Minister to release the report to tell us what the Government's plan is for the future of media in this country. </p><p>I will turn to the individual complaints mechanism.  The Internet brings risk.  This Bill has identified the loss of personal data, exposure to harmful content, cyberbullying, negative effects on health and mental health, online grooming and extortion.  There is a scheme in the Bill for nominated bodies that will be able to notify the media commission about harmful content and non-compliance with the online safety codes.  However, that does not go far enough.  The Bill should specifically provide for an individual complaints mechanism to ensure citizens have access to an effective remedy.  When someone's rights are not respected by online providers, and that person has exhausted all appropriate channels with an online platform, the State should then have a mechanism in place to allow an effective remedy for the individual.  I appreciate the Minister has established an expert group to consider the issue.  It will report to her before 90 days at this point, but this work should have been completed in parallel with the pre-legislative scrutiny process.</p><p>I hope the Bill will not leave the Seanad before we get access to the advice from the expert group.  It is important for Senators to be able to consider the Bill with the advice from that expert group to hand.  I hope the Bill will not go to the D&aacute;il, be amended there and then return to this House.  While I welcome the piece about nominated bodies, I am not convinced such organisations, for example, NGOs, have the time or resources to do this type of work.  Having super-complainants is a useful provision, and one I understand social media companies have in place, but it is no harm to put that on a legislative footing.</p><p>I will refer briefly to public service programming and prominence.  It is something I brought up at the committee at numerous points.  The prominence of our public service broadcasters and public service media must be safeguarded in law.  This is particularly important when it comes to the Irish language.  We used to be able to turn on the television and the public service broadcaster would be right there.  It now takes multiple steps to find public service content.  It is important we maintain prime billing on viewing menus, for example, so the regulator can step in and ensure public service content is easy to find.  As I said, there are multiple steps a viewer has to take to find public service content now, whether that is through a Sky box and so on.  I do not want a situation where public service broadcasters are being drowned out.</p><p>The new media commission will have the power to impose financial sanctions on broadcasting services and designated online services.  I am mindful when I read these sanctions that another commissioner, the Data Protection Commissioner, has come in for international criticism for being too soft on big tech companies such as Facebook and Google.  Ms Frances Haugen said that Ireland faces a conflict of interest when regulating these companies.  The Government needs to get tough and this media commission needs to be tough on tech companies.  I am also concerned that the Minister of State at the Department of Enterprise, Trade and Employment, Deputy Robert Troy, has given confidentiality to Facebook and other tech companies when they meet that Department. </p><p>I would like to raise the issue of the ban on advertising to children.  I remember the Connemara film-maker, Bob Quinn, always fought against advertisements during children's programming when he was on the RT&Eacute; authority.  In 1970, he called for a complete ban on all advertising directed at children.  Recommendation 24 from the committee's pre-legislative scrutiny report is a ban on advertising to children online, including, at the very minimum, advertising of junk foods, alcohol, foods high in fat, salt or sugar, and gambling.  There should be an online safety code that addresses this issue.  I believe an explicit reference is required that makes it clear from the outset this will be included in the work of the new regulator because it is in public health interest of children.  The same applies to the content levy.  The media regulator will have the ability to introduce the levy but there is no date for that.  Does the Minister believe it will happen if we leave it and do not make explicit reference to its introduction at the start of the Bill?</p><p>My last point relates to public interest research based on the data provided by regulated platforms.  Ms Frances Haugen was a product manager researching misinformation on Facebook's civil integrity team.  She will be before the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Tourism, Culture, Arts, Sport and Media tomorrow.  She disclosed internal documents showing Facebook's internal research teams had evidence of harmful content.  Facebook did not share those findings with the public nor did it give external researchers access to data to confirm their findings.  We need transparent data access.  Researchers can only access what Facebook wants them to see.  Researchers can see patterns on Twitter because its data is public, but Facebook and YouTube do not readily share data with researchers and, therefore, there is a void in research, which is the first step in understanding what is going on under the lid of these platforms.  Recommendation 23 from the committee was that provision be made in legislation to enable public interest research based on data provided by regulated platforms.  Is the Minister satisfied the Bill provides for data to be supplied to independent researchers and academics?  I do not think it does.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1683" speakername="Marie Sherlock" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#KK00200"><p>I welcome the Minister to the Chamber.  I welcome the Bill and when it is enacted, its impact will be groundbreaking.  It is a long overdue development that recognises the multiple media forms that now exist in our lives.  It is important to say the establishment of the new media commission and the three commissioners will be vital in forcing our regulatory system to deal with the enormous challenges posed by online activity and recognising, as many others have said, that for many people on-demand audiovisual services now overtake the main broadcast media in how they consume broadcast content.</p> <p>Before I go into the detail of the Bill, it is important to acknowledge the enormous work undertaken by the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Tourism, Culture, Arts, Sport and Media.  I am not a member of that committee - I have sat in on its meetings a number of times - but I am certainly aware of the extensive number of hearings and the very detailed report and recommendations issued by it.  While some of the committee's recommendations were incorporated into the Bill before us, a number of them were not.  I am also conscious of the commitments to address some of the outstanding concerns, such as the report that has been commissioned into the individual complaints mechanism.  There are also concerns with regard to how much detail in the Bill relates to the online safety commissioner.  These are not peripheral but core issues.  There is a real question about the timing of this Bill coming before the House when these fundamental issues have not yet been fully addressed.  Like others, I would like these issues to be fully addressed and brought back to the House before this Bill is passed.  I hope it is not rushed through this House and into the D&aacute;il before those issues are fully resolved.</p> <p>Others have spoken about the issue of the absence of the individual complaints mechanism.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Marie Sherlock:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=MarieSherlock&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->To me there is a real issue about the point of this Bill if it cannot facilitate meaningful and direct recourse for those affected by online safety issues.  We have heard from groups like the Children&rsquo;s Rights Alliance, CyberSafeKids and the Irish Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Children, ISPCC, all having concerns that failure to have an individual complaints mechanism will perpetuate the harm online and, in particular, will leave children and other vulnerable persons exposed and unprotected by this Bill.  While I recognise that there is a provision for expert groups and NGOs to report, unless there is a direct recourse for individuals then this Bill will be failing in what it sets out to do, namely provide regulation and support to those affected by harmful online activity.</p><p>The following point is important to me.  While regulation and sanction of harmful online content is the most groundbreaking element of this Bill, when I look at the detail there is also a lack of ambition in certain elements of it.  Why has the Government shied away from naming non-criminal, harmful content such as advertising to children of gambling products and of high-fat, high-salt and high-sugar food products?  Instead of being brave and hardwiring a Bill on advertising to children of these products, we are told that responsibility for the regulation of advertising of these products lies with their line Departments, namely the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine or the Department of Justice.  There is an inconsistency at the heart of the Bill because the responsibility for online safety is rightly placed within the media commission; the online safety commissioner will be tasked with regulating content to ensure the online safety of children and adults and when it comes to some of the thorniest and most harmful online exposure, responsibility is sent back to the Departments.  To be fair to the Departments they are looking after the commercial interests of food production companies and other enterprises.  We can hardly expect a Department other than the Department of Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sport and Media to be a neutral arbiter on these issues, whereas we could expect an online safety commissioner and the media commission to have a strong role in this.  It is regrettable that outright bans are not named in this legislation.</p><p>The other big issue is the advertising of infant milk formula products.  A key point that has been made by the Baby Feeding Law Group Ireland is that this Bill should seek to protect all children and not just those who are old enough to consume digital or analogue advertising.  When I say all this, I recognise that there will always be demand for infant formula and mothers have a right to decide what is best for themselves and their families.  This is not about stigmatising choices but it is about protecting families from marketing that is purely driven by profit considerations, not by any interest in the advancement of public health.  That is why I strongly feel we should have an outright ban on the advertising of infant formula products for children up to the age of 36 months.  We know Ireland has been found wanting in comprehensively implementing the World Health Organization international code of marketing breastmilk substitutes and that we have had an ambivalent attitude towards the marketing of breast milk, marketing online and within some Irish hospitals.  There is an opportunity to introduce a ban within the legislation, not to commit to something that may be looked at down the road.  We also need to introduce a ban on the profiling or tracking of babies or children&rsquo;s data and anybody who has been pregnant over the last decade will tell you that if you become pregnant after a while your search history will start to throw up all sorts of advertising online.</p><p>The online world is only a safer place because of the incredible work of content moderators on various platforms.  Unfortunately we do not have any regulation of their work in this Bill.  While it could be argued that regulation of their work could be dealt with within health and safety legislation, the performance of content moderators is vital in the self-regulation of platforms in this country.  If we do not ensure that we have proper supports in place for self-regulation, that places an enormous pressure on the regulatory infrastructure, namely the media commission.  There is a serious need to look at how this Bill relates to content moderators.</p><p>I mention the overdue publication of the report of the Future of Media Commission..  There is a growing frustration that we have not seen that.  In my role as Labour Party spokesperson on media I talk to local and national media and we need to see that vision from Government.  I urge the Minister to press on with that publication.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#LL00200"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House.  She can hear the interest in this Bill as it is discussed.  For a long time there was a little bit of complacency among some of the major players in the tech industry around the idea that they would always be slightly ahead of Government and regulation and that this was an area of such complexity.  I remember being in a situation once when I was told that it is maths and that was used to say these areas are not in the scope of appropriate regulation.  We have seen that they are in the scope of appropriate regulation and that they are areas of responsibility for us as national and European legislators.</p><p>The online space does not exist separately; it exists in real spaces.  From the issues of data centres and where they are located, through to where and how data is processed, it is in the real world and in real jurisdictions and it is subject to real regulation.  We have instruments and the skills to do that regulation.  We have seen that in the general data protection regulation, GDPR.  We have heard about innovation and the regulatory innovation that Europe showed in GDPR was fundamental and incredibly important.  There is something we got right about that which I hope we can follow through with in how we treat the likes of the audiovisual and media services directive, the Online Safety and Media Regulation Bill 2022, the digital services and the algorithmic legislation when it comes through.  We took an approach with GDPR that avoided the twin dangers of a <i>laissez-faire</i>approach of market self-regulation and an authoritarian approach where the state owned all the data.  It is neither a matter of commercial nor state ownership.  Instead we took up an approach which was rights-based.  It was strong, regulatory, ambitious and also fundamentally rights-based.  We can do that here again and we need to make sure we do so, while improving the one place that GDPR has fallen down and where Ireland has unfortunately fallen down on GDPR, namely in implementation and enforcement.</p><p>In that context I will point to some of my recommendations and concerns, which will seem to go to either direction on this.  On the one side we need to be more ambitious in making sure that individuals are able to assert their data rights.  There must be an individual complaints mechanism and that will be core to this legislation, to its effectiveness and meaningfulness and to whether it sits legitimately side-by-side in a complementary way with what we did before.  There has to be an individual mechanism and in that I would suggest that we probably should not be looking at this on Committee Stage in the Seanad until we have that expert online safety group report back.  It was given 90 days from the end of January to report and its brief is to consider: &quot;whether it is practicable to include an individual complaints mechanism in the Bill and, if so, how this may be done&quot;.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Alice-Mary Higgins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2480"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2480&amp;amp;pid=AliceMaryHiggins&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->There has to be an individual complaints mechanism.  That was very clear from the committee scrutiny.  It is fundamental and I hope the discussion we have on Committee Stage is one on how there has to be such a mechanism.  That is important.<br/><br/>There are areas within regulations and codes where we can move ahead and give strong legislative protection that would be better, such as in the area of infant formula.  If one knows an issue is a concern, it is always better to have it in the primary legislation.  That is the strongest place we can have protection around areas such as infant formula, junk food, alcohol and gambling.  These are areas where we can now put proper protections in place in the primary legislation.<br/><br/>In the special space, we also need to have care that harmful practices or what gets defined as harmful is not entirely solely left to the commission and that it would come back to the Oireachtas.  What we do not want is that we have things we know are harmful and will not necessarily get captured or might be an overreach that get defined as harmful down the line and that creates inadvertent consequences or, potentially, suppression.  The legislation should be as clear as possible.<br/><br/>In that regard, a crucial issue is profiling and microtargeting of children.  The Minister will be aware this is recommendation 26 from the Oireachtas committee scrutiny which was very clear on profiling.  This issue is on its way.  We know it will be part of the Digital Services Act.  The European Parliament has voted to ban targeted advertising and profiling under the Act.<br/><br/>I would like if we could engage between now and Committee Stage.  This is already in Irish law because Senator Ruane and I, in section 30 of the Data Protection Act 2018, won an amendment which is in the law but the section was never commenced.  It explicitly banned, back in 2018, a company or corporate body processing personal data of children &quot;for the purposes of direct marketing ... or micro-targeting&quot;.  It was not perfectly worded.<br/><br/>We were told it would be refined.  However, it was not commenced and has not been refined.  I suggest we have a tool there we might need to revisit.  The precedent has already been set by the Oireachtas ahead of EU law.  This House determined it believed this should be a key concern and should be addressed, back in 2018.  I am sure we could do it better than it was worded in 2018, but it is important that mandate is a historical one.<br/><br/>I have concerns in terms of overreach on some of the issues, such as looking at how far warrants go and the kind of information.  Authorised officer powers need to be very carefully scrutinised, especially when it comes to interpersonal communication and cloud storage, for example.  There are a few gaps, which we will come to on Committee Stage.  If information is taken from somebody, he or she should be entitled to have a copy of what is taken.  I am a little concerned that we need some more checks and balances around the authorised officer powers with regard to that.<br/><br/>One of the very exciting things about the audiovisual and media services directive is the <i>exception culturelle</i>.  Senator McGahon spoke about the beginning being the US Communications Decency Act 1996.  Actually, 1993 and the <i>exception culturelle</i>are the fundamental origins of the AVMS directive.  The <i>exception culturelle </i>was the idea that culture is not solely commercial but that there is a right to participation in culture and diverse representation.<br/><br/>Many of the measures in the Bill around the levies and supporting public service broadcasting are not simply about market share for Europe.  They are around the idea of the right to cultural expression and participation for all citizens, including those with a disability, those for whom Irish Sign Language may be their main language and regional and rural communities.  I hope that we can be very ambitious in that section and reflect the spirit of the <i>exception culturelle</i>from 1993.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1638" speakername="Malcolm Byrne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#MM00200"><p>I thank the Minister for coming in with this vitally important legislation.  It is critical to how we define our society, culture and democracy.  There has been much reference already to the Oireachtas Joint Committee Tourism, Culture, Arts, Sport and Media and the work it has done on this Bill.  I have to say, along with Senators Cassells, Warfield and Carrigy, and our colleagues in the other House, we worked very closely in a collaborative way.  We put aside our party differences and realised how important this work was.</p> <p>I am very grateful, as I am sure all my colleagues are, that the Minister took on board most of the 33 recommendations from our committee, especially in the area of a strong and well-resourced online safety commissioner.  I also thank all of the witnesses who came before us and the officials from the Minister's Department who have done significant work on this.</p> <p>The Bill is so critical to our democracy and Second Stage debate is about the broad principles, but dealing with it on Committee Stage will be very important and analysing it section by section.  I hope that this debate is not rushed when it goes before the House.  I appreciate there is an urgency to some elements of this legislation, but sufficient time needs to be given to some of the debates around the issues.  Debates on these issues include the question of how one balances freedom of expression with responsibilities and tackling online harms and other issues to which some colleagues have already referred.  Being able to get philosophical concepts tied down into legal definitions will be challenging, but we must do it and get it right.</p> <p>I noted the Minister was somewhat specific in terms of staffing levels.  Colleagues have already referred to one of the challenges around the levels of resourcing.  If this agency is to be the one to act around the enforcement and oversight of the Digital Services Act, I am not convinced that 300 members of staff will be sufficient.  This is likely to be the most powerful regulator in the State or, certainly, one of them.  The Minister needs to ensure there is ambition, not just in staffing numbers, but in terms of the level of staffing.  We cannot have a situation, which has arisen with regard to the Data Protection Commissioner around the enforcement of data privacy, arising in this area.</p> <p>Senator McGahon is right about how this will go.  This regulator will be looking at regulating activity in the metaverse.  It will be dealing with a convergence of new technologies, ones about which we have not even thought.  We have to ensure the regulator is ahead of the curve.  I welcome that we are looking at codes, algorithmic decision making and the use of algorithms more widely.  That will certainly be important.</p> <p>My party and the Government strongly supports the introduction of a content levy.  We see its purpose as, very clearly, to support the vibrant independent production sector here in order that we can ensure Irish stories are told internationally.  It is important we know how this content levy will operate.  We need to have it in detail and in a way that will enhance and develop the Irish independent content creation sector.  </p> <p>I will turn to the issue we debated most which is the question of how we deal with online harms and safety.  I am sure the Minister will be aware this will probably be the biggest element of the debates we will have.  One of the most interesting discussions we had was with Mr. Julian Inman-Grant, the Australian eSafety Commissioner.  That office has been up and running for six years.  We can certainly learn a lot from what has happened and the experience in Australia.</p> <p>I understand the challenges around an individual complaints mechanism and I support it.  However, given the sheer volume of complaints, what one does not want, especially if we are regulating at a European level, is for a regulator to be overwhelmed.  We need to look at very clear definitions in the legislation around online harms.  A taxonomy of online harms needs to be drawn up.  We need to use technology and harness AI and other technologies to be able to tackle some of the problems we face.</p> <p>I appreciate why the Minister gave the 90 days to the expert group.  I am not sure it will necessarily be able to come up with all the answers within that period.  Similar to Senator Higgins, I have concerns around the terms of reference given to the group.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Malcolm Byrne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;MemberID=1111"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1111&amp;amp;pid=MalcolmByrne&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->One final point on it is something I will look to amend.  It is something we talked about with the students who came in, for instance, from Kinsale Community School and Tallaght Community School, around the idea of an online safety youth advisory council.  It is that we engage young people to be able to advise the online safety commissioner.  This is something we might explore further.</p><p>I sincerely thank the Minister.  I know she is committed to this Bill.  This is hugely important - I would even say one of the most important items of legislation that we could enact over the term of this Oireachtas.  I hope that, on Committee Stage, we have sufficient time to debate in detail the core philosophical questions that we have to address.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1665" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#NN00200"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire.  I welcome the Minister to the Chamber.</p> <p>I would like to acknowledge the work of the Oireachtas joint committee on this Bill.  It has been a lot of work for all the members in terms of preparing the report and I am glad to see that at least some of the recommendations that were advocated and recommended have been taken on board by the Minister.  Some of them are still under review as part of the ongoing work over the next period of time and that is important as well.</p> <p>I would make one point first, in relation to the commission itself.  Generally, when new agencies are being established, they are established with a CEO and a chief financial officer, CFO, and a team of civil servants, and a board of directors would oversee the work that they carry out.  This is the establishment of the commission, and perhaps it relates to its independence.  I do not know how or why that path was taken.  I am concerned in relation to the number of commissioners - less than three and not greater than six.  Is there a board that is overseeing the work of the commission as well or is the commission doing the work of the board?  It is unusual the way it is.  In any other experience that I have had with agencies, they have an overseeing board that is accountable.  In this case, there will be six commissioners who will be staff of the Coimisi&uacute;n na Me&aacute;n.  That whole process is somewhat strange.</p> <p>I welcome the establishment of the new regulator, Coimisi&uacute;n na Me&aacute;n, and the implementation of the EU services directive as well - the updated regulatory framework for broadcasting and on-demand audiovisual media.  No doubt times are changing and things are changing.  Certainly, we need to move with the times and ensure that there is regulation of all forms of media.  That is certainly to be welcomed.</p> <p>I welcome the initiatives that have taken place as well regarding the provision of the levies on content to be invested in Irish content.  Irish audiences, as Screen Ireland has said, are paying international online media services and to be able to charge a levy to ensure that that money is invested in original Irish content is certainly welcome.  However, there are concerns that the Bill does not state when this levy would start.  There would be concerns that we are missing out on valuable funds that could be invested in Irish content.</p> <p>I certainly welcome - perhaps this came from the committee as well - the provision in the powers and functions of the commission that the democratic values enshrined in the Constitution, especially those relating to rightful liberty of expression, are upheld, that the interests of the public, and in particular the interests of children, are protected, which is hugely important, and in the proposed new section 7(3)(d), that the commission shall promote and stimulate the development of programmes in the Irish language - t&aacute; s&eacute; sin f&iacute;or t&aacute;bhachtach - and that programmes relating to climate change and environmental sustainability are included.  I am wondering why those two latter points alone are included and if this should be the case for other areas such as, for example, programmes to encourage accurate portrayal of history and to encourage people, in particular, young people, to be made aware of or shown accurate historical content in an easier way to learn.  We are missing out in this country and across the world on our history in a wide range of areas and it is hugely important.  Over the past number of years, we have seen the proliferation of jargon around fake news.  That is an issue of concern.  I suppose it originated in a particular jurisdiction but the proliferation of fake news is an area of concern across the world.  Public service broadcasting is hugely important to provide accurate portrayal of the news, not one's opinion or one side's opinion.  The partisan media that are portrayed in the United States certainly are not something that I would like to see.  The facts should be the facts.  They should not be your facts or my facts; they should be just the facts.  There needs to be a reliable source of news, journalist integrity and a public service broadcast that can state what the indisputable facts are.  That is important.</p> <p>I welcome the Bill.  It is complex.  I acknowledge the amount of work that has gone into it and I certainly hope that there will be a fuller debate on Committee Stage on all relevant sections.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#NN00300"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House.  I thank the Minister for prioritising this important Bill and for all the work that she has put into it along with her officials.  I thank also the Oireachtas committee for the work it has put in, in terms of examining it.  I certainly appreciate the Minister's clarification on a number of issues at the start - it was very welcome - and her thorough analysis of the Bill and all of its parts.  I am certainly pleased to support this Bill in the House this evening.</p> <p>Media safety is so important.  The integrity, honesty and transparency that we attach to media and the need to know that they are all of those things are really important.  It certainly deserves a lot of focus on it.  While there are already significant regulatory and legal frameworks in place in relation to many online issues such as data protection and criminal justice responses to criminal activities online, there is a serious gap, both internationally and here in Ireland, when it comes to addressing harmful online content.  It is good to see that this new Bill will close the legal gap and it will establish a robust regulatory framework to deal with the spread of harmful online content.</p> <p>The fact that this Bill will establish a new regulator, a multi-person media commission to which an online safety commissioner will be appointed, is very welcome.</p> <p>Having a strong, robust and reliable media and social media is so important, especially in light of the key role that the media played during the Covid pandemic.  The considerable role that the media performed in dispersing key Covid and health messaging shows the vital role that they play within our society when used correctly and in a positive manner.  You cannot beat the media in terms of the dispersal of accurate and true information.  Ensuring that citizens are provided with accurate and comprehensive information is of vital importance.  Citizens need to be well informed of the goings on within their country.  The media are a key link between decision-makers and the people but they also are a vulnerable one.  Many people rely on them for information from the Government and for other factual content and it is important that they are getting correct and reliable information.</p> <p>While media freedom is at the core of democracy, it is paramount that there is little or no disinformation being spread by the media.  The need for professionalism and fact-checking is crucial when giving information is vital, especially in times of crisis.  I am pleased to hear that Ireland ranks 12th out of 180 countries regarding the 2021 World Press Freedom Index.  This proves our dedication to free media and our media's dedication to combating disinformation.  However, we must always remain vigilant and this Bill certainly helps us to do that.</p> <p>We have seen the power of disinformation in recent years, months and, would I say, days, especially in terms of recent US presidential elections and the concerted efforts made by Russia to utilise modern media and social media platforms to spread misinformation and to combat the reliability of certain media.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Fiona O'Loughlin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2441"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2441&amp;amp;pid=FionaOLoughlin&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Online safety is obviously a key part of this.  Especially in the debate we had around Coco's Law, there was a really strong demand for an online safety commissioner.  That is the key part of this for me.  A significant proportion of our lives happen online nowadays and this is particularly true for those of us in public office.  We all need to be vigilant about our own safety and know the signs to look out for online.  This is especially important for our younger generations.  We must protect our young people, children and teenagers.  I refer to those who are growing up online, engaging in their first relationships online and using online tools and social media in their daily lives.  We must ensure that we have a regulatory framework that is fit to purpose but also that we are educating our young people about how to conduct themselves online in a very safe way.  I have every confidence this Bill will go a long way to doing that.  When it gets to Committee Stage we will look at all the detail, much more will be examined and there will be further analysis.  I welcome this Bill reaching Second Stage and thank the Minister for the work she has put into it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1648" speakername="Emer Currie" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#OO00200"><p>I welcome the Minister.  I thank the joint committee for putting a huge amount of work into this.  That includes the report and the numerous meetings it had.  I am sorry I missed it and that I am not on the committee as it has been very interesting.  However, I worked in advertising and marketing for 15 years so I know how important this Bill is and how much it is needed.  It will be one of the most important Bills we work on during this mandate.  We must take proper account of the influence of new media.  I was watching "Pam and Tommy" on Disney+ over the weekend.  I watched how that was part of the explosion of the Internet.  It reminded me of how important this Bill is and how old that seems, but this has only happened over the past couple of decades.  The Bill is absolutely necessary.  This should be the time responsible digital citizenship catches up with unregulated online platforms and, therefore, I completely get how significant this is.</p> <p>We have heard all the good reasons for this around online safety, bullying, the influence on diets and image and the list goes on.  I do not like referencing when other Senators say things I think inappropriate but I have an issue with a Senator saying we are here because parents are not doing their job.  I give my phone to my seven-year-old and I know what she is watching.  Giving a child a phone, under supervision of a parent, is not a bad thing to do.  We are not here to judge people.  If we are going to recognise we need laws and rights for children in the real world then why would they not need them online?  We have recognised the online world is the Wild West so we either provide rights and regulations there or we leave it as it is, and for me that is not an option.  This is indeed about protecting rights but it should not be about judging parents.</p> <p>On aspects of the Bill, I agree with what Senators have said about the individual or direct complaints mechanism.  We have a huge responsibility here not just to our citizens but because we are tech leaders, this has an impact on 27 other member states and we must rise to that challenge.  I understand where the Minister is coming from and welcome the report the expert group is doing but if we want to see the step change we need this must be part of it.  While initially it might take significant resources, there should be a standard that is set out and that changes behaviour.  Similar to what other Senators have said, this is not about us being reactive but about us becoming proactive and investing in keeping up with technology and proactively challenging the damaging algorithms that are out there.</p> <p>On community radio, I have been asked to request that the scheme for professional journalists on practices in community sound broadcasting be extended to television as well.  I ask that there be more specificity about what those schemes are with respect to the monetary value and how many of them there will be for community radio, which is a huge and important part of the media landscape.</p> <p>I have one last point; I apologise as I am running out of time.  I agree we need an explicit reference to banning online advertising of junk food, alcohol and gambling.  I worked in the industry and the TV and radio code is not effective enough.  Companies had to get their ads approved when I worked in the industry.  They had to be approved by RT&Eacute; for radio and TV.  That does not happen in the online space.  It has been recognised the BAI needed to address it and it did not because of this Bill.  Children do not watch TV just up until 6 p.m. with their parents and it is not just children's programmes, where TV is concerned.  With online, we must definitely look at the recommendations of the committee and enforce them in that regard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#OO00300"><p>The Bill will, among other things, establish a new regulator and multi-person media commission, to which an online safety commissioner will be appointed.  While there are significant regulatory and legal frameworks in place to address many online issues such as data protection and criminal justice responses to criminal activities online, there is a serious gap in Ireland and internationally when it comes to addressing harmful online content.  This new law will close that legal gap and establish a robust regulatory framework to deal with the spread of harmful online content.  The commissioner will govern this new framework through binding online safety codes and robust compliance, enforcement and sanction powers.  Online safety codes will deal with a wide range of issues, including measures to be taken by online services to tackle the availability of harmful online content, such as cyberbullying material, on their services.  The media commission will replace the BAI and be responsible for overseeing updated regulations for broadcasting and video-on-demand services and a new regulatory framework for online safety created by the Bill.  The Bill will also transpose the revised audiovisual media service directive, AVMSD, into Irish law, including the regulation of video sharing platform services as part of the regulatory framework for online safety.  As the Minister pointed out, harmful online content will be defined by reference to defined categories of content, including a category containing a schedule of criminal offences and three further categories relating to cyberbullying, the promotion of suicide and self-harm and the promotion of eating disorders.</p> <p>I have every belief the Minister is strong and resilient about this Bill.  I have no doubt she will see this through.  I assure her that the public very much welcome this Bill.  I will be honest.  Though they do not say it do us, many families are frozen by fear.  Do I take the phone off my youngster?  Do I talk to them?  If I do that, what way should I approach it?  There is a horrendous fear out there.  The Minister and the Government are bringing forward robust legislation, which I agree may need to go though Committee Stage a little slowly so we cover every aspect of it.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Eugene Murphy:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2444"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2444&amp;amp;pid=EugeneMurphy&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Once people see it going through and an effort by all of us to put this in place, I think they will be very happy.  Ms Frances Haugen is a hero in my eyes.  She is travelling the world, informing us and others of what is going on.  Remember, she is coming from the inside out.  She had a very well-paid and well-to-do job.  She took a huge decision to do what she is doing.  We should be grateful and thankful to her.  I think she will be around the Oireachtas tomorrow.  </p><p>To be honest, I do not have much trust in the tech companies.  They create many jobs here and many people have good employment with them and I acknowledge that.  However, I, like many of the Members, have had family deeply traumatised because of big tech companies failing to act and deal with material that was vile, evil and downright threatening.  This has happened to thousands of people.  We heard on RT&Eacute; over the weekend of those vile threats to people in Galway involved in politics.  </p><p>The Bill is strong and if necessary, we can make further improvements to further strengthen it.  We must all acknowledge, perhaps sometimes we are afraid to say it, that misinformation is all over our political system.  It is doing enormous damage to democracy.  We always had the cut and thrust of politics.  What comes up now on social media is very damaging.  What is annoying is that so many people believe the most outrageous lies that come up there.  Therefore, we are in a very difficult situation.</p><p>I reiterate that the Minister and the Oireachtas committee deserve much praise.  I have no doubt we are doing the right thing.  I would be careful about saying parents have responsibilities.  While they do, we are in a very different world with social media.  We all know its good aspects but there are really bad aspects of it.  I will go back to what I said earlier, which is that many families are frozen with fear and they will very much welcome this lead being taken by the Minister and the Government.  I hope it pays dividends.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1693" speakername="Pauline O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#PP00200"><p>I welcome the Minister.  This Bill is well overdue and we can all acknowledge that.  It is also one of the most comprehensive legislative measures in the world when it comes to dealing with social media.  Too often we come into the Seanad Chamber and say that the law is not in the same place as people are.  This Bill acts as a vanguard when it comes to online safety for children and, indeed, all of us.  We said the same thing when it came to the Climate Action and Low Carbon Development (Amendment) Act and now we have legislation here to which people all over the world will point and they will say that Ireland is a leader when it comes to tackling the problems.</p> <p>I often say that I believe children should be educated in an online world because this is the way we all socialise now.  Let us be honest about it.  With that comes danger, particularly around advertising.  We know that we are targeted more and more than we ever were before when it comes to advertising.  This Bill listens to the stakeholders.  A significant amount of time was spent in pre-legislative scrutiny and this is the first Government to take the time with pre-legislative scrutiny of all of these Bills.  The Bill is being welcomed by a number of organisations, which is to the credit of the Minister and the Oireachtas joint committee.  Thirty-three of the recommendations were taken on board by the Department, which just goes to show the seriousness with which the Government and the Minister&rsquo;s Department is taking the work of the Oireachtas committee and the stakeholders and witnesses that came before it.  </p> <p>We have to be honest about it and state there are two sides to the coin.  There are those who will say that we need freedom of expression and those who will say that we have to regulate something that can cause danger.  In the first instance, this Bill refers to liberty of expression, which is unusual in legislation, but it also looks to be flexible.  The Minister has taken on board some of the concerns that organisations had and she went beyond where the legislation will go by setting up an expert group on the safety of children online.  That, again, is the right thing to do.  </p> <p>The Bill is a massive 146 pages long.  As a lawyer myself, I note every single word matters.  Some 146 pages of words that have been well thought through and comprehensive but are flexible enough to be able to adjust the situation that we all find ourselves in is exactly what we need at this point.  </p> <p>There is always room for improvement.  I would love to see more on infant formula, which was one of the suggestions in the Oireachtas joint committee and something about which I feel very passionately, as does the Minister.  On thinking back, I have been a breastfeeding advocate and set up breastfeeding support groups with friends in the past.  The landscape has changed and it is not just what we see on the breaks as we watch television programmes.  It is now at 3 a.m., when we are desperate and have a child who will not sleep and we are searching online and looking for something for mastitis or something to make the child fall asleep.  That is when we are being assaulted by online advertising saying that it has the answer and it is something that can be sold to us.  That is where the danger lies for all of us.  Therefore, we have to be agile enough.  Setting up expert groups on the back of this legislation is agile enough but I would love to hear the Minister&rsquo;s thoughts on that and what we can do.  We do not know all of the answers now, even with this legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#PP00300"><p>This is extremely important legislation.  It is probably some of the most important legislation that we will debate in this House because of the far-reaching effects it will have on people&rsquo;s lives.  With that, I would like to thank the Minister for coming in today.  It just shows how important this piece of work is, that the Minister is here with us.  I commend the manner in which she is running her Department and dealing with issues.</p> <p>Given that Internet companies are unable to regulate themselves and have clearly failed to do so, it is time that a country stood up and regulated the tech companies.  That is what we are trying to achieve in this Bill. </p> <p>The Acting Chair, Senator Cassells, worked in local media for many years.  In those days, there was integrity, decency and a sense of responsibility.  All of that has, unfortunately, gone out the window when it comes to social media.  There are absolutely good elements to social media.  Many people have connected in and through social media in a way that would have only been dreamt of ten, 20 or 30 years ago.  It is extremely important when it comes to issues such as crowdfunding, GoFundMe, raising awareness on issues, running campaigns and so on.  </p> <p>However, there is a dirty, rotten side to it.  That dirty, rotten side is where the fake news, terrorists and people who want to humiliate, bully, harass and intimidate have a forum behind a keyboard where they can do it with anonymity and get away with it.  They have been allowed to get away with it by the big tech companies that are more interested in their billions than in regulating the industry.  Therefore, I welcome this Bill.  It is a wonderful piece of work.  I want to commend the Oireachtas committee on the work it has done because that work has gone on over a protracted period.  </p> <p>When one opens a bank account, one has to have forms of identification.  One has to have a passport, a driver&rsquo;s licence and so on.  I often wonder why somebody is allowed to open a social media account without verifiable proof as to their identity and a traceability that if it is abused and used for wrongful purposes, it could be traced and linked back to somebody.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Martin Conway:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2347"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2347&amp;amp;pid=MartinConway&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->When someone buys a mobile phone and opens an account, he or she has to go through those processes.  Unfortunately, that does not happen with disposable mobile phones, although I think it should.  If somebody wishes to open a Facebook, Twitter, Instagram or any other social media account, there should be a verifiable, four- or five-step process.  Technology is wonderful, so why can it not do that?  It is because the companies do not want to do it.  If somebody under the age of 18 wishes to open an account, his or her parents should have to provide multiple forms of identification and take responsibility for the account.  Of course, this does not suit the tech companies.</p><p>I am happy our country is taking a lead on this.  We have taken a lead on many different issues over the years.  Given some of the social change this country has led, with the support of popular referendums, we can do it.  This legislation is another example of us standing up to the world and saying this is not right.  Our small country is going to change it, and when that happens, others will follow.  I wish the legislation well.  I am glad there was a productive, meaningful and wholehearted engagement on it during this debate.  I look forward to it being refined and improved and I wish the Minister well with it.  It is probably one of the most important items of legislation she will bring through during this term of Government.  We cannot forget about local media and the challenges it faces in trying to embrace social media because there is no money in it for local media.  That is why we need a root-and-branch review of the entire licensing system, with the introduction of a household media charge, because that will bring in more money and ensure we can resource public service broadcasting, not just at national level but at local level as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1471" speakername="Catherine Martin" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#QQ00200"><p>I thank the Senators for their valuable contributions.  The constructive approach demonstrated during the debate reflects our shared determination to put in place an effective regulatory framework for online safety and audiovisual on-demand services.  It builds on the intensive scrutiny the Joint Committee on Tourism, Culture, Arts, Sport and Media gave to the general scheme of the Bill last year.  The diverse range of issues raised on the floor in the past few hours highlights both the scale of the Bill and the fact it will break new ground regulating sectors that have so far not been subject to oversight.  As such, it represents an important step into a new frontier of lawmaking.  I agree with Senator McGahon that this Bill is not the final word when it comes to legislation in respect of the online world but rather the first of many in the coming years as more legislation comes from Europe.</p> <p>I reiterate the core contents and objectives of the Bill.  It will ensure we are all exposed to far less harmful online content and that online services will be required by law to respond to, and robustly deal with, complaints when they are made.  While the Bill will not and cannot address every issue of concern arising from the online world, it will create a robust and adaptable framework for accountability that can be amended and expanded over time to match the pace at which, as Senator McGahon mentioned, the tech world moves.  This framework will be enforced by Coimisi&uacute;n na Me&aacute;n, which will include an online safety commissioner and have one of the most modern and robust suites of regulatory powers in Irish law.  In providing a basis and starting point for the regulation of harmful online content, the establishment of Coimisi&uacute;n na Me&aacute;n is the most vital part of the Bill.  In regard to broadcasters and streaming services, the Bill is fundamentally about the modernisation of the regulatory environment, enabling the commission to deal with the continuing changes in how we engage with and support our media in Ireland.</p> <p>The Bill has a critical EU law dimension, given it will transpose the revised audiovisual media service directive, which has strongly informed the underpinnings of the coimisi&uacute;n.  As Senators will be aware, given the complexity of this legislation, we missed the transposition deadline for the directive, which is one reason I am especially keen to see the legislation progress through the Houses to enactment as soon as possible.  Having said that, I am committed to comprehensive debate in this House on Committee and Report Stages, which will provide opportunities for us to discuss each section of the Bill and any amendments in further detail.</p> <p>In the time that remains, I will endeavour to address the issues raised by various Senators.  I thank Senators Martin, Cassells, McGahon, Warfield, Sherlock and Higgins for raising the individual complaints mechanism, a matter I have been considering closely for some time.  The issue of providing for avenues of redress against individual pieces of content in the online world is complex.  The approach in the Bill as published is to provide Coimisi&uacute;n na Me&aacute;n with the power, through the making of binding online safety codes, to require that regulated online services have effective complaints mechanism in place, with powers of audit and investigation in that respect.  In addition, the Bill provides that the coimisi&uacute;n shall establish a super-complaints scheme under which bodies such as NGOs or other expert groups may be nominated to notify the commission of matters relating to online safety, including in respect of the availability of harmful online content.</p> <p>There are practical issues with providing the online safety commissioner with an almost ombudsman-like role in this regard, including the volume of content online, the fact it will regulate some services on an EU-wide basis, issues of due process and questions of how quickly decisions could reasonably be made.  However, in light of the recommendations of the Oireachtas joint committee in the pre-legislative scrutiny report on the general scheme of the Bill, I am examining how these issues can be addressed.  As I set out at the start of the debate, this is why I established an expert group to report to me within 90 days on these matters, with recommendations I may use as the basis for an amendment to introduce an individual complaints mechanism.  The terms of reference of the expert group are very much focused on the practicalities of whether the individual complaints mechanism can work.  Senator Malcolm Byrne mentioned the Australian e-safety commissioner, and this group will engage with that commissioner.  I had hoped the Australian e-safety commissioner could be a member of the group but she was not available.  Instead, she has committed to engaging with the expert group, which is important.  As I have said on many occasions, if an individual complaints mechanism can be provided for in the Bill, I will ensure that is done.  I met the expert advisory group and made clear at our first meeting that that was my intention.</p> <p>Given the timeline set out in the terms of reference for the group, I expect to receive the report at the end of April and then consider whether and what amendments will be required in the context of Committee Stage in the D&aacute;il.  Taking account of the work of the expert groups under way, I do not want to pre-empt or prejudge any recommendations it may make, although I reiterate I am committed to a full and open discussion of any Government amendments made in the D&aacute;il when the Bill, as amended, is returned to this House.</p> <p>Senator Keogan raised the issue of the commission being funded from the licence fee.  The Bill will enable this but not require it.  It is carried over from the Broadcasting (Amendment) Bill 2019 and will allow the broadcasting levy to be reduced for broadcasters, including independent radio.  To clarify, TG4 is not funded from the licence fee.  Senators Keogan and Pauline O'Reilly spoke about how a rights-based approach has been taken in the Bill, which will underpin the work of Coimisi&uacute;n na Me&aacute;n.  This means there will be a careful balance between the need to safeguard freedom of expression while taking into account that children and other members of the public need to be safeguarded.  Their rights matter too.</p> <p>Senators Martin, McGahon, Warfield, Kyne, O'Loughlin and Murphy raised the issue of disinformation.  This is, of course, a significant and complex issue that requires a distinct and targeted response.  The EU is reviewing the code of practice on disinformation in order to strengthen it and to link it to the forthcoming Digital Services Act, which will set out the standards for platforms in dealing with these issues.  The code of practice, a European Commission imitative, has involved a range of online platforms, leading social networks, advertisers and advertising industry players to sign up to self-regulatory standards to fight disinformation.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Catherine Martin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2425"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2425&amp;amp;pid=CatherineMartin&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The commission intends that the code will evolve into a co-regulatory instrument under the Digital Services Act.  In addition, the European Commission has established the European Digital Media Observatory, including a hub in Dublin City University, which has been tasked with monitoring the implementation of the code.</p><p>Senator Sherlock asked about specifying the role of the online safety commissioner.  This is primarily a drafting issue.  During the drafting process, legal advice was given that explicitly carving out specific roles within the multi-commissioner model could create difficulties if, for example, a commissioner was ill or if we wanted to appoint more than one online safety commissioner to an coimisi&uacute;n.  I am looking at how these issues can be overcome and will table an amendment to the Bill to address this matter.  In any case, it is my intention, and that of the Government, to advertise for, and recruit, an online safety commissioner this year through an open, transparent and effective process managed by the Public Appointments Service.  Work is under way in this regard. </p><p>Senator Kyne questioned why this would be a commission and not a board.  This is the model for many regulators.  For example, the Competition and Consumer Protection Commission has an executive chair and a number of commissioners, while ComReg and the Commission for Regulation of Utilities also have a multi-person commission model.</p><p>Senator Malcolm Byrne raised the issue of youth advisory groups.  The Bill, I am glad, provides for advisory committees to coimisi&uacute;n na me&aacute;n to be established.</p><p>Senator O'Loughlin asked about the educational role of the media commission.  The online safety commissioner will have a role in carrying out educational initiatives such as public information campaigns and I will work with existing educational bodies such as the Department of Education, webwise.ie and the National Council for Curriculum and Assessment on this.  The commissioner will also be able to endorse third-party providers of online safety educational materials, which will help schools source appropriate and robust online safety materials for students.</p><p>Senators Cassells and Warfield raised the Future of Media Commission report.  The programme for Government, Our Shared Future, provided for the establishment of the commission to consider the future of print, broadcast and online media.  This was in recognition of the challenges facing the media sector, such as falling advertising revenue arising from the shift in consumption patterns due to evolving technology.  The commission was tasked with making recommendations to the Taoiseach and myself to ensure that the future funding of public service broadcasting could be sustainable, give security of funding, ensure independent editorial oversight and deliver value for money to the public.  The commission completed its work last autumn and submitted its report to the Taoiseach and me.  As Senators can imagine, the report's recommendations are far-reaching and will inform media and broadcasting policy in the coming years.  The commission's recommendations require careful and detailed consideration, particularly in light of a range of other complex and interrelated issues that will require decisions by the Government in the wider media and digital space.  It is intended that the report be brought to Government for consideration shortly.</p><p>Senators Cassells, McGahon and Malcolm Byrne raised the issue of staffing.  Some &euro;5.5 million was secured as part of budget 2022 to establish the media commission on an administrative basis prior to the enactment of the Bill.  This funding will help in the recruitment of key personnel.  I previously stated that staffing of approximately 120 will be required during the start-up phase of the media commission.  In the longer term, I estimate that the commission will require in excess of the 300 I mentioned at the beginning of the debate to fully operationalise its envisaged functions.  I anticipate the need for additional staff, should the commission be assigned further functions in the future, including in respect of upcoming EU legislation.  Of course these staff would need to have specific expertise.  That goes without saying.</p><p>With regard to the data tracking issue raised by Senator Sherlock, that is a different matter from content regulation and lies with the Data Protection Commissioner.  However, the Bill provides for co-operation between the online safety commissioner, coimisi&uacute;n na me&aacute;n and other regulators. </p><p>Senators Cassells, Warfield, Sherlock, Higgins, Currie and Pauline O'Reilly raised bans on the advertising of gambling, alcohol, foods high in fat, salt or sugar, or HFSS foods, and infant formula, particularly with regard to advertising to children.  It is not a question of bravery.  These are significant and cross-cutting matters that bring together a range of different policy areas under different Ministers.  For example, the regulation of gambling advertising is set out in the recently published general scheme of the gambling regulation Bill, which comes under the Department of Justice.  Infant formula, food and alcohol advertising are policy areas under the Departments of Agriculture, Food and the Marine and Health and are already subject to extensive regulation through, for example, the Public Health (Alcohol) Act 2018.  While my officials are engaging with officials from other relevant Departments on these matters, it is clear that the functions and expertise for these policy areas lies more appropriately with those Departments.  The online safety commissioner will have a role in regulating commercial advertising on certain online services through its online safety codes.  Just as the BAI does currently, the commissioner will engage with health experts and others in developing these codes and will reflect public policy in this regard.  This will also be the case in respect of media codes and rules that will apply to broadcasters and video on-demand services.</p><p>Senator Higgins raised section 30 of the Data Protection Act, which banned processing of children's data but was never commenced.  This confirms that the issue has a strong data protection dimension.  The regulators will collaborate.  The Senator also raised the potential overreach.  The powers have been scrutinised by our legal advisers but I am open to listening to concerns in that regard.</p><p>The Bill provides for measures to ensure the prominence and findability of public service content.  I agree with Senator Warfield that this is an important matter as the volume of content and services expands.  On the matter of data and access for researchers, this will be provided for in the Digital Services Act.</p><p>Senator Conway raised age verification for children online.  There is a real issue with young children accessing online services that simply were not designed with them in mind.  It is an issue of which I am particularly aware, both as a parent of young children and as chair of the National Advisory Council for Online Safety, which recently released a comprehensive report on children's online safety.  We need to find workable solutions to the negative uses of online spaces.  Anonymity raises a number of complex issues, including privacy and data protection matters that would need to be resolved before a solution could be effectively implemented.  In this regard, an EU-funded pilot programme called euCONSENT is in development.  That pilot aims to deliver a system for online age verification and parental consent that balances the rights of children with the need to protect them from online harm and age-inappropriate content.  The outcome of this pilot will inform any approach taken to this issue at EU and national level.  I will ask an coimisi&uacute;n to look at this issue as a priority and to identify potential options and solutions to dealing with this complex issue.  As I said previously, not everything can be dealt with in a single Bill but what matters now is that we have the framework in place.</p><p>Senators Cassells, Warfield, Malcolm Byrne and Kyne raised the issue of the content production levy.  The revised AVMSD provides member states with the option of introducing a levy on television broadcasting and video on-demand services to fund audiovisual content production.  To exercise this option, section 53 of the legislation provides that coimisi&uacute;n na me&aacute;n may introduce a content production levy and a content production scheme to fund the production of European works, including Irish works.  The proceeds of any such levy would go into a content production scheme, which producers could apply for funding from.  It would be similar to the sound and vision fund.  It is intended that this levy would be introduced by the comisi&uacute;n, subject to an assessment of its viability and whether it would have negative effects.</p><p>As I said earlier, there are risks as well as benefits here for the Irish audiovisual sector.  In line with EU law, any levy introduced under the Bill must be imposed equally on all services targeting the Irish market, including Irish services and those based outside Ireland.  That means that Irish media service providers such as RT&Eacute; or Virgin Media Television would also be subject to this levy.  In addition, both Irish services and those based in other member states of any size will then be eligible to apply for the content production fund established as a result of the levy.  Any levy will only apply to income earned within this State.  For example, for a provider such as Netflix, which earns 2% of its overall EU revenues in this State, the levy can only apply to that 2%.  The aforementioned factors could significantly constrain the overall positive impact on the potential level of additional funding for Irish content.</p><p>I was asked if I would set out the exact percentages and the process involved with the levy in the legislation.  That approach would be inflexible and an coimisi&uacute;n, as an independent body, should have the power to design and enforce the levy and change it over time.  I expect that an examination of the content levy will be among the priorities of an coimisi&uacute;n upon its establishment.</p><p>I am almost out of time.  I apologise to those who raised issues I did not address.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Catherine Martin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2425"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2425&amp;amp;pid=CatherineMartin&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I look forward to a constructive and detailed debate.  As I said, I am committed to that debate.  The interest Senators have shown, their attendance and their varied contributions show how important this legislation is to many Senators.  I look forward to debating it further.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#SS00200"><p>I thank the Minister for her comprehensive response and for clearly engaging with the arguments put forward.  I could not help thinking while she was speaking that it must be unique to have a Minister address the House with her brother, a distinguished Member, listening.  It is a unique and wonderful occasion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.132" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#SS00400"><p>When is it proposed to take Committee Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1693" speakername="Pauline O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#SS00500"><p>Next Tuesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#SS00550"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.136" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Committee Stage ordered for Tuesday, 1 March 2022.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.137" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#SS00700">Electricity Costs (Domestic Electricity Accounts) Emergency Measures Bill 2022: Committee and Remaining Stages</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.138" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>SECTION 1</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#SS00900"><p>I welcome the Minister for the Environment, Climate and Communications, Deputy Eamon Ryan, to the House.  Amendments Nos. 1, 7, 8, 11 to 13, inclusive, 15 and 24 are related and may be discussed together.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.140" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Amendment No. 1 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.141" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Section 1 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.142" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>SECTION 2</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#SS01200"><p>Amendments Nos. 2 and 9 are related and may be discussed together.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.144" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Amendment No. 2 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#SS01400"><p>Amendment No. 3 is deemed out of order as it imposes a potential charge on the Exchequer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.146" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Amendment No. 3 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#SS01600"><p>Amendments Nos. 4 and 21 are related and may be discussed together.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.148" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Amendment No. 4 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#SS01800"><p>Amendment No. 5 is deemed out of order as it imposes a potential charge on the Exchequer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.150" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Amendment No. 5 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#SS02000"><p>Amendments Nos. 6 and 17 are related and may be discussed together by agreement.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.152" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 6:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.153" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#SS02300"><p>I move amendment No. 7:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 4, line 32, to delete &ldquo;domestic electricity accounts&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;active domestic electricity accounts&rdquo;.  </blockquote> <p>This amendment is linked to amendment No. 1.  It substitutes the words &quot;active domestic electricity accounts&quot; for the words &quot;domestic electricity accounts&quot;.  This is tied to the proposal in amendment No. 1 to use the information the ESB has on the use of electricity in households.  This information, which is given to the Central Statistics Office, CSO, is used to identify which homes may be vacant homes or holiday homes.  Amendment No. 1 provides that an amount of energy consumption be used to identify holiday homes.  It would, therefore, allow the measure to be slightly more targeted and would prevent those who have holiday homes from receiving the rebate, or do a decent job of trying to identify those who have holiday homes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#SS02400"><p>We exercised discretion in allowing the Senator to speak to the amendment.  Does the Minister wish to respond?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#SS02500"><p>While I understand the purpose of the amendment, we cannot accept it because this as an emergency measure and we want to be quick.  There is benefit in universality.  It is much easier, much quicker and much less expensive.  We have the electricity meter or billing system to be able to action this.  If we start trying to separate out a number of exceptions, we would be stuck in appeals and a whole range of other processes.  This would put back the delivery of this important financial payment to people at a particularly hard time.  I am afraid, therefore, that we cannot accept the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.157" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#SS02700"><p>I move amendment No. 8.</p> <blockquote> 	In page 4, line 36, to delete &ldquo;domestic electricity accounts&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;active domestic electricity accounts&rdquo;.  </blockquote> <p>I have spoken to this amendment, which is the same as amendment No. 7.  It proposes to delete the words &quot;domestic electricity accounts&quot; and substitute the words &quot;active domestic electricity accounts&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#TT00100"><p>I have a similar response, I am afraid.  I cannot accept the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.160" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#TT00400"><p>I move amendment No. 9:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 4, between lines 37 and 38, to insert the following:   	&ldquo;(e) The Minister shall make provision in the Electricity Costs Emergency Benefit Scheme to identify those who own holiday homes or multiple properties and put in place a mechanism to ensure such individuals do not receive more than one electricity costs emergency benefit payment. <br /><br />(f) The Minister shall make provision in the Electricity Costs Emergency Benefit Scheme to identify those who are renting, to ensure renters receive the benefit of the electricity costs emergency benefit payment, and the Minister shall put in place a dispute resolution mechanism to resolve any disputes between renters and their landlords or property management companies over the electricity costs emergency benefit payment. <br /><br />(g) The Minister shall make provision in the Electricity Costs Emergency Benefit Scheme to ensure those who do not need the financial support from the electricity costs emergency benefit payment, can inform their electricity supplier to redirect their electricity costs emergency benefit payment to a charity that supports and helps those living in energy poverty.&rdquo;.  </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1672" speakername="Rebecca Moynihan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#TT00500"><p>I wish to come in on amendment No. 2.  I had expected to hear the bells go off but I did not.  Hence, I am little late.</p> <p>These amendments are related.  They are specifically around ensuring that people who are paying the electricity bill, particularly those who are in rented accommodation, are the ones that will benefit from this measure.  I understand that it is an emergency measure.  I take the Minister&rsquo;s points about universality being important.  However, universality also needs to apply to people who are not necessarily the named person on the bill or the final payee, but to those who are renting and, therefore, are the people who are paying.  I ask the Minister to accept this or, if possible, to introduce another regulation for renters, as well as for people who are paying an electricity bill, who are often in housing insecurity and who are paying insanely high rents, which are going up month-on-month.  They should be the people to benefit from this cost-of-living measure, particularly regarding heating.  Many renters around this country are now afraid to turn on their heating.  This is because they are being hit with the double whammy of rental increases and the massive increase in the price of heating.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.163" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#TT00700"><p>Amendment No. 10 is deemed out of order as a potential charge on the Revenue Commissioners.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.165" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Amendment No. 10 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.166" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Section 2, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.167" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>SECTION 3</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#TT01000"><p>Amendment No. 11 has already been discussed with amendment No. 1.  We will again exercise the same discretion both ways.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#TT01100"><p>I move amendment No. 11:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 5, line 9, to delete &ldquo;domestic electricity accounts&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;active domestic electricity accounts&rdquo;. </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.170" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.171" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Section 3 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.172" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>SECTION 4</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.173" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#TT01600"><p>I move amendment No. 12:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 5, lines 14 and 15, to delete &ldquo;domestic electricity accounts&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;active domestic electricity accounts&rdquo;. </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.174" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#TT01900"><p>I move amendment No. 13:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 5, lines 29 and 30, to delete &ldquo;domestic electricity account&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;active domestic electricity account&rdquo;. </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#TT02000"><p>I cannot accept the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.177" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#TT02200"><p>Amendment No. 14 is deemed out of order as a potential charge on the Revenue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.179" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Amendment No. 14 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.180" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Section 4 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.181" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>SECTION 5</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.182" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#TT02700"><p>I move amendment No. 15:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 7, line 7, to delete &ldquo;domestic electricity account&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;active domestic electricity account&rdquo;. </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.183" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.184" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#TT02900"><p>Amendment No. 16 is deemed out of order as a potential charge on the Revenue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.185" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Amendment No. 16 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.186" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 17:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.187" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#TT03300"><p>Amendment No. 18 is deemed out of order as a potential charge on the Revenue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.189" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Amendment No. 18 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.190" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Section 5, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.191" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Sections 6 and 7 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.192" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#TT03800"><p>Amendment No. 19 is deemed out of order as not relevant to the subject matter of the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.193" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Amendment No. 19 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.194" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#TT04000"><p>Amendment No. 20 is deemed out of order as a potential charge on the Revenue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.195" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Amendment No. 20 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.196" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Section 8 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.197" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>SECTION 9</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.198" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#TT04500"><p>I move amendment No. 21:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 8, line 38, after &ldquo;Oireachtas&rdquo; to insert the following:   	&ldquo;excluding those monies which were allocated to budget sub-heads related to the prevention of energy poverty&rdquo;.  </blockquote> <p>Amendments Nos. 4 and 21 are linked in that the budget subheads of the money that would be funding this particular initiative would not be coming from money that has already been allocated to the prevention of energy poverty.  That comes on the back of freedom of information, FOI, requests that have already been made.  The Minister is saying that this is an energy poverty measure, but we do not want it to come out of money that has been allocated to other areas of energy poverty, including retrofitting.  That is because in the FOIs, it was indicated that that is where the money is coming from.  We are saying that this should be new funding that should be given towards energy poverty, given the level of the crisis.  It should not come out of existing funding.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.199" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#TT04600"><p>I thank the Senator for that succinct proposal.  I invite the Minister to give a response to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.200" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#TT04700"><p>I thank the Senator and I can understand the concern, but I do not think that it applies in this case.  None of the funding that has been allocated to this measure will come out of those other energy poverty measures, such as the better energy warmer homes scheme within our Department or several other measures which are also designed to tackle energy poverty.  A certain amount of the funding will carry over from the previous year when, due to Covid-19, we were not able to carry out certain body works.  However, the remainder will come from a separate Supplementary Estimate from my Department.  This will be organised in conjunction with the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform.  It will not lead to a diminution of any of the existing schemes.  I am afraid, therefore, that I cannot agree to the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.201" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.202" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Section 9 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.203" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#TT05100"><p>Amendment No. 22 is deemed out of order as not relevant to the subject matter of the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.204" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Amendment No. 22 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.205" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Section 10 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.206" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>TITLE</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.207" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#TT05500"><p>Amendment No. 23 is deemed out of order because it would involve a potential charge on the Revenue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.208" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Amendment No. 23 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.209" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#UU00100"><p>I move amendment No. 24:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 3, lines 10 and 11, to delete &ldquo;domestic electricity accounts&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;active domestic electricity accounts&rdquo;. </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.210" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.211" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Title agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.212" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Bill reported with amendments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.213" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#UU00500"><p>When is it proposed to take Report Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.214" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#UU00600"><p>Now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.215" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#UU00700"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.216" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Bill, as amended, received for final consideration.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.217" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#UU00900"><p>When is it proposed to take Fifth Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.218" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#UU01000"><p>Now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.219" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#UU01100"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.220" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question, "That the Bill do now pass", put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.221" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#UU01300"><p>I thank the Minister and colleagues very much for their co-operation on this very important matter to the people we represent.  When is it proposed to sit again?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.222" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1670" speakername="John McGahon" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022022200002#UU01400"><p>Tomorrow at 10.30 a.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-22a.223" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar athl&oacute; ar 7.23 p.m. go dt&iacute; 10.30 a.m. D&eacute; C&eacute;adaoin, an 23 Feabhra 2022.</p><p>The Seanad adjourned at 7.23 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Wednesday, 23 February 2022.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>