<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.4" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Thomas Byrne that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:<blockquote><br />The need for the Minister for Health to discuss and justify the proposal to charge medical card holders for respite care.</blockquote>I regard the matter raised by the Senator as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment and it will be taken at the conclusion of business.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.7" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700002#A00300">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.8" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700002#A00400"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, statements on flooding, to be taken at the conclusion of the Order of Business and conclude not later than 1.15 p.m., with the contributions of all Senators not to exceed six minutes and the Minister to be called on to reply not later than 1.10 p.m.; and No. 2, statements on foreign affairs - an update on developments in the Middle East and Ukraine, to be taken at 1.30 p.m. and conclude not later than 3 p.m., with the contributions of all Senators not to exceed five minutes and the Minister to be called on to reply not later than 2.55 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700002#A00500"><p>There must be an election in the air because three Departments have each made a major announcement in the past three days.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700002#A00600"><p>It is all par for the course.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700002#A00700"><p>We sorted out the country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700002#A00800"><p>It is being sorted out all right.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700002#A00900"><p>We had to exit the troika programme first.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700002#A01000"><p>Please allow Senator Mark Daly to continue, without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700002#A01100"><p>The Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government, Deputy Alan Kelly, stated last week that he intended to leave a legacy.  While there is no doubt that he will be remembered, unfortunately, it will be for all the wrong reasons.</p><p>A new Garda Commissioner was appointed two days ago.  Despite being an insider, we have been promised that she will sweep the Garda clean.  Somehow or other, the Commissioner saw nothing when so many penalty points were being quashed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700002#A01200"><p>The Senator's comment is not fair to the Garda Commissioner's reputation.  She is not here to defend herself.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700002#A01300"><p>These issues were raised at the Joint Committee on Justice, Defence and Equality with the Commissioner present.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700002#A01400"><p>She is not here to defend herself.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700002#A01500"><p>She would be most welcome if she were to come to the House to defend herself.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700002#A01600"><p>The Senator must withdraw his remark.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700002#A01700"><p>I have ruled on the matter.  Does Senator Mark Daly have a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700002#A01800"><p>As I stated, the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government, Deputy Alan Kelly, wishes to leave a legacy, but he will make his mark for all the wrong reasons.  The housing plan announced yesterday was a reannouncement of previous plans.  It is, to a large degree, a work of fiction.  The Health Service Executive's service plan which will be published today will also largely be a work of fiction.</p> <p>Hans Christian Anderson would have been proud of it because the plan is way different from the reality.  The reality we see on the ground is exemplified by the report of the Coroner's Court in Limerick, as detailed in today's newspapers.  A critically ill man was brought to the accident and emergency department of Limerick University Hospital but never saw a doctor before he died.  That is the reality on the ground.  What we also see in emergency departments is paramedics arriving with patients on stretchers and having to stay there for hours before over-worked doctors can take the patients off their hands.  The ambulances involved are not available during that time because the system is not working.  That is the reality.  Today there are 800 people in hospitals, taking up beds, who should not be there.  They are there because the fair deal scheme has been cut.  That is the reality on the ground.  Whatever about the plan - which is a work of fiction to a large degree - the reality is entirely different.</p><p>In Kerry,  the scandal ---</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700003#B00200"><p>The Senator should not display newspapers in the Chamber.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700003#B00300"><p>There are no service plans.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700003#B00400"><p>Does Senator Daly have a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700003#B00500"><p>I ask the Leader to organise a debate on the HSE service plan.  I will not push it to a vote on the Order of Business today because the plan has only been published but we should have a debate on the service plan next week to see how real it is.</p><p>I know a debate is scheduled for today on the situation in Ukraine and the Middle East.  I ask the Leader to invite the Minister of State, Deputy Jimmy Deenihan, to the House, as the first ever spokesperson on the Irish overseas and the diaspora, to discuss President Obama's executive order.  Some of the 50,000 undocumented Irish in the United States will be assisted by it but I ask the Leader to encourage the Government to ensure that funding is made available to the Irish centres throughout the US.  The Aisling Irish Community Centre in New York does great work, as do the Irish pastoral centres in Boston and San Francisco.  However, they need assistance and funding.  I would ask the Leader to urge the Government to look for a humanitarian visa for those who are not covered by the executive order so that they would be able to come home at times of bereavement.  I would also like to see waivers being granted to those who have violated the terms of their visas in the past.  </p><p>I wish to thank the Leader and Deputy Leader for facilitating the passing of a motion relating to Cumann na mBan.  That motion is No. 8 on the Order Paper and I wish to move it today.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700003#B00600"><p>Is Senator Daly moving an amendment to the Order of Business?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700003#B00700"><p>Yes.  I move that No. 8 on the Order Paper be taken today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700003#B00800"><p>I welcome the appointment of Ms N&oacute;ir&iacute;n O'Sullivan as Garda Commissioner, following her recommendation by the Public Appointments Service as the only suitable candidate.  It is important to note that there was an open and transparent recruitment and appointment process.  As well as welcoming her appointment it is also important that we would all support her in the ongoing important work of reforming the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  We are all very conscious, after this year in particular, of the need for reform.  I know that the new Commissioner has given a commitment to ongoing reform.  In that context, I would like to ask the Leader for a debate on policing reform, specifically in light of the recent Garda Inspectorate report which threw up particular questions around the recording of crime statistics, which I have raised in the House previously.  Perhaps we might have that debate in the new year.<br/>I very much welcome yesterday's announcement by the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government, Deputy Alan Kelly, of the social housing strategy.  Whatever grudging comments may be made about it by the Opposition, it is hugely important.  Indeed, it is a legacy issue which this Government is dealing with.  The reality is that during the boom years, there was almost no investment in social housing.  The real scandal is that when the money was there to build social housing units and when waiting lists were actually climbing before 2011, there was almost no social housing being built.  That is the real scandal which is often neglected in the discussions about the need for housing and the homelessness figures.  The strategy announced by the Minister yesterday is a very real and ambitious programme to ensure that we deliver on social housing for those who need it.  What he has proposed is 35,000 new social housing units to be delivered over six years, by 2020.  He is putting forward &euro;3.8 billion, most of which is direct Government funding, to meet the costs of building, acquiring and leasing those 35,000 units.  While it is very ambitious, it is achievable.<br/>I would urge all Members to read the strategy which sets out very clear pathways or methods of working to ensure delivery of the plan.  It is ambitious, admittedly, but it is dealing with a legacy of neglect of this area and the failure, over successive years, of previous Governments to deliver social housing for those who needed it.  That, as I have said, is the real scandal of our housing and homelessness situation.  I ask the Leader to organise a debate on this issue in due course.  It would be advisable to allow some time to see the strategy begin to be operational.  Perhaps in a couple of months we could review the strategy and discuss its implementation.  It is entirely good news which must be welcomed, in fairness, by Members on all sides of the House.<br/>I wish to welcome another good news item in the context of legal change, namely, the proposed changes to our adoption law.  Proposals have been brought forward for changes to our adoption laws to enable, in particular, children who are in long-term foster care to be adopted.  Up until now, as colleagues will be aware, only a tiny number of such children have been eligible for adoption because of the highly restrictive nature of our adoption laws.  Once we see the children's rights referendum decision being delivered, which I understand is imminent, the way will be cleared for legislation to enable the adoption of an estimated 2,000 of the 6,000 children currently in care.  That will give those children legal security.  It will also give legal security to their foster parents, who may have been caring for them, <i>in loco parentis</i>, for many years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700003#B00900"><p>This morning the Christmas road safety drive will be launched by the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Paschal Donohoe, the Garda Commissioner, Ms N&oacute;ir&iacute;n O'Sullivan, and the chairperson of the Road Safety Authority, Ms Liz O'Donnell.  All three have been appointed to their posts relatively recently and I wish Ms O'Sullivan and Ms O'Donnell every success in their respective roles.<br/>The emphasis on this occasion will be on drug driving.  However, the deliberations of this House show that the whistleblower issue merits further investigation, which I hope the Commissioner will initiate.  Furthermore, there are court cases taking place where it is not a requirement to produce a driving licence and therefore the licence cannot be endorsed.  The absence of a requirement in Ireland that those who drive should have their driving licences with them has led to the situation, as reported to the House, whereby 40% of penalty points were incurred by people who were recorded as having no driving licence.  However, that was not true.  Those people were not boy racers.  The requirement to produce a driving licence in court and to have one when driving should be examined as part of improving road safety.  Our road safety statistics have started to deteriorate again.  We had an excellent period for road safety but that is changing.<br/>I also wish to raise the issue of the requirement for mortgage applicants to have a 20% deposit which was endorsed by the Governor of the Central Bank, Mr. Honohan, at yesterday's meeting of the Joint Committee on Finance, Public Expenditure and Reform, as well as by Ross Maguire, SC, of New Beginning this morning.  The endorsement by Mr. Maguire is very important, given the work being carried out by New Beginning.  The proceedings of the committee are described by Mr. Thomas Molloy - a very witty and erudite journalist - in today's <i>Irish Independent</i>who notes that Mr. Honohan is in favour of the 20% deposit requirement.  Mr. Molloy goes on to say:<blockquote>His paymaster, Michael Noonan, clearly wants the property party to continue indefinitely.  The European Central Bank, to which Mr. Honohan has sworn an oath to consider the big picture, wants the opposite.  </blockquote>Those of us who know Deputy Noonan know that this is not an accurate description.  Indeed, nobody wants property bubbles.  More and more people in economic circles are saying that the 20% deposit requirement is a good idea.  It may seem like harsh medicine at the beginning but we must save the country from what the banks would do through irresponsible lending.  It will also save people from getting into unnecessary debt.  Those endorsements of the 20% deposit requirement are very important in terms of assisting us in developing a policy to prevent house price bubbles from happening here ever again.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700003#B01000"><p>The comments by Senator Daly on the new Garda Commissioner are outrageous and I would ask that he withdraw them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700003#B01100"><p>I have already ruled on that issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700003#B01200"><p>The Senator did not withdraw his comments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700003#B01300"><p>Senator Daly also made reference to works of fiction.  The greatest work of fiction, or comedy, was when former Deputies Dermot Ahern and Noel Dempsey stood on the plinth and said that the IMF and the ECB were not coming into the country and that a bailout was not necessary.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700003#B01400"><p>That is a total misrepresentation of what actually happened.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700003#B01500"><p>Allow Senator O'Neill to speak without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700003#B01600"><p>That was the greatest work of fiction we have ever seen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700003#B01700"><p>Senator O'Neill should withdraw that remark.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700003#B01800"><p>Does Senator O'Neill have a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700003#B01900"><p>I know we have had a lot of debate already on the water issue but we should reopen the debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700003#B02000"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700003#B02100"><p>I ask the Leader to arrange another debate on water because of the hypocrisy of the Sinn F&eacute;in party.  More than 35,000 water meters have been installed in Northern Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.44" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700003#B02300"><p>Senator O'Neill should not display newspapers in the Chamber.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700004#C00100"><p>It is time that party stated in this House-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700004#C00200"><p>Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700004#C00300"><p>I am asking the Leader to arrange a debate on water provision in order that we can find out what is the true Sinn F&eacute;in policy on water charges.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700004#C00400"><p>Stand for election.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700004#C00500"><p>If it is in government after the next general election, it will decide to leave water charges in place because it will need the revenue to improve the infrastructure.  It should not try to cod the people all of the time; it is doing one thing in the North and another in the South.  I seek a debate on its policy on Irish Water.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700004#C00600"><p>On Senator Pat O'Neill's point about the Garda Commissioner, while on a personal level I wish her well and hope she will do a good job, Senator Mark Daly was perfectly within his rights to make a legitimate point.  It is a fact that the person in question was deputy commissioner when many of these issues came to light.  That is worth noting and remembering.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700004#C00700"><p>Is the Senator expressing confidence in her?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700004#C00800"><p>I expressed hope, not confidence.</p><p>Will the Leader arrange a debate on the contribution of the Governor of the Central Bank in recent days?  I believe he is wrong and would like to see what science informs his push for 20% deposits.  I worked in the building society sector more than 20 years ago, long before there was a boom, and the policy was to seek a 10% deposit.  In fact, one could obtain an additional 2% if one had a bond.  Of course, one also had to have a clear income and savings record and there were clear metrics in terms of the multiples of one's salary or the main salary plus the second salary with which one had to comply.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700004#C00900"><p>That was before the cowboys were on the pitch, some of the people whom the Senator encouraged.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700004#C01000"><p>Senator Marc MacSharry to continue, without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700004#C01100"><p>The Punchestown gang.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700004#C01200"><p>Long after the horse has bolted, the Central Bank is attempting to close a door it need not even leave ajar.  The reality is that people are struggling and will struggle to get on the housing ladder.  Appropriate regulations on lending are required.  There is no need to discriminate against young families starting off, which is precisely what a measure such as this will do.  It will not affect Governor Honohan in the ivory tower on Dame Street or anybody in these Houses, given the salaries and supports we have available, but it will affect many others throughout the country.  It is discrimination.  I do not like to disagree with my learned colleague, Senator Sean D. Barrett, but he, too, is wrong on this issue of the 20% deposit.  There is no science whatsoever that can take from what is a discriminatory move by the Governor of the Central Bank.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700004#C01300"><p>I welcome the very positive job figures published yesterday by the Central Statistics Office which show that 80,000 more people are at work compared to the first quarter of 2012, when An Action Plan for Jobs was first initiated.  Employment in the last quarter increased in all eight regions of the country, with the strongest increases in the west, the Border region and the south east.  However, we must continue to fine-tune the plan to ensure every sector is given the opportunity to benefit from the general upturn in the economy.  I look forward to having the Minister back in the House shortly to discuss An Action Plan for Jobs 2015.</p><p>Will the Leader arrange a debate with the Minister for Education and Skills on career guidance and counselling in second level schools?  I make this request in the light of a survey conducted by the Education and Training Boards of Ireland, ETBI, which runs one third of all second level schools in Ireland.  The survey shows that nine out of ten school principals believe they are not delivering an adequate guidance service to pupils and that the service requires a 50% increase.  We are all aware of the pressures young people are under, not only in making career choices for the future but also with mental health issues, bullying and other general pressures.  In 2012 schools lost an entitlement to hours for career guidance and counselling which are now provided out of the standard teaching hours quota.  The cuts have had a big impact on the time available to students and also put huge pressure on principals and deputy principals.  The survey also highlights the concerns of principals and deputy principals about the inadequacy of middle management structures in schools generally and the impact this is having on their ability to implement the many educational reforms.  The general secretary of the ETBI has called, sensibly, for a forum to develop practical proposals to address these issues.  This House would be an ideal place in which to discuss the viability of such a forum.  Perhaps the Leader might arrange a debate with the Minister on this significant issue which is hugely important to school principals.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" speakername="Feargal Quinn" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700004#C01400"><p>Today is Thanksgiving Day and there is much for which we can be thankful.  I have in mind two newly appointed Ministers, both of whom are former Members of this House, the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Paschal Donohoe, and the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government, Deputy Alan Kelly.  The Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport is announcing today some developments in the pursuit of road safety, particularly in regard to drugs and alcohol.  Senator Sean D. Barrett also referred to this issue.  These two men have come into their new jobs with enthusiasm, commitment and energy, as we have seen with the Minister, Deputy Paschal Donohoe, in the case of road safety and the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government, Deputy Alan Kelly, in the case of social housing, an issue to which Senator Ivana Bacik referred.  It is a reminder of what can happen if the right Minister is appointed to do something.  A lot can be done on that basis.</p><p>The reason I mention this issue is that a few weeks ago I raised the matter of pensions and the big challenge it posed for us.  The United Kingdom and Australia have a Minister for pensions.  Between now and the next general election we must discuss the question of pensions and the solution is to have a Minister for pensions.  It is a huge crisis and challenge for the future.  Four Departments have responsibility for pensions - the Department of Social Protection, the Department of Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation which looks after the insurance aspect, the Department of Finance which looks after the major income in the sector and the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform.  Each Department is holding onto its own piece of the sector, whereas in other countries such as the United Kingdom and Australia and perhaps others there is a Minister for pensions.  Between now and the next general election we should make enough noise to ensure the incoming new Government - it will not happen before then - will have a Minister for pensions.  It is easier to do it when a new Government is being formed because it will not have to take the task away from four existing Departments.  I urge that we have a debate in the coming year - the election could be held in less than one year or perhaps later - on the huge crisis in pensions.  The figures are huge.  If we do not discuss the issue in the near future, the new Government will end up with the same difficulties as the current Government.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700004#C01700"><p>I wish to distance myself from the remarks made about the Garda Commissioner.  I wish Noir&iacute;n O'Sullivan the best of luck.  It is a great week for her and her family.  To be the first female Garda Commissioner is a significant achievement.  It is worth noting that practically all of the senior positions in the justice sector are now held by females.  We are witnessing positive changing times.</p><p>Will the Leader organise a debate on casual trading?  We have seen an evolution in casual trading in recent years.  There are very successful farmers' markets in practically every county; there are numerous such markets in some counties which are all very positive and create a European style trading environment.  The most healthy produce is produced in this country, as well as great artisan food, crafts and so forth.  Therefore, a debate on the issue would be welcome.  There are areas that require examination, particularly what is defined as casual trading in the case of events such as festivals.  If one purchases and pays for a product to take away, that is deemed to be casual trading.</p> <p>However, if one goes to a fortune-teller or psychic and hands in &euro;20, or &euro;50 in some cases, and does not bring away anything, that is not classified as casual trading.  As such these people do not come under the remit of casual trading by-laws.  Their vehicles must be considered in the same remit as casual trading, because money does change hands.</p><p>We must update our casual trading legislation.  In advance of that, a debate in this House on the issue of casual trading, both the positives and the negatives, would be welcome.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700005#D00200"><p>Roinnt mhaith uaireanta sa ch&uacute;pla bliain &oacute; toghadh m&eacute; t&aacute; m&eacute; tar &eacute;is c&aacute;s na l&iacute;omhaint&iacute; gne&iacute;s i gcoinne Domhnall &Oacute; Lubhla&iacute; nach maireann, bunaitheoir Chol&aacute;iste na bhFiann, a ard&uacute; sna Tithe seo agus muid ag lorg fiosr&uacute;ch&aacute;n maidir lenar tharla, maidir le fiosr&uacute;ch&aacute;in na ngarda&iacute; agus ar uile.  I have raised the case of Domhnall &Oacute; Lubhla&iacute;, deceased, the founder of Col&aacute;iste na bhFiann and the allegations of sexual abuse against him by potentially up to 100 people.  A number of court cases ensued on allegations going back to 1955 and the cases collapsed because of a lack of evidence brought forward in the courts.  I have raised the issue a number of times on the Adjournment, etc., with different Ministers, because this crosses over the Departments of Education and Skills; Arts, Heritage and the Gaeltacht; Health; and Justice and Equality, and An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.</p><p>There has been an internal investigation by An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  I am concerned to hear this week on the appointment of the new Garda Commissioner, N&oacute;ir&iacute;n O'Sullivan, that two of the victims in this case received a letter from An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na saying that the internal review has concluded and the report will not be made available to them in any form, redacted or otherwise.  This is a bad move in light of the statements made about how there will be openness, transparency and a whole new ethos in An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, because it is felt that the cases in court fell apart due to a lack of competence on the part of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and that evidence was not made available when it was needed.  I called at the time for an internal inquiry into that.</p><p>It is also interesting that the report has been made available to the Minister since 21 July, I am told.  She has not contacted the victims in the case and has not made the report available.  I am also told that the internal HSE investigation is being held up because it has not received documents from the Department of Justice and Equality, and An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  I am very concerned about this.  I do not think it augurs well for the new regime in An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  I am also aware that the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Frances Fitzgerald, would have been aware of this case when she was Minister for Children and Youth Affairs.  We still have serious questions to answer.  I call on the Leader to arrange a debate on openness and transparency in the Department of Justice and Equality and An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na on these issues.  I also call on him to use his good office to contact the Minister and ask her whether the report will be made available to the victims----- </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700005#D00300"><p>The Senator is way over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700005#D00400"><p>-----and how soon this will happen, whether the other reports could be expedited and whether we could have a full and open discussion on this whole case.  If there are other victims out there-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700005#D00500"><p>The Senator is way over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700005#D00600"><p>It is important to say that victims could be listening to this and if they have information they should come forward and seek support in any way needed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700005#D00700"><p>I welcome the good news that has been referred to already - the approximately 80,000 additional people working compared to the first quarter of 2012, the 35,000 new units of social housing and the &euro;3.8 billion that will be invested in that over the next six years.  It is very challenging and ambitious but worthy of doing.  It is a legacy issue, as has been said - something we inherited which must be tackled.  We have had practically a 9% increase in visitor numbers and in the number of people employed in tourism, as those opposite will know, and the public service obligation on the Kerry and Donegal flight routes has been retained.  All of this is tremendous news.  It will build our confidence and get us beyond the fragile state we are in.  We know the graphs are going in the right direction.  This will do wonders in particular for the construction sector, which will have an effect through the rest of the economy and is to be greatly welcomed.  I do not want to be harsh on my colleague opposite, Senator Daly.  His remarks regarding-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700005#D00800"><p>The Senator is trying to provoke me.  I can see it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700005#D00900"><p>I will not be harsh on the Senator this morning.  I hope his remarks regarding the Garda Commissioner, whom I heartily congratulate in line with everybody else, were rather unfortunate, but perhaps he will think better of it and correct the record.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700005#D01000"><p>I commented on her inability to see anything that was going on.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700005#D01100"><p>With respect, I do not believe it was necessary for him to move any amendment to the Order of Business because as we knew - we had a chat about it - the Leader was going to move that motion on Cumann na mBan this morning.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700005#D01200"><p>I am not surprised that the Government side is applauding the fact that the unemployment rate is down and I would certainly be very happy for anybody who has been out of work and has found work.  I hope that continues, but it is cold comfort to 160 people in Carrick-on-Shannon and the surrounding areas of my hometown in County Leitrim, who are losing their jobs this morning in the MBNA office in Carrick-on-Shannon.  A workforce of 200 will be left in a state-of-the-art building which housed some 1,100 employees from all over the hinterland of Carrick-on-Shannon when it opened.  There are people in my hometown of Drumshanbo who will be out of work today.</p><p>What have the Government and the IDA been doing about it?  They have been doing damn all, with due respect.  There has been one visit by the IDA to my county in the last couple of years and we do not even know where it was.  Here we have a highly-skilled workforce in the financial sector, a state-of-the-art building and a willingness and enthusiasm by the local authority and local elected representatives to welcome any company that would come into that building.  In fact, yesterday a high-powered delegation from Leitrim County Council, led by my colleague, the chairman, Councillor Paddy O'Rourke, with the CEO of Leitrim County Council and the county enterprise officer, Joe Lowe, met the Minister of State at the Department of Finance, Deputy Simon Harris, who has responsibility for the financial sector as well as Government procurement.</p><p>I am pleading with the Government to do something for my part of the country.  There is an unevenness about employment prospects in this country.  If one happens to live on the east coast, one has a far better chance of getting a job with some of the foreign multinationals that come in here, but what is the Government going to do about County Leitrim?  What is it going to do about Carrick-on-Shannon and the workers who are now without work four or five weeks before Christmas?  What will they tell their children?  Will they tell them there will be no Santa this year?  The Government should get real about what is happening in rural Ireland.  The national figures may look great, but on the ground there are people who are suffering because they are out of work.  They should not be out of work.  If we are to believe that the economy is moving fast and that it is improving, where are the jobs?  I am pleading with the Government and I am asking the Leader that Deputy Richard Bruton, the Minister responsible, would come into this House and outline the Government's policy on regional development and the provision of jobs in counties like my own and in towns like Carrick-on-Shannon.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1196" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700005#D01300"><p>I am quite disturbed by what we learned yesterday from the Governor of the Central Bank and I second Senator MacSharry's request for a debate on this issue.  The European Central Bank, ECB, has decided it will not participate in the Irish banking inquiry.  This shows a total disregard for the European concept of democracy.  It looks like Mr. Draghi will not be dragged before the Oireachtas to explain the ECB's role in our bust.  The Irish banks did not get the money to fuel the boom that led to this unholy bust from the sky.  Somebody somewhere gave them the money and it now looks like those who gave it to them want to wash their hands of it.  They have forced us to repay their bondholders and to put our economy on the rocks to save the ECB.</p> <p>The European Central Bank was the ultimate authority when the Irish Central Bank failed to bring in controls to manage our economy.  People sat on their hands and allowed it to happen.  Now Draghi and his cohort have turned around and said we can hold an inquiry, but they are not going to come here and answer for their part.  I yesterday called for a vote.  I said the banking inquiry was a farce.  If we cannot have them attend, that is all it is.  I therefore second Senator MacSharry's request that we hold a debate on this.  </p><p>I disagree with the Senator on the 20% deposit issue.  I am sticking to my guns on this.  A 20% deposit is essential to cool the market.  We can pretend there is no bubble but we all know there is.  There was a time when a person could borrow only two and a half times his or her salary.  Now a person can borrow three and a half times his or her salary.  I am currently running a survey of councillors across the country.  Most councillors want a loan-to-income rather than a loan-to-value regime introduced.  I ask the Leader to arrange the debate. </p><p>Senator Mullins called for a debate with the Minister for Education and Skills on guidance counselling.  I second that also.  I ask, however, that we do not have that debate before 10 December.  I have arranged a briefing session with the National Parents' Council, the guidance counsellors' association and Headstrong.  That will take place on Wednesday, 10 December.  I ask that as many Senators as possible attend it.  Then we will be able to have an informed debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700006#E00200"><p>I second Senator Daly's amendment to the Order of Business and join with other colleagues in welcoming the launch today by the Road Safety Authority, the Minister for Justice and Equality and the Garda Commissioner of the Christmas safe driving campaign.  I also welcome the fact that the loophole that existed in the Road Traffic Acts preventing garda&iacute; from getting samples of blood from people involved in serious accidents who were unconscious or seriously injured has now been closed.  The garda&iacute; can now do so.  This will lead to safer roads.</p><p>I suggest to the Leader that we have a specific debate on road safety.  Those of us who have been commuting to and from Dublin are aware that we have recently had very dense fog, particularly over the last two nights.  I was amazed at the number of people driving without their fog lights.  Believe it or not, some were driving without any lights on.  I do not know how it is that there were not more serious accidents.  It is time to have a general debate on road safety.  It is time the Government made a substantial allocation to the Road Safety Authority so that it can conduct major publicity campaigns on safer driving.  It is very necessary.  </p><p>I join with Senators Daly and MacSharry and others in calling for the debate suggested by Senator O'Neill on the water charges debacle.  We cannot have a proper debate without the man who created this mess present in the Chamber.  He did not listen to the people in this Chamber, nor for the three hours in the lower Chamber.  That man is now a European Commissioner.  He is over in Brussels, happy to be away from us all.  He created this mess-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700006#E00300"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700006#E00400"><p>-----by rushing into establishing Irish Water without giving sufficient time to allow this to work properly.  We should have that debate.  The European Commissioner should be invited to the House to answer our questions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700006#E00500"><p>I wish to mention the housing issue briefly.  The announcement this week by the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government on a new housing strategy was touched on already today.  The same strategy was announced, with less money, on 14 October.  I have read the Minister's announcement, and whatever way it is viewed, there appears to be very little new in the report.  The Minister speaks about the provision of 75,000 places through a new scheme which will be administered by local authorities.  This is to replace the rent supplement scheme and the rental accommodation scheme, RAS.  At the end of 2013, there were 79,000 places under the RAS and the rent supplement scheme combined.  I am not sure what the benefit is.  On the other side, he speaks of the capital provision of housing.  I very much welcome that.  However, when one looks closely at what the Minister is talking about, one can see he is proposing the building of 22,500 houses or leasing of a further 11,000 houses.  Also, councillors will be provided with money to allocate the 2,300 currently vacant properties owned by local authorities.  We have to welcome the strategy.  However, we must examine the detail.  I ask the Leader to facilitate a debate with the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government on the provision of social housing.</p><p>Coupled with this is the issue raised by Senator MacSharry pertaining to the Central Bank's new mortgage proposals.  I give a guarded welcome to the Central Bank's proposals.  The bank situation is leaving many young couples in Dublin unable to rent or buy a house.  Years ago - before my generation were buying houses - people had to save up before they got a loan.  The banks are pushing the agenda at the moment through rent-seeking behaviour and their attempts to get policy makers such as ourselves to lobby for a reduction in the 20% threshold as sponsored by the Central Bank.  That is a dangerous road to go down.  Interest rates at a European level could rise.  The Central Bank did nothing prior to the bust in 2008.  We were very critical of it for not having relevant information.  It is now trying to do something. It should be acknowledged for what it is trying to do.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" speakername="Jim D'Arcy" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700006#E00600"><p>I too wish to speak on the social housing strategy for 2020, and I ask that the Minister be invited to the House.  The strategy outlines a &euro;1.5 billion guaranteed, up-front Exchequer investment in social housing from 2015 to 2017.  There will be a further &euro;300 million for housing projects by public private partnerships.  The sum of &euro;400 million will be made available through a new housing finance entity.  I welcome the strategy, but there are pinch points.  Take, for instance, a voluntary housing agency looking for a developer to build ten houses.  The cost of a three-bedroom semi-detached house would be on average &euro;160,000.  The housing agency pays four fifths of the market price.  This would be &euro;138,000.  It will cost the builder &euro;145,000 to build the house.  The opportunity for buying and selling is limited.  An average leasing price is &euro;800 per month.  This would be a high price in some areas but is low in Dublin.  In some areas, people are paying &euro;500 per month for a three-bedroom house.  Working with the figure of &euro;800, a housing agency will pay four fifths of that, &euro;640.  The developer will have a yield of 2% from this.  Bank costs are 4.7%.</p> <p>Realistically, it will be difficult under the current model.  There are other pinch points such as the fact that local authorities have land that was bought for millions of euro.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700007#F00200"><p>Is the Senator looking for a debate?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" speakername="Jim D'Arcy" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700007#F00300"><p>I am setting out two of the pinch points.  Local authorities must charge &euro;40,000 per site as a result.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700007#F00400"><p>The Senator is over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" speakername="Jim D'Arcy" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700007#F00500"><p>We need to have the Minister of State with responsibility for housing attend to ensure that this excellent strategy and the funding provided can be spent in the next three years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700007#F00600"><p>I call for a sense of reality in respect of the exuberance on the Government side on the increase in employment.  Below the radar, one does not have to read into the detail too far to find that 23% of young people in the State are unemployed.  Of those, 57% are long-term unemployed, meaning they have been out of work for over a year.  We have a crisis, notwithstanding that the unemployment rate has improved.  Thousands of our young people continue to emigrate.  While many of them have jobs, they still want to leave.  We must address the reasons we cannot hold on to many of our young people who have jobs.<br/>Multinationals thrive in Ireland where conditions are perfect for them, but the conditions are not quite perfect for small and medium-sized Irish companies as ISME has so frequently reminded us.  Last Friday night, Mr. Hugh Kelly, the president of the Irish Exporters Association, said:<blockquote>We need to increase considerably the number of Irish companies exporting.  We need to encourage Irish companies to believe they can succeed at exporting and we need to help Irish companies to risk to derisk rather than never to take a risk.  We need to box clever to stretch our nation's limited resources.</blockquote>I call for an urgent debate on the unbalanced regional development we have nationally.  It was referred to already this morning regarding Leitrim.  I want to discuss the lack of women entrepreneurs taking the risk of setting up businesses.  I remind Members that 23% of young people in this country are unemployed of whom 57% have been out of work for over a year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700007#F00700"><p>Many of them are in County Leitrim.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1189" speakername="Paul Bradford" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700007#F00800"><p>I welcome the intervention of Senator Jim D'Arcy on the housing programme announced yesterday.  He introduced a note of caution and realism.  While will certainly need to have the Minister of State attend to tease it out with him, I hope we have a housing strategy rather than a strategy for developers and the construction industry.  We must reflect on the fact that they are not the one thing.</p><p>We all receive magazines every month from various interest groups and we may not always reflect on them fully.  We had an interesting magazine from the Construction Industry Federation within the last month, however.  I read with interest the comments the director of that organisation made when he introduced the Minister of State at the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government, Deputy Paudie Coffey, at the construction industry's AGM.  He welcomed and boasted about the fact that the construction industry had its own Minister once again.  I want the Minister of State to be the Minister for housing and for housing families, not the Minister for developers and the construction industry.  We know what happened with that type of policy during the so-called &quot;Celtic tiger era&quot;.</p><p>The Minister of State and the senior Minister at the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government are fully aware of the housing crisis in the State but the approach to resolving it must be cautious.  It must also be immediate.  I find it difficult to comprehend economically and socially how there remain tens of thousands of almost completely finished or fully finished vacant houses, some owned by NAMA and some by others, across the length and breadth of the country.  Why can we not marry that solution to the housing crisis solution?  In a sense, it leads back to Senator Mooney's point about balanced or unbalanced development in the State.  Given the housing wastelands in some of our regions, leading in turn to economic wastelands, we should try to front-load some of the new housing budget into finishing estates and putting families into those houses.</p><p>We could debate this topic all day.  It is something I feel very strongly about and we need to meet with Deputy Coffey on it.  While everyone must welcome a plan which sets aside billions of euro, billions of euro were used in the construction industry before and it was not to house people and for families.  The money was used to turn millionaires into billionaires and to zone land which should never have been zoned.  It caused the economic crisis from which we are still trying to recover.  We do not want to repeat that problem.  We need a realistic proposal whereby the housing of ordinary people - to use that phrase - is at the core of a policy led by the Government and its housing Minister, not the construction industry or developers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700007#F00900"><p>It is regrettable that Senator Mark Daly questioned the suitability of the Garda Commissioner.  It is reprehensible on a morning where she has only just been appointed.  I am sorry again that Senator Daly has nothing positive to say about the housing strategy and nothing positive to say about the health service plan which has not even been announced yet.  There is no positivity on that side of the House for something that is not even announced.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" speakername="Jim D'Arcy" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700007#F01000"><p>He is not a very positive person.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700007#F01100"><p>He is actually.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700007#F01200"><p>I support the all-party motion on Cumann na mBan.  I have no problem with that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700007#F01300"><p>That is a positivity.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700007#F01400"><p>I am being positive again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700007#F01500"><p>I thank the Leader.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700007#F01600"><p>Senator Bacik and many other Members referred to the housing strategy which was announced yesterday.  I note the points made by many speakers on the matter.  I assure Senator Bradford that the housing strategy is one for ordinary people and certainly not for developers and the construction industry.  It is a roadmap to accommodate by 2020 all 90,000 households on the waiting lists with homes in which to raise their families.  That is the aim of the plan.  I will certainly try to arrange to have the Minister of State, Deputy Paudie Coffey, attend in the House before the break to have a debate on this very important issue.</p><p>Senator Bacik also welcomed the proposed changes to adoption law.  We all agree with that.  Senator Barrett referred to road safety issues, in particular the requirement to provide driving licences in court and the problems arising from that.  Senators Barrett, MacSharry, Craughwell and &Oacute; Domhnaill referred to the 20% deposit policy of the Central Bank.  Senator MacSharry differed from the other three speakers on the matter.  I agree that we should have a debate on the matter in the House.  There is obviously a difference of opinion on the issue among Members.</p><p>Senator Pat O'Neill and others asked for a debate on water.  I assure them that we will have a further debate as the Water Services Bill will be dealt with before the end of the current session.  There will be ample opportunity to discuss the matter again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700007#F01700"><p>Will the Commissioner be here?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700007#F01800"><p>We will have a very flowing debate on the Water Services Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700007#F01900"><p>Uisce faoi thalamh.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700007#F02000"><p>Some will sink and others will swim as a result.  Senator Mullins welcomed, as do I, the good news that 80,000 more people are at work.  People have been calling for a debate on jobs and the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, Deputy Richard Bruton, will be with us next week to discuss the Action Plan for Jobs.  Senator Mullins and Craughwell referred to guidance teachers and counsellors.  I note Senator Craughwell's announcement that he will hold a seminar here on 10 December.</p> <p>As I doubt whether I will be able to have the Minister come to the House before then, he will be all right in that regard.  </p><p>Senator Feargal Quinn welcomed the enthusiasm of the new Ministers, Deputies Paschal Donohoe and Alan Kelly, who are former Members of the House.  We could add the Minister of State, Deputy Paudie Coffey, to that list.  The Senator also mentioned the need to have a Minister for pensions in the next Government and asked for a debate on pensions in the meantime.  It is a very important and pressing issue, on which I agree with him.  We will try to arrange that debate in the next term.  We had such a debate some time ago.  </p><p>Senator Martin Conway asked for a debate on the issue of casual trading.  He said there was a need to update the legislation in that regard.  </p><p>Senator Trevor &Oacute; Clothartaigh referred to a specific case of victims of sexual abuse and the need for more openness and greater transparency in that regard.  I agree with the sentiments he expressed.  He has tabled Adjournment matters on the subject; perhaps he might table another.  </p><p>Senator Paul Coghlan welcomed the good news on jobs, the housing strategy and the tourism figures.  Senator Paschal Mooney and other Members on both sides of the House welcomed the 80,000 jobs created.  I note the Senator's point on job losses in Carrick-on-Shannon, which are very regrettable.  We will have an opportunity to discuss the matter with the Minister next week.  </p><p>Senator Diarmuid Wilson welcomed the plugging of the loophole in road traffic offences linked with the taking of drugs and asked for a debate on road safety.  I will ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Paschal Donohoe, to come to the House to discuss the matter.  </p><p>Senators Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill, Jim D'Arcy and Paul Bradford referred to the housing strategy.  </p><p>Senator Mary White referred to the 23% rate of youth unemployment, which is still a major problem, irrespective of how many jobs have been created.  It is something we will address next week with the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, Deputy Richard Bruton.  The Senator is perfectly correct about exports, which are the key to the success of the economy.  It is important for Irish companies to be involved in that sector.  There is a need to open markets abroad.  I support the Senator's comments in that regard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700008#G00200"><p>Senator Mark Daly has proposed an amendment to the Order of Business that No. 55, motion No. 8, be taken before No. 1.  The Leader has indicated that he is prepared to accept the amendment.  Is the amendment agreed to?  Agreed. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.102" nospeaker="true" time="11:20:00" ><p>Order of Business, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.103" nospeaker="true" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700008#G00300">Cumann na mBan: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700008#G00400"><p>I move:<blockquote><br />That, in this year, the 100th anniversary of Cumann na mBan, Seanad &Eacute;ireann: - encourages local authorities to name currently unnamed public buildings, roads or parks after Cumann na mBan or a member of Cumann na mBan from their county; and <br />- believes it is fitting and appropriate that local authorities recognise those women of Cumann na mBan and also the role of other women who have made a significant contribution to our society.</blockquote>I thank the Leader, the Deputy Leader and all Members for their support.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700008#G00500"><p>Is there a seconder?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700008#G00600"><p>I second the motion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.107" nospeaker="true" time="11:20:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.108" nospeaker="true" time="11:20:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 11.35 p.m. and resumed at 11.45 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.109" nospeaker="true" time="11:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700009#J00100">Flood Management: Statements</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="11:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700009#J00200"><p>I would like to welcome back to the House the Minister of State at the Department of Finance, Deputy Simon Harris.  These are familiar surroundings for him.  I now call on the Minister of State to make his contribution.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1106" speakername="Simon Harris" time="11:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700009#J00300"><p>Thank you, Acting Chairman.  I am extremely grateful to the Leader of the Seanad for making time available for me to address the House on matters relating to flooding and flood risk management.  It is a timely opportunity for this debate as there have been a number of policy developments in this area.  As a country, we are still continuing to spend a significant sum of money on flooding relief.  It is an issue that has impacted on every county and on so many communities throughout the country.</p><p>In the months since my appointment as Minister of State, I have visited many areas of the country that have been affected by flooding and have heard at first-hand the experiences of people who have seen their homes, businesses and farms damaged by flood waters.  The loss and hardship that these people - and many others like them - have suffered is truly dreadful and while we will never be able to solve all the flooding problems in the country, much is being done to address the worst affected areas through the valuable work being done by the Office of Public Works in conjunction with local authorities. </p><p>A core objective of the OPW's strategy on flood risk management is that we have a robust, proactive and sustainable approach to managing flood risk in this country.  Following on from the adoption by the then Government of the report of the Flood Policy Review Group in 2004, the development and implementation of the Catchment Flood Risk Assessment and Management, or CFRAM, programme is the central means by which this core objective is being achieved.</p><p>The CFRAM programme is a central pillar of national policy on flood risk management and its implementation is ensuring that Ireland will meet the requirements of the EU Floods Directive.  The programme is assessing and mapping existing and potential future flood hazard and risk within 300 areas throughout the country, which have been recognised as being at potentially significant flood risk.  These are known within the programme as the areas for further assessment or AFAs.  The designated AFAs were selected following a preliminary flood risk assessment which was carried out under the programme in 2011.</p><p>The CFRAM programme will produce a comprehensive suite of flood maps for each AFA, which will identify the risk in those areas for flooding events of varying severity - ranging from frequent events, such as those we might see every couple of years, up to extreme events that might not be seen for generations.  The programme will then look at all possible options to address flood risk in each AFA and, where possible, will identify viable structural and non-structural flood risk management measures to manage or reduce the flood risk within the AFAs and within each river catchment as a whole.  The identified measures will form the basis of a series of flood risk management plans which will set out the medium to long-term strategy and a prioritised programme of work to achieve the effective and sustainable management of flood risk in Ireland.</p><p>The CFRAM programme is being progressed through six engineering consultancy projects commissioned by the OPW and in partnership with local authorities, with each project covering the main river catchments in the east, south-east, west, south-west, the Shannon and the north-east/Neagh Bann.</p><p>The programme is now at the stage of production of draft flood maps and the OPW and its consultants are currently rolling out a series of informal public consultation days on the draft maps in the AFAs.  These are being advertised locally and I would encourage all elected public representatives and the public generally to attend these events wherever possible.  While the maps have been developed using state-of-the-art technology and make use of all available information, local residents may have some information or knowledge that can further improve the flood maps.</p><p>This is an important point.  No engineers, no matter how good they are, sitting at a desk in Dublin or elsewhere, can necessarily have the degree of knowledge that people who have been living in an area for decades or generations can have.  We are eager to get this process right and to ensure that we can harness all that local knowledge and take it on board where possible.  A further formal statutory consultation on the maps will take place early next year when all the draft maps are completed.</p><p>The CFRAM programme will not be simply a series of scientific studies which will not be acted upon.  People at risk of flooding do not need a nice, glossy report to sit on a shelf.  These flood maps will contribute directly and in a very real way to the better management of flood risk.  These maps are being produced for 300 communities around the country covering 90 coastal areas and nearly 7,000 kms of river.</p><p>The maps can and will inform sustainable planning, to help ensure that we avoid repeating the mistakes of the past by building in flood prone areas.  The State and Government will no longer ask taxpayers to intervene or to provide relief where development is undertaken in known areas of flood risk.  This is an important message for local authorities.  I have outlined that local authorities and the OPW work well in partnership.  Once these maps are published, however, if people go ahead and choose to build and develop on lands that are known to be flood prone, those developments will not be included in a cost-benefit analysis when it comes to carrying out schemes.  It is important for the planning process to play its part as well.</p><p>These maps can also inform the emergency response authorities to help ensure an effective response to reduce damage during flood events.  They can also help to make local residents and businesses aware of the risk from flooding and, if so, to be able to prepare for flood events.</p><p>In addition, the management plans under CFRAM will provide a clear roadmap on how to deal with the risk of flooding in each area.  The measures to manage flood risk included in the plans will have been developed to outline design following a process which involves a robust assessment to make sure the defined measures are cost-beneficial and that they will be socially and environmentally acceptable to communities.</p><p>A critical element of the CFRAM programme is the establishment of flood risk management objectives.  The objectives set out what we are trying to achieve and will play a major role in the formation of the management plans.  The objectives are fundamental to the CFRAM process because they will significantly influence which flood risk management measures, such as a flood relief scheme or a flood warning system, will be adopted for each community or area.  They will influence the priority given to the measures for each community or area around the country and, hence, determine when the measures will be implemented.</p><p>The objectives are grouped under four broad criteria: social, economic, environmental and technical.  The OPW is currently engaged in a public consultation on the objectives which commenced on 14 October and will end tomorrow, on 28 November.  It is important that we get as broad a viewpoint as possible on the proposed objectives.  I would encourage anyone who is interested to go to the CFRAM website and to make known their comments and observations, which can be done up to 5 p.m. tomorrow.</p><p>I wish to acknowledge the help of many stakeholders.  I have had an opportunity to meet with chambers of commerce, business groups and the IFA, both locally and nationally.  We have had a national stakeholders' consultation day in Dublin Castle.  The role being played by community, business and agri organisations feeds into the process and stress tests it.  Their members' concerns and input are important.  I am grateful for the time they have devoted to the process.</p><p>The CFRAM management plans will result in a significant number of proposed measures to address flood risk in the locations covered by the programme.  The cost of these measures will be substantial and it will be possible to implement them only over an extended time period.  For this reason, the recommended measures will be prioritised on the basis of a multi-criteria analysis.  This prioritised list of measures will essentially determine the medium to long-term capital investment programme for flood risk management in Ireland.  There is no doubt that this process of prioritisation will be challenging, socially and politically, but it is an essential element of a properly structured and transparent flood risk management programme.  The word &quot;transparent&quot; is important.  When we start ranking areas of priority in terms of schemes once this process is completed, it is important that people can see the logic behind it.  They must be able to see how we arrived at this area being No. 1, while another area is No. 161.  Transparency in the consultation process of developing those criteria is important.</p><p>Obviously, we are not waiting and sitting idly by for the outcome of the CFRAM process to take practical action to defend against flooding.  The Government has committed &euro;225 million to flood risk management under its Infrastructure and Capital Investment 2012-2016 Medium-Term Exchequer Framework.  This is a substantial capital allocation which is enabling the OPW to continue with its flood relief capital works programme in collaboration with local authorities.  Under this programme major flood relief schemes in cities and towns such as Dublin, Clonmel, Carlow, Kilkenny, Mallow, Fermoy and Ennis have been, or are very nearly, completed.  Other major projects are currently under construction at locations including Bray, Waterford and on the rivers Dodder and Wad in Dublin.</p><p>In 2015, we are aiming to commence construction, subject to procurement and statutory approval processes, on other major schemes including Bandon, Skibbereen, Templemore and Claregalway.</p> <p>Many more schemes are in the pipeline.  The largest scheme currently at design development stage is the lower Lee flood relief scheme, which will provide flood protection for the city of Cork, as well as Blackpool and Ballyvolane.  The outline design of this scheme is currently being finalised following comments and views submitted at and since public information days held last year and earlier this year.  I was in Cork with Senator Colm Burke recently to meet business groups to discuss it.  This will be followed by a statutory public exhibition, which I expect will take place in February or March 2015.  Detailed design of the scheme will be ongoing throughout 2015, and construction should commence early in 2016.</p><p>Apart from these major schemes, assistance is also available to the many areas of the country that are affected by more localised flooding events.  Since 2009, the OPW's minor flood mitigation works and coastal protection scheme has provided funding to local authorities to undertake smaller-scale works to address localised flooding and coastal protection problems within their administrative areas.  The funding allocated under this scheme now totals almost &euro;30 million, involving almost 470 projects in total.  The minor works scheme has made a very real and practical contribution to addressing flood risk in many communities throughout the country.  Members of both Houses will have seen the practical application and often make representations to the OPW and work with the local authorities to arrange for applications to be lodged.  Thus, a local authority can apply for an allocation of up to &euro;500,000 to address what is termed minor flood mitigation works, although a minor flood can often cause major problems in a local community.</p><p>All works carried out or funded by the OPW, whether major or minor, are subjected to cost-benefit assessments, and only those schemes that are shown to be economically viable are proceeded with.  Dublin city provides an excellent example of the value of good investment in flood defences.  In 2002, tidal flooding in Dublin caused &euro;65 million worth of damage.  Since then, significant works have been carried out by the OPW and Dublin City Council on improving and strengthening the tidal flood defences, particularly along the tidal stretch of the Dodder river.  I inspected these works a few weeks ago.  At the start of this year, Dublin had a greater tidal event than in 2002, but the total damage on this occasion was less than &euro;100,000.  It shows the economic benefit of these schemes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="11:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700010#K00200"><p>Absolutely.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1106" speakername="Simon Harris" time="11:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700010#K00300"><p>In addition to its capital works programme, the OPW will continue to implement its programme of maintenance of arterial drainage schemes, entailing average annual expenditure of &euro;17 million and maintenance of approximately 2,200 km of drainage channels annually.  Perhaps I will return to the rest of my script at the conclusion of the debate.  I very much look forward to the interaction with Senators on this important issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="11:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700010#K00400"><p>Ba mhaith liom mo bhu&iacute;ochas a chur in i&uacute;l don Aire St&aacute;it as teacht go dt&iacute; an Teach ar&iacute;s agus as an obair chuiditheach at&aacute; ar si&uacute;l aige.  The Minister is doing constructive work here on flooding.  The OPW has always been a very constructive organisation and seems to operate well.  Thinking back to former Ministers of State who have had responsibility for it, such as Noel Ahern, Martin Mansergh, the Minister of State's predecessor, Brian Hayes, and the Minister of State himself, they have been very involved directly on the ground in the various issues the OPW deals with, particularly flooding.  I welcome the work the Minister of State has described, the studies being done, the public consultation and the CFRAM programme.</p><p>We look back in anger at those responsible for zoning land on flood plains because, by and large, it was known that they were vulnerable to flooding.  It was no surprise to people who zoned the land that it would flood - for example, if it was in a valley with a river running through it, why would it not flood?  Referring to a particular estate in County Meath, someone told me he used to shoot ducks there as a child.  We did not need an OPW or CFRAM study to tell us that.  That is the shame of those who zoned land.  Every day, I thank God I was not a councillor.  Those who zoned land on flood plains cannot have a clear conscience, no matter what the reasons for it.  Since the first day I became a candidate it has been an issue.  I react with deep anger when I see flooding in areas where houses should not have been built.  There are many examples around the country.  I am glad to see many new councillors on board and I expect, hope and know they are on board with the way planning should be done.  Flood plains should be left for their purpose, which is to provide somewhere for water to go when heavy rain increases river levels.  There should not be houses in the way.</p><p>Over the past few years, with our changeable weather, every so often storms and surging tides have inflicted severe damage on homes, commercial property and infrastructure.  In some areas of Meath we have had flash floods, including in parts of Slane where we did not have floods before, not necessarily beside the river.  There have also been flash floods in Ashbourne, about which I have spoken to the Minister of State.  If he has an update on the situation in Ashbourne, I would be grateful.  We have also had problems in Dunboyne, County Meath, and the OPW did a fantastic job there a number of years ago which, by and large, prevented the sort of flooding that happened before.  Councillor Damien O'Reilly has asked me to ask where responsibility for the maintenance of the scheme lies.  Sediment has built up, and the banks of the Castle and Tolka rivers are overgrown.  This may be the only river system the OPW does not maintain.  While I do not expect the Minister of State to have an answer directly, he could check it.  We do not want these good works to become obsolete in a few years' time because nobody has thought to do anything about them in the meantime.</p><p>I pay tribute to the local communities, the Civil Defence, county council staff, the OPW, my party colleagues on the ground - Councillors Se&aacute;n Smith, Damien O'Reilly, Wayne Harding and Stephen McKee - and other party councillors, who were out there with their communities and colleagues working on a cross-party basis, mucking in and trying to get some relief for the people affected in Dunboyne, Ashbourne, Duleek, Slane and Stamullen, where we had major flooding on that particularly bad night two weeks ago.  Although Stamullen is not a place where people are used to flooding, there are problems there with drains and there was some frightening flooding.</p><p>We wish the Minister of State well.  We want as much funding as possible.  We want to put an end to zoning on flood plains and anywhere there is any doubt about flooding.  There should be no pressure to zone or solutions offered.  Councillors should not do it.  It is wrong, it is dangerous and it still causes families the heartbreak of seeing a foot of water in their homes where it may have been avoidable.</p><p>Approximately two years ago, excellent work was done on the river in Drumconrath, County Meath - I think it is called the Neagh river, although nobody ever seems to be certain.  I raised the need for it in the Seanad and the then Minister of State, Brian Hayes, undertook to do it.  It was done, but it has caused problems elsewhere along the river, particularly at Corstown.  Much work remains to be done.  Apart from anger at the bad planning practices, we must also praise the people involved who are helping and trying to change things, the councillors, OPW staff who are working hard, county council staff, Civil Defence and local communities who were very active in County Meath two weeks ago.  In his reply, could the Minister of State sum up the interaction between the OPW and the county councils, about which there is often confusion?  The OPW has a direct role with the official OPW schemes.  What is its role if a place floods that never flooded before?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="11:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700010#K00500"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House.  I agree with my good friend, Senator Byrne, particularly his comments on planning and what our predecessors across the political divide have done in zoning land on flood plains.  They contributed significantly to the cynicism that people have about politics.</p> <p>It is heartbreaking to see the flooding of houses that unfortunate people had purchased on known flood plains.  This occurs because previous Governments and councillors during the years were not brave enough and lacked the conviction to refuse planning permission for such developments.  In significant cases councillors overruled recommendations made by An Bord Plean&aacute;la that these areas not be zoned for housing.  Similarly, people in coastal areas were granted planning permission to build houses too close to the sea, often following representations made by politicians.  In many of these cases planning permission was granted in the face of opposition by planners.  That is the negative side. </p><p>Since assuming office, the Minister of State, Deputy Simon Harris, has engaged positively with communities.  He has a deep understanding of the effects flooding has on people's lives and shown great empathy for those he has met whose homes, businesses or farms have been flooded.  We are moving into what I would describe as a proactive phase.  Until recently, we reacted to flooding and dealt with its consequences.  The mapping project in which the Minister of State and his officials are engaged is a proactive one.  Let us identify zones where there are problems and implement a programme to address them.  We should identify the areas at the greatest risk of flooding, start to address these problems and work our way down the list.  </p><p>We all remember the scenes broadcast on television on 3 January and 1 February depicting the destruction of many homes along the coast and the erosion by the sea of significant portions of the coastline.  As the Minister of State noted, this was an event that only occurs once in a number of generations.  It focused the minds of the Government, the media and citizens on the need to implement a long-term solution.</p><p>We are an island nation surrounded by water and, as such, must invest in coastal protection works.  Our European colleagues will understand the need for an island nation on the periphery of Europe to invest in coastal protection works.  The Minister of State's mapping project, once complete, will equip the Government to make a case to the European Union for additional funding.  The funding available in the future will probably fall significantly short of what is needed to successfully implement a comprehensive programme.  For this reason, we will need to develop a partnership on the issue with our European colleagues.  </p><p>I thank the Minister of State for providing funding for a feasibility study in the Clonahinchy area where a number of homes were flooded on 3 January and 1 February and his commitment to follow up on the study's recommendations.  He will be made very welcome in County Clare tomorrow when he visits Ennistymon to perform an important function.  I hope I will have an opportunity to brief him on a matter in Clehane, near Liscannor, where a similar feasibility study will be required to find a long-term solution to protect homes in the area.  Much work remains to be done on flooding.  During the Celtic tiger years, when we had an opportunity to do so, we failed to establish the necessary investment programme.  </p><p>We must involve all stakeholders, follow through on the consultation process and take advantage of local knowledge.  As the Minister of State correctly noted, engineers can go 80% or 90% of the way but incorporating local knowledge in an overall pathway will make a real difference.  This is the type of consultation and engagement with communities that the people who vote for us expect.  The Minister of State recognises this and is fully committed to acting in this regard.  He went off script to make that point, which is welcome. </p><p>I am proud to live in a beautiful seaside area which attracts many tourists and generates significant tourism revenue.  This year more than 1 million people visited the Cliffs of Moher, which are only a couple of miles from my home.  This resulted in significant revenue and a considerable number of jobs in the general area.  Unfortunately, there is also a downside, which we saw earlier in the year.  What we need is a balanced approach and commitment from the Government which have been forthcoming.  I look forward to working with the Minister of State to ensure we make coastal communities safer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1162" speakername="Denis Landy" time="11:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700011#L00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Simon Harris.  My colleague, Senator Martin Conway, will be delighted to hear me make representations to the Minister of State to have the bridge in Ennistymon fixed.  Perhaps he might visit the bridge on his visit to the town tomorrow.  I made several representations to the Senator on the matter on behalf of people in my area.  The problem, which is minor, has been ongoing for several years and I hope the Minister of State will look at it tomorrow, with a view to having it rectified before the 2015 tourism season commences.</p><p>The ongoing work on flooding, including the required mapping project, is very important.  The Government has shown great commitment to dealing with the problem of flooding, as did previous Governments of all colours.  There is nothing as bad as one's house being flooded unexpectedly or in the middle of the night.  The Seanad debated this issue in February following the worst flooding in some parts of the country for 100 years.  The debate took place during a nationwide emergency and &euro;17 million was committed to address the problem in the week in question. </p><p>It is also good to debate the issue when we are not in the middle of the crisis.  Thankfully, while we had severe weather conditions in recent weeks, we did not have major flooding.  I propose to use my time to reflect on what is being done and what needs to be done.  The Minister of State has clearly indicated that money will not be spent in areas where flooding occurs as a result of the rezoning of land in flood plains.  If this were the only measure he were to take on flooding in his term, I would singularly commend him.  Authoritative local opinion, including the views of officials of local authorities and An Bord Plean&aacute;la, has been disregarded in too many places in my locality and elsewhere in the country, with the result that housing developments are regularly flooded. </p><p>We still have a major problem with insurance companies refusing to provide insurance cover for houses that have been flooded previously.  Carrick-on-Suir has one of the most successful flood mitigation projects in the country.  The second most successful project is about to be completed in Clonmel, which also lies on the River Suir.  Carrick-on-Suir and Clonmel were both destroyed in the 1990s as a result of flooding.  I related a story during a previous debate about receiving a call from a cousin at 6 a.m. to attend the house of another cousin, since deceased.  When we arrived on a dark morning in January 1995, the water was up to our waists in the kitchen and we carried out our cousin's belongings.  This incident has stuck in my mind because it demonstrates to me how important it is that Governments, irrespective of which political parties are involved, deal with this issue as urgently as possible.</p><p>The late Hugh Coveney visited Carrick-on-Suir within two days of that flooding event and we set in train a flood mitigation project.  The town has successfully withstood flooding for the past five years, including in January and February when the worst floods on the River Suir for more than 100 years occurred.</p> <p>This is proof positive that it is possible to deal with these issues.  There are a number of other things we can do outside of infrastructure changes and mechanical fixes.  One involves afforestation.  Currently, the rate of afforestation in the country, at under 10%, is the lowest in Europe.  This day last week, Deputy Andrew Doyle, Chairman of the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine, launched a report on land usage.  Integral to that was the need to encourage the agricultural community to increase levels of afforestation.  Despite this, there is still a reluctance in farming circles to use lands for afforestation.  It needs to be continuously encouraged as a solution, by virtue of the root infrastructure of trees, for the retention of water on land.  </p><p>Re-afforestation is another big issue.  I learned from Senator Comiskey, who being engaged in private business in this area is well versed in the forestry industry, that the roots of trees can now be eradicated while the trees are being cut down.  An acid formula can be put into the root of the tree by the saw being used to cut the tree down.  I did not know this and I am sure the Minister did not know this either.  This means the fallow period is reduced.  We need to get that message out there and we need to encourage more afforestation so that we do not have the same runoff from land into water, which we had previously, caused by less trees being on the land.</p><p>Following recent flooding, the systems in place by the Department of Social Protection are very much welcome across the country.  Immediately after a flooding crisis, there are a number of services available to affected people.  These include the provision of replacement clothes, food and furniture, funding for electrical equipment replacement and major housing repair.  That is welcome but it is after the event.  We should work towards preventing the event.  </p><p>This week, at the committee on the environment, a presentation was made by the Irish Planning Institute.  I have heard presentations by the institute at various events across the country, including when I was a councillor.  Development on flood plains and how to prevent it is coming centre stage.  Despite the existing legislation, we should constantly keep an eye on this.  Development plans have to go to the Department before they are ratified.  Changes have been made and some development plans have not been ratified by the Minister.  If memory serves me correctly, the last time this happened it was in relation to the Monaghan County Council development plan.  A greater responsibility should be placed on local elected representatives and a re-embellishing of the necessity to ensure flood plains are not interfered with.  </p><p>During the terrible flooding in Carrick-on-Suir in the early 1990s, the late Noel Davern was a junior Minister in the Department of Agriculture.  At the time, I put a proposal to him for a payment to farmers down river to set aside land.  This would be for farmers in tidal water areas such as Carrick-on-Suir.  I requested the Minister to look at this as a mitigating system.  The late Minister, Mr. Davern, who was a jovial individual and with whom I got on very well, took it as a throw-away remark.  I was extremely serious about it and I am still serious about it.  We are channelling water and forcing it under bridges.  The bridge in Carrick-on Suir was built before Columbus discovered America.  That will tell us how old it is.  That bridge sustains unbelievable pressure during flooding.  Previously that water went into land and flooded land, naturally, down river.  One half or a quarter of the money that was spent in Carrick-on-Suir is all that would be required to give the people who owned that land a set-aside payment.  I ask the Minister to keep this in mind when dealing with projects resulting from this national survey.  It is not a mad or half-baked idea.  To echo the Minister of State's opening statement, it is something that I have discussed with the local people such as fishermen and farmers who own the land.  It is something that can be done as a mitigating methodology for the future.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="11:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700012#M00200"><p>Before calling on Senator White, I welcome to the Visitors Gallery Fr. Bernard Shaughnessy from Tuam in County Galway who is paying his first visit to Leinster House.  He is very welcome and I hope he enjoys his tour.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="11:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700012#M00300"><p>I also welcome Fr. Shaughnessy.  My mother was Maureen Quinn from Tuam.  I am delighted to see him here today.</p><p>I welcome the Minister of State.  It is my first time attending here with the Minister of State in the House.  I heartily congratulate him.  He has had a meteoric rise, if I may so.  Well done to him.  </p><p>On coastal flooding, there are serious fears that Fenit Island could become separated from the mainland.  On behalf of Councillor Tom McEllistrim, I wish to raise the matter of sewage seeping into the water regularly.  The pipes are not able to cope with flooding.  It is very serious and new infrastructure is required.  There was heavy flooding two weeks ago.  It is normally in January and February.  It would be most helpful if the Minister of State could personally address the issue of flooding on Fenit Island.  There is a beautiful 16th century castle on the island also.  The island is accessible from the mainland but we want to ensure it remains so.  I would be very grateful if the Minister of State could give his attention to it on my behalf.</p><p>I wish to raise the issue of the River Clare in Galway on behalf of Councillor Malachy Noone.  I have visited the area a number of times.  The Minister of State knows the situation there is very serious.  Can the Minister of State give us more detail on when the intended works will take place?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1106" speakername="Simon Harris" time="11:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700012#M00400"><p>Is the Senator referring to Claregalway?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="11:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700012#M00500"><p>Yes.  When will the works take place?  A man died as a result of the situation.  His house flooded and he took his own life about three years ago as a result.  I saw the house which had been totally destroyed.  The situation and the landmass is very vulnerable there.</p><p>It is also appropriate to mention the recent flooding on Friday, 14 November in Nutgrove Avenue.  The flooding happened on the Thursday night.  I was there myself mid-morning.  I had never before seen flooding like that in Dublin.  Having started a small business which is now a medium sized business, I know that every day in business there are challenges to be conquered.  The flooding caused devastation to seven or eight small businesses in Ely House on Nutgrove Avenue.  There are people working there who maintain cars, gear boxes and so forth.  The machinery is very expensive and the place was completely flooded.</p><p>Having jumped the hurdles of business myself, I felt the pain they were suffering.  It is hard enough for these people.  They are self-employed.  The Government wants them to keep going.  Enough precautions were not taken on the Little Dargle River.  It is a stream but it is called the Little Dargle River.  It is a beautiful stream with crystal clear waters in Loreto Park.  Mr. Robbie Campbell and Mr. Peter Phelan are still devastated about what happened to them.  At the moment, D&uacute;n Laoghaire-Rathdown County Council are being very supportive and co-operative.  It had workmen on the ground that morning.</p> <p>They have been very co-operative with me in working on their behalf and will be putting in claims for compensation.  A young man was fixing pianos in one of the buildings and my heart went out to him when he had to carry some out through the flooding.  A lady who had set up a gym just a few months before had to take up wooden floor tiles.  I empathise with them because I know how hard it is to do business in normal times and natural crises such as flooding make it so much more difficult.  </p><p>Ms Philomena Poole is the brilliant CEO of D&uacute;n Laoghaire-Rathdown County Council and one of the few female county managers in the country.  I am hoping that council will put its heart and soul into helping to obtain compensation.  It also forms part of the remit of South Dublin County Council.  Two families at the lower end of Nutgrove Avenue are in the South Dublin County Council area.  Their houses were flooded when water got in through vents at the perimeter.  They were traumatised as a result.</p><p>Every precaution should be taken in advance of flooding.  The Little Dargle River is able to make its way through Nutgrove Park and the culvert without being stopped by debris.  </p><p>I appreciate the Minister of State's attention.  I also thank the Acting Chairman.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="12:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700013#N00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State.  I welcomed the report published in July on the lower Lee-Cork city flood relief scheme, which is long overdue.  The report deals with the recent history of flooding in Cork city.  In 1986 the Macroom, Ballincollig, Blarney and Cork city areas were badly hit.  In November 2000 the same happened, as it did two years later.  In October 2004 there was tidal flooding, which was different in terms of high rainfall volumes.  Flooding also occurred in December 2006, November 2009, June 2012 and March 2013.  Major damage was caused to properties on each occasion.</p><p>The most serious flooding in Cork city occured in November 2009, with attendant costs.  My home place is one mile west of the Inniscarra hydro-electric dam.  For the first time in 50 years since the dam was built, the road that divided my old house from the lake was flooded.  It was a clear indication that water levels behind the dam must have been close to spilling over the dam wall if the flood gates were not open.  That is how serious the position was.  Water was allowed to build up in the previous few weeks and this was followed by heavy rainfall in November.  Huge damage was caused as a result.  UCC had built a brand new building to house its computer equipment which was located in the basement which was badly damaged.  The paintings stored in Glucksman Gallery were badly damaged, as was the UCC sports campus.  The insurance claim was for &euro;25 million.  The Cork city flood relief programme will come in at a cost of about &euro;50 million.  I hope it will come in under that figure, but I am being optimistic.  That in 2009 the cost of flood damage to one institution alone was &euro;25 million emphasises the importance of undertaking a proper flood prevention programme. </p><p>On the same night in 2009, walls were broken alongside the Mercy Hospital in Cork when water flowed down Shear Street into the courthouse which we had just completed refurbishing at a cost of around &euro;24 million or &euro;25 million.  The courthouse was the last place anyone expected to be flooded.  Computer equipment has been placed in the basement, but it was destroyed by the water which poured in.  Substantial flood damage was also caused to many business premises which had not been flooded previously and it was all due to a wall near the Mercy Hospital breaking that night owing to the force of the flood waters which caused extensive damage.  Businesses had to close because the cost of reopening would have been prohibitive.</p><p>I welcome the OPW's proposals for flood prevention works in Cork city.  It is a comprehensive plan which it has opened up to consultation.  It is important that people make their views known on what they consider to be the best way forward.  They should become involved in the consultation process.  I went to the open day held in Cork city hall and the people available were able to deal with questions or concerns the public wished to raise. </p><p>There is a long history of flooding in the Blackpool area of Cork, which reflects a lack of forward thinking on building projects.  For instance, screens were placed in the river in Blackpool to stop debris from going into culverts.  However, when debris accumulated at the screens, the water was forced out over the riverbank, down the road and into commercial premises.  How did that occur?  Would it have been better to place the screens further upriver on a phased basis, rather than having one at each culvert?</p><p>I do not understand some aspects of planning.  Jury's Hotel was purchased by developers and rebuilt.  They provided an underground carpark and on the night of the bad flood it was untouched.  They was no flooding in that development, yet less than half a mile away the brand new complex in UCC was destroyed.  Someone somewhere along the line did not consider the event that happens once every 50 years.  </p><p>The new St. Finbarr's multi-storey carpark was built alongside the river.  A brand new road was built to take traffic from Sharman Crawford Street onto the Western Road, which is under the flood level for the river.  When the wall between the road and the river was built, railings were put in in order that when the tide was high the water would flow through the railings.  These are simple things, but when those undertaking engineering projects do not consider the possibility of there being higher than normal water levels, adequate precautions are not taken to prevent flooding.  St. Finbarr's carpark was built in the past ten or 12 years, but one cannot get in or out of it when the road is flooded.  Someone has fallen down and such failings should be avoided in future urban developments.  Even with flood defences in place, engineers should take into account what would happen if flood defences were to be breached.  Are there adequate precautions on floor levels in new buildings?</p><p>There is a development proposal concerning the 500 acres of land stretching from Cork City Council's offices to P&aacute;irc U&iacute; Chaoimh.  The long-term plan simply states road levels must be raised by 3 m.  This form an extremely important part of the planning process in developing the area which has huge potential.  The plan drafted a number of years ago referred to 6,000 residential units, educational infrastructure and commercial development.  However, as the area can be subject to flooding, it is important to do the right thing in undertaking the development.  Those who designed the overall master plan had the foresight to know what needed to be done to prevent major flood damage being caused and that if the one in 50 year event happened, it would be adequately catered for.</p> <p>I wish the Minister of State well in bringing forward the important project for Cork city.  As the State's second city, it is important that business there is protected.  We have a problem in the city centre at the moment in that we have created a doughnut effect.  There is very good development in Blackpool with shopping centres and offices and it is likewise in Mahon, Douglas and Wilton.  The result is a doughnut effect in the city whereby everything is happening outside the centre.  Part of the problem is that if one rents a premises now on Oliver Plunkett Street or nearby, one cannot get insurance for the ground floor.  It is therefore extremely important to have adequate flood defences if we want to grow and develop the city centre.  That is why this is so important.  While Patrick Street is not affected by flooding, some 16 ground floor premises are vacant due to the overall shortfall in footfall.  That creates the wrong impression about Cork and we must do everything possible to encourage businesses back into the city centre.  I note that four or five premises on Patrick Street are due to be occupied in the next few months and hope it is the start of a change.  The key to the growth and development of the city centre, however, is having adequate flood defences in place and a planned programme and funding to implement that long-term plan.</p><p>I thank the Minister of State for the work he is doing and all those in the OPW for the enthusiasm with which they are now dealing with this matter.  It is long overdue, particularly in relation to Cork.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="12:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700014#O00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House and thank him for his contribution.  I endorse everything Senator Colm Burke has said.  There was a period when the lines "where we sported and played in the green leafy glade on the banks of my own lovely Lee" referred to sub-aqua sport rather than to any other kind.  I look forward to the Minister of State or his successor singing the song when the scheme is completed.  It is badly needed.</p><p>The matter requires some management.  The Department must consider that there are certain times when the ESB must empty the dam, as Senator Burke has said, rather than to have it full and then to flood the city of Cork.  To the outsider, it appears there is a game of pass the parcel between Cork City Council and the ESB as to who is responsible for what happened on that dreadful occasion.  Cork is the country's second city and I commend the Minister of State as I commended his predecessor, Brian Hayes, for starting the programme.</p><p>Economists have a huge interest in this area.  I remember reading an impressive book on water resource economics by Professor Otto Ekcstein of Harvard.  The first adaptation of that thinking was when Colonel Rydell was asked by the Government in the 1950s to report on the Shannon where there had been severe flooding.  His views were most interesting.  He said the flooding occurred in winter when there was not much growing there.   He suggested that a relatively small scheme of moving dwelling houses to higher points in the Shannon valley would provide most of the benefits without incurring vast costs.  He thought that all the alternatives would cost too much.  The Cork situation requires the Department, the ESB and Cork City Council to act in a co-ordinated way.  The Minister of State's Department might be the one to do it as the other bodies did not co-ordinate on the dreaded night Senator Burke has described.</p><p>On page 6 of the document, the Minister of State lists schemes which have worked out well.  I compliment him and his staff on the Dublin one.  On the following page, it states that the damage was less than &euro;100,000 from the flood in 2014 whereas &euro;65 million worth of damage was done overall.  The works that have been carried out around the city have provided a very good return.  I hear similar reports from Clonmel and Kilkenny.  Deputy John McGuinness's job as Chairman of the Committee of Public Accounts is to dispute costs.  He was annoyed about some of the costs and fish passes and so on, but they have kept Kilkenny in a state with which we are much happier.  I note also Mallow and Fermoy but have not seen the Ennis one.  The Cork one is definitely urgent.</p><p>There may be a case for co-ordination with planners on the likelihood of floods.  There are 3,500 miles of sea to the west of us.  During the floods over the new year, I saw interviews with people whose houses seemed to be on ground a couple of feet high beside the Atlantic.  We must acknowledge those risks.  There has been a great deal of coastal erosion between Greystones and Wicklow in the Minister of State's own county.  People do not build there and the railway forms the boundary.  We must have some common sense as well.</p><p>I hope that when we carry out an improvement, the insurance industry will pass on the benefit to people who have premises in the adjacent area.  Insurers are inclined not to do so in the case of the work of the Road Safety Authority where we have reduced accident numbers dramatically and want to see premia come down.  Where the OPW goes to a great deal of expense, we want to see reductions in the costs of insurance in places like Oliver Plunkett Street in Cork.  We want to see the results for Kilkenny, Clonmel and the other towns also.</p><p>One of the concerns about some of the rural schemes proposed to the Minister of State were summarised.  We could spend a great deal of money turning wet rocks into dry rocks.  Where there is a land-price appreciation from a drainage scheme, some level of cost sharing should be considered.  If it is successful, it enriches landlords and that is a measure of the benefits.  There were some small schemes where cost sharing was considered in the past, but it should also be considered in respect of major schemes.  Part of the problem we have all encountered since coming to the House in 2011 is that everybody is in favour of something for free.  However, if a scheme benefits landowners in a certain valley who will obtain higher agricultural outputs afterwards, why load the entire cost on the taxpayer?</p><p>It is an important area and one the Minister of State has entered into with the enthusiasm he has shown in other aspects of his brief.  The results can be measured and the benefit-cost ratios can be calculated.  We can do a great deal of the work in advance.  The immediate issue is that we know the rainfall level in the area west of the dams on the River Lee.  Let us ensure that the area behind each dam has the capacity to avoid having to open sluice gates and flooding our second city.</p><p>One thing that was very controversial in relation to Dublin was the expensive proposal to deal with Clontarf.  It annoyed many residents there that they would not be able to see the sea.  A low-cost solution - and let us hope for the best - has worked so far.  The damage caused by flooding on either side of Dublin Bay was much reduced in the beginning of 2014 and the flood control people deserve credit for that.</p><p>I note prospective schemes that were probably not worth carrying out as in the turlough areas in south Galway where streams go underground and come back up again.  The solution lies with the planning regime in respect of houses in those areas.  It would be extremely expensive to drain the turloughs and the gains are not there.  It is a matter for discussion between the Minister of State's Department and planners.  If there are areas where it is just not possible to protect people against flooding, why build there?  That applies to certain coastal areas also.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="12:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700014#O00300"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House and thank him for taking this important debate.  We have debated the issue in the House on previous occasions following more serious flooding.  Obviously, we have had flooding over the course of the last few weeks in some parts of the State as well.</p><p>I start with a positive experience which shows that flood relief measures work.</p> <p>There was a huge investment in flood relief measures on the quay in Waterford, wrapping around the  St. John's river, where the flood wall and a flood barrier was put in place on the quay.  It was a part of Waterford city that was subjected to continuous flooding but since the alleviation measures were put in place, they have worked and there have been very few examples of flooding in many parts of the city.</p><p>We should first look to where measures have worked and then look at the areas where problems remain and invest.  I know that is not easy because we have had planning problems in Cork and other areas where, unfortunately, development took place on flood plains, where it is much more difficult to solve the problems.  The Minister of State's predecessor spoke at length about the problems in Cork, where he met with stakeholders across Cork city to come up with the best possible solution.  I concede that is a difficult issue but it is one we must examine.</p><p>On the last occasion we raised this issue, one of the calls I made was that both the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine and the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government would have contingency plans in place to deal with severe weather, and that they would set up sub-committees.  My understanding is that the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine has set up a sub-committee but the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government has not yet done so.  The Minister might look into that.</p><p>Many of the issues that arise with regard to flooding come under the control of local authorities but as a result of cutbacks in local authority funding over the past seven years we have roads which are in a very poor state, as is obvious to anyone who travels around the country, especially areas that are subject to flooding.  Most local authority managers one talks to will say they do not have the money to keep the roads up to the required standard, and that is creating problems.  Roads get washed away and damaged because of floods so we must ensure we maintain our roads in all areas.  It is not just roads but bridges, signage and other infrastructure which is under the responsibility of local authorities.  As the Minister knows, all of those have been subject to cutbacks and short-term savings in these areas lead to long-term damage.  I would make that point with regard to funding.</p><p>I was at a meeting and therefore not here to hear the Minister's contribution but the issue of planning is important.  He may have made reference to that already.  Have we learned the lessons of the past in terms of building on flood plains, and what new legislation is planned by the Minister's Government to make sure we do not make the same mistakes again because at some point there will be a pick-up in development?  Hopefully, at some point we will see movement in the private sector.  Where new housing estates are built we will have more rezoning, and all that is necessary to meet the demand of citizens in terms of housing.  That will happen at some time, although I hope not in the disastrous way it happened in the past for various reasons, but there will be private development at some point.  What lessons have we learned from the past, from the Minister's perspective?  What new measures from a planning perspective will be put in place by his Government?</p><p>I apologise again for not being here for the Minister's contribution but I will conclude the way I started.  The Minister should look at the positive experience of Waterford city as a good example of where investment is made and we get a return.  The people of Waterford and the businesses of Waterford have benefited hugely because of the investment made over a number of years in the city.  I would want all towns and cities to get the same level of investment and the same level of protection against floods and flood damage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1106" speakername="Simon Harris" time="12:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700015#P00200"><p>I have a lot to get through and I want to deal with it all.  I thank Senators for their constructive contributions on this important topic.  I have listened carefully to the contributions and it is clear that flooding is a problem that is at the forefront of the concerns affecting many communities throughout this country.  Many issues and some specific local problems were mentioned during the course of the debate.  I am aware of some of those already.  I have taken note of those of which I was not aware and I will revert on them.</p><p>Flooding is a natural phenomenon.  It has been always with us and we will continue to live with the risk of flooding into the future.  The critical question for this House and for Government is the way we manage that risk.  It is beyond question that we need to move to a more sustainable, planned and multidimensional approach to dealing with flood risk.  That is a message and a call I heard from many Senators.  This is what the catchment flood risk assessment and management, CFRAM, programme is about.  We are adopting a strategic approach to managing flood risk, which will allow for the fullest possible assessment of the risks and consideration of the best possible options, both structural and non-structural, for dealing with those risks on a long-term basis.  CFRAM does two things: it tries to identify the risks and then come up with the solutions to tackle and mitigate against those risks.</p><p>Many mistakes have been made in the past which have contributed to the flooding problems we are experiencing today.  There has been insufficient co-ordination of the activities of the different arms of the State and this has led to bad decisions being made on where houses and business have been built.  The development of a new strategy for flood risk management requires the fullest possible co-ordination between all the relevant stakeholders to ensure we can avoid poor decisions being made in the future.  This greater co-ordination and consultation is happening under the CFRAM programme.  As I said in my opening remarks and reiterate, the State cannot and will not continue to intervene to provide relief where development takes place in identified flood prone areas.  Local authorities have a part to play.  They need to step up to the plate.  I have stood in a house that should never have been built.  It is in a state of devastation.  The family's lives have been destroyed.  They have been moved out.  That house should not have been built and, as Senator Byrne said, often local authorities are aware of the information.  A lot of this is not rocket science and if local authorities wish to continue to go down this route, the taxpayer will not count such developments as part of a cost benefit analysis.</p><p>I made reference in my opening statement also to the need for greater understanding and awareness of the timescale for advancing with major flood relief capital works.  It is worth mentioning again that it is not always possible to implement a quick solution to a flood problem. The engineering and environmental issues involved can be complex, and there is a process that needs to be followed.  However, wherever possible, quick solutions will be progressed but in many cases the work needed to develop a full and proper solution takes a number of years.</p><p>I want to return to the issue of flood insurance because it was raised during the debate.  That continues to be a difficult issue for a number of people and businesses experiencing difficulty in accessing insurance at affordable prices or at all.  While I accept that insurance companies make their own assessment of risk in any particular case, and that is their own business matter, I cannot accept that in areas where flood defence and alleviation works have been carried out, properties protected by this significant public capital investment would not be able to receive a quote for insurance at a reasonable cost.</p><p>A huge effort has been made by the Office of Public Works, OPW, to engage with the insurance industry, and I have met with them, and agreed a format for exchange of information on completed flood defence schemes and the standards of protection offered by such schemes.  This work was formalised in the production of a memorandum of understanding in March 2014, which set out the principles and arrangements to apply in the exchange of information on flood relief schemes.  The OPW, however, can only go so far with the industry. The OPW does not have an oversight or regulatory role in regard to the insurance industry.  I am calling on the industry to respond now.  If the taxpayer is investing significant resources in flood defence schemes, and working with the insurance industry and making information available, we need to see progress on the side of the insurance industry.  I call on them to do that today.</p><p>There is no doubt that the insurance industry has suffered substantial losses from major flood events in recent years, and I acknowledge that.  Based on the industry's own figures the cumulative cost of the eight major flood events since the year 2000 has been &euro;697 million. Against that, however, must be balanced the very significant investment made by the State in major urban flood defence schemes since 1995 and the huge benefit I outlined earlier, and which Senator Barrett reiterated, deriving from that investment in terms of properties protected and losses avoided.</p><p>Communities and the public in general have a significant role to play in the management of risk, and I am eager that we have their involvement in the CFRAM process.  I again encourage people to make their views known through the online consultation process on the CFRAM website, which is open until tomorrow.</p><p>On some of the specific issues raised, regarding Dunboyne, I will revert to Senator Byrne on that.  The basic answer is that it would depend on whether it was a scheme done under the Arterial Drainage Acts.  If it was it is the responsibility of the OPW.  If not, it will be the responsibility of the local authority or private landowner, but I will come back to the Senator on that.</p><p>The Senator asked the key question, which is the relationship between the OPW and the local authority.  This is an issue that arises all the time.  Local authorities are responsible for the maintenance of water courses and drainage channels under the drainage districts.  The OPW is responsible for the maintenance of drainage channels and schemes done under the Arterial Drainage Acts.  The local authorities can carry out flood works under their own statutory powers.  I have seen that in Waterford, Bray and other areas but with OPW funding.  The OPW has a close collaborative relationship with the local authority in terms of the development of schemes but it is important to remember that local authorities are responsible for urban drainage and for flooding which results from inadequate storm or surface water infrastructure. The minor flood works scheme is available to assist local authorities in devising flood solutions.</p><p>Senator White took me around the country; I think we were in Kerry at one stage, then Galway and then back in Dublin in a very informative contribution.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="12:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700016#Q00100"><p>She has a big support base.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="12:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700016#Q00200"><p>The Minister of State without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1106" speakername="Simon Harris" time="12:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700016#Q00300"><p>Regarding the islands, Kerry County Council needs to assess the problem and see if there is a viable solution.  If it does, it is welcome to submit a minor works application which would then be assessed by the Office of Public Works, OPW, to see if there were cost-benefit elements to it.</p><p>I have seen the devastation experienced by businesses caused by flooding.  In the case of Nutgrove Avenue, Rathfarnham, it is up to the local authority to devise a solution and then apply for funding under the minor flood works mitigation scheme.</p><p>I thank Senators Byrne and Burke for their acknowledgment of the good work of the OPW in this area.  I am proud of the staff we have working in the OPW around the country and the positive contribution they make.  I will revert to Senator Byrne on the recent flooding in Ashbourne, County Meath, with the most up-to-date information.  OPW officials have met with Meath County Council to come up with solutions to the flooding problem there.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="12:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700016#Q00400"><p>Was there any arterial drainage scheme there in the past?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1106" speakername="Simon Harris" time="12:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700016#Q00500"><p>No, I would imagine there was not.  If the local authority can devise solutions, it can then apply for funding for them under the minor flood works mitigation scheme.  The OPW can provide a funding mechanism of up to &euro;500,000 under the scheme.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="12:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700016#Q00600"><p>We are grateful officials came to the town so quickly after the floods there.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1106" speakername="Simon Harris" time="12:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700016#Q00700"><p>Yes, they are very efficient.<br/>I will look into the points Senator Byrne raised about the arterial river in Drumconrath, County Meath, which is known as the River Neagh, as confirmed by the Acting Chairman.<br/>The Claregalway relief works are a major scheme and priority for my office.  We have had many representations on it and are eager to progress it.  Its EIS, environmental impact statement, is being evaluated by consultants hired by the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform.  I hope it can go to construction in 2015.<br/>I was delighted to visit Cork city with Senator Burke recently and meet stakeholders there.  I gave a commitment on that visit to return in January to have a further engagement on the flooding problems there.  I am aware of the issues there and I am grateful to the Senator for outlining them again today.<br/>Senator Barrett is correct that co-ordination between the various agencies is key to this.  The whole purpose of the catchment flood risk assessment and management programme is rather than having an <i>ad hoc</i>response, there is a proactive co-ordinated response.  I am excited by the CFRAM process.  I accept it will not be without difficulty but for the first time a national strategic approach to flooding will be in place.<br/>I am eager we continue engaging with the insurance industry but also that it sees benefits for the taxpayer.  We try to come up with flood relief schemes that are acceptable to communities, so there is quite a level of consultation in this regard.<br/>I will check out the bridge in Carrick-on-Suir referred to by Senator Landy and look forward to meeting delegations with Senator Conway.  Senator Landy's suggestion about CFRAM is not flippant.  We will explore all options.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1162" speakername="Denis Landy" time="12:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700016#Q00800"><p>Will that include set-aside land?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1106" speakername="Simon Harris" time="12:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700016#Q00900"><p>Yes, as well as other measures such as natural flood plains, afforestation, deforestation and so forth.</p><p>I am pleased to hear of the success of the scheme in Waterford city.  Lessons must be learned from the past and the taxpayer cannot continue to pick up the tab for failures to adhere to best planning practice.  We are making as much information available as possible which is the purpose of CFRAM.  There will be no doubt from the flood maps as to what areas are at risk.  It is the responsibility of the local authority to respond accordingly.</p><p>Much has been achieved in tackling flooding problems.  I pay tribute to communities which have worked with local authorities which, in turn, worked with my staff in the OPW on flood relief schemes.  Hundreds of thousands of acres of agricultural land have been successfully drained to improve its productive potential while thousands of homes and other properties have been protected.  Much still remains to be done and I will continue to give this area my full attention.  I look forward to further updating the House on this in the future.  My door is always open to Members for discussions on schemes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.140" nospeaker="true" time="12:35:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 1.05 p.m. and resumed at 1.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.141" nospeaker="true" time="12:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700017#R00100">Situation in Middle East and Ukraine: Statements</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="12:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700017#R00200"><p>I welcome the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade, Deputy Charles Flanagan.  He will give an update on developments in the Middle East and Ukraine.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1055" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="12:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700017#R00300"><p>I am pleased to be before the Seanad to report further by way of update on developments in the  Middle East and Ukraine, following on the specially-convened emergency debate held here in July.  I will commence by addressing the Middle East peace process.</p><p>Three months after the end of the latest Gaza conflict, the humanitarian situation remains dire.  A total of 24,000 people are still sheltering in UNRWA schools and a further 17,000 families are still lodging with relatives or elsewhere because their  homes are uninhabitable.  Water and electricity supplies are poor or intermittent.  There is reconstruction, but at a rate that will take years to make any form of progress.  Senators will recall that at the Gaza reconstruction conference in Cairo in October, I pledged a sum of &euro;2.5 million for immediate humanitarian needs and longer-term recovery and reconstruction.  Overall, most substantial sums were pledged at the conference, but everybody made it clear they would want to see a more permissive environment and longer-term stability before releasing the reconstruction funding.  </p><p>Three months on, the ceasefire has proved lasting but planned talks to address the wider context of an end to the attacks on Israel and to the Israeli restrictions on Gaza have really made very little progress. There have been some positive steps by Israel - an agreement with the United Nations on allowing in reconstruction materials, some movement on exports from Gaza and an extension back to six miles of the fishing limit, and - unexpected and most welcome - approval for 5,000 work permits for Gazans to work in Israel.  These are welcome steps but they are only the beginning of what is needed.  Frankly, similar indications in 2009 came to very little in the end.  </p><p>There may be some recognition in Israel that these conflicts with Gaza have become cyclical and the cycle needs to be broken, but for them, as for many of the donors at Cairo, the return of Palestinian government control to Gaza is the key to further progress on reconstruction and possible normalisation.  Continuing suspicion and disagreement between Fatah and Hamas means there has been almost no progress on that front.  </p><p>The Palestinian government, Israel and even Hamas may be willing in principle to try and find a new way in Gaza, but there is grave danger that caution and suspicion on all sides may prevent this from being translated into real improvements for the people of Gaza.  We have warned repeatedly that without this, the recent conflict will without doubt recur, and quickly.  International opinion, including ourselves in the European Union, must try to persuade all parties to act more urgently and decisively.  Elsewhere on the ground, the position is equally worrying.  There is no real prospect of political talks resuming any time soon, leading to a loss of faith on the part of some in political action as a way forward.  The relentless announcements of settlement expansion continue, entailing as they do continued evictions of Palestinians to expropriate land and resources - including water - for settlers.  The result has been a worrying rise in demonstrations, the use of lethal force by Israeli authorities against demonstrators, and most recently in a number of mostly random and deadly attacks on Israelis in the Jerusalem area.  I have issued a number of statements on behalf of the Government, expressing our clear condemnation of both settlement expansions and of the recent violent attacks and civilian deaths in Jerusalem and calling for restraint in relation to provocative efforts to undermine the existing status quo governing the highly sensitive holy sites in Jerusalem.</p><p>There is much soul-searching going on in the international community about what we can do to break the stalemate in the Middle East.  Ireland has concentrated on pressing within the EU for a serious reappraisal of overall Middle East strategy, and in particular for stronger action against the policies on the ground which are making a two-state solution harder and harder to achieve, principally those related to the settlements.  This is and will be a difficult discussion, and one on which member States by no means agree, but we are working to push forward the matter.  Already we have seen how effective was the collective EU decision in 2013 that EU funding and research grants may not be spent in settlements.</p><p>Where there is no agreement at EU level there is still scope for member states including Ireland to push ahead with further measures on settlements and settlement goods.  This year Ireland and a large number of other EU member states have published advice warning citizens and companies against investing in settlements.  Work on another measure - guidelines for the labelling of settlement products - was put to one side while the talks were ongoing, but we have already raised the question of bringing them forward now, and we will actively pursue this issue at EU level.  If these proposals are indefinitely stalled at EU level, we will look again at our national guidelines.  Sweden's decision to recognise Palestine has focussed attention on that as a possible new direction.  I am fully aware of course of the view expressed by Seanad &Eacute;ireann on this issue.  There is also now reflection taking place within the EU on this issue, following an initial exchange of views at the Foreign Affairs Council last week.  We will actively participate in this discussion.</p><p>It has been our view that recognition of a Palestinian state - something to which we have looked forward and worked towards achieving for many years, under many Governments - should come about as part of a comprehensive agreed peace in the area.</p> <p>At present that remains the view of the vast majority of EU partners.  I am not sure that immediate recognition would make a positive difference.  However, as I made clear to the Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs and Trade last week, I have an open mind on this issue.  I am very conscious of the lack of political movement and the worsening situation, and I am not excluding any approach, including an early recognition of Palestine, that might help move things forward and advance what has always been our goal of a negotiated two-state solution.  </p><p>We will be exchanging views with our partners on this issue over the coming weeks.  It is important to be realistic and aware that mere recognition will not end the occupation.  Most states have recognised Palestine for years without affecting the occupation at all.  The key focus for me remains trying to get substantive negotiations started to bring the occupation itself to an end, which is the most certain way in which we can help to bring about a Palestinian state.</p><p>The other major crisis which the Middle East has had to confront in recent months has been the growing threat posed not only to the region but to the wider international community by extremist jihadist movements such as ISIS, the Islamic State in Iraq and Syria-al-Sham, to give it its full title.  All right-thinking people will have been appalled by the violence and sheer brutality which has characterised ISIS's campaign of terror since it intensified in June, with its advance into north-western Iraq and the capture of the city of Mosul.  </p><p>The ideology which ISIS and other extreme jihadists propound is utterly bankrupt, and characterised by hatred and intolerance which respects the rights of no-one, whether man or woman, Sunni or Shia, Yazidi, Kurd or Christian.  We have to be clear that ISIS represents no-one but itself in its efforts to establish a so-called Islamic state.  The new caliphate of which it and its leader, Abu Bakr al-Baghdadi, speak has been loudly condemned by respected Islamic commentators and scholars throughout the Middle East.</p><p>The international community cannot afford to be complacent about the threat which ISIS and other extreme jihadists represent.  This threat was widely discussed during the ministerial week at the UN General Assembly which I attended in September.  During that week, the UN Security Council, chaired by President Obama, adopted a new resolution, 2178, which specifically deals with the threat posed by those now travelling in large numbers to the Middle East to take up arms on behalf of extremist jihadist movements such as ISIS.</p><p>Coupled with Resolution 2170 adopted by the Security Council last August, these two resolutions call on all member states to take a range of measures to combat the growth of terrorism and extremism including: active steps to stop incitement of terrorist acts and the flow of foreign fighters to the conflicts in Syria and Iraq; the prevention of recruitment and radicalisation of possible members of terrorist groups, including through community outreach initiatives; and tackling effectively the sources of terrorist financing.  It ultimately remains for each individual member state to determine in what way it can best contribute to the concerted international effort under way to tackle the threat posed by ISIS and other fundamentalist groups.</p><p>For the Government's part, Ireland will continue to emphasise the importance of the political and humanitarian dimensions to the crises resulting from the ISIS offensive in Iraq and Syria.  ISIS must be regarded as a symptom, rather than a cause, of the ongoing conflicts in both countries.  Ultimately, both conflicts can only be resolved politically, and not by military means.  This will continue to be a hallmark of our policy as it has been since the onset of the conflict in Syria in March 2011.  Ireland remains strongly supportive of the new UN special envoy, Steffan di Mistura, in his efforts to progress a solution based on the Geneva principles which provide for transition to a new, agreed form of government within Syria.  We also need to engage all relevant regional stakeholders to use their influence in support of the UN-led peace efforts.</p><p>Equally, within Iraq, the new unity Government led by Prime Minister al-Abadi must be strongly encouraged to continue efforts to promote reconciliation and more inclusive policies within the country.  All of Iraq's minorities must be empowered to feel they have a genuine stake in the governance of their country.  Sunni alienation has been the source which has enabled ISIS and, before it, al-Qaeda in Iraq, to develop its murderous campaigns and unless it is tackled through effective political actions, it will continue to fester and promote further instability.  </p><p>Ireland will also continue its strong efforts to deal with the humanitarian consequences of both crises which are compounding the threat to the entire region.  We have contributed over &euro;29 million in humanitarian assistance to date in response to both crises, placing us firmly as one of the top European contributors to the Syria crisis on a per capita basis, and we stand ready to do more as required.  </p><p>We must not forget the need for accountability for all those, including the many members of minority communities, who have suffered grievously at the hands of extremists, be it ISIS or the Assad regime.  That is why Ireland will continue to strongly support referral of the situation in Syria to the ICC.  The EU's approach to the crisis posed by ISIS is fully consistent with our own.  Last month, the Foreign Affairs Council agreed a new EU strategy on counter-terrorism and foreign fighters, as originally called for by the August 2014 European Council.  </p><p>The Council has also continued to emphasise the ultimate need for a political resolution to the related crises in Iraq and Syria, and has now requested the new High Representative, Federica Mogherini, to develop a comprehensive regional strategy for Iraq and Syria which looks beyond the immediate threat posed by ISIS.   The High Representative has also decided that Iraq-Syria will be the main theme for discussion at the next Foreign Affairs Council scheduled for 15 December in Brussels.  ISIS has been born out of a fundamental crisis of governance in Iraq and Syria.  It has nothing to offer but the assurance of more violence, terror and murder.  It is for the international community to now demonstrate the appropriate resolve to tackle this failure of governance through promoting effective political resolutions in Syria and Iraq.</p><p>On Ukraine, I regret to say that the current situation is very fragile and remains a cause of great concern.  Since I was here in July, there have been a number of developments in the conflict, some encouraging and others less so.  There was some ground for optimism when, following the serious intensification of hostilities in eastern Ukraine during August, the parties agreed on 5 September in Minsk to a 12-point peace plan brokered by the OSCE, including a ceasefire.  The ceasefire led to an immediate reduction in the levels of violence and resulted in the release of large numbers of hostages by both sides.</p><p>Regrettably, however, hopes that the Minsk peace plan marked a turning point in the conflict have not been realised.  Little progress has been made on some crucial elements of the plan, in particular the creation of a security zone along the ceasefire line, the permanent monitoring of the Ukraine-Russian border and the withdrawal from Ukrainian territory of all foreign forces, weapons and military equipment.  In addition, over the past few weeks violations of the ceasefire have increased significantly.  A recent UN report indicates that almost 1,000 people have been killed in the three months since the agreement was reached.  A lasting ceasefire remains key to the success of efforts to reach a sustainable political solution based on respect for Ukraine's sovereignty and with clear guarantees on border security, the disarmament of all illegal groups and the withdrawal of foreign forces.</p><p>The unilateral decision by the separatist groups to proceed earlier this month with parliamentary and presidential elections in the areas of Donetsk and Luhansk under their control marked a further serious setback to these efforts.  The EU regards these so-called elections as illegal as they were not held in accordance with Ukrainian law, as required by the Minsk protocol.  As I underlined at the Foreign Affairs Council meeting last week in Brussels, the Minsk agreements offer the only credible basis for resolving the crisis and ending the bloodshed.  It is crucial, therefore, that all parties fully implement the commitments they signed up to.  No actions should be taken to undermine the objective of a negotiated and peaceful end to this crisis that respects Ukraine's sovereignty and territorial integrity.</p><p>The Russian Federation should use its undoubted influence over the separatists to encourage them to end the violence and fully embrace the Minsk process.  However, there appears to be little sign so far of a willingness to play such a role in the region.  Reports of convoys of heavy weapons, tanks and troops crossing into eastern Ukraine in recent weeks are deeply worrying.  This development represents a re-escalation of the conflict and raises serious questions over stated commitments to the search for a peaceful resolution to the conflict.  I urge the Russian Federation to take all necessary and appropriate actions to prevent any further movement of convoys from its territory and to immediately withdraw any troops, weapons and equipment under its control.</p> <p>When I was here in July, I mentioned that the EU had just agreed on a package of economic sanctions at the end of July which targeted sectoral co-operation and exchanges with the Russian Federation.  The restrictive measures impact on Russia's access to capital markets, arms supplies, dual use goods and technology relating to deep water oil exploration and production.  </p><p>These sanctions were further strengthened in early September in response to the serious deterioration of the situation in eastern Ukraine.  At the Foreign Affairs Council last week, Ministers decided in light of recent developments to ask the EEAS and European Commission to prepare additional listings of those subject to visa bans and assets freezes that targeted separatists.  A decision will be taken on this proposal in the coming days.</p><p>I believe that the imposition of economic sanctions against Russia was and is necessary.  The sanctions send a strong signal that the EU is ready to take determined action when required.  The measures in question can be intensified or lessened according to how developments unfold on an ongoing basis.  As the situation evolves, we will discuss with our EU partners what adaptations or further measures might be required.  For the moment, there would appear to be little grounds for optimism that sanctions will be eased in the near future, given recent developments in eastern Ukraine.</p><p>On a more positive note, on 26 October, millions of Ukrainians turned out across the country to cast their vote in parliamentary elections.  The outcome saw parties in favour of closer relations with the EU secure a majority of seats.  The elections marked an important milestone in Ukraine's democratic development, and I look forward to the formation of a stable, inclusive government.  The new government can be assured of our full support as it begins the urgent and important task of enacting much-needed reforms that are central to Ukraine's future economic development and political stability.</p><p>There is no doubt that we must remain firm in our response to Russia's actions in Ukraine.  We must also recognise the importance of keeping open channels of communication with all parties to the conflict.  From the outset, Ireland has consistently underlined the need for dialogue in seeking to bring this tragic conflict to an end.  Ireland will continue to support Ukraine as it works towards a peaceful resolution of the conflict in the east, and we will stand with the people of Ukraine as they seek to build a more secure, inclusive and democratic future.</p><p>I am pleased to be here and I look forward to the contributions of Senators.  I will take note of contributions and I look forward to responding to the issues raised before the conclusion of this important debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="13:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700019#T00200"><p>I remind Senators that they have five minutes each.  We have a lot of speakers, and the Minister is to reply at 2.55 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1154" speakername="Averil Power" time="13:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700019#T00300"><p>Given that time is limited and each Senator only has five minutes, I wish to state that I share the Minister's concerns about ISIS and Ukraine but I will focus my remarks on Palestine, particularly the motion passed by this House just over a month ago calling on the Government to recognise the state of Palestine.  I thank the Minister for attending the House today.  The Leader gave a commitment when we passed that motion that the Minister would come to the House to discuss the issue with us, so I welcome the fact that he is here.  I would also like to thank Members on all sides of the House who supported the motion, because we passed it without a vote.  It is essential that Ireland moves on this issue and recognises the state of Palestine without further delay.  I hope the Minister will say more on this when he makes his concluding remarks.  As he has noted, recognising Palestine will not of itself bring peace to the region.  However, it is a strong statement of support for the Palestinian people and their right to self-determination.  In the aftermath of Israel's latest assault on Gaza last summer, now more than ever, the Palestinian people need to know that they have real support in the international community.<br/>It is also important that we do everything we can to bolster moderate Palestinian and Israeli forces and help them work for peace.  As the Minister knows, the lack of progress in the endless peace talks - there have been talks in so many different guises since Oslo, all of which have brought about no resolution of the situation - have led to a lack of faith among many regarding political action as a way forward.  This is very dangerous for all concerned.  We are at a particular flashpoint where, if more action is not taken, things will deteriorate.  We have seen that with the recent spate of violence.  <br/>I am sure the Minister is aware that recently, more than 650 prominent Israelis wrote to Members of the D&aacute;il asking them to follow through.  They welcomed the motion passed in the Seanad and called on the D&aacute;il to pass a similar motion recognising Palestine.  That letter was signed by former Israeli ministers and ambassadors, the former speaker of the Knesset, a Nobel laureate and retired army generals.  In their letter, they expressed concerns about the continued political stalemate, the occupation and Israel's settlement activities.  They stated that Israel's security and existence depend on the existence of a Palestinian state and that Ireland recognising the state of Palestine would advance the prospects for peace.  <br/>A total of 135 countries already recognise the state of Palestine, including, most recently, Sweden.  Last Friday, I shared a platform at the UN with Swedish parliamentarians.  The Swedish deputy secretary for foreign affairs addressed the meeting and explained the rationale behind her country's move to recognise Palestine.  It was met with almost universal acclaim from all present, apart from the Israeli ambassador, who was particularly aggressive and rude in his response to her remarks.  I thought she gave a very even-handed explanation of the reason Sweden acted as it did.  It is driven by a desire to promote peace.  There was universal acceptance in the room that this was a positive thing.  In speaking, many members referred to the Seanad motion that was passed, among them the Palestinian ambassador and the chairman of the UN committee on Palestine, and called on us to move forward and take the same step.  I hope the Minister will listen to Members of this House and do that.<br/>While symbolic statements are significant, they are not enough.  We must also do everything we can to make a Palestinian state a reality.  I very much hope that the Security Council will agree a resolution soon setting out a clear deadline for Israel's withdrawal from Palestine.  I know there are talks and that the Palestinians are lobbying hard to get support for that in the General Assembly and the Security Council.  Such a resolution will only have real impact if it is backed up by proper monitoring and strong enforcement measures.  We have seen how Israel has chosen to ignore Security Council resolutions for decades and how there have been no consequences.  When Iraq invaded Kuwait in 1990, the Security Council did not just condemn the invasion, as it has condemned Israel's invasion of the West Bank several times over; it also acted to put in place sanctions to help bring an end to it.  It is ridiculous at this stage that Israel has been militarily occupying Palestine for 50 years without any consequences.  I welcome the article from the Minister and the Finnish minister for foreign affairs in which they state:<blockquote>We have time and time again called on the Israeli authorities to end this settlement policy, which clearly contradicts international law.  But commitment is nothing without action.  Continuation of this policy must bring a strong response from the international community, including the EU, if our commitment to upholding international law is to be taken seriously. </blockquote>I welcome that excellent article.  I call on the Minister to deliver on that and to ensure that the EU takes real action.  At the very least, we should ban settlement goods.  It is ridiculous that we criticise the settlements consistently, pointing out that they are illegal, yet we help to make them economically viable by buying from them.  It is complete hypocrisy.  Ultimately, the EU-Israel Association Agreement should be suspended until Israel starts to abide by international law.  Unless Ireland and other countries are prepared to stand up and take real action, things will only deteriorate.  I welcome the Minister's article.  He asked for questions, and I will conclude with two.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="13:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700019#T00400"><p>I ask the Senator to conclude.  She is one minute over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1154" speakername="Averil Power" time="13:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700019#T00500"><p>One question concerns when the Minister will listen to the motion from this House and recognise Palestine.  In his article, the Minister alluded to the need for the EU to take action.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="13:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700019#T00600"><p>The Senator has repeated that three times.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1154" speakername="Averil Power" time="13:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700019#T00700"><p>I ask him to outline in his closing remarks what action he had in mind in the article.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="13:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700019#T00800"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House and thank him for his very comprehensive statement.  Given the fact that the ceasefire is holding, we are all extremely concerned that very little progress has been made in negotiations to bring about a lasting peace between Israel and Palestine.</p> <p>We are all concerned by the growing tension and increasing violence in the area and all support the call made that all parties should refrain from engaging in actions that might worsen the situation.  Political leaders must work together.  In this regard, recent settlement activity in east Jerusalem is totally unacceptable and unhelpful, as it jeopardises the possibility of Jerusalem being the capital city of both states in a two-state solution.</p><p>Formal recognition of the state of Palestine and the motion supported by Seanad &Eacute;ireann have been mentioned.  It is welcome that the Minister has an open mind on the issue.  I note his view that recognition of the state of Palestine might best be achieved in conjunction with a peace agreement.  It has been accepted that recognition should be subject to a common decision by the European Union; therefore, this is something we will continue to tease out.  The humanitarian crisis, loss of life and destruction in Gaza are of major concern.  It is welcome that at the recent reconstruction conference held in Cairo the Government pledged &euro;2.5 million towards this cause.  It is only a drop in the ocean compared to what is required, but it is a start.</p><p>The Minister spoke about the threat posed by ISIS and jihadist terrorists.  I wish to refer to the awful situation in Syria where the conflict has been raging for three and a half years and an awful civil war has ensued.  Some 3.2 million people have fled to neighbouring countries, which has put appalling pressure on Lebanon, Jordan and Turkey to shoulder the burden of the Syrian crisis.  The Geneva II conference failed to make progress owing to the refusal of the Assad regime to agree to a transitional governing body.  This has weakened moderate Syrian opposition and the associated Free Syrian Army.  As a result, radical jihadist forces have been considerably strengthened, as mentioned.  I very much welcome the appointment of Mr. Staffan de Mistura as the new special representative charged with reviving the peace process.  We wish him well in his very difficult task and hope he will succeed in bringing all influential parties to the table, including Iran and Israel.</p><p>I note that the French Foreign Minister recently called on the international community for urgent military support for the moderate opposition to help to protect civilians.  At a recent meeting of the foreign affairs committee Dr. Nader Hashemi, an expert on Syria from the Josef Korbel School of International Studies at the University of Denver, urged support for the Jimmy Carter peace plan of self-determination, with free elections overseen by the international community.  He said such a plan must involve a serious programme to arm and support modern Syrian rebels; he said this would not topple the Assad regime but could turn the tide in the fighting and shift negotiations.  What does the Minister think of this?  On the other hand, yesterday some of us met the Bishop of Aleppo, the president of Caritas Syria, who was accompanied by representatives of Tr&oacute;caire.  He said there could not be a military solution to the problem and that all efforts must focus on a political solution.  He wanted Mr. de Mistura to produce a radical plan supported strongly by the international community.  He also said it would help greatly if the United States and China stopped selling arms to neighbouring countries such as Saudi Arabia.</p><p>Ireland has called repeatedly for implementation of the Geneva Principles and for President Assad to hand over power to a traditional governing body.  The Minister referred to war crimes.  Will he outline the Government's plan for accepting Syrian refugees to ease the pressure on neighbouring countries?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1167" speakername="Fiach MacConghail" time="13:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700020#U00200"><p>I welcome the Minister to the Seanad and appreciate his constant willingness to come before this House for debates.  He has integrity and I congratulate him on his article yesterday.  It is refreshing that he is not flimsy and is open to other opinions.  He articulates his thinking process publicly, which is refreshing because he does not feel the need to be deterministic on either side.  As I only have five minutes, I will give a personal reflection on my recent trip to Palestine, particularly the West Bank, from which I returned on Monday.  I will conclude by making a modest request of the Minister.</p><p>I have visited the occupied territories in Palestine three times in the past 12 months and spent the equivalent of a month there since November 2013.  I have also visited Israel and seen places such as Jaffa, Umm al-Fahm, Tel Aviv, Jerusalem, Jericho, Jenin, Hebron, Tulkarem, Nablus, Deir Istya, Yanun, Majdal Shams on the Golan Heights and Ramallah.  I have spoken to citizens, refugees, temporary residents, displaced persons, diplomats, Palestinians under occupation, Ministers, non-governmental organisations, NGOs, playwrights, actors, politicians, schoolchildren and teachers.  What I am witnessing is the final episode in the complete fragmentation of the West Bank, the choking of Jerusalem and hopelessness in ever achieving a two-state solution.</p><p>I was in Jerusalem all last week during a highly tense period.  I recognise the state of Israel and the state of Palestine.  I am unhappy with the 1967 Green Line, but in the interests of peace and sovereignty, I will accept it.  Under Article 49 of the Geneva Convention, an occupying power cannot transfer its population onto occupied territory.  Settlements and the barrier, wall or fence are enormous violations of international law.  On 9 July 2004, over ten years ago, the International Court of Justice issued an advisory opinion on the legal consequences of the construction of the wall in occupied Palestinian territory.  The UN Security Council also recognises this violation.  The International Court of Justice has called on Israel to cease construction of the barrier inside the Green Line and around east Jerusalem.  It has also requested the dismantlement of the section already completed, but ten years on 62% of the barrier has been constructed - it includes 200 km added since the International Court of Justice's advisory opinion.  Some 85% of the barrier route runs inside the territory of the West Bank.  </p><p>Some 150 illegal settlements and 100 outposts have been erected and they contain over 500,000 Israeli settlers, which represents 20% of the Palestinian population.  That is quite an occupying force.  Ironically, 20% of the population of Israel consists of Palestinian and Arab people; perhaps, therefore, we might examine a one-state solution.  When the barrier wall is completed, it will be 700 km long, the equivalent of a car journey from Dublin to Kilkenny to Cork to Killarney to Galway to Achill Island.  Many Palestinian farmers live on one side of the wall and tend to their olive trees on the other.  Data collected by the UN Office for the Co-ordination of Humanitarian Affairs, OCHA, show a reduction in yield of around 60% from such olive trees compared to those on the Palestinian side.  This is evidence of the destruction of the fabric of Palestinian agriculture and society.  I accept that Israel is worried about defence, but such a barrier is illegal inside the Green Line.</p><p>A combination of the barrier and settlements has contributed to the deliberate fragmentation and annexation of the West Bank.  Over 42% of the land on the West Bank, including around the Jordan valley and the Dead Sea, has been confiscated and allocated as settlements that are off limits to Palestinian developments.  If Palestinians had access to the Jordan valley and the Dead Sea, it would negate any need for international aid as, according to the World Bank, the equivalent of &euro;3 billion of income would be generated for Palestine through the exploitation of natural resources.  Palestinians cannot exploit the rich resources of the Dead Sea.</p><p>On Sunday I drove from Jericho to Jerusalem and saw the physical impact of settlements.  I saw displaced Bedouin farmers thrown out of Jericho.</p> <p>I have seen the constriction and choking of the E1 zone and the settlements suddenly disappearing, and I believe east Jerusalem is in danger.  Approximately 4 million Palestinians from the remainder of the occupied territory are prohibited from entering east Jerusalem without a permit, and we know there is a crisis there.</p><p>I welcome the Minister and make a modest request which I am happy to discuss with him bilaterally.  The Government gives aid to Palestinian NGOs in the areas of health and education, and my request is that a small portion of this funding be directed towards cultural activity.  I have seen Palestinian theatre companies at work in Hebron, Jenin, Jaffa and Golan.  We know the power of drama to articulate dignity, integrity, self-development and self-confidence, and it is an enormous boost.  France, Sweden and Norway invest quite strongly in this area.  I am aware the Minister is reviewing Irish aid and I would love to give him some examples of how a modest sum would create solidarity and connect Irish artists with Palestinian artists working in Jaffa and other cities in Israel.  This funding would not necessarily have to come directly from Irish Aid but could be channelled through NGOs that already exist.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1173" speakername="Lorraine Higgins" time="13:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700021#V00200"><p>I welcome the Minister.  This is the first time I have had the opportunity to address him since he became Minister, and I wish him well in his role.  I would like the House to note that today marks the first session of the newly elected Ukrainian Parliament after the country's general election in October.  Since February of this year, Ukrainian citizens have experienced a protracted crisis in which many people have been killed or displaced and had their homes and livelihoods destroyed.  There is no doubt that today is a very important step towards the reassertion of peace and stability in the region.</p><p>While the Ukrainian conflict may not dominate the headlines in this part of the world as it did earlier this year, it is important to note that the conflict is ongoing, particularly in the eastern region where Russian-backed separatists and the Ukrainian army continue to clash.  Since a fragile ceasefire was declared in Minsk on 5 September, the UN estimates that 13 people have continued to be killed each day, bringing the death toll since the ceasefire began to almost 1,000.  Those monitoring the situation cautioned that this most delicate of ceasefires could end at any time, potentially plunging the country into increasing warfare.  </p><p>The human cost of this conflict is simply horrendous.  According to estimates from the UN, as of 20 November, 9,921 people have been wounded and at least 4,317 have been killed.  The fatalities include the 298 people on board flight MH17, which was shot down on 17 July and on which there was an Irish citizen.  There are 5.2 million people estimated to be living in conflict areas and 454,000 internally displaced people within Ukraine, with 489,000 people fleeing to neighbouring countries, of whom 400,000 have gone to Russia.</p><p>UN observers also note ongoing violations of international human rights and humanitarian law, including serious human rights abuses by armed groups.  These involve torture, arbitrary detentions, summary executions, forced labour and sexual violence as well as destruction and illegal seizure of property.  In addition to the fatalities, social upheaval and human rights abuses, this ongoing conflict has led to economic turmoil, bringing Ukraine to the brink of financial meltdown, with the IMF warning in September that the country could need a further $19 billion in emergency funding if there is no resolution.</p><p>In rural areas of eastern Ukraine, entire streets and neighbourhoods have been destroyed and, unsurprisingly, businesses and their employees are fleeing the region.  Last Monday night alone, press agencies reported that three more Ukrainian soldiers were killed in clashes.  As the Ukrainian President and Parliament begin their important work today, it is incumbent on the international community, including Ireland, to support and help the Ukrainian people and their newly elected government to bring peace to the region and strengthen its democratic institutions.</p><p>Under the conditions agreed in Minsk, a European observer team has been monitoring the ceasefire.  However, their actions are limited to observing the troop movements and escalating violence, which does little towards brokering a sustained peace in the area.  Western governments which called for the swift creation of a new Ukrainian government after the October elections must now retain their focus on the region and channel it into support, both practical and diplomatic.  The international community must also continue to support the Ukrainian government's demand that Russia withdraw its troops from Ukraine.  These troops number in the region of 7,000, according to recent estimates.  Despite condemnation from the US and Europe, Russia's annexation of the Crimean peninsula continues in what is a violation of international law and an affront to the sovereignty of Ukraine, further undermining stability in the region.</p><p>Given the significance of this day to the Ukraine and its people, who have suffered so much over the past year, as their newly elected government begins the important work of bringing an end to this crisis, I would like to use this opportunity to wish them well and to remind the Ukrainian government of the support it has from the international community of democratic states.  I call on the House to do the same.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="13:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700021#V00300"><p>I welcome the Minister and thank him for entering the Chamber during the recess.  That was a very good debate, which reflected favourably on the House in the media, as did his presence here.  It was a good day.</p><p>On the issue of recognition, he says that most states have recognised Palestine.  I gather that 135 states have done so, with the major exception being states of the European Union.  When the EU reflects on why it is so unpopular among its citizens and why there are motions of censure on the Commission before the European Parliament this week, it might reflect on the tradition in European countries of going out and colonising other countries.  It is a tradition that Ireland does not share.</p><p>Last night I was reading the account by the former Secretary General Noel Dorr, in the Frank Aiken biography, of the independent foreign policy Ireland pursued in New York in the 1950s and 60s.  It is extremely well written, as the Minister can imagine.  We have to bring that dimension to this debate.  As Senator Mac Conghail has said, the two-state solution is disappearing before our very eyes and Europe is sitting on its hands.  In a crucial stage of the Northern Ireland peace process, David Trimble said, &quot;I jumped; now you must jump.&quot;  Ireland has to jump now.  What is taking place is illegal under international law, as Senator Power and others have stated, and the settlements are destroying the possibility of peace.  There are also ramifications for the rest of the region and the problem of ISIS.  It feeds ISIS when Europe is seen to be unfair in its dealings with Israel and Palestine.  The Minister has said he is open to recognising the Palestinian state, but that it is the view of the great majority of European partners that this is not the time to do it.  How long more should we wait?  As a neutral country without any tradition of colonising others, we should stand aside from Europe if the other member states insist on their present policies.  They are consigning the Palestinian people to increasing misery, and if they are not conscious of this it is about time they took a trip with Senator Mac Conghail to see what is going on.  They cannot hide from this any more.</p><p>I welcome the Minister's statement on the &euro;29 million that has been given in Syria.  He and his Department have a proud record in foreign aid.  On Ukraine, is there some possibility that diplomatic links might be made through our contacts with Russia, particularly with regard to Shannon, Aeroflot and so on?  Mr. Putin is not the most popular man on the world stage but we do need to bring him into this as well.  I appreciate the broad thrust of the Minister's support for Ukraine, but can somebody exercise diplomatic persuasion with the Soviet Union?  </p><p>Senator Norris normally speaks on these issues and is a distinguished member of the Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs and Trade, but he is indisposed today.  </p><p>I commend the attendance of the Irish ambassador at the Cenotaph in London and the Minister's interest in reopening the Northern Ireland talks under US Senator Gary Hart.  One of the items raised this week was diplomatic immunity.  As the Minister knows, there have been two cases, one this week involving the United Arab Emirates embassy, in which &euro;80,000 was awarded to three people, and one last year in which the Labour Court awarded staff at the Nigerian embassy a similar large amount.</p> <p> There are protocols on diplomatic immunity, but we need to define them.  One appreciates freedom of speech and the necessity of maintaining diplomatic relations, but these breaches detract from Ireland's reputation as well.  I gather that Ireland's obligations relate to the Vienna Convention, and we respect diplomats.  However, we also have to respect the staff who work in such venues.  They were badly treated and that reflects badly on this country.</p><p>I thank the Minister for coming here and wish him every success in his post.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="13:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700022#W00200"><p>I, too, welcome the Minister to the House.  I also welcome his balanced approach to the complex issue of the Middle East.  I agree with him and utterly condemn the outrageous attack on a synagogue in recent times in which four rabbis died and 13 other people were injured.  Let us remember that 24 children lost their fathers, a fact which is sometimes forgotten in all of the reportage on this issue.</p><p>President Abbas, who is in charge of the Palestinian Authority, condemned the terror attack.  I have great respect for him and believe he is trying very hard to resolve the conflict in the Gaza Strip.  In contrast, his Fatah party congratulated the two attackers on Facebook and called it a blessed operation, Palestinians in Gaza, Judea and Samaria took to the streets and celebrated the brutal murders, Palestinians served sweets and baked goods to people on the street and launched firecrackers in a display of celebrations, and the Palestinian social media has been awash with cartoons and graphics celebrating the attack and encouraging more terror.  The Palestinian Arab leadership should be held responsible for inciting violence, and I say that in the context of trying to resolve this conflict in a peaceful manner.  They have called for days of rage against Israel and glorified the murderers as heroic martyrs.</p><p>I have given the other side of the story and stated the reaction within Palestine and by the Palestinian state as we see it geographically.  It has not been recognised by all countries as a political entity yet.  I do not oppose, in principle, the recognition of the Palestinian state.  That has been Ireland's position since the time of Frank Aiken or, to be more correct, Brian Lenihan senior.  Ireland was the first country to do that.  I am proud of that particular piece of history, and we should continue to pursue that view, but as the Minister pointed out, one must take all the conditions into account before granting recognition.  I accept that many countries - Senator Barrett said 135, but I gather the figure is around 130 - have recognised the state of Palestine.  The Minister said in his debate yesterday with my colleague Deputy Smith that while it was important to recognise Palestine, &quot;it is not by any means a magic wand to resolve the conflict,&quot; and that is essentially true.  However, I do not want to get sidetracked by the issue of recognition of the state of Palestine.  If Ireland is going to recognise it that is fine, but it will not solve the conflict.  There still a conflict even though 130 countries have already recognised the state of Palestine.  Therefore, we must get back down to the basics of dialogue.</p><p>Everybody will criticise Israel, and rightly so, for the settlement expansion programme, which I think is outrageous.  I remember speaking across the table at the Israelis when I visited that country a number of times some years ago.  I asked them whether they had not learned the lesson of history - that we in Ireland suffered from the legacy of plantation in Ulster for 400 years.  The British came in and planted settlements, bringing in people from England, over the Irish population and took their land from them, and we are living with that legacy 400 years later.  At least we have peace on our island, but it is still an underlying part of what the conflict was and remains in order to completely resolve the differences between those from the Unionist tradition and the rest of the island.  I have argued that with Israel, and I know the Minister himself is aware of the history of that from Ireland, so we are very well placed to be an honest broker in the context of dialogue.</p><p>I understand that we in Ireland gave &euro;10.7 million in funding to the Palestinian people last year.  Perhaps that could be used as leverage.  We have talked about levering Israel, but that funding could be used as leverage with the Palestinian Authority to encourage it to renounce incitement of violence against Israel and the Jewish people, which inevitably leads to the cold-blooded murder of Jews.  Hamas still has it in its charter.  People can hide it all they want, but those are the people that are proposing that all the right is on the Palestinian side and all the wrong is on the Israeli side.  It is still stated in the Hamas charter that not only does it want the extinction of the State of Israel, but it wants the extinction of all Jews.  </p><p>What about the Arab states surrounding Israel and Palestine, many of whom are paying lip service to the Palestinian cause?  How much money are they putting into the reconstruction of Gaza?  How many people are question the attitude they have towards the Palestinian refugees in their own countries, whom they treat as second class citizens?  There are questions also to be asked of the Arab states that provide so-called support for the Palestinian cause.  Let them put the their money where their mouths are.  Why should it always be those countries that are neutral that are expected to put equal pressure on the Israelis to resolve the conflict?  People sometimes forget that there are two countries involved in this conflict - the Israeli State and the Palestinians.  If recognition of the Palestinian state means that we would move one inch further towards a peaceful solution, I will be out celebrating on the streets and saying &quot;That was a good day when we recognised Palestine, because it is going to resolve the conflict, and we are never again going to see what happened in Gaza last summer.&quot;  What happened in Gaza will Inevitably be repeated at some point because of the massive superior military power of the Israelis.</p><p>If one was living in Israel during the period of the Gaza invasion, one would have experienced the fact that 2,500 missiles were sent across into Israeli territory.  But for the efficiency of the Iron Dome defence system, there would have been a mini-massacre in the State of Israel.  I would not like to be living in the State of Israel, having to go down into a bunker every few hours, not knowing whether the missiles would get through the Iron Dome system and maybe land in my back garden, killing my family.  I would not like to live in an environment in which all of the states around me were so hostile to my very existence that I could do nothing else but arm myself for protection.</p><p>Of course the Israelis are to be criticised.  I will be the first to do it.  What Israel did last summer in Gaza is indescribably horrific.  I would hate to have been in the Gaza Strip during that period, trying to protect my family.  Let us remember all of the children who died unnecessarily and all of the attacks on UN protected buildings.  I have always argued that there are two sides to this conflict and there is no such thing as one side being right and the other side being wrong.  The current Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade fully understands that, and I hope he will, through the European Union, adopt a particular approach.  If it means having to introduce sanctions against products from the settlements, he should do it, if it is going to bring Israel a little further down the road to dialogue.  The Palestinian side has a responsibility too.  The Israelis are open to dialogue right now and have been at any time.  There is no question that the Palestinians are against dialogue.  It is about trying to get both sides to the table, putting aside certain baggage, as happened in the peace talks here on this island.  That historical baggage put aside, they must look to the future - a future in which the children of both states can live in peace.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" speakername="Jim D'Arcy" time="13:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700022#W00300"><p>There are representatives from Palestine and Israel in the Visitors' Gallery.  I am reminded of the Balfour declaration of 1917 and Arthur Balfour's famous statement, "Nothing matters very much, and few things matter at all."  I do not agree with that.  It matters greatly.  What I would like to see, in the words of St. Paul, is for the two states to settle their differences and come together in peace and harmony.  Left to themselves, they would be able to do that.  That is what we all want, because we feel deeply for both Israel and Palestine.  Go back to Camp David and Oslo and sort out your differences.</p> <p>I believe that Israel and Palestine are, in a sense, victims of a proxy war and are being used by other, stronger forces in the Middle East.  I was on the OSCE/PAS election observer mission for the presidential election in Turkey in August 2014 and also for the early legislative elections in Ukraine in October 2014.  In Turkey I was based in Diyarbakir, a Kurdish city in the south east, not too far from the Turkey-Syria border.  We travelled quite close to the border and to the town of Kobani, which is at present an area of hostilities.  Things are not great there.  In general the Kurds have something of an existential existence, being alone and abandoned.  There are 30 million Kurds on the borders of Turkey, Iraq, Iran and Syria.  They have no homeland and feel politically abandoned.<br/>I was very conscious that when I was on the banks of the River Tigris I was in the cradle of Indo-European civilisation, where the Celts came from and the Kurdish language and cadence is very close to Irish.  I learned one word - &quot;<i>inshallah</i>&quot; when I said to a Kurdish woman &quot;You will have a little president of Turkey next time&quot;.  She said &quot;<i>inshallah</i>&quot;, which means &quot;That will be the day&quot;.  Hopefully now the Kurds will have their day.  To understand the Middle East and its problems, one must look first at the ancient Shi&rsquo;ite-Sunni situation, which goes back as far as the second caliphate in 632 following the death of Mohammed.  In other words, a large part of the conflict is between Iran and Saudi Arabia, mostly by proxy war.  Hence Iran supports Hezbollah, Hamas and the Muslim Brotherhood in Egypt.  Saudi Arabia opposes these bodies fundamentally, but on the ground the religious in Saudi Arabia - not the monarchy - supports ISIS.  It is a proxy war that is going on in the Middle East.  To complicate matters further, America now has little strategic interest in the Middle East, so there is a vacuum and nature abhors a vacuum.<br/>On Ukraine, it is Russia's intention to build up its borders with Europe.  It will do this incrementally.  It is a long-term strategy.  We must stand by the territorial integrity and unity of Ukraine, as the Minister said.  I was in Kharkiv in eastern Ukraine for the early legislative elections.  Although it was controlled by pro-Russian forces, it is now stable and under Government control, but the situation is extremely volatile and needs our support.  Allied to that, although we support Ukraine turning towards Europe, there is massive corruption in Ukraine and some of the pro-European forces are involved in that corruption.  It is 154th out of 178 countries on the corruption league.  That must be addressed and we cannot lose sight of it.  These people need wise guidance.  Having gone through the situation we have gone through with the North, we know what regions of conflict are like and we know that one must talk in the end, so one might as well talk now.  It is with a deep sense of affection and compassion for what is going on in the Middle East and Ukraine that I speak.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700023#X00200"><p>The Senator is way over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1155" speakername="Kathryn Reilly" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700023#X00300"><p>I will try to keep within the time limits and not go over things that have been mentioned by other Senators.  We are at a critical juncture in the Middle East peace process with Palestine and Israel.  As has been mentioned, Israel's continued settlement-building in the West Bank and East Jerusalem is putting the existence of a two-state solution at risk.  The recent backing by the Israeli cabinet of a Bill that would enshrine Israel as a Jewish state discriminates against the 20% of the population who are Arab Christians and Muslims.  It is also discriminatory and treats minorities as second-class citizens.  Even the Israeli Attorney General criticised the Bill for placing the Jewish nature of the state over its democratic nature.  The dangerous politics that is being played with religious sites in occupied East Jerusalem at the moment could raise tensions to the point of reigniting a new <i>intifada</i>.  As was mentioned by a number of Senators, we all watched as Israel bombarded the illegally blockaded the Gaza Strip, killing over 2,000 people and committing what many academics and critics said were war crimes.  The Minister came to the House in the recess to discuss this.<br/>At what point will the international community stop appeasing Israel by turning a blind eye to its war crimes and human rights abuses?  Ireland and the international community have a responsibility to support the Palestinian people, especially at this critical moment, when things are hanging by a thread.  The focus in the media has changed.  We are not hearing any more about what is happening in Gaza and Palestine as we were during the summer, but the public needs to know that recent events have the situation reaching boiling point once again.<br/>I mentioned during the summer when the Minister was here that it was wrong that we abstained on the UN Human Rights Council vote during the Gaza onslaught and it is wrong that we voted against the motion at the annual International Atomic Energy Agency meeting calling on Israel to sign up to the Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty, NPT.  It is disappointing that we have not led by example in the EU by officially recognising the state of Palestine.  We continue to hear that Sweden has acted outside of agreed measures by unilaterally doing this, but we have not followed suit and shown similar leadership.  If the Minister were to do this, he would have the overall support of the people of Ireland and of the Opposition parties in these Houses.  There is an urgent need for a peaceful solution in the region and it is key that Ireland plays a role in aiding this process.  Recognising the state of Palestine based on the 1967 borders with East Jerusalem as its capital would go a long way towards assisting that peace process.  I know the Minister and his predecessor have continued to seek a deal at EU level, but while the Palestinian people need the strong support of the EU, that does not stop us acting in parallel and independently on this.<br/>Turning to other issues, I am horrified by the brutal and sectarian attacks by ISIS militants in Syria and Iraq.  Their sexist, racist and sectarian agenda must be challenged and defeated.  I commend the Kurdish communities that have been bravely fighting the attacks in northern Syria and Iraq and repelling ISIS advances on their liberated areas.  These areas have seen a democratic and social revolution, which is a beacon of light for others in the Middle East, especially considering the issues of women's and minority rights.  Unfortunately, Turkey's reaction during the battle of Kobani, for example, when its forces literally sat on their tanks as ISIS advanced on the towns, was shameful.  I ask that the Minister's Department consider supplying these Kurdish communities with the humanitarian assistance they need and to ensure the transport and delivery is organised with the Kurdish authorities.  There have been complaints that international aid meant for Kurdish areas sent to Ankara or Damascus has been misappropriated.<br/>I am concerned about the deteriorating situation in Ukraine, especially in the east of the country.  While the truce is still in place, a UN report last week stated that since the truce came into force, 957 people have been killed and there are continuing violations on both sides.  That is an average of around 13 people killed per day.</p> <p>In all, at least 4,300 people have been killed since the conflict erupted in April.  Additionally, as winter is setting in, there is a real worry about gas supplies which come from Russia.  Again, we call on all sides to abide by the ceasefire and for all Ukrainian forces to enter into dialogue.  International actors need to stop interfering in Ukraine for geopolitical and selfish reasons.  Rather, they should be encouraging peaceful negotiations.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1196" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="13:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700024#Y00200"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire.  This is the first time I have had the pleasure of addressing the Minister in this House.  I thank him for the presentation he made today, which was measured, as one would expect from him.</p><p>I am aware of the fact there are representatives from both Israel and Palestine here, so I want to say I have no idea what it is like to live in a place where, at any moment, a suicide bomber can take people out or a rocket can be fired from some place.  However, I cannot begin to imagine what it must be like to live on the other side where, at any moment, a fleet of bombers will come in and flatten an entire area.  The reaction by Israel, particularly this summer, is reprehensible.  Having said that, the actions of Hamas are reprehensible.</p><p>The Israeli Defence Force and the politicians who control it really have to step back and see what they are doing.  We live in an era where it is possible to take out a specific house.  I was told recently that the satellite system is so good that it is possible to pick out a man on a street corner picking his nose, and more importantly, it is possible to see what he picked out of it.  I do not believe there is any justification for flattening entire streets.  For people who migrated largely as a result of the horrors of what went on during the Second World War in Europe, it is absolutely unbelievable to see them turn an entire geographic area into what they themselves suffered in Europe, in particular in Poland.  I just cannot believe it.  I cannot believe that it has been going on and that, at no stage, the people who vote for the Parliament in Israel have not been able to turn around and say, &quot;Do you know what lads, the response here is a total overreaction&quot;.</p><p>I would have to say, from this side of the world, looking at what has happened, particularly last summer, the Israeli Defence Force has become the greatest recruiter for ISIS and Hamas.  Even somebody like me would find myself swaying towards the other side when I see the reaction.  I agree with Senator Mooney that there are two sides to this issue.  However, I do not see a real willingness on either side to actually engage in dialogue.  There is a lot of smoke and mirrors but I do not see any real dialogue.  If there were a real desire to enter into real peace negotiations, surely the settlements would have stopped by now.  We in Ireland know what it means to have property grabbed by a foreign state and we know what it led to in this country for several hundred years.</p><p>Some years ago, as president of the Teachers Union of Ireland, a motion was passed at our annual conference setting up an academic boycott of Israel.  At the time, I had misgivings about it and I did not propose the motion.  However, immediately the motion was passed, I was subjected to several hundred threatening e-mails with some of the most outlandish threats I have ever heard.  Having said that, I received several hundred e-mails congratulating the union on the brave stance we took.  I do not believe either side was right.  Certainly, if I receive e-mails as a result of what I have had to say here today, bring them on - I do not care.  At some stage, we are going to have to speak out and stop what is going on in this part of the world.  It is time for this country to recognise the sovereign state of Palestine and I would ask the Minister to bring that forward as quickly as he can.</p><p>I want to make two final points.  I want to recognise the tremendous contribution that has been made by this country, in particular by our Defence Forces, many of whom have lost their lives in the pursuit of peace in countries all over the world.  I want to recognise the job the Defence Forces have done in maintaining peace in countries we have really nothing to do with.</p><p>Finally, given the representatives from Palestine and Israel are here, I plead with them, in the name of the children that are being born, would they please respect human rights, start some serious dialogue with one another and stop the constant incursions onto each other's lands?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1055" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="13:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700024#Y00300"><p>I acknowledge with thanks the contribution of Members to this debate.  If time will allow, I will conclude with some remarks on the issues and questions raised.  If the House will agree, I will deal with the matter of Ukraine first, then the issue of Syria and I will retain the bulk of my commentary for the Middle East peace process, which Members will acknowledge did form the majority of the debate this afternoon.</p><p>On the matter of Ukraine, I wish to specifically acknowledge the contribution of Senators Higgins, Barrett and Jim D'Arcy.  The crisis in Ukraine is one of the most serious the European Union has faced in many years.  Ending the conflict in a peaceful manner that safeguards the sovereignty of Ukraine and acknowledges its independence and its territorial integrity is an absolute priority for Ireland and the international community.</p><p>I acknowledge what Senators have said, namely, Russia has a key role to play in this regard.  Russia needs to take urgent steps to de-escalate the situation in eastern Ukraine, not least by asking and encouraging the rebels it supports to join the other parties in fully implementing the commitments signed up to in Minsk.</p><p>As I said earlier, the agreement in Minsk does provide the basis for a peaceful, inclusive and negotiated settlement that we all wish to see for Ukraine.  Last month, the people of Ukraine gave their political leaders a clear and strong mandate to proceed with long overdue political and economic reforms.  Included in the reform agenda is the very valid point made by Senator D'Arcy on the matter of corruption and the need to ensure that best international practice and standards are observed.  It is vital, therefore, that the new Government in Kiev seizes the opportunity to reform the country and place it on a path to economic stability and, indeed, to prosperity.</p><p>I want to take this opportunity to express my deep gratitude and appreciation for the vital work the OSCE is carrying out in Ukraine.  The special monitoring mission played a key role in helping to secure agreement on the ceasefire and on the peace plan.  The brave men and women of the mission travelled throughout the conflict zones under difficult and mostly dangerous conditions.  Without their tireless efforts, it is difficult to envisage how the peace agreement could otherwise have been reached.  The mission also has an important role to play in monitoring the ceasefire line and ensuring Ukraine's full and effective control of its border with Russia.  I wish to pay tribute to the five Irish members of the mission for the valuable contribution they make in pursuit of stability and peace in the region.</p><p>I wish to refer briefly the humanitarian situation in Ukraine, which was referred to by Senator Higgins.  Of course, the conflict has exacted a heavy toll in terms of the trauma, difficulty, displacement, violence and death.  Thousands of innocent civilians have been subjected to deplorable violence and suffering over many months and we are now faced with a serious humanitarian crisis.  The EU has led the way in providing urgently needed support for the local people.  Ireland is currently examining the scope for possible bilateral support for Ukraine at this time.  In this regard, I might say, for the benefit of Senators, that Ireland intends ratifying the three association agreements with Ukraine, Moldova and Georgia together and we will seek parliamentary approval for the three agreements over the coming months.</p> <p>Senator Mullins mentioned the issue of refugees and minorities in Iraq and Syria.  The protection of Christian and other religious minorities in the region is, as the Senator said, a matter of real concern.  Again, I stress that refuge in Europe or Ireland does not offer anything like a real solution because the numbers are too great and because it would mean the end of the ancient Christian communities which have survived in the region, as Senator Jim D'Arcy said, since the earliest days of Christianity.  The solution is to tackle the threats experienced by these communities and safeguard their rights to live in their homelands.  Senators will be aware that the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Fitzgerald, has ultimate responsibility for such issues, and efforts have been made to ensure Ireland is as accommodating as possible to those fleeing conflict.  All of this year's intake of refugees under the annual scheme operated in conjunction with the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees will come from Syria.  The intention is that the level will increase next year and into 2016, resulting in more than 300 Syrian refugees coming to Ireland during the period, some to my home town, Portlaoise, and my constituency.  In response to Senator Mullins, I have separately raised the issue of Ireland receiving some of those from Christian communities in Iraq who are attempting to flee the violence, and the Minister for Justice and Equality is heavily engaged in the process.<br/>I acknowledge the points raised by Senators Power, Reilly, Mullins, Mac Conghail, Barrett, Mooney and Craughwell on the Middle East.  The prospect of the resumption of direct negotiations is, as Senators said, very poor.  Neither Israeli nor Palestinian leaders are in a position to negotiate successfully, for different reasons.  We would support a renewal of negotiations because, as Senator D'Arcy said, there is no other way to reach agreement.  However, talks are worth having only if both parties genuinely seek to forge an agreement.  That is why I would argue strongly for a greater focus within the EU on the occupation, especially the settlements.  We need to exert pressure so that Israel sees the end of occupation as something to be achieved in its own national interest.  Although many Israelis have always believed it, we need to strengthen the position.<br/>At the Cairo conference on Gaza, many speakers stressed, as I did, that we could not return to the <i>status quo</i>.  I very much agree with Senator Craughwell&rsquo;s points on this.  Without a sustained political attention to resolving the underlying problems of Gaza, the <i>status quo</i>will resume by default and, regrettably, the cycle of violence will continue.  Senator Mac Conghail mentioned Irish Aid and I acknowledge his first-hand reflections and have taken note of the points he raised.  At the Cairo conference, I pledged &euro;500,000 for immediate humanitarian aid to Gaza, and this has been paid to the United Nations Relief and Works Agency, UNRWA.  This is in addition to the &euro;500,000 donated when the crisis arose earlier this year.  I also pledged &euro;2 million over the next two years in reconstruction aid, and Senators will be aware that Irish Aid already supports the Palestinian people with &euro;10 million per year, of which a significant proportion goes to Gaza.  I take Senator Power's points on this and will look into the cultural engagement which Senator Mac Conghail mentioned.<br/>I paid very close attention to the debate earlier in the autumn on the recognition of Palestine and the motion on it last month.  I also listened very closely to the points made this afternoon, particularly those of Senators Power, Barrett, Craughwell, Mooney and others.  I assure the Senators, as I did the members of the foreign affairs committee earlier this month, that I do not have a closed mind on the issue.  Along with the great majority of EU partners, we continue to seek recognition by agreement as part of an overall settlement.  It is not clear that recognition now would contribute to reaching the objective.  We must not think of it as some type of panacea that will immediately make a huge difference.  However, I acknowledge the sentiments, comments, observations, points and advice I have received here this afternoon.<br/>Senator Mooney raised the point that there are negative side to be considered, such as the possible collapse of the Palestinian Authority - which has renamed itself the State of Palestine - were Israel to renounce the Oslo Accords and given that the Palestinian Authority controls less than half of the West Bank.  There is a process of reflection across the EU on the issue of recognition, and we are actively engaging in it.  I am very conscious of the stalemate in the peace process and the unacceptable and daily worsening situation on the ground.  I do not rule out any option, including an early recognition of Palestine, if it will help move things forward positively towards our overriding goal of a two-state solution.<br/>I acknowledge the contribution of Senator Power and the reflections of Senator Mac Conghail on the settlement products.  In recent years, Ireland has focused strongly on the effects of the settlements and the need to press Israel specifically on the issue.  In EU statements and Council conclusions we have succeeded in focusing much attention on the issue.  I accept Senator Power's point that we need to do more, and quickly.  Settlement products are, in some ways, a distraction from the main issue, which is the settlements themselves.  Most settlements produce nothing.  However, we have continued to exert pressure on this aspect of the issue.<br/>Settlement goods attract a higher duty on entry to the EU.  In the last year, the EU has clarified that EU research funding may not be spent in settlements and that it will not accept Israeli veterinary certification of meat coming from the settlements.  I want the EU to go ahead as promised and introduce the guidelines on labelling of settlement goods.  If this does not happen soon, and progressively, we will consider doing so ourselves.  However, an outright ban is not feasible.  There is no possibility yet of achieving EU agreement to exclude settlement products altogether, and as long as they can enter the EU market, we cannot exclude them from Ireland.  The proportion of such products reaching shelves is quite small.<br/>Members mentioned the human rights issues and we concentrate our main focus and resources on the overall political issue.  Only by ending the occupation will these problems truly be resolved.  Ironically, those partners which are more protective of Israel are better placed to press it on specific human rights issues.</p> <p>Ireland also supports a range of Israeli and Palestinian human rights organisations which regularly combat the direct effects of these policies.  </p><p>I am pleased to come before the House.  I acknowledge the contributions of Senators and thank them for their engagement.  I have taken careful note of all of the points raised over a wide range of issues. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1154" speakername="Averil Power" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700026#AA00200"><p>I thank the Minister for his response.  The article published in <i>The Irish Times</i>yesterday refers to action by the European Union.  Apart from products from Israeli settlements, does the Minister have any other actions in mind?  To what specific actions was he referring?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700026#AA00300"><p>Statements are concluded.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1154" speakername="Averil Power" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700026#AA00400"><p>The Minister invited questions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700026#AA00500"><p>We do not have questions during statements.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.173" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1055" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700026#AA00600"><p>There are a range of issues on which the European Union needs to clarify its position and it needs to intensify its hand in the negotiations.  Undoubtedly, the Middle East peace process is important to the European Union because the countries of the region are our neighbours.  I acknowledge that over recent years, the matter has not been as high on the agenda as it could have been.  Following my intervention at the October Foreign Affairs Council meeting, I was pleased that the matter not only moved up the agenda but also that the recently appointed High Commissioner, Federica Mogherini, visited the region on 7 and 8 November and presented a detailed report to members of the Council.</p><p>I am urging my EU colleagues to use the Union's undoubted influence with the parties involved in the conflict to ensure we can bring about a sustainable solution.  We must build on the peace because it is not sufficient to endure a ceasefire or what could be described as a negative peace.  We must impress upon the parties the need to engage and ensure the conflict is brought to an end.  This will involve dealing with the issues raised by Senator Power, including the unacceptable settlements, labelling of settlement products and the introduction of guidelines, policies and advice to ensure we can impress upon the Israeli Government in particular our view that the consistent expansion of settlements is entirely unacceptable and in direct conflict with what we all want, namely, a viable two-state solution.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.174" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700026#AA00700"><p>When is it proposed to sit again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700026#AA00800"><p>Ar 2.30 p.m. D&eacute; M&aacute;irt seo chugainn.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.176" nospeaker="true" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700026#AA00900">Adjournment Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.177" nospeaker="true" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700026#AA01000">Respite Care Services</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700026#AA01100"><p>I welcome the Minister of State at the Department of Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, Deputy Damien English, to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.179" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700026#AA01200"><p>Gabhaim bu&iacute;och leis an Aire as ucht teacht isteach sa Seanad inniu chun an t-&aacute;bhar t&aacute;bhachtach seo a phl&eacute;.  I and my colleague, Councillor Damien O'Reilly, have been contacted by constituents in Dunboyne, County Meath, who have a family member who regularly avails of respite services.  This gives the family respite from their duties of constant care and attention.  The family recently received a letter from the Health Service Executive prescribing charges of &euro;25 per day for the respite service in certain circumstances.  This is the first the family has heard of this charge.  While I understand a system of charges has been in place for some time, I wonder if it is being enforced.  The only people who will be affected by the charge are families who are in a difficult position and must carry a significant burden because a family member is badly in need of respite services.  This burden is also one of love.  While they love their family member, the duty of care they have clearly make it difficult for them at times.  It appears such families will be required to pay a significant amount of money that many of them do not have for a respite service.  Will the Minister of State outline the position regarding charges for respite services?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700026#AA01300"><p>I thank Senator Byrne for raising this matter.  I apologise on behalf of my colleague, the Minister of State, Deputy Kathleen Lynch, who could not come to the House as she is in the D&aacute;il.  I understand she is not aware of the details of the case raised by the Senator.  Perhaps he will furnish her with a copy of the letter to which he referred to enable the matter to be explored.</p><p>I propose to clarify the position in response to the Senator's request that the Minister discuss and justify the proposal to charge medical card holders for respite care.  The provision of respite care is vital in meeting the needs of individual service users.  It also helps reduce the pressures elsewhere on the wider health service, such as acute hospitals and long-term residential care.  Respite care is provided in a number of different ways and settings to provide support for carers of persons with care needs in the home.</p><p>No new proposals to charge medical card holders for respite care have been brought forward by my Department during the lifetime of this Government, nor are any such proposals currently under consideration.  However, charges for the maintenance element of long-stay inpatient services, which may include respite inpatient services and which apply to adults with full or limited eligibility, were provided for under the Health (Amendment) Act 2005.  These charges came into effect on 15 July 2005 under the Health (Charges for In-Patient Services) Regulations 2005.</p><p>Under the Act, long-stay charges for inpatient services only apply to the further provision of inpatient services to adults who have already received at least 30 days of inpatient services during the immediately preceding 12-month period.  Accordingly, many respite episodes would not attract any charge.  Those receiving ongoing acute care and those being supported under the nursing homes support scheme are excluded from these charges.</p><p>The regulations provide for two different classes of income-based charges in respect of the maintenance element of the inpatient services provided.  Class 1 relates to charges for those receiving inpatient services on premises where 24-hour nursing care is provided, subject to a current maximum of &euro;175 per week for a person whose income is &euro;208 or more.  Class 2 charges apply where 24-hour nursing care is not provided, subject to a current maximum of &euro;130 per week for a person whose income is &euro;194 or more. </p><p>Affordability and the avoidance of financial hardship are built in features of the charging provisions under the 2005 Act and regulation.  First, the Act caps the amount which may be charged at 80% of the non-contributory State pension weekly rate.  This currently means an upper limit of &euro;175.20 per week.  Second, the charges are structured to ensure that those paying them retain a reasonable income for personal use, namely, at least &euro;33 per week for those paying class 1 rates and at least &euro;64 per week for those paying class 2 rates.  Third, the Act provides that the HSE may reduce or waive a charge imposed on a person if necessary to avoid undue financial hardship.</p><p>To assist in the fair application of the provisions of the 2005 Act and regulations, the HSE has developed national guidelines for the determination of long-stay charges for inpatient services.  These include the need to have regard to the individual circumstances of each service user and his or her dependants.  The guidelines ensure that the applicable charge is determined taking account of each person's income and necessary outgoings while receiving care, including reasonable regular financial commitments.  This avoids any unfair burden on the service user or his or her dependants.  Perhaps the Senator will furnish us with the letter in order that the case can be investigated as it appears some confusion has arisen.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.181" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014112700026#AA01400"><p>The position is clear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-11-27a.182" nospeaker="true" time="14:15:00" ><p>The Seanad adjourned at 3.10 p.m. until 2.30 p.m. on Tuesday, 2 December 2014.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>