<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Leas-Chathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.4" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Fintan Warfield that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Culture, Heritage and the Gaeltacht to extend the Copyright and Related Rights Act 2000 to include the legal deposit of digital publications.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Frank Feighan of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Culture, Heritage and Gaeltacht to outline the targets set by Waterways Ireland for traffic potential on the Shannon-Erne waterway this summer.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Maura Hopkins of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Justice and Equality to provide an update on the planned refurbishment of Roscommon courthouse.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Rose Conway-Walsh of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine to provide an update on how his Department is dealing with revenue laws, tax compliance measures and sales to vulture funds insofar as they relate to the farming community.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Colm Burke of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Business, Enterprise and Innovation to introduce a pilot quota of employment permits for the nursing home sector. </blockquote> <p>I regard the matters raised by the Senators as suitable for discussion.  I have selected the matters raised by Senators Fintan Warfield, Frank Feighan, Maura Hopkins and Rose Conway-Walsh and they will be taken now.  Senator Colm Burke may give notice on another day of the matter he wishes to raise.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.7" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#A00300">Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.8" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#A00350">Digital Archiving</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#A00400"><p>I welcome the Minister of State.  I requested the presence of the Minister for Culture, Heritage and the Gaeltacht to address the upcoming Copyright and Other Intellectual Property Law Provisions Bill 2018 in the knowledge that it would soon be taken in the Chamber.  It was my hope some clarity could be provided on the amendment to section 198 of the principal Act.  It is my belief and that of many within libraries and the heritage sector that there is a serious omission from the amendment that will result in an increasing hole in national memory which will make the future understanding of our society difficult.  This is a live issue as the average life of a webpage is 100 days.  Currently, legal deposit legislation provides that a library, for example, has a responsibility to obtain every hard copy publication in the State.  That provision needs to be adapted for the digital age.  Libraries must be able to harvest the  dot ie domain.  We entrust them with the responsibility to collect hard copies and it is time to do the same for digital formats.  The consultation process on the Bill came within the remit of the Department of Culture, Heritage and the Gaeltacht, but the Bill comes within the remit of the Department of Business, Enterprise and Innovation.  I wonder whether if the two Departments are talking about this.  Have they explored the recommendations made in the report of the copyright review committee?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1261" speakername="Jim Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#A00500"><p>The Minister for Culture, Heritage and the Gaeltacht thanks the Senator for raising this issue.  Legal deposit legislation is an important instrument in national cultural policy.  In most countries it is relied on to ensure the published output of the nation is collected and preserved by one or more prescribed institutions in order that citizens and researchers within the country and abroad will be guaranteed permanent access to the intellectual and cultural memory of the nation.</p><p>Under the Copyright and Related Rights Act 2000, there are 13 prescribed institutions that are legal deposit libraries, of which the National Library of Ireland Is one.  The remainder include the main university libraries such as Trinity College Dublin, the National University of Ireland and the University of Limerick, as well as UK-based libraries such as the British Library and the national libraries of Wales and Scotland.  Last year the Department of Culture, Heritage and the Gaeltacht undertook a public consultation process on the legal deposit of published digital material in the 21st century in the context of copyright legislation.  A total of 42 submissions were received in response from members of the public, publishers and the library and archives community.  In the consultation process the views of stakeholder were sought on whether policy on legal deposit should include the collecting, preserving and making available of all contemporary publication formats, including online digital formats such as websites.</p><p>I will summarise the findings of the consultation process.  There was general agreement that a failure to provide for policy extensions to keep pace with technology would have serious consequences for academic research and access to information for Irish citizens and could lead to an increasing digital black hole.  There are opportunities to innovate and explore new ways of interrogating data, as well as recognition of the fundamental principle of the provision of continuing access to information as part of a fully functioning society.  Access to material under copyright should be balanced with respect for the privacy of the individual, the rights of content creators and publishers, for whom their content is their economic livelihood.  Responses from national libraries in other European countries highlighted the fact that such legislation was <i>in situ</i>in their countries and was, in effect, a best international practice requirement in this area.</p><p>The Copyright and Related Rights Act 2000 is the responsibility of my colleague, the Minister for Business, Enterprise and Innovation.  In March the Department of Business, Enterprise and Innovation published the Copyright and Other Intellectual Property Law Provisions Bill 2018, which includes a provision to amend the Copyright and Related Rights Act 2000 aimed at broadening the copyright deposit system to enable existing copyright deposit institutions to accept published material in digital format, as well as, or instead of, physical copies.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Jim Daly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2328"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2328&amp;amp;pid=JimDaly&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This amendment is aimed at broadening the copyright deposit system to enable existing copyright deposit institutions to accept published material in digital format as well as, or instead of, physical copies.  The amendment will allow copyright deposit institutions to accept publications in electronic format on a voluntary basis while creating an obligation on publishers to comply with any request for such material in electronic format.  The Bill is on Second Stage in the D&aacute;il and the Department of Culture, Heritage and the Gaeltacht continues to liaise with the Department of Business, Enterprise and Innovation regarding it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#B00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  His response was extremely positive until the second last paragraph which stated that the amendment would allow copyright deposit institutions to accept publications in electronic format and require publishers to comply with any request.  It is impossible for the National Library of Ireland, for example, to contact the several million websites we have in this country.  It has already swept the ".ie" domain and it cannot obviously display that information on site at the library or online for the public to see.  As such, we need stronger legislation.</p> <p>The current proposal is silent on web archiving.  The copyright review group proposed legislation, including a provision to the effect that it would not be an infringement of the rights conferred in the Act if a board or authority reproduced any work made available in the State through the Internet.  We will seek to propose amendments if the Bill remains as it is when it comes to the Seanad.  It would be disappointing if we allowed the Bill to go through the Oireachtas without making this amendment and allowed the legislation to remain silent on web archiving.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1261" speakername="Jim Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#B00300"><p>I understand the points the Senator makes.  They appear to be valid suggestions.  He makes the point that submission of the data would be on voluntary basis and the Bill should be strengthened in that regard.  As I outlined, the Bill is on Second Stage in the D&aacute;il and there is still ample opportunity for the Houses to deal with some of that detail, in particular on Committee Stage.  The submissions which have been made can be reviewed.  In that context, amendments can certainly be made to the legislation if the Houses so approve.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.14" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#B00400">Waterways Issues</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#B00500"><p>The development of the Shannon-Erne waterway has been one of the unsung benefits of the Good Friday Agreement.  It is a flagship cross-Border project which involved the major reconstruction of many canal structures to make them suitable for modern cruisers.  The canal was opened to traffic on 23 May 1994 on time and within budget.  Since that time, the link has opened thousands of miles of navigable waterways in both the Republic and Northern Ireland.  It links the two great waterways on our island, namely, the Erne system and the Shannon navigation.  As Waterways Ireland states on its website, the waterway has opened up countryside which few had ever seen.</p> <p>Over the past few decades, this tranquil stretch of water has grown in popularity, in particular in the towns and villages along its length.  One can travel by boat now from Limerick to Enniskillen.  The beauty of this waterway system is incredible and must be seen to be believed.  Unsurprisingly, it has become a major attraction for both domestic tourists and visitors from all corners of the world.  It has also been of significant benefit to local economies along the route as tourists stop off at towns and villages while cruising the waterways.  A number of boat hire companies have also been created over the years offering barges and cruisers for weekend trips or week-long journeys.  Walking and bike trails have also been developed along the route of the waterways.</p> <p>There has been some concern in recent times at the introduction of restricted lock opening times on the Shannon-Erne canal system.  Since the canal system was reopened in 1994, the automated locks have been operational between 9 a.m. and 8 p.m. from April to the end of October.  This year, however, Waterways Ireland restricted the operating times from 9 a.m. to 6 p.m. until 16 May.  A number of local people have contacted my office to tell me this restriction will also apply from mid-September to the end of October.  Of course, any restrictions will have a knock-on effect on the towns and villages which benefit from the waterways.  Waterways Ireland must do all it can to ensure the waterways system is marketed to the fullest extent to ensure these towns and villages have the opportunity to maximise its benefits.  This includes ensuring maximum access to the water for tourists and boating enthusiasts to maximise traffic potential.  I am also interested to know what Waterways Ireland&rsquo;s targets are in this regard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1261" speakername="Jim Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#B00600"><p>Waterways Ireland has informed the Minister for Culture, Heritage and the Gaeltacht, Deputy Josepha Madigan, that the Shannon-Erne waterway locks will be open daily from 9 a.m. to 8 p.m. as of 17 May 2018 onwards throughout the summer season.  Operational hours will continue to be subject to ongoing review to ensure Waterways Ireland delivers a high quality service to waterway users in the most efficient and effective manner.</p> <p>Waterways Ireland measures boat traffic by the number of lock passages.  There were 1,600 lock passages at lock 1 on the Shannon-Erne waterway in 2017 and 1,439 passages at lock 16.  It is expected that the 1,600 lock passages recorded will be exceeded in 2018.  According to visitor monitoring devices, there were 155,273 user incidents, which is a mix of walkers and cyclists, in 2017.  Waterways Ireland expects in excess of 160,000 locals and visitors to experience walking and cycling along the Shannon-Erne in 2018.  One of Waterways Ireland's main goals, with the support of the Department of Culture, Heritage and the Gaeltacht, is to inspire more people to discover and enjoy recreational activities on inland waterways and to explore the rich environment and heritage attractions along the 1,000 km of navigation in its care.</p> <p>The Shannon-Erne waterway runs between Leitrim village and just north of Belturbet and comprises 63 km of river, lake and still-water canal which links the two great waterways on the island, the Erne system and the Shannon navigation.  Over the past two decades, this tranquil stretch of water has grown in popularity, particularly in the towns and villages along its length.  Cruisers and barges move freely along its waters, mooring up in some of the six fully serviced public marinas found along its length.</p> <p>There are 16 locks which are managed electro-hydraulically by a smart card which helps ease passage through the locks while a number of boat hire companies offer barges and cruisers for hire.  Waterways Ireland currently avails of a number of social media platforms such as Facebook, Instagram, Twitter and YouTube to promote the use of the Shannon-Erne waterway as well as through its own publications and website.  Waterways Ireland highlights the tranquility that can be found at the heart of the Shannon-Erne waterway as well as the opportunities for walking and cycling adjacent to the waterway.  Waterways Ireland highlights in particular for visitors the Ballyconnell canal walk, Ballinamore canal bank walk and cycle route, the Leitrim village to Kilclare walk and the Kingfisher cycle trail, which has its starting point in Ballinamore.  Waterways Ireland also draws attention to the local mountains for the more adventurous among visitors and the myriad of wildlife that can be observed along the route.  Anglers are assured of finding a paradise of fishing and several golf courses in the area are also highlighted for potential enthusiasts.</p> <p>The Minister informs me that Waterways Ireland has targeted a growth rate of 5% overall and aims to achieve it through a strategic marketing plan.  "Head into the Blue" and "Blueway do it your way" are the taglines used to promote the Shannon-Erne blueway which showcases a staggering 70 km of paddling trails from Leitrim village to Belturbet while connecting with the Erne system at Crom Estate.  Along with its partners, F&aacute;ilte Ireland, the Irish Sports Council, the National Trails Office and Canoeing Ireland, Waterways Ireland markets 15 individual paddling journeys on lakes, rivers and canals.  Trail heads, access points and services are all shown on downloadable maps available on the Waterways Ireland website.  The paddling trails are complemented by 30 km of walking loops and linear trails along with 12.5 km of superb cycling options around Ballinamore.  In addition to the marketing of the Shannon-Erne waterway itself, Waterways Ireland also promotes accommodation and culinary options in the surrounding areas.</p> <p>The spring campaign to market the Shannon-Erne blueway for 2018 ran across national radio, national and regional press, both print and online, as well as across social networks and Waterways Ireland's website.  It included familiarisation trips for journalists to the Shannon and Erne systems.  Waterways Ireland's extensive events programme delivers new events on the Shannon-Erne waterway, encouraging greater spectator and participants to the waterways.</p> <p>The development of the brochure "The Life Aquatic" focused on the Shannon-Erne system and the delivery of business to activity and hospitality providers along its length.  The brochure also had an online persona and was shared and promoted across social media networks, providing people with lots of reasons to stop, stay and explore.</p> <p>In line with Project Ireland 2040, the Minister, Deputy Madigan, and staff of the Department of Culture, Heritage and the Gaeltacht are striving to protect the natural heritage which provides the setting and inspiration for our island's creative output.  Critical investment in our inland navigable waterways will benefit both rural communities and our national tourism.  Deputy Madigan's Department will continue to facilitate, support and assist the work of Waterways Ireland in this endeavour.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#B00700"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his comprehensive response and note again that the Shannon-Erne waterway is a truly wonderful asset which has seen many spin-offs.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Frank Feighan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2014"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2014&amp;amp;pid=FrankFeighan&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->As the Minister of State noted, one of them is the Shannon-Erne blueway which features 70 km of paddling trails from Leitrim village to Belturbet.  The trail is complemented by more than 30 km of beautiful walking and cycling trails around the town of Ballinamore.  Needless to say in the context of this discussion, other towns such as Keshcarrigan, Ballinamore and Newtowngore need to have the greatest possible access to tourists who use the Shannon-Erne canal system in order that they can avail of the benefits of tourism.</p><p>I live in Boyle which is close to Lough Key forest park and residents of the town also have access to the River Shannon.  We can do much more with this natural resource, especially given that the weather changes little throughout the year.  We should further develop this cross-Border project that has provided great joy for many people on the island and further afield since 1994 and before the Good Friday Agreement was signed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1261" speakername="Jim Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#C00200"><p>I do not believe the Senator and I could do any more to promote the Shannon-Erne waterway through Waterways Ireland than we have in our contributions.  As someone from west Cork, I have a strong sense of my county's natural assets and the need to promote them.  Therefore, it goes a little against the grain to promote the Senator's local area, but I do not resent doing so.  I congratulate him and hope he will continue to promote it.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.20" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#C00300">Court Accommodation Refurbishment</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1415" speakername="Maura Hopkins" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#C00400"><p>I thank the Minister of State, Deputy Jim Daly, for coming to the House to discuss the refurbishment of the courthouse in Roscommon town.  I raised this matter many times with the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Charles Flanagan, most recently on his visit last week to Roscommon and Galway.  I emphasise the importance of the project and the need for it to proceed in a timely fashion.  I am aware that it was included in Project Ireland 2040.  </p> <p>Facilities in Roscommon courthouse which has two courtrooms are inadequate and not fit for purpose in a modern courts system.  Great work has been done in recent years to support vulnerable witnesses in the courts process.  The current facilities in Roscommon courthouse are not adequate in that regard.  Locations at which family law sittings take place, including Roscommon town, have a particular need for special protection measures for witnesses.  This very much highlights the importance of the work carried out.</p> <p>A certain amount of work has been done in respect of Roscommon courthouse.  When Roscommon County Council moved from Roscommon courthouse into its new &Aacute;ras on Chontae building, the Courts Service which had occupied the other part of the courthouse purchased the entire building.  That is a positive development which I hope highlights a commitment to modernise the entire building to facilitate the Courts Service.  I understand that, when completed, the project will include the development of a third courtroom, judicial chambers, consultation rooms, custody facilities, as well as facilities for staff, jurors and members of the legal profession.  What is the timeframe for completion of the Roscommon courthouse project under Project Ireland 2040?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1261" speakername="Jim Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#C00500"><p>On behalf of the Minister for Justice and Equality, I thank the Senator for raising this matter.  The Minister acknowledges her interest in the subject and regrets that he is unable to be present.</p> <p>The Senator will be aware that a significant courts building programme was included in the Government's 2012 infrastructure stimulus package which included the construction and extension or refurbishment of seven courthouses in Drogheda, Letterkenny, Limerick, Wexford, Waterford. Cork and Mullingar, respectively.  The Minister is pleased to confirm that new courthouses have been delivered in Drogheda, Letterkenny, Wexford, Limerick, Waterford and Cork since June 2017, with the final project, Mullingar courthouse, due to be completed in the coming weeks.  The total capital cost of this initiative is approximately &euro;149.9 million.</p> <p>In terms of scale, the courts public private partnership, PPP, bundle project is the largest capital building project ever undertaken by the Courts Service, delivering 31 courtrooms and 36,000 sq. m of accommodation nationwide.  The Government's investment of more than &euro;523 million in courts infrastructure between 2003 and 2016 underlined its continued commitment to improving access to justice and providing modern and comfortable facilities for all users of the courts.</p> <p>A number of further developments related to Courts Service accommodation requirements are outlined in the Government's recent national development plan 2018 to 2027.  They include further new or refurbished courthouses in regional cities and county towns where facilities remain substandard, including Roscommon, Galway, Wicklow town, Portlaoise and Tralee, and further provincial locations such as Tuam and An Cloch&aacute;n Liath or Dungloe, with the latter to serve as the Gaeltacht court for the region; regional family law centres; and a nationwide condition survey of all court buildings in the estate which will be undertaken to determine their condition and identify works required to address any issue identified and meet ongoing maintenance requirements.  The precise allocation and timing of additional funding over the entire ten-year period will be determined following further detailed planning and analysis to determine the prioritisation of projects from a timing and budgetary perspective.</p> <p>As the Senator is aware, under the provisions of the Courts Service Act 1998, management of the courts, including the provision of accommodation for court sittings, is the responsibility of the Courts Service which is independent in exercising its functions.  The Courts Service has advised that, on completion of the courts bundle PPP programme of work, five provincial city and county town venues will still be in need of major investment in court facilities.  They are Roscommon, Galway city, Wicklow town, Portlaoise and Tralee.  The Courts Service has confirmed that, collectively, these cities and towns will be the next priority for investment in courthouse facilities outside the capital under the Courts Service provincial capital building programme.  However, the Courts Service has assured the Minister that it is committed to providing improved court facilities in Roscommon town, one of a small number of county towns where a new or refurbished courthouse remains to be provided.</p> <p>The Minister is aware of the shortcomings in the court facilities in Roscommon courthouse.  The Courts Service has confirmed that the capacity of the courtrooms is limited and that facilities for court users are not satisfactory.  The Senator will be aware of the historical significance of Roscommon courthouse.  The Courts Service confirms that the current courthouse which was built in the 1830s comprises two courtrooms, is in poor condition and lacks the facilities expected in a modern courthouse.  The aim of the Courts Service is to refurbish and extend the courthouse to provide three courtrooms, with current plans envisaging one jury courtroom and two non-jury courtrooms, as well as related facilities, including judicial chambers, consultation rooms, custody facilities and facilities for staff, jurors and members of the legal profession.  The refurbished courthouse will also provide improved accessibility.</p> <p>The Courts Service has further informed the Minister that, until recently, the courthouse was occupied jointly by Roscommon County Council and the Courts Service.  In 2017, with a view to facilitating the envisaged refurbishment works, the Courts Service purchased the council's share of the building and now owns the entire courthouse.</p> <p>As I explained, under the provisions of the Courts Service Act 1998, management of the courts, including the provision of accommodation for court sittings, is the responsibility of the Courts Service which is independent in exercising its functions.  As I indicated, the Courts Service has advised that now that the new and refurbished courthouses at seven provincial city and county town venues have almost all been delivered, it will move to concentrate on the five provincial city and county town venues still in need of major investment in court facilities, including Roscommon.  It confirms that they will, collectively, be the next priority for investment in courthouse facilities outside the capital under the Courts Service provincial capital building programme. </p> <p>On behalf of the Minister, I thank the Senator for raising this matter and giving the Minister an opportunity to provide an update on the planned refurbishment of Roscommon courthouse.  The Courts Service has informed the Minister that it will keep the issue of Roscommon courthouse under review.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1415" speakername="Maura Hopkins" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#C00600"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his positive response.  As I stated, the purchase by the Courts Service of the entire Roscommon courthouse building, part of which had previously been used by Roscommon County Council, is a positive development as it indicates a commitment to commence works at the courthouse.  I would like to have a timeframe for completion of the building project.  I will continue to work closely with the Minister on the issue.</p> <p>As an aside, I welcome the students and staff from Kilteevan national school in Roscommon who are accompanied by a number of parents.  I am thrilled that they are visiting the House.  I spent time with some of the students on Monday and their many questions showed that they had a very bright future ahead of them.  Perhaps some of them might sit in this Chamber in the years ahead.  I welcome them to the House. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#C00700"><p>I, too, welcome our visitors.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1261" speakername="Jim Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#C00800"><p>I welcome the students from Kilteevan national school to the Seanad.  I am sure they are proud to see one of their public representatives highlighting the need for better infrastructure for the Courts Service in County Roscommon.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Jim Daly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2328"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2328&amp;amp;pid=JimDaly&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I am sure it is a proud moment for all of them.  I hope they enjoy their visit to the Oireachtas.  I again thank the Senator.  Her duty, as a public representative, is to maintain momentum for the delivery of capital projects and the response I have outlined is positive.  Seven projects have been completed and Roscommon courthouse is among the next five priority projects.  Subject to planning and other statutory obligations being dealt with, I am assured by the Minister's reply that it will progress in a timely manner.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#D00200"><p>I am glad that Tralee courthouse has also been mentioned.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.28" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#D00250">Farmers Indebtedness</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#D00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State for coming to the House.  I have a few specific questions related to agriculture and particularly the relationship between Revenue and his Department.  What is the position on approval by the European Commission of a levy on a lower rate of stamp duty for the purposes of consolidation?  Farmers are keen to know when it will happen.  Will it be applied retrospectively from January?  </p> <p>Will the Minister of State consider making changes to the age limits for farm transfers to young trained farmers to enable those who want to take up farming to purchase from non-relatives at the lower stamp duty rate in order that they will not have to be aged under 35 years.  I am particularly mindful of returning emigrants who wish to purchase land for a farming career.</p> <p>Some of this year's budgetary measures related to agriculture contain sunset clauses which will end on 31 December.  I refer, in particular, to stock relief for young trained farmers.  Is work being done to extend it beyond this year? </p> <p>Low income farmers faces pressures in complying with Revenue requirements as they have to engage accountants and so on.  That is expensive when, more often that not, they record little or no profit.  I acknowledge that newspapers are reporting today that dairy farmers are making increased profits, but that is not the case for many farmers in the west, particularly in County Mayo, from where I come.  Simplicity is one of the attributes of an effective and good tax system.  Can the reporting procedures be made simpler for farmers, particularly those on low incomes?</p> <p>I am concerned about the impact of vulture funds on the farming community, particularly now that more loans will be sold off.  My experience in talking to farmers who find themselves in this position is that they have performing loans but that they need them to be restructured to suit their business or income.  Will the Minister of State do everything he can to force the vulture funds to engage with farmers to work out a restructuring plan with them because the vulture fund-farmer relationship is in danger of having detrimental short, medium and long-term effects on the fabric of communities in rural Ireland?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1356" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#D00400"><p>The script I have been given relates mainly to the final issue raised by the Senator, but I will get to the other points she raised.  </p> <p>While the Minister for Finance and Public Expenditure and Reform has responsibility for taxation matters generally, the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine liaises closely with him on agri-taxation policy.  A public consultation process on agri-taxation was launched recently by the Departments and we consult regularly in that regard with the farm bodies.  The Senator might consider making a submission as part of the consultation process on the earlier issues raised by her.</p> <p>Operationally, the Revenue Commissioners have responsibility for taxation matters.  They have assured me that they understand temporary cash flow difficulties can arise for taxpayers, including farmers, from time to time.  When cash flow related challenges arise or are expected to arise, Revenue encourages early engagement with it as a means to agreeing a way forward in achieving tax compliance.  I am also informed by Revenue that, in its experience, where such early engagement occurs, it is generally possible to arrive at an accommodation that gets the taxpayer successfully beyond the payment pressure point.  The Government has committed to assisting all viable small and medium enterprises operating in Ireland to support economic growth and employment in the economy.</p> <p>Primary responsibility for banking policy lies with the Department of Finance which liaises with the Central Bank and the Financial Services and Pensions Ombudsman on consumer protection in the area of personal banking, the purchase of financial products and financial issues generally.  I am informed by the Department that the sale of a loan does not change the terms and conditions attached to it before it is sold.  Borrowers have the same protections and rights and obligations as they have before the sale.  They include the consumer protection code, the code of conduct on mortgage arrears and the Central Bank (Supervision and Enforcement) Act 2013 (Section 48) (Lending to Small and Medium-Sized Enterprises) Regulations 2015, as amended.  Notwithstanding the fact that borrowers are protected under the existing framework, the Government is supporting the Consumer Protection (Regulation of Credit Servicing Firms) (Amendment) Bill 2018 that was introduced by Deputy Michael McGrath last February.  The Bill which was passed on Second Stage in the D&aacute;il in March will require credit owners to be regulated.  With the approval of the Government, officials from the Department of Finance are engaging with the Office of the Attorney General, the Central Bank and Fianna F&aacute;il to resolve technical issues with the Bill and draft amendments.</p> <p>I urge people who are having difficulty in making repayments to financial institutions to seek professional assistance in finding ways to resolve the issue.  I am aware of the work being done by some of the representative organisations in helping farmers.  I am conscious that the prolonged winter will have put some individual farmers under pressure in respect of cash flow.  In recognition of this, the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine recently met the chief executive officers of the main banks and discussed the current cash flow and liquidity position of the primary sector.  The Minister emphasised to them that they should recognise the temporary and exceptional nature of the current position and that they should be flexible and put in place measures to support their customers.  They indicated that there were no signs of a liquidity issue in the sector as a whole, while acknowledging that there might be pressures in individual cases.  They assured us that they would provide supports such as extended overdraft facilities and term loans for their customers and asked that those in difficulty contact them as soon as possible.  The Minister asked them about their approach to non-performing loans and stressed that any sale of farm assets impacted negatively on the ability to meet ongoing commitments.  The banks that have sold or are selling such loans have informed us that the proportion of farms affected is relatively low and that sales occur mostly in cases in which there has been no meaningful engagement with the banks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#D00500"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his reply.  I appreciate that I asked a number of specific questions that were not indicated in the matter raised by me.  I will seek further answers from the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine.  It is important that there be better congruence between the Departments of Finance and Agriculture, Food and the Marine to ensure farmers who are struggling with all of these issues will be given clear and accurate information and that officials within the Department of Finance and Revenue understand the nature of farming and the flexibility needed in that regard in that farmers may find themselves without an income for a number of months.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Rose Conway-Walsh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2462"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2462&amp;amp;pid=RoseConwayWalsh&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->That is due, in no small part, to delayed payments by the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine.  Such delays can be caused by computer problems, issues with commonage framework plans and so forth.  That congruence can create an easier climate for farmers to be able to meet their obligations but also to be helped where needed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1356" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#E00200"><p>I thank the Senator.  Some of the issues she raised at the outset including stamp duty, stock relief and changes to the limits merit further consideration.  Stock relief has certainly rolled in the past.  The same is true of the capital acquisitions tax relief, the value of which has increased recently.  In 2012 and 2013, a full agritaxation review was conducted for the first time in a generation.  As a result of that review, there has been a more continuous and ongoing collaboration and communication between Revenue, the Department of Finance and the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine.  That must be welcomed and it must continue so that we can fine-tune our agritaxation policy to reflect realities on the ground.  That is something to which we are all committed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.34" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 11.02 a.m. and resumed at 11.30 a.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.35" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#G00100">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#G00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, statements on Palestine, to be taken at 2.20 p.m and to conclude no later than 3.50 p.m., with the contributions of all Senators not to exceed six minutes and the Minister to be given no less than five minutes to reply to the debate; No. 2, statements on bed capacity at the National Rehabilitation Hospital, to be taken at 3.50 p.m and to conclude no later than 4.30 p.m, with the contribution of all Senators not to exceed four minutes and the Minister to be given no less than four minutes to reply to the debate; No. 3, statements on rural development, to be taken at 4.30 p.m. and to conclude no later than 6 p.m., with the contribution of group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes and all other Senators not to exceed five minutes, and the Minister to be given no less than six minutes to reply to the debate; and No. 4, Private Members' business to be taken at 6 p.m., with time allocated not to exceed two hours.  </p> <p>If I may be permitted, I will explain to the House the reason for the delay to 2.20 p.m.  The Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade, Deputy Cannon, was not available and we were not sure if the Data Protection Bill 2017 would conclude last night, so we had to leave time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#G00300"><p>On the Private Members' business, is it No. 66, motion 14?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#G00400"><p>Yes, it is No. 66, motion 14.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#G00500"><p>Thank you for the clarification.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#G00600"><p>Sorry for the Cork accent, a Chathaoirligh.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#G00700"><p>I am learning that.  I call Senator Daly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#G00800"><p>I wish to raise to the issue of housing legislation.  I know that there are statements today but what is important is legislation, which can effect change.  The Government promised legislation on housing but the Bill has not yet been published and has not gone through pre-legislative scrutiny.  The Government made a call to the private sector on its proposals on off-balance sheet initiatives.  Trying to get information on that from anybody working in the housing sector has become impossible.  Could we get clarity on when the legislation on housing will be brought forward?</p> <p>The next issue relates to insurance.  Again, legislation was promised by Government on the insurance industry.  In 2017 there was an 11% increase in premiums and since 2012 there has been a 31% increase in premiums.  There is the ongoing investigation by the European Union into the Irish insurance industry which seems to be a cartel run by the industry.  The establishment of a national claims database was a key recommendation.  We were promised the legislation on it would be enacted by 2017 but the Bill has not been introduced and there is no timeframe.</p> <p>What we have is a lot of activity, which is only masquerading as action.  We all agree the Government needs to bring forward the legislation on housing, a promise on which it has not delivered.  The Government said it would do something on insurance cost, which is a cost for motoring, housing and business.  </p> <p>A group affected by this is Men's Sheds, which has faced massive increases in its insurance costs.  Many of the Men's Sheds will close down.  It will affect about 10,000 people who use Men's Sheds, which are very important for social interaction among people who feel isolated and vulnerable.  Men's Sheds also do much good in their communities in terms of projects and yet are being shut down by our insurance industry.  What I outlined last week should be borne in mind.  Some 10% of the money paid out by the insurance company goes to the claimant and the person injured while 90% goes in costs and outlay to the legal industry.</p> <p>I do not have to point out that when the troika was here that was one of the key reforms it sought in regard to costs of doing business in Ireland and in ensuring people got access to justice and that they were be able to afford justice.  At the moment people simply cannot afford justice and this is having a detrimental effect on the wider economy in terms of people insuring their homes and motor cars and on the Men's Sheds.</p> <p>What I see are lots of promises of legislation on insurance and housing but nothing coming forward.  There is a huge backlog of Bills at the justice committee.  I think at the last count there was a backlog of nearly 100 Bills to go to this committee but there is no chance that many of those will ever see the light of day.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#G00900"><p>It is called new politics.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#G01000"><p>The Senator's party is in charge.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#G01100"><p>There is no majority.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#G01200"><p>We are having statements all day today.  There is nothing stopping anybody taking legislation.  I pointed out to the Leader that in May of last year the Government said it would look at the Corporate Manslaughter Bill but we are still awaiting amendments.  If those amendments are not tabled before the recess, I propose that this House pass that Bill as it is and as proposed by the Law Reform Commission.  If the Government is not willing to table amendments, then we should pass the legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#G01300"><p>The Senator had statements on it last week.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#G01400"><p>With all due respect, statements do not make any difference to anyone's life.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#G01500"><p>Please, Leader, there will be a chance to reply.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#G01600"><p>Unbelievable.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#G01700"><p>I am asking for legislation on corporate manslaughter,-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#G01800"><p>You are prolonging the-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#G01900"><p>-----insurance and housing.  If we could do that before the summer recess, it would be a good week's work.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#G02000"><p>The Senator is unbelievable.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#G02100"><p>Thank you, Senator Daly.  The Leader will have a chance to respond later.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#G02200"><p>I might not bother at all, a Chathaoirligh.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#G02300"><p>On the issue of insurance, it so happens that yesterday I received my renewal notice for my house and car insurance.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#H00100"><p>For your mansion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#H00200"><p>My car insurance has gone down by &euro;20 to &euro;380 fully comprehensive for a 2 l car-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#H00300"><p>That is not a lot.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#H00400"><p>-----and my house insurance has gone down by &euro;200.  I do not know if people are going to the right brokers.</p> <p>There has been much debate in recent weeks with respect to the eighth amendment, and there have been fairly serious debates on both sides.  A lady approached me and asked me a question.  When a public patient in this country is referred to the care of an obstetrician, she does not get a choice as to who she is allocated.  As we have seen, some consultants have entrenched positions on either the "Yes" or the "No" side.  Is a potential patient entitled to be told what the position is-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#H00500"><p>No.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#H00600"><p>-----given that it may have an effect, not necessarily on the treatment because I believe all doctors will act professionally, but on the mindset?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#H00700"><p>What about the secrecy of the ballot?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#H00800"><p>There should be no interruptions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#H00900"><p>It is an important issue.  Any time I have needed a consultant I have had a choice and I have been able to ask people about different consultants.  I once had a consultant allocated to me to whom I would not bring my beagle.  Is this something that needs to be considered in the future in the post-referendum days?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#H01000"><p>I commend all of those who are organising the rare breeds conference in Mulranny this weekend, starting on Friday.  It is a very important conference which I attended last year.  Wonderful work is being done in this country on rare breeds, their development and the importance of that to the agricultural sector.  It impinges on other sectors as well.  I wish the organisers well for the conference in Mulranny on Friday and I look forward to attending at least part of it.</p> <p>I wish to talk about the rainy day fund.  We should not be looking at a rainy day fund when we have a crisis in housing and health.  The recent stability programme update shows why the so-called rainy day fund should be scrapped.  The &euro;500 million to be put aside next year will only be money diverted from services.  It is more akin to a black hole than a rainy day fund.  It is a crisis now for 10,000 homeless people and hundreds of thousands on the waiting list.  There are also hundreds of people on trolleys every day in hospitals.  They do not need reassurance that we are prepared for the future.  They need things to happen now.  It is an insult to them to say that it is better to lock people's money away while so many are waiting for treatment.  I just received a call from a woman who was to have a vital procedure in Galway hospital today.  She was all ready to go but she was told there is no bed.  There has been a reduction in the number of nurses in recent years, including in Mayo.  The money that has been set aside for the rainy day fund should be put into the services that are needed right here and right now.  It should also be used for investment in infrastructure in rural areas.  Last week I spoke about a community between Westport and Louisburgh that did not have any proper quality water.  There should be a reconsideration of the rainy day fund and the investment should be made there.  That makes absolute sense because of the multiplier effect in terms of job creation.  It is vital that such investment is made now in rural areas.  We recently ratified the UN convention on disability.  Substantial funding will be required to ensure the implementation of the convention.  The money should be used for that as well.</p> <p>In reply to my colleague, Deputy Pearse Doherty, the Minister for Finance recently said his intention remains to transfer &euro;1.5 billion from the Ireland Strategic Investment Fund, and to make annual transfers of &euro;500 million per year in each year from 2019 to 2021, as was published last month in the stability programme update.  What guarantees are there that this will not just be a backup fund for bankers and speculators if they behave deplorably again?  It is being said that this is to make our economy more resilient, yet the Government continues to reference the economic crash when justifying its set-up.  There needs to be a rethink about that.  It shows the Government does not have an understanding of the immediate issues that need to be addressed here and now.  If we did not have homeless people and people who are left waiting on trolleys for vital treatment, then we could have a rainy day fund, but not under the current circumstances.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#H01100"><p>On behalf of my group I express sincere sympathies and condolences to the families of the two young women so tragically killed in recent days, Jastine Valdez and Anastasia Kriegel.  I am sure all colleagues will want to join in that.</p> <p>Perhaps the Leader could arrange to have a debate after the referendum on women's health.  I hope, as do all who are canvassing for a "Yes" vote on Friday, that we will wake up on Saturday morning to a more inclusive, caring and compassionate Ireland if the "Yes" vote prevails, which I very much hope it will.  It is so important for women's health that we see a change to our law to enable us finally to reform the law on abortion, to lift the absolute bar that exists in the Constitution, and to allow us to legislate for the many women who need to be able to access abortion care services here in Ireland.  Anyone who has been canvassing across the country, as I have in recent weeks, will be conscious of how many people accept that the law is too restrictive and that after 35 years it is time for a change.  I wish everyone canvassing the very best and hope that the "Yes" vote will prevail on Friday.</p> <p>Could I also ask the Leader for a debate on a related matter, namely, CervicalCheck?  I received much correspondence from many who have been affected by that, both women and men, who have been bereaved because partners or wives have died of cervical cancer and are now deeply concerned about the accuracy of the CervicalCheck system and also concerned about the communication strategies within the HSE, and with consultants and CervicalCheck itself.  People are still looking for reassurance in that regard.  I know everyone will follow the Scally inquiry closely.  On Saturday a group of people gathered at Leinster House to express their concern about the very real issues that still remain on CervicalCheck.  We clearly need greater transparency around the guidelines on communication.  I know we have had debates on it in the House but we might have an ongoing debate on it, as on other important issues of women's health.</p> <p>On a positive note I very much thank all those involved in making Friday evening's event in the Seanad Chamber such a success.  We held an event as part of the V&oacute;t&aacute;il 100 programme to commemorate the centenary of women's suffrage in conjunction with the National Museum.  It went very well.  We had a big crowd in attendance.  It was wonderful to see the great interaction with audience members and to get so much support from Oireachtas staff - ushers, communications staff and all of those involved.  I thank everyone involved.  I also thank the Committee on Procedure and Privileges, CPP, which initially gave permission for the use of the Chamber for this event and for a number of other events run in conjunction with the National Museum.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#H01200"><p>I welcome the extension of the hours during which rural link buses operate.  They are extending until 11 p.m. at night on a couple of days at the weekend on a pilot basis over a considerable part of the country, including five routes in my constituency of Cavan-Monaghan.  It is a good initiative because we have a real problem with rural isolation and people who are not able to access a social life.  We must reconcile the absolute need for road safety with the equal right of people to access social amenities, to shop in town and to have a social drink, if that is what they want to do.  With that in mind I ask the Leader to bring the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Ross, to the House to discuss the real need to incentivise publicans to leave their customers home, and in some instances to collect them.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Joe O'Reilly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1610"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1610&amp;amp;pid=JoeOReilly&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This is happening informally in any case because publicans are responsible people who are concerned about their customers.  The practice could be incentivised, however, and this could be done at low cost or virtually on a cost-neutral basis if one factors in the revenue this would generate.  If, for example, a vehicle registration tax exemption were applied to the vehicles of publicans and measures were introduced to impact positively on their insurance costs, it would incentivise them to bring customers home.  Moreover, it would create a moral imperative and societal requirement for publicans to do this because once a community learned that publicans were being provided with advantages for brining customers home, the practice would become the norm.  It would also save lives and give people access to their local pub.</p><p>There is a serious problem of people being cut off from having a social life and this can cause mental illness, depression and associated difficulties.  Everyone should have the right to have the same quality of life as his or her peers.  Why should someone living near a Luas line in Dublin have a different quality of life and better access to a social life than someone who happens by choice and often not by choice to live in an isolated area and also wants to access a social life?  I appeal to the Leader to take this issue seriously and ask the Minister to come to the House to discuss a range of measures to incentivise publicans to bring home their customers.  This will mean creating an expectation among customers that publicans will provide such a service and publicans will be rewarded for providing such a service.  This practice is common already but it is done informally.  We should formalise, normalise and support it.  Given that it can be done in an almost cost-neutral way, it is a no-brainer. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#J00200"><p>The general data protection regulation, GDPR, comes into force on Friday, 25 May.  Many public information campaigns have highlighted the need for data controllers to prepare for this event and many companies and businesses have been advising employees on how best to prepare to ensure they are compliant with the GDPR.  Unfortunately, a number of school principals have contacted me indicating that they have not heard a dicky bird from the Minister for Education and Skills or his officials on this issue.  Schools have not been given any direction on how best to handle this particular issue.  Surely the Minister should have introduced a circular long before now advising schools on the steps they must take to ensure compliance with the new regulation that will come into force on Friday next.</p> <p>I note, however, that the Minister issued a circular this week advising schools to consult parents on the use of smartphones.  As we know, smartphones can be used to record video and audio and send texts.  A question arises as to who is in charge of these types of information and this raises serious issues about data control and how the use of smartphones should be regulated on school grounds.  I am disappointed to note that it appears from the evidence, with less than two days to go before the GDPR takes effect, that the Minister is very much behind the curve on this issue.  I appeal to the Leader to impress on the Minister the urgent need to issue advice to schools, even at this late stage, on how to become compliant with the GDPR by Friday.  The current position is unfair to schools and boards of management, which should not have been placed in this position. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1439" speakername="Ian Marshall" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#J00300"><p>It would be remiss of me not to acknowledge and address the national farm survey statistics published by Teagasc last night.  I am pleased to note that the average farm income has increased by 32% to slightly more than &euro;31,000.  The dairy sector, in which income has increased by 65%, is the major contributor.  Incomes in tillage have increased by 20% and incomes in sheep farming are up by 8%.  While this is good news, it must be treated with care because average figures can be deceiving.  Someone once told me that the best description of an average is a person whose feet are in the freezer and whose head is in the oven because while his body temperature may be average, he will be dying.</p> <p>Subsidies and support from the European Union account for 56% of farm income, which is a substantial portion of the revenue of farmers.  As all of us know, dairy fortunes are market driven and the increase in dairy incomes is a reaction to a deficit in the market for dairy produce.  If we remove dairy incomes from the equation, the average income for farm businesses stands at approximately &euro;20,000, with a beef unit averaging between &euro;12.500 and &euro;16,000, which is not a large amount of money with which to raise a family.  The current position is not sustainable.  We must be mindful that in isolation and without support mechanisms, agriculture would not be sustainable.  We must also bear in mind that the success of the sector will be key to the success of the country.  It needs investment, including support for research and development, innovation and education as these will be critical if we are to professionalise the industry and make it fit for purpose, fit for the future and sustainable.  It would be dangerous to be complacent based on the Teagasc figures.  We must, therefore, avoid complacency. </p> <p>It would be a major mistake to reduce pressure to provide support for the agriculture industry.  We must maintain this pressure, invest for the future and support the areas to which I referred.  Marketing of the food produced on the island of Ireland will be key to this success.  We should also bear in mind that yesterday's figures were produced against the backdrop of the uncertainty surrounding Brexit.  We must not be misled by one set of encouraging figures for the agrifood industry and farming because serious concerns remain.  We must all put our shoulder to the wheel to ensure agriculture is supported, profitable and sustainable. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#J00400"><p>I welcome an announcement made today on the Garda's use of pedal power.  This morning, I attended a meeting with representatives of Retail Excellence Ireland at which concerns were raised about the visual presence of garda&iacute;.  In Limerick this morning, the Garda announced that 36 garda&iacute; will be trained for deployment on bicycles.  Of these, 12 are in training, while the remainder are to be trained in the coming week.  Senators may laugh and ask why garda&iacute; need training to ride a bike.  It seems they need to learn particular techniques for dealing with crime while cycling.  This approach will create a more visual Garda presence and enable garda&iacute; to reach scenes of crime much faster and approach culprits silently from behind.  This will be important because concerns about a lack of Garda visibility on the streets were raised by traders this morning.  I welcome the announcement that the number of garda&iacute; in Limerick is to increase.  I hope this approach will be replicated nationwide.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#J00500"><p>The new deal for post offices has been endorsed by 80% of postmasters and postmistresses.  Of the 1,189 post offices, 584 voted in favour.  Did any of the postmasters and postmistresses seek legal advice on what they were signing?  Incidentally, the documents they signed are not legally binding.  They were offered a new contract, which involves taking an exit package of &euro;15,000 or &euro;25,000.  Those who choose to remain on the current package face being wound down as their income will be only be guaranteed for two and a half years, after which they will be on their own.  It costs &euro;75 million per annum to run the post office network, yet the Government only committed &euro;30 million this year, of which &euro;15 million is for the mail division and a further &euro;15 million is for the post office network.  It is proposed to shut down 390 post office branches, which means only the great will survive.  The banks have left our towns and villages and members of the public must deal with machines every time they visit a bank branch, even in Ranelagh.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#J00600"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#K00100"><p>They have effectively gone from rural Ireland but we need not worry because the post offices will do the job for them.  What job?  That is my question for this morning.  The post office is going to bolster the immoral failing banks.</p> <p>They tried this in the UK.  The UK wanted to bail out the post offices because the banks were making all the profits.  Why can we not have the Kiwi community banking system developed in Ireland?  It could be given to the post offices as opposed to using the greed of our failing banks through the post offices while taking all the profits.  Why will this new pilot banking system not be allowed through our post offices?  The Government says it will put the banking services into the post offices.  What banking services is it talking about?  It is talking about the already big greedy banks we have in Ireland.  The Kiwi banking community systems operates in New Zealand.  After 19 years the system commands 20% of the actual profits.  Can we imagine such money being put back into locales?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#K00200"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#K00300"><p>I know I have gone on a little.  What has happened to promote the Private Members' motion signed up to by 158 people in the D&aacute;il on the Kiwi banking system?</p> <p>I propose an amendment to the Order of Business.  I want the Minister to come in.  I would like to ask him to explain these questions.  I heard the Minister speaking in the D&aacute;il last evening to Deputy Harty.  He did not explain the answers to any of these questions.  This is serious because it is about privatisation.  It is about the big boys staying as the big boys and the bigger boys, who have failed this country banking-wise, being put in as kind of mentors for our already brilliant post offices.  No new system is being allowed in the door.  We keep on pushing it onto a shelf.  We do not deal with it even as a pilot programme in three or four banks.  Why can the Kiwi community system of banking not be put in as a pilot programme?  I would like the Minister to answer some of those questions so I am proposing an amendment to the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#K00400"><p>The proposal is that the Minister will come in today.  Is that correct?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#K00500"><p>It is for the Minister for Communications, Climate Action and Environment, Deputy Naughten, to come in today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#K00600"><p>I wish to clarify this.  You want implementation in this country of the New Zealand style community banking by using the post office network here.  Is that correct?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#K00700"><p>Yes, I do.  There were 158 votes in the D&aacute;il for it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#K00800"><p>That seems to be clear.  Senator Paul Gavan is next.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#K00900"><p>As it is the last day that we will be speaking before the referendum, I wanted to say a few words on it this morning.  I will start by congratulating the Minister for Health, Deputy Harris.  I thought he did exceptionally well yesterday evening in the debate.  There is no question but that he won the debate last night.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#K01000"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#K01100"><p>I want to expand on that point.  A number of us from all parties have been working with Together for Yes.  It has been an inspiring experience to work with Together for Yes.  We have seen young men and young women in particular coming in for the first time to politics to debate this crucial issue.  Wherever I have worked with them, whether in Limerick, Dublin or Athlone, it has been very impressive.  We had 60 people out in the north side of Limerick on Monday evening for a canvas.  The group incorporated representatives of the Green Party, the Labour Party and the Social Democrats.  There was of course a big Sinn F&eacute;in presence and there were people from no parties at all.  We came together to work towards what is hoped will be a successful result on Friday.</p> <p>I was particularly struck in Athlone on Friday evening.  I am from Westmeath originally.  My first engagement in politics was in 1983 when campaigning against this awful amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#K01200"><p>Go on.  Senator Gavan is from London.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#K01300"><p>It was a difficult time.  Frankly, we were isolated at the time during that campaign.  I came back on Friday to see a huge crowd of people marching through Athlone demanding justice and a "Yes" vote.  The extraordinary passion and integrity of that crowd struck me.  Regardless of the result on Friday we have to recognise the tremendous contribution of the Together for Yes campaign.  I think it is a template we can use, one hopes, to make progressive politics real in many other instances.</p> <p>My last word on this topic is to call for those who are still unsure about which way to vote to look at the key fact that I learned on the committee.  I suspect the Leader will agree with me.  No change is possible in respect of the awful circumstances of fatal foetal abnormality, rape or incest.  A 12 year old child had to travel to England in March this year to get help.  No change is possible at all unless we repeal the eighth amendment.  I appeal to everyone to come out and support that campaign.  I hope we will get the right result on Friday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#K01400"><p>I would like to raise the worrying trend of the creeping up of oil prices and, in particular, the recent spike in the price of a barrel of oil.  The rise has abated but only slightly on account of the increase in production by the Organisation of Petroleum Exporting Countries, OPEC, or the release of crude oil.</p> <p>While it all sounds very international, it has real consequences for our economy.  Stock exchange traders are telling us that in the medium to long-term we are looking at an increase in oil prices.  It serves to remind us how dependent we are on oil for transport and heat, and how, notwithstanding our great ambitions, we are not making great inroads to displacing our dependence on fossil fuels.  Not only has this the ability to impact on business and on how we operate commercially, it impacts on the ordinary household as well.  When a person goes to the petrol pump, she pays for oil or diesel and for home heating oil as well.  This eats into disposable income of people in spite of all the hard-won gains resulting from increased employment.  Many people are also paying over-the-top mortgage interest rates, but that is another debate.  It has to be a critical concern.</p> <p>This has to be a clarion call for us to get something done with regard to alternative fuel sources for oil and heating.  At the moment, even the SEAI grant to upgrade a boiler involves replacing it with an oil-fired central heating boiler.  It is the same in local authority housing, where those responsible are upgrading the heating systems but are putting in oil and nothing else.</p> <p>The battery car seems to be more of a novelty than a reality, notwithstanding that we encourage people to switch.  There are not many hybrids and they will be seen as transitional.  There have been drives to encourage liquefied petroleum gas but the technology has not been rolled out for commercial fleets or heavy goods vehicles.  We are far behind.  It is amazing.</p> <p>The Citizens' Assembly considered climate change.  The headline was to the effect that we should put another carbon tax on farmers.  There is a great deal of ignorance on the issue.  It would be another good reason for the Minister for Communications, Climate Action and Environment, Deputy Naughten, to come to the House, especially since the European Commissioner, Mr. Hogan, told us that our 2020 renewable energy targets will not be rolled over to 2030 and we could face fines of at least &euro;600 million per year.  That is only estimated since the European Court of Justice would decide the fine.  This is critical and urgent.  It has the potential to stymie our economic growth, impact on households and prevent us from achieving our climate change targets.  Will the Minister come to the House for a serious debate on the matter?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#K01500"><p>First, I second the amendment of Senator Marie-Louise O&rsquo;Donnell.  It is very important that the doctor who was in charge of the international inquiry into the death of Savita Halappanavar came to Ireland and said authoritatively and definitively that the eighth amendment was the cause of Savita Halappanavar's death.  That is it, full stop, end of story.  It was the cause.</p> <p>It is extraordinary to me that with two days to go and after 35 years, the "No" side has suddenly decided that it is prepared to tinker with the amendment.  What a laugh.  Does anyone in this country believe them?  I certainly do not.</p> <p>A total of 50% of pregnancies end in early miscarriage.  That is an astonishing statistic and it means that Mother Nature is a great abortionist.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#K01600"><p>Maybe it should be left to Mother Nature.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#K01700"><p>The Minister was excellent on RT&Eacute; television last night.  Well done to the Minister.</p> <p>Earlier this week, I commended the Pope on his gentle and loving words towards a young gay Chilean man.  I have discovered since then that one of the Dutch cardinals has attacked him for heresy.  I am altogether grateful to him for bringing to my attention the fact that one of his other complaints is that a group of cardinals are talking about blessing gay unions.  Good for them.  I said many years ago that considering the fact that they bless domestic animals, including goldfish, tractors and bombs, it would not burst them to bless a couple of fairies while they are at it.  I happen to know that goldfish are not lesbians in any case.  With goldfish, it is impossible to tell.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#K01800"><p>How do I answer that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#K01900"><p>I have to laugh at the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Ross, and this blather about the Judiciary.  The Judiciary is made up of thoroughly decent people.  I do not know of a single instance of judicial corruption.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator David Norris:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1758"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1758&amp;amp;pid=DavidNorris&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is old rubbish from the Minister, Deputy Ross.  It is like saying we should establish a panel of lay people to pick Government Ministers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#L00200"><p>They are called voters.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#L00300"><p>It is a bloody laugh.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1423" speakername="Ray Butler" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#L00400"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#L00500"><p>I thank the Senator for his very entertaining contribution.  I call Senator Paul Coghlan.  Follow that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#L00600"><p>I will do my best.  It will not be easy.  I will certainly never be as entertaining.</p> <p>With a referendum upon us, there is huge concern about the electoral register, the maintenance of which is shambolic.  The environment committee of the Houses found at the last election that the register contained almost 500,000 more people than it should have.  There are huge inaccuracies, as we know, which leaves the system open to abuse and voter fraud.  It leads to a bloated and totally incorrect electoral register.  Equally, there are situations in which people have been taken off the register who are still alive and at their home addresses.  Neighbours who have emigrated, however, remain on the register.  We cannot do much about it in the short term but there is great concern about the electoral register at the moment.</p> <p>On the important subject matter on which we have to vote on Friday, I agree with Senator Bacik that women's health is a very important issue, as is the health of men and children.  It would be very wrong to equate that with the extinguishment of human life by making it lawful.  That would be totally wrong.  It runs counter to everything we ever stood for or believed in.  I hope we will be sensible on Friday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#L00700"><p>I thank the Senator for his plea.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#L00800"><p>I had a Commencement matter on the post office network yesterday, which was attended by the Minister of State at the Department of Communications, Climate Action and Environment.  I support the call, therefore, for the Minister, Deputy Naughten, to come to the House.  Of particular concern is the fact that the social welfare contract represents 60% of post office business yet we have no commitment as to its long-term future with the post office network.</p> <p>Joanne, Natalia, Anastasia and Jastine are four women that we know of who have been murdered in as many months in Ireland.  Ireland was not built for us.  The recent launch by Women's Aid of, "Against the Odds", its femicide watch report for 2017, includes stark and frightening statistics of violence against women and children and uncovers the largely hidden abuse in Irish society.  A YouTube video was sent to me by some young women in Australia.  Many of our young women are abroad.  They are very anxious to have their say but they will not be here.  They have made a documentary called "This is Ireland".  They cover our history from the inception of the State regarding institutions right up to the fatal CervicalCheck scandal of recent times.  It shows that this country was not built for women.  Ours are the voices which will change this nation.  We will cast our vote on Friday to ensure this.  We must support "Together for Yes".  I also ask the Leader to prioritise the recommendations of the Women's Aid publication "Against the Odds".</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#L00900"><p>As the Brexit negotiations carry on in the Republic of Ireland, we want to see as good a deal for our friends and neighbours in the United Kingdom as possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#L01000"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#L01100"><p>However, there was an article in the <i>Express on Sunday</i>last weekend which said there would be a concerted effort at the British-Irish Parliamentary Assembly in Sligo in two weeks' time to go over the head of the Taoiseach on ten reasons Ireland should leave the EU.  This will not happen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#L01200"><p>Absolutely.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#L01300"><p>We are absolutely committed members of the EU.  At the last poll, over 92% expressed satisfaction with the EU.  I say again that we want a good deal for our colleagues in the United Kingdom, but the following is also happening.  The Right Honourable Jacob Rees-Mogg has said that if the Irish Government obliges the UK to choose between the Republic of Ireland and the Union, they will chose the latter.  We are in a very difficult situation but there are two people drowning here.  There is the European Union and the United Kingdom.  If people like Jacob Rees-Mogg continue to make unhelpful statements, they could be the catalyst for the break-up of the United Kingdom.  Not only that, Mr. Rees-Mogg may also come to be seen as the midwife who delivered a united Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#L01400"><p>I apologise for being late.  I have just come from the housing committee.  I acknowledge the great Kerry gardener, Mr. Billy Alexander, who was announced today as one of the major prize winners at the Chelsea Flower Show.  It is a remarkable success story.  People may know him from his famous wild Atlantic garden at Kells Bay.  Anyone who has not been should go.  It is an amazing story which is being covered in the media.  Conscious of that, I express the hope that many of us will make the effort to support the Bloom festival, which starts next week.  It is the premier show championing Irish horticulture.  It deals with food, innovation, organics, nursery stock and production and it is a very important showcase for Irish horticulture.  Hopefully, we will revisit that on next week's Order of Business.  The nursery stock industry is a vibrant one with enormous potential for growth and job creation and I congratulate Mr. Billy Alexander on his success at Chelsea.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#L01500"><p>I thank the 16 Members who contributed on the Order of Business.  I note regarding the amendment proposed by Senator Marie-Louise O'Donnell that the Minister is not available today but he will be here on Wednesday when he is prepared to make time available after he deals with his Bill for statements on the matter the Senator raises.  I will come back to her comments later.</p> <p>Senator Mark Daly raised the issue of housing.  The Department is working on the approved housing Bill and residential tenancies Bill.  It is intended that the legislation will be published this term with a view to enactment.  To be fair, it is important to acknowledge that the Government has not been stalling this in any way.</p> <p>Senator Daly also referred to the issue of corporate manslaughter.  Last week, the Minister came to the House at Senator Daly's request.  I refer Minister Daly - Senator Daly, I mean, albeit perhaps a future Minister - to the Minister's reply.  When I called the Senator "Minister", there was a chilling effect.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#L01550"><p>I will not be that bad.  Do not worry.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#L01575"><p>I will not read the Minister's reply to the House but Senator Daly must be fair here.  We have never, on this side of the House, blocked a Bill coming in.  The Senator made a request to us and the Bill passed on Second Stage.  The Minister made a very clear point to the Senator last week and he needs to be fair about it.  It is the Minister's understanding that it is not expected that such Bills will not be accepted without due consideration.  The Senator should also read what the Minister said about the aspects of the Bill which require further consideration and the fact that the legislation sponsored by the Senator is almost identical to the Bill published by the Law Reform Commission.  The Minister repeated in his reply to the Senator the offer of further engagements with officials and indicated that if Senators considered that it would be helpful, the Department was open to other suggestions they might have.  As such, the Minister has an open door for the Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#L01600"><p>I know.  We are only at it 14 years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#L01700"><p>To come in and pretend otherwise is unfair.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#L01800"><p>All we want is the amendments which were promised last year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#L01900"><p>To listen to the Senator this morning, one would swear there was no engagement or willingness to get involved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M00100"><p>There are no amendments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M00200"><p>The Leader should not open the gully trap.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M00300"><p>The gully trap needs to be plugged as well or the water will keep leaking.</p> <p>The Department is working on the insurance (amendment) Bill to implement the recommendations of the Review of the Framework for Motor Insurance Compensation in Ireland report and it will be published soon.  As the Senator knows quite well, the Minister, Deputy Eoghan Murphy, when he was Minister of State at the Department of Finance, set up a working group, with which the Minister of State, Deputy D'Arcy, is engaging.  Senator Craughwell, in his contribution, referenced his own story.  If one were to listen to Senator Mark Daly this morning, one would never know there was a 14% decline last year in the cost of car insurance and that, since 2016, there has been a 20% decline.  A point that Senator Mark Daly did not reference this morning was that between 2003 and 2016 there was a 70% increase, the most of which was in the Senator's party's time in government.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M00400"><p>There is no legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M00500"><p>I am just saying-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M00600"><p>The Government promised legislation.  I asked where was the legislation the Government promised.  The Government has not brought in the legislation.  A minuscule drop in some areas does not make any difference to those concerned, including the Men's Sheds and the businesses that are beholden to pay enormous costs-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M00700"><p>I cannot allow Senators to come back in.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M00800"><p>-----because of inaction by the Government.  That is all I pointed out.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M00900"><p>The Leader to respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M01000"><p>I fully understand the protestation of Senator Mark Daly because I would be embarrassed at seeing those costs under the reign of Fianna F&aacute;il.  The Senator is correct though.  We should not put up a barrier and the insurance companies must have a social responsibility to organisations, such as the Men's Sheds or community associations.  I agree completely with the Senator on that because those organisations are providing a significant service to the community and they are an inspiration.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M01100"><p>The insurance companies have only an obligation to their shareholders under the Companies Acts.  The Government has a social obligation.  That is who has a social obligation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M01200"><p>If the Leader and Senator Mark Daly both continue to interact, I will suspend the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M01300"><p>As the-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M01400"><p>Does Senator Mark Daly want the House suspended?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M01500"><p>All right, we do not want the House suspended.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M01600"><p>It is not allowed.  Everybody gets a chance and sometimes the Leader might do best not to antagonise the questioner.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M01700"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M01800"><p>We can continue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M01900"><p>The working group has been set up.  Where I again agree with my learned colleague is that the cost of motor insurance is unacceptably high.  What we must have, though, which Senator Mark Daly has not said-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M02000"><p>Is legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M02100"><p>It is not just legislation.  You come with a one dimensional view to life and you are always right.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M02200"><p>Through the Chair.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M02300"><p>Here we are in the House that legislates.  I wonder what I am supposed to be doing.  Where is the legislation that the Government promised?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M02400"><p>This is the reply to the Order of Business, not Senator Mark Daly's hour.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M02500"><p>Senator Buttimer will be a contrary ol' man.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M02600"><p>The Leader is anxious to conclude.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M02700"><p>We have distinguished visitors in the Gallery and I welcome them.  We must look at what are the costs associated with why the premiums are so high, whether it is the compensation system and what are the other factors around the cost of insurance being so high, and that is what the Minister of State, Deputy D'Arcy, is committed to and what Government has started.  Reductions of 14% and 20% are a good start.  I accept we have, to borrow Fianna F&aacute;il's famous phrase, &quot;a lot more to do&quot;.</p><p>Senators Craughwell, Bacik, Gavan, Norris, Devine and Coghlan all made reference to the eighth amendment and the vote that will take place on Friday.  I will not - the Cathaoirleach will be glad - engage in a party political reply.  It is in the hands of the people to make a decision on Friday.</p><p>Like many Members of the House, I was privileged to be a member of the Joint Committee on the Eighth Amendment of the Constitution.  I chaired the Joint Committee on Health and Children which dealt with the protection of life during pregnancy legislation.  I respect that within this Chamber there are differing viewpoints, as there are in Irish society.</p><p>This referendum is an important one.  Senator Gavan is 100% correct.  The only way we can change the present system is by voting &quot;Yes&quot; on Friday.  If we vote &quot;No&quot; on Friday, the <i>status quo</i>remains.  It is completely disingenuous of one side of the argument to say that we can change and deal with the so-called &quot;hard cases&quot;.  The hard cases are about the lives of those who have been affected - women, their husbands or partners-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M02800"><p>And children.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M02900"><p>-----and children.  Without argument, I accept that.  However, there is no way that we can change the present constitutional arrangement unless the people vote &quot;Yes&quot; on Friday <i>quod erat demonstrandum</i>.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M03000"><p>Well said.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M03100"><p>I respect, as I stated at the beginning of this debate, whatever way the people will vote but I hope that the people will go out and vote and that they will vote in a compassionate and genuine way.  I will not give a lecture to anybody today, but let us be fair.  There is only one way we can change and deal with life in general, and that is by voting "Yes" on Friday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M03200"><p>I might interrupt the Leader briefly to welcome a delegation.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.148" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M03300">Visit of Croatian Delegation</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M03400"><p>I am sure that Members of the House will wish to join with me in welcoming a delegation from Croatia led by Mr. Zvonko Milas, State Secretary of the Central Office for Croats Abroad, together with the Croatian ambassador, His Excellency Mr. Ivan Ma&scaron;ina.</p> <p>On my own behalf and on behalf of all my colleagues in Seanad &Eacute;ireann, I extend a very warm welcome to you and good wishes for a very successful visit to Ireland.  Enjoy our sunshine.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M03500"><p>As Leader of the House, I join with the Cathaoirleach in welcoming our distinguished guests.  Mr. Milas and the ambassador, H.E. Mr. Ivan Ma&scaron;ina, are very welcome.  Thank you for being here today.  It is important that we continue to forge good relations.  You are most welcome.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.151" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M03600">Order of Business (Resumed)</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M03700"><p>First, I join with the Senator Conway-Walsh in hoping that the conference in Mulranny on rare breeds will be a success.  The Senator is correct, and as Senator Marshall also said, the agricultural community is very important to our country.</p> <p>Senator Conway-Walsh raised the issue of the rainy day fund.  Sometimes - I know the Cathaoirleach will lecture me - the voodoo economics of Sinn F&eacute;in beggars belief.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M03800"><p>Senator Buttimer is antagonistic today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M03900"><p>No, I am not but it really does.  Let us be fair.  The National Pension Reserve Fund, which was the rainy day fund, is nearly gone because of the collapse in our banking system.  The Government is committed to getting, and has got, money back from the banks.  We are creating a new fund to maintain progress in terms of the living standards and the needs of our people.  If Senator Conway-Walsh wants to go back to the days of boom and bloom, she must look at what happened.  It became not boom and bloom, but bust.  That is the reality.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M04000"><p>It is really not that.  The Leader knows what I am talking about - a Keynesian approach.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M04100"><p>I think both Senators know.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M04200"><p>One does not even have to say it here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M04300"><p>The Leader knows that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M04400"><p>What the Minister is proposing is that we take &euro;0.5 billion per annum and build it up to &euro;8 billion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M04500"><p>Why will the Government not spend it on water?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M04600"><p>Sinn F&eacute;in is the party that opposed Irish Water.  It would not pay for water at one level.  One will not have investment.  Senator Conway-Walsh cannot talk out of both sides of her mouth.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.162" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M04800"><p>Senator Conway-Walsh was against Irish Water.  She was against paying for water.  Who will pay for the investment in water?  Will it be the people?  Come on, be fair.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M04900"><p>The &euro;0.5 billion the Government will put into the rainy day fund.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M05000"><p>As I have stated previously in interactions between the Leader and Members of the Seanad, I allowed everybody who wanted to contribute to do so for two minutes or three minutes.  I have been flathi&uacute;il with the time allocated.  Please allow the Leader reply.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M05100"><p>Our tax revenue is high.  There are more people back at work.  By the end of this year, there will be more at work than ever before in the history of the State but we must plan for the future.  We also have, which the Sinn F&eacute;in Party has not acknowledged, a deficit that we cannot allow to grow.  The importance of the rainy day fund is that we plan for our future so that we can invest for our people.  I would be happy to have the Minister come to the House.</p> <p>I will not repeat what I said on Irish Water.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M05200"><p>It sounds like Senator Buttimer is.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M05300"><p>We all want to have a water network system that brings water to people that they can use and drink.  The model of delivery costs money and Sinn F&eacute;in has not proposed how we will pay for it other than that we will not pay for it all.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M05400"><p>Tell him to grow up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#M05500"><p>Senator Bacik raised the issue of cervical cancer and the importance of the need for transparency, and I agree with her.  That is why the Scally inquiry was set up and we will get to the truth and get the full facts in regard to the events that took place.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The overriding concern of the Government is that we establish the full facts, hold people to account and put in place a system whereby there will be greater transparency and support offered to the families of the women involved.  I fully agree with Senator Bacik.  We need to get the full answers.<br/><br/>Senator Joe O'Reilly raised the extension of local link and welcomed the pilot scheme.  It is an important scheme and lifeline for rural Ireland.  I am sure the incentivisation of publicans will be fraught with contention, but the important point is that a pilot scheme is being established to offer a lifeline to people in rural Ireland.  The Senator is correct.  We must ensure that people in Bailieborough, Reenascreena or Belmullet have the same type of connectivity as those living on a Luas line.  I fully subscribe to that point.<br/><br/>Senator Gallagher raised the issue of the GDPR and schools.  I draw the attention of the Senator to <i>www.dataprotectionschools.ie</i>which is a portal for schools and has a specific section on data protection.  I draw his attention to circular 0829/2018 which has a specific reference to GDPR.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#N00200"><p>The Leader does not need to draw my attention to that.  The Leader needs to draw the attention of school principals.  I am only-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.173" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#N00300"><p>I do not know whether the Senator wants to hear good news or bad news.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.174" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#N00400"><p>I want the facts.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#N00500"><p>They are the facts.  Go and check them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#N00600"><p>Is the Leader telling me that the school principals who phoned me are deluding themselves?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.177" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#N00700"><p>I ask the Senator to do me the courtesy of checking <i>www.dataprotectionschools.ie</i>.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#N00800"><p>Does the Leader mind if I get school principals to contact him?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.179" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#N00900"><p>By all means.  I will refer them to the Minister, Deputy Humphreys, or Senator Reilly and we can give them the information.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#N01000"><p>If someone can give them a proper answer I do not care who the Senator refers them to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.181" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#N01100"><p>The Senator can check the specific section on his phone.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.182" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#N01200"><p>That is not what they were told.  They received no correspondence whatsoever.  I am only telling the Senator what I-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.183" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#N01300"><p>The important point which should not be lost in our back-and-forth exchange is that there is a need for compliance and information.  There were workshops and Catholic schools' principals had a meeting recently.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.184" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#N01400"><p>They had, but the Department did not.  That is my point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.185" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#N01500"><p>Whatever is going on today must be the result of a bit of sunshine.  I include the Leader in this.  Answer the questions raised.  If you are not happy do not encourage-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.186" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#N01600"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.187" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#N01700"><p>Be a bit more gentle.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#N01800"><p>I will be a bit more gentle.  The Cathaoirleach is right.  It is important that the fake news being propagated is not disseminated across the county.  That was called other things before.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.189" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#N01900"><p>Senator Gallagher and others raised the matters in good faith.  If the Leader does not agree with them, he should say so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.190" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#N02000"><p>I am responding in good faith.  I am giving them the correct information.  I cannot-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.191" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#N02100"><p>I am only passing on what schools have contacted me about.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.192" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#N02200"><p>You have made your point and the Leader has made his, so we can move on.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.193" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#N02300"><p>Refer them to <i>www.dataprotectionschools.ie</i>and circular 0829/2018.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.194" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#N02400"><p>Perhaps it would have been an idea for the Department to refer to that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.195" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#N02500"><p>I join with Senator Marshall in welcoming the rise in farm incomes.  The point he made was very valid in terms of the importance of agriculture to our country, North and South.  We need to continue to ensure there is growth in our farming communities and that we put in place supports for the Brexit negotiations and, as Senator Mulherin mentioned, the rising costs of diesel and oil.  Agricultural communities are subject to volatility given the weather and so on.  The Minister, Deputy Creed, will come to the House in a couple of weeks' time.</p> <p>Senator Byrne referred to a meeting today with Retail Excellence Ireland.  She highlighted the lack of a Garda presence and welcomed the announcement in respect of Limerick today that there will be 36 garda&iacute; trained in pedal power to tackle crime.  She called for that to be replicated across the country.  I fully agree with her.  It is an important dimension to our Garda force that we have a division dedicated to crime as well as cycling and being available.  I commend that.</p> <p>I fully agree with Senator Marie-Louise O'Donnell regarding post offices.  She has been a champion of them in the House.  The Minister, Deputy Naughten, has been in the House and will be back next Wednesday.  Senators O'Donnell and Devine referred to social protection.  It would be beneficial to renew the contract automatically.  I am open to correction, but I have been told that EU rules preclude that.  As a people we all need to use our post offices.  I agree with Senator O'Donnell that the banks have let rural and urban Ireland down.  In certain parts of this city or Cork city, there are no counters in banks and everything is done by machine.  That is unacceptable.  We will have a debate with the Minister, Deputy Naughten, next Wednesday.</p> <p>Senator Mulherin raised the issue of oil prices and OPEC.  She commented on our dependency on oil.  We need to overcome that and work to become less dependent on oil.  I would be happy to have that debate with the Minister, Deputy Naughten, in the coming weeks.</p> <p>Senator Norris raised, along with the referendum, the issue of the Dutch cardinals.  He has covered that well.  I could not copy the goldfish remark.  It is important to recognise that there are diverse views.</p> <p>Senator Devine referenced the appalling four deaths.  We all condemn the murders of women and we deplore the killing and treatment of women.  The Houses of the Oireachtas passed domestic violence legislation, which we will all welcomed.  It brings us a step closer to the Istanbul Convention.  I hope this will be a country for all and that no woman feels that the country is not for her.  That would be wrong and we must all work to ensure that our country is for all of us.  I take her point in terms of what has taken place.  It is important we continue to work to make our society a more gentle and caring one where we are all treated as equal.</p> <p>I commend Senator Feighan for his work on Brexit.  His point is that we will not be leaving the European Union is one we must reiterate.  We must stand strong as being a proud part of the European Union and defend the interests of our country, North and South, in the forthcoming Brexit negotiations.</p> <p>I join with Senator Boyhan in commending and congratulating Billy Alexander on his success.  I thank him for pointing to his pre-eminence.  As a champion of the horticulture society, he is correct to highlight the importance of Bloom as a showcase for our country.  I will be happy to have a debate.  The Minister of State, Deputy Doyle, recently discussed horticulture in the House.  I commend the Senator for his work as an advocate of the horticulture sector.  It is playing a very important role in economic development.</p> <p>I wish to advise Senator Marie-Louise O'Donnell that the Minister, Deputy Naughten, will come to the house on next Wednesday, if that is agreeable to her.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.196" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#N02600"><p>Senator Marie-Louise O'Donnell has moved an amendment to the Order of Business, "That the debate with the Minister for Communications, Climate Action and Environment on the question of piloting New Zealand style community banking in Ireland through the post network", be taken today.  Is the amendment being pressed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#N02700"><p>No.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.198" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#N02800"><p>The amendment is withdrawn by leave of the House.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.199" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#N02900"><p>We will have the debate next Wednesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.200" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#N03000"><p>I thank the Leader.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.201" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.202" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#N03200"><p>I understand we will suspend until 2.20 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.203" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#N03300"><p>The Minister of State, Deputy Ciar&aacute;n Cannon, is not available until 2.20 p.m. because of the contingency around the debate on data protection yesterday.  I gave a commitment that the Bill would not be guillotined but it finished quicker than we thought.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.204" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#N03400"><p>The Leader has proposed that we suspend until 2.20 p.m.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.205" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 12.40 p.m. and resumed at 2.20 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.206" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#Y00100">Situation in Palestine: Statements</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.207" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1241" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Cannon" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#Y00200"><p>I thank the Seanad for inviting me to make a statement on Palestine on behalf of the Government.  Last week, we all watched the news reports from Gaza with a sense of shock and despair.  Who could fail to be moved by images of despairing families grieving for the loss of loved ones and of individuals dealing with horrific and life-changing injuries?  Over the course of six weeks of protests in Gaza, beginning on 30 March, there have been reports of protestors being targeted by live fire with tragic consequences.  On 14 May, the highest casualty toll in the Gaza Strip in a single day since 2014 was recorded.  The UN reports that a total of 102 Palestinians, including 12 children, have been killed in the course of the demonstrations since 30 March.  These 102 lives were lost primarily as a result of live fire from the Israeli Defence Forces guarding the border fence between Israel and Gaza.  The UN reports also that the cumulative number of injured persons has exceeded 12,600, of whom 55% have been hospitalised.</p><p>Particularly worrying has been the high percentage of those killed and injured by live ammunition, which points to the excessive use of force and the use of live ammunition as a form of crowd control.  The T&aacute;naiste made three public statements on these incidents on 31 March, 9 April and 14 May calling on all sides to show restraint and, in particular, calling on Israeli forces to temper their use of force.  Last week, the Taoiseach supported the call of the Secretary General of the UN for an independent international investigation into these events.</p><p>At this point, I acknowledge that while the vast majority of the demonstrators over the course of the six weeks of protest were peaceful, there were elements among them who sought to cause trouble.  Violence on the part of some protestors is regrettable and the organisers and those in <i>de facto</i>control of Gaza have a clear responsibility to prevent such actions.  We recognise that not all those participating in the protest were non-violent.  Stones were thrown, Molotov cocktails were hurled and some protestors attempted to breach the border fence when there had been explicit warnings of the consequences of doing so.</p><p>There have also been reports that many of those shot were members of Hamas.  It is important to reiterate that we recognise Israel's right to protect itself and protect its borders from attack.  While acknowledging that right to defend itself and to protect its people, we must also note its obligation to ensure the response to any threat is proportionate.  Responding to unarmed protestors with live fire is far from proportionate.  Membership of a terrorist group is not in itself a valid reason to use deadly force where the person targeted is unarmed.</p><p>I recognise also that it would have been better if children were not allowed to participate in the protest and were kept away from the border fence.  However, what struck me as particularly tragic and indicative of the loss of hope in Gaza was the fact that many of the children interviewed by UN agencies as to why they put themselves in harm's way said they were there out of curiosity and boredom.  These protests were something to see and do for children with very little stimulation or opportunity to engage in creative activities.  Palestine's rapidly growing young population badly needs to see the development of a future democratic, free and tolerant state.  More must be done to empower those young children and provide them with greater opportunities for employment and entrepreneurship as well as with some degree of hope.  More must also be done to offer the people of Gaza alternative political models, especially when it comes to young people who are so isolated from the outside world and vulnerable to the influence of Hamas.</p><p>I must refer to the very troubling reports of health professionals and aid workers being shot during the protests.  These professionals were among the first responders at the scene to assist the injured and dying.  They were clearly identifiable as health workers.  Nevertheless, the WHO has documented that since the start of the protests on 30 March, there have been numerous attacks on health facilities and personnel.  One health worker has been killed and 229 have been injured while providing treatment to injured people during the mass demonstrations.</p><p>It is also reported that 32 ambulances were damaged.  On 15 May, a paramedic was shot and died of a chest injury.  The WHO reports that other paramedics were unable to reach him because of heavy firing.  This is unacceptable.  Hospitals in Gaza are barely able to cope with the serious injuries which have flooded in.  In the meantime, the health system must continue to function to serve the needs of the Gazan population.  It must continue to provide maternal and child services, for example, and to treat non-communicable diseases.  I take this opportunity to pay tribute to the professionalism, dedication and, indeed, courage of those working in the health sector in Gaza.</p><p>It is imperative to establish the facts of what happened in Gaza last week and in the six weeks leading up to it.  The Taoiseach and the T&aacute;naiste have publicly supported the call of the UN Secretary General for an independent investigation.  Last Friday, the Human Rights Council of the UN held a special session on the deteriorating human rights situation in the occupied Palestinian territories, including east Jerusalem.  At this special session, a resolution was passed, which Ireland supported, to set up an independent international commission of inquiry to investigate all violations of international humanitarian law and international human rights law in the context of recent protests.  The resolution was backed by 29 members of the Human Rights Council, with 14 abstaining and only two voting against it.  While Ireland is not currently a member of the Human Rights Council, we made it clear in our national statement at the special session that force must only be used in cases of real and immediate threat to life and only as a last resort when all other methods have failed.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Ciar&aacute;n Cannon:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2253"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2253&amp;amp;pid=CiaranCannon&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The use of force should also be proportionate to the threat posed.  We strongly supported the call of the UN Secretary General and others for an independent and transparent investigation into these events.  I take this opportunity to call on Israel to co-operate with the commission of inquiry to allow it to examine the circumstances fully, including threats and provocations, that led to the loss of so many lives.</p><p>Following the tragic events of last week, the T&aacute;naiste summoned the Israeli ambassador to express the Government&rsquo;s serious concerns and dismay at what had taken place and at the actions of the Israeli Defence Forces.  In this way we could ensure that our concerns were conveyed directly to the Israeli Government.  Ireland has been providing direct support to the Palestinian people for more than two decades, reflecting a long-standing commitment to the peaceful development of a viable, sovereign Palestinian state.  Through the Irish Aid programme, we provide in excess of &euro;10 million annually in development and humanitarian assistance to meet the needs of the most vulnerable Palestinian men, women and children.  A key element of this programme is directed towards strengthening the ability of the Palestinian Authority to meet those needs.  Enabling Palestinians to build institutions and provide essential public services is critical to laying the foundations for a future Palestinian state.  Another important part of our aid is the support we provide to UNRWA, amounting to &euro;4.25 million so far this year, to support the provision of services and assistance to 5 million registered Palestinian refugees, including in Gaza.  This is an increase of &euro;250,000 on the 2017 allocation.</p><p>I have focused today on the situation in Gaza, which is at the forefront of our minds, but Senators should rest assured that the Government remains engaged on all of the issues related to this conflict, including Israeli security concerns, of course, but also the impact that the occupation has on the Palestinian people, including speaking out on settlement construction and on the displacement of Palestinian communities.  The T&aacute;naiste continues to engage with both sides, with our EU partners, and with other players such as the US, to ensure that these issues remain high on the international agenda, and to bring Ireland's views on these issues to bear wherever and whenever the way forward is being discussed.  We will continue to use every opportunity to engage with both sides and to do what we can to contribute to the resolution of this 70 year old conflict, a resolution that will see the establishment of two states, Israel and Palestine, living side by side within secure borders.  This is the only way to ensure that events like those of last week are not repeated.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.209" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#Z00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for coming to the House and outlining the issues and the Government's proposals and actions in response to what has happened in Palestine and Gaza recently.  It is all too familiar given the previous attacks on Gaza by the Israelis, the escalating casualty count in Gaza and the ongoing humanitarian crisis that has been there since 2007 and well before that.</p> <p>As we mark the anniversary of the Nakba, the catastrophe, of the Palestinian people and look at the consequences for them of the establishment of the state of Israel, we also have to look at the solutions in terms of engagement.  We know that previously the US Government has acted as a negotiator, with the Oslo Accords being one of those occasions.  Many have said it was a missed opportunity, but the Palestinians felt they were getting too little in the Oslo Accords.  In the West Bank alone, the Israelis were getting 80% of the water resources with 20% for the Palestinian community, and water is a vital issue.</p> <p>Given the deaths and shootings in Gaza, the phrase "disproportionate use of force" is an understatement.  It sounded a bit like some of the statements put out by the British after Bloody Sunday.  Yes, there was the throwing of stones, and yes, there were Molotov cocktails, but there was the use of live fire in response.  The suggestion that some were using guns is always put out by the opposition.</p> <p>It was Brian Lenihan senior who put forward our party's policy in 1980 on the issue of a two-state solution, which has been adopted by the EU and others since.  At the time, Brian Lenihan said the Palestinian people had a right to self-determination to establish an independent state of Palestine.  We believe this is possible, but it is only possible if we put all the elements of a peace process together.  According to experts on peace negotiations, a number of elements are vital.  One is a hurting stalemate, which is that both parties are hurting so much, and can inflict no more pain on each other, and so are willing to negotiate for peace.  This is obviously not the situation that is prevailing currently in Israel and Palestine, although one side is hurting enormously, having had huge punishment befall them with innocent people being killed, as we saw last week.  Then we need an honest broker.  There has not been an honest broker in the situation and there is not one now.  We also need to ensure there are no third parties acting against the peace process.  As we know, Iran is acting against Israel, using proxies in the Middle East against Israel, and using some elements of the Palestinian community for its own ends.  We also need leadership, and the leadership is not there or is unwilling to compromise from its position.  The Israeli's point of view is they have what they want and they do not need to compromise on peace.</p> <p>I have been to the West Bank and near the Gaza Strip.  For such a small place it sure holds a lot of pain and suffering for many of its inhabitants, especially the young people living in Gaza and the West Bank.  The Minister of State asked why young people went to the fence to see what was going on.  It was because they have nothing else to do.  People who have nothing else to do get radicalised, and we have seen this across Europe.  We have seen it in Paris and Brussels and we have seen it in Northern Ireland.  That is a crucial issue.  The list of grievances the Palestinian community has is too numerous to mention in the time we have allocated.  Take the issues of child detention, water, housing or settlements.  When Ronald Reagan was President there were 40,000 illegal settlements in the West Bank.  Today there are more than half a million.  As we know, this is a problem not just for future generations but for centuries to come.</p> <p>We acknowledge that the move by the US Government to put its embassy in Jerusalem has not assisted the peace process in any way, shape or form and has removed the US as an independent broker in the situation.  We have to ask ourselves what is the solution.  We must also acknowledge the fact the Muslim world has a role to play and it does not seem to be doing anything in a substantive way any more to assist the Palestinian communities that are scattered around Israel, the West Bank, Jordan, previously in Syria, Lebanon and other places.</p> <p>Where we are now does not seem like there is much hope, but there has to be solution because what we have now is not sustainable.  Israel needs to recognise it does need to be generous in what it should do for the Palestinians who are on its doorstep, because people who do not have hope have nothing to lose.  The Israelis have to make sure they provide a pathway for the peaceful and prosperous future that the Palestinian people deserve to have in their own homeland, as the Israeli people deserve to live in peace.  This is why we continue to support the two-state solution we advocated in 1985 through the former Minister for Foreign Affairs, Brian Lenihan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.210" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1399" speakername="Neale Richmond" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#Z00300"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House once again and I appreciate all the great work he, his officials, the T&aacute;naiste and the Minister of State, Deputy McEntee, are doing in the Department at a very difficult time.  I speak in place of our regular foreign affairs spokesperson, Senator Joe O'Reilly, who unfortunately cannot be here due to parliamentary business.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Neale Richmond:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2472"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2472&amp;amp;pid=NealeRichmond&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Like everyone in this Chamber - I think it is a universal opinion - I was absolutely appalled by the atrocities carried out last week.  While it is right to acknowledge that Hamas was complicit in an element of it, the over-reaction by the Israeli Government was truly shocking.  The most shocking thing is that last week was not the first time this has happened.  It is absolutely right that the use of live ammunition be condemned.  The manner in which we react to it as a country, as a Government and as a people will allow others to judge how we are contributing to this situation.</p><p>To be frank, Irish people and particularly politicians are obsessed with the Middle East.  I do not mean that in any way negatively.  We regularly have statements on the Middle East.  Issues relating to the Middle East are regularly raised on the Order of Business.  When I was a member of a local authority, we considered motions relating to the ongoing conflict in the Middle East every couple of months.  We are right to be obsessed with this part of the world, which I visited last year, because we have invested socially, culturally, economically and emotionally in everything that is going on there.  As the Minister of State said, Irish Aid provides &euro;10 million to the Palestinian people every year.  We have embassies in Tel Aviv and Ramallah.  Scores of workers from Ireland are working in non-governmental agencies across Gaza.  As Senator Lawless might confirm, there is a surprisingly large Irish diaspora living in Israel.  A couple of drinks in Molly Bloom's Irish pub in Tel Aviv made that quite clear to me not so long ago.  We have invested in this part of the world.  I strongly believe that if we are going to have a positive influence on it, we need to stay invested in it.  This means we need to keep our embassies in Tel Aviv and Ramallah open and we need to keep the Israeli ambassador in Dublin.  Any efforts we make in terms of sanctions or other actions should be made in a co-ordinated way through the EU, in line with other agreements.  Isolated actions by the South African and Turkish Governments are great for a couple of days of news headlines, but they do not really have an impact.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.212" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#AA00200"><p>They do.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.213" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1399" speakername="Neale Richmond" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#AA00300"><p>I respectfully disagree.  I join the Minister of State and the T&aacute;naiste in calling for a truly independent investigation, led by the UN, into last week's atrocities and into the ongoing conflict in the region.  As Senator Mark Daly said, there are many factors at play here.  The current American Administration is not helping the situation.  The same thing can be said of the Iranian Administration and of the Egyptian Government's policy in respect of the border in southern Gaza.  All of these things are contributing to the tinderbox that exists.  If we are truly serious about wanting peace and using our experience and knowledge of peace and reconciliation to the benefit of ordinary people, rather than the political leaders in Likud, Hamas or Fatah, we strongly need to stay engaged.  When I speak about "ordinary people", I am referring to Israeli and Palestinian people - Jews, Christians, Muslims and everyone else - regardless of ethnicity or religion.  We must try to be a benevolent force in this region.  The approach that has been taken by this country has worked in certain areas where it has had a positive impact.  We need to keep doing that.  If we disengage, protest and throw people out, we will turn our back on and absolve our responsibility to a part of the world we have invested in over many years.  I appreciate the opportunity to express my thoughts on this subject.  I appreciate that differing views will be expressed in this Chamber, as they always are.  It is right that such views generate an emotional response from all sides.  We need to clear through the fog.  We need to think about the ordinary people on the ground in Palestine and Israel, some of whom are Irish.  We need to chart a course forward and try to play our part.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.214" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1408" speakername="Frances Black" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#AA00400"><p>I have to say I am disappointed with some of the comments made by the Minister of State in his speech.  I was in Gaza last week.  I have also been to the West Bank.  I do not think the word &quot;horrendous&quot; is sufficient to describe the traumatic nature of my experience.  The Minister of State said that &quot;Violence on the part of some protestors is regrettable and the organisers and those in <i>de facto</i>control of Gaza have a clear responsibility to prevent such actions.&quot;  He referred to &quot;reports that many of those shot were members of Hamas&quot; even though there is absolutely no proof of that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.215" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#AA00500"><p>So what if they were?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.216" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1408" speakername="Frances Black" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#AA00600"><p>The Minister of State suggested that many children "were there out of curiosity and boredom".  I was at the border protest and I met the people who were there.  I saw families there.  I saw mothers, fathers and children.  There was a playground there.  They were there because this is the only hope they have left.  They are living in absolutely desperate conditions.  They have no hope.  The only hope they have is these protests.  They marched to the border to try to let the people of the world see the situation they are in.  I met staff from non-governmental organisations who are dealing with mental health issues on the ground.  They do not know how to cope.  I met a therapist who told me about meeting a completely and utterly traumatised woman who was on the verge of a nervous breakdown and feeling that she was telling the therapist's story.  Every single person is living with the same horrendous trauma.  Their water is polluted.  They are living in slum-like conditions.  At least 45% of them are unemployed.  They have no hope whatsoever.  They are in prison.  I went through the security.  I saw what they have to go through if they are allowed out.  They are not allowed in or out.  They are separated from their families.  They have no medical care.</p> <p>I met personnel from the UN Office for the Coordination of Humanitarian Affairs the morning after I had been with the protesters.  They informed me that according to their projections, Gaza could be unlivable by 2020.  That is what we are dealing with here.  We have to stop to consider what is going on for the ordinary people and families we are talking about here.  The projections I have mentioned have been made by a UN office, rather than by some non-governmental organisation or other organisation working for Palestinian rights.  It is the job of the UN to monitor the situation and to make sure people know what is happening.  People who are working at the coalface on the ground are telling us that this cannot go on any longer.  Gaza faces collapse in just over a year.  I heard the same story from everyone I met.  They said "please help us" and asked why the international community is dong nothing.  They pleaded with me.  The reality here is that we are running out of time.  We cannot forget this in the weeks and months to come.  How many more people are going to die in the weeks and months to come?</p> <p>Last week, Deputies and Senators came into the Oireachtas to express their shock about the tragic loss of life in Gaza.  I was glad to hear colleagues across the D&aacute;il and the Seanad condemning in the strongest terms the disproportionate and senseless violence that had occurred.  I was happy that Ireland was one of the first countries to call for an independent investigation.  I was really grateful for that.  I urge the Government to keep pushing for that in every possible way.  The truth is that we are right to be outraged.  The Israeli defence forces have said that the use of lethal force against unarmed protesters is proportionate.  This is an insult to language and to human life and dignity.  We are right to state firmly that this is a flagrant breach of international law and that wilful killing in the context of occupation may amount to a war crime, as the UN said in the aftermath of last week's events.  We are right to put it on the record of this Parliament that we reject the shameful treatment of living and breathing human beings and families that we are talking about here.  I promised everyone I met in Palestine that I would do this, at the very least.  The loss of life last week has made it even more important for me to do so.  I feel I have to do something.</p> <p>The Minister of State needs to go to Palestine.  I know the T&aacute;naiste has been there.  He is very compassionate on this issue.  I have spoken to him about it at length.  I was in the settlements as well.  I have tabled a Bill that would end Irish complicity in settlements that have been condemned as illegal for a long time.  I will speak briefly on this point.  I know the T&aacute;naiste has committed to a more focused debate and vote on this specific legislation in June.  I am grateful that he is going to bring this back in next month.  I urge the Government sincerely to reconsider in the coming weeks its stance on banning settlement goods.  My firm belief is that nothing will change in Palestine unless the EU and the wider international community are willing to put real and meaningful pressure on the Israeli Government.  Last week's events were another tragic reminder of this sad fact.  An Israeli Minister responded this morning to the most recent EU criticism of the massacre in Gaza by saying that the EU can "go to a thousand, thousand hells".<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Frances Black:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2474"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2474&amp;amp;pid=FrancesBlack&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This is what we must deal with and this is the attitude we have faced for decades.  Unless we do something it will continue.  If the EU is at a point of gridlock and if the consensus is not there, then we must ask ourselves if we accept it, or are we willing to take small meaningful steps ourselves - grounded firmly in international law - to show some leadership on this issue.  Is there a point at which the situation can get so bad and the violations of human rights so widespread that we will look to take action ourselves?</p><p>Ireland can lead on this.  I urge colleagues across the House, both in Fianna F&aacute;il and Fine Gael, to consider deeply the real and tangible steps Ireland can take.  It is no longer enough to simply express our sadness; we need to take action.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.218" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#BB00200"><p>Hear.  Hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.219" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#BB00300"><p>In his speech the Minister of State said:</p><blockquote>We recognise that not all those participating in the protest were non-violent.  Stones were thrown, Molotov cocktails were hurled and some protestors attempted to breach the border fence when there had been explicit warnings of the consequences of doing so.  There have also been reports that many of those shot were members of Hamas.</blockquote> <p>If this was a British Army commander speaking after Bloody Sunday I would ask the Minister of State to spot the difference.  That is exactly the justification it gave for its actions on Bloody Sunday.  It is outrageous that an Irish Government Minister of State read out those words today.  This is the defence the British Army gave for Bloody Sunday.  Whoever drafted that speech today on behalf of our State should be ashamed of themselves.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.220" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#BB00400"><p>Hear.  Hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.221" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#BB00500"><p>Last week the United States of America and Israel marked the locating of the United States embassy in Jerusalem.  The Israeli Prime Minister, Benjamin Netanyahu, said it was &quot;a glorious day for Israel&quot;.  The US President, Donald Trump, said it was &quot;a great day for Israel.&quot;  For Palestinians, however, it was an horrific day as the toll of dead and injured rose.  It was also the 70th anniversary of Nakba, the catastrophe.  This annual commemoration remembers the nearly 700,000 Palestinians who were forced from their land and homes by the Israeli army, and who have become refugees.  I have visited many of the locations where the refugees live and the Occupied Territories.</p><p>This years' <i>Nakba</i>is now marked by a new catastrophe.  The Israeli army murdered dozens of Palestinians in Gaza that day and more than 2,700 others were wounded.  An eight month old baby died as a result of inhaling tear gas.  There are 1.3 million Palestinian refugees in Gaza.  Today it is the biggest prison in the world.  Throughout the last seven weeks they have protested for the right of return for Palestinian refugees forcibly expelled from their homes in 1948.  Since the protests began on 30 March Israeli forces have killed more than 100 Palestinians in Gaza.  The Israeli forces have murdered more than 100 Palestinians.  They have wounded more than 13,000 men, women and children.  I put it to the Minister of State again that whoever wrote those lines in his speech should be utterly ashamed of themselves.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.222" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#BB00600"><p>Hear. Hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.223" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#BB00700"><p>The brutality and savagery of the Israeli army has once again been laid bare for the world to see.  The Israeli army fired live ammunition indiscriminately and it gassed protestors.  The Government must give a strong and unambiguous statement that there can be no impunity for Israel's mass killing and murder of Palestinian citizens, and its continued illegal occupation of Palestine.</p> <p>The Minister of State has said that Ireland will not move to expel the Israeli ambassador in protest at these killings or recall the Irish ambassador in Tel Aviv.  Nothing will change in Gaza or the West Bank until the international community moves on from empty rhetoric and puts some real pressure on Israel.  Ireland must stop sitting on the sidelines wringing its hands when real, concrete, tangible steps are proposed.  The Government is afraid to show leadership.  Last January Sinn F&eacute;in supported Senator Frances Black's Control of Economic Activity (Occupied Territories) Bill 2018 in this House.  This Bill proposes to end Irish economic support for Israeli settlements in the West Bank that we have long condemned as illegal.  The Government, however, refuses to take any real action on the settlements.  These are defined as war crimes under international law.  We listened in disbelief to the Israeli ambassador on the RT&Eacute; "Six One News".  He stated that Israel was doing its best to minimise its fire and there was no link to the US decision to move its embassy to Jerusalem.  More than 100 Palestinians are now dead and more than 13,000 have been injured, and this is with Israel limiting its firepower.  We must be clear that it was not clashes but, rather, a massacre.  I was sick to my stomach while watching the television footage.  I know that many Irish people share my horror.  Why did the Taoiseach again state in the D&aacute;il last week that Ireland cannot recognise Palestine because it does not exist yet?  Perhaps the Taoiseach could have a chat with his Swedish counterpart.  Sweden recognised the state of Palestine four years ago.  Perhaps the Taoiseach could visit the UN and chat with the leaders of 135 other countries that recognise Palestine.  More than 70% of the countries that are members of the UN recognise the state of Palestine.  Motions were passed unanimously in this House and in D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann in recent years to recognise the state of Palestine.</p> <p>If Ireland will not expel the Israeli ambassador, will not recognise the state of Palestine and will not support legislation that asks us to ban commerce with people who are involved in war crimes, then where are we?  Ireland took a stand in the days of South Africa's apartheid system.  Our women workers took a stand in Dunne's Stores.  In our Government, where are the women of Dunne's Stores today?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.224" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1438" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#BB00800"><p>I welcome the Minister of State for the debate on Palestine.  I was a Member of the Lower House and this issue came up on a regular basis.  There is no doubt that it will come up again in the future because nothing seems to be happening.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.225" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#BB00900"><p>Damn right there is nothing happening.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.226" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1438" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#BB01000"><p>Since 1946 when the Israeli State was brought into existence nothing has happened with regard to the Palestinian people.  The only thing that has happened is that they have been forcibly removed from their houses.  Even today, as we speak, Palestinian people are being moved off lands in the West Bank so that Israeli settlers can take the land.  People do not seem to understand that there are consequences to this.  If Israeli property is located in the West Bank, no Palestinian can walk close to it.  If I was a Palestinian and wanted to go from this side of the Chamber to the other side and if there was a Jewish, or Israeli, building in the middle, I would have to walk down to Merrion Square, cross over Merrion Square and come back up the other side to get into the far side of this Chamber.  People do not understand the type of harassment going on in the West Bank.  I saw it myself in Hebron where school children had to walk an extra mile to get to their homes or they would have walked in front of Israeli property.  These are the simple things that people must deal with day-to-day.</p> <p>People do not understand that fishermen in Gaza can only go out 3 km from the coast to fish.  They cannot go any further.  Farmers are restricted to growing their crops 500 m from the fence line.  These are the types of restrictions that are going on.</p> <p>If anyone here knows their history, the situation would remind them of the Warsaw Ghetto during the Second World War.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Anthony Lawlor:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=2283"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2283&amp;amp;pid=AnthonyLawlor&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->That was a situation where an extreme right wing super power controlled a minority people.  That is exactly what is going on in Gaza and the West Bank.  Jerusalem was chosen as the capital of Israel 3,000 years ago.  The Israelis could wait that long and their objective now is quite simple: a border from the Jordan Valley to the sea, from the Sinai Desert to the mountains north of Ramallah.  They can wait.  </p><p>I have heard calls for investigations.  There have been calls for investigations after every incident within the West Bank or Gaza and nothing has happened.  It is too late to call for investigations.  When I was in Jerusalem I walked through the Damascus Gate with Muslims, Christians and Jews.  Inside the gate there are many Muslim coffee shops and lots of Israeli Jews were having coffee there.  It is possible for the people to coexist if there is a willingness to do so.</p><p>Most Israeli settlements in the Jordan Valley use the water from that site to produce peppers and aubergines.  When we go to buy a red pepper we should check where it comes from and if it comes from Israel we should not purchase it.  We should purchase something that may come from Spain or even our own farmers, over anything else.  These are the small things that started when the Dunnes Stores staff worked to remove South African produce from the stores.  That is something simple that we can do. </p><p>Removing the Israeli ambassador removes a source of communication.  Then our ambassador will be removed.  What will be achieved?  We need to open communications.  The sad point is that the only thing that will hurt Israel is money not public opinion.  If we can hurt it financially let us do so.  I will not be purchasing produce from the settler community in the West Bank. </p><p>The soprano Celine Byrne did not participate in the 70th anniversary celebrations for the Israeli state in Jerusalem.  Perhaps the music industry could consider action like that too.  If this conflict is not resolved or no steps are taken we should reconsider our artists' participation in the Eurovision next year.  </p><p>We need to act individually as citizens and as a Government to bring Israel to the table.  The two-state solution is not on Israel's agenda although it seems to be on the world's agenda.  Until it is, there will be no further progress on this issue. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.228" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#CC00200"><p>I welcome pupils from St. Mary's of Dunmanway who are here at the invitation of Deputy Murphy O'Mahony.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.229" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#CC00300"><p>Oh God, I am weary of speaking about Palestine.  I have been speaking about it for 30 years.  I know the area very well.  I had an apartment in Jerusalem for many years.  My partner was an Israeli Jew who was an activist for Palestinian human rights.  As a result he has been harassed, arrested, framed, jailed and he has finally had a stroke and not a bloody thing has been done.  Just as in the 1930s Europe stood by and did damn all for the Jews, we are doing damn all for the Palestinians.  I am tired of mentioning the Euro-Mediterranean Partnership, EUROMED, that has human rights protocols attached to it.  We have never even monitored or examined them to see what their impact is.  We know from every speaker here today that there have been massive human rights abuses and war crimes committed by Israel but we do not monitor the EUROMED agreement.</p> <p>The Minister of State talks about live fire.  The Israelis have been using dumdum bullets against children.  These are bullets that enter the body, expand and burst open tissue, sinew, flesh and bones.  The exit wound is three times the size of the entry wound.  That is the kind of thing they are doing.  We are told stones and Molotov cocktails were thrown.  Can the Minister of State tell me how many Israelis were killed?  Not one.  Some of those shot were members of Hamas &ndash; so bloody what?  Hamas was elected in Gaza and the world turned its glance away and refused to recognise it.  I do not care whether the people shot were in Hamas.  They are human beings and they have every right to respect.  </p> <p>The Minister of State talks about attacks on health facilities and personnel - absolutely.  Four years ago when they were bombing schools, they were deliberately targeting them.   We had the co-ordinates.  We knew that they knew they were hitting schools and hospitals, sewage treatment plants and water facilities.  The Israeli intent is to degrade the Palestinians to a state lower than animals.  </p> <p>The Minister of State talks about the two-state solution.  It is impossible.  He talks about the two states with secure borders.  How can the Palestinians have secure borders?  There are two scraps of land and in the West Bank they are peppered with Israeli settlements, like measles.  How can we possibly say to the Palestinians they have a secure border when they are completely and utterly infiltrated?  The tragedy is that Europe attempted to solve the moral problem of the Holocaust at the expense of the Palestinians who were not involved in it.  That explains the German situation.  Let us forget about the EU.  We must act independently as a sovereign nation.  The EU will do nothing because of the German bad conscience.  The Germans are turning around and doing exactly the same to the Palestinians as they did to the Jews in the 1930s.  That should be forcibly pointed out to them. </p> <p>I have been described as anti-Semitic.  It does not matter that I lived with an Israeli Jew for 40 years or that the Palestinians are Semites.  Nobody accuses the Jews of being anti-Semitic for their attitude towards the Palestinians.  </p> <p>Look at the terrible damage the Israelis are doing to themselves.  The wonderful Jewish ethical code that he who saves a life saves the universe has been completely blotted out.  Look at the damage to the Israeli soldiers who are young impressionable men.  We have seen them gloating after shooting children.  That is appalling. </p> <p>What about the Palestinians?  They are in the largest, most horrible, ghastly prison environment the world has seen.  They are in a state of total and absolute despair.  They can do nothing.  The world will not listen.  I remember being in the West Bank and saying, "I do not know that my Government will do anything".  They said, "At least tell our story".  That is the only reason I am standing here today.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator David Norris:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1758"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1758&amp;amp;pid=DavidNorris&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->What can we do?  We can recognise the state of Palestine.  Why not?  This House passed a resolution that we should do so.  The Government must listen to the voices of the elected representatives of this country and recognise the state of Palestine.  That might put the fear of God into the Israelis.  We should boycott all of the illegal settlement goods, withdraw our ambassador for consultation and we should certainly not take part in next year's Eurovision song contest in Israel.  This is not a matter for entertainment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.231" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#DD00200"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.232" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#DD00300"><p>People are dying.  People are being massacred by the Israelis.  In the few seconds remaining to me I urge the Minister of State to stop waffling, for God's sake, and get something done.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.233" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#DD00400"><p>Senator Bacik is next and she has six minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.234" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#DD00500"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House and thank the Leader for organising this debate.  I am one of the Senators who sought it.  We were all utterly shocked at the appalling loss of life in Gaza, which the Minister of State acknowledged in his speech.  As he pointed out, 14 May recorded the highest casualty toll in the Gaza Strip in a single day since 2014, with a total of 102 Palestinians, including 12 children, killed and an appalling number injured, some 12,500.  We all remember the really tragic case of the death of little Leila Anwar Ghandoor, an eight month old baby.</p><p>Like other colleagues, I was shocked at some of the language used in the speech of the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade at the time which appeared to suggest that blame lay with the victims of this appalling atrocity.  We must be very clear about the complicity and the conduct of the Israeli forces in bringing about these civilian deaths.  I am no apologist for Hamas and do not believe anyone here is, but it is important to acknowledge the cause of these awful deaths.</p><p>We also have to acknowledge the context for all of this.  The Gaza Strip is occupied territory in which 2 million live in appalling conditions which were described so eloquently by Senator Black and others.  Mr. Declan Walsh wrote a very good article in <i>The Irish Times</i>which sums up so well the pressures of life in Gaza, a poverty stricken, crowded enclave that has been under Israeli blockade for the past 11 years.  This has been well documented.  I am a member of the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs and Trade and we have had numerous hearings on the conditions for people living in Gaza and for Palestinians living in occupied territories, conditions for Palestinian detainees, including child detainees, in Israeli prisons and on breaches of international law by Israel.  All of this is well known and, like Senator Norris, many of us feel that we have been speaking about this for so long but so little has been done.  </p><p>What we have seen in recent days is a new development, unfortunately, and one which was precipitated by the decision of the current US President to move the US Embassy to Jerusalem.  That is a new and very negative development that sets us back even further from any sort of peaceful path towards the settlement that we all wish to see.</p><p>I speak today for the Labour Party which has a long tradition of being to the forefront in advocating justice for the Palestinian people.  My party has a long-standing position on the Middle East, informed by three core principles, namely: the need for a comprehensive, multilateral peace agreement between Israel and Palestine which respects international law; the delivery for the Palestinian people of a secure, viable and contiguous state of their own; and the recognition of the legitimate right of the people of Israel to live in peace, prosperity and security with its neighbours.  That is a clear set of goals to which many members of the international community have signed up but, unfortunately, with the recent decision by the US President, we have seen a real step away from any path that makes that settlement more likely.</p><p>What can we do about this?  I accept that an independent inquiry would be useful to establish the full facts and to establish beyond doubt what lay behind the conduct of the Israeli troops.  However, we need to be more assertive in Ireland in terms of how we go about addressing this outrageous atrocity by Israel.  We have to move within the EU and be more assertive there, as a stakeholder.</p><p>The Minister of State has pointed out that Ireland has provided more than &euro;10 million annually for the Palestinian people.  We provide aid bilaterally and also multilaterally through the EU, which is a major stakeholder in the region.  The foreign affairs committee has also heard several times about the outrageous situation whereby the EU is providing funding to construct buildings which are subsequently demolished by Israeli forces.  The EU is funding infrastructure to support education and healthcare, for example, for the Palestinians which is then dismantled and destroyed by Israeli forces.  It defies logic that the EU does not intervene in a more proactive manner.</p><p>I support Senator Norris and others who have called for such intervention.  The EU should take a much stronger interventionist role in this.  In Ireland we should step up further by complying with the motions passed by D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann and Seanad &Eacute;ireann calling for the recognition of the state of Palestine.  That would be a significant step forward and would exert more pressure within the EU.  We must play a more assertive role in assuring greater justice for Palestinians.</p><p>The former T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade, Eamon Gilmore, addressed the UN General Assembly in September 2011 and said that Ireland would support the Palestinian bid to become a full member of the UN.  At that point Ireland was taking a very proactive role within the EU in its recognition and assertion of Palestinian rights.  We need to do more of that, particularly after this absolutely egregious attack on Palestinian civilians.</p><p>I was very glad to support Senator Black's Control of Economic Activity (Occupied Territories) Bill which points a way forward for Ireland to take a stronger stance in asserting the condemnation of the Irish people of the actions of the Israeli state.</p><p>It is also important to express support for the Boycott, Divestment, Sanctions, BDS, campaign which is led by Palestinian civil society.  That campaign seeks to build on the work of the international anti-apartheid movement which played such a strong role in helping to dismantle the apartheid state of South Africa.  Of course, we all recall the proud role played in that international movement by the Irish anti-apartheid movement.  We could be doing more in Ireland to assert a voice for the Palestinian people through the international mechanisms to which we have access through the EU and also through asserting recognition of Palestinian statehood.</p><p>I ask the Minister of State to clarify whether the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade will support and implement the motions of D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann and Seanad &Eacute;ireann in that regard.  There is overwhelming support for this among Irish people.  I do not believe there is political controversy about this issue in Ireland.  People here are so exercised, dismayed and distressed by the reports of what has happened in Gaza recently that now would be an appropriate time to do this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.235" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#DD00600"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House.  I will begin by asking the Minister of State to withdraw that disgraceful paragraph in his speech which makes reference to &quot;some&quot; of the protesters being non-violent, to Molotov cocktails and to members of Hamas being shot.  There is no evidence for any of that.  I do not know who wrote that script but the Minister of State must be honest enough to acknowledge that it is not true and to withdraw it.</p><p>As the Minister of State knows, 62 Palestinians were slaughtered a week ago and over 13,000 have been maimed in the last seven weeks.  Since 2000 Israel has murdered 9,000 Palestinians, including 2,060 children.  The Minister of State must acknowledge what most of us already know, namely, that Israel is an apartheid state.  This Government has never done that.  In the past when we have highlighted this, the Government has described our position as &quot;one sided&quot;.  In fairness, the Government is right.  If one is against apartheid, as we in Sinn F&eacute;in are, then one must stand against and not just pose as some neutral arbiter.</p><p>We know Israel is an apartheid state but let me make it clear why that is the case.  The United Nations defines apartheid as, &quot;an institutionalised regime of systematic oppression and domination by one racial group over any other racial group&quot;.  As Senator Lawlor said, in what was a fine speech, that is exactly what is happening and the Minister of State knows this<b>.</b>Under Israel's immigration policy, it is possible for all Jews to emigrate to Israel but Palestinians are refused any right of return.  There are 5 million Palestinian refugees as a direct result of a religious and ethnically-based immigration policy.  Contrast the systematic demolition of Palestinian homes with the ever-expanding settlements for Israeli citizens, numbering over 600,000 at this stage.</p><p>Then there is the economic apartheid whereby more than 20,000 Palestinians work in the Israeli settlements while the systematic destruction of Palestinian infrastructure and resources continues unabated.  This destruction includes the uprooting and burning of millions of Palestinian olive trees.  We have seen the theft of water and land and the cutting off of electricity, telephone, water and Internet services as collective punishment.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paul Gavan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2469"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2469&amp;amp;pid=PaulGavan&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->There is no freedom of movement for Palestinians.  We have seen checkpoints and military bases, daily harassment and discrimination.  Separate judicial systems operate with civil systems for Israelis and military courts for Palestinians.  There are separate road systems.  It is illegal for any Palestinian to join any political party.</p><p>The Government knows all this but still contends that the way forward is dialogue.  It is not.  The way forward is through sanctions, just as it was with apartheid South Africa.  The way forward is to stop trading with Israel.  The way forward is to stop buying arms from Israel.  A total of &euro;14.75 million has been spent by our Government since 2005.  Will the Minister of State answer this question for me?  Why does he believe it is okay to buy arms from an apartheid state, particularly one which boasts that its products have been battle-tested?  Where does the Minister of State think they have been battle-tested?</p><p>There are so many positive things the Government could do.  The Government could choose to recognise the Palestinian state but it is refusing to do so. The Minister of State could commit to an arms embargo and show us as a country leading the way on this crucial issue, but he will not.  The Government could endorse boycott, divestment and sanctions, but it will not.  The Government could support Frances Black's Bill to boycott Israeli goods from the occupied territories.  Unfortunately, it has given no indication to date that this will happen.  I call on the Minister of State to give such an indication at the least in his response.  I will ask my colleague, Senator Daly, to ensure Fianna F&aacute;il comes up to the mark one month from now.  We should all stand together on this issue.  The Government could expel the Israeli ambassador, but it will not.  The Government could choose to expel other Israeli diplomats, like it did to the Russians without any evidence, but it will not.</p><p>We understood one thing in the 1980s but the Minister of State does not understand it today.  It is not okay to do business with an apartheid state.  It is actually quite shameful.  The fact that the Government will not acknowledge Israel's apartheid state is unacceptable.  There were apologists for apartheid in the 1970s and 1980s as well.  Unfortunately, several were from the Minister of State's party.  Most famously, the former Deputy Patrick Donegan lauded the tour of the Springboks team to Dublin in 1970.  I had hoped things would have moved on by now, but it appears not.</p><p>The people are demanding justice for the Palestinian people.  They are demanding action against the apartheid Israeli state.  For every day that the Government refuses to take such action, it is letting all of us down.  I have heard enough empty words and seen enough crocodile tears.  I have heard enough coded statements calling for restraint from both sides.  We cannot allow the slaughter of these people to become another footnote in the tragic history of the Palestinian people.  The world is crying out for justice.  The Minister of State should stand up and find the courage to take meaningful action.  He should end the shameful arms trade with Israel, endorse sanctions and expel the ambassador.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.237" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#EE00200"><p>Yesterday, 22 May, strikingly enough, marked the anniversary of Carol Ann Kelly.  Carol Ann was shot and killed by a rubber bullet in Twinbrook on her way home from getting a carton of milk for her mother in 1981.  When Carol Ann was murdered and fatally fell to the ground, the organs of the state kicked into gear immediately and began to victim-blame.  They blamed her, her family and the community in which she lived for the actions carried out by the British Army that day.</p> <p>Given what other Senators have said, the Minister of State seriously needs to reflect and spend a little time on this.  I understand he has been handed a script by an official.  The Minister of State must avoid engaging in the kind of deliberate, calculated and very dangerous propaganda that is emanating with regard to the Palestinian people and what is happening in Gaza at the moment.  It is perfectly clear to me and anyone who wants to see it, that what is being implemented and playing out in Gaza is slaughter.  It is the massacre of innocent protesters.  It is familiar to us but, although even given the gravity of what Ireland suffered as a result of colonialism, we have not seen anything close to the type of awful horror inflicted on the Palestinian people, not least those in Gaza.  The Minister of State might reflect on that and might do what Senator Gavan has encouraged him to do and withdraw his offensive, if not very ill-considered, remarks.  The problem is that it is a mantra that has become all too familiar in practices of colonialism and brutality throughout the world in this era as well as many before it.</p> <p>This country has a proud record in standing against apartheid.  The Houses have voted to recognise the state of Palestine.  The Government ignores this will, much like the Israeli Government ignores international law, given the implementation and carrying out of war crimes against the Palestinian people.</p> <p>Like Senator Norris said earlier, I am here a relatively short time but already I am tired of having to come in and repeat the exact same things on Gaza and Palestine about the suffering those people have to endure.  I understand the geopolitical sensitivities and that the Government has to engage in a degree of diplomacy, but I do not believe we are dealing with an ordinary state.  We are certainly not dealing with an ordinary conflict between two ordinary states.  We are seeing people in Gaza being massacred.  As people have rightly said, this is an open air prison.  I have no wish to rehearse all of the horror that we have articulated many times, but that is the position.  It is not too much to ask this Government, given its actions with the Russian ambassador, to bring in the Israeli ambassador and expel him from Ireland.  His state is in breach of international law.  It is committing war crimes.</p> <p>I have no doubt that the Minister of State and his officials have exhausted whatever diplomatic avenues are open to them, modest as they are.  Like any conflict resolution situation, there is of course a time for engagement and dialogue.  However, there is also a time for action.  There is a time for standing for what is right and just.  There is a time for standing against things like apartheid.  For God's sake, we must find a way to stand against apartheid and show Ireland standing against apartheid on the international stage.</p> <p>We heard lovely things earlier about what we invest in that part of the world, the Irish bars there, going for pints and meeting the lovely Irish diaspora.  They ought to be ashamed of themselves, to be honest, if, as Irish people, they are standing and participating in full knowledge in a system and economy like that of Israel - an apartheid regime.</p> <p>What can we do?  We can, we should and we must expel the Israeli ambassador if we have any degree of understanding of the horror and wrongness of apartheid and if we have any respect for international law.  We have endured colonialism, brutality and occupation.  For God's sake, we have to take a stand on the international stage in the full knowledge that it will be a modest stand and that it will not have the necessary impact with other states throughout the world.  When has that ever stopped us before?  As has been rightly said, we took a good, proud and valiant stand against apartheid in South Africa.  What is the difference in this case?</p> <p>Why will the Irish Government not stand in support of the Palestinian people?  I suspect somewhat cynically that we all know the reason.  I believe we are being hampered by the EU structures.  I believe we are being shackled by the EU structures from doing the right thing and supporting not only the expulsion of the Israeli ambassador but Senator Black's Bill which proposes a boycott of Israeli goods from illegal settlements in the proudest Irish tradition, which we started.  We should stand with the Palestinian people to send a clear message to them that they have our solidarity and support and that none of this will prohibit us from supporting and engaging with diplomatic and conflict resolution initiatives later on.  The time has long since passed for us to take action.</p> <p>I hope the Minister of State will reflect on his contribution and bring back the views of the House with regard to the rubbish inflicted upon us.  The Minister of State should adhere to the will of these Houses and recognise the state of Palestine.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.238" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1241" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Cannon" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#FF00100"><p>The very passionate contributions we have heard today reflect the deep and long-standing engagement the House has had with the situation in Palestine.  I spoke at the outset about the loss of hope of the people of Gaza and Palestinians in general, how they are dealing with this incredible level of atrocity being committed against them and how it is feeding into the desperate acts that cause ordinary people, including children, to put their lives in danger while venting their frustrations through peaceful protest.  I spoke also about what more needs to be done to address the situation of hopelessness, and considerable work has already been done by Members of the House, many of whom have visited the region to bring attention to the plight of the Palestinian people and propose ways to contribute to their ongoing well-being.</p> <p>Some Senators have taken exception to the Government acknowledging that some protesters threw stones and Molotov cocktails.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.239" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#FF00200"><p>Imagine.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.240" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1241" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Cannon" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#FF00300"><p>I mention this because it is necessary to tackle head on the arguments being put forward by some in Israel that these actions could be a justification for the deeply disproportionate Israeli response.  I was also very clear that stone throwing does not in any way justify the use of live ammunition on young people and protesters who were unarmed.  I was very specific in making this point over again.</p> <p>Many Senators referred to Senator Black's occupied territories Bill, which was debated here earlier this year and which we will discuss again before the summer break.  The T&aacute;naiste has already committed to this.  The Government is very much aware that the intention in proposing the Bill is to show Ireland's clear support for the Palestinian people and to show condemnation of the creeping annexation of Palestinian land by Israel in the form of these illegal settlements.  I assure the House that the Government is wholly opposed to the construction of these settlements in Palestinian territory and has consistently condemned their relentless expansion, which undermines the very basis for the two-state solution.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.241" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#FF00400"><p>Well then, that's much better.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.242" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1241" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Cannon" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#FF00500"><p>I also want to acknowledge the efforts made in framing the Bill to differentiate between illegal settlements and Israel itself.  It is not an effort to impose a boycott divestment sanctions policy, which the Government would wholly oppose.  However, the Bill proposes to regulate international trade, which, ultimately, is a matter of exclusive EU competence, falling under the EU's common commercial policy.  This is not a matter on which Ireland can act alone, and if we were tempted to do so, infringement proceedings could be taken against the State for breaching EU law.  This might be the impact rather than the powerfully political impact which the framers of the Bill have aimed for with regard to settlements.</p> <p>Some in the House have also raised the possibility of Ireland recognising the state of Palestine, and I assure the House the Government remains committed to doing this as part of a lasting settlement of the conflict.  Ireland has long looked forward to being able to recognise a sovereign Palestinian state, but the Government must consider carefully whether recognition by Ireland now, at this point in time, of a state of Palestine, prior to its actual achievement on the ground, would be a helpful step towards that goal.  We have not yet concluded that immediate recognition by Ireland would be a helpful step in our efforts to move the peace process forward, but I assure the House this matter is being kept under continuous review-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.243" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#FF00600"><p>There is no peace process.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.244" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#FF00700"><p>What peace process?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.245" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1241" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Cannon" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#FF00800"><p>-----particularly in light of the views expressed by the D&aacute;il and Seanad in 2014, to which many Senators referred.</p> <p>I want to address once again an issue raised in the debate by many Senators on the position of the Israeli ambassador and the embassy here.  Asking an ambassador to leave is hardly ever done anywhere, not least because it cuts off an incredibly important channel of dialogue and influence.  The T&aacute;naiste used that channel last week when he conveyed Ireland's strong views on the Gaza events directly to the Israeli ambassador and, ultimately, asked him to pass those messages onto the Israeli Government.  To remove the Israeli ambassador would shut off that line of communication indefinitely.  We have to question how we would have arrived at a successful conclusion to the Northern Ireland peace negotiations if we had decided over 25 or 30 years ago to shut off communications with the leaders of one of those communities in Northern Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.246" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#FF00900"><p>Fine Gael opposed it, to be fair.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.247" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1241" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Cannon" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#FF01000"><p>I do not think we would have been celebrating 20 years of the Good Friday Agreement recently if we had decided to shut off communication completely with one of the communities involved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.248" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#FF01100"><p>That is a cop-out.  How is the current dialogue going with Israel?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.249" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1241" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Cannon" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#FF01200"><p>The protests of recent weeks were a reaction to the unsustainable situation in Gaza.  The 1.9 million people who live there deserve an end to the blockade, so they can start to build what we would describe as normal lives, something that has been all but impossible for more than a decade.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.250" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#FF01300"><p>An end to apartheid.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.251" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1241" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Cannon" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#FF01400"><p>Through our support of Palestine we have endeavoured to address some of the difficulties faced by the people of Gaza but, ultimately, the two-state solution with an independent Palestine and a democratic Israel, both secure within their borders, is the only possible outcome that will see an end to the decades of violence.  This is why the T&aacute;naiste has made, and continues to make, engagement with the Middle East peace process an absolute priority.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.252" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#FF01500"><p>That concludes statements on Palestine.  The next item, which is statements on bed capacity at the National Rehabilitation Hospital, is not due to start until 3.50 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.253" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1438" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#FF01600"><p>I move that the House suspend until 3.50 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.254" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#FF01700"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.255" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 3.35 p.m. and resumed at 3.50 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.256" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#HH00100">Bed Capacity at National Rehabilitation Hospital: Statements</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.257" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052300002#HH00200"><p>I welcome the opportunity to make statements on the beds available at the National Rehabilitation Hospital.  I thank Senator Victor Boyhan for raising this important issue.  Since 2016, I have been tracking it closely and in regular contact with the Health Service Executive on it.  I welcome Mr. John O'Donovan from the HSE.  </p> <p>The HSE has advised that the complexity of the medical conditions of patients referred to the National Rehabilitation Hospital for rehabilitation programmes has increased significantly in recent years, resulting in greater challenges for the hospital.  In response, in late 2016, management at the hospital reduced its bed capacity by 12 to enable it to provide a safe and appropriate level of care for patients from within existing resources.  Eight of the beds were in the brain injury programme and four in the spinal cord injury programme.  Thankfully, the position at the hospital has improved since.  In September and October 2017 funding was secured to reopen four of the closed beds.  Two brain injury programme beds were reopened in September and in October another brain injury programme bed reopened, with one in the spinal cord system of care programme.  In late December 2017 additional funding was secured to reopen a further two beds in the brain injury programme through the assistance of the Health Service Executive's national social care division as part of its winter planning strategy for the period 2017 to 2018.  As things stand, a total of six beds have been reopened at the hospital, five of which are in the brain injury programme and one in the spinal cord system of care programme.</p> <p>The Department of Health is working closely with the HSE to maximise potential capacity at the National Rehabilitation Hospital.  As always, the first priority will be providing safe and appropriate services for patients.  The hospital was not in a position to reopen additional beds in early 2018 owing to the ongoing risk of infection through multi-drug resistant organisms, MDROs.  The hospital has eight single rooms which are appropriate for isolation purposes in the control of MDROs.  It has been requested to forward a proposal to the HSE for increasing these facilities in the light of the increased challenges associated with the admission of patients with suspected MDRO infections.  The HSE most recently met hospital management on 16 April and was advised that a submission to increase the number of single rooms, above the eight available, was nearing completion.  The hospital also confirmed that a submission had been provided for the national hospitals office on the reopening of an additional six beds at the facility.  The proposal is also being evaluated by the HSE's community health division.  The HSE's operations and service improvement division has also sought to reopen the same beds through the winter planning process for the period 2018 to 2019.  However, such considerations will only be concluded by October and November; therefore, if successful, the beds will be opened after this date.  The Government recognises the excellent rehabilitation programme which the hospital delivers and its excellent patient outcomes.</p> <p>On capital development, the current priority is the delivery of replacement accommodation at the National Rehabilitation Hospital.  The redevelopment of the hospital which is under way and which I warmly welcome will be a major enhancement to rehabilitation services.  It will have a direct and significant impact on patient recovery by providing an optimal ward and therapeutic environment for patient treatment.  An investment of &euro;64 million will ensure the existing ward accommodation at the hospital will be replaced by a new fit for purpose ward accommodation block of 120 single en suite rooms, with integrated therapy spaces, a new sports hall, a hydrotherapy unit, a temporary concourse, as well as clinical and ancillary spaces.  In addition, links with the existing building will ensure full integration between the new development and the existing hospital on the site.  The contracts for development works at the hospital were signed on 28 August 2017 and construction commenced on the site immediately.  The construction of the hydrotherapy unit and the sports hall is expected to be completed by the end of the year, with the remainder of the construction works due for completion by the end of 2019 and expected to be operational in 2020.  Phase 2 of the redevelopment of the National Rehabilitation Hospital involves the expansion of services to include all existing therapies and support facilities to the new hospital.  Funding for phases 1 and 2 of this major redevelopment project is provided for in the national development plan 2018 to 2027.  It is part of an overall &euro;10.9 billion strategic investment in health services under the Project Ireland 2040 policy initiative.  </p> <p>I thank the House for giving me the opportunity to address these issues.  I look forward to listening to the contributions of Senators.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-23a.258" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Additional debate to follow.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>