<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.4" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Kieran O&rsquo;Donnell that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport to provide an update on current plans he has for the funding and construction of the M20 Cork to Limerick motorway.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Paudie Coffey of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport to outline his plans to provide capital funding to Waterford Regional Airport to extend its runway so that a sustainable future for the airport can be secured.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Terry Leyden of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to address concerns regarding funding for the &euro;7.87 million ten-bed rehabilitation unit at Roscommon University Hospital and detail when the planned development will commence.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator M&aacute;ire Devine of the following matter: </p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to outline how his Department intends to deal with the serious concerns being raised by the Psychiatric Nurses' Association which have led to planned industrial action.</blockquote> <p>I regard the matters raised by the Senators as suitable for discussion and they will be taken now.  Senator Devine has withdrawn her Commencement matter which I had selected.</p><p>I welcome the Minister to the House.  I always knew he would be in that seat one day.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.7" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#A00300">Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.8" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#A00400">Road Network</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1374" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#A00500"><p>I welcome the Minister, Deputy Ross.  It is particularly significant that he is a former Member of this House, but the issue I am bringing up today is more significant.  As a Senator based in Limerick city, the upgrade of the N20 to a motorway, the M20, between Cork and Limerick is the number one infrastructural project for both Cork and Limerick at the moment.  If one travels from Cork along the N20 to Limerick at the minute, it is approximately 100 km in length and takes well over an hour and a half.  In the last 12 to 14 months alone, there have been nine fatalities on that route, so we need the motorway from a safety perspective if for no other reason.  It takes an hour and a half to drive 100 km.  If one drives on the Limerick to Dublin motorway, the M7, it takes just over two hours to do double that, 200 km.</p> <p>We speak about regional development, but we need to put it into action.  We need balanced regional development where the Cork-Limerick-Galway axis acts as a counter-pole to Dublin, which is bursting at the seams.  We need the M20 to grow this western corridor from Limerick to Cork.  Many of my constituents in Limerick are commuting on a daily basis between Limerick and Cork.  Likewise, many have businesses in both locations.  A rising tide lifts all boats for us in the southern region.  We want this M20 for this route between Limerick and Cork.</p> <p>There are a couple of aspects to it.  Route selection has already taken place, and the plan had gone to An Bord Plean&aacute;la.  Due to finances, the project was discontinued in November 2011.  What is now required from the Minister is a ministerial direction to restart the scheme.  Transport Infrastructure Ireland, TII, formerly the NRA, should be required to prepare an updated business case for this M20 route.  It will stand on its own merits.  It will grow and will provide the engine to drive growth in both Limerick and Cork.  I understand it is a costly project, but the Minister will know, as a former member of the Public Accounts Committee, that we are looking for value for money.  The construction of this route, which would be 80 km in length, would cut the time by about 30 minutes.  One would be able to commute from Limerick to Cork in just over an hour.  At the moment it takes at least an hour and a half.  We are at a comparative disadvantage in the region, where we have a substandard road linking the second and third largest cities in Ireland.  In terms of being a modern economy, we have to ensure that takes place.</p> <p>Much of the work along the existing route selection - that is, environmental impact studies, motorway orders and oral hearings - had started with An Bord Plean&aacute;la.  I understand the Minister will probably have to go through the same process again, but if it transpires that the existing route is the one chosen, much of the work will already have been done.  I thank the Cathaoirleach for allowing me to raise this matter on the Commencement.  What I want from the Minister today is a clear direction that he will get the planning process under way again.  I know a mid-term review of the capital plan is due over the next year.  Will he ask TII to upgrade the business case, which it can present to him so that he can kick-start the process again?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#A00600"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach.  It is nice to be back.  It does not seem like six years since I was in this House.  The surroundings have not changed very much, although the occupants have.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#A00700"><p>Not all of them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#B00100"><p>Nearly all of them, although I must add that I have always been much fonder of the surroundings than the occupants.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#B00200"><p>That is mutual.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#B00300"><p>If the Minister is being totally honest, he misses this place.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#B00400"><p>That is right.  I congratulate the Members on being elected to the Seanad.  It is a great honour.  It will be a great Seanad.  Seanad reform is coming and it is wonderful to have a House in which there is no Government overall majority ramming things through.  The Government will have to talk to the other parties and Independent Senators to get legislation through.  I welcome that and I believe the Seanad will play a significant role, which it has not played in the past.  I look forward to being in the House frequently over the next five years.</p><p>I thank the Senator for the opportunity to address this matter.  I welcome him in the Seanad although I am sorry he is here because he was a very good Member of the other House, as also applies Senator Coffey.  No doubt they will be back in the D&aacute;il in the near future.</p><p>As Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, I have responsibility for overall policy and funding for the national roads programme.  The planning, design and implementation of individual national road projects is a matter for Transport Infrastructure Ireland, TII, formerly known as the National Roads Authority, NRA, under the Roads Acts 1993 to 2015, in conjunction with the local authorities concerned.  Within its capital budget the assessment and prioritisation of individual projects is a matter in the first instance for TII in accordance with section 19 of the Roads Act.</p><p>Ireland has just under 100,000 km of road in its network and the maintenance and improvement of national, regional and local roads places a substantial financial burden on local authorities and the Exchequer.  As a result of the financial position, there have been very large reductions in the Exchequer funding available for roads expenditure over the past number of years.  For this reason the focus has had to be on maintenance and renewal rather than on major new improvement schemes.  The proposed upgrade of the M20 was one of a range of proposed road development projects which had to be deferred.</p><p>The capital plan published in September 2015 outlined proposed transport investment priorities to 2022.  The transport element of the plan was framed by the conclusions reached in my Department's strategic investment framework for land transport.  This report highlighted the importance of maintenance and renewal of transport infrastructure together with targeted investments to address particular bottlenecks and critical safety issues.  The capital plan provides &euro;6 billion for investment in the roads network in the period to 2022, with &euro;4.4 billion earmarked for the maintenance and strengthening of the existing extensive network throughout the country and &euro;1.6 billion for new projects.  Allowing for the commitments relating to the public private partnership, PPP, projects, the balance available for new projects within the available capital envelope was limited.</p><p>Given the funding constraints a project of the scale of the M20 would have absorbed a<i></i>substantial proportion of the budget for new projects.  In those circumstances, as I understand it, the decision made by my predecessor was to provide for a mix of smaller scale projects across the country to address particular constraints, including bottlenecks and port connectivity.  While it will not be possible to address all the demands for improvement schemes over the capital plan period, the plan provides for the gradual build-up in capital funding for the road network towards the levels needed to support maintenance and improvement works.  In this context a number of important projects in Cork are included in the plan, including the upgrade of the Dunkettle roundabout and the N22 road between Ballyvourney and Macroom.  In addition, the plan also provides that the N28 upgrade scheme will also commence, subject to necessary approvals.</p><p>We are all conscious that the recovery of the economy is generating spending pressures across the system, including capital investment needs.  As part of the programme for partnership Government there is an increased emphasis on the need for spending on public services, but the Government still must operate within the EU fiscal rules and this constrains options.  There will be a mid-term review of the capital plan, as Senator O'Donnell mentioned, and this will provide an opportunity to assess progress and consider what scope there is for increased levels of investment depending on economic growth.  As regards the M20, I expect that the position with the project will be considered as part of the mid-term review.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1374" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#B00500"><p>I ask the Minister to request or direct Transport Infrastructure Ireland to carry out an updated business case for the M20.  The business case conducted in 2009 clearly indicated the need for this route between Limerick and Cork.  It is a huge concern and priority for my constituents in Limerick.  Furthermore, the fact that there have been nine fatalities on that route in the past 12 to 14 months provides an added impetus for this project to get under way.  The Minister should request the TII to produce an updated business case to be delivered to him and I ask him to inform the Seanad of the outcome of that business case review.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#B00600"><p>I take the Senator's point about the fatalities.  It is very serious and I have heard it from many other sources aside from the Senator.  I am not familiar with the road network of Ireland yet, but this is one that has been highlighted by the Senators and others.  It is a serious point.</p> <p>Regarding TII, I will not necessarily do exactly as the Senator wishes.  However, I am due to meet representatives of the TII shortly, because I am meeting representatives of all of the semi-State bodies.  I will put the question the Senator has asked to the TII representatives and listen to the case for why they should or should not do this.  I will make a decision after I have talked to them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1374" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#B00700"><p>Will the Minister inform us of the outcome of that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#B00800"><p>I will keep the Senator informed.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.20" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#B00850">Regional Airports</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1422" speakername="Paudie Coffey" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#B00900"><p>I welcome the Minister, Deputy Ross, to the House.  It is very familiar to him.  Indeed, I served a term as Senator with him from 2007 to 2011.  I also served a term with him in the Lower House.  This is my first opportunity publicly to wish the Minister well with his portfolio.  He brings vast experience to the office and I believe he will do a good job.  He has a good understanding of what is required in terms of transport, tourism and economic development.</p> <p>As we heard in the earlier debate, transport and tourism are undoubtedly key economic components of Ireland's economy.  Like the roads mentioned by Senator O'Donnell, other infrastructure such as our rail, ports and airports are critical to unlocking the economic potential our regions offer to the economy.  I have often compared Dublin and its environs to an economic vortex, where it sucks the economic activity from the regions of this country as well as our young educated people.  They come to Dublin where the jobs are and, unfortunately, do not return to the regions.  Until we address the long-term strategic decisions of our country for regional development and critical infrastructure development we will not change that situation.</p> <p>There is a unique opportunity for all of us, including the Minister, to make strategic decisions in the interests of sustainable regional development.  For that reason, I raise an issue of which the Minister is well aware, the long-term sustainable future of Waterford Airport.  It serves the south-east region, a region that has been under-performing due to the deficits in critical infrastructure.  In fairness, some of them have been addressed over the last number of years.  With the development of the motorway to Waterford one can see already the economic development it brings.  Investments made by the Minister's Department and his predecessors in tourism initiatives have also brought economic activity.  I refer to the Viking Triangle in Ireland's oldest city, Waterford, and the D&eacute;ise Greenway which is due to open later this year and will link the oldest city in Ireland to one of the most beautiful harbour towns in Ireland, Dungarvan.  It runs across the mid-county of Waterford with the coast on one side and the Comeragh Mountains on the other.</p> <p>Waterford and the south-east region are very proud of what they have to offer.  However, we need help in terms of delivering the critical infrastructure that will allow us to layer economic activity and employment on top of that.  Waterford Airport has experienced some difficulties over the years with operational airlines coming and going.  VLM Airlines is the most recent airline at the airport but it has announced it is to discontinue its service to Birmingham and Luton.  That is an important connection to the UK, our neighbour, which brings people to the region who will spend there and create the activity I have mentioned.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paudie Coffey:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2237"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2237&amp;amp;pid=PaudieCoffey&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The board and management team at Waterford Airport have worked assiduously in very difficult circumstances.  The previous Government supported the airport through the worst economic times this country has experienced by providing grant aid of more than &euro;5 million to keep it going.  However, we now need to move to the next level.  We must move on and a runway extension at Waterford Airport is critical so that jet aircraft can land there and in order that more operators will be interested in bringing passengers to and from not just Waterford but also the wider south-east region, where all economic indicators are showing that we are underperforming.  As a region, the south east can contribute to the economic recovery.  It can contribute to job creation, in which we are all interested, but, more importantly, it can contribute to the sustainability of the economy.</p><p>The Minister has a critical role to play.  I understand that he faces challenges and that he must spend his money wisely in terms of capital investment.  If, however, he invests in this project, it will be a move he will not regret.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#C00200"><p>I thank Senator Coffey for his kind words and congratulate him on his election to the House.  I look forward to meeting him here in the near future.</p> <p>I thank the Senator for raising this particular matter.  I am well aware of the difficulties he is experiencing, particularly in the context of the airport in Waterford.  A colleague, Deputy Halligan, chews my ear off daily about the matter as well.  The Senator can rest assured that his raising of it in this House is extremely useful and adds to the strength of the argument which undoubtedly exists.  To reassure him and anyone who might think otherwise, I do not believe that the benefit of regional airports can be measured in the annual profit and loss accounts or balance sheets alone.  I know there is a serious regional benefit for the whole locality in Waterford Airport and in other airports as well.</p> <p>My Department has, for many years, operated a programme of support for our regional airports, including Waterford Airport, with substantial levels of funding provided in recognition of their contribution to balanced regional development.  The latest iteration of this programme covers the five-year period 2015 to 2019 and was approved in August last year by the EU Commission as being in conformity with its 2014 guidelines on state aid to airports and airlines.</p> <p>The national aviation policy, which was published by my Department last year, acknowledges the role played by the regional airports in Donegal, Ireland West Airport Knock, Kerry and Waterford in promoting a level of international connectivity to support the tourism and business sectors in the regions in which they are located.  I should also mention that an extra &euro;10 million in capital funding is being provided in the programme for Government for the regional airports.  This is additional to the &euro;28 million already provided for this purpose in the capital plan 2016 to 2022 and will enhance my Department's ability to further support the four airports.</p> <p>In terms of capital support, my Department's regional airports programme provides Exchequer funding to the four regional airports to assist them with implementing necessary safety and security related projects, including measures in these two areas that are requisite to comply with regulatory requirements.  The funding that is provided by my Department for such safety and security purposes is vital for these smaller airports and it is no exaggeration to say that without this Exchequer support, the airports would almost certainly be unable to continue to facilitate scheduled passenger services.  In the past five years, Waterford Airport has received &euro;9.6 million in operational and investment support from my Department.  In April of this year, a further &euro;157,500 in grant aid was approved for a number of security projects, including new X-ray equipment, at Waterford Airport.</p> <p>While our support programme for safety and security measures is important to the airports, it does not extend to investing in new capacity or expansions in airport infrastructure.  The Exchequer is not in the business of investing in airports for development purposes and has not engaged in such investment, whether at State airports or regional airports.  However regrettable, decisions of that nature - for example, in respect of extending a runway to cater for larger aircraft, expanding the capacity of a terminal building or building a new car park - are commercial matters for airport authorities.  I am aware that the authorities at Waterford Airport have ambitions to extend the runway there and I understand that they are pursuing local interests for funding in respect of these plans.  I will give them all possible encouragement.</p> <p>I was disappointed to hear last week that VLM Airlines, the only remaining commercial operator using the airport, has now withdrawn its London-Luton service.  VLM also withdrew from another route last month.  However, I understand that the airport is in detailed discussions with a number of airlines with a view to securing a replacement carrier.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1422" speakername="Paudie Coffey" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#C00300"><p>I acknowledge the Government support that has existed in recent years.  I was closely involved in ensuring - in conjunction with the Minister's predecessors - that grant assistance was in place for the past five years.  I am also conscious of the efforts of the Minister of State, Deputy Halligan, and am working with him on this matter.  I know that this is also a matter of deep interest to my colleague, Senator Grace O'Sullivan, who is present in the House.  We, as Oireachtas Members from Waterford and the south-east region, want to work with the Minister.  He is correct that the board of management and the management team at Waterford Airport have already undertaken big advances in terms of obtaining compulsory purchase orders on land for the runway extension.  They have the support of the local authorities in the region, which have put their money where their mouth is to support the airport.  They are also actively out there with business and commercial interests raising funding to ensure that this runway extension is delivered.</p> <p>Having said that, we still need support from the Minister and his Department.  He is right in saying that this is not just about the balance sheet.  This concerns the knock-on economic benefits that access brings to a region.  I have mentioned some of the jewels in the crown in the Waterford area.  They are to be found throughout the south east.  Ireland's Ancient East is a programme that is being run by the Minister and his Department.  Waterford city and county, as well as the region, will play a major role in emulating, in a different way, the economic benefit the Wild Atlantic Way has brought to the west.  We need to do the same in the east and south east and Waterford Airport is a critical component in that effort.</p> <p>We look forward to working with the Minister to try to advance what are not just local interests but regional and national interests also for the benefit of the economic activity of our regions.  As my colleague has said and as many colleagues in this House will continue to say, we need to develop critical infrastructure in our regions if we are going to lock their inherent potential.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#C00400"><p>Does the Minister wish to add anything?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#C00500"><p>I assure Senator Coffey that I am sympathetic to everything he said.  He must realise the restrictions under which we work.  He will, as a previous Minister of State, be aware of those restrictions.  These are not just the restrictions of the Exchequer but also, particularly, the rules about state aid under which we work as well.  We have to abide by them.  Deputy Halligan has asked me to visit the airport and I am willing to go and have a look.  I will inform the Senator when I am going of course.  I am very wiling to explore what avenues are open to us to ensure that those types of crises which Waterford Airport met in recent few weeks on foot of VLM's decision are not repeated.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.27" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#C00600">Hospital Services</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#C00700"><p>The next matter is in the name of Senator Terry Leyden.  We will wait for the Minister of State, Deputy McEntee, who is due to come in to take it.  I thank the Minister, Deputy Ross, for his visit.  I now welcome the Minister of State, Deputy McEntee, to the House and wish her luck with her new brief and I wish her well in her political career.  Senator Leyden has four minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#C00800"><p>I wish to clear up a misunderstanding that occurred yesterday morning.  I felt that this matter would have been taken yesterday but I received texts, which I had not read at that stage, to the effect that it would be taken today.  When it was not read out yesterday, I got the impression that it would not be included.  I apologise to the Clerk if there was any misunderstanding.  It was not intentional on my part.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#C00900"><p>The Senator is human.  Once he has sorted it out with the Clerk, we will move on.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#C01000"><p>We did sort it out.</p> <p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy McEntee, and congratulate her on her appointment.  That said, I was expecting the Minister for Health, Deputy Harris, to be here.  I know the Cathaoirleach and the Leader cannot dictate this, but I would like assurances that when a matter goes to the Minster with responsibility for the overall situation, he should be here unless there is good reason for him not being present.  It is not fair to send new Ministers of State into this House on issues such as this when they are not in a position to give a definitive response to any supplementary question.  That said, I welcome the Minister of State and wish her a successful career in the Department.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Terry Leyden:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=636"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=636&amp;amp;pid=TerryLeyden&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I was there for a period and I hope that she receives proper delegation of authority and responsibility, delegated and signed by the Minister, unlike in the past when no delegations were made.  Ministers had full responsibility and did not delegate any responsibility to Ministers of State.  That is very important and all Ministers of State should insist on that and have their delegated responsibilities signed off and approved by the Government.  <br/><br/>I raise the issue of the withdrawal of approximately &euro;8 million for a rehabilitation unit at Roscommon University Hospital.  In a statement published in the <i>Roscommon People </i>on 3 June 2016, Dr. Gerry O'Mara, a consultant geriatrician at the hospital stated, &quot;I believe that if this project does not go ahead, this hospital will eventually lose its inpatient beds and be allowed to wither.&quot;<br/><br/>It was announced in May 2015 that the Health Service Executive, HSE, had approved &euro;7.85 million to build a ten-bed unit which would operate as a satellite centre for the National Rehabilitation Hospital in D&uacute;n Laoghaire.  Now the HSE has stated that due to funding constraints and competing priorities, no funding can be allocated to this project in 2016.  The executive confirmed that funding for the unit was included in the 2016-21 capital programme and that it was not intended to commence this project until later in that programme.  <br/><br/>Roscommon lost its year-round, 24-hour accident and emergency unit.  By way of compensation it gained a new endoscopy unit which has been partially opened and is very welcome.  However, the loss of the accident and emergency department was a disaster for Roscommon University Hospital and represents a broken promise by the Taoiseach, Deputy Enda Kenny, and the former Minister for Health, Senator James Reilly.  That promise, made prior to the general election of 2011, resulted in a reward of two seats for Fine Gael in the constituency of Roscommon-South Leitrim.  It is most regrettable that the accident and emergency department is now being pushed aside completely and was not included in the new programme for Government.  The restoration of the accident and emergency service at Roscommon's acute hospital has been sacrificed for seats at Cabinet and other positions.  The people of Roscommon will never forgive or forget those who set out to destroy the future of Roscommon University Hospital.  I have stood by that hospital through thick and thin.  During my period in office, we held on to the accident and emergency department.  Accident and emergency departments are at the heart of any hospital, maintaining a throughput of patients.  We need to ensure that we restore the accident and emergency service at Roscommon University Hospital.  I commend those people who have protested every Saturday, in all weathers, at the loss of the accident and emergency unit in 2011.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1337" speakername="Helen McEntee" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#D00200"><p>I congratulate the Cathaoirleach on his new role and wish every Senator well in this term.  I hope, like my colleague the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Ross, to be here for the next five years to engage and debate with Members of Seanad &Eacute;ireann.</p> <p>I thank the Senator for raising this issue, which I know is very important to him.  The Minister for Health, Deputy Harris, sends his apologies and hopes to engage with the Senator on this matter at a later date.  Roscommon University Hospital is a model 2 hospital within the Saolta University Health Care Group.  It provides a significant range of hospital services to patients in the region including extended day surgery, certain acute medicine services and local injuries services.  It also provides a wide array of diagnostic services including endoscopy, laboratory medicine, point of care testing and radiology, as well as specialist rehabilitation medicine and palliative care.  The hospital has 86 inpatient beds and includes an acute mental health unit.</p> <p>Roscommon University Hospital plays an essential role as part of the Saolta group of hospitals and will continue to do so into the future.  We know that the future growth in health care will be in the areas of chronic disease management, day surgery, diagnostics and rehabilitation.  The activity levels of model 2 hospitals such as Roscommon University Hospital will continue to increase over the coming years as these hospitals specialise in providing these services to meet the needs of their local populations.</p> <p>A new endoscopy unit at the hospital opened on a phased basis on 1 June 2016.  When fully operational, all endoscopy procedures will be carried out in the new unit, freeing up theatre capacity for more day surgery cases to be carried out in Roscommon.  The official opening of the unit will take place later this year and I am sure Senator Leyden will attend, along with many colleagues.</p> <p>The specialist rehabilitation unit planned for Roscommon University Hospital was one of the many projects in the HSE multi-annual capital plan 2015 to 2019 and internal HSE approval was granted to progress the development of the unit in 2015.  The spatial plan for the hospital was approved in the first quarter of 2016 and the project team, comprising hospital, clinical and estates personnel, is currently being assembled.  Following this work by the project team, the project will move to the next stage.  The HSE has advised the Department of Health that funding for the project would be considered in the 2017 to 2021 multi-annual period.  It is my expectation that every effort will be made to fund this project as early as possible in that time period.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#D00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State for her reply and thank her for her interest in Roscommon, where she will always be welcome.  I ask her to take a personal interest in this particular issue and should she do so, I would have confidence that the project will commence in 2017.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.35" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 11.10 a.m. and resumed at 11.30 a.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.36" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#G00100">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#G00200"><p>I call the Seanad to order.  Although not everyone is present, I have a couple of suggestions because as it happened yesterday, the Order of Business was cumbersome in many ways and went on for too long.  While we must sort it out in the Committee on Procedure and Privileges, I suggest the Order of Business should not last for more than one hour.  I am simply thinking out loud and I am not dictating or imposing or anything like that, but I have a notion regarding the rota of speakers.  The leader from each group, for example, would be a speaker each day but then, because Fine Gael is the biggest, the Government side might have at least four speakers with the Leader, and then perhaps three speakers with the leader for Fianna F&aacute;il and different groups.  Moreover, these could rotate if someone has something to say.  At present, the leaders have three minutes to speak and perhaps by readjusting, the leaders would have four minutes on some important issues about which people are passionate.  People could rotate and Members would curtail it to have a more streamlined and focused Order of Business rather than having everyone hopping up and down or whatever.  While my style is not to stymie any debate, at the same time, had there been a Minister waiting in the ante-room yesterday with important legislation, he or she would not have been happy with me for having, as we would say in west Cork, a leadr&aacute;nach Order of Business.  That said, I will now ask the Leader to outline the business for today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#G00300"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, statements on delivering sustainable full employment, to be taken at 12.45 p.m. and to adjourn no later than 2.15 p.m., with contributions from all Senators not to exceed six minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#G00400"><p>First, I congratulate Senator Paul Coghlan on his election yesterday as Leas-Chathaoirleach.  I know he will be a fair and prudent Chair like the Cathaoirleach.  I express my congratulations to him and his family.  I have known one of his daughters, Aoife, for a long time as I was in the Gaeltacht with her almost 20 years ago.</p> <p>I also wish to address the House regarding the tragic death of a nurse in Our Lady's Children's Hospital, Crumlin.  While the matter is being looked into by An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, I express my sympathy and that of the Fianna F&aacute;il to her work colleagues and family.</p> <p>There is a growing sense of fear and frustration among families about reports that bin charges could be on the rise again from 1 July.  Any rise in charges is a struggle nowadays as people are still doing their utmost to pay their mortgage and other bills.  The policy change agreed by the former Minister, Deputy Kelly, to pay by weight could result in charges increasing from &euro;200 to &euro;400 per year.  This is unrealistic and completely unfair.  Last January, the former Minister, Deputy Kelly, had the audacity to state the pay-by-weight system would realise savings of 87% to customers.  Instead, they face a doubling of bin charges.  Unless action is taken now, Members will face a situation that could quickly become uncontrollable.  Waste will be disposed of illegally and there will be chaos in respect of payments.  People are being faced with a double whammy of standard fees being increased under the pay-by-weight system, which will add extra costs.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#G00500"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#G00600"><p>The reaction on Joe Duffy's radio show in recent days has been from reasonable people who have genuine concerns and lectures on competition will not resolve this issue.  There are no exemptions for low-income households, the infirm or people with young children.  In today's edition of <i>The Irish Times</i>, Miriam Lord described it as &quot;the wheelie bins are coming&quot;.  Unless the Minister, Deputy Coveney, takes immediate action to address the genuine concerns, people will be faced with marches on the streets and more people being unable to pay bin charges in respect of which they have been co-operating in recent years.  The pay-by-weight system will penalise families with young children, particularly those who are in the nappy stage, and families tend to have more rubbish anyway.  Options for recycling already have dwindled in the city and there are no substantial plans to bring in an education system to advise people on how to keep their waste to a minimum.  The Government must listen to the concerns and must not keep ignoring the problem in the hope it will go away, as it will not.  I call on the Minister, Deputy Coveney, to come to the House to explain what actions he intends to take to address this problem and to address the exorbitant bin charges that are being sold to Members as climate change measures.  Personally, I do not buy that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#G00700"><p>I thank Senator Ardagh and call Senator Craughwell.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#H00100"><p>Will the Leader indicate when it is proposed to take No. 6.2, which is the motion on city and county councillors?  I hope that debate will not be partisan on any side.  All of us are equally committed.  Yesterday, along with a number of Senators, I met with AILG, which is seeking a timeline for when its concerns will be addressed.  I am open to any suggestion in that regard but I would like to be able to report back that a timeline in terms of when the matter will be dealt with has been agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#H00200"><p>I congratulate Senators O'Donovan and Coghlan on their appointments as Cathaoirleach and Leas-Chathaoirleach, respectively.  I also congratulate Senator Jerry Buttimer and all the other leaders on their appointments as group leaders.  This is my first time as a Member of the Seanad.  I get the sense that there will be a great degree of working together and consensus in this Seanad, which is welcome.</p> <p>The Public Health (Alcohol) Bill approved by the previous Government last December provides for minimum pricing and health labelling of alcohol products and so on.  During the last D&aacute;il I was Chairman of the Joint Committee on Transport, Tourism and Sport which published a report on sports sponsorship and so on.  There is a need to progress the Public Health (Alcohol) Bill and, in terms of a sponsorship, a need to identify other streams of funding for sporting bodies.  In that context, I welcome the announcement yesterday by the Minister of State, Deputy Patrick O'Donovan, of a &euro;1 million fund for the Camogie Association and the Ladies Gaelic Football Association in respect of training and so on, which is an indication of equality of provision in the sports area.  Had the Government not provided that funding those organisations would have had to seek it elsewhere.  </p> <p>Will the Leader invite the relevant Minister to this House to provide us with an update on the progress of the Public Health (Alcohol) Bill?  I am aware that there are obstacles in that regard from a European point of view but I would very much welcome an update on the issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#H00300"><p>On behalf of the Sinn F&eacute;in group I, too, extend sympathy to the nurse who tragically lost her life in Crumlin hospital.</p> <p>I also wish to raise the issue of bin charges and the anxiety being caused by the proposed increases in that regard.  I suppose this was to be expected once the decision to privatise such an essential service was made.  The chickens are now coming home to roost in that regard.  Citizens need to be protected from the folly of that privatisation and what it will bring, as happened in the case of the privatisation of Eircom, our main communications company.  </p> <p>I draw the attention of the House to No. 6.1 on the Order Paper, which deals with Seanad reform, the rationale for which I would like to explain.  The motion seeks the establishment of a time limited committee and commends the report of the working group on Seanad reform.  In this regard, we were happy yesterday to support the Bill tabled by the Independent Group.</p> <p>There are two key reasons we are of the opinion that a committee on Seanad reform needs to be established and tasked to come back to the floor of the Seanad with its recommendations within six weeks.  First, there are 42 new Senators in this Seanad.  We believe it is important that those new voices be heard and have ownership of the reform process.  Second, there is a need for the Seanad to be distinctive from the D&aacute;il and to play a key role in the scrutiny of European policies and directives as well as the North-South initiatives that permeate throughout the report.  We agree with this but we are concerned that the Bill put forward does not reflect this.  In particular, we are concerned about the absence of speaking rights for MEPs and MLAs and believe that this needs to be examined.  We are mindful of the major failings of all previous Seanad reports, which never reached implementation stage.  Notwithstanding this, we believe that a time limited committee, as described in the motion, would enhance the final outcome in an inclusive and collaborative way.  We ask, therefore, that motion No. 6.1 be taken next week.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#H00400"><p>I join with other speakers in congratulating the Cathaoirleach and Leas-Cathaoirleach on their appointments.</p> <p>In terms of today's Order of Business, there are two issues I would like to highlight.  The Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation will be in the Seanad today for a debate on sustainable full employment.  I express the hope that we will also hear during that debate about proposed legislative measures to reflect the recently agreed Labour Party motion in the D&aacute;il on employment issues such as if-and-when contracts, protection in cases of insolvencies and, crucially - given the process of development of our public procurement policies in terms of our trade agreements such as CETA and TTIP - protection of employment standards within public procurement.  These are legislative issues which we know are on the table.  I look forward to us having the opportunity to speak again to the Minister on these types of concrete measures and the need to move forward on them.</p> <p>Today is Bloomsday.  It is a day in which Ireland's arts, heritage and culture are celebrated across the world.  I am sure others will speak more knowledgeably on that issue.  It is important that on this day we address the wide concern expressed in regard to what has been perceived as a roll-back on the commitment to the arts.  It is unfortunate in the context of the future debate on the heritage Bill that the term "heritage" is not reflected in the title of any Department.  Ireland lags behind the rest of Europe in terms of its funding for the arts.  We need to move towards an 0.6% average, which is the average across Europe, as opposed to the 0.3% which currently applies.  I urge the Leader to inquire of the Minister what opportunities the Seanad may have to engage around Culture 2025, plans around our sustainable development goals and the right to cultural participation.  I look forward to having an opportunity in the future to discuss those issues with the Minister. </p> <p>I am slightly concerned about the proposed change to Standing Orders.  I believe the current system, which allows for a diversity of voices to be heard, is important.  I am sure we will have an opportunity to discuss this further through the appropriate channels.  I support the idea of the imposition of a one-hour limit on the debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#H00500"><p>As this is my first time to speak in the Seanad I take this opportunity to congratulate the Cathaoirleach and Leas-Chathaoirleach on their appointments.  I also congratulate Senators Buttimer and Ardagh on their appointments as group leaders.</p> <p>As stated by Senator Higgins, today is Bloomsday.  It is also the first anniversary of the tragic accident that occurred in Berkeley last year.  As a House, we should remember those who died on that day and those who were seriously injured.  There were six fatalities, Eimear Walsh, Olivia Burke, Ashley Donohue, Niccolai Schuster, Eoghan Culligan and Lorc&aacute;n Miller and many serious casualties, including Jack Halpin, Clodagh Cogley, Aoife Beary, Sean Fahey, Conor Flynn, Niall Murray and Hannah Waters.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Gerry Horkan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2476"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2476&amp;amp;pid=GerryHorkan&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is important to remember those who died or were injured and their families and friends.  It was a very tragic day last year, particularly for the area I represent in D&uacute;n Laoghaire.  I apologise to Senator Craughwell if I am being parochial but it was a national tragedy for all these young people who left Ireland for the summer on J1 visas to experience a different culture and earn some money before returning to college.  Some of them did not make it back alive.  It would be good for this House to remember that on the anniversary, as the day was very dark for south Dublin and the country in general.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#J00200"><p>I sound a warning about reform of the Seanad.  I heard this morning about the question of European Union scrutiny.  At our small meeting, I warned about this as it is extremely dangerous.  People are given the impression that the legislation of the European Union will be scrutinised without it being clearly defined.  There is an enormous amount of material spewed out every week from Europe so if we set ourselves up as monitor and watchdog, we will fail and the public will rub our noses in that failure.  The other issue is speaking rights.  Elected Members of this House have speaking rights and others can and should be invited; they do not have speaking rights.</p><p>It is Bloomsday and it is wonderful.  I have been to three or four events already and the whole city is throbbing with energy.  So many places not mentioned in <i>Ulysses</i>have little groups of people with straw boaters and actors performing.  We had the Lord Mayor at our breakfast in the James Joyce Centre and I was at the wonderful Westland Row community breakfast before going to Sandymount Green.  Joyce's power of reputation helped to save North Great George's Street, as one of the crucial buildings there, No. 35, was identified and it is now the centre of the Joycean m&eacute;nage throughout Dublin.</p><p>That brings me to the inner city.  I note the Taoiseach, Deputy Enda Kenny, spent some time in the inner city and I very much welcome that.  It is about bloody time.  The north inner city of Dublin has been grotesquely neglected throughout my entire lifetime, including when the Prime Minister of this country, former Deputy Bertie Ahern, represented the constituency and did sweet damn all for it.  Apparently, the Minister responsible for tourism, transport and whatever else you are having has decided to demand that Stepaside police station be reopened - this is on the agenda.  I would like to hear it for Fitzgibbon Street.  I was lied to in this House about Fitzgibbon Street Garda station as I was told it was being closed for refurbishment.  Rubbish.  They closed it down.  Now there are murders every second day of the week and a drugs problem in the north inner city.  We are down 136 garda&iacute; and something must be done about that.  What about the stripping of every decent thing from the north inner city and its replacement with down-market drug clinics that they would not have in Ballsbridge or the affluent suburbs of the country.</p><p>Mr. Tony Gregory was a great friend of mine and I remember when he initiated the whole Criminal Assets Bureau, CAB, business.  He did not call it CAB but he said something had to be done to link income tax collection, social welfare and the Garda.  Essentially, that was realised with CAB.  After Veronica Guerin was shot, the Government took the idea and claimed credit for it.  I made sure in this House that Mr. Gregory was remembered.  I put it forward in this House, in concert with Mr. Gregory in the D&aacute;il, and I asked that the money taken by CAB should be reinvested in employment, housing and education in the north inner city.  It should be ring-fenced as the money was bled from the veins of the most vulnerable people in the north inner city.  The Department of Finance squashed that.  It is time to put major reinvestment into the north inner city.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#J00300"><p>The Senator is blooming today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#J00400"><p>Minus the straw boater.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#J00500"><p>There was an old defence in law, long abolished, that if a person was caught in a pub or hostelry more than three miles from home, he or she was a bona fide traveller.  There is one man I will call next because he is a bona fide traveller; his home is the furthest from this House.  It is against the rules somewhat but I will allow the Senator speak for a minute.  I know he is facing surgery as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1429" speakername="Billy Lawless" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#J00600"><p>I reiterate that we should remember today the terrible tragedy that occurred in Berkeley last year.  It would be every parent's nightmare, of course, when their children go to the United States for summer employment on J1 visas.  We all get calls and everybody tries to help.  I compliment the Irish centres and especially those in California that rallied around parents when they came out last year after those people were killed and injured.  These Irish centres deserve incredible support.  Senators may know there are problems with the J1 programme this year as students must be pre-employed before they are issued with visas.  That is wrong and, from what I gather, the process was initiated by one or two agencies.  I do not believe what they are doing is legal and I am certainly looking into it.  That is a matter for further debate at some stage.</p><p>I will read a letter I received last night into the record.  It is from the White and it states:</p><blockquote>Dear Billy,<br /><br />Please accept my congratulations on your appointment to the Seanad.<br /><br />As I have noted before, your story is a powerful one and it reflects the enduring ties of friendship between the peoples of the United States and Ireland.  In beginning this new chapter, I trust you will reflect on all that has led you to this point with tremendous pride.<br /><br />Again, congratulations.  You, Anne and Billy have my warm regards,<br /><br />Sincerely,</blockquote> <p>It is signed by President Barack Obama.  I read this not for self-congratulation but to highlight the importance of the ties between the United States and us.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#J00700"><p>Ag lean&uacute;int, ar bhealach, leis an t&eacute;ama sin, ba mhaith liom a bheith ceangailte leis na moth&uacute;ch&aacute;in at&aacute; luaite ag na Seanad&oacute;ir&iacute; Horkan agus Lawless maidir leis an dream &oacute;g a mara&iacute;odh i Berkeley agus an dream &oacute;g a d'fhulaing i Berkeley agus an dream ar fad timpeall orthu a thug taca&iacute;ocht agus mar sin d&oacute;ibh.</p> <p>It would be very good to have a debate on the diaspora and I agree with Senator Lawless that there are concerns around the reform of the J1 visa programme.  I was concerned by statements made by the Minister of State, Deputy McHugh, about cherry-picking the emigrants he wants to attract back to Ireland.  If there is a pick-up in the economy, as we are told, it is important that people are invited and encouraged to come back and that we make the environment suitable for that to happen.  I am concerned that the Minister of State was speaking about cherry-picking engineers and professional people with degrees, etc.  Our diaspora is so diverse, and there are so many people across the globe, that there are many issues that must be discussed in the area.  It would be good to see his vision for the role.  There are serious matters such as representation in the Houses, voting rights and how we work to help the undocumented abroad, etc.  Irish people abroad need us to address issues of that nature in the House.  It is good to have Senator Lawless here to represent that cohort.  I know there are many groups outside the House that are regularly in contact with us and a debate on issues concerning the diaspora would be very pertinent.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#J00800"><p>Today is Bloomsday and I note Senator Norris, a great Joycean scholar, has left the Chamber.  I add my voice to that of Senator Higgins on the status of arts in Ireland, particularly with the perceived, if not real, downgrading of the arts from a department structure perspective.  There is a lack of a Minister of State with responsibility for arts in the Department.  Even with the Taoiseach's nominees to this House, five years ago, Fiach Mac Conghail, the director of the Abbey Theatre, took up a role here and added greatly to the debate on the cultural importance of the sector to social and political life.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2301"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2301&amp;amp;pid=AodhanORiordan&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->That is also an omission.  Could the Leader invite the Minister to come to the House to discuss arts funding and the importance of the arts?  We are the only country in the world that has a musical instrument as its national symbol.  While we often view the arts and cultural life as being somewhat of a luxury, from my work in the equality field, I know those on the edges of society often do not have any other means of expressing the lives they lead and the trials and tribulations they go through.  The only way they can do that is through the arts.  </p><p>Following on from what Senator Ardagh outlined earlier, there is quite a level of unease and disquiet around the issue of waste charges.  I heard on the radio this morning that the Minister intends to meet with various private sector companies in respect of this issue next week.  It would be a good idea to have a calm debate on the floor of this House on what the situation is because when there is a vacuum, fears can be raised.  As Senator Ardagh rightly said, people have fears regarding how they can meet bills as the situation continues.  I hope we can progress the issue of the arts and their importance to this country.  I hope we can get clarity regarding the situation around waste charges and to this end, we should invite the Minister to come to the House to further that debate.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1399" speakername="Neale Richmond" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#K00200"><p>Keeping to the cultural theme, I wish the House a happy Bloomsday, particularly Senator Norris who has moved on from this morning.  Like every football fan on this island, I am delighted to see both Irish teams competing in the European Championships this year.  To qualify in the first place was a massive achievement and although both teams are playing well, we are still awaiting a first win.  I hope it comes tonight for Northern Ireland against Ukraine.  That said, I cannot help thinking how much stronger an all-Ireland football team and indeed an all-Ireland football association could be with the likes of Kyle Lafferty and Shane Long playing alongside each other and, more important, the pooling of grass-roots resources into a united effort to get more boys and girls off the couch and on to the sports field.  With a lifetime involvement in many sports, I have seen at first hand the benefits of cross-Border co-operation in sport, whether it was playing schoolboy rugby matches in Belfast or a more recent visit to Craigavon to play American football of all things.  Sport is always the winner and one of the best tools to break down many barriers.  The exemplary behaviour of both sets of Irish fans, including Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in, at the weekend, has been heartening against the background of hooliganism over the weekend in Marseilles and, unfortunately, again last night in Lille.  The tribute paid by fans at the game against Sweden on Monday following the tragic death of Ballymena man Darren Rodgers was not just fitting but very moving.  It shows how far both sets of fans have come since the dark days of the Troubles, days when my late father and his friends were afraid to cheer Gerry Armstrong's goal against Spain in 1982 in a Dublin pub for fear of abuse and when Republic of Ireland fans dreaded the sectarian atmosphere of Windsor Park.  Those days, thankfully, are passing, if not completely passed.  The issue has been raised by in the previous Seanad by Senator Noone and former Senator, Paul Bradford.  </p> <p>With a new Government in place, I ask the Leader to call on the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, who is a keen football fan, to engage with us in the Seanad and talk to his Northern counterpart as well the CEOs of both football associations to build on the progress of the Setanta Cup and to follow the example of the GAA's international rules team, the Irish rugby team which had a great win at the weekend, the Irish hockey team which will be going to Rio de Janeiro for the first time and the Irish cricket team which is currently battling the showers against Sri Lanka in Malahide.  Let us merge our two football teams and every sports team on the island to put Ireland on the strongest possible footing in every sporting contest.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#K00300"><p>I received two letters and three telephone calls in the past two days relating to the National Rehabilitation Hospital in D&uacute;n Laoghaire.  It has been said on numerous occasions that a totally new hospital was to be built there.  It was then said that there were setbacks and that it was to be an extension.  On his next visit to the House, could the Minister for Health give us a comprehensive update on the suggestion in the last few days at the hospital that it will be delayed to 2017 and that it will be a much modified scheme?  The staff and the people who run the hospital are unhappy and there needs to be greater clarity about this major project.  I would appreciate it if the Minister could address it when he next visits the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1408" speakername="Frances Black" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#K00400"><p>I welcome Senator O'Mahony's remarks about the Public Health (Alcohol) Bill.  It is great to see movement on the Public Health (Alcohol) Bill considering it has been seven years in the making.  Back in December 2009, alcohol was included in a national substance misuse strategy.  In those seven years, we have failed our fellow citizens by allowing alcohol misuse to be an acceptable part of our culture.  This Bill will go a long way towards helping to change our attitudes and relationships with alcohol.  On a daily basis, I see the mental health issues, devastation and heartbreak caused to families all over this country.  We must remember that we are enacting this Bill to protect them and future generations.  It is important to know how much we are drinking if we are trying to stay within the low-risk weekly guidelines for alcohol consumption and it becomes even more important to track our alcohol intake when one considers that the most comprehensive survey of alcohol consumption ever carried out in Ireland revealed that we underestimate what we drink by about 60%.</p> <p>Alcohol marketing, including advertising, sponsorship and other forms of promotion, increases the likelihood that adolescents will start to use alcohol and drink more if they are already using alcohol.  Young people&rsquo;s drinking patterns have a direct effect on their health, development and welfare.  Therefore, reducing children&rsquo;s exposure to alcohol marketing is a child protection issue.  Yet every day, in numerous ways and through numerous media, children and young people in Ireland are continually exposed to positive, risk-free images of alcohol and its use.  Due to a lack of effective regulations, young people are poorly protected from these sophisticated and powerful influences on their drinking behaviour and expectations.  They are bombarded with positive images of alcohol through the marketing of brands and products.  In effect, the alcohol industry has become a child's primary educator on alcohol.  Marketing can shape youth culture by creating and sustaining expectations and norms about how to achieve social, sporting or sexual success; how to celebrate; how to relax; and how to belong.  The failure to protect children from exposure to alcohol marketing is associated with earlier and increased alcohol consumption.  Restricting advertisements for alcohol products to content about the nature of products will mean that advertisements will be less likely to glamorise alcohol or make it appealing to children as they will no longer see alcohol products aligned with physical performance, personal success, social success and a variety of other positive outcomes.</p> <p>Minimum unit pricing is a targeted measure designed to stop strong alcohol being sold at very low prices in the off-trade, particularly supermarkets, where alcohol is frequently used as a "loss leader" and sold below cost.  The easy and widespread availability of such cheap alcohol has contributed to a dramatic shift in our alcohol purchasing and consumption habits from pubs towards the off-trade sector, which now accounts for the majority of alcohol sold in Ireland.  Minimum unit pricing is able to target cheaper alcohol relative to its strength because the price is determined by and directly proportionate to the amount of pure alcohol in the drink.  Minimum unit pricing would be effective in reducing alcohol consumption; alcohol harms, including deaths, hospital admissions, crime and workplace absences; and the costs associated with those harms.  The analysis estimated that with a &euro;1 minimum unit pricing, alcohol-attributable deaths would be reduced by approximately 197 per year in Ireland after 20 years, by which time the full effects of the policy will be seen due to the time lag involved with many serious alcohol-related illnesses, such as liver cirrhosis and alcohol-related cancers.  We would also see almost 6,000 fewer hospital admissions per year and a reduction in alcohol-fuelled crime and workplace absences while the total societal value of these reductions in health, crime and workplace harms is estimated at &euro;1.7 billion.</p> <p>The alcohol companies will lobby to change the core elements of this Bill.  We need to listen to words of warning from Dr. Margaret Chan, director general of the World Health Organization, WHO, when in April 2013, she stated that he development of alcohol policies is the sole prerogative of national authorities.  She said that in the view of WHO, the alcohol industry has no role in the formula of alcohol policies, which must be protected from distortion by commercial or vested interests.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Frances Black:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2474"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2474&amp;amp;pid=FrancesBlack&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> I would welcome the enactment of the Bill by both Houses without the undue influence of the alcohol industry.  We need to do this for the well-being of our fellow citizens, for the future of our country and to ensure a reduction of the impact that alcohol has on families across the country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#L00200"><p>As Senators know, this is carers' week.  A very important contribution to care is the assistance provided by the private nursing sector.  Nursing Homes Ireland made a presentation yesterday.  Unproductive meetings are one of the issues that the organisation has raised with me, which I am sure it has raised with other Oireachtas Members.  When its members meet the Department of Health to discuss something they are advised that the matter is one for the HSE, but when they meet the HSE they are advised that the matter is one for the Department.  NHI has suggested - I have raised this matter previously - that a forum be set up to ensure there is clear communication.  When the organisation meets the Department it wants to also meet the HSE, the IMO and the INMO in order to deal with all of the issues.  The NHI also wants a formal structure set up to deal with care of the elderly, not just with regard to nursing homes but also associated areas such as delayed discharges in hospitals.  A forum would ensure that all of the issues could be dealt with.  It might only meet every four or six months but it would ensure the attendance of all of the people involved in providing elderly care.  Even though I have already brought the matter to the attention of the Minister for Health, I ask the Leader to do the same because I want the issue to form part of the debate on health and long-term planning.</p> <p>The provision of elderly care will be challenging over the next 15 years because the number of people over the age of 65 will increase from 600,000 to over 1 million by 2031.  Therefore, we need to ensure that we provide services sufficient to meet these challenges.</p> <p>Let me state another important figure.  At present, 51% of all hospital beds are occupied by people over the age of 65, which poses a challenge, particularly with a growing elderly population.  We must provide more services in order to tackle the discharge process in hospitals.  We need to debate this important issue.  I ask that the Minister, his Department and the HSE work together and take this challenge on board rather than continue with the constant buck-passing that has gone on for years.  We need to create an efficient and effective service but we can only do so by working together.  I ask the Leader to bring this matter to the attention of the Minister for Health and I want it to form part of our future debate with him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1431" speakername="P&aacute;draig &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#L00300"><p>T&aacute; mise ag iarraidh labhairt ar feadh c&uacute;pla n&oacute;im&eacute;ad mar gheall ar ch&uacute;rsa&iacute; fiontra&iacute;ochta, entrepreneurship.</p> <p>I ask the Leader to invite the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation to come in here to discuss two main topics.  The first is that of small businesses.  There are more than 200,000 SMEs in Ireland and they represent 99% of all businesses here.  They employ approximately 74% of the private sector, which is a very significant body.  There is significant support available in the form of advice and mentoring if one is an exporter, but support is not all about finance.  Exports constitute an important sector for us, but a small one.  The vast majority of small and medium-sized businesses do not export.  I want the Minister to have an opportunity to speak to us and outline his vision and strategy for small businesses that do not export.  </p> <p>There is a second matter.  I am not sure whether we can invite someone to the House, as I am new here.  Can we invite Mr. M&aacute;irt&iacute;n &Oacute; Muilleoir. the new Minister for Finance in Northern Ireland, to address the House?  He is an entrepreneur who has created businesses and is very much involved in the community.  From my perspective and knowledge of enterprise and entrepreneurship in Ireland, I know that the relationship between entrepreneurs in the North and South is hugely important.  A fair amount of business takes place between entrepreneurs on both sides of this island of ours.  I ask the Leader to invite the Minister for Finance in Northern Ireland to come here to inform Senators about strategies for entrepreneurs in the North.  As it happens, I will meet him next Wednesday morning to discuss this sector and I believe the meeting will prove helpful.  It would be a big step forward if this House could invite such people to address us, particularly when we have a very strong common interest.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#L00400"><p>I call Senator Butler, as I do not think he spoke yesterday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1423" speakername="Ray Butler" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#L00500"><p>I did not speak yesterday even though I had prepared a speech.  There was such a big crowd yesterday that I decided to hold off until today.</p><p>I would like to take this opportunity to congratulate the Irish team on its outstanding performance against Sweden on Monday in Paris and wish them continuing success in their next games.  I wish to acknowledge the tens of thousands of Irish football fans who have travelled to France for being incredible ambassadors for Ireland.  They have shown the world how to create and enjoy a positive, safe and fun atmosphere in which we can all join.  They have done us proud and I urge them to keep it up.</p><p>I wish to offer my sincere condolences to the family of Darren Rodgers, a Northern Ireland football fan from Ballymena who tragically lost his life over the weekend in Nice.  I also wish to express my deepest sympathies to the victims of the Orlando nightclub shooting whose lives were abruptly and brutally cut short.  There are no words of comfort for all the families who have lost their loved ones in this barbaric act of terrorism.  May they rest in peace.</p><p>Before I address my specific reason for speaking today, I wish to congratulate Senator Denis O'Donovan on being appointed Cathaoirleach, Senator Paul Coghlan on being appointed Leas-Chathaoirleach and Senator Jerry Buttimer on being appointed Leader of the House.  I also wish all of my colleagues in the Twenty-fifth Seanad a successful term ahead.</p><p>I am delighted that my first speech in the Twenty-fifth Seanad refers to statements made by the Minister for Health which were published last Tuesday and Thursday in the <i>Irish Independent</i>.  I welcome his statement that he plans to close the gap between the self-employed and PAYE workers.  Like many others in the Oireachtas, such as Senator Marie-Louise O'Donnell, I have campaigned about social protection and sought social welfare for the self-employed.  Over the past five years I have continuously campaigned in the Lower House, along with others, for the social welfare status of the self-employed to be addressed.  We are the only country in the industrialised Europe that does not provide social protection for the self-employed.  There are 330,000 self-employed people who have no protection in terms of social welfare.  If they get sick or suffer a disability in the morning they are entitled to nothing.  We had the Mangan report on social insurance in the Lower House during the five years that I was a Deputy, and I hope the report will be implemented.  Social welfare is a huge issue for the self-employed.  If we want people to create jobs and get people back to work then we need to put a safety net in place.  I will table a motion in the House that I hope will be supported by all parties.  I also hope all Senators will support the plans of the Minister for Health for the self-employed.  I call on the bigger unions that represent self-employed people to come on board.  The elephant in the room on the last occasion was whether to make the initiative mandatory or voluntary.  I suggest that it must be mandatory, because nothing in the social protection sphere works voluntarily.  I welcome the chance to speak today.  I will table a motion on this matter that I hope will be supported by everybody in the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#L00600"><p>I thank the Senator for his kind remarks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#L00700"><p>I welcome Bloomsday, which celebrates a great writer.  James Joyce's imagination and creativity made him an exile and he chose to live outside of this country.  His departure was a great loss to us, although he remembered Dublin.  Interestingly, it has been said that if Dublin was laid to waste, Ulysses could be used to reconstruct the city because it is so topographically and geographically correct.  I ask that we remember this great writer today.</p> <p>I would never presume anything about the background of any Senator because I have a great belief that when they join this Chamber they come with a wealth of knowledge and expertise.  I know Senator Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in is not here but I wish to point out that I come with a wealth of experience in the arts.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Marie-Louise O'Donnell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2390"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2390&amp;amp;pid=MarieLouiseODonnell&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I was reared, and have worked, in the arts.  There are young children in the Visitors Gallery today, who are very welcome, and I know that singing, dancing, drama, visual art and sport mean a great deal to them.  Many of them might go on to have a career in that area.  I worked from when I was a child in the arts, right up to being involved in Dublin City University, DCU, the Larkin concert series, artists in residence, arts in education and I know what the arts mean to culture and creativity and how they have a language above and beyond politics.  In Palestine, where there was terrible trauma and terror, I saw how the arts superseded that.  I wish to point out to Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in that the Taoiseach has a spokesman for the arts in the Seanad, one who is very vocal, perhaps verbose and very dramatic, although it is great to be a visual aid for one's subject.  I hope to continue to do that and to argue as a spokesman for the arts with all parties in the House in the future.  We should never presume about the expertise of whoever is sitting in front of or behind us or about what they bring to the House, as one can see with the new brilliance in backgrounds which the 42 new voices and faces have brought with them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#M00200"><p>It is obvious, Senator, that your long association and involvement with the arts stands you in good stead in the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#M00300"><p>I endorse the request to invite the North's Finance Minister, M&aacute;irt&iacute;n &Oacute; Muilleoir, to make a presentation to the House.  I have great personal admiration and respect for M&aacute;irt&iacute;n &Oacute; Muilleoir.  His passion for people, equality, investment and prosperity is palpable.  As a whirlwind of politics and human endeavour, it would be good to have him here.  Is Gael go smior &eacute; chomh maith.</p><p>Will the Leader of the House urgently invite the relevant Minister to the House to discuss the report by the Police Ombudsman for Northern Ireland, Dr. Michael Maguire, on the police investigation of the Loughinisland massacre?  I do not know if Members are familiar with the damning report published by Dr. Maguire on the police investigation into that atrocity.  When Loughinisland is mentioned it conjures up many images and memories for people.  I recall that our family was holidaying in Minerstown, which is approximately a 20 minute drive from Loughinisland, after enjoying the match like everybody else.  When word arrived, we were put in the car and taken home, such was the palpable fear that this was not the end of such events or that something equally bad or much worse was on the way.</p><p>When we say the word &quot;Loughinisland&quot; we might reflect on The Heights Bar, the image from outside the bar and on the fact that this week and over the coming weeks many of us will gather at home, in pubs and in clubs to watch and cheer on Ireland as the team progresses through another international tournament, just as the people in The Heights Bar were doing.  We think of the photographs of the six men who lost their lives: Adrian Rogan, aged 34; Malcolm Jenkinson, aged 54; Patrick O'Hare, aged 35; Eamon Byrne, aged 39; Daniel McCreanor aged 54, and his uncle, Barney Greene, aged 87.  They were slaughtered for their faith and their support for a team in a terrible time.</p><p>When I think of Loughinisland now, I think of the campaigning families of those men whose stand for justice and truth has been beyond admirable.  It has been extremely difficult for them.  They have faced obstacles and obstruction, but the report published by Dr. Maguire validates their stand.  Not only was there collusion and obstruction in the investigation into the event, but that collusion reached the highest level.  I will quote a brief paragraph from what is a long and frightening report on the institutional and deliberate failings in that investigation:</p><blockquote>I have found that Special Branch held intelligence that paramilitary informants were involved in a range of activities, including command and control of Loyalist paramilitaries; the procurement, importation and distribution of weapons; murder and conspiracy to murder.  They have not been subject to any meaningful criminal investigation.</blockquote> <p>It is incumbent on the Irish Government not just as a body that upholds the rights of Irish citizens, but also as a co-guarantor of the Good Friday Agreement, to take a clear, strong stand after the Fresh Start Agreement on the policy of the British Government in recent times to use national security as a veto to any further investigation or any truth recovery process.  This does not just apply to Loughinisland but also to Pat Finucane and any investigation of the Dublin and Monaghan bombings.  This should concern not only the Members of this House, but also the Government.  Given the severity of the report, I ask the Leader to respond as urgently as possible.  It was discussed in the D&aacute;il this week and it is incumbent on us to hear from the Minister what he can do to maintain the pressure and ensure that there is no such veto or that no shutter will be pulled down on a future investigation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#M00400"><p>Will the Leader invite the relevant Minister or Ministers to the House to address an issue that is close to the hearts of people from rural Ireland, the cuts in funding for regional local roads?  Thankfully, in recent years, a great deal of money has been spent on the surfacing of regional local roads and they were brought up to a satisfactory standard.  Unfortunately, however, in recent times funding has been cut dramatically, so much so that the road network is crumbling under our feet or our cars' tyres.  We talk about looking after and protecting rural Ireland, but one of the most important aspects of that is providing access to rural areas.  I ask the Leader to invite the relevant Minister to the House to address that issue.  When the Minister is here we could also discuss the reinstatement of funding for local improvement schemes.  These were for private lanes, where people lived on country boreens.  Until recently, there was funding available and specifically ring-fenced for their maintenance and upkeep.  That funding was cut a number of years ago to such an extent that the network of such roads is also crumbling.  The issue is particularly relevant to rural Ireland and I ask that the Minister come to the House to address it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1374" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#M00500"><p>I wish to raise a point that came to mind as I travelled the country during the Seanad election campaign.  It is a bugbear of mine.  It might seem small, but not with regard to the promotion of tourism.  The directional road signs in Ireland are atrocious.  Unless one has a satnav, one cannot find the areas we should be marketing as tourism attractions.  Will the Leader and the Cathaoirleach ask the relevant Minister, in either the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport or the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government, to instigate an audit of road signs throughout Ireland, particularly small road signs?</p> <p>Ireland has probably the best tourist destinations, but that is no good unless one can find them.  Members will be aware from the Seanad election campaign that the satnav does not always work.  There should be good, old-fashioned signs.  Perhaps we could learn from the French.  When one arrives in a village or town, one should be sent to its centre and see signs to wherever one wishes to go.  When travelling in Ireland one might be going to a town that is, perhaps, ten miles down the road, but its name is not given on the sign while the name of the town five miles further on is on it.  This is basic.  There is a need to conduct a simple, proper audit of road signs throughout the country to ensure we can market Ireland in the best possible light.</p> <p>There is another aspect to this.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Kieran O'Donnell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2207"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2207&amp;amp;pid=KieranODonnell&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->IDA Ireland brings prospective employers to various parts of the country and Enterprise Ireland wants people to locate in rural villages.  I represent an area which is both urban and rural and we need to be able to find a place.  Good old fashioned signs are still as important as they were 20 or 30 years ago, in the pre-satellite navigation era.  This may seem to be a very simple matter but it could yield an enormous dividend from a tourism, business and personal perspective.  I ask that the Minister be invited to the House to discuss this matter and that an audit such as that to which I refer be carried out.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#N00200"><p>From my long experience of Seanad campaigns, most candidates will go through fire and water to find a councillor and will not rely on either satellite navigation systems or signposts.  I am not taking from the point the Senator is making but-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1374" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#N00300"><p>I am sure the Cathaoirleach has many friends all over the country and I have no doubt that he can drive into any village and people will say, "Is that you, Cathaoirleach?".  However, for the average tourist, this is something we should do to market Ireland and it is a very simple way of doing so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#N00400"><p>I was amused by a story about the most recent campaign when a certain person climbed an eight foot gate at 8.15 a.m. to canvass a vote in a county which shall remain nameless.  We must wrap up this discussion shortly.  I ask the remaining speakers to be brief.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#N00500"><p>I will be very brief.  Like many others here, I spent recent months travelling the length and breadth of the country, from Malin Head to Mizen Head and from Galway to Dublin and back, during the course of which I became very intimately acquainted with-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#N00600"><p>Very successfully, I think.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#N00700"><p>I was a slow starter but I got there.  I came to understand the deficiencies of our mobile phone system very well, as I am sure did many others.  I am not talking about broadband or Wi-Fi but basic mobile phone coverage, which is very important.  Invariably, I found that one particular network worked but another did not.  The State obviously issues licences to mobile service providers and it is time to invite the Minister for Communications, Climate Change and Natural Resources to the House to discuss mobile phone coverage and mobile services in general.  One will invariably find on the new motorways that one will not get a service.  I do not use the phone when I am driving but would pull in and use it now and again.  On most of the new roadways, however, one can forget about doing so.</p> <p>I would also like to say something about customer service by the mobile network providers.  If one happens to have the misfortune of going into a mobile phone shop, one will generally be obliged to queue for service.  I was in one such shop the other day and there were several elderly people present but there were no chairs for them to sit on, despite the fact that the queues were lengthy.  There are lots of other issues I could raise but it is a bit late in the day to do so.  I ask the Leader to accommodate a debate on mobile phone services at his earliest convenience.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#N00800"><p>Just to remind the House, I called on the Leader to wrap up about 15 minutes ago.  I am not trying to stymie discussion but we must wrap up some time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1422" speakername="Paudie Coffey" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#N00900"><p>I will be brief.  I commend Senator Ned O'Sullivan, who has an admirable political antenna.  Whether it is seagulls or mobile phones, he certainly picks up on the issues that affect citizens.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#N01000"><p>It was magpies this morning.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1422" speakername="Paudie Coffey" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#N01100"><p>I wish to pick up on points made earlier about the importance of recognising the Irish diaspora.  In that context, I commend Senator Lawless on the work he has done.  I also commend all of the Irish Americans and the Irish centres all over the United States of America on their tremendous work promoting Irish culture, heritage and the connections that sustain links with the Irish who currently reside on the other side of the Atlantic.  As Minister of State, I had the honour of visiting the mid-west of the United States in 2015 and in the cities of St. Louis and Indianapolis I met a very proud Irish community.  However, the members of that community were very concerned that the traditional links with Ireland were weakening.  Some of the Irish people who had been to the forefront in promoting Irish links had passed away or were no longer as active as they had been previously.  There is a concern that the mid-west, which would not have seen the same level of interaction as areas on the east and west coast of the USA needs to see more sustainable linkages developed in terms of culture, education and business.  It is important that this House recognises those links.  I know that Irish Americans really appreciate it when Irish representatives, be they mayors, Ministers or other representatives of the State, go to the USA to strengthen those links.  I urge the Leader to invite the Minister of State with responsibility for the diaspora, Deputy McHugh, to the House for a debate on this issue.  I know that such debates are appreciated and we must consistently raise and recognise the importance of the diaspora in this House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#N01200"><p>I know that the Cathaoirleach is under pressure but I am delighted to see Senator Lawless, one of the Taoiseach's nominees, in the House.  It is great to have someone in this Chamber who has a direct link to the White House.  That can only be good for this country and this Senate.  I am also very much in agreement with what Senator O'Donnell said with regard to the arts.  For many decades now she has been performing in the arts and continues to do so in this House.  She is someone with a direct link to the Taoiseach, which should also be of huge benefit to the House.</p> <p>I ask the Leader to invite the Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy Bruton, to the House in the coming weeks to discuss adult education, the plc sector and the Youthreach training centres.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#N01300"><p>Finally, I call Senator Martin Conway, who has just reappeared.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#N01400"><p>I am sorry, I missed my slot earlier.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#N01500"><p>I am being very lenient today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#N01600"><p>The Cathaoirleach is always a gentleman and that is not going to change.  I commend Senator O'Sullivan on his contribution regarding mobile phone coverage although I am coming at the issue from quite a different perspective.  I intend to bring a SIM registration Bill to the floor of the House in the coming weeks which aims to ensure that all SIM cards sold by mobile phone operators are registered in a database and that anyone who wishes to buy a SIM card will have to produce a utility bill or a passport to do so.  Mobile communication is great and the ongoing advances in this area are wonderful but, unfortunately, the possibilities of such communication are being abused, particularly by gangland criminals who are buying multiple SIM cards at will.  There is no minimum age limit for the purchase of a SIM card.  Children as young as nine or ten can go into mobile phone shops with &euro;50, buy ten SIM cards and walk away.  Those cards can then be put into electronic devices and used to cause mayhem.  It is really not good enough.  Many other European countries have registration systems for SIM cards and it is time to take some degree of control over the pay-as-you-go market.  I hope this House will support the forthcoming SIM registration Bill and send it to the Lower House for approval.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#N01700"><p>I will begin by quoting James Joyce, "Love loves to love love" and wishing everyone a happy Bloomsday.  I hope, in keeping with today's theme of the arts, that we will continue to promote arts and culture, not just in this House but across the country.  I remind members of the Fianna F&aacute;il Party that today also marks the anniversary of Jack Lynch's victory in the 1977 general election, held on 16 June.  At the risk of sounding a discordant note, perhaps the motor tax policy that was referred to by Senator Gallagher had its origins then, when there were cuts to funding.  However, I will not go back in history now, except to say that today is a very important day.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#N01800"><p>The Senator can go back if he likes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#N01900"><p>Senators Ardagh, Conway-Walsh and &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in raised the issue of bin charges but as Members know, the movement now is towards a pay-per-weight system.  It is being introduced, by regulation, from July.  I am surprised that Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in did not remember that it was his own party colleague, the former Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government, Deputy Alan Kelly, who signed the order.  It follows the standard of the polluter pays principle.  I agree that we should have a debate on waste policy.  In that context, Sinn F&eacute;in has tabled a Private Member's motion on the issue which will come before the House next week for debate.  Oral hearings are currently being conducted by An Bord Plean&aacute;la in Cork concerning incineration.  Many people are against incineration but our landfill sites are not able to cope with the amount of refuse being generated.  It is important that we educate ourselves and the next generation on the importance of recycling, reducing and reusing waste materials.  We must reduce the amount of waste going to landfill sites.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->If we are to have effective prevention measures, it is important that people are rewarded based on how they treat and dispose of their waste.  The EPA and CSO produced data which show that 87% of householders will see a reduction in their charges, 8.5% will see no charge and a small number will see an increase.  I am pleased the Minister is meeting bin companies.  Senators Conway-Walsh and Ardagh are correct.  People should not have to pay more.  Private operators should not exploit their customers.  One of the major tragedies of the elimination of municipal waste collection was that the waiver system in many coastal areas has gone.</p><p>It is important that we are proactive.  The Minister is working with companies.  They should not be exploitative and should instead work with their customers to ensure proper charges are applied.  We will take up the issue.  Awareness and segregation of waste are important, and we should continue along that route. </p><p>I refer to Senator Conroy-Walsh's motion.  As I explained at a meeting earlier, there are a number of discrepancies in the motion.  As Leader of the House, I cannot allow it because it has implications for the Cathaoirleach and the House.  The motion is not within Standing Orders.  </p><p>Based on yesterday's remarks in the House, I look forward to the Twenty-fifth Seanad bringing about change in how the House works, does its business, and how it is perceived across the country by the Fourth Estate, citizens and constituent members.  I am not afraid to examine the electoral system or the internal workings of the Seanad.  Let us do so in the context of what is best for democracy and representation in our country.  Let us put aside our vested interests and put our country and people first in our reform of the Upper House.  We are the current occupants of the House.  A generation has gone before us and a generation will come after us.  It behoves us, as Members of the Seanad, to do the right thing.  I hope we will all do that because it is important that we continue to be representatives of whoever puts us in here.</p><p>I agree with Senator &Oacute; Domhnaill about North-South relations.  It is incumbent on us to carry on the work of the last Seanad and the work many of us did in committees in working with our partners in the Northern Ireland Assembly.  We are all part of the one island and must work together to ensure that the Good Friday Agreement is implemented and the quality and standard of life of all of our citizens, whether Catholic or Protestant, are espoused and advanced.  That is our duty.</p><p>To be fair, the Orange Order visited the previous Seanad.  That is a matter for the CPP in the context of Senator &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh's request for the Northern Ireland Minister for finance to come to the House.  It is important that we continue to build bridges and relationships.  As Leader of the House, I look forward to doing that.  Senators will find no obstacle from me in that regard.  My record as Chairman of the Joint Committee on Health and Children will show that we went to the Assembly in Belfast and a reciprocal committee came to Dublin.  It is important that we continue with that process.</p><p>Senators Higgins, &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in and O'Donnell referred to the year of the arts.  I welcome the passion of Members of the House for the arts, in particular the eloquence of Senator Marie-Louise O'Donnell.  I am pleased that she is the spokesperson on arts because she brings not just knowledge but a passion for, interest in and experience and wisdom of the arts.  It is important that they continue to be at the forefront in the House.  I want to assure Members that the Government is committed to the arts.  The Minister, Deputy Heather Humphreys, retains full responsibility.  There has been no denigration or dilution of roles.  The buck stops with the Minister.  That can be seen in the programme of work of the Government, where the Minister is committed to producing the first ever national policy on culture, with a view to publishing it in the next couple of years.  Culture policy 2025 is the plan to which the Minister is committed.</p><p>Equally, the Government as a whole is committed to the arts, culture and heritage, and there will be no downgrading of them by the Government.  Significant funding was provided for the arts by the Government at a time when the country had no money.  I remind Members that &euro;30 million was provided for the new National Gallery, &euro;8 million was provided for a new expansion project for the National Archives and there was a &euro;10 million renovation of the National Library at a time when the country was bereft of money.  That was the legacy of the previous Government, which the current Government will continue.  Let us ensure that we continue with that policy and keep the arts to the forefront of what we do.</p><p>I join with other Members in offering sympathy to family and colleagues of the nurse who died in Crumlin.  It is a tragedy and we all must await the post-mortem results.  It is important that we acknowledge that a human life has been lost and people are mourning today.  I sympathise on behalf of the Government and all Members with the family and staff affected.</p><p>Senator Craughwell referred to his motion on terms and conditions for councillors.  Senator Paddy Burke yesterday raised a Commencement matter to which the Minister, Deputy Varadkar, responded regarding K-class PRSI.  As I said yesterday, it is important that we speak as a unified voice on the terms and conditions of councillors.  We should not all bat as individuals trying to seek political points.  N&iacute; neart go cur le ch&eacute;ile.  If we stand together as a body elected by councillors we can progress change, but if we all go off on divergent paths we will all end up on the road less travelled and will not achieve the result we all want.  Senator Craughwell can move his motion in Private Members' time.  The Government will be happy to work with him regarding that and I will happy to talk to him.  I am not saying the Senator is scoring political points.  We must work together.</p><p>Senators O'Mahony and Black referred to the Public Health (Alcohol) Bill.  I am pleased to say it was restored to the Order Paper yesterday.  The Government is committed to taking it at the earliest possible opportunity.  It will come back on Committee Stage.  A large amount of work has been done.  I refer the Senators to the Bill and the previous Joint Committee on Health and Children, which did some strong pre-legislative scrutiny on alcohol.  I compliment Senator James Reilly and former Minister, Alex White, on the work they did in progressing the Bill.  Without them, it would not be on the Order Paper.  We need to address the issue because alcohol misuse is costing the nation dearly in terms of lives, work hours and the quality of life for families.  Too many homes are affected by the blight of alcohol.</p><p>Senator Higgins referred to the Department of Arts, Heritage, the Gaeltacht and the Islands.  We will return to that issue. </p><p>Senator Harkin and others referred to the anniversary of the deaths of young people in Berkeley.  It is important that we remember them.  As we speak, young men and women are on flights across the Atlantic Ocean heading off to a new summer experience.  I spent a summer on a J1 in America.  It is important that we provide such young people with resources.  </p><p>I welcome Mr. Brian O'Dwyer and Mr. Mike Carroll from New York who were very helpful in providing jobs and working with Irish-Americans.  As Senator Coffey said, today we remember.  Irish community centres and the diaspora in the four corners of America have helped many young people.  It is important that we remember the young men and women who died in Berkeley and I thank him for raising the issue today.</p><p>Senator Norris referred to the inner city.  I do not want to cause a political row, but I do not think Tony Gregory formed CAB.  I will not go into the issue.  He is correct.  The inner city of Dublin requires regeneration and the Government is committed to that.  The Taoiseach and Ministers visited the area this week.  It was not, as some people said, a circus.  Rather, they were there to listen and continue the work that is being done.  I have worked in deprived areas.  It is important that the arms of the State reach into such areas and work in a cross-departmental way to help people live their lives.  </p><p>Senator Lawless referred to a letter from President Obama.  I am sure he will be able to persuade him to speak in the Seanad at a later date.  It might be a nice gesture.  It is good that he is a Member of the House and it is important that the President acknowledged his role.  He is not a token Senator.  He has a valid mandate to represent us, himself and the diaspora, and I look forward to working with him in that regard.  </p><p>Senator &Oacute; Clochartaigh also referred to J1 visas.  I would be happy for the Minister of State, Deputy McHugh, to come to the House to discuss voting rights and the diaspora.  It is important that we reach out beyond our shores and acknowledge that the diaspora have an important role.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->As Senator Coffey correctly said yesterday, we do have a skills shortage in some areas, so the Minister, in singling out certain professions or skill sets, is appealing to people because of the shortages and he is right to do that.</p><p>I referred to Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in's contribution already.</p><p>Senator Richmond's comment about a unified North-South team is an interesting one.  I am not sure how the Football Association of Ireland and the Irish Football Association in Northern Ireland would feel about that, but perhaps it is something we should consider.  The Senator might suggest the issue as one that could be discussed by the committee with responsibility for sport.  All of us join in wishing every success to the Northern Ireland team tonight and the Irish team at the weekend.  It is important that we continue to build on what has been achieved and that Irish fans continue to show the importance of being good ambassadors for the country.  We have seen videos on social media of the fun Irish fans are having, but I would sound a note of caution to all Irish supporters and ask them to be careful, not to travel off the beaten track and to take their time.  A consular service is available and they should put the contact number in their mobile phones or their wallets, because people can get lost for whatever reason and it is important that we continue the good record.  It would be a shame if the good spirits of supporters and the manner in which they are viewed across France is damaged.  All fans should put the number of the consular service in their mobile phones in case anyone gets in trouble.</p><p>Senator Boyhan mentioned the National Rehabilitation Hospital.  He is correct that it is a very important facility.  The men and women who work there do a tremendous job and the facility is long overdue an overhaul.  I will ask the Minister to come to the House to comment.  As a short-term measure, perhaps the Senator would consider tabling the matter for discussion on the Commencement.  The Senator is correct that it is an issue we must put on the radar.</p><p>I spoke about Senator Black's contribution.  Senator Colm Burke raised the issue of the HSE and the Department.  He is correct.  If we are engaged in new politics, then the HSE and the Department of Health must engage in new business measures and they must operate differently.  The Minister for Health is to be congratulated on his ten-year strategy, but it should include all stakeholders, which would involve some of those suggested by Senator Burke.  That would result in a ten-year strategy similar to social partnership, which did not include a political element.  I welcome the creation of a policy committee of the D&aacute;il to consider a ten-year strategy.  I hope the Minister will expand the committee to include the Seanad, because Members of this House could play a constructive role in the health policy promotion area.  The health committee the Minister has established is a good one, but he should go further and model it on the social partnership system.</p><p>I referred to Senator &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh's remarks about small business and the Northern Ireland Minister for Finance.  That is a matter for the Committee on Procedure and Privileges.  As Leader, I would not have any problem if Senator &Oacute; Domhnaill and Senator &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh wish to write to the CPP about that.</p><p>I congratulate Senator Ray Butler on his maiden speech.  I welcome him to the House and compliment him on the work he has done to promote the needs of the self-employed.  He has always been very vocal in that regard.  I look forward to bringing the Minister for Social Protection, Deputy Varadkar, to the House to discuss the issue.  Senator Butler is correct that there is an important deficit with regard to the self-employed.  I hope the Mangan report will be the starting point for improvement in that regard.</p><p>I already mentioned Senator Marie-Louise O'Donnell's reference to the arts.  Senator &Oacute; Domhnaill referred to Loughinisland.  I would be happy for the Minister to come to the House and I will try to facilitate that.  Senator Gallagher is correct that roads are important, and now that we are in a period of economic recovery it is important that we invest as a country in upgrading regional and national roads in particular.  It is important that we follow his suggestion of bringing the Minister to the House.</p><p>Senator Kieran O'Donnell is correct in what he said about road signs.  Any of us who travel the country are aware that road signs can be misleading and also dangerous in many parts.  A plethora of commercial signs are now getting in the way as well.  That is a matter we should discuss with Transport Infrastructure Ireland, TII, the Department and local councils.  I will certainly arrange to have the Minister come before us to discuss the matter.</p><p>Both Senator O'Sullivan and Senator Conway raised the issue of mobile phone coverage.  It is a worrying trend that the quality of the mobile phone signal is decreasing.  The Cork to Dublin road is an example.  I can pinpoint three or four spots where the coverage automatically goes.  It is an important issue.  As Senator Mulherin said to me, from an economic point of view, that is something we must address, because if investors who come to this country consider that the mobile phone coverage is not good enough - that it is poor and patchy - they might think twice about coming here.  The points the Senators raised are ones we should take up as well.</p><p>Senator Coffey mentioned the diaspora and the Irish-American centres.  He is correct that we should discuss those matters.  Senator Wilson referred to education.  I am a former director of adult education and I believe adult education and continuing education are very important.  I will invite the Minister to come before us to discuss that.  Senator Conway's Bill on SIM cards is one we should accept and embrace as it relates to data protection and safety.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.93" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.94" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#P00300">Delivering Sustainable Full Employment: Statements</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#P00400"><p>The Minister has been patiently waiting outside with her staff for some time.  That is another reason we should try to be a bit more strict in the timing of the Order of Business.  I will achieve that in due course.</p> <p>I formally welcome the Minister, Deputy Mitchell O'Connor, to the House and wish her every success with her new portfolio and her Ministry.  The contribution of all Senators is six minutes.  I invite the Minister to commence her statement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1247" speakername="Mary Mitchell O'Connor" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#P00500"><p>Thank you very much, a Chathaoirligh, for your good wishes.</p> <p>I welcome the opportunity to address the Seanad today on the important issue of getting people back to work.  I look forward to working with the House.  I respect the way in which the House does business.  This Government's goal is to achieve sustainable full employment.  We want all people to have the opportunity to enjoy rewarding work.  We want to ensure that all people can participate and contribute their full potential to the economy and society.</p> <p>The programme for a partnership Government sets our ambition to help create 200,000 additional jobs by 2020.  A total of 135,000 of those jobs are to be outside of Dublin.  We also want to reduce unemployment to 6%.  Our target this year is to add 50,000 new jobs.  We have made a good start.  More than 15,000 new jobs were created in the first three months of 2016.  In early 2012, the first Action Plan for Jobs was launched.  At the time, the unemployment rate was above 15.1%.  In May this year, it fell to 7.8%.  A total of 155,000 more people are in employment today than in 2012.  That surpasses the original target to have an extra 100,000 people at work by the end of 2016.</p> <p>The Government is committed to sustaining the rate of job creation and delivering full employment by 2020.  The enterprise agencies of my Department have been pivotal in addressing the jobs challenge in recent years.  Employment in Enterprise Ireland and IDA Ireland-supported companies increased by 22,000 in 2015.  The local enterprise offices supported the creation of more than 3,500 new jobs.</p> <p>I wish to give the message loud and clear that unemployment has declined in all regions since 2012.  A total of 20,000 jobs were created in the past year alone outside Dublin.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Mary Mitchell O'Connor:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2284"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2284&amp;amp;pid=MaryMitchellOConnor&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Almost two thirds of the new jobs created by Enterprise Ireland clients in 2015 were outside Dublin and over half of the jobs created in IDA Ireland companies in 2015 were also outside Dublin.  However, we cannot be complacent.  It is my job to ensure that the jobs go to regional areas.</p><p>In 2015, we developed eight regional action plans for jobs to ensure the recovery would be felt in every region.  The overall target is to grow employment in each region by 10% to 15% by 2020 and we have set up a regional implementation committee to oversee and drive each plan.  The programme for Government also commits to reducing each county's unemployment rate to within 1% of the State average.</p><p>The first progress reports on the implementation of the regional action plans will be published in the second half of this year.  As I have mentioned, the number of people out of work has declined considerably since its peak in 2012.  However, unemployment remains too high.  This Government is placing a particular priority on youth unemployed and long-term unemployed.  In May of this year, the rate of youth unemployment was 15%, down from 20.8% in 2015.  We cannot be complacent about youth unemployment and we must ensure that group is targeted so that it has employment.  The number of long-term unemployed declined by 27,000 in the past year.  This is, of course welcome.  However, I am conscious that we must continue to reduce this number further.</p><p>As unemployment continues to fall, it is timely to focus on the quality of employment.  The quality of employment is a key determinant of the well-being of individuals and of households.  The number of part-time workers increased by 3.7% in the year to the end of March 2016.  Women are more likely to work part-time than men.  Two thirds of part-time workers are women.  In some cases working part-time is by choice.  It is positive that we have those flexible opportunities.</p><p>There are also people working part-time who would work additional hours if such were available.  The number of underemployed part-time workers declined by almost 14% in the past year.  Underemployment among women fell by 15.1%.  We need to ensure that this trend continues.</p><p>Ireland has a comprehensive suite of employment rights legislation.  We strongly protect those who work on a part-time basis or on a temporary basis.  In the area of zero and low-hour contracts, the Government is preparing an appropriate policy response to the University of Limerick, UL, study.  It was essential that stakeholders were given an opportunity to consider and respond to the UL study.  The large number of submissions received requires careful consideration by my Department.  These submissions will inform the policy response to be considered by Government.</p><p>The Low Pay Commission will make its next recommendations on the national minimum wage for 2017 in July.  Its recommendations must be evidence-based.  We want a minimum wage that is both fair and sustainable.  We want to assist as many low-paid workers as is reasonably practicable without creating significant adverse consequences for employment or competitiveness.  I look forward to receiving and taking forward that report.</p><p>Innovation is at the heart of Government policy for enterprise and creating high-quality jobs.  Leadership in science, research and innovation play a crucial role in attracting, developing and nurturing business.  They are also essential ingredients in creating and maintaining employment.</p><p>Research and development active firms also do better in terms of job creation and exports.  Our Innovation 2020 strategy sets out the vision for Ireland to become a global innovation leader.  Innovation 2020 is focused both on delivering a strong sustainable economy and a better society.  We want to see greater numbers of enterprises engaging in research and development.  We need more enterprises progressing to a point where innovation is embedded as a key part of their business model.  We have a target to increase our spend on research and development to 2.5% of GNP by 2020.  This is a key priority for my Department.</p><p>I am acutely aware that the rising economic tide may not yet have reached every business.  Through the Action Plan for Jobs, we have made significant progress since 2012 to make it easier for SMEs to do business in Ireland.  This strong focus on SME competitiveness and growth will continue.</p><p>Creating a fertile environment for entrepreneurship and start-ups is one of my top priorities.  This includes targeted actions by El and the LEOs to promote female entrepreneurship.  Participation by female entrepreneurs in El's high potential start-up programme increased to 20% in 2015.  The target was 18%.</p><p>The Action Plan for Jobs is working.  However, we cannot be complacent.  We remain vulnerable to external shocks.  Key among these include Brexit, increases in oil prices and exchange rate movements.</p><p>We must protect the gains in competitiveness achieved over the past few years.  We have moved to seventh place in IMD global competitiveness rankings but more remains to be done.  I will be working with the National Competitiveness Council and my ministerial colleagues to ensure we get progress on the key competitiveness issues.  We need to address the issues of costs for business.  We need to prioritise action on infrastructure bottlenecks.  We need to ensure we have sufficient skills and talent supply.</p><p>I have asked my Department to initiate the process to develop the 2017 action plan for jobs.  This is now under way.  We will be consulting widely with external stakeholders over the coming months.  As I said earlier, we want to gather the best ideas for sustainable job creation.</p><p>My priority is to deliver a business environment that is among the most competitive internationally.  I want to use our collective resources across Government to support enterprise and sustainable employment growth in all of the regions.  Through collective action, I am convinced we can achieve sustainable full employment by 2020.</p><p>I am delighted to be here.  I look forward to hearing the Senators' ideas through this session.  I also want Senators to know the door is open in the Department and if we can help, we are there to help.  EI, IDA Ireland and the LEOs are all there.  I would ask all Senators to familiarise themselves with the plan for their particular region.  It is available on the web.  If we can help, as I said, we would be delighted to do so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#Q00200"><p>I, too, congratulate the Minister on her appointment to Government.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#Q00300"><p>Ba mhaith liom comhghairdeas a dh&eacute;anamh leis an Aire on her new appointment.  No doubt Deputy Mitchell O'Connor will certainly bring great enthusiasm to her new post.</p> <p>I listened intently to the Minister's forecasts - 200,000 jobs by 2020 and 135,000 of these will be outside of Dublin.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Aidan Davitt:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2475"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2475&amp;amp;pid=AidanDavitt&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This is starting to sound like a sketch from <i>Alice in Wonderland.  </i>The new quote of 200,000 jobs would be welcome and we would be delighted to see them.  We could certainly look at that figure.  One would have to agree that the Mad Hatter came up with the figure of 135,000 jobs outside of Dublin, 68% of new jobs outside Dublin and the current figure being 50%.  I cannot see the figures adding up.  I wish the Minister well with all the jobs.  As she said there has been a great improvement in recent years.<br/><br/>The document goes on to deal with IDA site visits.  It is easy to see that the jobs follow the site visits.  Some 50% of all site visits were in Dublin and 48% of IDA jobs were created in Dublin.  It is no coincidence that the unemployment blackspots of the north east, north west and midlands had an average of 2.5% each of these site visits.  The IDA is doing a great job but there will have to be a focus outside the M50.  Our local IDA park in Mullingar has one business which was relocated from Mullingar after lengthy negotiations by my fellow Oireachtas Member, Deputy Robert Troy.  The estate is a place the IDA forgot about, 45 minutes from the M50 waiting for use.<br/><br/>Rural Ireland has been strangled to death following the closure of Garda stations, Army barracks, schools and the abolition of town councils.  These were all Government-led.  The services fled - banks, post offices, shops and retail.  We need to lead from the front and give these country communities hope.<br/><br/>Skilled manufacturers and tradespeople need support with the apprenticeship model.  It is unfair that they have to suffer the loss of their trainee while at college and also expect them to contribute &euro;16,000 over the four years to fund the programme.  This is the reason the number of apprenticeships is at an all time low of 8,000, down from a peak of 30,000.  This is an issue on which the Minister could focus.<br/><br/>Another subject glossed over today by the Minister in her contribution was that of wage discrimination.  When we come into this world and when we leave it, we are in the hands of nurses.  Teachers are the people who model us, encourage us and introduce us to the world of learning during our formative years.  The Garda and Defence Forces protect us and put their lives on the line every day so we can have a normal functioning society.  The wage discrimination that the Government forced on garda&iacute;, nurses, teachers and soldiers starting at &euro;22,000 to &euro;25,000 gross is degrading.  If the Taoiseach wants to keep the recovery going, he should start with those on whom we are so dependent.  None of those starter public servants is on a living wage.  This has become a divisive issue in their workplaces.  When formulating her document I ask the Minister to look at these particular areas, and if there is anything I can assist with, I would be happy to oblige.  I appreciate her coming here today and offering an open ear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#R00200"><p>During the Order of Business there was some discussion on the arts and I neglected to point out that we have somebody from the Fine Gael side of the House who has been very proficient in the arts for more than four decades, Senator Joe O'Reilly.  We look forward to his performance.  The Senator has six minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#R00300"><p>I thank the Acting Chairman for the introduction.  I could return some of those compliments and enlarge on them.  Be that as it may, I appreciate the kind remarks and wish him well.  I know he will chair the session with great skill.</p> <p>I congratulate my great personal friend, the Minister, Deputy Mary Mitchell O'Connor, on her appointment.  I am delighted for her and I think she will bring to the office a tremendous energy and a natural leadership skill.  I am confident she will get the results and I wish her well.</p> <p>As a background to this debate, there is nothing that gives people more dignity than a job.  It is crucial to the family and friends of people and to their whole self worth.  It is important to keep that perspective in mind.  The dignity of work is so important to people and it is sadly absent from those who do not have it.  It is well-established that the way to remove people from the poverty trap is to get them employment.  The intergenerational effect of getting people back to work is enormous.  About three generations will be affected by somebody coming off unemployment.  The great success of our times and of the recent past has been reducing unemployment.  No other achievement is greater and we should revel in it and be proud of it.  Since 2012, 155,000 more people are at work than previously.  We are about to break the 2 million number of people in employment in the country.</p> <p>In May 2016, the unemployment level was 7.8%.  Of course we are not happy with that level but it is a huge change from 15.1%.  Youth unemployment has fallen by 5% in the past year from a level of 15%.  All of these achievements are enormous.  As a people and as a nation we can be proud of them because every individual in the country contributed to this outcome.  In that context, I congratulate the Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy Richard Bruton, previously Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, and his Minister of State, Deputy Damien English, on their achievements in that sphere.  What has been achieved to date should give us confidence that we can finish the job and get much more done.  The big challenge is to bring back our emigrants.  We have an enormous pool of talent among our emigrants and we need to get them back.  With their new experiences, the great education with which they left and their natural flair, they will come back and create jobs, so it will have a domino or a multiplier effect.</p> <p>There are some things that are not glamorous but which need to be said in this debate.  We need to keep the public finances under control.  We have to remain competitive.  If we keep the public finances under control, borrowing for infrastructure will be cheaper and will be available to us.  Inward investment will be attracted to the country.  In addition to keeping the public finances under control, we need to maintain the correct tax environment.  Also, and this is not a very popular concept, we need to keep wage control.  The greatest act of patriotism and the greatest act of selflessness that our workers and their organised bodies can do is to engage while achieving realistic and well-justified pay increases as the economy improves but to show the level of restraint that will allow for further job creation.  The kind of patriotism that is called for now is a new patriotism.  It is the new Christianity in action, the new meitheal or the new commitment to the common good.  We need to see everything in terms of job creation and we need to be restrained in wage demands with that in mind.</p> <p>If we have industrial unrest, it will adversely affect inward investment and create all kinds of difficulties.  One good aspect of job creation to date is the good cross-sector increase in jobs.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Joe O'Reilly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1610"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1610&amp;amp;pid=JoeOReilly&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We have had 9,500 new jobs in the construction sector in the first quarter of 2016.  That is important.  There is great potential to increase the number of jobs in construction as the housing crisis is tackled.  We need major emphasis on apprenticeship training, upskilling workers and creating the skills among displaced former construction workers so that they can re-embrace the sector.  An interesting thing-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#S00200"><p>The Senator has half a minute.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#S00300"><p>I have so many points I would like to make.  I have not got used to the time constrictions of the Seanad yet.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1374" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#S00400"><p>Give us the abridged version.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#S00500"><p>The whole issue of full-time carers is an interesting one.  If that were upgraded and got more status, we could create jobs.  Finally, I am well aware of the achievements in spreading jobs regionally, but I am anxious that we get far more IDA Ireland itineraries into the rural areas.  Will the Minister look at the shortage of IDA Ireland itineraries in areas like my own constituency of Cavan-Monaghan and see if they can be increased over the coming years?  I am convinced that if we get the IDA Ireland people in, with their potential employers, they will stay and we will get the jobs.</p> <p>Finally, since the Leas-Chathaoirleach is in the Chair and despite the fact that he is cutting me short, I take the opportunity to wish him well and to congratulate him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#S00600"><p>I call Senator Conway-Walsh, who has six minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#S00700"><p>I thank the Leas-Chathaoirleach.  I also thank the Minister for coming before us and congratulate her on her new job.  It is lovely to see a woman here as a Minister.  She is the first woman Minister we have had before us.</p> <p>Any discussion around sustainable jobs must include a discussion of what constitutes a sustainable labour market.  We know the labour market is crucial to creating sustainable jobs in communities and in terms of the economic, social and cultural well-being of society.  According to data from the most recent quarterly national household survey for 2016, employment has increased by 2.4% in the year to the first quarter of 2016.  This was an increase in total employment of almost 47,000 jobs, 31,000 of which were full-time and 16,300 of which were part-time.  It is an increase of 2.1% in full employment and almost 4% in part-time jobs.  While I welcome the increase in the number of people at work, I do so cautiously on the back of the recent CSO figures that provide us with evidence that there is zero jobs growth in the west.  This is not a surprise to us living in the west; for every new job that is being created, there are job losses every day.  We only have to look at the loss of over 200 jobs last week in Sligo with the closure of the family-owned McCormack Garages.  I want to send the solidarity of this House to all of those affected by those job losses and their families.</p> <p>I cannot mention job creation in the west and in rural Ireland without begging the Minister to speak to her ministerial colleagues about fast-tracking broadband.  We need the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources here to discuss how we can fast-track it.  It is not good enough to cite 2022 as a date in terms of broadband.  I see the problem for myself.  I cannot communicate with the Houses of the Oireachtas because I do not have proper broadband where I live.  The Minister does not need me to tell her that without adequate broadband and telecommunications, the Government&rsquo;s jobs plan is not worth the paper it is written on.  </p> <p>We need to talk about emigration and its impact in terms of the reduction in the number of unemployed people.  Emigrants are employed in other countries.</p> <p>Alongside the lack of employment opportunities we must examine the fact that the Irish labour market is characterised by major problems with low pay, the proliferation of precarious work and increasing industrial unrest, as was outlined.  This promotes inequality and jeopardises our economic growth.  Ireland now has the dubious distinction of having the second highest number of low-paid workers in the OECD.  Contrary to the Government&rsquo;s spin on figures quoted above, I find the high rate of increase in part-time jobs extremely worrying.  I say this because all the research shows us that part-time workers make up a high percentage of those who are concentrated in low-paid employment sectors.  They are the most vulnerable to exploitation, precariousness, low pay and if-and-when contracts.  They also tend to receive less training and development.  That is worrying in terms of how people progress.  Low pay and weak workers&rsquo; rights architecture are bad for workers, the economy, communities, and society.</p> <p>By continuing along the track of non-standard work, we are creating a whole new community that I call the working poor.  They are the people who have to pay for everything and do not have adequate income to do so.  They are the people who struggle to get to the end of the week or the end of the month, worrying whether they have enough to pay their ever-increasing bills.  That is why we see such outrage in regard to bin charges and what that extra cost may mean for people.  These are the mothers &ndash; it is mostly women &ndash; who look at their sick children and wonder if they can get through the night without bringing them to the GP because they cannot afford the &euro;40, &euro;50, or &euro;60 fee they will have to pay.  They are trying to balance between taking their child to the GP and doing their shopping at the weekend.  That is the reality.  They are the people I see every day.  We must remember that these families are not just those working in the private sector; they are the low-paid workers in the public sector such as teachers, garda&iacute; and clerical staff in local authorities.  They are barely able to survive on the wages they are getting at the moment.</p> <p>Low pay also puts significant pressure on the State in terms of social transfers, with the result that the State ends up supplementing the pay of vulnerable workers.  In 2015 alone, the State spent a record &euro;350 million on subsidising the income of thousands of families in low-paid work.  The rapid rise in the number of workers in receipt of family income supplement and other social transfers &ndash; about 60% in recent years &ndash; is essentially topping up employers&rsquo; profit margins and highlights the extent to which workers and their families are at risk of poverty.  This transfer of wealth from the State is, in essence, reproducing, year in, year out, huge profits for large companies that see nothing wrong with bullying and exploiting their workforce.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#S00800"><p>The Senator has half a minute left.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#S00900"><p>That was really quick.</p> <p>I will cite Dunnes Stores, Tesco and other companies like them.  Dunnes Stores has the highest number of workers receiving the family income supplement.  That is not right and it needs to be tackled.</p> <p>I will leave out the rest of my speech out of respect for everybody else because my time is up but I ask the Minister to put in place legislation to regulate zero-hour contracts and to examine thoroughly the many issues that make up a sustainable working market.  I welcome what the Minister said at the beginning about her office and her Department being open.  I look forward to working with her for the west of Ireland, for rural Ireland and for Mayo in terms of getting the jobs we desperately need to stop emigration and to bring life back into our communities.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#S01000"><p>Senator O'Donnell has six minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1374" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#S01100"><p>I wish the Leas-Chathaoirleach well.  I expect he will perform his role with great aplomb.  I also congratulate the Minister, Deputy Mary Mitchell O'Connor, on her appointment.</p> <p>In the brief time I have, I want to speak about what I know, which is the constituency I represent, Limerick, and on the theme of sustaining full employment.  Many jobs have been created over the past three to five years, and they are to be welcomed.  However, I want to look at the issue of sustaining full employment in an Irish context, of which Limerick would be a microcosm, both urban and rural.</p> <p>Competitiveness is the key to employment.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Kieran O'Donnell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2207"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2207&amp;amp;pid=KieranODonnell&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->A couple of things would bring competitiveness.  In respect of employment costs, it is important that the marginal rate be brought below 50% for staff take-home pay. I welcome the fact that JobBridge is to be discontinued.  It served its purpose for a period but it was open to abuse, although not by everyone.  Now we are considering sustainable jobs.  We have to get a handle on insurance costs, which are a huge factor.  The low cost of energy is external to us, as is the rate of exchange for exports, and the Brexit debate may have an impact but we cannot control that.  I hope the Taoiseach&rsquo;s intervention will encourage people in the United Kingdom to vote to stay in the EU.</p><p>I want to see balanced regional development in Limerick, with the 2030 plan progressed so that we have the infrastructure required, particularly buildings in the city centre that the IDA and Enterprise Ireland can showcase.  I would also like the Hanging Gardens, and the projects for the Cleeve's site and the opera centre site to be expedited.  That is extremely important.  The IDA has committed to bringing 66 projects to the region by 2019.  We will hold it to that.  The development of the knowledge box is critical.</p><p>There are several villages in rural east Limerick, including Cappamore, Murroe, Caherconlish, Castleconnell and Ballyneety.  Many people have emigrated from rural villages as well as cities.  The real challenge in terms of sustainable employment is to get emigrants back and get people to set up businesses in their own communities.  It is not always about foreign direct investment; we need to create an environment for the person from the area who wants to set up a business.  There are weaknesses such as the speed of, and access to, broadband.  Pressure has to be kept on the national broadband plan, particularly in rural areas such as east Limerick.  I find that mobile phone coverage in many areas has got worse rather than better.  Something needs to be done.  This is extremely important for attracting people into rural areas.  Access by road is not as big a factor as the other two in the Internet age.  What incentives can we use to encourage people to set up in a rural village?  We need to put thought into this.  They may be tax or grant incentives, or access to services, but the rural area needs to compete on an even level with an urban setting when people are deciding where to set up a business.  I see in these villages that people have sustained businesses against all the odds, but they need people to come in to provide extra employment so that they can survive and prosper.  They offer benefits in terms of the number of pupils in schools and the existing businesses.  I look forward to welcoming the Minister to Limerick and showing her what Limerick has to offer and what she can bring to promote it.</p><p>On a national level, we must have a proper review of skills shortages, not just with regard to third level education but also apprenticeships.  Germany has a model such that when people leave school they can go into apprenticeships.  I look forward to the Minister&rsquo;s comments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1419" speakername="John Dolan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#T00200"><p>I congratulate the Leas-Chathaoirleach on his appointment yesterday.  As the lone male member of the Civil Engagement group, I join with Senator Conway-Walsh in welcoming a female Minister to the House.  At her opening words about "getting people back to work," my jaw dropped.  The paragraph picked up at the end when she said "all people can participate ... to their full potential".  The programme for Government refers to its goal &ldquo;to deliver sustainable full employment&rdquo; so that all our people have the opportunity to enjoy rewarding work and participate and contribute to their full potential to our economy and society.</p> <p>The coin has two sides and it is extremely important for us to recall that.  A word of caution: because it is written does not mean it will happen.  There can be a slip between cup and lip.  There was a huge impetus to get people back to work.  We remember Dell and Waterford Crystal and others in the first few months.  We all have micro-memories of job losses among people who were close to us - local small enterprises that went to the wall overnight and never made the news - but they were all real people.  It is very important to keep that in mind. </p> <p>When things go wrong in the economy, people on the margins - those with disabilities or mental health problems, those who carry the burden of addiction and various issues, and the long-term unemployed - are affected.  Before coming in here I used to drive through Ballybough, in Dublin&rsquo;s north inner city.  In the great days before the collapse the queues of people collecting their unemployment benefit were out the door onto the street.  There is a hard core of unemployed people, and although the figure has come down, 6% is still high.  They are in Dublin and the rest of the country.  The people with the problems I mention are in every community.  That has to be core to our considerations.</p> <p>In the 1980s there were fewer than 1 million in the workforce.  Now we are edging up to 2 million and we still have a bit of work to do.  When we talk of the diaspora, the parents and families of people with disabilities do not go to Dublin Airport to meet their young people.  People with disabilities cannot be part of the diaspora.  We sucked people from all over the world into our labour force up to ten years ago but we did not take people with disabilities.  There were almost 100,000 long-term unemployed in the country.</p> <p>In the early days of the last decade our manufacturing industry went down the tubes.  We did not notice it because there was another crane on the skyline.  Young lads ran from agriculture onto diggers and dumpers and trucks because that was where the big money was.  We degraded manufacturing and agriculture, which are not the exciting sectors of our workforce.  However, we were very proud of agriculture in the dark days when it and the agrifood sector kept the flag flying for us internationally.  There are parts of our economy that are not connected with research and development and the high-flying new technology but which are important and provide real work for people across the country.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator John Dolan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2479"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2479&amp;amp;pid=JohnDolan&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I challenge anyone in this Chamber or elsewhere to give me examples of when he or she heard about disabled people losing their jobs when the bust came.  They did not, as one cannot lose what one does not have.  I do not state that in a recriminatory sense but simply observe that we missed out when we were top dog with full employment.  We had money to burn but still could not do it for people who badly needed to be in the workplace.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#U00200"><p>The Senator has one minute left.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1419" speakername="John Dolan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#U00300"><p>I am being asked to come to a-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#U00400"><p>No, the Senator is not.  I simply am giving him a gentle reminder that one minute remains.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1419" speakername="John Dolan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#U00500"><p>I am being asked to round it up in that sense and I thank the Leas-Chathaoirleach.  A robust model of sustainable employment needs a few things.  Ireland has a worldwide reputation and relationships, which is a soft but valuable asset.  The ambition must be for employment for all.  Dependable and comprehensive public services are also needed.  I refer to the economic and the social and that old-fashioned term, the social wage.  While upward wage pressure is coming, we can dampen those expectations if we have dependable social and public services.  As for people with disabilities and others, issues such as education, training, social protection, mobility and transport must be considered.  Members must look outside the core areas they normally consider and pull them together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#U00600"><p>I congratulated the Leas-Chathaoirleach this morning when he was not in the Chair and now that he is installed, I do so again.  I wish him well.  I also welcome the Minister, Deputy Mitchell O'Connor, to the Chamber and congratulate her on her elevation to the Ministry.  She has good west of Ireland roots and the issue of spreading regional jobs is top of her agenda, which I welcome.</p> <p>One thing the previous Government got right was job creation.  As the Minister stated, what must be done now is to spread those jobs.  Senator Conway-Walsh mentioned that effectively, the reduction in unemployment is because everyone has emigrated.  However, it is a fact that 155,000 extra people are working.  As many of them would have been obliged to emigrate had those jobs not been created, I greatly welcome that creation, as well as the statistics on the reduction in long-term and youth unemployment, which also are priorities.</p> <p>Another issue that has arisen recently is the JobBridge scheme.  We are in a different place at present than was the case in 2011 and at the time, the JobBridge scheme served its purpose.  Many people secured full-time employment as a result of being part of that scheme but we are now in a different space.  I welcome that it is to be phased out because it is not needed now as much as it was then.</p> <p>The key issue the Minister addressed regarding regional growth and the spread of regional jobs is absolutely crucial.  This can be done in a number of ways and as the Minister mentioned, IDA Ireland, Enterprise Ireland and the local employment offices, LEOs, are in place.  I wish to be constructive but people, businesses and potential employers are falling through the cracks because LEOs operate mostly in mentoring and providing many services in a one-stop shop, which is an excellent idea.  I have been involved with a number of small businesses that had the potential to employ more than ten people.  However, as they were not exporting, Enterprise Ireland was not applicable to them and, similarly, foreign direct investment was not involved.  The key to small businesses, the self-employed and all of this is to somehow put in place structures to support the five, ten or 15 jobs in indigenous Irish companies.  The incentives are not in place for them and one is accused that were the jobs coming in from abroad, there would be bells and whistles.  I ask the Minister to give consideration to this issue.</p> <p>Some agencies already have been set up and I will mention the Western Development Commission in the context of the west and the north west.  Its remit covers the five Connacht counties of Mayo, Galway, Leitrim, Roscommon and Sligo, as well as counties Donegal and Clare.  The commission has done excellent work in providing jobs and through the Look West campaigns because there are many advantages to relocating to the west that are not available in urban areas.  However, its budget is very small and in a possible model for the rest of rural Ireland, this commission could provide the incentives to that sector to which I refer that is left out at present.  I urge the Minister to consider this area.</p> <p>The broadband issue was mentioned earlier today and a survey came out this morning which suggested that 20% of small businesses were not online.  I imagine this is not by choice in many cases; it is simply that they do not have broadband.  While the date of 2022 has been mentioned, that is the date by which every house and business in the country will be connected.  A great deal of work is under way in the roll-out of broadband at present.  It is important that this process be speeded up and I am aware the Minister's colleague, the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources, is anxious to do this.  However, when people hear the date 2022, they ask whether no one will have broadband in rural areas until then, whereas many people will have it.</p> <p>Competitiveness is another area the Minister addressed in her contribution.  Another success of the previous Government over the past five years concerned the tourism and hospitality sector and the 9% VAT rate but at present we are in danger of losing that edge of competitiveness again to increasing costs.  This issue must be monitored but there are huge opportunities and I welcome the Minister's enthusiasm to continue that because while I am aware of other issues and services that must be upgraded, as well as restoration and so on, one must not lose sight of full employment.  It is achievable in our present circumstances and I wish the Minister well in the task.  I look forward to working together with her.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#U00700"><p>I congratulate the Leas-Chathaoirleach on his elevation to his new role and congratulate the Minister on her appointment.  As anybody who has run a primary school will find running a Department to be very easy indeed, I wish the Minister the best of luck.</p><p>Comments have been made in the Chamber about how, statistically, we have done much better in recent years in bringing down the unemployment rate, which obviously is to be welcomed.  Over that time, that Government also managed to bring in many protections for workers' rights at the same time.  It not merely increased the minimum wage twice but I also refer to the reintroduction of the joint labour committee, JLC, system, the employment regulation orders, EROs, and collective bargaining legislation.  Consequently, a threshold of decency was placed under the economy.  However, I remind the Minister of the Private Members' motion that was passed by D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann only two weeks ago.  The motion was in the name of the Labour Party and was written by Senator Nash, who did a huge amount of work in the Minister's Department in the previous Government.  The motion states:</p><blockquote>That D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann:<br /><br />affirms that, as economic conditions continue to improve, it will stand up for working people and ensure that employees secure a fair share of growing national prosperity;<br /><br />accordingly calls for a programme of incremental increases to the national minimum wage until it is pegged at 60% of median earnings, and for a living wage of &euro;11.50 per hour to be adopted throughout the public sector;<br /><br />believes that, alongside tackling low pay, we must address root causes of insecurity at work, commit to further protections for vulnerable workers in precarious employment and bring an end to exploitative employment contracts that foster increased casualisation of workers;<br /><br />calls therefore on the Government to prepare and introduce a legislative package that will protect and enhance workers&rsquo; rights by:- ending the abuse of &quot;if and when&quot; contracts;<br /><br />- combating bogus self-employment;<br /><br />- ensuring freelance workers have the right to collectively bargain;<br /><br />- extending the transfer of undertakings regulations (TUPE) to workers in services such as catering and security;<br /><br />- protecting workers in &quot;informal&quot; insolvencies and collective redundancies;<br /><br />- providing statutory redress for the victims of workplace bullying;<br /><br />- promoting employment standards and the living wage in public procurement; and<br /><br />- preventing unilateral reductions in pay;notes in particular the University of Limerick report to the Government, Study on the Prevalence of Zero Hours Contracts among Irish Employers and their Impact on Employees, and, commissioned following the outrageous treatment of Clerys workers in June 2015, the Cahill-Duffy Expert Examination and Review of Laws on the Protection of Employee Interests When Assets are Separated from the Operating Entity; and<br /><br />commends the recommendations set out in both these reports and calls on the Government as an urgent priority to prepare legislation for their implementation.</blockquote> <p><!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2301"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2301&amp;amp;pid=AodhanORiordan&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->As the Minister is aware, this motion was passed by the D&aacute;il, the main House of the Oireachtas, so I would like to hear her comments on that, because I may have misheard but I have been led to believe that she is not minded to accept the report from the University of Limerick.  If that were the case, it would fly in the face of the expressed will of D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann and what is right and just, particularly given that the Clerys workers are marking the first anniversary of their disgraceful treatment this week.</p><p>I will touch on the dignity of work and how work is so important for vulnerable sectors of our society.  It is often forgotten about in the economic debate.  During the turbulent time as unemployment levels crept up, it was often said that unemployment costs the Exchequer &euro;27,000 for every person unemployed, including in respect of the loss of VAT receipts and welfare payments, but this completely misses the point.  It is the loss of dignity and self-worth that is the major deficit caused by unemployment.  There are sections of our society that are not necessarily benefiting from the Action Plan for Jobs.  During the Celtic tiger period more than 100,000 people were in consistent unemployment.  Whatever action plan the Government comes up with and whatever efforts are made to reduce unemployment, they do not seem to permeate into every sector of our society.  The comprehensive employment strategy for people with disabilities should have been part of the Action Plan for Jobs, but during the tenure of the last Government, the Department did not really want to know about this strategy, which was effectively run as an equality measure within the Department of Justice and Equality.  That is disappointing, because if one looks at certain sectors of our society, such as people living in disadvantaged areas, members of the Traveller community, people with disabilities and migrants, one can see there are particular barriers and issues those communities face in gaining employment, being protected in work and ensuring their employment rights are enhanced.  In terms of that comprehensive employment strategy, perhaps the Department will again look at how it can engage in and drive it and be more positive about it, because when I was involved in putting that strategy together, I felt that the engagement from the Department was less than positive.  </p><p>I wish the Minister well in respect of what she is trying to do.  The threshold of decency is everything.  Having statistics that we can roll out and being able to say that unemployment has come down is laudable and all very well, but dignity in work and the threshold of decency in the economy are everything.  Workers' rights and the sense of dignity a worker has every morning in getting up and going to work are what keeps society together.  I reiterate my request to the Minister to deal in a positive manner with the Labour Party motion that was passed in the D&aacute;il with the support of other parties two weeks ago.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1423" speakername="Ray Butler" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#V00200"><p>I wish Senator Coghlan all the best in his new position as Leas-Chathaoirleach.  I congratulate the Minister on her new post.  She has always been a great people person and she is the right person for the job.</p> <p>Rebuilding the economy to support job creation, leading to the delivery of sustainable full employment, has been a key objective of this Government and the previous one, which I had the pleasure of serving under.  In 2011, Ireland's employment rate was below the EU average and its unemployment rate was the fifth highest in the EU.  Our Action Plan for Jobs was introduced in early 2012 when the unemployment rate was 15.1%.  Today, it has fallen to 7.3%, with 155,000 more people employed by the end of the first quarter of 2016, bringing the total number of unemployed to just under two million to date.  Stimulating growth in all regions has been a priority to ensure that all areas achieve their economic potential, allowing communities to benefit locally.</p> <p>We continue to make great strides in this area with incentives such as the Wild Atlantic Way and the recently launched Ireland's Ancient East, which takes in my local area of Trim, south Meath and Meath west.  We have seen the recent opening of hotels and businesses along the west coast, increasing employment locally and substantially building our tourism industry.  Another incentive was the filming of certain scenes from the hugely popular "Star Wars: The Force Awakens" on the magnificent site of Skellig Michael in County Kerry.  These scenes have placed Ireland's rare beauty centre stage all over the world and can only have a positive effect on tourist figures for this year and many more years to come.  In 2015, our tourism industry reached a record number of visitors, beating a previous record set in 2007.  We are working towards creating an additional 50,000 jobs in this industry by 2025.  To date, the lower VAT rate of 9% for the hospitality sector, together with the removal of the travel tax, has been successful in boosting tourism levels, and moving forward is now imperative.  It is vital to maintain value for money for visitors to ensure continued growth in this industry.  </p> <p>We have been successful in attracting major multinationals to our country with our highly educated and motivated workforce.  Another reason for this is our 12.5% corporation tax rate, which has been controversial with some US politicians, some EU member states and certain members of the Opposition, who seem to oppose everything.  It is important that we maintain this rate of corporation tax to attract support and increase jobs.  However, we must not become complacent either.  It is our SMEs that employ most of the workforce.  Together with our up-and-coming entrepreneurs, these companies need to encouraged and given support to start up and continue growth.  </p> <p>It is imperative that certain areas be addressed in order to facilitate and encourage further growth among SMEs and thus enhance employment for others locally.  The issues I have pencilled in are bank loans and the Irish Credit Bureau.  During the height of the recession, I said that the Irish Credit Bureau was not fit for purpose.  It was all right before the crash, but when the crash happened, many businesses fixed their bank loans, and because of this and the fact that they are repaying the loans, they have defaulted in the eyes of the Irish Credit Bureau and will not get loans for the next five years.  It is an area at which we must look.  These people are paying their way but they face difficulties when they look for more credit facilities to move forward with their businesses and employ new people.  I recently visited a furniture factory in Navan.  The owner had renegotiated his loans, wanted to move on and could have employed ten people straight away, but he could not do so because he could not get the money.  It is a significant issue out there.  We must examine the Irish Credit Bureau.  </p> <p>Another issue I raised this morning and about which I will soon table a motion relates to social protection for the self-employed.  The motion will call for the implementation of the Mangan report.  Another issue concerns commercial rates.  There are huge levels of debt when it comes to commercial rates.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Ray Butler:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2303"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2303&amp;amp;pid=RayButler&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I am speaking to the owners of businesses that are in debt in sums of &euro;40,000 to &euro;70,000 from commercial rates.  The sum of &euro;10,000 or &euro;15,000 for commercial rates might not be a whole lot on 1 January 2016, but if not paid by 31 December 2016 it is a mountain going into the next year and adding up.  We have to look at commercial rates, which should be charged on a profit system instead of by square footage.</p><p>The other huge issue, which many Members have already raised today, is broadband in rural areas.  This is a huge issue.  There was a report this morning that 20% of rural businesses do not have broadband.  In certain areas, I imagine some of them do not even have mobile phone reception.  To kick the can down the road to 2020 is to kick it too far.  We should be implementing this and getting it on the road in the next three to four years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#W00300"><p>I am delighted to welcome the Minister to the House and I was also delighted to have met her in Carlow last Friday.  It is great to see a female Minister.  I am thrilled and wish her well.  It is great for women because I always think we fight for everything.</p> <p>I want to talk about the south east.  As she knows, it continues to have the highest unemployment rate.  An action plan for jobs has been set up but I was disappointed recently, when researching this area, to discover that IDA Ireland visited Dublin more than 100 times last year while Carlow got two visits.  Will the Minister look after rural Ireland?  Rural Ireland is so important and towns like Carlow, Bagenalstown, Hacketstown and Tullow also need employment.  We need IDA Ireland to visit us more often.  Will the Minister address the issue and revert to me on it?</p> <p>As the Minister knows, in the past week there has been major coverage in all the newspapers on the university for the south east.  That is massive.  It is massive for Carlow because Carlow IT is one of the biggest employers in Carlow, employing more than 700 people.  Further, it is crucial to have university status for the south east, especially Carlow and Waterford.  Figures show that 7,260 people are missing out on higher education places because of this.  This is crucial for students and parents who want to give their children an education in life that can open up many a door.  Will the Minister commit on this because it is crucial for the south east?</p> <p>I know the issue of apprenticeships has been addressed already.  These are vital in building a skilled workforce and I think that aspect is missing.  We need as many jobs as possible but we need to ensure that there are apprenticeships for people who want to become electricians, builders and plumbers.  We have to ensure that they are being catered for as well.  This is something I feel the Minister will address.  It is something that needs to be addressed. Not to be repetitive but between 2011 to 2015, 338,000 people emigrated from Ireland due to lack of jobs.  SMEs provide great jobs and employment but they are not getting credit from banks.  Credit is a massive issue and these enterprises are not getting the support they need.  Will the Minister ensure that SMEs are looked after and get the credit they need from banks?</p> <p>Another matter that is very dear to my heart because I have been dealing with cases in respect of it in the local authority is local development contributions.  I know of a case where in the boom a building was bought but the banks now own it.  There are people who are interested in buying this building.  They will create jobs and give employment but for them to buy this building they are being asked to pay a &euro;70,000 development contribution to the local authority.  Will the Minister please do something about these development contributions?  They need to be taken away.  That is what is stopping small SMEs from setting up new businesses.  Will the Minister address the issue?</p> <p>We have spoken about rates.  We also have what is called the global re-evaluation of rates and businesses.  It is a newly introduced system.  There is an awful fear now because small businesses are being reassessed for their rates and many of them are being increased.  Will the Minister examine this global re-evaluation to ensure rates do not go up?  I can tell the Minister that I know of three or four people who are being assessed and whose rates are being increased.  This will result in the loss of jobs.  Evaluations are great and all but at the end of the day it must be ensured that the rates paid by businesses are not increasing.</p> <p>I was a little surprised that the issue of online shopping was not addressed this morning.  Online shopping is absolutely huge, in particular for younger people who are inclined to be spending all the time.  What can be done?  As the Minister knows, towns such as Carlow, Bagenalstown and Hacketstown are trying to rejuvenate their town centres.  This issue needs to be addressed.  We need to ensure that new shops open and that footfall is increased in town centres.  These town centres are affected by online shopping.  I do not wish to be repetitive but broadband is definitely affecting businesses, as is phone coverage.</p> <p>All I can tell the Minister is that we have what I too believe is called the working poor.  These people can only afford to have one parent go out to work because they cannot afford the cost of child care.  Will the Minister please look after the working person?  This is the person that is most affected.  Will she ensure the south east gets its fair representation from IDA Ireland and from businesses and will she ensure that university status is achieved for Carlow and the south east?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1415" speakername="Maura Hopkins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#W00500"><p>I wish the Leas-Chathaoirleach well in his new position.  I also congratulate our Minister, Deputy Mitchell O'Connor, on her new appointment and wish her every success in her new role.  This is my first contribution in the Seanad and I believe it appropriate that I would do so on the important issue of sustainable full employment.  As a young Senator from Roscommon, I believe the single biggest issue facing the west is the need to create greater job opportunities.  North Roscommon is one particular region in the west which has suffered hugely from lack of employment opportunities over recent years and outward migration, with many of our young people working in more urban centres.</p> <p>As Senator John O'Mahony pointed out, the good work of the Western Development Commission in conducting research has found that between 2012 and 2015, the total number of people at work in the west grew by almost 3% whereas the number of people at work in the rest of the country grew by 6%, that is, by double the amount.  The said report, which was published two years ago, also emphasised the real challenges we face in our rural areas.  Towns such as Ballaghaderreen, Boyle, Castlerea, Strokestown and Carrick-on-Shannon have great communities.  We have huge potential, but we need support and help to breathe life back into our towns and make them attractive again for young people to return to work and set up business.</p> <p>As stated by the Minister, the programme for a partnership Government has set ambitious targets.  It is important that we set ambitious targets.  The last Government showed huge progress in ensuring that our unemployment rate is now under 8%.  The new commitment surrounds ensuring that we have an extra 200,000 people back at work by 2020, with 135,000 of these people working outside Dublin.  It is absolutely critical that we deliver on this target.</p> <p>Last Monday was a really good day in Ballinasloe, with the creation of 100 new jobs in a medical devices company along with an investment of almost &euro;10 million in research and development.  I thank the Minister for attending.  The employment of 100 additional people in Ballinasloe will have a hugely positive impact on the town and surrounding area.  It will create an environment where highly skilled individuals are attracted back to our region to live, work and raise their families.  The Government must continue to create an environment where we see more action like this.  Many of our rural areas offer excellent educational, sporting and community facilities as well as a great quality of life.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Maura Hopkins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2478"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2478&amp;amp;pid=MauraHopkins&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Recently, Roscommon County Council introduced a rates incentive scheme for new businesses opening in derelict or vacant premises, which is progressive.  However, it needs to be more ambitious in the short term for it to be successful.  We cannot do this alone and central government across relevant Departments must take a more active role in assisting with funding of important initiatives like this.  Broadband, mentioned several times in the context of this debate, is the single most important priority in infrastructure on which we must deliver.  There should be urgent action on broadband delivery in rural areas.  We are currently at a competitive disadvantage.  Action must be taken because matters are not moving quickly enough.</p><p>I ask that every effort be made to assist those areas with the greatest need.  It is absolutely critical that every employment agency should invest its energy and prioritise support and funding to areas that are in dire need in order to attract people back.  From actively seeking the generation of ideas to assistance with funding applications to those funding applications being approved to allow for the creation of sustainable jobs, these employment agencies must act.  The good work of the Western Development Commission has already been mentioned.  That work has the potential to be expanded.  Enterprise Ireland, local enterprise offices and others must be proactive in assisting the process.  The regional action plan for jobs seeks in some way to achieve this but we need to have more localised targets - even down to specific towns - in order to ensure progress is measured and delivered.  The Commission for the Economic Development of Rural Areas, CEDRA, report emphasised the need for the development of rural economic development, RED, zones in towns and their hinterlands.</p><p>I very much welcome the Minister's focus on the need to place greater emphasis on supporting rural areas and tackling youth and long-term unemployment.  Real action is needed, however, if our young people are to return to the west, where there is much potential for many individuals to enjoy a great place to live, work and raise a family.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#X00200"><p>I thank the Leas-Chathaoirleach.  It is my first time to speak before him and I am delighted to welcome him to his new position in the Chair.  I am delighted to see the Minister and to see her appointed to her portfolio.  I would love to have seen her appointed to the education portfolio, as her expertise could really be used there.  On considering the matter, however, I know she will bring a new perspective to the area of job creation because of her educational background merging with a desire to drive forward issues.  I have known the Minister for many years as a very hard-working politician and I am sure she will put in much effort to the role she has been given.  I congratulate her again.</p> <p>I stated yesterday that I did not want the Seanad to be laboured with statements during current session.  With respect to colleagues, we are reiterating what members of the public hear every day of the week from the political class.  It would be more useful to sit down to consider three or four initiatives that might lead to job creation rather than making rand statements about broadband, roads and various other matters.  We should be trying to single out a couple of issues that would assist the Minister in driving matters forward.</p> <p>With all due respect to my colleague from the south east, the establishment of 16 university campuses in Ireland would do nothing for job creation.  The likes of Massachusetts Institute of Technology, MIT, one of the most renowned academic institutions in the world, does not need the tag "university" to make it relevant.  I was in Carlow recently at the military graduation and I can state that it is the finest third level establishment and has the most forward-thinking people with whom one could ever ask to work.  It does not need the tag "university" to make it relevant.  Carlow Institute of Technology is delivering educational programmes to Aer Lingus in Dublin and the military-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#X00300"><p>Why is the Senator so worried about Carlow?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016061600002#X00400"><p>We must adjourn the debate as per the order of the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-16a.132" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>The Seanad adjourned at 2.15 p.m. until 2.30 p.m. on Tuesday, 21 June 2016.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>