<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.4" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Marc MacSharry that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to explain the delays in appointments being granted to patients referred to the symptomatic breast clinics at University College Hospital Galway and Letterkenny General Hospital within the best practice required timeframe despite some individuals presenting with both mastalgia and a lump and the fact that as few as 16% of urgent cases are being seen within the medical best practice target timeframe at some of these centres.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator David Cullinane of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Education and Skills to provide an update on the progress to date in respect of the plans for a technical university for the south east.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Hildegarde Naughton of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation to intervene to ensure existing jobs and future expansion are not put at risk at Parkmore industrial estate, Galway.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Michael Comiskey of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Arts, Heritage and the Gaeltacht to investigate a recent issue which has arisen with regard to performing rights for amateur drama groups in Ireland whereby applications for performing rights for certain plays have been transferred from the Drama League of Ireland to an agency in London.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Paschal Mooney of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister of State with responsibility for the Office of Public Works to seek funding to combat coastal erosion at Tullaghan, County Leitrim, which seriously threatens Tynte Lodge, a listed building, and the two castellated stone folly towers on the cliff top overlooking the Atlantic Ocean.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Catherine Noone of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Finance to outline the current position regarding the home carer tax credit, how many people are in receipt of same and if there are plans to reform it.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Colm Burke of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Education and Skills to work with the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs towards providing adequate funding for the Life Centre in Cork.</blockquote> <p>I regard the matters raised by the Senators as suitable for discussion.  I have selected the matters raised by Senators MacSharry, Cullinane and Naughton and they will be taken now.  Senators Mooney, Noone and Burke may give notice on another day of the matters they wish to raise.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.7" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#A00300">Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.8" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#A00500">Cancer Screening Programmes</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#A00550"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Paudie Coffey.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#A00600"><p>Notwithstanding the fact that the Minister of State has taken the time to come to the House, I am disappointed that the Minister, Deputy Varadkar, is not here for the debate on this very important issue.  Some weeks ago, I raised with the Minister the issue of ladies being referred to the symptomatic breast clinic at University Hospital Galway and who, effectively, were being sent home to undertake a form-filling exercise and to self-monitor for three months.  At that time, I expressed concern to the effect that this is critical time that could be lost for those people, particularly if they are among the 7% of individuals who go from suffering with mastalgia, or breast pain, to developing the more serious problem of breast cancer.  I was particularly worried by the fact that the Minister described the person on whose behalf I raised the matter as being the subject of an inappropriate referral.  That proved not to be the case.  The woman in question was lucky enough to have the funds available to allow her to have a private assessment carried out.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Marc MacSharry:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2010"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2010&amp;amp;pid=MarcMacSharry&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Thankfully, it happens that all is well and she is not one of the 7%, but the question that I rightly posed at the time was about those who were.<br/><br/>Today has seen a worse situation.  Following the press coverage of my raising the matter with the Minister, Deputy Varadkar, a lady contacted me.  I will quote most of her e-mail, as it speaks for itself.  She wrote:</p><blockquote>On reading the article I felt a pang of personal concern as I am currently on the public waiting list to see a doctor in Galway Breast Clinic.  Initially I was told by the clinic I would only be 4-6 weeks due to the fact I was referred with a lump and discomfort in each breast and I am in a high risk group.  The clinic confirmed on the day of my appointment to see the doctor if required any tests, mammograms would be completed.<br /><br />After the 6 weeks passed, I re-contacted the hospital to learn that it may be up to next Feb before I see a doctor and any tests I may require will not be completed on the day.  The lady was very kind and mentioned to contact my GP, [but that] realistically it is highly unlikely I would be seen before Christmas.  Earliest may be Jan, latest end of Feb.<br /><br />I am now quietly scared and worried, I had an encounter with cancer over ten years ago and it was early detection through the public system that prevented me having to go through a lot of treatment.  Surgery and careful monitoring was [sufficient].<br /><br />I am doing my best to stay positive, I do understand and take on board that over 70% of women with lumps and discomfort are usually okay and it can be hormonal or contraception issues.  At the back of my troubled mind is the little nagging doubt... when I get to Galway will I have lost vital time?</blockquote><p>These words are compelling and speak for themselves.  While I appreciate that the Minister of State's area of responsibility is the environment and not health, this is an issue that requires the highest action by the Government.  Recent years have seen debacles in the shutting down of various breast clinics, the setting up of other breast clinics and the so-called centres of excellence.  In a matter of a couple of weeks, we have encountered two further incidents, one involving someone who had cancer previously and is in a high-risk age group being put on the never-never and another involving someone who was sent a booklet and told to self-monitor and fill out forms.  The first person, who had more serious symptoms in terms of lumps and pain, was told that the clinic might get to her by the end of February and that not all of her tests would be done on that day.<br/><br/>There are also reports that the symptomatic breast clinic in Letterkenny is only seeing 16% of high-priority patients within the required timeframe.  It is important to portray the health system as going well and, when one is lucky enough to access the service, the health professionals are probably doing very good work for people, but it is not acceptable for us to massage waiting lists and put patients like these two ladies at risk.  I am sure that is not the Minister of State's intention.  I worked with him in this House when he was a Senator.<br/><br/>It is unacceptable that the Minister, Deputy Varadkar's approach to this issue when it was first raised a few weeks ago concerning a different patient was to speak of inappropriate referrals.  The Minister of State has heard this lady's words.  She had a brush with cancer previously and is in the high-risk age group, yet she, too, is being put on the never-never.  When the Minister of State leaves the Chamber, will he immediately contact the Minister, if not the Taoiseach as well, and ask that the appropriate interventions be made in the first instance for this patient, on whose behalf I have written to the Minister, and to outline how many people are only in this space because we seemingly do not have the resources in the Galway-Letterkenny-Sligo area to deal with them?  We will seek to amend the Order of Business to bring the Minister to the House on other health matters.  I might have an opportunity to raise this issue with him then, but this is not the appropriate time and I do not want to take from the importance of this issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1092" speakername="Paudie Coffey" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#B00200"><p>I thank Senator MacSharry for raising this issue and giving me the opportunity to update the House.  I am taking this debate on behalf of the Minister, Deputy Varadkar, who apologises for unfortunately not being able to attend.</p> <p>The symptomatic breast clinic in Galway forms part of a range of services that is in place for women with breast symptoms.  Referrals are dealt with in accordance with the guidelines that have been developed by the national cancer control programme, NCCP.  Most women experience breast pain at some stage.  While this can cause worry, it is found that, in the absence of other symptoms, breast pain is rarely indicative of breast cancer.  The NCCP, in collaboration with the Irish College of General Practitioners, ICGP, developed a booklet to support women with breast pain.  It explains the types of breast pain, their possible causes and how pain might be easily remedied.  It contains a three-month diary to help determine whether the pain is cyclical, as this information can help with prevention and care.  This approach is evidence-based and regarded as good practice.  The booklet highlights the importance of making a specialist referral if other symptoms are present.</p> <p>General Practitioners, GPs, have also been provided with a guideline for managing breast pain in primary care centres.  This guideline contains the same advice as that in the patient booklet.  Where the patient's clinical examination is normal, she is asked to follow the advice in the booklet for three months.  If, after that time, the pain has not been resolved, a referral is warranted.  All referrals to the symptomatic breast clinics in Dublin, Cork, Waterford, Limerick, Galway and Letterkenny are triaged on receipt and appointments are then offered.</p> <p>Breast cancer survival rates have increased significantly in recent years due to a combined approach of screening, symptomatic detection and improved treatment.  Breast cancer five-year survival is estimated at 81% for women diagnosed between 2006 and 2011, representing an increase from 72% for those diagnosed between 1994 and 1999.</p> <p>Last November, the Minister announced the extension of BreastCheck to the 65-69 year age group in keeping with EU guidelines.  I am pleased to confirm that the first invitations have issued and the screening of 500 women in that cohort will take place this year.  Earlier this year, the Minister launched the national clinical guidelines on the diagnosis, staging and treatment of patients with breast cancer.  Clinical effectiveness is fundamental to our health service.  Implementing good quality clinical guidelines and audits can improve health outcomes for patients, reduce variations in practice and improve the quality of clinical decisions.</p> <p>The Minister has asked me to assure the Senator that all women with breast symptoms are welcome at specialist breast services, including those with persistent and troublesome breast pain as outlined in the guidelines.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#B00300"><p>What about lumps?  We heard nothing about those.  This is not the Minister of State's core area but, to quote the lady in question, "when I get to Galway will I have lost vital time?"  These patients are not being referred by lay people, traffic wardens or people in the street.  They are being referred by medical professionals with seven years of training.  I am bound to say that these delays and the speeches today and by the Minister about best medical practice do not stack up.  There was no mention of the individual patient, but the Minister's office is aware of this case.  Will the Minister of State raise her case with the Minister?  She is on the never-never.  She has breast lumps and pain, so it is not just mastalgia.  The form filling, book reading exercise is not one that gives confidence to the ladies of the north west.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1092" speakername="Paudie Coffey" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#B00400"><p>I welcome the Senator's raising of an important matter.  Any elected representative would identify cancer as a major challenge for any family touched by it.  The Senator is right to state that concerns arise where ladies find lumps in their breasts.  It is important that there be early intervention and diagnosis to deal with problems.</p> <p>I will reiterate the Minister's comments.  He assures the House that all women with breast symptoms are welcome at specialist breast services, including women with persistent and troublesome breast pain as outlined in the guidelines.  As to the specific case raised by the Senator, I undertake to relay his concerns to the Minister directly.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.15" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#B00500">Technological Universities</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#B00600"><p>I welcome the Minister, Deputy Bruton, to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#B00700"><p>I also welcome the Minister and thank him for taking this important motion, even though it does not fall into his portfolio.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator David Cullinane:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2357"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2357&amp;amp;pid=DavidCullinane&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I am glad the Minister has taken this Commencement matter because he has taken a hands-on approach to what has been happening in the south east in recent years with the jobs action plan and the south-east action plan as well.  The Minister will be aware of the importance of the need for a technological university for the south east.  I am sure that in all the consultations he has had in the area and the region generally, the need for that university to be put in place comes up every time.  It is seen by all the policymakers and stakeholders, including captains of industry, the business community generally, trade unions and those within the institutes of technology, that this clearly needs to happen for the region.  By having a university the south east would then be on a level playing field.  It is a vital cog in the region in terms of economic development and it needs to be delivered.</p><p>The problem is that the Government strategy up to now has been dogged with problems, delays and disagreements - some of them internal in the region while others are external.  At times there has been chaos.  The whole project came to a halt last year and then we had the appointment of Professor Michael Kelly and subsequently the publication of the Kelly report.  We were led to believe that the report would offer a roadmap and some sort of direction on how we could get to the end product, which is a technological university for the south east.</p><p>I am very supportive of a technological university and have backed that strategy from day 1.  As the Minister knows, in 2012, I published a report on the issue.  I was involved in consultations across the region and heard at first-hand the desire, need and support for such a university.  I hate to say this but at this point we do not seem to have a clear plan, model, the necessary engagement, or the required buy-in.  I do not see that buy-in coming either from the Department or the Higher Education Authority.  There is a clear problem in that it is all very abstract.  We all know that we want a technological university but there is no vision or model that people can buy into.  Without such a model it is more difficult to convince people in the Carlow and Waterford institutes of technology who might be hostile or negative towards the creation of a technological university.  It gives them the excuse when we do not have a tangible model that people can see.  What we need is a new university, but such a model is simply not there.</p><p>I am seeking an update from the Minister as to where exactly the strategy currently is.  Do we have any indication as to a roadmap, timeframes or when we will arrive at the final destination?  Many people are sceptical about all this and it is not even seen in the context of a broken Government promise; it is a question of whether or not the region and the other stakeholders from the Department and the HEA are really committed to making this happen.  Are they committed to bringing it to life and ensuring that the region will have a university?  </p><p>I do not want to place all the problems on the Minister's shoulders or the Government generally because there are many different issues at play here.  We need to name them and to be clear about where the problems lie.  We also need to have a clear roadmap, plan and model.  Unfortunately, however, I do not see them at this point.  Perhaps the Minister can give us a positive update today on where things are.  I look forward to his response.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#C00200"><p>I thank Senator Cullinane for raising this issue.  From my own work in the region I know it is regarded as being pivotal for the long-term development of the south east.  To be fair, when the National Strategy for Higher Education to 2030 was published back in January 2011, there was a clear roadmap as to what needed to be done.  The journey was clearly mapped out and it recommended the consolidation of the institutes of technology sector and the creation of a small number of multi-campus technological universities.  That is the roadmap that people now need to fulfil.</p> <p>The process for designation as a technological university, TU, consists of four stages and requires the merger of two or more institutes of technology prior to application for designation as a TU.  The technological university for the south-east project was initiated in 2011 and consists of a consortium of Carlow and Waterford institutes of technology.  The consortium made good progress initially and submitted a stage 1 expression of interest in 2012.  However, following this initial promising start, the consortium encountered a series of challenges and difficulties, and did not succeed in finalising a stage 2 plan prior to the decision by WIT to suspend merger activities in October 2014.</p> <p>Following meetings with both institutes in early November 2014, the Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy Jan O'Sullivan, announced the establishment of a new process of engagement and consultation with the governing bodies, staff and students of both institutes, together with the wider community in the south east.  The Minister appointed Mr. Michael Kelly to lead the process of consultation.  While a ten-week timeframe was initially set for the process to be completed, the timeframe to completion was extended due to a number of factors, including the change in governing authorities of both institutions at the end of the first quarter of 2015.</p> <p>The Minister for Education and Skills recently met with Mr. Kelly and received his report on the outcome of the engagement and consultation process.  Mr. Kelly has undertaken a thorough and extensive consultation process with regional stakeholders on this important issue.  Mr. Kelly met with stakeholders in all counties of the region in the last few months, including local authorities, chambers of commerce, employers, the enterprise development agencies, and social and community croups, as well as public representatives.  I understand that some 40 meetings took place and the Minister wants to place on record her</p> <p>Mr. Kelly presented his report to the Minister on 2 July last.  Following receipt of that report, the Minister discussed it with Cabinet colleagues.  She subsequently met with the presidents and chairpersons of both institutions on 21 July to discuss the findings and recommendations in the report.  The report was published on 27 July.</p> <p>As outlined at the time of publication, it was agreed that a plan for a process of preliminary facilitation would be developed by mid-August for consideration at ITC and WIT governing body meetings planned for the end of August.  The facilitation process is the first step recommended by Mr. Kelly in order to assist with building mutual trust and respect between the two institutions.  The governing bodies of both institutions held meetings at the end of August and agreed to engage in the proposed facilitation process, which is now under way.  The Minister is pleased to report that there has been very good engagement in the facilitation process by the presidents and chairpersons of both institutions to date.  This is an important building block for future collaboration.  The Minister expects this facilitation process to be completed before year end.</p> <p>The Minister believes there is a compelling rationale for a new type of higher education institution to support the economic and social development of the entire south-east region and this is clearly the wish of stakeholders in the region.  The Government is committed to supporting the development of such an institution.  The Senator can see from this reply that the Minister for Education and Skills has been very active in seeking to get this issue across the line.  The work in this respect is ongoing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#C00300"><p>It is obviously good and useful that both institutes are at least talking and that some progress is being made, if I am to take the Minister's word at face value.  I am sure that some progress has been made.  I have spoken to people in both institutes on numerous occasions, as well as other stakeholders mainly in Waterford but also in the wider region.  The problem is that while they may be talking and there might be some progress, in the absence of a visible plan and model it is difficult to see how we can get to the end product.</p> <p>The Minister is correct in saying that there is a legislative process in place which enables institutes to merge.  That is fair enough and they are the nuts and bolts of how a merger can be created.  We should ask what this technological university will mean for the south east, what model it will be, what type of courses it will deliver and where the main campus will be.  All these issues are not there, however, so people do not see the big picture.  Maybe that is one of the reasons we have these stumbling blocks because there will obviously be tensions within both institutes.  In the absence of a clearly worked out model on the table, I would fear for the future of this project, although I am hugely supportive of it.  I want to see it getting over the line, the same as everybody else.  We all do, but we are nearly five years into this Government's term of office and unfortunately we cannot say that we are close to the end by any stretch of the imagination.  I am not saying that all, or even any of it, is the Government's fault, but I am saying that there are clear problems.  In my view, the biggest problem is that there is an absence of an actual model.  Until we get that model, which may have to come from both institutes, I do not think people will have confidence that it will in fact be delivered.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#C00400"><p>First of all, the two institutions have been very important in this regard.  I have worked to try to drive employment creation in the region.  It is gratifying to see that in the last three years 24,000 extra people are at work in the south east.</p> <p>I have also worked with both colleges in supporting new enterprises - one in China with Carlow Institute of Technology, and several from Waterford Institute of Technology.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Richard Bruton:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=119"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=119&amp;amp;pid=RichardBruton&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->They offer great technology and great support to enterprise.</p><p>Ultimately, a marriage is about the meeting of two sides and about people having a degree of consensus and understanding that their relationship is a working one.  I have just been going through Mr. Michael Kelly's report and he has set out that this can be delivered within three years.  As a result, there is an ambition or a roadmap, as the Senator described it, in place.  Mr. Kelly is highly committed and he made a huge effort to bring this together but this process must go through a systematic route and it has to be something that endures and adds value in the region.  To be fair, in the context of the work that has been done by all players, a route has emerged but moving forward will require everyone working together.  One thing I have discovered from working in respect of the south east is that bringing people together is an important part of lifting a region.  This is one of the areas in which - just as we did elsewhere - we seek to work to build new collaborations.  I am optimistic for the south east and this is an important element but it must be done right and on a sustainable basis, which the Senator recognises.  I will convey his concern to the Minister but people are putting in a significant effort to make this work.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.23" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#D00150">Industrial Development</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1187" speakername="Hildegarde Naughton" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#D00200"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House and I thank him for taking the time to deal with this important issue.  In light of yesterday's encouraging unemployment figures, the lowest since 2008, it is more important than ever that we should not take our eyes off the ball.  The Minister agrees that we must do everything we can to continue to drive the recovery and the best way to do that is to create high-value, secure jobs while also ensuring that existing employment is maintained and developed.  It is in this light that I wish to raise the issue of Parkmore industrial estate in Galway city.  The Minister will be aware that IDA Ireland has been excellent in marketing this hub.  It is home to companies from various industries, including medical devices, IT and research and development.  More than 7,000 employees commute to the area daily and the value of that number of jobs is significant not just for Galway but for the western region as a whole.</p> <p>Business leaders in the area have informed the public that severe traffic issues are having a direct effect on expansion, business productivity and the quality of life of their employees.  Such is the problem that businesses have engaged in car pooling and flexitime for employees to ease the stress involved in getting to and from work.  It is a simple fact that a relatively short commute in the area can take a multiple of the time it should.  This problem did not appear overnight; it has become increasingly worse over the past two to three years and has reached the stage where business leaders in Parkmore have formed a group comprising chief executive officers and senior executives of the companies in the area to voice their concerns.  The group has agreed to work with Galway City Council, Galway County Council and IDA Ireland in a constructive and proactive manner in order to try to find solutions.  There are options on short-term, medium-term and long-term solutions, including changes to traffic light signalling, road markings, the addition of more exits, new bus routes and additional lanes at junctions.  All these will help but they involve multiple agencies, including CIE, IDA Ireland, two local authorities, the National Roads Authority, NRA, and various other State agencies involved in planning.  Funding is also an issue in the context of the works required.</p> <p>The overarching consideration is jobs.  While there has been movement in that the local authorities and IDA Ireland have met business representatives from the area to formulate a plan, I am concerned that, following several years of traffic chaos, we might experience more years of administrative delays until this matter is resolved.  It is simply not good enough that we, as a nation, cannot sort out our infrastructure in a timely manner to ensure that jobs in Parkmore are retained and further investment is encouraged.  I do not seek to blame anyone.  Like the Minister, I am in the business of solution politics but I ask him, as a matter of urgency, to contact the State bodies concerns to emphasise the importance the Government places on the retention of jobs in Parkmore and future expansion there and to offer whatever assistance is required.  I have details of the business community group in Parkmore.  Will the Minister agree to meet a delegation from Parkmore to hear for himself the frustrations and issues of the employers and their employees?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#D00300"><p>I am aware of the issue and I have met some of the people involved.  IDA Ireland is working hard with the local authority to find a solution to this.  It is correct that this is a frustrating experience for a number of companies at Parkmore business park.  It has been a successful park with companies such as Metronic, Merit Medical, Celestica and Creganna.  The pressure has built against a background where over the past four years IDA Ireland has expanded its employment base in Galway by 33%, with 3,500 additional people working in its companies.  The other backdrop to this is I have recognised clearly that we need to develop a much more integrated regional enterprise strategy where local authorities, State agencies and educational institutions work together as they seek to develop sectoral opportunities.  It is very much part of my thinking to embrace the local authority as an equal partner in seeking to drive this matter forward.</p> <p>IDA Ireland has been examining this matter for some time.  It has developed proposals and is in discussions with the local authority in respect of them.  Meetings were held as recently as last week and, arising out of them, both parties and their engineering teams are considering how this can be resolved.  The Senator is correct that there is an immediate problem for the industrial estate.  However, the local authorities are developing a longer term solution, which involves a considerable number of additional measures such as adding traffic signals, a widening of the road and changes at the N17 Parkmore Road junction.  A comprehensive plan is under development and the urgency has arisen, particularly since schools reopened in September, because the companies experiencing significant congestion.</p> <p>Mr. Pat Dunne, the managing director of Creganna has set up a group, which is active in this regard, and the IDA is working closely with them.  I assure the Senator that this issue is not bring overlooked.  IDA Ireland, which is under my remit, is working closely with the engineers and I hope that a solution can be developed.  I spoke to IDA Ireland officials earlier and will continue my contacts with them.  I will also speak to local authority officials should that be helpful.  A sincere effort is being made by all sides to find a solution to a problem that has resulted from the success of the park and the region.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1187" speakername="Hildegarde Naughton" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#D00400"><p>I thank the Minister for his detailed reply and I welcome his engagement with the relevant agencies.  I appreciate that work is going in the background but, given the number of agencies involved, there are many different moving parts involved.  Leadership is needed whereby one person can pull all those moving parts together to make sure there are targets, delivery times and a timeframe.  That would give greater confidence to the employers and employees working on the industrial estate.  Many practical solutions can be put in place and I welcome the Minister's intervention in the context of speaking with IDA Ireland officials.  I would welcome it if he contacted the local authorities as well because we cannot afford to allow this matter drift any longer.  There are solutions and people are willing to put in the time and effort, including the business community.  Businesspeople have been proactive and they have approached this in a positive and constructive manner.  However, there is a leadership issue with regard to setting timeframes and pushing the matter forward to ensure jobs are protected and industries in the west can develop.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#D00500"><p>I agree with the Senator that timeliness is essential..  I fully recognise there are different bodies involved with different demands, standards and expectations to meet and they have to make sure that agreed proposal is robust within the context of the demands which are rightly placed on them.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Richard Bruton:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=119"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=119&amp;amp;pid=RichardBruton&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We have to work within that.  There has been good engagement on both sides.  There is a willingness to find a solution.  The Senator is correct.  We need to be able to find timelines for interim and longer-term measures and to see those integrated in a sensible way.</p><p>As I understand it, the two sides have had useful engagements.  The engineering teams on both sides are assessing their respective needs and potential to resolve this issue.  There is a willingness to do this.  We have recognised at national level that a big part of continuing our recovery is to have a closer integration at regional level.  The Department of Public Enterprise and Reform has agreed funding for significant property investment by the IDA to resolve issues over time and create the capacity to develop.  There is a commitment on all sides to find a solution.  Having raised the issue, I hope the Senator will underline her anxiety and that of many business people to see that the issues which are important are handled in a speedy and effective way.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.29" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 11.12 a.m. and resumed at 11.30 a.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.30" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#G00100">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#G00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, motion re Planning and Development (Urgent Social Housing Supply) Policy Directive 2015 - referral to committee, to be taken on the conclusion of the Order of Business, without debate; No. 2, Child Care (Amendment) Bill 2015 - Report and Final Stages, to be taken at 12.45 p.m. and to adjourn not later than 2 p.m., if not previously concluded; No. 3, Finance (Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill 2015 &ndash; Committee and Remaining Stages, to be taken at 3.30 p.m., with all Stages to conclude not later than 4.30 p.m., if not previously concluded; and No. 4, motion for the earlier signature of the Finance (Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill 2015, to be taken on the conclusion of No. 3, without debate.  Private Members' business is No. 71, motion 17, to be taken at 4.30 p.m., with the time allocated for this debate not to exceed two hours.  The House will also have tributes to former Senator Jack Fitzsimons at 2 p.m., to conclude not later than 2.45 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#G00300"><p>I propose an amendment to the Order of Business, namely, that the Minister for Health, Deputy Leo Varadkar, come to the House to account for his supreme ability to talk the talk and inability to walk the walk.  The latest debacle is the complete abandonment by the Government of its plan to introduce universal health insurance, which has been Fine Gael policy since 2007 and Labour Party policy since 2001.  Minister after Minister promised the plan would be implemented.  Meanwhile, queues are lengthening and cancer patients in the north west who are in high-risk categories are unable to get appointments.  When I raised this issue this morning during Commencement Matters, the Government could only muster a Minister of State at the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government.  Such is the priority it gives to these matters.</p> <p>The supreme commentator, the Minister for Health, Deputy Varadkar, tells us that everything is still on track and going to plan, despite the Government's complete abandonment in the past 24 hours of one of the core and sacred elements of its five-point plan, namely, universal health insurance.  In 2013, the Fianna F&aacute;il Party commissioned our own research from health economist, Dr. Brian Turner.  We highlighted and advised the Government that its plan for universal health insurance was not possible and would cost more.  However, the Government pressed ahead with its plan, which the Taoiseach stated his Government intended to deliver.  When it was put to him as to how he could do this in a time of crisis - the Minister argues now that it is no longer possible to do so at this time of crisis - the Taoiseach stated, "I respectfully disagree.  Real reform only occurs in times of crisis."</p> <p>I have no doubt that another five-point fantasy plan will be put to the people to buy the next general election, as occurred during the previous general election campaign.  This time, however, the Government will not be able to follow a plan produced by the late Brian Lenihan and may find itself on its own.</p> <p>It is important that the Minister for Health comes to the House to account for the total mismanagement of the health service.  The Fine Gael Party was right to shaft the previous Minister for Health.  Great hopes surrounded the capabilities of the current Minister.  As a physician, I am sure it galls him to have to put up with the level of mediocrity that surrounds him at the Cabinet table and the lack of resources that have been provided.  The former and current Ministers for Health and the Taoiseach are in complete denial and deluded when they speak of being vindicated and everything being very much on track.  I did not believe it possible to trump the headless chicken approach associated with the performance of the previous Minister for Health, Deputy Reilly.  In the past 24 hours, however, we had the comedy of the current Minister describing the fiasco of universal health insurance as a vindication.  We must press to ensure he comes to the House today to account for himself.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#H00200"><p>Can the Senator provide the wording of the proposed amendment?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#H00300"><p>I propose that the Minister for Health, Deputy Leo Varadkar, come to the House today to account for the fiasco which is the Government's abandonment of universal health insurance.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#H00400"><p>I congratulate those couples who got married yesterday, the first day on which gay couples in Ireland were able to marry.  It was a very welcome and historic day and it was great to see celebratory photographs in the newspapers after such grim news from Paris and elsewhere in recent days.  I know all colleagues will want to join me in welcoming what happened yesterday.</p> <p>I welcome the new Stormont House agreement, A Fresh Start, reached in Northern Ireland yesterday.  I hope it offers some resolution of the outstanding issues which have been obstructing progress for so many months in Northern Ireland.  I ask for a debate on the changes and their relevance to us, particularly the proposed change in corporation tax.  While our schedule is very full in terms of legislation between now and Christmas, we might have a debate early in the new year once we have had time to absorb the terms of the new agreement.  I also welcome the fact that we were able to conclude Committee Stage of the Residential Tenancies (Amendment) (No. 2) Bill last night.  The Bill and the changes to it debated on Committee Stage received a broad welcome across the House.  It was a constructive debate and I look forward to the speedy passage of the Bill.  The Leader might confirm that Report Stage will be taken next week.</p> <p>I welcome the schools building programme.  Many colleagues referred to it on the Order of Business yesterday and I referred to it in my response.  It is particularly welcome to see a new secondary school proposed for my own area in Dublin's south inner city.  That school is very much needed and the announcement in respect of it is welcome.  I hope it will be an Educate Together school because there is a huge need for multi-denominational secondary schools to accommodate the many children who are coming out of Educate Together primary schools in the north and south inner cities.  We will also see a development at the Harcourt Terrace premises where there was a school previously, the Portobello Educate Together national school, which I was involved in setting up.  That school is also set for development into a three-stream school in Dublin 2.  I also welcome that.</p> <p>In responding on the Order of Business yesterday, I informed colleagues that we would seek a debate in due course on security issues in the context of the horrific attacks in Paris.  I know the Leader will support that call.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#H00500"><p>I echo what Senator Bacik has said about the Northern Ireland agreement, A Fresh Start, which includes compensation for the removal of the peace walls.  I hope the latter will be possible.  There will also be a fund to secure, once and for all, the end of paramilitary groups, which have done much damage.  There is also some funding for project relating to the A5, which connects Aughnacloy, Derry and Monaghan.  Watching the Stormont proceedings when the negotiations were on, it was clear that there is a working Parliament there of which all the Members can be proud.  That is surely an advance over the previous situations which obtained in Northern Ireland.  Nostalgia in the Ulster Unionist Party for traditional opposition is misplaced.  A power-sharing government is the way to proceed.  Traditional opposition politics along the lines of the Westminster model was tried for 50 years and it did not work.  It is not a society that needs an adversarial model.</p> <p>I note with concern that it is proposed to take the Legal Services Regulation Bill tomorrow.  What we know about the Bill indicates serious disarray in the Department of Justice and Equality.  Well after 8 p.m. last night, I received 68 pages of text from the Minister containing 159 amendments.  I do not think it is much of a Bill and I have tabled 37 amendments - across five pages - in respect of it.  Our colleagues in Sinn F&eacute;in have tabled 24 amendments and these cover eight pages.  It appears we are ignoring the advice of the troika to the effect that Ireland has a serious high-cost legal system that is damaging the economy.  Why do we implement cutbacks in respect of carers and social welfare and not implement the troika proposals regarding the legal system?  We are also ignoring the advice of the National Competitiveness Council about the damage which high legal costs are causing.  There is a report of approximately 200 pages in length from the former Competition Authority which points out that the Irish legal system is in need of serious root-and-branch reform.  We need separate conveyancing from the monopoly and the right to talk to a barrister without solicitors milking that transaction for fees.  The Bill we are due to discuss tomorrow seems to be a shambles.  It does not take into account the research that has been prepared.  In addition, it is being dealt with at the last minute, which is a bad way to proceed with legislation.  We should at least have the weekend to go through, as the Minister has, the 159 faults she sees with the Bill.  There are lots more as well.  We should not be taking that at less than 48 hours notice tomorrow.  If it is too late to take that item off the Order of Business for tomorrow, I wish to raise it today.  It is not the way we should be proceeding.  The Irish legal system needs massive overhaul and reform.  It is not effective, it is high cost and it exercises far too much influence over the Department of Justice and Equality and at the Cabinet table.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#H00600"><p>I join colleagues in welcoming the agreement reached in Northern Ireland last night.  It is the culmination of ten weeks of very hard work.  I pay tribute to everybody involved, including the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade, Deputy Charles Flanagan.  The agreement builds on the Stormont House Agreement and is, hopefully, a significant step in normalising politics in Northern Ireland and society generally.  The agreement is a credible roadmap for the implementation of many aspects of the Stormont House Agreement, tackling the continuing impact of paramilitarism, reconciling of all peoples on the island and bringing about of greater economic prosperity.  We all welcome the fact that a joint agency task force will be established to identify priorities for combating cross-Border organised crime and to oversee operational co-ordination.  This will be given additional resources.  This is an issue that has been raised by many Members in the House.  It is causing serious damage to economic life north and south of the Border and it is an issue that must be tackled.  Hopefully, the agreement will bring about greater prosperity and reconciliation on the island and the normalisation of politics even further.</p> <p>I very much welcome yesterday's announcement on the schools capital building programme.  Nationally, 310 schools will benefit.  Every county will see investment in new schools and refurbishment.  In County Galway alone, 30 projects will be funded between 2016 and 2021.  I am particularly pleased that in my town of Ballinasloe, the Scoil an Chro&iacute; Naofa will proceed in 2016 while the project relating to St. Theresa's special school will commence construction in 2019.  It is only right and proper that our children are educated in the best possible facilities and that we see the end of prefabricated buildings once and for all.  The programme will create much needed employment in the construction sector.  I welcome the fact that unemployment has fallen below 9%.  Hopefully, these construction projects will drive that figure down further over the coming years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1142" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#H00700"><p>I was not in the Chamber yesterday but I wish to add my voice to those which expressed shock and horror at the events in Paris.  Those events were barbaric in the extreme and they have left hundreds of families bereft.  It is worrying to note that major sporting events had to be cancelled yesterday and last night.  To a certain extent, this possibly creates a greater encouragement to these people and the hatred within them.  I hope and pray that politicians across the world will realise the gravity of the situation and pull together once and for all.  This has the potential to have the same impact as the events in Sarajevo in 1914 or invasion of Poland prior to the Second World War.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Ned O'Sullivan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2233"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2233&amp;amp;pid=NedOSullivan&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We are not too far away from a third world war if this kind of thing goes on.</p><p>On a brighter note I give a cautious welcome to the latest agreement in Northern Ireland.  Thank God they are not calling this one "historic" as that word has been played out.  It is encouraging and I am glad that our Government had an input into it, but for how much longer will the two major parties in the North expect everybody else to stop everything and hold their hands when they are having another one of their problem "stop the world I want to get off" fits? Real politicians are supposed to solve problems in a real way.  I have nothing against the two major parties but I am encouraged by the signs of life that are coming up in the Unionist side and the other Unionist group and in the change in leadership in the SDLP which may reinvigorate politics generally in the North and make for more inclusion by the people.  I have a feeling there is stranglehold up there and that people are possibly afraid to move outside the two major mega blocks of the Democratic Unionist Party and Sinn F&eacute;in.</p><p>I welcome, in advance, the announcement of the Fianna F&aacute;il programme to restore local government, and specifically town councils, if and when we are next in government which hopefully will not be too long away.  It was a rash move by the Ministers Phil Hogan and Alan Kelly and I think it is already having a negative effect in towns around the country.  I speak in particular of towns in Kerry and their sense of ownership of their mayor, their pride in their town hall and their town chamber.  All of that has been diminished despite the great work being done by the county councillors to fill the void which was created by the local area municipal groups.  I welcome a good, healthy debate on that issue in the new council on the new Seanad and I hope to be in the House to take part in that debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#J00200"><p>I welcome the passing of Committee Stage of the Residential Tenancies (Amendment) (No. 2) Bill last night and I thank all sides of the House for their general broad support for the measures it contained, especially in rent regulation and the introduction of the deposit protection scheme.  I also note the number of contributions during that debate which emphasised the need to expedite housing supply.  The Leader has indicated that he would be happy to have a debate on that subject and on the wider subject of access to home ownership.  Some of the measures proposed by Senator Barrett in his own Private Member's Bill are also worthy of consideration regarding access to finance for home ownership, specifically for low-income households.</p> <p>I ask the Leader for a debate on youth policy.  We had an excellent budget and, whether one thinks it was enough or not, there was something for nearly everybody in the audience but with the notable absence of provisions for the under 26 year olds.  We need to have a debate around our attitude towards young people and whether we do or do not consider them to be equal members of our society, especially when it comes to access to benefits.  I welcome yesterday's announcement that unemployment levels have fallen below 9%.  Clearly young people benefit significantly from that fall but there is a broader issue in terms of our under 26 year olds.  In an ideal world that should be debated by both the Minister for Social Protection and the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs.</p> <p>I agree with colleagues who have called for a debate on the situation in Northern Ireland.  It is welcome to see an agreement in place but on recent visits to a number of housing estates in Belfast I have noticed the significant number of new "peace walls" which have appeared between areas of Belfast.  There is nothing more clear, more obvious or more evident of the continued existence of sectarianism than seeing a wall dividing two communities.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#J00300"><p>I was not free to attend the House yesterday but I wish to have on the record my abhorrence at the disgusting behaviour by the Daesh group in Paris on Friday evening.  Hopefully East and West, the United States and Russia, can work together and put their power struggles behind them to try and bring about a resolution to this most serious issue in the Middle East.</p> <p>I welcome yesterday's agreement and the reference made in this House this morning to the walls coming down.  It is much easier to take down the physical walls than it is to take down the walls and barriers in people's hearts.  The real walls are in the hearts and how long will it take to break those barriers down?</p> <p>I welcome yesterday's announcement by the Minister of State, Deputy Joe McHugh, that an extra &euro;25 million will be allocated to the A5 road project bringing a total of &euro;75 million in capital funding from the Government to the project for 2007-19.  As a member of the Joint Committee on the Implementation of the Good Friday Agreement I draw attention to the N2 section of the A5.  The N2 from the Border to Clontibret is about 18 miles long which is approximately 28 km.  This road is in dire condition and I have pleaded that the Government would allocate the modest sum of &euro;1.5 million to narrow the road alignment from 400 m to 100 m and to allow the route planning to proceed to the next stage.</p> <p>I had a private meeting, along with other members of the committee, with the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Paschal Donohoe.  I could not believe that he stuck his heels into the ground in that he could not see the value of a &euro;1.5 million allocation to Monaghan County Council to allow it to define the road exactly and to have the plans ready for when the money is available to start the road building, rather than waiting for the word and to then have to start designing the road.  It is absolutely crazy.  I congratulate the Minister of State, Deputy Joe McHugh.  He was chairman of the Joint Committee on the Implementation of the Good Friday Agreement and was worn out listening to me pushing for this N2 road from the Border to Knocknacloy.  It is a very dangerous road.  Historical records from the period 1996 to 2009 obtained from An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na show a total of 112 personal injury accidents, of which 11 were fatal and 15 resulted in serious injury.  If the Government is serious about Northern Ireland, in developing the route from Dublin to the north west and in the social and economic development of the area, then let it give the &euro;1.5 million to Monaghan County Council to proceed and design this N2 road.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#J00400"><p>I join with all sides of the House in welcoming yesterday's agreement in Stormont and I welcome the increase of funding towards the development of the A5 which is a main arterial route running to and from the north west.  This will prove a major boon for the economy for the north west and particularly for Donegal.  However, I attended a meeting over the weekend of the British-Irish Parliamentary Assembly as did some of my colleagues and - in the context of a debate about the possibility of a Brexit - while I will not say there was hostility, issues were raised by the representatives from the Scottish Parliament and the Welsh Assembly about the amounts of money being given to the Northern Ireland Assembly and to Stormont.</p> <p>One figure that stuck in my mind is that the Northern Ireland Assembly receives 23% more in block grants than the constituent bodies in Wales and Scotland.  I will not say that there is not a great deal of sympathy for what is going on in the North but I echo one or two comments made in this House when I say I am glad that the parties in the North have seen a little bit of reality.  Any suggestion, as has emanated from some sources in the North, that the British Government was going to continue to dole out the largesse in the North certainly came into stark relief yesterday in the discussions with the people who represent the Scottish people, and those who represent the Welsh people.  They are not at all happy about the fact that they are not getting as much money as Northern Ireland is getting.  I was glad there was an injection of reality and that this has happened because the parties in the North were very much on the precipice over the last couple of weeks.</p> <p>I am very glad to see my colleague, Senator Ned O'Sullivan, back in the House after his recent illness and I hope that he will continue to make his valuable contributions here.  I also welcome the indications that the Fianna F&aacute;il manifesto will commit to the restoration of town councils. </p><p>To put this in context, in the past couple of weeks there was a memo from Sligo County Council relating to a tradition that had been built up by Sligo borough council, which gave small grants to resident associations in Sligo town and district.  My colleague, Senator MacSharry, is familiar with this.  As it was a constituent borough council, it had the budget to do this but because the council is gone and there is a now a municipal area that is much larger, geographically, there is not a budget to provide the funding for Sligo specifically, as it would have to provide the same money for resident associations all over the county.  The resources are not there to do that.  This is just a small example of how local democracy has been somewhat thwarted.  I therefore strongly welcome what seems to be a commitment by Fianna F&aacute;il - the manifesto has not yet been published - as the indications are that we will put forward a proposal to restore town councils based on population.</p><p>I remember at the time of abolition pointing out that Denmark has one of the purest forms of local democracy right down to town councils.  It is example of the process working efficiently.  Nevertheless, the last Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government decided in his wisdom that we would become less democratic in this country, which I found an ultimate irony.  I second the amendment proposed by my colleague, Senator MacSharry.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#K00200"><p>I call for a debate on the funding of local authorities from the central Exchequer and on the road we are taking in this respect.  I concur with Senators Mooney and O'Sullivan about the demise of local government and the abolition of town councils.  It appears that many local authorities, particularly rural counties, are being starved of funding.  My advice to councillors in the Munster area, particularly those from the parties on this side of the House, is that they should rail against agreeing a budget where the consequence will be that very hard-pressed medium and small businesses, including clothes shops, pubs and restaurants in rural Ireland, will be hit with severe rates bills.</p><p>Many of these businesses are almost buckling under the pressure of rates bills when the economy has declined significantly over the past number of years.  The Valuation Office is dealing with the revaluation of properties that were valued for a certain number of millions of euro eight or ten years ago but are not worth that now.  The Valuation Office is understaffed and overwhelmed with appeals.  The problem is nationwide, which is bothering me.  I understand, for example, that in Offaly the Valuation Office has fast-tracked the reduction of rates for telecommunication masts.  This means that in that small county, &euro;1.5 million is to be wiped off the funding stream of Offaly County Council, and I am sure the same is happening in many other counties.  Who will pay for this other than the hard-pressed rate payers?  There will be no fast-tracking for a small shop in Skibbereen, the rural pub in some part of Kerry or businesses struggling to survive.  I know one restaurant in my area - I will not mention the town or the business - that, because of a rates bill and the bank taking away a &euro;20,000 overdraft facility, had to close approximately five years ago, with the loss of 20 jobs.  I am deeply concerned that unless there is a confrontation with the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government and the Department of Finance, where local authorities are not being funded properly, there will be a public revolt on this very shortly.  I am asking for an urgent debate on this issue.  If that is not forthcoming in the next couple of weeks, I will push the issue to a vote.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" speakername="Terry Brennan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#K00300"><p>I welcome the new agreement that was completed yesterday in Northern Ireland.  The new deal will help stabilise power sharing and tackle the toxic legacy of paramilitarism.  The agreement underlines this Government's commitment to peace, reconciliation and stability on this island.  The Central Statistics Office figures issued yesterday indicate a 12% increase in employment in the Border region in the past year and this agreement will help protect and continue this progress, keeping the recovery going.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#K00400"><p>I note Senator MacSharry's points on the comments of the Minister for Health, Deputy Varadkar.  I understand the Minister is in Belfast today so I cannot accede to his request for an amendment to the Order of Business in this regard.  We have seen many advances in our health services but there are many problems as well.  We need to put the building blocks in place.  The timeframe will certainly change due to variable factors.  Free GP care has already been introduced and begun, and it will continue.  There is a need for more GPs, with 500 new GPs to be put in place.  It is possible to have many more specialists and consultants; we will hire over 100 new consultants this year and we hope to ramp up the number to 150 by the end of the year, with more to come in future.  Many reforms have taken place and more needs to be done.  I am sure the Minister will come in at a later date to explain his policy on universal health insurance but it will not be today because, as I noted, he is in Belfast.</p><p>I note Senator Bacik's comments welcoming the commencement of gay marriage in the country yesterday.  I inform the Senator that Report Stage of the residential tenancies Bill will take place next Tuesday.  Senator Bacik and several others welcomed the schools building project that will transform educational facilities throughout the length and breadth of the country, and I am sure that will be well received by all.  I also welcome the agreement in Northern Ireland, to which Senator Barrett and many others referred.  Such an agreement is most welcome.  As Senator Mooney mentioned, I attended the meeting of the British-Irish Parliamentary Association over the weekend and the Scottish, Welsh and English members were worried that Northern Ireland was getting 23% more funding than their areas.  I am glad agreement has been reached and I hope we will see a normalisation of politics there in the coming years.  That was referred to by many Senators on the Order of Business.</p><p>Senators O'Sullivan and White spoke about the dreadful terrorist attacks in Paris, where so many people were murdered.  Senator O'Sullivan also spoke about the proposed manifesto and particularly the indication that town councils will be restored.  I am sure we will all examine the manifesto when it is published as it will be up for public scrutiny.  Senator Hayden welcomed the passage of the residential tenancies Bill through Committee Stage.  As I mentioned, we will have Report Stage next Tuesday.  She also called for a debate on youth policy and especially access to benefits for youths.  I will certainly try to arrange that.</p><p>Senator Barrett asked about the Legal Services Regulation Bill 2011, to be taken tomorrow, and I agree that the comments of the troika and the National Competitiveness Council should be examined thoroughly.  I understand the Minister is available for briefings to any Member on proposed changes.  I assure the Senator that we will not rush through this Bill and we hope to have a very comprehensive debate on it tomorrow.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Maurice Cummins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2003"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2003&amp;amp;pid=MauriceCummins&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We will see how far we can get on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#L00200"><p>I thank the Leader.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#L00300"><p>I note Senator White's comments on the additional funding of more than &euro;20 million for the A5 road.  As Senator Mooney mentioned, this project will be a major boon to the economy of the north west.  I also note what Senator White said about the &euro;1.5 million that is being sought by Monaghan County Council for the N2 road.  I am sure that matter will be addressed in the coming months.</p> <p>Senator O'Donovan referred to the funding of local authorities.  Those authorities now have the power to increase or decrease the property tax rates that apply locally.  The tax in question is a source of significant extra revenue.  I note the Senator's point that recent revaluations of electricity, telecommunications and other utility companies have led to reductions in the rates imposed on a number of them.  This is causing a problem for local authorities because they are being obliged to address shortfalls in funding of up to &euro;1 million in some cases.  It is the job of local authorities to try to deal with these issues.  If additional funding is necessary, they have the means to collect it through property tax.  I agree that rates have been an especially crushing burden for small businesses.  Local authorities in the vast majority of counties and cities have kept that burden down, particularly in recent years.  Let us hope they will be in a position to do so again when they are forming their budgets for next year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#L00400"><p>Senator MacSharry has proposed an amendment to the Order of Business, "That a debate with the Minister for Health on the abandonment by the Government of universal health insurance be taken today."  Is the amendment being pressed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#L00500"><p>It is.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.52/1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#L00600"><p>Amendment put:</p><p>The Seanad divided: T, 12; Nl, 22.</p><br/><br/><p>Tellers: T, Senators Ned O'Sullivan and Diarmuid Wilson; Nl, Senators Aideen Hayden and Michael Mullins.</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.52/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2015-11-18" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#L00600">
            <divisioncount ayes="12" noes="22" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" vote="aye">Sean Barrett</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1196" vote="aye">Gerard Craughwell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" vote="aye">David Cullinane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" vote="aye">Mark Daly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" vote="aye">Marc MacSharry</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" vote="aye">Paschal Mooney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" vote="aye">Darragh O'Brien</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" vote="aye">Denis O'Donovan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1142" vote="aye">Ned O'Sullivan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" vote="aye">Mary White</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" vote="aye">Diarmuid Wilson</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1176" vote="aye">Katherine Zappone</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" vote="no">Ivana Bacik</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" vote="no">Terry Brennan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1208" vote="no">M&aacute;ir&iacute;a Cahill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" vote="no">Eamonn Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1124" vote="no">Michael Comiskey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" vote="no">Martin Conway</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" vote="no">Maurice Cummins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" vote="no">Aideen Hayden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1152" vote="no">Imelda Henry</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" vote="no">Ca&iacute;t Keane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" vote="no">John Kelly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1162" vote="no">Denis Landy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" vote="no">Marie Moloney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" vote="no">Mary Moran</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1134" vote="no">Tony Mulcahy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" vote="no">Michael Mullins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1187" vote="no">Hildegarde Naughton</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" vote="no">Catherine Noone</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" vote="no">Pat O'Neill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1163" vote="no">Tom Shehan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" vote="no">Jillian van Turnhout</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1143" vote="no">John Whelan</mpname>
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.52/3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#L00600"><p>Amendment declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.53" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.54" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#M00200">Planning and Development (Urgent Social Housing Supply) Policy Directive 2015: Referral to Joint Committee</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#M00300"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That the Planning and Development (Urgent Social Housing Supply) Policy Directive 2015, a copy of which has been laid in draft form before Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 29th October 2015, be referred to the Joint Committee on Environment, Culture and the Gaeltacht, in accordance with Standing Order 70A(3)(<i>j</i>), which, not later than 26th November, 2015, shall send a message to the Seanad in the manner prescribed in Standing Order 73, and Standing Order 75(2) shall accordingly apply.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.56" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.57" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 12.25 p.m. and resumed at 12.45 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.58" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#O00100">Child Care (Amendment) Bill 2015: Report and Final Stages</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#O00200"><p>I remind the House that a Senator may speak only once on Report Stage, except the proposer of an amendment who may reply to the discussion on the amendment.  I welcome the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs, Deputy Reilly, to the House.  I also remind Members that each amendment on Report Stage must be seconded.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" speakername="Jillian van Turnhout" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#O00300"><p>I move amendment No. 1:</p><blockquote>In page 5, between lines 26 and 27, to insert the following:<b>&ldquo;Amendment of section 29 of Principal Act</b><br /><br /><b>5. </b>Section 29 of the Principal Act is amended by the insertion of the following new subsection after subsection (4):<blockquote>&ldquo;(4A) In subsection (5), &lsquo;relevant court documents&rsquo;, in relation to any proceedings referred to in that subsection&mdash;<blockquote>(a) subject to paragraph (b), means&mdash;<blockquote>(i) any notice of application or other originating document in the proceedings,<br /><br />(ii) any pleading, report and other document (including the terms of settlement, if any) produced to or lodged with the court, or included in any book of pleadings or reports, in the course of the proceedings, and<br /><br />(iii) any order made or judgment delivered by the court in the proceedings,</blockquote>(b) does not include any document the contents of which are expressed to be without prejudice or in terms having a like effect.&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></blockquote> <p>For the record, Senator Wilson will be seconding the amendment.  I welcome the Minister to the House once again.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jillian van Turnhout:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2391"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2391&amp;amp;pid=JillianVanTurnhout&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->On the amendment, not only must justice be done but it must be seen to be done.  The principle of ensuring that justice is administered in public, including law proceedings subject to protecting the anonymity of the parties, has been accepted by successive Governments, for example, in the Civil Liability and Courts Act  2004, as amended, the Child Care (Amendment) Act 2007 and the Courts and Civil Law (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act 2013.  The first two of these Acts permitted academic institutions and other bodies named in regulations, including persons engaged in child care law research, to report on family law proceedings while the latter opened up family courts to the media for the first time.  Similar measures have been undertaken in England and Wales, which, like Ireland, previously had a highly restrictive regime.<br/><br/>The Civil Liability and Courts Act 2004 was amended to clarify that relevant documents, which is the crux of the issue we are discussing, included all documents generated in the course of proceedings in order to ensure that reporting could be comprehensive and accurate.  No such amendment exists clarifying the meaning of relevant court documents relating to the child care proceedings in the 2007 Act and no statutory definition of this term exists.<br/><br/>In child care proceedings, reports are routinely produced for court by social workers, guardians <i>ad litem</i>and other professionals detailing and analysing any risk to a child thought to exist.  These are sworn into evidence and are normally then outlined orally to the court and the author of the report is subject to cross-examination in contested proceedings.  However, where the proceedings are not contested, the judge may state that he or she has read the report and does not need to hear evidence, and then makes the order sought.  Without sight of the report, the child care law reporting project has no way of knowing the basis for the order - how the threshold outlined in the Act has been applied - and therefore cannot report on this or fulfil its statutory remit &quot;to provide information which will assist in the better operation of this Act&quot;.  It is interesting that the Civil Liability and Courts Act 2004, which first modified the <i>in camera</i>rule in family law, did not have any such purpose of assisting in the better operation of any Act.<br/><br/>It is difficult to accept that the Oireachtas, when opening up the child care courts to reporting, through the Child Care (Amendment) Act 2007, did not intend that a person carrying out that task, including providing information that would assist in the better operation of this Act, would have access to the same information as the court and all other participants.  Indeed, counsel for the child care law reporting project argued, in its Circuit Court appeal submission against the decision of the District Court president, Her Honour Judge Rosemary Horgan, not to provide the child care law reporting project with a copy of a social work report which was submitted in evidence as part of a child care case, that the reason the definition was not included in the 2007 Act was that it was unnecessary as an earlier High Court judgment had ruled it was permissible for child care proceedings to be reported provided that there was judicial permission while it had not been possible to report private law proceedings.<br/><br/>It is also a feature of European law that more, not less, transparency is required of proceedings where the State is involved in curtailing the rights of citizens, in this case, family rights.  The European Court of Human Rights examined the <i>in camera</i>rule in two cases: B and P <i>v</i>. United Kingdom, involving private family law in which two parents were in dispute; and Moser <i>v</i>. Austria, involving public family law and taking a child into state care.  Distinguishing the latter case from the former, the court stated it &quot;considers that in this sphere, the reasons for excluding a case from public scrutiny must be subject to careful examination&quot;.  The court ruled against Austria's blanket ban on reporting child care proceedings.<br/><br/>Granting reporters access to documents along with access to court proceedings has also been considered in the United Kingdom.  There was a recent judgment in the High Court of England and Wales family division, on 19 October this year, allowing a journalist access to documents in a child care case, Tickle <i>v</i>. Council of the Borough of North Tyneside and Ors.  After ruling in favour of allowing a journalist report on a specific case, including interviewing the mother in the case, and having laid down conditions to prevent the identification of the children or their parents, the judgment states, &quot;any party to the current or previous proceedings relating to the children may disclose to Louise Tickle [the journalist] documents produced for the purposes of those proceedings, for the specific purpose of informing her journalism, and provided that those documents themselves may not be published in full or further distributed by her&quot;.  I would be completely happy for such non-publication or distribution of documents conditions to be inserted into any amendment in this regard.  The judge referred on several occasions in his judgment to finding an appropriate balance between the public interest in the media being able to report child care proceedings and the interest of privacy of those whose lives are intimately involved.<br/><br/>No good reason has been advanced for preventing the child care law reporting project or any other body permitted under the relevant regulations from having access to documents in a broader context where the content of these documents is usually discussed in the court in their presence and, subsequently, reported upon by them.  The only purpose in a permitted class of person having sight of these documents, on request and subject to any directions or restrictions the court may impose, is to ensure that their research and reports are comprehensive and accurate, and in the specific case of the child care law reporting project, that they can provide information which will assist in the better operation of this Act.  In my view, the current situation contravenes the spirit of the legislation and the intention of the Oireachtas to bring transparency to child care proceedings.<br/><br/>I ask that the Minister give my amendment his positive consideration in the interests of transparency and accountability in child care proceedings in the courts, published report and the information provided to the public on the operation of the child care system.  As I stated on Committee Stage, the child care law reporting project has provided us invaluable reports but without access to these documents when a case is uncontested, we are not able to satisfy the obligation that the Oireachtas laid down that they must provide information which will assist in the better operation of the Act.  Thus, I commend my amendment to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#P00200"><p>I second the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#P00300"><p>I take the opportunity to welcome to the Gallery the children from Clare.</p> <p>Senator van Turnhout knows my views on this amendment and I do not propose to accept it.  As we discussed on Committee Stage in this House, the amendment would provide for a definition of "relevant court documents" for the purposes of section 29 of the Child Care Act 1991.  The section in question provides for the powers to report on child care proceedings before the courts where it is likely that such reporting may assist in the better operation of the Act.</p> <p>At present, under regulations made under this section, the child care law reporting project has been examining cases before the courts over the recent past.  All such reporting must be anonymised.  By way of clarification, the project in question is permitted to report on such proceedings under regulations.  It does not have a statutory remit in this regard.</p> <p>The proposed amendment would provide access to all documents lodged to the courts in child care proceedings.  Such an amendment, were it to be inserted in the Act, would not only apply to the aforementioned project but any future body given access to report on court proceedings in a similar fashion.  As Senators will appreciate, in many child care cases before the courts information of an extremely personal and sensitive nature is submitted.  This may encompass everything from financial reports to psychological reports, reports on addiction issues and alleged cases of physical and-or sexual abuse which relate not only to the child but also to his or her parents and wider family.  The balance in providing access to such information must be very carefully weighed.  The potential for a positive impact, in terms of what an examination of such reports may yield for policy or operational gain, must be considered against the right to privacy of the individual.  This must be examined from a constitutional perspective and also in terms of obligations under international treaties to which Ireland is a signatory.  I remain to be convinced that the intrusion would be appropriate or proportional to intended potential gain.</p> <p>As I stated previously, I will keep an open mind on the matter and the views of the Child and Family Agency have been sought by my officials.  An in-depth legal and policy examination of the issues associated with any such amendment would also be required.  Were it deemed to be possible and desirable, a consultation with key stakeholders, given the nature of the documents in question, would be necessary.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy James Reilly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=2180"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2180&amp;amp;pid=DrJamesReilly&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Finally, I would also like to establish if other avenues might be explored to provide the information sought for reporting purposes.  For those reasons, I will not accept the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" speakername="Jillian van Turnhout" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#Q00200"><p>I am disappointed but I will not press the amendment.  I draw the Minister's attention again, though, to the judgments I have cited, and I ask his officials to examine them because we are in violation.  We are not acting in the spirit of the legislation.  I take the bona fides of everything the Minister said but I have not had evidence of intrusion by the child care law reporting project.  We have to ensure that whatever we provide, we do not open up unintended consequences.  I welcome his commitment to undertake a consultation and I hope this can be done in a timely way.</p> <p>I will seek another avenue, perhaps in other legislation, to progress this issue to allow for more time for it to be considered.  It is extremely serious because the more we understand of the cases brought before the courts in respect of children being taken into care, the more we can explain to the public the reality of the cases.  During the referendum on children's rights, as I travelled around the country, I became aware of a misunderstanding and misinformation caused by the vacuum that is there.  The child care law reporting project has provided invaluable information in helping our understanding but we do not have information from the cases that are uncontested.  We do not know at what threshold children are being brought into the care of the State.  There needs to be scrutiny and the Oireachtas has a role in ensuring that happens.  I appreciate the Minister's response, but will he go back to ask for this issue to be re-examined?  It is not going away.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.66" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.67" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Bill received for final consideration.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.68" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That the Bill do now pass."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" speakername="Jillian van Turnhout" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#Q00600"><p>I would have loved this Bill to go further.  We had the discussion about changing "may" to "shall".  That does not take away from the importance of the Bill, which will now go to the Lower House.  I am a big believer that change is incremental.  I therefore welcome the passage of the Bill through the House.  I received correspondence from the Care Leavers' Network, which highlighted the importance of acting much earlier.  Even when a child is 16, it can be too late.  It is important to provide these young people with an education, housing rather than homeless accommodation, and continuing traditional, holistic and medical therapy, if required.  They often suffer post-traumatic stress and they need to be helped.  Family support should be offered, with opportunities for family therapy, especially with respect to sibling relationships.  We often consider the parent and the child, but the sibling relationships are neglected.</p> <p>More needs to be done for these children.  None of us wants to read reports on children who have died in the care of the State, and we all want to do better.  The Bill is a significant step in that direction and I thank the Minister and his officials for all the work they have done and for taking on the considerations of the Joint Committee on Health and Children during its hearings, which we greatly appreciate.  I hope the legislation will be enacted in the coming weeks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Moloney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#Q00700"><p>I thank the Minister and his officials for the work they have done.  I welcome the passage of the Bill.  Like Senator van Turnhout, on Second Stage I outlined provisions that I would have liked to see included, but it is great that this process will be put on a statutory footing.  I am always nervous about the resources available to the agency.  I hope the funding will always be available to provide necessary and adequate aftercare for these children and young adults and that the necessary personnel will be put in place with the expertise that is needed.  I welcome the proposal for additional inspectors, which we did not discuss very much because the provision of aftercare took over in the debate.  The Minister stated on Second Stage that he would appoint additional child care inspectors.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1152" speakername="Imelda Henry" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#Q00800"><p>I also congratulate the Minister and his officials on the Bill's passage.  I compliment the Department on all the work that has been done over the past four and a half years.  We have at long last put the importance of children to the forefront.  I congratulate the Minister, particularly on his commitment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#Q00900"><p>I thank the Senators for their contributions today and over the past two weeks.  The Bill provides for an explicit requirement to prepare an aftercare plan in respect of a specified cohort of children and young people as they transition from State care.  It puts aftercare planning on the same footing as other statutory obligations of the Child and Family Agency.  The legislation underpins significant initiatives and reforms that have taken place in recent years, which have been developed with the goal of improving aftercare services to deliver better outcomes for young people leaving the care of the State.</p> <p>The Bill attempts to take account of the need for a degree of nuance in planning for leaving care that is appropriate and sensitive to the young person's needs.  I note the issue around siblings and, as one of 11 children, I would not underestimate the importance of that.  Most importantly, the child or young person will have a central role in the development of the aftercare plan, which is critical at a time when we say we want to respect our young people and our children and we want them to be involved and able to contribute.  Nothing could be more important from their point of view than being able to contribute to the plan that affects them so centrally and personally.</p> <p>I pay tribute to the House for the manner in which the Bill has been welcomed and for the constructive comments and contributions given here.  A number of issues were raised, including the question of providing aftercare support to young people in full-time education beyond the age of 23 and agreeing aftercare plans in advance of the deadline stipulated in the legislation.  Our discussion of these and other topics raised has been fruitful.  I would also like to acknowledge Senators' acceptance of the Bill at short notice, which will facilitate the progression of the Bill through the Houses as quickly as possible.  I thank them for their contributions and for listening to what I have had to say on the legislation.  Along with the other legislation passed over the past year and a half, this Bill will make Ireland a much better place for young people and children.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.73" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.74" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 1.10 p.m. and resumed at 2 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.75" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#W00100">Tributes to Former Senator Jack Fitzsimons</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#W00200"><p>We will now pay tribute to the late Jack Fitzsimons who was an honourable Member of this Chamber.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#W00300"><p>It is a custom in this House that we pay tribute to former Members and I am delighted that Jack's widow and five children are in the Public Gallery today to listen to the tributes we have to offer.  I hope that they will give them some satisfaction.</p><p>I offer the collective sympathy of this side of the House.  Some Members may have dealt with Jack through politics or through his profession as an architect and a distinguished author.  Jack first came to national prominence in 1971 when he penned what was to become a best-selling book called <i>Bungalow Bliss</i>.This work challenged many of the preconceived ideas held at the time about development practices.  It is credited nationally with making the construction of homes more affordable by reducing the prices people paid for professional plans from architects and draftsmen.  Interest in the book and its ideas continues today in the context of the debate on one-off housing, which has been brought to the floor of this House on many occasions.  Jack continued to write and went on to publish a history of his native parish in Kilbeg, entitled <i>The Parish of Kilbeg</i>.  This was an indication of Jack's pride of place and sense of community, both of which served him well in his public life.  He also authored<i>Democracy Be Damned</i>, as well as books on County Meath's heritage and its thatched cottages.  The latter includes photographs he took during and after his political career.</p><p>Following a term on the urban council in Kells, Jack first entered Seanad &Eacute;ireann in 1983 when he was elected from the Industrial and Commercial Panel.  He was elected as a Fianna F&aacute;il Member to the 17th Seanad and was subsequently re-elected in 1987, serving on both occasions with a nomination from the Royal Institute of the Architects of Ireland, RIAI, an organisation he represented with distinction in the House.  He lost his seat in 1989 and resigned from Fianna F&aacute;il in the same year, following a well-documented falling out with his then party leader.  It was around this time that he wrote <i>Democracy Be Damned, </i>which has a certain humour to its title.</p><p>Following his time as a Senator, Jack stood in the local and European elections as an independent candidate on an anti-blood sport ticket, seeking a mandate for his view that hare coursing should be banned.  He was elected to Meath County Council on that platform and worked tirelessly to highlight the plight of the hare in the Irish countryside.  He organised a march from his native Kells to Dublin where he spoke to a large gathering outside D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann about the need to protect the Irish hare.  This spoke volumes of his devotion to the cause.  In 1994 Jack published a book in which he made a powerful case against hare coursing,<i>Coursing Ban Be Damned</i>, continuing his whimsical and ironic humour in the titling of his works.  He went on to back Deputy Tony Gregory's attempt to tackle hare coursing by means of a Private Member's Bill in 1993.  Although the measure was voted down, it led to coursing clubs muzzling greyhounds from then on.</p><p>Jack is a loss to his numerous friends in many fields, including in the Irish political landscape and in Kells where he served as a councillor.  It is his family, however, who will miss him most.  I wish to express my sincere sympathy to his wife and family on behalf of the Government.  Ar dheis D&eacute; go raibh a anam d&iacute;lis.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#W00400"><p>On my behalf and on that of the Fianna F&aacute;il Parliamentary Party, I offer my condolences to the family of the late Jack Fitzsimons, a former Member of this House.  To his wife, Anne, his children, Cora, Lana, Lloyd, Emla and Ken, and his grandchildren I offer the collective sympathy of this House and of the people of Meath, many of whom crossed paths with Jack not only through politics but also through his professional career as an architect and businessman in Kells and as a distinguished author.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Thomas Byrne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2203"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2203&amp;amp;pid=ThomasByrne&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->In welcoming Jack's family to the Gallery today, I offer them our sympathies once more.  At the time of Jack's passing just over a year ago, I commented that he was one of the most influential people in County Meath in the latter half of the 20th century in the spheres of politics and architecture.  We recall the massive funeral that Jack had in Kells last year.  I remember thinking at the time that it could be one of the last civic-type funerals to take place in the town, following the abolition of Kells Town Council.  The presence of local political representatives meant it was almost like a State funeral in the town.  It was absolutely huge.  It was a mark of respect to Jack and a sign of the respect in which he was held in the town.  In light of the abolition of Kells Town Council, b'fh&eacute;idir nach bhfeicfimid a leith&eacute;id de shochraid ar&iacute;s.<br/><br/>Jack first came to national prominence in 1971 when he penned <i>Bungalow Bliss</i>, which was to become a best-selling book.  As I remarked to Mrs. Anne Fitzsimons, the last person I met in the foyer of the Leinster House 2000 building before I came to the Chamber today asked me what business was taking place in the Seanad this afternoon.  When I explained that we were having expressions of sympathy for the late Jack Fitzsimons, the woman in question told me that she got her house from <i>Bungalow Bliss</i>.  It is clear, therefore, that Jack enabled a substantial number of people to build houses in the countryside.  In many cases, people were able to come out of really bad living conditions by getting these plans at a reasonable cost and furthering their lives and those of their families.  The book, which contained more than 75 house designs, was later credited with making the construction of houses more affordable nationally by bringing about reductions in the professional fees that people had to pay to architects and draftsmen.  Jack helped thousands of young families throughout the country to construct their homes at much-reduced rates.  I understand that <i>Bungalow Bliss</i>was reprinted ten times.  More than 250,000 copies of it were sold, which is an indication of the level of interest in it and its popularity.<br/><br/>In 1974, Jack published a comprehensive and detailed history of his native parish of Kilbeg.  I have a copy of the book, <i>The Parish of Kilbeg</i>, which was bequeathed to a colleague of mine who keeps it at home.  It survives as one of the most informative and illuminating books written in north Meath in the latter part of the 20th century.  When one dips into that book, one gets some fascinating insights.  I have a huge interest in the Irish language.  Jack explains clearly that the etymology or derivation of the placename Staholmog comes from the word &quot;teach&quot; in the Irish language.  The manner in which that word used to take an &quot;s&quot; in front of it in the Irish language is peculiar to these surrounds within County Meath and led to placenames like Staholmog, Stagreen, Stameen, Stamullen and Stackallen in the county.  Jack wrote a lovely paragraph about this topic, which I certainly find fascinating.  His interest in the Irish language was demonstrated in many Seanad debates.  As the Leader has said, Jack went on to write many books and essays, including <i>Democracy Be Damned</i>, <i>Bungalow Bashing</i>and <i>New Homes from Old</i>.<br/><br/>I would like to speak about Jack's political career.  He was appointed as a peace commissioner by the Minister for Justice in 1973.  He was elected to Kells Urban District Council, as it then was, in 1979.  He was re-elected in 1985 and became chairman of the council after the local elections of that year.  He ran for election to the Seanad in 1981 on the Industrial and Commercial Panel, having been nominated by the Irish Architects Society.  When he won a seat in the Seanad in 1983, he was one of three people from Meath and the part of Westmeath that was in Meath at the time to be elected to this House.  He was elected to the Seanad along with Donie Cassidy and Michael Lynch from Oldcastle.  Jack's relationship with the Fianna F&aacute;il Party was not always harmonious.  His resignation in 1989 has been well documented and reported on in the past.<br/><br/>Today we pay tribute to a man of zealous political capability who was prepared to put his way of thinking on the line.  He was an extremely principled man.  When our Leader mentioned the issue of hare coursing, I recalled a story that Michael Lynch told me about canvassing with Jack in County Tipperary.  They were on different panels, so they were not in direct competition with each other.  Michael Lynch told me that he begged Jack to tone down his opinions on hare coursing in front of the Tipperary councillors, but he was simply not prepared to do so.  He went to Tipperary with what would have been an unpopular viewpoint among Fianna F&aacute;il councillors and refused to set aside the principles to which he was deeply committed.  I think that is to be commended, because too often politicians are worried about what people want to hear.  Jack certainly did not go with that.  With Jack's passing, we have lost one of life's great gentlemen and most colourful characters.  We have lost a man of distinction and immense ability.  Jack's political life reminds the rest of us who are so lucky and privileged to be elected to these Houses that we must not always follow the herd instinct.  We must stand up for what we believe in and, in some cases, disregard our own political ambitions and aspirations for the greater good.  Jack was bold, brave and courageous in all facets of his political and personal functions.<br/><br/>In preparation for today's tributes, I read through some of the debates to which Jack contributed as a Member of the Seanad over a six-year period.  He made significant contributions to the debates on the Air Pollution Bill 1986, the Building Control Bill 1984 and the Animals Bill 1985.  His direct involvement and deep input into the National Monuments (Amendment) Bill 1986 cannot be underestimated and must be remembered.  He drew on his professional experience when contributing to that Bill and others.  As a Member of this House, Jack spoke on a wide range of topics, including the pollution of our waterways and the role of European law.  In March 1986, Jack made an absolutely excellent speech on the use of the Irish language, about which I am passionate.  One of the points he made was &quot;ba mh&oacute;r mar a chuideodh s&eacute; leis an teanga n&aacute;isi&uacute;nta a leathadh mar ghn&aacute;th-theanga na ndaoine d&aacute; mb'eol d&oacute;ibhsean go raibh an gradam is dual di ag an Ghaeilge i dTithe an Oireachtais&quot;.  He was saying that if the Irish language was used more often in the Houses of the Oireachtas, it would enjoy much more respect among the public and get much more use among the public.  That is certainly something I believe.  I think we need to redouble our efforts in this regard.  We have done that from time to time here in the Seanad.  We have tried to speak Irish not only when debating Gaeilge or Gaeltacht issues, but also in general debates.  The point made by Jack in that 1986 debate will stick with me.  I will try to implement his vision and influence others to do likewise.<br/><br/>Jack was a role model to the public and to public representatives.  He was an extensive legislator as well.  His contributions to the drafting of legislation in Seanad &Eacute;ireann shaped many different areas.  It is evident from his speeches that Jack was always aware of the difficulties faced by ordinary working people.  The people who benefited from <i>Bungalow Bliss</i>were ordinary working people, by and large.  Jack's work made the dream of owning a home much more affordable for them.  Following Jack's departure from the Seanad, he remained a consistent advocate for good planning and the preservation of our wildlife heritage.  He continued to work tirelessly for the causes he believed in.  He also continued to write and publish books.  Jack had much to be proud of, including his family, his home and the successful business he set up in Kells.  There was much more to the life of Jack Fitzsimons, however.  The positive, constructive and innovative contribution he made to public life in Ireland and in the Oireachtas is something to be proud of.  I know his family is very proud of Jack's achievements throughout his life.<br/><br/>It would be remiss of me not to mention Jack's deep and profound love for the town of Ceanannus M&oacute;r, County Meath, where he lived for most of his life, where he reared his family and where he set up and ran his business.  Throughout Jack's professional life and his involvement in many community and voluntary organisations in Ceanannus M&oacute;r and throughout County Meath, he was much loved and cherished by the people he encountered.  I know for a fact that Jack was respected by his peers, his neighbours, the students of nearly schools and the people of the town as a man of substance, distinction and high estimation.  He is sadly missed by his loving family - I know they miss him dearly - and by the community of Ceanannus M&oacute;r and beyond.  Go nd&eacute;anfaidh Dia tr&oacute;caire ar a anam d&iacute;lis.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#X00200"><p>I would like to join other Senators in paying tribute to the late former Senator Jack Fitzsimons, who died last year.  I welcome his family to the Gallery.  I would like to express sympathies on behalf of all of us here in the House and in particular in my role as leader of the Labour Party group.  As others have said, Jack was a Fianna F&aacute;il Member of Seanad &Eacute;ireann.  He was elected in 1983 and re-elected in 1987.  He was based in Kells, County Meath.  As we have heard, he was very active in his local community.  His work had an impact well beyond his own community.  As others have said, his work as an architect and his publishing record - I am thinking particularly of the famous 1970s publication, <i>Bungalow Bliss</i>- had a huge impact on many people throughout Ireland.  This book has been described as a design handbook for affordable housing that shows how bright modern bungalows can be synonymous with escape from rural poverty and domestic drudgery.  It spawned a great deal of debate on development and planning across the country.</p><p>As we have heard, Jack was also well known for his views as a vocal opponent of hunting and hare coursing and his resolutely principled stance on those issues.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Ivana Bacik:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2248"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2248&amp;amp;pid=IvanaBacik&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->As others have said, he also took a principled and independently minded stance with his resignation from Fianna F&aacute;il in 1989 on the grounds that there was, apparently, no ideology, consistency or positive approach within the party at the time.  As others have said, he went on to have a very active career in local politics and to run for the European Parliament.  While in the Seanad, as we heard, he contributed to debates on a range of topics, including the Irish language and, perhaps most important, the national monuments legislation.  His work in planning and conservation arising from his professional practice as an architect deserves honourable mention.  His publications, including not just <i>Bungalow Bliss</i>but others on Meath, democracy and other topics, have been mentioned and are particularly noteworthy.<br/><br/>I express sincere sympathies to his wife, Anne, his children, his grandchildren and his extended family.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#Y00200"><p>I am very honoured to have the opportunity to be associated with the tribute to former Senator Jack Fitzsimons.  I am alone in those present in having served with Senator Fitzsimons as I was first elected in 1987 and he was here for two years after that.  Reference has been made to a very distinguished career both in national and local politics and I will not reiterate all that has been said about the detail of that political career.</p><p>We all know, of course, about <i>Bungalow Bliss</i>.  A rather interesting aspect is that it generated controversy and I understand there was a disagreement between Jack and the environmental journalist, Mr. Frank McDonald, who coined the phrase &quot;bungalow blitz&quot; as part of a series of articles attacking what he called the spreading fungus of the proliferation of ribbon development bungalows in Ireland.  In an essay, the academic, Mr. Stephen Quilley, highlights the country's planning laws rather than the architectural qualities of the bungalows as being the main problem of the time.  The essay refers to one of the core drivers of <i>Bungalow Bliss</i>, which was that &quot;bright, modern bungalows were synonymous with an escape from rural poverty and domestic drudgery&quot;.  As we know, Jack published a further range of books on aspects of Meath, its heritage and politics, as well as some fiction.</p><p>On a more personal level, reference has been made to his falling out with Fianna F&aacute;il.  He was a bitter opponent of Mr. Charles Haughey and, as Senator Byrne noted, he was a man of great principle and enormous political courage.  I remember he took the position against hare coursing at a number of parliamentary party meetings during my time here when there would have been a very powerful hare coursing lobby.  Senator Byrne was correct in his description of the anecdote involving Senators Lynch and Fitzsimons and the Tipperary councillors.  I remember canvassing at the time and being asked straight out my position and that of Senator Fitzsimons.  I regret to say that my opinion now is the same as my opinion then.  He lost his Seanad seat directly as a result of the position he took on hare coursing within the Fianna F&aacute;il group.  He was certainly one of the most effective Senators, as has been outlined.</p><p>There was a bit of a joke about Jack as the amount of correspondence he sent to councillors throughout the country was voluminous.  It is a tradition of all Senators relying on county councillors to be elected that they would keep in touch regularly, but Jack always went the extra mile.  As a new Senator, I was deeply in awe of his ability to connect with his councillors, which makes it all the more sad and regrettable that it was on that issue - my contemporaries of the time would agree - that he lost his election.  It was not because he was a poor Senator or because he did not contact his electorate.  It certainly was not because of the extraordinary and frequent contributions he made in the House.</p><p>His resignation from Fianna F&aacute;il was regretted by many of us who knew Jack as a decent and honourable man but who also understood him as a man of great passion and strength of principle.  He just did not like Charlie Haughey.  It happened after his defeat in the Seanad election.  He subsequently wrote a book, which has probably been referred to here, and it was interesting to us here that he referred to his time in the Seanad, highlighting those people who had impressed him.  I obviously did not have much of an impact on Jack as I was not mentioned.  I remember very well poring through the book to find the names of the people to whom he referred and whether they were good, bad or indifferent.  He was not in any way critical but it was his opinion nonetheless.  It was a matter of great regret to me at the time that I was not mentioned in Jack's opus.</p><p>Jack was very friendly with the then chairman of the General Council of Irish County Councils, which has now been renamed.  The man, former councillor Jim Joe Shortt from County Leitrim, would have been known to both of my colleagues.  He and Jack had a very strong rapport.  In the 1997 election, Jim Joe and I were very close friends.  He came to me saying that Jack was a very good friend and an Independent councillor and that he would go to Kells to try to get Jack to vote for me.  I welcomed that, of course, and I remember as if it were yesterday being in the house in Kells, having the chat and, before we left, Jack saying he would give me the number one, not because of me but because of Jim Joe Shortt.  He did not mean that in any sort of negative sense at all but he was still somewhat estranged from Fianna F&aacute;il.  He did it in a most gentle way and from my perspective, it did not matter at the end of the day as I was getting the vote.  I had no doubt about the vote and as those of us who have gone through a Seanad election will testify, a voter may not follow through every time he or she indicates she will vote for a person.  I knew, leaving Kells and knowing Jack, that he had nailed his colours to the mast.  I remembered that in the course of trying to gather some thoughts about my time with Jack here.</p><p>The family must be justifiably proud of the long legacy he has left.  It is something for a politician to have a legacy and something for people to talk about, even long after that person's passing.  I extend my deepest sympathy to all the family, including Anne, who is here, and also to Cora, Lana, Lloyd, Emila and Ken, as well as the grandchildren, who are also here.  As often happens between younger and older generations, they probably miss their grandad more than anybody.  Ar dheis D&eacute; go raibh a anam d&iacute;lis.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#Y00300"><p>I welcome the Fitzsimons family, whose names are on the record.  These are very important occasions in which the Seanad pays tribute to former Members.  We stand on the shoulders of giants here and traditions, including interest in the environment, were built by the likes of Jack Fitzsimons and enhanced every day.  Senator Norris is the leader of the university group of Senators and has asked me to communicate his condolences.  He served with Senator Fitzsimons.</p> <p>From what we have heard, we know he was practical, principled and a preservationist.  Currently we are preparing for the climate change conference in Paris at the end of the month, so interest in the likes of thatched cottages and their preservation is very important.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Sean D. Barrett:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2370"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2370&amp;amp;pid=SeanDBarrett&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We are interested in growth as well, and they criticised <i>Bungalow Bliss</i>.  Dr. Mary Corcoran and Dr. Michel Peillon, in their book, <i>Ireland Unbound</i>, wrote of how Ireland emerged in the early years of the 21st century from poverty and drudgery, and the bungalows were part of that.  The sales of 250,000 copies is an immense achievement but it is hardly surprising because Kells today hosts a significant book festival, the Hay Festival, every year.<br/><br/>Of his interest in local history, in Kells, everybody feels that.  It is a place of great historical context, huge connotations in music, the great theatre, memorials to the late Maureen O'Hara and the late Dick Farrelly, the composer of the music for &quot;The Quiet Man&quot;.  It is not surprising he was so proud of Kells and Kilbeg, and as Senator Byrne stated, wrote Kilbeg's history.  We acknowledge all of those achievements.<br/><br/>He was a principled man.  As for <i>Democracy be damned</i>, one of the things we have had to do in this Seanad is to try and restore democracy because there was such pessimism three or four years ago when the country had to be rescued by the IMF.  All of us in public life must restore that trust and confidence, and that includes paying tribute to those who embodied the traditions that we seek to uphold and to further today.<br/><br/>His opposition to hunting and hare coursing would fit with the opinions of many today, and he had the courage to do it, as Senators Mooney and Byrne stated, even in the heart of coursing territory, such as Tipperary.  He was a man of principle.<br/><br/>The final point on occasions such as this, which I value very much, is to thank his family.  The life of Senators and Deputies demands extremely long hours and the families, wives and children who share Members of the Oireachtas with this House and with Leinster House in general deserve our thanks because it is a life which is, in many cases, not family friendly.  We hope the family will feel gratified today that we held the late Jack Fitzsimons in the same esteem in which I am sure they did.  I thank them for sharing him with us.  Ar dheis D&eacute; go raibh a anam d&iacute;lis.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#Z00200"><p>As Leas-Chathaoirleach, I also pay tribute to the late Jack Fitzsimons who was a Member of this House.  Although I did not serve with him, I became a Senator, in October 1989, in the same year that he lost his seat in the Seanad.</p> <p>It is a great honour and privilege for anybody, irrespective of party politics, who gets elected to the local authority, town council or local county council, and it is a particularly elevated honour to serve as a Member of the Oireachtas, which Jack did for six years, 1983 to 1989.</p> <p>He was an architect by profession and published a range of books.  He was not a tunnel-vision politician, unlike many of us who get bogged down in the cobwebs of politics and do not look outside the Pale or beyond our life in politics.  It must be a great tribute to his family that he not alone served in the political system but did other work, such as writing books.  It takes a lot of dedication to produce books.</p> <p>Earlier Senators spoke of his dedication and principled stand.  No doubt not relinquishing his principles in the area of hare coursing probably cost him his seat.  Having canvassed in places such as Waterford and Tipperary, and, indeed, Kerry and parts of Cork, I am aware that it is nearly a crime to mention anything about those involved in hare coursing, who are a powerful and strong lobby.  As Leas-Chathaoirleach, I am honoured to pay tribute to Jack today.</p> <p>I thank the Senators who contributed, the Leader of the Seanad, Senator Cummins, Senators Mooney, Barrett and Bacik but, more particularly, Senator Thomas Byrne, a fellow Meath man, who made a strong and heartfelt tribute.  I heard Thomas speak, when Jack passed away, of the huge respect in which Jack Fitzsimons was held in the local community.  As a colleague of Senator Byrne, I know of the huge regard he has, not alone for the late Jack Fitzsimons but for his entire extended family, and he said so on more occasions than one.</p> <p>To his wife, Anne, and children and grandchildren, this is a special, poignant occasion.  They are very welcome to this Chamber.  I now ask my colleagues to stand for a minute's silence as a gesture of respect to the late, great honourable Senator Jack Fitzsimons.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.86" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Members rose.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.87" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 2.36 p.m. and resumed at 3.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.88" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#FF00100">Finance (Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill 2015: Committee and Remaining Stages</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.89" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sections 1 to 4, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.90" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>NEW SECTION</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#FF00400"><p>I move amendment No. 1:</p><blockquote>In page 6, between lines 22 and 23, to insert the following:<b>&quot;5. </b>Where the burdens of bank recovery and resolution impose excessive burdens on a member state of the eurozone an agreed re-introduction of a national currency and a flexible exchange rate regime shall be a permitted alternative to the bank recovery and resolution measures of <i>Part 2 </i>of this Act.&quot;.</blockquote> <p>As always, I welcome the Minister of State at the Department of Finance, Deputy Simon Harris, to the House.  He informed us on Second Stage that &quot;this Bill is very much of a technical nature and is designed primarily to address certain national and international obligations arising from a number of issues associated with the EU financial services legislative and transposition agenda&quot;.  The purpose of the amendment is to address this issue.  It provides that where a bank recovery and resolution imposes excessive burdens on a member state of the eurozone, an agreed reintroduction of a national currency and a flexible exchange rate regime should be permitted as alternatives to the bank recovery and resolution measures set out in Part 2.</p><p>The austerity agenda, as it is known, the bank collapses and rescues and the major burden that every Member of the Oireachtas has borne and substantially dealt with over the past four years could all have been alleviated if a measure such as that proposed in the amendment had been available.  I am seeking to have included in the Official Report of a Parliament of a member state of the eurozone confirmation that an alternative exists by providing that countries must not stick rigidly to a fixed exchange rate and make those on the receiving end miserable forever.  I specifically have in mind Greece, its fixed exchange rate <i>vis-&agrave;-vis</i>Germany and all the trouble and turmoil Greek people have endured.  If Greece had a separate exchange rate - the Minister for Finance referred to this on one occasion when he used the example of feta cheese - it could have varied the exchange rate to increase the number of German holidaymakers and exports of goods.</p><p>It is a design fault of the euro that it does not provide an exit mechanism and instead provides for a lobster pot means of making economic policy.  It is very easy to join the euro but impossible to leave it.  It the case of some eurozone member states, for example, Italy, Portugal and Greece, it would be easier to reintroduce a devalued national currency than to have the relentless imposition of austerity that has been associated with rigidly maintaining a fixed exchange rate, regardless of the underlying economic conditions.  Greece and most other countries are not Germany and the single currency is not essential to the operation of the European Union.  Countries outside the euro include Denmark, Sweden and large member states such as the United Kingdom and Poland.</p><p>The exchange rate benefits of the euro may have been exaggerated.  What we lost on joining the single currency was the ability to use the exchange rate and interest rates as instruments of economic policy.  Colm McCarthy described it, in his inimitable way, when he compared the exchange rate to the canary in the coalmine and stated that the EU shot the canary, meaning we did not have danger signals emerging from the types of policies that were pursued.  The excess flow of capital in massive quantities and the tsunami of capital from German and French banks into Irish banks were promptly used to undermine the economy.  The major inflow of bank funding was the start of the property bubble and we have all been required to participate in the rescue of the banks. </p><p>Irish banking dates back to 1783 and Grattan's Parliament.  Since then, there have been approximately 20 massive shocks to the system, none of which bankrupted the Bank of Ireland.  They included the Famine, revolutions and two world recessions.  The bank was bankrupted, however, by the decision to join the euro in 2008.  We were warned against joining the single currency by people such as Milton Friedman who noted that without an exit mechanism, we had locked ourselves in and thrown away the key.</p><p>As the Minister of State indicated on Second Stage, the Bill involves an element of retrofitting.  Last November, a bank resolution mechanism finally came into operation for a currency that had been in place for the best part of 20 years.  There is a respectable economic view that much of this would not be necessary if we had not been so rigid about the fixed exchange rate.  Keynes described Churchill's decision to restore the gold standard in the United Kingdom as crucifying an economy on a cross of gold.  There are also design faults in the euro currency.  In addition to the loss of the interest rate and exchange rates, one also has weak bank regulation, which was only remedied last November, and the absence of an exit mechanism.</p><p>While it may be most unwelcome to Mr. Trichet, Mr. Draghi and others, there are still parliamentarians in the member states who think for themselves and propose alternative policies.  It seems particularly strange that they will hang themselves on the absence of an exit mechanism, even where the policy of fixed exchange rates between the Deutschmark and all the other countries does not work.  Some of this arrogance spilled over in the statement to the Minister for Finance that if bondholders were burned, a bomb would go off in Dublin.  We need to address the problem of countries being stuck at the wrong exchange rate.</p><p>The purpose of the amendment is to place on the agenda the message that in at least one member state parliament, there are people who do not see the euro as the be-all and end-all of economic policy.  There are alternatives to the regime of austerity.  We threw away some without properly considering them, while others caught us unawares.  The tsunami effect of the massive flow of capital into the Irish banking system imposed costs on the economy which it had never borne in the 217 years between 1783 and 2000.  When we had policy discretion we used it wisely.</p><p>The purpose of the amendment is not to annoy the Minister or undermine his work.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Sean D. Barrett:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2370"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2370&amp;amp;pid=SeanDBarrett&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I want to get across that when we go to Brussels and Frankfurt there must be a discussion of equals about whether fixed or flexible exchange rates are correct and whether the one-size-fits-all policy, which is part of the Franco-German alliance, applies to peripheral countries, rather than what has been done heretofore, which is blaming people in peripheral countries for being lazy or incompetent and refusing to talk to them in a parliamentary context and being pretty patronising to them in the European Parliament.  A very rigid alternative has been chosen.  Many economists would have chosen something different, and I have tabled the amendment to show that in the world of learning which is the subject of economics, it did not have to be this way.  It was chosen and we were locked in, but it did not have to be as immutable as it has been made.  We should have discussions every time a policy comes from Brussels or Frankfurt, because it is not inevitably and inextricably the correct one.  We must use our own thinking caps in the interests of this country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1106" speakername="Simon Harris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#GG00200"><p>Far from annoying me, I always enjoy Senator Barrett's view and very much accept his sincerity on all of these matters.  We had a chance to speak about this, and I believe the Senator will understand that regardless of my views or his, I am not in a position to accept the amendment, as Part 2 does not provide for the bank recovery and resolution measures available to Ireland.  Its purpose is simply to ratify the intergovernmental agreement to enable the operationalisation of the Single Resolution Mechanism.  The recovery and resolution measures are covered by the European Union (Bank Recovery and Resolution) Regulations 2015 which transpose the EU bank recovery and resolution directive, and also by the EU Single Resolution Mechanism regulation.  It also would not be possible to introduce a legislative change for members of the eurozone through national legislation.  I know the Senator knows this and that he feels strongly about wanting to make the point, but for the reasons I have outlined I am not in a position to accept the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#GG00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his contribution, as always.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.95" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.96" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sections 5 to 7, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.97" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>SECTION 8</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#GG00800"><p>I move amendment No. 2:</p><blockquote>In page 8, line 24, to delete &quot;stand&quot; and substitute &quot;stands&quot;.</blockquote> <p>This is a small amendment on grammatical matters, and I will leave it to the Minister of State to handle it on Report Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1106" speakername="Simon Harris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#GG00900"><p>I pay tribute to the Senator's attention to detail, but we have consulted the Office of the Parliamentary Counsel on this point and it has indicated that while it can appreciate, as can I, where the Senator is coming from with his proposed amendment, its view is that it matters little in practice because it is difficult to see how whichever word we use, be it "stand" or "stands ", can be interpreted as other than what is intended.  In other words, it unambiguously refers to a situation where there is no money left in the legacy fund, no matter which word is used.  While one can contend between "stand" and "stands", and I take the point the Senator is making, the Office of the Parliamentary Counsel has advised me it will make no material difference, and because of the urgency in passing this legislation to ratify the agreement, I do not propose to accept the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.100" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.101" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Section 8 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.102" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Section 9 to 11, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.103" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>SECTION 12</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#GG01400"><p>I move amendment No. 3:</p><blockquote>In page 11, line 11, to delete &quot;2 weeks&quot; and substitute &quot;1 week&quot;.</blockquote> <p>This is taken from the note supplied by the Oireachtas Library and Research Service that the ECB might like a faster period of reimbursement, hence the proposal of one week rather than two.  The Department of Finance told the Oireachtas Library and Research Service this was being discussed and it might have been included by the Minister of State at this stage.  I will leave it to his discretion.  There is literature on whether one week or two weeks is correct.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1106" speakername="Simon Harris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#GG01500"><p>The Senator is quite right to raise this matter, and I am happy to provide clarity on it.  Under section 8 of the Financial Services (Deposit Guarantee Scheme) Act 2009 as it stands, the period for repaying the Central Bank for a short-term advance it has provided is three months.  We have consulted the European Central Bank on the matter and I can inform the House it is satisfied that two weeks is a sufficiently prompt time which does not create any monetary financing concerns for it.  We sought the opinion of the ECB and it is happy with the two-week period.  Therefore, I do not propose to accept the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#GG01600"><p>I accept the point made by the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.107" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.108" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Section 12 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.109" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sections 13 to 21, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.110" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>NEW SECTIONS</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#GG02100"><p>I move amendment No. 4:</p><blockquote>In page 17, between lines 23 and 24, to insert the following:<b>&quot;22.</b>The Minister shall submit to both Houses of the Oireachtas an annual report on the regulation of the Insurance sector including solvency, premium increases, competitiveness and all matters included in Part 4 of the <i>Finance (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act 2015</i>.&quot;.</blockquote> <p>I have a number of concerns in this regard, including a bill for &euro;92 million for Setanta which was supposed to operate in Malta, massive losses in Quinn and, before that, in PMPA and the Insurance Corporation of Ireland.  Such matters were within the province of the Minister for Industry and Commerce, the portfolio having had various changes of title since.  In its 2015 report, the National Competitiveness Council stated the Minister should present reports on financial regulation, which now includes insurance.  We have a bad record in this field, with insurance companies going bankrupt, and a bad record of high claims and high costs, and people such as Mr. Conor Faughnan have referred to this recently.  As this legislation will put insurance firmly in financial services rather than in its previous location, there is a need from the point of view of national competitiveness for us to call the sector to account.</p><p>I do not know how Setanta, being registered in Malta, is an Irish cost.  The other companies were obviously not very well supervised.  I understand Setanta is also the Catalan word for 70, so I do not know whether we could have transferred it from Malta to that part of Spain.  Insurance has been a nuisance and a high cost in the Irish economy for a long time, and the National Competitiveness Council recommends it should be part of a report on the financial sector.  Something seems to be wrong as its costs are increasing, claims are excessive compared with jurisdictions with which we compete such as the United Kingdom, much higher rates of damages are paid and we have much higher incidence of whiplash.  Of course, a constant mantra is the much higher level of legal costs.  If we do not regulate the insurance sector thoroughly, which is the purpose of the amendment, it will be a burden on the rest of the economy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1106" speakername="Simon Harris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#GG02200"><p>I thank Senator Barrett.  On Second Stage we had an opportunity to discuss the issues relating to Setanta and the importance of ensuring we have enhanced monitoring through the market intelligence on freedom of services firms in the Central Bank.  I was pleased to be able to assure the House that since the issues arose with Setanta, the Central Bank has enhanced its market intelligence on freedom of services firms and will maintain regular contact with the regulators of those insurance firms about which it has concerns.  The Central Bank will also conduct more on-site inspections of intermediaries and manage general agencies which distribute products underwritten by freedom of services insurers.  In addition to this, we will have the underlying framework regarding the insurance industry which will be strengthened with the introduction of Solvency II from 1 January next year.</p> <p>With regard to the amendment, my colleague, the Minister for Finance, is responsible for the development of the legal framework governing financial regulation, and the Central Bank of Ireland as the regulator is responsible for prudential supervision of insurance companies.  This is the division of roles and responsibilities.  Under the Central Bank Act 1942, as amended, the Central Bank of Ireland is accountable to the Oireachtas in the exercise of its regulatory functions and is required to prepare an annual statement for the Oireachtas relating to its performance in regulating financial services.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Simon Harris:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=2338"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2338&amp;amp;pid=SimonHarris&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Further, I would highlight that section 33AM of the Central Bank Act of 1942 provides for certain staff of the Central Bank, including the head of financial regulation, to appear before a joint committee of the Oireachtas responsible for examining matters relating to the bank and provide that committee with such information that it requires, subject to certain conditions.  This provision was introduced under the Central Bank Reform Act of 2010 and is quite a useful and important provision available to Members of the Oireachtas in terms of obtaining information and providing a degree of scrutiny.  The head of financial regulation at the Central Bank can be called upon to appear before a joint committee of the Oireachtas, presumably the Joint Committee on Finance, Public Expenditure and Reform.</p><p>The Central Bank also publishes insurance statistics annually.  This includes a large amount of data relevant to the insurance sector operating in Ireland, including the life, non-life and re-insurance sectors.  This information is a summary of the life assurance and non-life-insurance returns made to the Central Bank pursuant to the European Communities (Life Assurance) Framework Regulations of 1994 and the European Communities (Non-Life Insurance Accounts) Regulations of 1995.  The most recent report was published on 30 September regarding business written during the year ended 31 December 2014.  Therefore, for the reasons I have outlined in terms of the current provisions already available to the Oireachtas and its committees and the information being provided by the Central Bank, I am not in a position to accept the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#HH00200"><p>The recommendation from the National Competitiveness Council is that the Central Bank and the Department of Finance should continually review and monitor the accuracy and proportionality of financial services regulation, which, as the Minister of State has said, now includes the insurance sector.  The money involved for Setanta was &euro;92 million, while Quinn Insurance lost &euro;905 million in 2009 and &euro;160 million in 2010.  There is the 2% levy, and we have statements from the Personal Injuries Assessment Board to the effect that insurers should be asked to explain price hikes.  There is a serious problem in this area and I do not question for one second the Minister's commitment to dealing with it; in doing so, he will have the support of this House.  That said, we have a bad record here.  This issue requires more attention from parliamentarians and those who have responsibilities in this regard.  Having underlined that point, I will not press the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.115" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#HH00400"><p>I move amendment No. 5:</p><blockquote>In page 17, between lines 23 and 24, to insert the following:<b>&ldquo;22. </b>The Minister shall not issue a direction to the National Treasury Management Agency when advised by the Agency that such a direction will reduce the value of its portfolio.&rdquo;.</blockquote> <p>This amendment seeks to remove doubt as to whether it was correct to overrule the NTMA and compel it to buy shares in Anglo Irish Bank.  My preference is that if the NTMA were to do that again, we would support it, because it cost &euro;30 billion the last time.  The Minister should have regard to what is happening to people's pension funds when good advice is being offered.  In fact, I praised the NTMA for doing that.  We found at the banking inquiry that the NTMA was one of the few organisations within the wider public sector to diagnose what was happening at Anglo Irish Bank.  It advised the former Minister for Finance, Deputy Brian Lenihan, that it would not be prudent to put any of the funds from the National Pensions Reserve Fund into the bank but he issued an order compelling it to do so.  My concern is that a mistake that happened in the past could happen again.  The advice from the NTMA was good and I commend it on that.  There were failures of regulation, particularly of Anglo Irish Bank, which ended up costing us &euro;30 billion.  That said, I do realise that this is part of the wider scheme in which the Minister has to operate.  I take the view that sometimes a financial institution should be allowed to fail because the cost of rescuing it is out of all proportion to any benefits that might accrue.  The banking inquiry will show that around 25 people accounted for the loss of &euro;30 billion.  Why did the other 4.5 million people have to bear the cost, with the pension fund reduced by &euro;30 billion?  It is a matter of balancing and I would have thought that some acknowledgement that the NTMA was right the last time might be worth putting on the parliamentary record.  Measures to prevent a recurrence of such events are worthwhile.  Maybe there should be better liaison between the NTMA, the Minister for Finance and departmental officials, lest we have a repeat, because nobody in these Houses wants a repeat of the scenario whereby &euro;30 billion from a pension fund disappears into a bank which proves to be worthless.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1106" speakername="Simon Harris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#HH00500"><p>I do not propose to accept this amendment on the grounds that it is not intended to revisit the operation of the NTMA or the Ireland Strategic Investment Fund at this time.  These will continue to operate in the manner prescribed in the NTMA (Amendment) Act.  This section of the Bill operates as a technical amendment and does not change the effect or the operation of section 37(a) of the NTMA (Amendment) Act or alter the ability of the Minister to issue directions to the NTMA.  It is a clarification to ensure that section 37(a) of the NTMA (Amendment) Act of 2014 operates in the manner intended by the legislature at the time of the enactment of that Act.  It aims to ensure there is no ambiguity in terms of ensuring that the way the Members of these Houses intended the NTMA to act in 2014 is the way it can continue to act.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#HH00600"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his response and will not be pressing the amendment.  However, I would prefer an intention not to put another &euro;30 billion into a dud bank.  I am highly unlikely to ever have to make such a decision, whereas the Minister is, so I will bow to that superior knowledge.  A system of checks and balances to make sure that it does not happen again would be very useful in terms of public policy making.  I thank the Minister of State and will not press my amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.119" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.120" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Section 22 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.121" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Schedule agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.122" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Title agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.123" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Bill reported without amendment, received for final consideration and passed.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.124" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#HH01200">Finance (Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill 2015: Motion for Earlier Signature</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#HH01300"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That pursuant to subsection 2&deg; of section 2 of Article 25 of the Constitution, Seanad &Eacute;ireann concurs with the Government in a request to the President to sign the Finance (Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill 2015 on a date which is earlier than the fifth day after the date on which the Bill shall have been presented to him.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.126" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.127" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 4 p.m. and resumed at 4.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.128" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#MM00100">Services for People with Asthma: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#MM00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State and call on Senator Mary Ann O'Brien to move the motion.  The Senator has ten minutes.  I understand Senator Averil Power will second the motion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1169" speakername="Mary Ann O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#MM00300"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>&ldquo;That Seanad &Eacute;ireann:<br /><br />notes The Case for Change report published by the Asthma Society of Ireland in February 2014, which included commentary on the prevalence and seriousness of asthma in Ireland; and<br /><br />acknowledges that:- there are very significant numbers of people in Ireland living with asthma;<br /><br />- hospital admissions from asthma are considered avoidable; recent OECD statistics show that the rate of admission in Ireland is slightly below the OECD average;<br /><br />- through a combination of the means-tested medical and GP card schemes and the phased roll-out of universal GP care, more people than ever before (over 2.1 million people) have access to a GP service without fees, including those families facing undue financial burdens and the youngest and oldest in society;<br /><br />- medical card holders are entitled to prescription medicines free of charge, subject to prescription charges capped at &euro;25 per month per person or family;<br /><br />- under the drugs payment scheme, no individual or family pays more than &euro;144 per month towards the cost of approved prescribed medicines, which significantly reduces the cost burden for families and individuals incurring ongoing expenditure on medicines;<br /><br />- significant progress has been made by the HSE in the development of the national clinical programme for asthma:<blockquote>- the programme has focused on the development of national asthma guidelines based on international best practice, both for acute care and ongoing asthma management;<br /><br />- emergency asthma guidelines for adults and emergency paediatric asthma guidelines have been published;<br /><br />- the emergency asthma guidelines for adults are currently being considered by the national clinical effectiveness committee and, once approved, will be formally launched;<br /><br />- guidelines for managing a patient with asthma in primary care have been approved by the Irish College of General Practitioners and were launched in May 2013;<br /><br />- the model of care for asthma has been approved by the HSE and is due to be launched in the coming months.  The model of care details how physicians, nurses, and other health care professionals will work with engaged patients to make the most appropriate clinical decisions and to collaborate with specialist colleagues in providing a safe, seamless patient experience within the health system in Ireland;<br /><br />- easily accessible patient asthma education supports have been developed in conjunction with the Asthma Society of Ireland to assist guided self-management;<br /><br />- the community-based asthma integrated care demonstrator project is scheduled to commence by the end of 2015; and<br /><br />- proposals for an audit of asthma deaths are being developed and will be expedited;</blockquote>- on 1st July 2015, GP care without fees at the point of access was introduced for children under six years, providing an enhanced service that includes an agreed cycle of care for children diagnosed with asthma;<br /><br />- negotiations are under way on a comprehensive new GP contract, a priority of which is the inclusion of chronic disease management, including asthma; and<br /><br />- the Government is committed to the extension of free GP services to all children under 12 years of age, subject to negotiations in relation to the scope of the service to be provided and the fee arrangements to apply.&rdquo;</blockquote> <p>I welcome the Minister of State.  I also welcome Sharon Cosgrove, chief executive officer of the Asthma Society of Ireland.  The two asthma sufferers with her are a little like Coca-Cola; they are the real thing.  They are Rebecca Fitzsimons and Catriona Kennedy.  I welcome them and thank them for coming to the Gallery this evening.</p><p>We are here to discuss asthma, which, believe it or not, directly affects 470,000 people in Ireland.  When I was approached by the Asthma Society of Ireland to table this motion, I quickly discovered that I had little knowledge of the prevalence of asthma in Ireland and the debilitating effect it can have on those with the condition.</p><p>What is asthma?  Asthma is a condition that affects the airways, the small tubes that carry air in and out of the lungs.  The airways become oversensitive which means they react to things that would normally not cause a problem, such as cold air or dust.  This reaction causes muscles within the wall of the airways to tighten and become narrow, thereby making difficult for the air to flow in and out.  The lining of the airways becomes swollen and sticky mucus is produced clogging up the breathing passage.  I have talked to some sufferers in preparation for this evening.  It is difficult for us to imagine.  It is somewhat like breathing through a tiny straw and being absolutely terrified while the chest is hurting at the same time.  It feels like one is fighting for one's life.</p><p>I wish to read some statistics into the record this afternoon in order to help us to keep our conversation in perspective.  Ireland has the fourth highest prevalence of asthma in the world.  In itself, the reason for that deserves to be a research project.  One adult in ten has asthma while one child in five has the condition.  Some 60% of people in Ireland have uncontrolled asthma, meaning they are at risk of an asthma attack.  Every 26 minutes someone visits an accident and emergency unit because of asthma.  More than one person every week dies in Ireland from asthma, although 90% of asthma deaths are preventable.  The economic burden of asthma is estimated to be &euro;500 million per year.  Adults miss an average of 12 days of work each year due to asthma and children miss an average of ten days in school due to asthma.  On average, asthma patients spend &euro;150 per month on medication and they can spend up to &euro;450 per year on general practitioner visits.</p><p>The information I have set out is rather stark.  My motivation in tabling the motion - and that of the Asthma Society of Ireland in encouraging me to do so - is to draw attention to the serious challenges that asthma presents to us as policy makers.  More importantly, it highlights the effects and burden that asthma places on those unlucky enough to have the disease.</p><p>The Asthma Society of Ireland was keen for me to acknowledge the Minister of State's positive engagement with it since she took up her position in the Department of Health.  In particular, the society referenced her most recent meeting with its representatives prior to the introduction of the budget in October.</p><p>We should reference the inclusion of the asthma cycle of care in the general practitioner contract relating to those under six years of age and the intention of the Minister of State to include that in the finalised contract relating to under 12s.  Furthermore, we should reference that the HSE is looking favourably on, and is engaged with, a proposal to fund the Asthma Society of Ireland asthma advice line next year for the first time.  This is a vital free resource for those with asthma in Ireland.  I hope the talks will conclude positively in the coming weeks.  I welcome the recent announcement by the Minister of State that the society would receive &euro;45,000 in nationally lottery moneys to help fund the inhaler technique campaign which the society ran earlier this year throughout the country.  However, despite these positive actions and the signs of future actions, many grave problems still exist for people in Ireland who are living with asthma.  I will outline some of these for the consideration and response of the Minister of State.  I know my colleague, Senator Power, will have a unique perspective on this topic as, unfortunately, she is asthmatic.  As with most situations in life, those who have walked in the shoes have the best understanding of the problems and challenges encountered on a daily basis.</p><p>As the Minister of State will appreciate from the time she has spent in the Department of Health and in politics in general, most of the time people clamour to highlight problems but few come to the table with suggested solutions.  I am not for a moment suggesting that this is what I am doing; I am merely going to point the House in the direction of the HSE national clinical programme for asthma, NCPA, which was agreed in 2011 following extensive consultation with all stakeholders.  Much to the frustration of the asthma society and its members, implementation has been slow, at best.  I note that the NCPA has developed a large range of guidelines.  However, I imagine even the Minister of State would acknowledge that implementation of the programme has not been seen, in particular, in primary care settings.  While this programme was developed before the period of the Minister of State in office, I am keen for her thoughts on why full implementation has been so slow.  I find it somewhat puzzling given that the HSE signed off on the plan.  Why has delivery been so difficult?  Has the Minister of State encountered opposition from the medical bodies or has the issue become lost in the broader health reform programme?</p><p>In its simplest form, the NCPA means that everyone with asthma in Ireland can avail of structured best-practice asthma care in their community.  Having read up on the programme it seems to me to draw on international best practice and learnings.  For the want of a better description, it presents the motorway to transforming the experiences of people with asthma in Ireland.  Interestingly, it should result in financial savings for the health service.  I call on the Minister of State to set out the achievements to date with the NCPA and outline her vision for its implementation in the period ahead.  I know the asthma society and those gathered in the Gallery are keen for the Minister of State to share her opinions on the following potential actions: the introduction of a scheme to assist people with asthma with the financial burden of their disease - a point Senator Power will illustrate in few moments; the delivery of a free annual asthma review for each person with asthma, as recommended in the HSE national clinical programme for asthma - this is crucial for a good asthma management; and, as per the national clinical programme for asthma, the undertaking of an asthma deaths study nationwide.  As a country, this is something we must address as soon as possible.  I await the contribution of the Minister of State with interest.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1200" speakername="Averil Power" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#MM00400"><p>I second the motion.</p> <p>I thank my Independent colleague, Senator Mary Ann O'Brien, for tabling this important motion.  The statistics she read into the record are stark indeed.  Two figures struck me in particular.  First, every 26 minutes someone visits an accident and emergency department due to asthma.  Second, someone dies every week because of asthma, yet 90% of these deaths are preventable.  That is frightening.  It means that every year we have approximately 50 people dying but 45 of them need not have died.  It is a great loss to their families and a sad indictment of our position in respect of this chronic condition.</p> <p>Asthma is a manageable condition.  With the right medication and proper management procedures there is no reason why someone should end up having an acute attack, let alone end up in an accident and emergency department or with fatal consequences.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Averil Power:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2351"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2351&amp;amp;pid=AverilPower&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Many successful athletes have asthma, including David Beckham, Ronan O'Gara and many GAA stars.  The Asthma Society of Ireland has worked with GAA stars to promote awareness of the fact that having asthma does not mean a person cannot exercise.  Even if one has exercise-induced asthma, there are ways of controlling it to enable exercise and help one to stay fit and look after one's health.  Having asthma does not need to hold people back and yet, as Senator Mary Ann O'Brien has said, 60% of people who have asthma do not have their condition under control.  I believe there are two main reasons for that.  One reason is under-developed primary care and a lack of education, and another reason is the cost of medication.</p><p>With regard to education, many asthma sufferers simply do know how to handle their condition properly using breathing techniques and in other ways that do not necessarily involve medication but that need to be taught.  I welcome the emphasis on asthma management under the programme of free GP care for children under six years of age, and I think it is good to start with young people.  Many people develop asthma while in their teens, so there is a need to help in that age group also.  I developed asthma in my teens.  I had my first asthma attack at a PE class in school.  I had no idea what was wrong with me.  All I knew was that I could not breathe and it was incredibly frightening.  A girl in my class handed me an inhaler and told me to take it.  I wondered what it was, but it worked.  I understand there are problems in some schools around the sharing of medication.  There is much bureaucracy and fear about taking medicines while in school and the possibility of someone taking the wrong medicine.  If that classmate had not handed me the inhaler I do not know what state I would have ended up in.</p><p>The cost of medication is the other big issue for people.  Asthma medication in shockingly expensive in Ireland.  I take a preventative inhaler called Seretide, which works extraordinarily well.  I exercise: I box, I run and I do all kinds of sport.  I can run on a treadmill for 20 to 30 minutes without taking any reliever inhaler because my preventative inhaler is so good.  However, it costs &euro;80 per month.  When I was in college I could not afford it.  On four or five occasions while I was in college I ended up in the accident and emergency department on nebulisers and had to stay in hospital overnight with frightening asthma attacks because I could not afford the inhaler.  There are costs to the health service because of that, let alone the cost to the individual of that frightening experience.  There is a cost to the health service of having people ending up in accident and emergency who, if they were getting proper medication, would not be there.  It should focus all our minds on what needs to be done.</p><p>Asthma is a chronic condition and I believe that people who have asthma should be entitled to participate in the long-term illness scheme, just as those with epilepsy or other long-term chronic conditions are entitled to the scheme.  Asthma is a lifelong condition and, as with diabetes or epilepsy, it is a life threatening condition.  It should be covered by the long-term illness scheme.  More needs to be done to bring down the cost of the medication. I know I am not unusual when I try to stockpile medication while I am away to avoid having to buy my inhalers in Ireland.  I bought my inhaler for &euro;38 in Greece last year.  In Ireland that inhaler costs me &euro;80, and while I know this is an ongoing issue with the pharmaceutical industry and the Government says it is trying to tackle it, a lot more needs to be done.  There is no justification for these exorbitant prices.</p><p>With regard to education, the Asthma Society of Ireland has done important work with schools and has provided education packs for schools, which is crucial.  Many young people will not realise they have asthma until they have an attack in a PE class or elsewhere.  It is important that teachers are equipped and that they know how to react without panic if a person has an attack.  The legislation is changing in relation to the use of EpiPens for people with nut allergies.  Will the Minister of State confirm whether that is also the case for inhalers?  I understand this caused concern in schools due to fears of litigation, but I believe it is important that a person should be able to get an inhaler without a refusal.</p><p>I will now turn the issue of GPs and the training for people with asthma to manage their condition.  Many GPs are so busy.  For example, in my own area of north Dublin we have the lowest rate in the country of GPs per head of population, with one GP for 3,500 people; the national average is one GP for 2,500.  If a person goes to visit a GP in north Dublin there is a trail of patients outside.  The GPs do not have the time they need to actually work with people to help them manage their conditions.  I appreciate that the Minister is doing that with the free GP care for those under six years of age, but this is also important across the general population.  The Asthma Society of Ireland has shown that when GPs in Finland engaged in a programme to help people manage their conditions and showed them how to use a peak flow meter properly, there was a 90% reduction in deaths and an 85% reduction in hospital admissions.  Education programmes are important, along with managing the costs of medications.</p><p>I thank Senator O'Brien for tabling this motion.  It is an issue that is important to me as an asthma sufferer.  It is quite shocking that Ireland has the fourth highest rate of asthma in the world, and the more we can do to tackle it - by managing people's conditions and also with clean air - the better.  One of the best policy decisions made by any Government was the smoking ban, because I know that if anyone smokes anywhere near me I can feel it aggravating my chest.  We need to do more to tackle pollution in the city, make the city more attractive for pedestrians and cyclists and promote a more healthy way of life that is good for everybody but especially for those of us who need clean air to survive and to avoid getting into problems.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#NN00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Kathleen Lynch, to the House.  She attends the House nearly two or three times a week.  I thank her for dealing with this very important matter.  I also thank the proposer of the motion, Senator Mary Ann O'Brien, and the seconder, Senator Averil Power.  Over 470,000 people are affected by asthma, which is a very large percentage of the population.  It is essential that we do everything possible to assist those who have asthma.  The motion talks about introducing a scheme to assist people with asthma with the financial burden of their condition, to deliver a free annual review for each person with asthma and to conduct an asthma death study nationwide.  There is one death per week, which is unnecessary in the sense that 90% of the deaths are preventable.  It is important to highlight the decisions that have been taken over the last three to four years. The Asthma Society of Ireland has done much work with all the interest groups - from the Department of Health to the HSE and the various research centres - in trying to progress a more comprehensive policy.</p> <p>On 1 July 2015 the Government brought in free GP care to those under six years of age, which had not been provided before.  Part of that process is the cycle of care for children under six years of age who have asthma.  More than 17,000 children have been registered under the programme, which is important for those children.  Up to now they did not have that free access to GP care, and where there are young children it is important that they get the best level of care at the earliest possible time.  Apart from the effect that asthma has on the individual, when we look at the figures on asthma we see that 1.4 million work days are missed each year, with a total of loss of earnings in the region of &euro;196 million.  Parents of children who have asthma are also losing many days from work because obviously they have to stay at home to look after their children and make sure the proper level of  care is provided.  The estimated cost of those lost days is &euro;67.5 million per annum.  This is a huge loss to those people who either have asthma themselves or whose family members have asthma.  Everything possible must be done to provide help and assistance for them.</p> <p>I understand that the national model for care for asthma has been approved by the HSE leadership team and should be rolled out within the next few months.  Another recent development is the health care professional education programme, which is a six-part modular theoretical e-learning programme.  We need to provide patient education also, and while those issues are progressing, are they progressing fast enough and what can be done to progress it?<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Colm Burke:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2353"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2353&amp;amp;pid=ColmBurke&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Access to health care is important.  Over 2 million people have a medical card or GP card.  It is important that over 2 million people have access to medical care without any real costs.  The next question is about the people who do not have that level of care.  How can we work with them to make sure they get the maximum benefit from our health services?  </p><p>This motion is important because of the cost to the health service of people who suffer from asthma.  The figures I have seen show that although there are 19,000 visits to accident and emergency departments yearly, only around 5,000 people are admitted to hospital.  If we can reduce the numbers who have to attend accident and emergency departments there will be less drain on our health services.  One of the frightening figures was that over a hundred people who suffer from asthma were admitted to intensive care.  That is nearly two people every week admitted to intensive care.  These are extremely frightening figures, which demonstrate why we need to make sure we have the best possible programme.  One of the earlier speakers referred to the programmes in Finland and Australia.  In Australia, a comprehensive programme was introduced which helped to reduce the level of the difficulties that people with asthma would run into and reduced the number of deaths.  Finland has reduced hospital admissions by something like 86%.  The evidence is there that if a comprehensive programme is provided and the work is done at local level by working with health care professionals such as GPs and nurses, people can be assisted with a planned programme of care.  That is extremely important.  We are going down the right road.  The question is how to expedite it and make sure that the programme is comprehensive in order to reduce the number of people who have to use hospital services in order to get the care they require.</p><p>I thank the Minister of State, the Department and the HSE for the work that has been done over the last three to four years.  We have a lot more to do.  It is important that we do everything possible to implement the programme in the shortest possible time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1115" speakername="Labhr&aacute;s &Oacute; Murch&uacute;" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#OO00200"><p>I compliment the Senators who tabled this motion.  It is clear from the statistics and from our own personal experience of people who have asthma that very often it seems to be below the radar.  If we get a common cold, we can feel very sorry for ourselves but we know it will pass very quickly.  One has to stop and think why people who suffer from asthma all the time feel they are not being listened to.  The Asthma Society of Ireland's report, Living with Asthma, which was published earlier in 2015, is quite clear in stating that people who have asthma feel they are not being listened to.  That is why this debate is so important and why we have to bring this issue back onto the radar.</p> <p>The absolute magnitude of the problem will be found in the statistics.  Almost half a million people suffer from asthma and 60% of these do not have it under control.  I would not have believed that until we got our documentation and read it.  That is why it is important that we are getting the documentation from the Asthma Society of Ireland and also from the Senators who are promoting the motion here this evening.  It is more telling, as in any health issue, when one knows someone who has asthma and sees how they suffer.  We are told, and I believe it to be true, that asthma does not have to be life-threatening or life-limiting.  That is what is important.  Yet it is life-threatening and life-limiting.  Why has this been allowed to happen?  As has already been mentioned here today, if 50 people with asthma go to an emergency department every day, then we have a serious situation.  As Senator Power has said, that is one person every 26 minutes.  That statistic alone has to be a wake-up call for us.  I believe that all intentions on these issues are correct, but there seems to be a piecemeal approach to the whole issue of asthma.  We do not have a holistic approach, which is absolutely vital because of the cost of medicines.  Asthma runs in families, so it may not be one, two, or three people in a family but a number of people.  Unless we have a proper overall strategy, the terrible statistics that have been presented here today will not change in the very near future.  We have had a huge debate on the cost of medicines in general over the past number of years and the Government has taken a step in the right direction to ensure that those costs are reduced.  That is progress.  Why has it not happened in this particular case?  I am sure the Minister of State will be able to tell us why it is the case that 25% of people suffering from asthma travel outside the country to buy their medicines because they cannot afford to buy them at home.  That statistic alone tells us that the medicines are available in other jurisdictions at a lesser price.  The question arises, as it did on our debate on medicines in general, of how it is happening and why it is possible.  I do not think we have any reason to disbelieve these statistics.</p> <p>I have never seen people being over-aggressive in looking for their rights on this issue.  Maybe that is part of the problem.  Perhaps assertive is a more appropriate word than aggressive.  I do not think they are aggressive, but they are suffering.  That is important.  The economic burden of asthma in Ireland is &euro;500 million every year.  We are told this could be reduced by two thirds.  I believe that will be the case if we have an overall strategy.  In today's debate we are all staying clear of partisanship and politics.  It is not about that.  It is about all of us trying to make some contribution to the way forward and towards a proper, focused, well thought-out, well monitored and well mentored strategy.  That is what people suffering from asthma want.  I praise the Asthma Society of Ireland for its fantastic work, not only for its publications or for giving us more information, but for the tenacity of the work it is doing and the way it sticks with it.  If the people suffering believe they are not being listened to, we need to listen and respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" speakername="John Gilroy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#OO00300"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the Chamber.  It is a very good and important motion, which I welcome.  I thank the proposer and seconder for introducing it here.  I find myself in full agreement with all that previous speakers have said.  I agree particularly with Senator &Oacute; Murch&uacute;, who said that we all think we know plenty about asthma until we actually do a bit of research into the figures and facts behind the obvious presentation of it.  I am psychiatric nurse.  I worked for nearly 30 years in hospitals and have come across asthma in its acute and subacute forms.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator John Gilroy:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2367"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2367&amp;amp;pid=JohnGilroy&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It was only when we started to read the research papers we were given on this issue that we realised the impact the condition has at the personal and societal levels.  I cannot conceive of anything more terrifying or alarming than finding oneself unable to breathe.  </p><p>Some of the statistics provided today give rise to serious concerns.  Senator Mary Ann O'Brien pointed out that Ireland has the fourth highest rate of asthma in the world, while Senator Power noted that one in five children aged between 13 and 15 years have asthma.  I was unaware of these figures, which are incredibly high.  Another awful statistic is that one person dies from asthma every week.  The general public is not aware of these facts, which should be disseminated more widely. </p><p>The medical approach is best left to medical experts in consultation with sufferers and user groups.  However, politicians have a role in the roll-out of policy at the medical, personal and societal levels.  It is great news that a national model was approved recently.  Will the Minister of State indicate what is the timeframe for the roll-out of the new programme?</p><p>Policy makers must consider ways in which we can make life easier for people who suffer from asthma and how the societal response to the condition can be made more cost-effective.  Ultimately, everything comes down to money.  Senator Burke spoke, for example, about the number of days at work and in school lost as a result of asthma.  The figures he cited are alarming.  I note also that 4,700 people are admitted to hospital as a result of asthma on average each year, with each hospital stay averaging 3.1 days.  This means the treatment of asthma accounts for 15,000 bed days in hospital every year.</p><p>Approximately 60% of asthma sufferers do not have their condition under control and 40% of this group cite the cost of their medication as the main reasons for this lack of control.  Asthma has a personal and societal cost.  A recent survey carried out by the Asthma Society of Ireland found that asthma sufferers spend between &euro;100 and &euro;144 per month on asthma medication.  Under the drugs payment scheme, no family or individual is required to pay more than &euro;144 per month for medication.  However, a person who pays &euro;144 per month on medication will need to earn &euro;3,500 before tax just to buy his or her medicines for the year.  To put this figure in context, a person suffering from asthma who earns the average industrial wage needs to spend 10% of his or her earned income on medication.  People suffering from asthma also report that they pay &euro;250 on average per annum for general practitioner services and lose an average of 12 work days per annum.  These are substantial costs for the individuals concerned.  </p><p>In addition to the large number of hospital admissions caused by asthma, Senators &Oacute; Murch&uacute; and Power pointed out that the condition is also responsible for approximately 50 attendances per day at accident and emergency units.  I wonder if the budgets for community care and acute hospital services are structured in such a way as to make it impossible to take such matters into consideration.  If the budget for the former declines, surely savings will be achieved in the latter budget.  They seem to be structured in such a way that these issues cannot be taken into consideration.</p><p>What would be the net cost to the Exchequer of adding asthma to the 16 conditions covered by the long-term illness scheme?  The figure should take into account the savings that would be achieved in many other areas and the significant number of asthma sufferers who are already covered under the medical card scheme.  There will be net and gross figures for the cost of including asthma in the long-term illness scheme.  I am interested in finding out the former.  It would be fantastic if the Minister of State intended to include asthma in the scheme.  If not, does she intend to roll out any other scheme that would specifically target asthma?  I look forward to hearing her response.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#PP00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for coming to the House to take part in this debate and commend the authors of the motion on raising the issue of asthma in the Seanad.  I was diagnosed with asthma a number of years ago, almost by accident.  I thought I had a bad cough linked to hay fever, a condition from which I suffer badly in the summer.  Most people do not realise that there is a connection between hay fever and asthma and it took me some time to figure out the link.  I was prescribed antibiotics for what I believed was a cough but it subsequently transpired that I was suffering from asthma.  The condition is often seasonal as I suffer most in the summer months when I also suffer from hay fever.</p> <p>A staggering 470,000 people in the State are living with asthma.  Even more disturbing is the statistic that one person dies from the disease every week.  Some of the facts and figures presented to us are incredible.  They demonstrate that asthma is a major problem on which a substantial amount of money is spent in the health service every year.  It is all the more important, therefore, that the issue is discussed in the House today.</p> <p>Attention must be drawn to the dangers of asthma and every effort made to put pressure on the Government, including the Minister of State, Deputy Kathleen Lynch, to take appropriate action to assist the almost 500,000 people in the State who suffer from the condition.  With regard to the management of asthma, the first step of the Health Service Executive's national clinical programme for asthma should be funded.  The Asthma Society of Ireland estimates that this would cost approximately &euro;2.5 million.  We often hear about the recovering economy, more fiscal space and more money about the place.  Given that all Departments are facing increased demands for more expenditure, I understand the need to prioritise.  However, &euro;2.5 million, while not an insignificant sum, is not an especially large amount when set against overall State income from taxation.  The Government can afford to provide the funding required to implement the first step in the national clinical programme for asthma.  The issue is whether it has the political will to do so.  According to the Asthma Society of Ireland, 59% of people surveyed believe asthma care would improve in Ireland if the programme were implemented.  It is disappointing to note that this it remains largely unimplemented, despite being adopted in 2011.  As a result of this failure, the Asthma Society of Ireland has called on the Government to set out a revised timetable and framework for its full implementation.  This is a reasonable request on the part of the society. </p> <p>The second step required is to introduce a free annual asthma review and written asthma action plan for all asthma sufferers.  This is a common sense and reasonable proposal, although clearly the issue of costs must be considered.  It is especially important given that it is reported that 59% of asthma sufferers have not had their condition reviewed in the previous years.  It is also alarming to learn that 72% of respondents in a survey did not have a written asthma action plan.</p> <p>A free annual asthma review is vital for good asthma management and care.  Chronic disease is responsible for the bulk of the workload of hospitals and its incidence is predicted to rise.  The long-term care of patients with conditions such as asthma represents a significant unnecessary cost burden on the acute hospital services where more timely and appropriate care could be provided in the primary care setting.  According to the Asthma Society of Ireland's Case for Change document, asthma is estimated to cost &euro;500 million per annum.  While some measures for the management of asthma and diabetes were announced in the most recent deals with general practitioners, these are limited in scope as they allow for just two years of asthma and diabetes care and only to those already receiving a certain level of care.</p> <p>A more fundamental debate about health service provision is required.  On the Order of Business this morning, Senators raised the national debate on whether universal health insurance will be introduced and what type of health model or service will be in place in future.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator David Cullinane:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2357"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2357&amp;amp;pid=DavidCullinane&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We need to reorient our health services and have a system based on need.  Its central focus should be placed on prevention, health promotion and primary care.  This is something on which the Government has done some good work, as should be acknowledged, as we have seen more focus on primary care centres.  We now see much more value in greater investment, prevention and primary care.  We must build on that in the time ahead as well.</p><p>The model of universal health care that my party is working to achieve includes GP and other primary care, as well as allied health professionals, medicines, dentistry, hospital and long-term care.  It deals with many of the issues quite rightly raised by Senator Gilroy regarding cost of health care for many citizens.  We end up paying anyway, whether it is through tax or private health insurance, or else people do not get the health care they need.  It is a big debate for all politicians to have as to whether we want a health service that delivers the health needs of people, going beyond reactive health care to invest properly in primary health care and prevention.  It costs money but we must have that debate.  Are we prepared as a society to pay for proper health services?  That forms part of this response as well, as it requires funding.  It is easy for us in the Opposition to say the Government should do certain things, but we must be able to say we are prepared to pay for it or ask people to pay more tax for that health care.  We cannot talk about universal health care or universal health insurance if we are not prepared to pay for it.</p><p>Quality of care is essential and must be at the core of the service.  Outside of waiting lists for specialists, perhaps nowhere is access to health services more unequal than in primary care.  In primary care, entitlements are given or denied on the basis of household finances or employment status rather than medical need.  I commend the authors of the motion.  It does not just mention the problem as it also puts forward solutions.  It calls on the Government to do a number of things, some of which I referenced.  The Government should consider the recommendations being made by the authors of the motion, as they have done their research, as well as the advocate organisations.  We all want the recommendations to be implemented.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#QQ00200"><p>I will call Senator Mullins next, if that is okay with Senator Eamonn Coghlan, because Senator Mullins will be taking the Chair.  I welcome to the Gallery Mike and Winnie Barbour, who are visitors to the country.  Winnie is an aunt of our good colleague, Senator Comiskey.  They are welcome and I hope they enjoy their visit.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#QQ00300"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Kathleen Lynch, to the House and thank her for coming her to facilitate this debate.  I particularly pay tribute to Senators Mary Ann O'Brien and Averil Power for giving us the opportunity to discuss the issue, highlighting the numbers of people who suffer from this condition.  I welcome the representatives of the Asthma Society of Ireland and compliment them on the information that has been supplied.  I am pleased to inform them that I helped with their recent church gate collection in my home town of Ballinasloe and we got a fantastic response.</p> <p>I did not realise the very significant numbers of people who suffer from asthma and we all know somebody who is affected.  I certainly did not realise it reached approximately 500,000 people, with a very significant cost borne by the health service.  It is estimated that 50,000 people use the GP out-of-hours services for the treatment of acute asthma every year, with 19,000 people visiting accident and emergency departments because of acute asthma.  There are 5,000 people admitted to intensive care because of the condition.  It is worrying that one person per week dies as a result of an asthma attack, but the good news is that 90% of those are preventable if services are provided and resources are made available.  It is very encouraging that people with asthma can lead a very full life, hold full-time occupations and participate in sport at the very highest level.  These are the positives.  The Government in recent times has provided GP care for those under six, which eases the burden on families.  That will be extended to those under 12, and those over 70 already have free GP care.</p> <p>A previous speaker referred to a negative in the form of medication costs.  Nobody has explained to me logically why the cost of medicine is so high in this country.  I was out of the country for a few days in the summer and I met a number of people on the flight whose main purpose for taking a break in the sun was to purchase medication for various conditions at a fraction of the cost here.  They paid only approximately a third of the cost that we would pay in Ireland for the same medication.  I cannot rationalise the issue so perhaps the Minister of State will refer to the matter in her response.</p> <p>Much has been achieved in recent years in heightening awareness of and assisting people with asthma.  We need to set some priorities for 2016.  The model of care for asthma is due to be launched in the next few months, and the resourcing of that model of care must be a priority for the Government and its successor in a few months.  We must create awareness and implement the national clinical guidelines for the management of acute asthma attacks in adults.  Integrated care services for patients with asthma must become a priority for the Government.  Senator Power referred to educational programmes for young people in schools in order that asthma in young people can be detected early.  Young people must be made aware of how to minimise the impact of asthma and how to seek assistance and medical care at an early stage.  We want to ensure that nobody in future will lose his or her life as a result of an asthma attack and we want to minimise the impact of asthma on the health services.  We want to see a reduction in the number of days lost at work and earnings forgone by parents as a result of having to take children with asthma to hospital in emergency cases.  The loss of production to the country is also significant.  We can work together as politicians to ensure resources are provided, with help and assistance made available.  The limited resources available to the State should be used in the most effective manner.</p> <p>I compliment Senators Mary Ann O'Brien and Averil Power on bringing forward the motion.  I look forward to hearing the Minister of State's response.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Michael Mullins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2368"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2368&amp;amp;pid=MichaelMullins&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I hope she will have positive news to impart to the House and to everybody adversely affected by asthma in this country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" speakername="Eamonn Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#RR00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House.  I would also like to thank and congratulate Senator Mary Ann O'Brien and Senator Power for bringing the motion to the House.  I had not intended to be here or even to speak on the motion today.  I had a meeting upstairs in my office and changed my mind about attending when I heard Senator Mary Ann O'Brien speak in an up-front fashion.  I was astounded to learn from her that in Ireland there are 470,000 people who live with asthma, that Ireland has the fourth highest prevalence of asthma in the world, that one in ten adults and one in five children suffer with asthma and that more than one person dies every week in Ireland from asthma although 90% of asthma deaths are preventable.  Therefore, it is important to highlight the effects of asthma on society.</p> <p>When I was growing up as a young boy, and as a young sports person, one never heard much about asthma or its affects.  One only heard about it when it was given as the reason a young person did not play sports, but such occurrences were rare and few.  Society has changed considerably over the past 40 or 50 years and so too has the affect of asthma on society, not just in Ireland but around the world.  I have often wondered why more people than ever before suffer from asthma.  The ban on burning coal and smoking cigarettes in public places has helped Irish society but asthma still affects us in a big way.  Why?  </p> <p>We know that asthma can be beaten and controlled.  As a matter of fact, from my sports career I am familiar with the female world record holder for the marathon, the great Paula Radcliffe.  She could run a marathon in two hours and 15 minutes, yet she suffers from asthma.  The great Haile Gebrselassie, a multiple world record holder, Olympic champion and world champion, has also competed over the years despite having asthma.  Listened to the debate on the monitor in my office, I heard Senator Power say that the great David Beckham suffers from asthma.  I know from my involvement in sports and coaching young children that quite a number of them have exercised-induced asthma.  Why?</p> <p>As a parent I have also witnessed asthma at first hand.  My son, John, had asthma but he happens to be a national athletics champion and even won a gold medal for Ireland in the European Cross Country Championships a number of years ago.  Senator &Oacute; Murch&uacute; has speculated that perhaps asthma runs in families.  My son has inherited his talent for running but there is no history of asthma among our immediate family and extended family.  My son is the only one in my family to suffer from it.  My wife and I have tried to find out why this is.  We were fortunate enough to have support in that we were able to find the best medical team available that prescribed the proper medication.  We were able to identify the correct time of day that he should use a flow meter, and whether it had to be done before or after exercise.  We also recorded everything daily for a long period in order to understand the condition.  Unfortunately, there are plenty of families who do not have the same support mechanisms available to them when it comes to tending to their asthmatic conditions.   </p> <p>People often wonder whether asthma comes from food, the musty damp conditions that are prevalent in some homes today, animal hair, pollen, carpet fibres and so forth.  My wife and I investigated whether these were the cause.  We even went to the extent of moving our son's bedroom.  Originally his bedroom was in the most northerly position of the house, where it did not get as much sun, and it tended to be a little damp.  We hoped that by moving him to another bedroom his condition would improve, and it did change his condition.  Over the past four or five years his asthmatic condition seems to have disappeared and he never talks about it anymore.</p> <p>Asthma is a serious problem and, as Senator &Oacute; Murch&uacute; has said, we need to focus going forward.  Senator Mary Ann O'Brien has recommended that we implement the HSE's national clinical programme for asthma, introduce a scheme to assist people with asthma with the financial burden of their disease, and deliver a free annual asthma review for each person with asthma, as recommended in the HSE national clinical programme for asthma.  I support the motion and look forward to hearing the remarks of the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#RR00300"><p>I had not planned to speak today but it is important that I put on record my appreciation for the motion moved by Senator Mary Ann O'Brien.  Sometimes we get so bogged down in our own little circles.  I was in the Chair for some time and I was not sure what the motion was about.  The motion is worthwhile and I thank her for tabling it.</p> <p>Thankfully, I have never smoked in my life and I have not had asthma.  A son of mine who is now an adult has suffered from asthma since he was a small child, yet he has had a successful rowing career and still runs a few marathons.  There was a psychological aspect to his asthma because he always had to have his little inhaler in his togs when he rowed, whether it was in the Lee Valley in Cork, Bantry Bay or the international Atlantic Challenge competition.  As a parent, one is always conscious of the fact that an asthma attack can strike at any time.  As my son grew older he was able to deal with it himself.  Thankfully, he seems to have grown out of asthma, particularly once he passed the age of 24 or 25.  He is still conscious of it, but asthma sufferers can live a normal life.  </p> <p>The motion calls for more to be done to ensure that people do not die from asthma and that they do not have to run in and out of the accident and emergency department taking up precious hospital time.  Asthma is a treatable condition.  I listened to Senator Eamonn Coghlan and I am not sure whether asthma is a climate issue.  Some people with the condition have found it to be upset by having animals in their homes.  Carpets can be another trigger.  I took carpets out of the rooms in my family home and replaced them with timber floors.  Some of these measures can help the condition.  I have a first cousin, who has been resident in America for many years, who suffered intensely from asthma as a child.  I remember what happened sometimes on the way home from mass at the nearest church in Kilcrohane, which was over a mountain.  I am one of 11 children and myself and my sister used to give my cousin a piggyback when he suffered an asthmatic attack in order to get him home.  Once he moved to the United States permanently his asthma disappeared.  I met him recently for the first time in 16 years at a funeral and he said that it never bothered him again, so perhaps asthma is affected by climate.  We should be cognisant in Ireland that we have a climate that is conducive to asthma, chest conditions and various other ailments.  However, there is no magic button to solve the issue.</p> <p>We have had a worthwhile debate and I thank the Minister of State for coming to the Seanad to debate the issue.  In conclusion, I offer my support and thank Senators Mary Ann O'Brien and Power for sharing their experiences, and the same goes for the Asthma Society of Ireland.  An asthma attack is very frightening for young children.  I have witnessed it and I know, as a parent, that one worries and seeks ways to cope with the condition.  Today's motion is very important and I am sure the Minister of State will respond sympathetically.  I also thank her for allowing me the grace to attend to another commitment outside this House tonight.  I am grateful to have been allowed to say a few words of support on a simple but important issue that the health sector and society has to deal with. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" speakername="Terry Brennan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#RR00400"><p>Ar dt&uacute;s ba mhaith liom f&aacute;ilte a chur roimh an Aire.  I, too, want to be associated with the compliments expressed to Senators Mary Ann O'Brien and Power on their motion and congratulate them.  The motion is simple but it is on a condition that affects many people.</p> <p>As I am the last speaker, many of my figures have already been quoted.  It has been estimated that nearly 450,000 people in Ireland have doctor-diagnosed asthma, with many other cases going undiagnosed.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Terry Brennan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2360"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2360&amp;amp;pid=TerryBrennan&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is one of the most common chronic conditions among Irish children and young adults.  Despite more than two decades of international asthma management guidelines, the majority of people with asthma in Ireland continue to suffer avoidable illness and poor quality of life.  Approximately 50,000 patients are established to use the GP out-of-hours service for the treatment of acute asthma in a year, as stated by my colleague, Senator Colm Burke.  More than 19,000 people visit accident and emergency departments annually with acute asthma while more than 5,000 patients are admitted to hospital.  Of these, approximately 100 are so severely ill that they are admitted to intensive care units.</p><p>The HSE's national clinical programme for asthma was set up to design and standardise the delivery of high-quality asthma care to all who need it.  Through the understanding of the current health status and needs of people with asthma, the programme can target measures where they are needed and measure the effectiveness of any interventions.  The initial focus of the national clinical programme for asthma has been the development of asthma education initiatives for patients and health care professionals, the development and implementation of national asthma guidelines and the organisation and better integration of national asthma services at primary and secondary care level.  This approach has been shown to be effective at international level with significant improved outcomes both for patients and care givers.  The national clinical programme for asthma is also focusing on improving asthma control in the community, thereby reducing acute asthma attendances at emergency departments, in-patient admissions and deaths from asthma.  When one considers that there is one death per week according to my note, albeit I understand it may even be one per day, a large number of people are dying from asthma attacks.  The national clinical programme for asthma has also focused on the development of national asthma guidelines based on international best practice both for acute care and ongoing asthma management.  Emergency adult asthma guidelines and emergency paediatric asthma guidelines have been published and the reports can be located on the HSE's website.</p><p>Asthma control in general practice guidelines for managing patients with asthma in primary care settings have been developed and approved by the Irish College of General Practitioners.  The model of care for asthma has been approved by the HSE leadership team and is due to be launched in the coming weeks.  A national clinical programme for asthma will also contribute to the development of a chronic disease pathway and is being progressed by the HSE.  A self-learning, six module, e-learning theoretical programme on asthma, based on the national evidence-based guidelines and developed by the NCPA in conjunction with the Asthma Society of Ireland, is freely available.  In addition, a practical workshop is also being delivered by the respiratory clinic and nurse specialists for staff in primary and secondary care settings.  To reflect the introduction of the under-sixes' free GP care contract, the NCPA is also in the process of updating educational programmes.</p><p>I will finish there, the rest of what I had to say having already being mentioned.  I congratulate my colleagues for bringing forward the motion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#SS00200"><p>Senator Moloney is next and has six minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Moloney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#SS00300"><p>I do not need six minutes as I am not an expert in this field.  I had no intention of speaking on the motion and have come to the House to relieve our party spokesperson on health.  I was listening to the debate in my office and the only reason I am going to speak is because I am now asthmatic.  I was diagnosed when I was pregnant many moons ago.  I would not even consider myself an asthmatic because I could go for two or three years without ever having to use an inhaler.  It is just something that crops up every now and again.</p> <p>This summer, however, when I was working here I began to get worse and worse.  It got to a point where I could not even climb the stairs outside without stopping at the top to cough and get my breath back.  I was doing all the usual things we all do involving nasal sprays, nasal washes and using the normal inhaler that I always keep in my bag just in case, but none of it was working.  I went to the doctor saying "Flip this for a game of soldiers, there must be something more wrong".  I was prescribed a new inhaler which cost &euro;85.  I am not complaining about the cost which I can afford, but there are many people out there who cannot afford it.  It is quite expensive for people when they are put on something as strong as that.  People have been lobbying, including the Asthma Society of Ireland and ordinary people who suffer from asthma, to have asthma placed on the long-term illness scheme.  I can understand the problems that would arise if that was to be done because there is a question as to where one would draw the line.  Does one go from the child with croup up to those people with full-blown asthma which threatens their lives?  In any event, I emphasise the cost of the medication, which is very costly for people.</p> <p>I have been in a country where one can walk into a shop and buy these medicines over the counter without the need for a prescription.  I cannot understand why one has to have a prescription in one country but not in another, notwithstanding that it is the same medication which will have the same effect.  I remember when I was diagnosed first, I was taking the medication in liquid form.  One got it over the counter and took it with a spoon.  I remember the doctor saying to me that it really needed to go on prescription because it was so dangerous.  People do not realise how dangerous it is because it opens the airways.  One can take too much and collapse on the street.  I had never realised how dangerous it was.  I went onto the inhaler and I do not think it is even possible to get it in liquid form anymore.  I am not sure because I do not use it.</p> <p>I thank the Senators for raising the issue.  While to some it might seem like a very mild illness compared to other illnesses out there, for the person who suffers badly with asthma and cannot breathe, it is dangerous.  A friend of mine was walking along the street one day and could not find her inhaler.  When she got to her car she had to hold on to it because she started to collapse.  She fell on the street.  Luckily, someone came along who had an inhaler and gave it to her.  I think that girl would be dead today had that stranger not come along with an inhaler in her bag.  We hear all the time of people dying from asthma and it is very sad.  I acknowledge that the Minister has a whole clinical programme going on.  There is a long briefing before us and Senators have put forward a very detailed motion for which I thank them.  I welcome the debate and await the Minister of State's reply with interest.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/982" speakername="Kathleen Lynch" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#SS00400"><p>I thank Senators Mary Ann O'Brien and Power and the Asthma Society of Ireland for their engagement over a long period in terms of the most Government appropriate response to asthma.  I thank the Members who contributed to the debate.  I say on most if not all occasions I stand up in the House that the Seanad gives people an opportunity to discuss issues that do not get the type of air time they may deserve.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Kathleen Lynch:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=656"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=656&amp;amp;pid=KathleenLynch&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is a very good platform in that regard.  The most peculiar matters are discussed in here.  In this instance, we are discussing something that could well affect each and every one of us.  I thank the Senators who tabled this motion and the Cathaoirleach for the opportunity to discuss it.</p><p>I do not think there is any dispute between on us on this matter.  I am delighted to support the motion before the House, which acknowledges the Government's commitment to the provision of primary care to people with chronic diseases such as asthma, which remains a significant challenge for our health services.  The motion also recognises that we are promoting healthier lives for everyone in our communities.  I agree with the point that has been made with regard to medication.  I have read through the speech that has been prepared for me but I am not sure whether it includes a reference to this issue, which I discussed with the president of the Irish Pharmaceutical Healthcare Association recently.  I understand that the Department will enter into further discussions with the association within weeks.  I will ensure the cost of asthma medication is on the agenda for those discussions.  I am happy to make that promise here.</p><p>I acknowledge those involved in the Asthma Society of Ireland and the HSE's national clinical programme for asthma.  I pay tribute to them for their joint efforts in improving the lives of asthma patients.  I am aware of the statistics highlighted in a report produced by the society, The Case for Change: Implementing the National Clinical Programme for Asthma, which was published in 2014.  These statistics, which can also be found in other available data, make it clear that asthma is a serious burden for patients and our health services.  This is compounded when one considers that up to 90% of deaths from asthma are preventable.  I do not intend to get into a debate on statistics.  One can get different statistics depending on what week it is and on what source one uses.  We have statistics from the CSO.  At times, we cannot be certain about the exact cause of death or the exact numbers.  This point is sometimes made in debates about suicide.  In 2012, the CSO recorded 39 deaths from asthma, 22 of which involved people aged 85 or older.  There was an increase in 2013, when 54 deaths were recorded, 35 of which involved people aged 85 or older.  This was followed by a decrease last year, when 37 deaths were recorded, 15 of which involved people aged 85 or older.  This is still too many.  I agree that we must strive to address this as soon as possible.</p><p>The HSE's national clinical programme for asthma was set up in 2011 to design and standardise the delivery of high-quality asthma care to everyone who needs it.  The programme has made significant progress since its establishment.  Initially, it focused on the development of asthma education initiatives for patients and health care professionals, the development, implementation and organisation of national asthma guidelines and better integration of national asthma services at primary and secondary care levels.  This approach has been shown to be effective at international level with significant improved outcomes for patients and care givers.  The national clinical programme for asthma is focusing on improving asthma control in the community.  Its aim is to reduce acute asthma attendances at emergency departments, inpatient admissions and deaths from asthma.  Among the specific priority solution areas being explored by the programme are the development of a national model of care with guidelines, care pathways and treatment protocols for use in primary and secondary care settings.  This work is being carried out in conjunction with other national clinical programmes, including those in the areas of emergency medicine, acute medicine, critical care, obstetrics and gynaecology, paediatrics and neonatology and primary care.</p><p>The development and delivery of asthma education programmes for health care professionals to underpin the guidelines is an important aspect of the work of the national clinical programme for asthma.  Integrated care initiatives that aim to improve the diagnosis and management of asthma patients in the primary care setting, with links to specialist adult asthma services, are also being developed.  Those involved in the Asthma Society of Ireland are probably more aware than most that the doctor is not always needed in these cases.  We can do far more if our approach involves getting specialist nurses or health care professionals involved in the management and education aspects of this matter.  I know that is the society's approach as well.  The national clinical programme for asthma has developed national asthma guidelines based on international best practice for acute care and ongoing asthma management, including emergency adult asthma guidelines and emergency paediatric asthma guidelines.  These reports can be found on the HSE website.  The emergency adult asthma guideline, which is a national clinical guideline for the management of acute asthma attacks in adults, has been prioritised and quality assured by the Department of Health's national clinical effectiveness committee.  It is due to be published and launched next week.</p><p>Work is ongoing on the emergency paediatric asthma guidelines, known as the national clinical guidelines for management of acute asthma attacks in children.  It is intended that these guidelines will be submitted to the committee in 2016.  Guidelines for managing patients with asthma in primary care have been developed and approved by the Irish College of General Practitioners.  They were launched in May 2013 and are available on the college's website.  The national clinical programme for asthma is planning to work with the college to update these guidelines.  The model of care for asthma has been prepared and is due to be launched in the coming months.  The model details how physicians, nurses and other health care professionals will work with engaged patients to make the clinical decisions that are most appropriate to their circumstances.  It also sets out how they can collaborate with specialist colleagues in providing a safe and seamless patient experience within our health system.</p><p>It is appropriate to say at this stage that an obvious need exists in this regard.  The economic and health impacts of asthma on society and on patients are also obvious.  That is why one of the first two chronic disease management programmes to be developed in the primary care sector relates to asthma.  That, in itself, is an indication of the realisation that this is an issue about which we can and should do something.  In anticipation of the launch of the model of care for asthma, the national clinical programme for asthma has been developing and preparing for the roll-out of the asthma integrated care demonstrator project across two initial sites.  These are linked to the catchment areas of the Midland Regional Hospital in Mullingar and Connolly Hospital in Dublin.  The demonstrator project plans to improve the diagnosis and management of asthma patients in the primary care setting with links to specialist adult asthma services.  Its aim is to improve health outcomes and reduce service demand.  Two new clinical nurse specialist posts have been approved for this project.  They were advertised last week.  It is hoped that the recruitment process will be completed before the end of the year.  The HSE will consider expansion of this initiative based on the success of the demonstrator project.</p><p>The Asthma Society of Ireland's report, The Case for Change: Implementing the National Clinical Programme for Asthma, highlights the importance of asthma education for health care professionals and patients.  The national clinical programme for asthma agrees with this approach.  A modular self-learning programme, which is based on the national evidence-based guidelines and was developed by the national clinical programme in conjunction with the Asthma Society of Ireland, is available online for health care professionals who wish to update their knowledge.  This programme will enable health care professionals to underpin their skill sets with theory.  A similar programme for general practitioners is available on the website of the Irish College of General Practitioners.  A practical workshop is being delivered by the respiratory clinical nurse specialists for staff in primary and secondary care.  The national clinical programme for asthma is updating education programme materials to reflect the introduction of the free GP care contract for those under the age of six.  Just as it is important to provide appropriate asthma education to health professionals, it is equally important that relevant education is made available to asthma patients.  In this regard, up-to-date information is available for patients and their families and carers.  The national clinical programme for asthma has implemented easily accessible patient asthma education supports in conjunction with the Asthma Society of Ireland to assist guided self-management for this chronic condition.  These supports are available on the websites of the HSE and the Asthma Society of Ireland.</p><p>As I said earlier, deaths related to asthma are preventable.  In this regard, the national clinical programme for asthma has initiated research work which will involve examining acute asthma deaths in Ireland.  The aim of the project is to identify and understand preventable factors relating to the management and self-management of asthma so that we can improve the further care of people with asthma and prevent further asthma deaths.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Kathleen Lynch:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=656"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=656&amp;amp;pid=KathleenLynch&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The objectives are to identify all asthma deaths in Ireland during the study period; explore the circumstances surrounding each death from asthma, including trigger factors, awareness at school or work, environmental conditions, lifestyles and activities, medication and adherence to treatment plans, and organisational aspects of care; analyse key themes, particularly preventable factors; and propose solutions for adoption by the national asthma programme in respect of clinical practice, service provision, education of professionals and patient education.  This work will be led by the programme's clinical lead and its public health specialist.  I have asked the HSE to start this work as soon as possible and I look forward to its findings, which I hope will lead to fewer asthma deaths in the future.</p><p>It is evident that the asthma programme and the Asthma Society of Ireland have been working strenuously together to address key issues relating to asthma care.  Progress may be slower at times than everyone would like but it is encouraging that steady progress has been made, especially at a time of scarce resources.  As our financial circumstances improve, I am confident that further improvements for asthma patients will be achieved.</p><p>I am pleased that the Government is playing its part in improving asthma care.  It is reforming the system of health service eligibility and seeking to make it fairer.  For many years, Irish patients have had universal eligibility for acute hospital services but the first point of contact with the health service, provided by GPs, has only been provided on a public basis to those on low incomes.  The provision of universal GP access through greater public investment in primary care services is a critical reform in resolving inequities and rebalancing services towards earlier prevention.  We want to shift the emphasis in our health system from an "illness model", dependent on care in hospitals, to a model where primary care services are strengthened and health and well-being are promoted.  A number of building blocks are fundamental to this shift from reliance on acute care to where it is best accommodated at primary care level.  GP care without fees is one of the principal building blocks to make this happen.  The Government is committed to introducing, on a phased basis, a universal GP service without fees.  Many people delay or even avoid going to their GP for essential medical care as they simply cannot afford the &euro;50 or &euro;60 fee per visit.  When people delay going to their GP and getting regular preventative and screening care, it results in the late detection of illness, poorer health outcomes and greater pressures on our hospitals - pressures that our hospital system can ill-afford.  The Government wants this to change and good progress has been made.</p><p>The new contract with GPs for children aged under six includes for the first time in primary care the provision of a cycle of care for child patients with asthma.  The asthma programme and the Asthma Society of Ireland have welcomed the introduction of this first step in the provision of a comprehensive programme for asthma across primary and secondary care.  The cycle of care includes key actions such as checking inhaler technique, provision of a written asthma action plan, review of asthma medications and recording of smoking status of the home.  In addition to the introduction of GP care without fees at the point of access for children aged under six, GP care without fees to all persons aged 70 years and over was introduced.  These represent the first phase in the delivery of a universal GP service.  On reading the research into asthma, I was not as conscious that the majority of deaths occurred in the over 85s age cohort and, therefore, free over 70s GP care provision will be crucial.  The under-six arrangements will also be important in the context of education and developing practice but the over 70s provision will be equally important.</p><p>Under the new arrangements, effective from 1 July 2015, an additional 270,000 children aged under six will benefit from GP care free at the point of access.  The new extended GP service applies to all children in this age cohort, including the 166,000 who held a medical card or GP visit card.  To date, more than 210,000 children have been signed up for the under six service, which includes age-based preventative checks focused on health and well-being along with the asthma cycle of care mentioned earlier.  More than 17,500 children have been registered for the asthma cycle of care by their GPs, under which each one of them will be reviewed annually by their doctor.  The introduction of GP care without fees at the point of access to all persons aged 70 years and over commenced on 5 August 2015.  To date, in excess of 47,000 people have registered for this service.</p><p>The HSE, the Department of Health and the IMO have commenced talks on a new GP contract, and a priority of these discussions will be the inclusion of chronic disease management for patients.  As a first step in this process, agreement has been reached on the introduction of a diabetes cycle of care for patients with type 2 diabetes who hold a medical card or GP visit card.  The cycle of care aims to augment the service available to GMS diabetic patients prior to the introduction of a comprehensive structured chronic disease programme.  The diabetes cycle of care commenced on 1 October and to date, more than 55,000 patients have been registered for the service by their GPs.  Currently, in excess of 2.1 million people can avail of free GP services, more than 1.7 million of whom can also avail of free prescribed approved medicines, subject to the relevant prescription charges.  The Government remains committed to expanding free GP to more patients and in this context budget 2016 committed to a further extension of GP care without charges to children aged 11 and younger.</p><p>This will be subject to negotiation with the IMO in respect of the scope of the service to be provided and the fee arrangements to apply and will be implemented in the context of overall new arrangements and not as a stand-alone extension or amendment to the current contract.  If we were going to bring it up to the under 12s, we should have brought it down to the over 65s as well, but I did not get my way on that.  I am confident that the ongoing work of the HSE's asthma programme and the Government's commitment to introduce universal GP care for the entire population will over time reduce the cost burden on asthma patients.  Meanwhile, where asthma patients do not qualify for free medicines under the GMS or the drug payment scheme, they or their family have to pay a maximum of &euro;144 each month for approved prescribed drugs, medicines and certain appliances for use by them or their family in that month.  I hope the negotiations with the IPHA will reduce that burden on patients.</p><p>I am confident all these initiatives will have a positive impact on the health of our nation, including asthma patients, and will reduce the burden on those patients and on our hospital services.  I thank the Senator again for raising this issue.  It is an excellent subject for debate and it will raise awareness of this issue, which is crucially important.  Somehow or other, we seem to look on asthma and other chronic conditions as ailments that people have to get on with when, in fact, there are mechanism for ensuring people can live a much healthier, longer and more productive life if they are managed properly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1169" speakername="Mary Ann O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#UU00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for her response and all the Senators who took time to contribute.  I would like to acknowledge the work of the Asthma Society of Ireland.  As we have all admitted, we have friends with asthma and I was aware of this at the start of my journey on this issue but I did not know that almost 500,000 citizens are affected by the disease.  Every Member should have been present for the debate, which has been positive.  I loved the word "promise".  The Department will have discussions with the IPHA regarding the cost of medication.  It is the equivalent of a small mortgage.  The Minister of State said individuals or families who do not have a medical card, which amounts to a significant number, will only have to pay a maximum of &euro;144 monthly but-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/982" speakername="Kathleen Lynch" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#UU00300"><p>I did not say "only"; I took that out of my speech.  It is in the Senator's copy but I did not say the word.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1169" speakername="Mary Ann O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#UU00400"><p>The Minister of State and I agree it is a small mortgage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/982" speakername="Kathleen Lynch" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#UU00500"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1169" speakername="Mary Ann O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#UU00600"><p>As Senator Power said, she can afford that but many cannot.  I have read the Finnish study and the Minister of State outlined the way she is going.  Education is a key factor and she is on that journey.  It is staggering what Finland achieved.  Aside from the 500,000 people who are suffering, there is a significant cost to the health service, which could be dramatically reduced.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Mary Ann O'Brien:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2389"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2389&amp;amp;pid=MaryAnnOBrien&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=18"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Senator Gilroy said that asthma accounts for 15,000 bed days a year in hospital.  If we reduce that by 90%, it will be down to 1,500 bed days every year.  Those bed days could be used in other ways.<br/><br/>I will return to the issue of education.  The Asthma Society and the HSE have given us much information.  That is what we are discussing and we can educate parents, families, patients, GPs, nurses and pharmacists.  Senator Power mentioned the EpiPen and that an inhaler can now be dispensed by a pharmacy without prescription.  My little daughter is only a mild asthmatic.  I was in Kilkenny at the heritage conference recently when she had an attack and she called me.  She did not have her inhaler because she has mild asthma.  I said, &quot;What do you mean you do not have your inhaler?&quot;  I went to the presentation in Kilkenny and ran into the pharmacy.  The pharmacist said she could not give it to me because I did not have a prescription.  The Minister of State has passed the legislation.  She should inform pharmacists soon that they can dispense inhalers without a prescription because it is serious when a child or adult cannot breathe.  The training will be rolled out but pharmacists should know that they can give inhalers to help people.<br/><br/>We talked a lot about Ireland.  Unfortunately, we have the fourth largest instance of asthma in the world.  It is not something we are proud of and we all question why this is.  I will ask the Minister of State a question about joining the dots.  Environmental conditions contribute to asthma and allergies and air quality has a huge effect on asthma sufferers.  Will the Department of Health and Children join the Department of Environment, Community and Local Government and the Environmental Protection Agency, EPA, to monitor the air quality in Ireland and crystallise a vision and strategy for the future to improve our air quality?  It is fantastic that we have stopped smoking and we have great plans on climate change.  We get our pollen counts from the UK because we do not have our own pollen count.  Pollen is the name of the game for asthma sufferers in the summer months.  Damp, mould and stress are also factors.  <i>Thorax</i>has published peer-reviewed research.  The Thoracic Society of Australia and New Zealand cites processed foods, a diet high in sugar and fat, and fast food.  Senator Eamonn Coghlan said earlier that long ago we knew a few people with asthma but it has become an epidemic.  The HSE should keep up to date with the peer-reviewed research.  Diet is becoming a modern plague and sometimes what we eat is a worry.<br/><br/>I thank Senator Mullins who was collecting for the Asthma Society earlier.  If any Senators want to offer their time at the weekend to collect for the Asthma Society, it will be delighted.  Senator Gilroy said correctly that we have a plan and now we need the timetable.  I thank the Minister of State for the timetable she has laid out.  In addition to her promise on medications, I ask her to push the HSE to move on in a timely manner.  The Asthma Society is doing great work but we have a serious problem in this country.<br/><br/>We have discussed our damp, mouldy climate and diet.  We have to move in a timely manner.  Much of the research and work has been done since 2011.  Given her responsibilities in the mental health area, the Minister of State has many things to worry about.  This is a bit of low-hanging fruit.  It is chronic but we have to address it.<br/><br/>The Acting Chairman will make me sit down.  I could talk for the evening because I have so much to say.  We should communicate with the pharmacists so they know they can give out inhalers without prescription.  I thank everyone and ask them to continue to discuss this subject because almost half a million of our citizens are suffering from this.  The Minister of State should reduce the cost of the medication and perhaps the introduction of a chronic illness card should be on the agenda in future for asthma sufferers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.158" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#VV00400"><p>When is it proposed to sit again?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015111800002#VV00500"><p>At 10.30 a.m. tomorrow.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-11-18a.161" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>The Seanad adjourned at 7 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Thursday, 19 November 2015.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>