<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.2" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 14:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.4" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.5" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#A00100">Gnó an tSeanaid - Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#B00100"><p>I have received notice from Senator P&aacute;draig Mac Lochlainn that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Education and Skills to provide an update on the provision of the new school building at Moville community college, County Donegal.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Tim Lombard of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Education and Skills to make a statement on the processes in place to ensure the provision of sufficient places for students with special needs.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Lorraine Clifford-Lee of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Education and Skills to provide an update on the status of remedial works and the completion of external precautionary measures identified for Ardgillan community college, Balbriggan, County Dublin. </blockquote> <p>The matters raised by the Senators are suitable for discussion and they will be taken now.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.7" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#B00200">Nithe i dtosach suíonna - Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.8" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#B00300">Schools Building Projects Status</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#B00350"><p>I welcome the Minister, Deputy McHugh, to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#B00400"><p>The Minister is familiar with Moville community college, having visited it a number of times over the years.  Last night, there was a large attendance of teachers, parents and students and there was great anger in the room at the delays that have been ongoing for years in delivering the new school buildings.  The Minister will be aware that the existing prefab buildings are completely unacceptable.  There are dilapidated conditions on the outside and leaks in the home economics room, for example.  Facilities have been completely inadequate for a long time.  Young people are crowded in together.  The physical education, PE, facilities are utterly unacceptable by modern standards.  There is no storage space.  They can only avail of two of the approximately 18 options on the PE curriculum because of the limited capacity.  The existing school building has substantial cracking throughout.  I visited recently and could literally see from one room into the next through a horizontal crack going the whole way along the middle of the wall.  They have an excuse for canteen facilities.  They have to have caterers come in from outside to provide food on a bench.  Toilets are closed.  Kids are literally sitting down on the floor eating their food.  This has been going on for years.  The teachers and students and the principal have acted in good faith and have waited for these plans to proceed to construction phase.  The prefabs in which they are teaching are Third World facilities.  It was said last night that they provide a First World education in the school with fantastic teachers but that they have Third World facilities.  This needs to come to an end.  The Minister is a Donegal man and I hope and trust that he feels as strongly as I do.  The anger in that room last night was palpable.  We need to send a message from this Chamber today that the bureaucracy is coming to an end and that we will fast-track this project to planning and construction.  We must end the period of the prefabs.  We also need to give assurances that the serious structural issues within the existing building are going to be resolved and made safe as soon as possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1290" speakername="Joe McHugh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#B00500"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this issue.  I was briefed on the meeting last night and I want to put on record my apologies to the staff and students for not being in a position to go as I had a prior engagement that was arranged last October.</p> <p>I thank the Senator for raising this matter as it gives me the opportunity to provide an update to the House on the current position regarding Moville community college, a building project that is critical in providing for the needs of the local community.  Under the Project Ireland 2040 plan, Moville community college will be provided with 4,500 sq. m of new space through a stand-alone extension.  This will allow for the expansion of the college to accommodate 550 pupils.  The new extension will include 13 new classrooms, science labs, engineering and technology rooms, a new library, a general purpose room and dining facilities, as well as a PE hall with ancillary space and a 550 sq. m special needs base.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Joe McHugh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2018"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2018&amp;amp;pid=JoeMcHugh&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=21"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> Delivery of the project to which this matter relates has been devolved to Donegal Education and Training Board, DETB. under a service level agreement finalised in January 2017.  While it has taken longer than expected to reach the current stage of development, I assure the House that DETB has been progressing the project as effectively and efficiently as possible and has been liaising with officials in the Department of Education and Skills, as appropriate.  This was one of the first items discussed at the initial meeting with the building unit when I was appointed as Minister</p><p>The House may wish to know that, in accordance with its terms of engagement, DETB has served a notice of termination on the existing architect.  No new appointment will be made until the notice of termination takes effect.  In the meantime, work is continuing on the project with the remaining members of the design team.  The project is currently at stage 2a - pre-planning design.  DETB and its design team met my officials on 12 February in respect of that matter.   A number of design issues were raised at said meeting and in correspondence with the DETB since.  These are being addressed.  I am satisfied that DETB will progress the project as quickly as possible with its new architect, once appointed.  Once the issues to which I refer are addressed and a new architect is in place, approval will be given to DETB to lodge a planning application for the new extension.  It is expected that a planning application will be lodged with Donegal County Council for the project in September or October.  Subject to any issues arising during the planning process, the project can then be expected to proceed to tender.</p><p>Separately and independently as a stand-alone project, I am aware that a number of issues with the existing building have been brought to the attention of officials in the Department of Education and Skills by DETB officials.  I am conscious that this is a cause of concern for the students, staff and parents of the school.  However, I can assure the House that officials from the Department of Education and Skills have been in regular contact with DETB, which is working diligently to address these issues.  In that regard, the Department has recently received two detailed reports on the matter from DETB.  On foot of these, it has approved the completion of a number of surveys and some essential works to be carried out over the course of this summer.  The outcome of those surveys will determine the further action required to address these issues.</p><p>In addition, DETB has been liaising with Departmental officials in respect of disability access issues, as well as the condition of the current prefab block of accommodation on site.  On the latter, I am conscious that the existing prefab accommodation requires refurbishment.  I am pleased to be able to inform the House that approval has recently been given for that refurbishment to take place to ensure that it provides for the needs of the school until the stand-alone extension is completed.  The works on the existing building and the prefabs will take place under one contract during the summer, and delivery of these works is also devolved to DETB.  I am aware from last night's meeting that there is a fear that this refurbishment work will not go far enough.  I have asked my officials to provide me with photographic evidence of examples of where this work has been carried out before.  I am happy to send those images on to the Senator, and he can share them with his contacts.  I do not want to force a decision that the school is not going to accept.  It has to buy into the project, and we should try to provide evidence of how good this work is.  I am conscious that if we go for new prefabs, they will require planning permission and the project will be delayed even further, possibly until the following summer.  I do not feel that is good enough.  I have been in the school and in that home economics classroom.  I share the concerns of the Senator.  This is, and will remain, a priority for me.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#C00200"><p>As a former teacher, the Minister will be aware that the teachers in the school were very reluctant to move to the point of holding a public meeting.  They have been patient and acted in good faith.  They waited and waited before drawing public attention to the issues at the school.  However, they ran out of patience and have lost much of their trust in the process.  It is critical that the timeframe set out by the Minister is met.  There was a lot of resistance to the idea of further refurbishment of the prefabs.  Teachers had anticipated that there would be a replacement of the prefabs.  If Department officials are insisting on that path, perhaps they would liaise with the teachers on the action committee to address the safety concerns they have about the prefabs in order to make matters as workable as possible while they await the new school building.  The latter should be as practical as possible in order that the gaps identified by the teachers last night might be addressed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1290" speakername="Joe McHugh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#D00100"><p>That is absolutely no problem.  I agree with everything the Senator said.   It is important to reassure members of the public in Inishowen, in particular in Moville, and the student body, that we will work together on this.  I put in timeframes that I want to see met.  I do not want to delve too much into the termination of the contract of the architect because it is not finalised yet but once that happens we will appoint a new architect.  In the meantime the design team is still in place.  It will continue its work and we will have a submission ready for planning.  I am happy to keep the Senator posted at every stage.</p> <p>I acknowledge the input of Mr. Paddy Kelly from the education and training board, ETB, whose expertise will be critical in ensuring we move forward on this.  I also acknowledge the input of the local county councillors who have been working very hard on this issue, and I will keep them in the loop as well.</p> <p>I acknowledge the frustration of the teachers in the staff room.  I met them and we considered potential options.  We discussed potentially replacing the prefabs and considered what would be the best option.  The advice I got back is that in order to do an effective job in a tighter timeframe, what is required is not simply replacing a roof, rather the electrics will need to be done and a full refurbishment to ensure there are a proper safety standards in place in these prefabs for the students and the teachers.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.15" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#D00300">Special Educational Needs Service Provision</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#D00400"><p>I welcome the Minister to the Chamber.  I put down this Commencement matter asking the Minister to provide an update on the process as to how it can forward plan the provision of sufficient places for students with special needs.  I have raised this issue with him on several occasions.  We need to ensure we have enough special needs places for students with special needs.</p> <p>Currently the pathway to such access is slightly unclear so the Minister might clarify that.  Students go into an early intervention setting, which is provided by the HSE.  They might spend two or three years in that setting and then go into a school setting.  They would seek a special needs place in a school.  I have been informed by parents that the process involves them applying to multiple schools for such a place for their child.  That does not make sense in a rural setting, or even in an urban one.  Parents have to apply to four, five or six schools.  There may be six such places per school and they have to wait until August to find out the school to which their child has got access.</p> <p>There must be a way of forward planning such provision.  Given that the HSE is involved at the early intervention stage, which is two or three years prior to a child going into the school setting, a forward planning network could be put in place to provide a place for the child in their nearest school.  Currently, children are being driven in taxis to and from schools that are a distance of 20 or 30 miles from their homes.  That does not make sense.  I hope a plan can be put in place to ensure parents can get access to the special education services their child needs.</p> <p>Parents seek clarity.  They want to ensure they can get a special needs place for their child and to ensure that when their child is assessed at the age of one or two that in three years' time they will have a special needs place in a school.  Such a link does not appear to be in place.  The Minister might clarify that.  It might be in place and simply needs to be worked on.  Such a link would provide an understanding of the system and would work to ensure parents have a school place for their child.  A school place, in particular in their local school, is one of main the issues they want addressed.  Many schools in my area have six special needs places attached to them, although some schools do not.  If there is such a need in a locality, that needs to be provided for at least two years in advance of a child entering the school setting.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1290" speakername="Joe McHugh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#D00500"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this issue on which we are intensively working.  We have a budget of more than &euro;1.9 billion for special needs and a Department budget of &euro;11 billion, which represents quite a substantial injection of money.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Joe McHugh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2018"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2018&amp;amp;pid=JoeMcHugh&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=21"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We have 1,500 SNAs.  We got an additional 950 this year.  Special classes have increased from fewer than 500 to approximately 1,500 since 2011.  There has been enormous progress.  However, I agree with what Senator Lombard said.  The piece of work we are doing at the moment is how we can do better at pre-planning and forward planning and how we can improve communication channels with parents.  It is not right that parents have to go around to schools or be given a list.  That is something I have brought up with the National Council for Special Education, NCSE, when I had a meeting with it last week.  I will continue to meet with it on that.  Timing is another issue in terms of when enrolment for special needs purposes happens.  I am happy to keep the Senator up to date in that regard.</p><p>The NCSE has a statutory function to plan and co-ordinate the provision of education and support services to children with special educational needs and consultation with the relevant education partners and the Health Service Executive.  This includes the establishment of special classes and special school placements in various geographical areas where there is an identified need.  In deciding where to establish a special class in an area, the NCSE takes account of the current and projected demand and available school accommodation both current and planned.  The council ensures that schools in an area can between them cater for all children who have been identified as needing special class placements.  As I outlined, they have increased from 548 in 2011 to 1,459 this year.  Provision in special schools has increased from 6,848 placements in 2011 to 7,872 this year.  When the NCSE sanctions a special class in a school, the school can apply to the Department for capital funding to reconfigure existing spaces or to construct additional accommodation.  Similarly, special schools can apply to the Department for capital funding to accommodate additional placements.</p><p>Notwithstanding the extent of the investment, issues remain.  In some parts of the country increases in population and other issues have led to shortages in capacity in the school system.  I assure Senator Lombard that this issue is being taken very seriously.  The NCSE formally advised the Minister for Education and Skills that there is insufficient special school and special class capacity in Dublin 15 and in Kildare.  The formal notification was sent to me in recent weeks.  The letter is a formal activation of a process under the admissions legislation under which ultimately a ministerial direction can be made requiring a school to make additional special education provision available.  The NCSE and the Department are actively engaging with education service providers in order to encourage them to address the shortage of places.  I am encouraged that, to date, those efforts have resolved the issue in Kildare and resulted in progress in Dublin 15.</p><p>Engagement with schools, patron bodies, parents and others is continuing in Dublin 15 to bring the required additional special class and special school placements on-stream.  The NCSE will keep in regular contact with the parents of the children concerned to advise them of progress and to identify placements as they become available.  The NCSE and officials from the Department of Education and Skills hosted a briefing session for Oireachtas Members in Leinster House on Tuesday last to advise Members on the approach being taken.</p><p>I again thank Senator Lombard because we have embarked on a very ambitious journey for special education inclusion and ensuring that special education is at the heart of the education system, but like any journey it is an ongoing and evolving one and I am happy to work with him along the way.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#E00200"><p>I thank the Minister for his comprehensive reply regarding the issue.  It is about trying to find a pathway so that when parents have a diagnosis they can access early intervention and are ensured of a place in two years' time.  That is probably the body of work that is required.  The HSE has the information and I am concerned that it would provide the information to the Department of Education and Skills in order that we can provide what is required, namely, access to a local school.  We have a school bus system and many other systems.  As the Minister correctly said, the education model is built on inclusivity and ensuring children can access education in the community and parish.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1290" speakername="Joe McHugh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#E00300"><p>We have been working on a school inclusion pilot project for Kildare and Wicklow and parts of south Dublin that will involve 75 schools and preschools.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Joe McHugh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2018"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2018&amp;amp;pid=JoeMcHugh&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=21"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->That understanding of need at an early stage is critical.  Regardless of whatever resources are needed in the aftermath, it has to be done in a comprehensive way whether it involves speech and language therapy, occupational therapy, complex medical need, behavioural support or whatever.</p><p>This pilot will start in September.  It has a budget &euro;4.75 million.  We will look at the pilot as a potential forerunner of a national roll-out.  We are looking at integration involving the Departments of Children and Youth Affairs, Health and Education and Skills in order to identify how we can more effectively work on the issue of inclusion raised by the Senator.  I acknowledge the officials in the respective Departments.  I know that officials can get a lot of negative attention when things go wrong but in politics, it is important to acknowledge creativity.  There is a creative approach to this school inclusion model that I believe will be very positive in the years ahead.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.22" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#F00150">School Accommodation</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#F00200"><p>I welcome the Minister and thank him for taking the time to answer this very important question on Ardgillan community college.  The latter is located in the town of Balbriggan in north County Dublin.  It not only serves Balbriggan but also surrounding villages such as Balrothery and the Naul.  Along with the rest of Fingal, Balbriggan is in the fastest-growing part of the country and has the youngest population in the State.  As a result, school provision is very important in Balbriggan.</p> <p>The school in question is under the patronage of the Dublin and D&uacute;n Laoghaire Education and Training Board.  Phase 1  of the school opened in 2009 and phase 2 was opened in 2015, with the school population increasing to 1,000 as a result.  It is an excellent school that has excelled academically and in sports, music and the arts.  The school has very high standards and, because it is very popular, there are long waiting lists for entry every year.</p> <p>Last October, significant structural defects in phase 1, which is the 18-classroom first section of the school, were discovered.  This discovery prompted urgent structural assessment of 30 schools built by Western Building Systems that included schools in Greystones, Tyrrelstown and Mulligar.  The students in the phase 1 building in Ardgillan community college are now being housed in the nearby Castlelands community centre but this is far from ideal.  It leads to the school lacking structure and being disjointed.  I do not think anybody is happy with the current situation.  They accepted it was a temporary situation.</p> <p>The school has requested the provision of temporary Portakabin accommodation but has received no information from the Department of Education and Skills on the provision of these Portakabins.  Could the Minister tell me whether this request will be granted, whether the Portakabins be on site and when they will be on site?  When will phase 1 be reopened?  This is very important.  Now that we are coming into the summer months, it is vital that as much work as possible be done in Ardgillan community college in order to bring it up to scratch for September.  The situation is very difficult for all the students concerned, their parents and the teaching staff despite the best efforts of the school principal, Michael O'Leary, and all the staff.  People in Balbriggan, Balrothery and the Naul are very concerned about the school.  I have been out canvassing with Niall Keady in Balbriggan and this issue comes up very regularly on the doorsteps.  It is a very real topic now that we are coming into the local elections.  People are asking Mr. Keady and me about what is happening, which is why I have raised it here today.  What is happening?  Many parents with children in St. Molaga's national school, who have been studying in really bad 19-year-old prefabs, are very dismayed at the thought that their children will now go into Ardgillan community college despite it being an excellent school because they must contend with temporary and insecure accommodation for their secondary education so it is a really important issue and we need answers and, more importantly, action.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.24" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#F00300">Visit of UK Delegation</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#F00400"><p>Before I call on the Minister to speak, I am sure Members will wish to join with me in welcoming the Right Honourable Sir Alan Duncan, MP, Minister of State for Europe and the Americas at the Foreign and Commonwealth Office.  On my behalf and on behalf of all my colleagues in Seanad &Eacute;ireann, I extend a very warm welcome to him and good wishes for a very successful visit to Ireland.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">An Cathaoirleach:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1988"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1988&amp;amp;pid=DenisODonovan&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=21"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Unfortunately, the Chamber is rather quiet on this occasion.  On Friday, there are local and European elections and a referendum and many Members who would normally be here are knocking at doors, etc.  Leaving that aside, he is most welcome.  I hope he enjoys his visit.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.27" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#G00150">Nithe i dtosach suíonna - Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.28" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#G00175">School Accommodation</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1290" speakername="Joe McHugh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#G00200"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this matter as it gives me the opportunity to provide an update to the House on the current position regarding the external precautionary measures remediation works of Ardgillan community college, part of which is closed since last October, following the identification of significant structural issues.</p> <p>No doubt the House will be aware that, in October and November last, my Department carried out initial assessments of 42 schools that were built by a contractor using the design and build programme of delivery and which includes part of Ardgillan community college.  The House will also be aware that of those schools, 22 required precautionary measures to enable continued safe occupation.</p> <p>Ardgillan community college is different from the schools with precautionary measures in place in that the nature and extent of the issues there are such that the building assessed was required to close.  The school remains operational in another building on site.  The safety of pupils and staff has been and remains our first priority.</p> <p>Following on from the initial assessments, which were based on sample opening-up works, my Department initiated a second phase of detailed investigations for the schools on 18 January last.  This next phase of the programme focused initially on the 22 schools that have precautionary measures in place and at Ardgillan.</p> <p>The purpose of these investigations was to determine the nature and scope of any permanent remediation measures required in each individual school and, from the technical information gathered by the appointed structural engineers, to design permanent remediation solutions where these are needed.</p> <p>In line with the update published in January, detailed structural investigations have now been completed in all the 22 schools with precautionary measures in place and at Ardgillan community college.</p> <p>In tandem with the investigations, significant work has been undertaken by my Department, supported by the National Development Finance Agency and an appointed multi-disciplinary team, to design and plan permanent engineered remediation solutions for each of these schools.  An individual work plan for each school will flow from this body of work.  These plans will feed into an overall time-tabled programme of remediation works for the schools which will commence during the summer months.  All efforts remain on track to achieve this objective.</p> <p>When the works programme is available, the details will be first shared at meetings with the patrons and the schools involved.  Arrangements are being put in place for such meetings with the patrons and the school authorities of the 22 schools, including Ardgillan, to be scheduled in June.</p> <p>In parallel with this work during the summer months, detailed structural investigations in 17 schools built by the same contractor without precautionary measures in place will also proceed.  A schedule for those detailed investigations issued to the 17 schools involved and their patrons last week.  The intention is that any remediation works that may be necessary in these schools will be carried out from 2020 onwards.</p> <p>I again acknowledge and thank the principals, staff, parents and pupils for their patience and co-operation as my Department works its way through this complex process.</p> <p>Specifically, regarding Ardgillan community college, I thank its leadership - Mr. Michael O'Leary, who has shown excellent leadership throughout this process, and his team - and also the students.  The scheduled detailed investigation phase has been undertaken and a programme of works to remediate the building is being put in place for implementation.  This is an education and training board school.  Pending the delivery of the remediation work, my Department will ensure, in continued consultation with the ETB, that any interim accommodation needs at the school are met.  In this regard, two additional temporary classrooms, a woodwork room and preparation area together with a disabled access toilet have been approved for September 2019.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#G00300"><p>I thank the Minister for his reply.</p> <p>I welcome the provision of the additional temporary classrooms.  I appreciate the update in that regard and the update in relation to the remediation works that are due to commence in the summer.  I wonder if the Minister could tell me if that time-tabled work shows the completion of these work by September.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1290" speakername="Joe McHugh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#G00400"><p>I would be hoping that we are in a position to have the vast majority of those 22 schools completed by September.  Given the significant impact on Ardgillan community college - it was the only school where they had to decamp on a permanent basis - I certainly will ensure that it will be prioritised and ready for September, if possible.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Joe McHugh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2018"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2018&amp;amp;pid=JoeMcHugh&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=21"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Some works in the 22 schools may continue into October but everybody will be back in school.  Nobody will be decanted.  I hope that we will have a solution ready for September for Ardgillan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#H00200"><p>I appreciate that the Minister is keeping Balbriggan and Ardgillan community college at the top of his priority list.  I will correspond with the Minister about it as the summer progresses.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.34" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 3.05 p.m. and resumed at 3.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.35" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#N00100">An tOrd Gnó - Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#N00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, motion re Sectoral Employment Order (Electrical Contracting Sector) 2019, to be taken without debate at the conclusion of the Order of Business; No. 2, Judicial Appointments Commission Bill 2017 - Committee Stage (resumed), to be taken at 4.45 p.m. and adjourned at 7 p.m., if not previously concluded; No. 3, Residential Tenancies (Amendment) (No. 2) Bill 2018 &ndash; Report and Final Stages to be taken at 7 p.m.; and No. 3<i>a</i>, motion re earlier signature of the Residential Tenancies (Amendment) (No. 2) Bill 2018, to be taken without debate on the conclusion of No. 3.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#N00300"><p>I extend my party's sympathies to the family and friends of the legendary Dublin footballer, Anton O'Toole.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Catherine Ardagh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2473"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2473&amp;amp;pid=CatherineArdagh&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=21"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->He was also known as the &quot;Blue Panther&quot; and he passed away aged 68.  I send my sympathies and those of the Fianna F&aacute;il group to his family and friends.  He won four all-Ireland senior football medals and transformed Gaelic football for the capital.  Ar dheis D&eacute; go raibh a h-anam d&iacute;lis.<br/><br/>In the context of the comments of the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government, Deputy Eoghan Murphy, on co-living accommodation, it is extraordinary that he thinks co-living in small spaces should be celebrated by young people.  We only have to look on <i>daft.ie</i>to see the tiny squats, apartments or bedsits that are now available at astronomical prices.  I do not know what planet the Minister lives on to think this should be celebrated.  It is a retrograde step and will give rise to the creation of the slums of the future.  The Minister has announced many policies.  If he implemented even one, I would say it would be fantastic.  The cost-rental model in Inchicore seems to have been abandoned or delayed so I would welcome any comments on where that stands.  We have not seen a master plan but if he stuck to one project at a time and finished it, he could be commended.  He has announced these co-living squats and it is not right.  This is an insult to people.<br/><br/>I will also mention the early childcare scheme.  I stated last week that there is a crisis because there are no places for babies and baby rooms in cr&egrave;ches have been abandoned because of the success of the early childcare scheme.  At the weekend, we saw how this has become a national crisis.  We also learned of a &euro;50 million deficit relating to the early childcare scheme.  I ask the Leader to schedule a debate on the subject as many young mothers simply cannot return to work because there are no spaces in cr&egrave;ches for their babies.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#O00200"><p>I will focus on one issue.  I commend the Taoiseach and those involved with the national Famine commemoration in Sligo yesterday.  It was a fitting and meaningful event.  The Taoiseach stated, "The best way we can honour those who suffered and died during the Great Famine is by showing empathy with those who are suffering today."  He said this in the context of the 1 million Irish people who were ultimately made refugees, having been forced from their homeland because of famine.  I could not get to Sligo, although I was invited and had intended to go.  Reading his words, I was reminded of the great issues by which we are challenged today and what we are doing about them.  I will bounce around a few ideas in that regard.</p> <p>In the context of the Taoiseach's words and in our knowledge of the great many people who left for Ellis Island and all the other places, forced from their homeland in need and who sought shelter, we, as legislators, must consider what we are doing.  Many of the people to whom I refer were rejected, cursed, damned and given no opportunities.  Others got such opportunities in the great places of America, Canada, New Zealand, Australia and elsewhere.  The challenge for us must be to follow through on what the Taoiseach said.  What are we doing about direct provision and the segregation of families?  How are we enabling, supporting and establishing new homes and safe communities?  How are we addressing migrant integration, particularly in the context of migrant children?  What are we doing to provide job opportunities, education and social care?  What are we doing to respect language, faith and difference?  What are we doing to address hate crimes and racism?  Why do we not celebrate more the arts, rich music, tradition and culinary aspects that come with the diverse cultures of our people?  We are talking about a real republic with a capital "R".  As legislators, we in these Houses must challenge ourselves and ask what we are doing and how we can empower migrant civil society to ensure that it can participate in the democratic process and governance.  I say that mindful of the elections coming up in the next few days or those that will take place in the future.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Victor Boyhan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2463"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2463&amp;amp;pid=VictorBoyhan&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=21"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I will finish on this point.  I think we need to tap in and create a new coalition of willing people who want to address this issue.  We need a debate in the House on the importance of migration flows.<br/><br/>The Leader is a member of the Organization for Security and Co-operation in Europe - Parliamentary Assembly, OSCE-PA, as I am, and we were furnished with a book at our last conference in Vienna entitled <i>Local Authorities Migrant Integration Guide. </i>I circulated it to every local authority.  We need to visit this and see how we as representatives of local, national and European governments can address the issue of extending a real warm welcome to migrants.  We must remember our past and our experience as migrant people.  I would like the Taoiseach to acknowledge that he has tapped into something really strong and powerful.  Let us take it to the next stage and debate those issues in this House and have meaningful engagement to discuss and address them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#P00200"><p>I commend the O'Neill pipe band from Clontibret, County Monaghan, who made history by performing here earlier today at the invitation of Deputy &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in, Chairman of the Oireachtas committee on justice and equality.  It was a fantastic event and I commend Ms Lorna Sherry, the pipe major, and Peadar Morgan, the founder of the pipe band.  Their performance of the Flying Pickets song Only You was absolutely tremendous.  The message around Irish Sign Language is that it is a language for everybody and that people are not disabled just because they are deaf.  They are a community of people with an unique language and that language is for everybody.  I commend them.</p> <p>Last week, I spoke about pyrite.  Many representatives from counties Mayo, Donegal and other areas welcomed the recent announcement on the pyrite remediation scheme.  Concern has been expressed, however, about the cost of the proposed testing, as detailed in the protocol.  The issue of the defective building materials has been live for many years and I would expect the Government has at least laid the groundwork for the scheme to begin immediately.  I have some questions.  In the absence of the Minister responsible, may I ask the Leader to pass on the following questions?  Will every house have to carry out the testing?  Who will pay for the testing and for the engineer's report?  The cost of the test, depending on the number of cores, may be more than &euro;8,000.  Based on the number of attendees that were at a recent course, are there enough engineers available to carry out the surveys that are required?  If one house in an estate that was supplied with the same building materials is deemed to have pyrite, will all of the houses have to be surveyed and tested in detail or would it be enough to know from the characteristics of the other houses that they also are affected by pyrite?  Are there sufficient laboratories available to carry out the required suite of testing that is needed?  Is there any official register of the complaints to date from counties Mayo and Donegal and who will establish such a register?  When will the procedure be available for the applicants and who will certify the payment of that?  What role will local authorities have and what input will they have into the schemes?  Will contractors be approved for such remedial works that may be required?  Will priority be given to the most seriously affected houses?  We need an urgent debate on the issue of pyrite because people are really fearful for their houses.  We welcome the announcement of the funding but we need to know that the can will not be kicked down the road again.  People are desperate for answers to these questions.  I ask the Leader to put these questions to the Minister and relay the response to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1404" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#P00300"><p>I acknowledge the recent publication which seems to conflate drug decriminalisation and the legalisation of cannabis, which are two very different debates.  The working group on drug decriminalisation has now given the Minister its report and this must be made public.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Lynn Ruane:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2481"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2481&amp;amp;pid=LynnRuane&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=21"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->There are various media articles that have taken pieces of that report and reported on them in an ambiguous way.  I have seen the report.  It has laid out three options, two of which are for variations of adult caution.  One of these is a watered down version of decriminalisation and I believe civil society groups and I could work with the Minister of State, Deputy Catherine Byrne, on this.  It is not fair that the media appears to get snippets of the report prior to it being laid before the Houses of the Oireachtas when we can engage in a meaningful way.  I read today that the chairman of the working group, retired judge Mr. Justice Garrett Sheehan, is seeking to bring forward a minority report that comes out against the three options in the report which are not even around drug decriminalisation.  I stand to be corrected but I believe that Mr. Justice Sheehan is looking for harsher penalties for a person who is caught in possession of drugs in his or her pocket for personal use.  I am appalled to think that a judge who has been in the system this long, and who has seen vulnerable people who came in front his court ending up in prison with worse drug addictions than they had before they entered the courtroom, would even suggest harsher penalties for people in addiction.  I would like the Leader to ask the Minister of State, Deputy Catherine Byrne, to come to the House to have a debate on the report and to get the report published so that Members can have a real conversation about it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#Q00200"><p>Last week the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government, Deputy Eoghan Murphy, explained that the Government had conflicting priorities around the business of this House.  To facilitate the Minister, I propose an amendment to the Order of Business that Report Stage of the Residential Tenancies (Amendment) (No. 2) Bill 2018 be taken immediately after the Order of Business, and that once the business is concluded on the Bill the House would adjourn until tomorrow.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#Q00300"><p>I ask the Leader to invite the Minister for Health, Deputy Harris, or the Minister of State, Deputy Finian McGrath, to the House to clarify for the more than 3,000 service users of Rehab in the State who are very concerned their service will be cut or affected in some way if Rehab is to pull out of providing essential services to people who have a disability.  From my area of County Mayo I am aware of the quality and calibre of service that Rehab staff offer.  It makes a real difference in the lives of people who have a disability and their families whose lives in many ways would be absolutely transformed for the worse if there is a reduction or change in the service provided.  There is a lot of fear out there on this issue.  I am aware that the Minister of State and the Minister for Health in particular - because he has spoken on it - are intent on trying to find a resolution with Rehab, but people and the service users need to know where they stand.  I truly hope that this resolution can be forthcoming very soon to put everybody's mind at ease and so the staff in Rehab can continue to provide the top-class service they do.  I ask that the Minister and the Minister of State are invited to the House to provide that clarification.  Other than that, as we all know, the State will be left carrying the can and trying to provide the service, which would be no small feat given the number of service users.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#Q00400"><p>I was very disappointed to hear over the weekend that a 12 year old girl from Carlow was not allowed to compete in the National Stadium for her second Irish boxing title, having already won at local provincial and national level.  She had trained hard and worked long hours with her coaches in Tullow.  This great fighter was refused entry to the competition by the Irish Amateur Boxing Association when it cited a rule that boxers cannot compete as a boxer while being a member of any other contact sport.  This sportswoman had previously won a silver medal at the Muay Thai World Youth Championships in Thailand.  There has been outrage locally and nationally at this refusal.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jennifer Murnane O'Connor:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2470"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2470&amp;amp;pid=JenniferMurnaneOConnor&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=21"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I have been onto the office of the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport about this.  At a time when we promote mental and physical health, this is unacceptable.  I know the Leader will bring this to the Minister for me.  </p><p>I agree with the previous speaker on Rehab and its services.  I have just left a meeting with Rehab where we heard about its serious concerns about the 3,000 people with disabilities who use its service.  There are 1,500 staff.  This is a crucial service.  I live near a Rehab service in Carlow town and it is absolutely excellent.  There is a meeting today at 5 p.m. with the Minister for Health and I ask that the families would not be concerned or worried.  They are tormented with worry about whether the service will be closed.  Rehab is telling them if it does not get &euro;2 million by 2020, this service will cease to exist.  That is unacceptable.  I ask the Leader to make sure this does not happen.  </p><p>I wish all the Fianna F&aacute;il councillors all the best in the elections.  It is very important that people come out to vote.  Every one of us has a vote and people should get out and use their votes.  I think there have been some issues about who registered-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#R00200"><p>We will be here tomorrow.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#R00300"><p>-----that is something we need to examine.  I wish everybody the best in the local and European elections.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#R00400"><p>I feel there is thunder in the air.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#R00500"><p>It will be Independents' day on Saturday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#R00600"><p>The weather might be breaking.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1429" speakername="Billy Lawless" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#R00700"><p>I would like to second everything my colleague, Senator Boyhan, has said.  I was honoured to attend the National Famine Commemoration last Sunday in Sligo and I would like to commend the County Sligo Famine commemoration committee on a superb event. I was so deeply moved by the booklet produced for Sunday&rsquo;s event, that I have requested a copy for every Member of the Oireachtas. It is vital that we read it and remember our past.  I would like to read this short recollection of the Famine from a Mrs. McDermott of Templeboy, Sligo:</p><blockquote>A man named Doherty lived with his wife and six children in Grangemore.  During the Famine they were starving.  His wife and six children died from hunger, and he carried them in a sack, and buried them in a hole in Shaw&rsquo;s field.  Some time afterwards, he died by the roadside and when he was found, grass and other green vegetables were found in and around his mouth.<br /><br />People died along the roadside and in the fields.  A man named Healy, who lived in Lugdun, was one morning going to the well for water, when he fell on the roadside and died.  He was buried in a box in his own garden.  Fourteen families, left Cartron and Lugdun for the Emigrant Ship in one day.</blockquote> <p>This is from <i>The Sligo Champion</i>of January 1847: </p><blockquote>Although 35 persons in fever were sent from the Workhouse to the Hospital, they are still lying three in a bed, in the former institution!  Good God!  Think of three fever patients crowded together, upon the one narrow bed!  Fever sheds are being erected as speedily as possible, and when they are completed the poor sufferers will, of course be better treated, and have a greater chance of recovery.</blockquote> <p>Ireland is now a prosperous and global nation but these recollections show us we must never forget this terrible blight on our history.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" speakername="Gabrielle McFadden" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#R00800"><p>On my travels over the weekend, I met a gentleman who has a tumour.  He is attending University Hospital Galway for scheduled treatment.  Every month when he goes for this treatment, there is no bed for him.  He was advised to go in through the accident and emergency department.  He does that and waits for up to 24 hours for a bed and has his treatment.  He was at pains to tell me that the doctors and nurses are exceptional and that once he gets in there, the treatment is excellent.  There is something seriously wrong when someone with scheduled treatment has to sit for 24 hours in the accident and emergency department.</p> <p>I am based in the midlands and we are advised to go east or west to centres of excellence for treatment.  We should not have to go through the accident and emergency department for scheduled treatment.  It is obvious that there are management issues.  The beds are available eventually and the money is there.  The service and exceptional staff are there.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Gabrielle McFadden:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2399"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2399&amp;amp;pid=GabrielleMcFadden&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=21"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I ask the Leader to use his good offices to ask the Minister to come before the House in order that we might discuss this issue in a constructive manner.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#S00200"><p>I echo the comments of Senator Ruane regarding the debate on the decriminalisation of drug use.  Notwithstanding the emotion Senator Lawless has about those who died at the roadside in Ireland 150 years ago - and while I agree with his sentiments - there are people dying at the roadside throughout Ireland and in its capital city every day as a result of drug overdoses.  We seem to have a romantic view of what happened 150 years ago yet we have a victim-blaming attitude to those who die in toilets, parks, stairwells of flat complexes and alleyways as a result of overdoses.  We have the third highest overdose rate in Europe.  The discussion on decriminalisation, which is at a sensitive point, purely aims to help somebody who has an addiction, not through the criminal justice system but through the health system.  It is just as radical as that.</p><p>There was a disgraceful letter in <i>The Irish Times</i>yesterday from 20 or more GPs who feel it falls upon them to derail the humanity of what we are trying to achieve.  To suggest that the move towards decriminalisation is a Trojan horse for anything but keeping people alive is outrageous.  As Senator Ruane indicated, it is beyond time for the debate on this matter to take place.  We are willing to work with the Government on the basis of the report, which may or may not already have been heavily leaked, if what comes out of it provides a basis upon which we can work.  To suggest that the decriminalisation argument is somehow trying to achieve something else is absolutely insulting to all of us who do not believe that people who are sick or who have addictions belong before the courts; they do not.  Someone who is sick, who is in need of medical help and who has an addiction does not belong in a courtroom, a prison or a Garda cell.  They should not be interacting with the criminal justice system.  Such a person needs a counsellor, a nurse, a doctor and a path to recovery.  That is the basis for decriminalisation.  It is not decriminalisation of the substances but of the person.  If this issue was taken seriously, we would have a lot fewer people dying on our streets as a result of what is a real and contemporaneous issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#S00300"><p>Nobody seems to speak for County Carlow in this Chamber.  Carlow came first in the divorce league, as reported in today's newspapers, and there is not a word about it from Senator Murnane O'Connor.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#S00400"><p>I am here now to make up for it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#S00500"><p>I just wanted to note that achievement.</p><p>Somebody has been careless enough to lose my seat on three occasions in the Lower House.  I was struck by an account in today's edition of the <i>Irish Independent</i>regarding a Member of that House who lost her seat while on a swing in a hotel in Harcourt Street recently.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#S00600"><p>That matter is<i>sub judice</i>.  I would tread carefully.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#S00700"><p>I just want to say two things without commenting on the merits of the case.  It would appear that 55 years after Belfast City Council unlocked the swings on Sundays, the proposition is being put in court that there should be supervisors for swings when adults are using them and that it is a matter of civil liability if there are not.  It occurs to me that we live in a strange world when civil liability can exist in such circumstances.  Perhaps we are only hearing a portion of the evidence.  Who knows?  It also occurs that if the Government is serious about driving down the claims culture, we cannot stand idly by when adults with two objects, one in each hand, lose their seat and fall off a swing and then claim that there should have been a supervisor looking after them, especially when it comes from somebody who has so much public influence and clear influence over Government policy in these matters.</p><p>As I understand it, the letter to <i>The Irish Times</i>to which Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in referred merely points out that the case for medicinal cannabis is being confused with the case for decriminalisation of all cannabis by cannabis users.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#T00200"><p>There was a lot of highly flavoured language involved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#T00300"><p>That is a legitimate point to make and I do not believe there is anything disgusting or disgraceful about making it.  This is not a simple issue.  There is a big problem with criminalising the possession of small quantities of cannabis; it is probably a waste of everyone's time prosecuting people for it.  However, decriminalising cannabis will have serious effects because it is a psychotic substance which causes psychosis among young people.  I know this and science has proved it.</p> <p>On a lighter note, marriage equality for homosexual people and the decriminalisation of cannabis came in at the same time in Canada recently.  It was stated in a newspaper there that evangelists were completely shocked by this and that they were worried about the phrase in the bible that "if a man shall lie with another man as if his wife, he shall be stoned".</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.64" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#T00500"><p>The Senator has a sense of humour.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#T00600"><p>How does one follow that?  A number of my colleagues have mentioned drug addiction, while one has mentioned the problems faced in emergency departments.  A couple of weeks ago I had the misfortune of having to spend the best part of 24 hours in an emergency department with a relative who was a frequent visitor to the place owing to chronic health issues.  I cannot begin to recount the girl's distress in sitting in the emergency department, surrounded by people who were either substance abusers, completely drunk or high on drugs.  Surely the emergency department is not the place to treat such persons?  We would change the entire system if a proper place could be provided for those suffering from substance abuse.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#T00700"><p>Whatever happened to the drunk tank?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#T00800"><p>Anyone sitting with the girl I was with, or the others sitting around us who were really sick would have been heartbroken.  At one point the queue had to be restarted because one of the substance abusers had run out of the place and a number of staff had to follow to bring her back in order that she could be fitted back into the queue.  I cannot begin to describe the hurt felt by the people sitting around me.  We really have to tackle the issue of substance abuse.  There is not a family in the country who do not have somebody suffering from substance abuse.  We have to tackle the problem.  They are crowding emergency departments throughout the country.  I have had the misfortune, owing to heart problems, to attend the emergency department at St. Vincent's University Hospital on several occasions and each time the place was full to the rafters.  It is desperate.</p> <p>I ask everyone in the House to join me in condemning those who are cutting down posters belonging to candidates running in local and national elections.  The posters cost a lot of money and anyone who acts in such a way is committing a vicious act.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#T00900"><p>First, I second-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#T01000"><p>I second Senator Humphreys'-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#T01100"><p>The Senator need not bother.  I second Senator Humphreys' proposed amendment to the Order of Business.  </p> <p>I was not going to speak, but since the question of hospitals was raised, I will say that yesterday I was in St. Vincent's University Hospital and looking at the notices.  Last year some 19,000 people failed to turn up for appointments, at a cost to the hospital of &euro;1.5 million.  We hear much squawking from the consumers of health services.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator David Norris:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1758"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1758&amp;amp;pid=DavidNorris&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=21"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->However, I would like to say it is a very fine service but it is not well served by citizens in every hospital in the State routinely failing to turn up for appointments, particularly when, as in the case of St. Vincent's hospital, a text message is sent to remind the person of his or her appointment.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#U00200"><p>The full facts have yet to come out about what happened to the baby who died in Holles Street.  What we can say is that this is something more than a case of a misdiagnosis and all the tragic consequences that followed.  It raises the most serious questions about the medical establishment and the establishment of some doctors within our system.  I spent a lot of time last year and in the past attempting to draw policymakers' attention to the fact that many parents in this tragic situation have felt patronised, sometimes pressurised-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#U00300"><p>The full facts have yet to come out.  This is unbelievable.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#U00400"><p>-----have experienced less than encouragement-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#U00500"><p>This is outrageous.  The Senator is a thundering disgrace.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#U00600"><p>-----and have felt passed over-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#U00700"><p>There is nothing he will not say.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#U00800"><p>Please, Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#U00900"><p>There is no tragedy the Senator will not politicise.  He is a disgusting disgrace.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#U01000"><p>Whether we agree or not, Senator Mullen is entitled to make his point.  I am in the Chair and I will make the ruling.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#U01100"><p>The Senator should hang his head and keep it hung.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#U01200"><p>Allow Senator Mullen to proceed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#U01300"><p>And passed over when it comes to important and, at the very least, relevant information.  We have seen in the case of the CervicalCheck scandal some parallels with tests abroad and lack of information and responsibility towards people at home.  We need to know more and hopefully we will know more and at that point more can be said by calm people-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#U01400"><p>The Senator does not know what he is talking about.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#U01500"><p>-----who want people to be properly and respectfully treated.</p> <p>Less of a life and death issue but nonetheless important is dentistry and people's oral and dental health.  I was very interested by what Dr. John Marley, dean of the faculty of dentistry in the Royal College of Surgeons in Ireland, RCSI, had to be say last week when he came before the Joint Committee on Health.  It probably will not surprise people that during the recession, many households cut down their spending on dental treatments but what would surprise them is that the faculty of dentistry in the RCSI had no input into the development of the national oral health strategy.  Dr. Marley pointed out some interesting matters of which I was unaware and of which other people may also be.  There is no foundation year &ndash; what we would call an internship year in the area of medicine - for dentists.  Dentists go into private practice without having such a foundation year pre-registration.  There is no mandatory continual professional development for dentists in the way there is for medics and other professionals.  As doctors and pharmacists have ongoing training in the latest medical developments, it is striking that no such system operates for dentists.  There is limited access to dental specialties.  There are only about two specialties and consultancies, orthodontics and oral surgery, in which people can work in Ireland while there are about 11 other specialties in the UK and internationally.  That is something we should discuss in this Chamber.  I was extremely surprised by all of those things Dr. Marley had to say.  We should discuss them with the Minister for Health, together perhaps with other issues in due course.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#U01600"><p>I want to say something positive.  It is about St. Vincent&rsquo;s hospital, where I have spent the last two days for family reasons, not my own but other family members.  I cannot begin to stress how wonderful the staff were.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#U01700"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#U01800"><p>It is packed - it is a city of the frail, the feeble and the very unwell - and accident and emergency departments are like that.  A man called Stephen Wilson, who is an advanced paramedic within the ambulance service, was outstanding.  Another man called Thomas Chirayath from Kerala, a healthcare assistant, was also outstanding, as was a man called David Kelly, who was given an award for heroism for his ability as an advanced ambulance paramedic who tried to save a child&rsquo;s life .  The child unfortunately died but the mother of that child recommended him for this award, which he received from the people of Dublin.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Marie-Louise O'Donnell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2390"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2390&amp;amp;pid=MarieLouiseODonnell&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=21"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It was not so much even that - particularly as I did not know any of it until later - it was just the care and attention in a city with a lot of people of all ages who are very unwell.  I just cannot say enough about it, and also about the health care assistants.  I keep talking about this because health care assistants do everything in between the doctors and the consultants.  They are outstanding.  They come from all over the world to work here.  They are happy to do so, to have lives here and tend to us, and we still will not give them a critical skills facility, or a proper trajectory and proper conditions in respect of their jobs in order that they can remain.  We need to look at that.  It is only when one is in that situation that one is so grateful for the care of others at consultant level but also at the level of the everyday in a city of the feeble and of people who are very unwell.  I thank those at St. Vincent's University Hospital.  We should remember the good things that happen every day in this country and the good health people enjoy.  We should also remember the Sisters of Charity who built the hospital.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#V00200"><p>I thank the Senator and call the Leader.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#V00300"><p>Go raibh maith agat.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#V00400"><p>A Chathaoirligh-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#V00500"><p>Senator Devine did not indicate but I will allow her to speak as she has been sitting there a long time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#V00600"><p>Do not.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#V00700"><p>I asked my very wise clerk if Senator Devine had indicated because I did not see her, but I will allow her in.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#V00800"><p>It was my fault.  That is grand.  I thank the Cathaoirleach very much.  I will not be long.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#V00900"><p>Senator Devine was sitting there patiently.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#V01000"><p>Senator Devine has 90 seconds.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#V01100"><p>Do I?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#V01200"><p>I am only joking.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#V01300"><p>That is great.  The HSE produced its service plan for 2019.  It is working towards a seven-day service for the child and adolescent mental health service, CAMHS, to ensure support for vulnerable young persons in line with the policy of Connecting for Life.  A couple of weeks ago, I received a response which indicated in black and white that there is no plan to implement the 7-7 service.  The period from Thursday evening to early Monday morning is when the demand for psychological and psychiatric services is at its greatest.  That is the reason we were hopeful that we would have not just a 7-7 service but a 24-7 service.</p> <p>I raised this issue on the Commencement last week and I received a response from the Minister of State, Deputy Finian McGrath, rather than the Minister of State, Deputy Jim Daly.  I was unimpressed by his response in which he did not once mention a 7-7 service.  It was a long spiel about the history of the HSE going back forever and about the current services but not the services that were promised for 2019.  He said he would bring my concerns to the Minister.  I look forward to some response because a 7-7 service is the minimum we must try to provide for children under the 2019 service plan.  There was also a letter from community healthcare organisation, CHO, 9 stating that it cannot put anybody on the mental health waiting list who is referred.  It also outlined its regret in having to inform people that, due to the high referral numbers, the primary care mental health service has ceased for the foreseeable future.  I would welcome some clarity from the Minister on the 7-7 service and mental health services in CHO 9.  I thank the Cathaoirleach and I also thank the Leader for his generosity.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#V01400"><p>There is some kindness in me.  I call on the Leader to respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#V01500"><p>I thank the 15 Members of the House who contributed to the Order of Business.</p> <p>Like Senator Ardagh, I begin by paying tribute to and remembering the late, great Anton O'Toole.  Those of us who grew up as part a generation that watched the Dubs display their prowess in the 1970s will remember him as a fantastic and skilful footballer.  We extend our sympathy to his family.  Ar dheis D&eacute; go raibh a anam dil&iacute;s.</p> <p>Senator Ardagh raised the comments of the Minister, Deputy Eoghan Murphy.  What he articulated is that co-living is one housing option.  It is about offering choice.  Co-living works in other cities and, to be fair, we cannot all judge on one concept, whether it is single housing or planning or apartment living.  We are concerned about increasing supply.  That is the reason the Government is committed to Rebuilding Ireland.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=21"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I would be happy for the Minister to come to the House for a debate on housing again.  <br/><br/>Senator Ardagh raised the issue of the early childcare scheme regarding places for babies.  The Government is committed to enabling people to have access to high-quality, affordable childcare.  It is a very important issue.  Under the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs, we have seen an increase in the budget over the past two budgets.  The Government is committed to ensuring that children in the nought to three age group referred to by Senator Ardagh are accommodated.  We have seen an increase in the number of young children accessing services from 13,000 in 2014 to 31,000 today.  I would be happy for the Minister to come back to us in June for a debate on the matter.  <br/><br/>Senators Boyhan and Lawless raised the issue of the Famine commemoration in Sligo last weekend.  In his very fine contribution, Senator Boyhan spoke about celebrating diversity and the need to have empathy, as the Taoiseach said, for those suffering today.  I would be very happy to have that debate in the context of migration and where we see ourselves as a culture and society within the EU project.  The remarks of Senators Boyhan and Lawless are ones about which we need a wider discussion, particularly on the issue of migration, where some people peddle a line that migration is bad for our country.  As we all know quite well, there are many fine immigrants in our country today making a very valuable contribution to our society and communities.  Freedom of movement of people is one that we all cherish.  As the Senator for the diaspora, Senator Lawless can testify to the fact that as a race of people, we have been welcomed across the world, particularly in North America.  That debate is one we should have and I commend Senators Boyhan and Lawless on their contributions.  <br/><br/>Senator Conway-Walsh raised the issue of pyrite.  As Members will be aware, the Government announced &euro;20 million in the budget for a pyrite and mica remediation scheme for affected houses in counties Donegal and Mayo.  It has committed to resolving the problem and the final aspects of the scheme are being worked out and will be published soon.  Many emergency and technical works have been undertaken to date.  The issue of standardisation of testing and other types of works will be fed into the scheme.  I would be happy for the Minister to come back to the House with regard to the matter raised by the Senator.  I join with her in commending the O'Neill Pipe Band on being here today.  I also commend the work of the Oireachtas Committee on Justice and Equality on Irish Sign Language.  Senator Conway-Walsh is not here but I was going to say to her that if she was talking about The Flying Pickets' song, I was hoping she might extend all her love to us on this side of the House.  <br/><br/>Senators Ruane, &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in and McDowell raised the very important issue of the decriminalisation of drugs.  It is a very emotional issue where we need to see a different type of approach.  I concur with some of the comments made by Senators Ruane and &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in, as I think we need to look at how we can do things differently while recognising that the letter to <i>The Irish Times</i>addressed a different issue.  I have to say that Senator McDowell's contribution regarding psychosis and cannabis is one we cannot just dismiss.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.106" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#W00300"><p>Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in should not make it all about him.  Sometimes it is not all about him.  Before Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in jumps in, I was going to say that as Minister of State, he did a significant amount of work of which I was supportive but there are issues around cannabis that we cannot ignore.  The views of a body of opinion were published yesterday and there were letters to the newspapers, which need to be part of a wider debate that I am happy to have.  In fairness to the Minister of State, Deputy Catherine Byrne, the report has not yet gone to Cabinet.  I am told that there is a need for cross-departmental review of and contribution to the report.  It is a complex issue but we need an informed debate on the matter and I look forward to the Upper House having that debate in due course.  I will not shy away from it.  Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in is right.  The pathway to recovery is one we need to examine.  As somebody who has been involved with a number of organisations in Cork, I know that it is one we need to examine further.</p> <p>Senator Humphreys proposed an amendment to the Order of Business that I cannot accept.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=21"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Senator Mulherin raised the issue of clarification regarding Rehab, as did Senator Murnane O'Connor.  It is important that we provide certainty and continuity to the users of Rehab.  That is why there have been talks going on between the Minister and the service provider, Rehab, today and prior to today.  I hope that a resolution can be found to the talks because it is an important service.  I will leave it at that.</p><p>With Senator Murnane O'Connor's permission, I will rejig the Senator's comment to wish all candidates in the local elections every success on Friday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#X00200"><p>They cannot all be successful.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#X00300"><p>To participate in democracy as a citizen is one thing but to be a candidate is another.  To all the men and women who are standing for election, irrespective of their hue, party or if they are Independent, I say, "Go n-&eacute;ir&iacute; libh".  I hope they all do well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#X00400"><p>Outside of Carlow?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#X00500"><p>Does the Senator want me to raise the Carlow candidates who I support?</p> <p>Senator Murnane O'Connor had better mark the calendar.  I completely agree with the Senator's remarks on that young boxer who should be allowed to participate in a variety of boxing events.  I thought we got rid of the ban in sport in our country.  The decision by the IABA is wrong.  There are two types of boxing and I do not see why one cannot participate in both codes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#X00600"><p>That is great.  I thank the Leader.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#X00700"><p>I feel the love.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#X00800"><p>A sudden swing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#X00900"><p>Senator McFadden raised the issue of University Hospital Galway.  That is a matter that deserves to be treated with the utmost respect and seriousness.  In fairness, Senator McFadden might get a better reply through a Commencement matter.  I addressed Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in's issue.</p> <p>In response to Senator McDowell, the issue of the swing is before the courts and I will not mention that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#X01000"><p>It is the swing vote I am worried about.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#X01100"><p>The swing vote did not benefit Senator McDowell on a couple of occasions.  It did on other occasions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#X01200"><p>Roll on independence day.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#X01300"><p>Senator McDowell was out casting the swing vote lately.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#X01400"><p>It might be wise for the Leader to swing away from that issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#X01500"><p>Swings and roundabouts.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#X01600"><p>I hear that Senator McDowell swings either way in terms of one-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.124" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#X01800"><p>But he is not stoned.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#X01900"><p>Not stoned.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#X02000"><p>Many hope Senator McDowell's prevarication ends soon.  The Senator is swinging one way or the other, depending on who he meets.  I really hope that he can.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#X02100"><p>Down with that sort of thing now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#X02200"><p>The issue of civil liability is one that, in the wider insurance debate, needs to be addressed.  We will have the Judicial Council Bill 2017 coming back before us and the Minister of State at the Department of Finance, Deputy D'Arcy, is working on reducing the cost of insurance.  I note Cork City Council has set aside &euro;20 million for insurance claims.  That is a huge chunk of money out of the budget of the city council.  It poses the question as to why we must have that kind of money.  Let us have that debate at a future time.</p> <p>Senator Craughwell raised the issue of the accident and emergency department and the distressed girl.  I have made the point repeatedly that the system of access to emergency departments should be changed.  We need more investment in primary care which we are providing.  Senator Norris, off-camera, made reference to the issue of drunk tanks.  We need a specific area of emergency departments for those with alcohol and drug issues who come into accident and emergency departments, clog them up and hold patients up.  Senator Norris is correct.  There are people who come into hospitals who need to be seen as outpatients but there are people who misuse the hospital system by failing to turn up, failing to notify and cancelling on a number of occasions and that adds to a backlog.  I would be happy to have that debate on the health system following the local and European elections.</p> <p>Senator Mullen raised the sensitive and tragic issue in the National Maternity Hospital.  The best contribution I can make is that we do not know all the facts.  There is a review under way in the hospital.  Let us await that conclusive report and then have a debate.  Let us treat the matter with sensitivity and not use anybody, anything or any place as a political football.  We all have concerns.  We all have issues.  Let us wait until we get the full facts when we can have the debate on the matter.</p> <p>Senators Marie-Louise O'Donnell and Norris commended those involved in the healthcare system, particularly in St. Vincent's.  The Senators are correct.  There is a significant amount of work being done.  We can have a real debate on the positivity around the healthcare system and about the need to keep the patient at the heart and centre of it.  The remarks of both Senators are ones that should be promulgated.</p> <p>Finally, Senator Devine-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#X02300"><p>On a point of order, I went on to talk about the healthcare assistants at a very real political level.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#X02400"><p>I said that would form part of our debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#X02500"><p>It is not about positivity.  That is actually determined negativity regarding their work.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#Y00100"><p>I said we should have a debate on the healthcare system to address the matters raised by the Senator.  I used the word "promulgated", which means to articulate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#Y00200"><p>I understand the English language.  I am just wondering what is the Leader's opinion on healthcare assistants.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#Y00300"><p>I cannot allow interventions.  Perhaps the Senator might speak privately to the Leader about the matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#Y00400"><p>I will be happy to have a debate on the healthcare system.  If there are issues that need to be addressed, let us promulgate them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#Y00500"><p>Healthcare assistants.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#Y00600"><p>I understand what Senator O'Donnell said.  I can hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#Y00700"><p>Really.  Very good.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#Y00800"><p>If there are concerns, let us have that debate.  I have to be honest.  There is much positivity in the healthcare system too.  We sometimes hear a lot of negativity in this House, but there is a lot of positivity too.  I am not saying the Senator is saying negative things but making the point as part of the debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#Y00900"><p>The Leader is putting me in that context after I made a speech about how marvellous the healthcare system was.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#Y01000"><p>I understand that.</p><p>I do not have an answer for Senator Devine to her question about CHO 9, nor do I have a further update.  She is unhappy with the Minister of State, Deputy McGrath's response last week.  The Government is committed to working on the issue of mental health.  On child and adolescent mental health services, I suggest, with respect, that the Senator resubmit her Commencement matter for further consideration.  We will have a debate on health issues again after the local elections.  The HSE's service plan is not debated in the Houses of the Oireachtas <i>per se</i>but at the Joint Committee on Health.  As a Member of the Oireachtas, the Senator should have the opportunity to meet representatives of the HSE in her area to speak about issues related to the service plan.  She should consider resubmitting her Commencement matter because I accept that it is an important issue.</p><p>I regret that I cannot accept Senator Humphreys' proposed amendment to the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#Y01100"><p>Senator Humphreys has proposed an amendment to the Order of Business: "That No. 2 not be taken today and that No. 3 be taken at 4.45 p.m."  Is the amendment being pressed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#Y01200"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.145" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Amendment put.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.146" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>The Seanad divided by electronic means.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#Y01500"><p>Under Standing Order 62(3)(<i>b</i>), I request that the division be taken again other than by electronic means.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.148/1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#Y01600"><p>Amendment again put:</p><p>The Seanad divided: Tá, 17; Níl, 16.</p><br/><br/><p>Tellers: Tá, Deputies David Norris and Kevin Humphreys; Níl, Deputies Gabrielle McFadden and John O'Mahony.</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.148/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2019-05-21" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#Y01600">
            <divisioncount ayes="17" noes="16" abstain="0" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" vote="aye">Victor Boyhan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" vote="aye">Lorraine Clifford Lee</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" vote="aye">Gerard Craughwell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1383" vote="aye">Paul Daly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" vote="aye">Robbie Gallagher</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" vote="aye">Gerry Horkan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" vote="aye">Kevin Humphreys</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1439" vote="aye">Ian Marshall</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" vote="aye">Michael McDowell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" vote="aye">R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" vote="aye">Jennifer Murnane O'Connor</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" vote="aye">Gerald Nash</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" vote="aye">David Norris</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" vote="aye">Marie Louise O'Donnell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" vote="aye">Denis O'Donovan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" vote="aye">Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1404" vote="aye">Lynn Ruane</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" vote="no">Colm Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1380" vote="no">Paddy Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" vote="no">Jerry Buttimer</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" vote="no">Rose Conway Walsh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" vote="no">Martin Conway</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" vote="no">Maire Devine</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" vote="no">Frank Feighan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1415" vote="no">Maura Hopkins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1438" vote="no">Anthony Lawlor</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" vote="no">Tim Lombard</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" vote="no">Gabrielle McFadden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" vote="no">Michelle Mulherin</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" vote="no">John O'Mahony</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" vote="no">Joe O'Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" vote="no">James Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1399" vote="no">Neale Richmond</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="abstain">
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.148/3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#Y01600"><p>Amendment declared carried.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#CC00100"><p>There is an equality of votes.  Pursuant to Article 15.11.2o of the Constitution, I exercise my casting vote and vote in favour of the proposal in this instance.  I, therefore, declare the question carried.  Is the Order of Business, as amended, agreed to?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#CC00200"><p>No.  On a point of clarification, is the import of the disappointing result of the vote that we will take the Residential Tenancies (Amendment) (No. 2) Bill 2018 now?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#CC00300"><p>Yes.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.152" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Order of Business, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.153" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#CC00500">Sectoral Employment Order (Electrical Contracting Sector) 2019: Referral to Joint Committee</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#CC00600"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That the proposal that Seanad &Eacute;ireann approves the following Order in draft: Sectoral Employment Order (Electrical Contracting Sector) 2019, a copy of which has been laid in draft form before Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 9th May 2019, be referred to the Joint Committee on Business, Enterprise and Innovation, in accordance with Standing Order 71(3)(<i>k</i>), which, not later than 28th May 2019, shall send a message to the Seanad in the manner prescribed in Standing Order 75, and Standing Order 77(2) shall accordingly apply.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.155" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.156" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#DD00100">Residential Tenancies (Amendment) (No. 2) Bill 2018: Report and Final Stages</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#DD00200"><p>I welcome the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government, Deputy Eoghan Murphy, back to the House.  I remind Senators that they may speak only once on Report Stage, except the proposer of an amendment, who may reply to discussion on the amendment.  Furthermore, each non-Government amendment must be seconded.  Amendment No. 1, in the names of Senators Craughwell and McDowell, arises out of committee proceedings.  I call Senator Craughwell.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#DD00300"><p>I move amendment No. 1:</p><blockquote>In page 8, between lines 39 and 40, to insert the following:&ldquo;(VI) refurbishment that meets a per square foot value investment as set by regulations published by the Minister for properties that are pre 1963,&rdquo;.</blockquote> <p>I welcome the Minister.  I appreciate his urgency regarding this Bill but this amendment has the backing of this country's leading expert in building energy rating, BER.  I am told this part of the Bill concerning housing which predates 1963 could be illegal in the context of European legislation.  Those regulations call for a national policy to cover major renovation where more than 25% of the building envelope is being refurbished.  There is no requirement for a member state to link this to rent caps but there is a requirement for all major renovations to be undertaken in a cost optimal way.  In other words, the refurbishment being done should not be so expensive as to result in no practical realisable saving for occupants.  </p><p>Will the Minister point to where I might find a report on cost optimal studies that may have been done for such buildings?  My information is that no such study has ever been done.  The same consultant advises that in his professional opinion, as one of the leading BER assessors in the country, it is almost impossible, in practical terms, to reach a seven point improvement in a building that dates from before 1963.  The practical reasons include the walls of architecturally sensitive buildings, which can only be dry lined.  To avoid condensation risk, that can only be done with specially formulated materials, such as calcium silicate boards, to absorb moisture from breathable brick structures.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Gerard P. Craughwell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2402"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2402&amp;amp;pid=GerardPCraughwell&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=21"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Those materials do not reach the U-value requirements, for example, that are required by the Sustainable Energy Authority of Ireland to support grant-eligible measures for dry lining, meaning homeowners would have to take the costs involved.  This appears to directly contradict the stated position of An Taoiseach, who indicated at the weekend that the Government will help to grant-support retrofitting.  As matters stand, all these folks would be excluded from the grant scheme because of the nature of the materials used.</p><p>In these pre-1963 buildings, many internal features, such as architraves, skirting boards, etc., are conserved, making it absurdly expensive for all but those with the deepest of pockets to undertake the necessary dry-lining in an architecturally sensitive way.  As there is a practical limit on the U-values to be achieved, there is also a practical limit on the renewable technologies that can be used in such homes to replace existing heating systems.  We should remember that most of these homes were originally designed to be heated with coal and turf fires and that the walls are inherently breathable.  As there is a U-value constraint-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#EE00200"><p>This is a Second Stage speech.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#EE00300"><p>It is not Senator Buttimer's business to make such a remark.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#EE00400"><p>I am trying to put some important facts on the record.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#EE00500"><p>Members should speak through the Chair.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#EE00600"><p>A heat pump operates most efficiently at a narrow-operating delta-T temperature range and would be very inefficient and costly to operate in such a home.  A demand-response heating system, such as oil or gas boilers, would be much more effective.</p> <p>Under the current rules it can be practically impossible to obtain window energy performance certification for bespoke wooden sash windows.  It can often be impossible to verify that the savings made under the current rules of the building energy rating system, even when the homeowner has installed the best available components in line with architecturally sensitive practice.  It is not simply a matter of the market responding to this demand either.  By its nature, bespoke or craft windows and door manufacturing is undertaken by one-man bands who do not have the resources to file for certification in accredited laboratories.  As windows dominate the front-facing facades of these types of buildings, this is a major issue.</p> <p>If the Minister insists on pushing through this legislation this evening, I would want some reassurance for those who own pre-1963 properties that he will put in place a form of compensation for the homeowners affected, perhaps by means of grant aid or something of that nature.  I ask the Minister to accept the amendment.  I would not ordinarily be a great supporter of the landlord class, as the Minister knows, but in this case I can see that the Bill is flawed and needs to be dealt with on that matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#EE00700"><p>As long as the Senator spoke to the amendment, I did not consider his contribution a Second Stage speech.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019052100002#EE00800"><p>I dispute the statement that there is a landlord class.  There are many different kinds of landlords, including huge institutional investors, individuals, pensioners and all the rest.  It is not appropriate to say there is a landlord class.</p><p>I can add a sentence or two of context.  Last Monday, we hit two new national records.  The first was the lowest number of dwellings ever offered to rent and the second was the highest figure for average rent.  The person who contacted me about those asked why anybody would be surprised because, for the past five or six years, punitive legislation has been enacted in waves, with each wave more extreme than the last.  I can provide some evidence a little later.  Another correspondent told me the following:</p><blockquote>Substantial refurbishment, which is in a tenant's interest too, can cost up to &euro;10,000, and this feature, if enacted, will cause deterioration in existing rental properties and create very poor accommodation as time goes by.  Substantial refurbishment is not financially possible when, effectively, rent control is in place.</blockquote> <p>The two elements are in conflict and, as the Minister can see, I have a sheaf of correspondence from landlords.  That is only a small portion and I have edited it so as to speak appropriately to the first amendment.</p><p>The Bill is so restrictive with regard to the definition of &quot;substantial renovation&quot; that most property owners will find it impossible to comply with the criteria and will not be able to increase their rent even after substantial expenditure.  Apartments and pre-1963 multi-unit accommodation will be hardest hit.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-21a.167" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Additional debate to follow.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>